Hey everyone, welcome to the DRIVE podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
All right, Kellyanne, great to be sitting down with you and talking about all things
neurodegenerative disease. This is something I've been looking forward to for a while.
And I don't know, I thought maybe just to begin, kind of give us a bit of a sense of
your background and how this has become of interest to you. Did you always know you want
to become a doctor?
So thanks for having me. I'm super excited to be on the show finally. So it's an interesting
question. I'm going to say I always wanted to be a doctor, sparing the fact that when
I was younger, I thought maybe I'd be a singer or a mermaid or something crazy like that.
I loved scuba diving, so I had a large fantasy.
That's a good point. Mermaid can combine the love for scuba diving with singing. It's
like it really is the perfect career.
It was the perfect career for me. But no, I was always a nerd, actually. I don't know
if I'm allowed to say this, but in high school, the quarterback of the football team joked
and said that I was a waste of pretty because I never went to any parties. And all I did
was study. I was obsessed with biology and obsessed with chemistry and was a bookworm
pretty much.
And did the brain always interest you? Did you always have a sense? I mean, so I found
that interesting subset of people when they go to medical school already know what they're
going to do. Many people do not. Were you that person who when interviewing for medical
school knew you wanted to do neurology?
No, not at all, actually. So I'm a first generation American. My dad and mom both didn't give
me a lot of coaching when I was growing up. But one thing that they taught me was whatever
you're going to do, just love it because you're going to do it for the rest of your life.
And when I was in medical school, I just loved learning. So I loved every single subject.
But when I got into the clinical rotations, I found myself a little disappointed in them
because I wasn't interested in the algorithms of the disease and the actual treatments that
were being offered. And when I was thinking about things like prevention or exercise or
diet, I pretty much just got shunned. So when I was thinking about specialties, I thought about
what could I read for the rest of my life and be fascinated by. And that was pretty much the brain
for me.
Now, a lot of people will say neurology is a pretty depressing specialty because a lot of the
patients you're caring for have conditions that can't really be reversed. So at least in my med
school, neurology was not a core rotation. We were not required to do it. So I assume that was the
same for you when you did it as an elective.
Yes, I did it as an elective. And it is so depressing. Most of these diseases,
almost all of them, we don't have effective treatments for sparing things like migraines
and MS now, but kleoblastoma, terrible disease, terrible treatment options. Not much has changed
in the field. And when you think about things like neurodegenerative disease, which is ultimately
what I went into, the diseases are devastating for both the patients and their families.
Now you did your neurology residency at Cornell, which is how you met our mutual friend,
Richard Isaacson. And that's, of course, how we became connected. And then you did a fellowship
at Mount Sinai in movement disorders specifically.
Yes.
I want to take a step back and make sure people, including myself, understand the breadth of this
field called neurodegeneration. So when you look at the actuarial statistics of mortality,
neurodegeneration accounts for the third leading cause of death. So you have all of the diseases
that are lumped under ASCVD, atherosclerotic cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease.
That's number one. Cancer is number two. And then neurodegenerative disease is number three.
And those three basically account for, sorry, there's one other, which actually, no, no,
those do account, those are the top three. And I think they account for 70% of death.
Quite a sobering thought. Now, within neurodegenerative disease, you have a lot of different
types of pathology, some of which we've spent a lot of time on this podcast talking about.
We've talked a lot about Alzheimer's disease. We're going to talk about that again today.
But what I want to do today is be more broad, because in getting to know you, I've come to
understand that there are some of these diseases that affect men more than women. And we have a
far better sense of how to discriminate between these diseases than I used to think we did. I
used to think that, for example, Alzheimer's disease and Lewy body dementia could only be
distinguished on an autopsy. They couldn't be distinguished clinically. I used to never think
about Parkinson's disease in the same way that I would think about, say, a cognitive disease.
And I really, until recently, never understood the differences in the patterns of where the
disease occurred in the brain and how that translated to deficits. Now, the other day,
you explained to me in a way that I thought was so elegant, looking at the different parts of the
brain. Maybe you could sort of rehash some of that for folks. Yeah. So let's take a step back
and talk about dementia, which is an umbrella term, and then a further step back, which is
neurodegeneration, which encompasses dementias and other processes like Parkinson's disease.
So when we think about neurodegeneration, everyone thinks about Alzheimer's disease because it's the
most prevalent and chances are, you know, somebody who was affected by this disease. But the other
diseases that we're going to talk about today are also very common and you've probably never heard
of them, but you should because there's a reasonable likelihood that they will affect you at some point
in your life or a loved one. So when we think about dementia, we're going to talk about
what falls under that umbrella. We have Alzheimer's disease, we have vascular dementia, we have
Lewy body dementia, frontal temporal dementia. But when we think about neurodegeneration as a
more broad term, we start thinking about diseases like Parkinson's disease, Huntington's disease,
ALS, and then more rare diseases like progressive supranuclear palsy, multiple system atrophy,
cortical basilar degeneration. So taking a step back in terms of understanding what these diseases
are and what symptoms people may present at, I like to look at it as what part of the brain
is this affecting? So neurodegeneration means death of the brain cells. Where is that death
happening? So for things like frontal temporal dementia or vascular dementia, you're talking
about the frontal lobe primarily and the frontal lobe is involved in processes such as planning
events, problem solving, speed of processing. These are all executive lobe functions. When we think about
Alzheimer's disease, we're thinking about the temporal lobe. That's where the degeneration
is mainly happening and that's mainly a memory problem, but it's also a language problem.
The language center is in the temporal lobe. For diseases like Lewy body, we're thinking about the
parietal and occipital lobe. The parietal and occipital lobe are involved with visual spatial
processing. So you get symptoms like issues with depth perception, issues following plot lines of
movies or following plot lines of books. Patients will have to reread passages over again to really
fully comprehend what's happening. And hallucinations is something that you can see later in the disease
course. And is the difficulty with depth perception part of what feeds into the movement disorder
that we see that kind of differentiates Lewy body from AD? Yeah, I really think so. And it's
interesting and we'll talk about this later. So maybe we'll sticky note it for now. But visual
impairment is a risk factor for neurodegenerative diseases. And how does that relate to how we can
prevent these diseases? Well, it's possible that the visual processing is needed to reinforce the
neuronal circuitry. And what I mean by that is our brain needs sensory input. It needs sensory
stimulation. When we don't have that, those neuronal circuits aren't getting exercised, for lack of a
better term, and they're more likely to atrophy. So if you don't use it, you lose it. And so in
relation to your question, yes, I think that that visual processing is why you have the depth
perception issues that you see in Lewy body. So I definitely will make a note of that because I want
to come back to not just the visual part, but the auditory part as well. Yes, I want to go back to
something you mentioned at the outset. You talked about how vascular dementia overlaps with frontal
dementia. What is it about that when I think of vascular dementia, in my mind, I'm thinking of
small vessel disease that's similar to atherosclerotic disease, basically some form of
ischemia. Why is that unique to the frontal cortex? And why is that not something that,
you know, the rest of the brain is just as sensitive to? So I actually think vascular
dementia and Alzheimer's dementia are the ones that overlap more. And the reason I say that is
because it's very difficult to discern clinically the difference between Alzheimer's and vascular
dementia. We classically will say, yes, the speed of processing issues are more prevalent in vascular
dementia versus Alzheimer's disease. It's more of a memory issue. But when we're looking at
metabolic changes in the brain, we see that the frontal lobe is hypometabolic in terms of glucose
utilization, in frontotemporal dementia, and in vascular dementia. And why is that? It's hard to
know exactly, but it may have something to do with the vasculature of the brain and what areas of the
brain are more sensitive to glucose metabolism, cholesterol metabolism, and vascular risk factors.
Yeah, it's very interesting because there is such a high association with diabetes
and this condition, but my recollection is that the brain doesn't require insulin the way the rest
of the body does to facilitate glucose transport into neurons. In other words, insulin resistance
per se should not be an issue in the brain proper. But of course, I've seen experimental data that
look at intranasal insulin injections that temporarily alleviate some of the symptoms
associated with this type of dementia, suggesting that maybe insulin resistance is playing a role
paradoxically. And of course, you always have to wonder if the metabolic syndrome that is associated
with type 2 diabetes in that entire spectrum is simply a marker of the underlying vascular
problems as well. So this is an area at Kellyanne where I really find myself confused. In the end,
it might not matter that much from a preventative strategy, but nevertheless, it creates a little
bit of confusion in terms of mechanism of action, at least in my naive mind. It's really interesting
clinically when you look at data. So we do cognitive testing on a ton of patients. So we
get to look at this in real time and we get to compare it to serum biomarkers. So thinking about
high cholesterol, meaning high ApoB, when we see high ApoB in patients, we often do see reduced
speed of processing. And clinically, we see that if you correct things like the ApoB, you see
improvement in speed of processing. Tell me about the time course there. Yeah, it can happen
rather quickly over a course of six months, but it's dependent on the person. That's kind of
amazing. I mean, obviously, we take this approach with patients, but a lot of our patients that are
in our practice don't really have the MCI that you were seeing in your clinic. The patients that you
and Richard took care of at Cornell were obviously far more advanced. And is there a point at which
you just didn't see any improvement in symptoms regardless of intervention? So like I said,
everyone's different and there are a lot of different factors that could influence something
like executive function and speed of processing. I think what's most helpful is looking at an
individual and putting their lab values and an understanding of what their risk factors are next
to each other. Because if you see somebody who, for example, does have out of control cholesterol
and you're looking at their executive function in tasks like generating words that start with
F or A or S, that's a really popular test that gives us clues into is the vascular risk factor
affecting this person's cognition. If you see that, the chance that you intervene on their
cholesterol and they have a notable outcome in the next 6, 12, 18 months is pretty high, but it
depends on the person. And it also depends on what other factors are playing a role. For example,
sleep. Sleep is huge and I can't emphasize enough how important sleep is to speed of processing. If
you are getting shit crap sleep, sorry, you really aren't going to see high speed of processing. You
really have to be sleeping in order to process information. So I want to put a pin in that as
well because I do want to come back to sleep staging. We've obviously separately and previously
talked a lot about REM sleep disruption and the implications for that. So I want to come back to
sleep, but let's go back to kind of this broader sense of what's going on. So you have sort of
these three areas of the brain that can be impacted that can lead to various types of
dementia. And each of them seems horrible in their own right. Ironically, Alzheimer's seems the least
horrible in that it's mostly a deficit of memory and language relative to robbing you of executive
function processing speed in the front of the brain and movement disorders and visual disorders
in the back of the brain. But to be sure, these are all awful conditions.
Let's talk a little bit about some of the things that we think about more with respect to movement.
So Parkinson's disease and obviously perhaps the worst disease of them all, ALS.
So ALS and Parkinson's disease are very different because ALS is more of a peripheral nerve problem.
Parkinson's disease is more of a central problem more related to Lewy body.
ALS is really rare. Only about 18,000 people in the US have ALS. Unlike Parkinson's disease,
which is much more common, a million people in the US have Parkinson's disease and the incidence of
Parkinson's disease is actually doubled in the last 25 years. It's the fastest growing neurological
condition in- And just for comparison, how many people in the United States carry a diagnosis of
Alzheimer's disease? About 6 million. Okay. So 6 million to 1 million to 18,000.
For Lewy body, it's about 1.4 million. So less common than Alzheimer's disease, but still-
That's actually pretty common. That's 25% of it.
Right, but still very common. So still a reasonable likelihood that someone listening
to this podcast today is going to be affected by one of these diseases, ALS less so. But the
interesting thing about ALS is that there's a connection between ALS and frontal temporal
dementia. So there are certain genetic risk factors. One is C9 ORF, is what I say, C9ORF.
It puts people at risk for both ALS and frontal temporal dementia. So some family members will
have the frontal temporal dementia and other family members will have ALS. We don't know what turns
one person to develop the more peripheral nerve problem versus the more central nerve problem,
but it's an interesting connection that you'll see. Now Parkinson's, again, I didn't realize it
was quite that prevalent. So is it a different disease when it occurs in young people than when
it occurs in older people, or is it basically the same disease and it just has a variable time of
onset? So we, in my opinion, aren't very good at the way we're diagnosing these diseases. So we're
using a clinical diagnosis to say somebody has Parkinson's disease. So you need to have
resting tremor, bradykinesia, which is slow movements, rigidity, which is stiffness of the
muscles, and or postural instability. So falling, not being steady on your feet. That is a really
rudimentary way of looking at the disease. Yes, it's saying that there's something going on in
the brain that you're losing dopamine neurons, but really these diseases are starting way, way,
way before those symptoms are actually presenting. So if you look at people who have REM sleep
behavior disorder, which is acting out your dreams, so punching, kicking, screaming in your sleep,
that is over 90% positive predictive value that you will go on to develop either a Parkinson's
or Lewy body-like disease. And that starts 20 to 30 years before a tremor or muscle stiffness
or postural instability will ever present. Wait, that's going to be a little scary to
some people because I think a lot of us think, boy, I move around a lot in my sleep, but
how is this diagnosis made? Is it relying on a spouse or someone in the bed with you,
or is it something that can only be done with polysomnography? So the gold standard is
polysomnography, but you actually don't need polysomnography to diagnose it. And in fact,
one simple question has a greater than 90% sensitivity and specificity for picking up
REM sleep behavior disorder, which is does your bed partner know that you are punching,
kicking, or moving a lot in your sleep? And when we're saying moving a lot, we're not just talking
about tossing and turning, we're talking about it's clear that this person is having some sort
of dream and they are acting that out in their sleep. It's different than just the tossing and
turning. And to be clear, are you saying that if that exists, so if someone in their 30s is experiencing
that there's roughly a 90% chance they're going to go on to develop Parkinson's disease or Lewy
body dementia? Correct. And it's a terrifying fact. It is a terrifying fact. But the way that
I think about it is knowing that is like picking up breast cancer when it's localized to the breast
tissue. The way that we're doing it now, we're picking up Parkinson's disease by the time we get
the diagnosis of Parkinson's disease. So by the time someone has tremor rigidity, pretty good.
Yeah, it's like diagnosing metastatic breast cancer.
Yes, 50% of the dopamine producing brain cells are already gone.
Okay, so let's actually tell people a little bit about what's going on in Parkinson's disease.
So let's explain what dopamine is in the basal ganglia and all these things so that people
understand how that happens. And so let's spend three minutes on just the med school explanation.
Because I think it's important to understand a little bit about the anatomy and the neurobiology
of this to understand the prevention stuff that we're going to want to talk about. So what's
happening in Parkinson's disease? So rudimentary medical school 101,
what is happening in Parkinson's disease? So dopamine producing brain cells, so dopaminergic
cells live in a part of the brain called the substantia nigra pars compacta, which is a center
that controls movement in the body. These cells are dark colored. And in Parkinson's disease,
these cells start to die, you need dopamine. So these cells produce dopamine, you need dopamine
to move. But you also need dopamine for a slew of other neurological processes, including mood
regulation. So if you don't have adequate dopamine, you often suffer from anxiety and depression.
So do we have any sense of what leads to the loss of those cells?
So what are the risk factors for Parkinson's disease is what you're asking.
Yeah, or even just more pathologically, like, for example, has it been ruled out that it's
autoimmune? Is there any reason to believe that the immune system is attacking those cells and
destroying them? Is it, you know, does it seem to be unaffected by anything else? Is it programmed
cell death, presumably not? Is it inflammatory? Is it is it an inflammatory environment that
destroys those dopamine producing cells? Do we have some sense of what it is mechanistically
that's doing this? So the immune system and inflammation seem to play a large role here,
but it may be more related to the mitochondria and the lysosome function. So autophagy and
removing damaged organellis seems to play a really big role in these diseases.
Which seems to be a common thread across all of neurodegeneration. We've talked about this on a
previous podcast with Eileen White. It's probably been two and a half years ago, but one of the
surest ways to impart neurodegenerative disease onto a mouse is to knock out the genes responsible
for autophagy. They'll basically also come to neurodegeneration. I want to say it's something
as absurd as at four months of age. Now four months for a mouse, right? That's the equivalent of,
I don't know, probably 15 or 20 years old for a human, maybe less. And to think that if the only
thing you've done is knock out autophagy, you might argue, well, they would have gotten other
diseases later on, but that the very first thing that they get and the thing that ultimately kills
them as neurodegeneration probably speaks to the importance of this process in homeostasis within
the brain. Absolutely. And I mean, we don't have perfect models for Parkinson's disease because the
models that we use are either models that are induced by toxic exposures or genetic models,
which there's no one size fits all. I think this disease is just so broad and can present in many
different ways and can have many different etiologies. But if you look at the genetic
models for the disease, really one of the main genes is called GBA. And what happens is that
enzyme gets stuck, the glucose cerebrocytes enzyme gets stuck in the endoplasmic reticulum and it
can't break down glucose fingocines. So you're not getting these chemicals broken down where
they should be. They start building up and when they start building up, the lysosome can't get to
these substances to break them down appropriately. So the lysosomal function is really impaired.
And once you start impairing the lysosomal function, then the mitochondria becomes affected,
then you start triggering a whole slew of inflammatory cytokines and the process just
is a vicious cycle. Two questions then, you can take them in whichever order you like.
We have a sense of what are the causative triggers, not just associative. What are the causative
triggers of Parkinson's disease? We should talk about the same for Lewy body, of course, as well.
But let's just focus on one. And secondly, if you're talking to that person who's 40 years old,
who is having the sleep disturbances that we now think have a high likelihood of predicting
the beginning of this damage, what do you do? So this is touching on so many points. So if you
want to first start with what is triggering the disease, well, we don't have the perfect answer,
but we know certain things do trigger it or seem to play a role. So pesticide exposure
seems to play a role. Solvent exposure. Which pesticides do we know? Yeah. So it's Paraquat
and Rodinone, which Rodinone is not used in the US anymore, but Paraquat is still used in the US.
So we see a higher prevalence of Parkinson's disease in people who live in more rural places
in the US. And if you look at epidemiological studies on where is Parkinson's disease
distributed in the US, you'll see there is a quote, Parkinson's disease belt,
and it really runs through the Midwest. Of course, the USDA and the FDA would never acknowledge this
because they would have to say that this is just noise and that there's no data there,
or they would have banned this pesticide. So what is it that you think that they don't see
in those data? Or how are they explaining that away as a confounder for something else?
You know, I don't think I have a very good answer to that. I don't know why they don't acknowledge
that these studies are real and these associations are pretty profound. There's clearly just like
there's a stroke belt in the South. There's a Parkinson's disease belt in the Midwest.
What are these pesticides used for? Agricultural farming.
Any foods in particular? Is it?
I don't know.
Okay. And you probably don't know if there's substitutes that could be used at a slightly
higher cost that are less toxic.
I'm not sure.
Are these pesticides in greater use today? What explains the fact that you said earlier,
Parkinson's is the fastest growing neurodegenerative condition in the US?
Yeah, great question. And there have been a lot of theories hypothesizing why the prevalence of
Parkinson's disease will grow in the future. And one of them, which makes me laugh a little bit,
is smoking. So smoking is quote, protective against Parkinson's disease. It's like one of those weird
things that you read about and you're like, oh, wait, why? Just like I think inflammatory
bowel disease also smoking is quote, protective against it. And they're saying, well, less people
are smoking now. So maybe that's what's driving the disease. But I don't really buy into that
because I don't really think smoking is offering that much protection to your brain. And it's doing
so many other terrible things for your brain and body that it's just not something to ever consider
when we're thinking about ways to optimize our health. I actually think it has a lot to do with
the movements that we're going through day to day and how much screen time we're spending every day.
But we can touch more on that later.
So you think it's a loss of movement capacity, basically?
Exactly. And just like we were talking about, or I think Richard talked about it in his podcast,
the idea of cognitive reserve, building as much cognitive reserve as possible. Well, you want the
same with your body. You want to build up as much movement reserve as possible because if you don't
use it, you lose it. And the less you move, the more likely you are to develop one of these
neurodegenerative movement processes, I believe. How many of those cases of Parkinson's disease
percent wise do we think have a clear genetic predisposition? And you mentioned one gene already.
We were going to talk a lot about the genes around Alzheimer's disease. What does the genetic
landscape look like here? So right now, we say 10% of Parkinson's disease is related to a clear
genetic etiology. GBA is one gene. LARC2, L-R-R-K2 is another one. And both of these
genes are tested in 23andMe, only one variant of each. So it's not a perfect test. So if it's
negative for you, it doesn't really mean you don't have a variant in one of these genes,
but those are the most common. There are other less common.
And are these more like ApoE4 where they are risk factors, but they're not fully penetrant
in the way that Huntington's is? Yes. Exactly. So if you have one of these genes,
it depends on a lot of factors, especially ancestry. So Ashkenazi Jewish people with Ashkenazi
Jewish ancestry have a higher risk that these genes will express, but we're looking at penetrants of
around 30%, but for LARC2, it can be much higher up to 80%. Some studies quote actually 100%
depending on how long you live, but I don't know if I believe it.
Okay. But not a huge, you said that's 10%. 10%. Yeah. Whereas in Alzheimer's disease,
two thirds of cases have E4, at least one copy of E4. So you could say E4 is playing a bigger role
there potentially. Yeah. I would say that our understanding of Parkinson's disease is so far
behind our understanding of Alzheimer's disease. And our understanding of the genetic architecture
of it is so far behind. I would say that we're probably at least 10 years behind the field of
Alzheimer's disease. And we will identify more genetic risk factors for this disease. I have
no doubt about it because the number of patients that I've seen that have a clear family history
and multiple family members and testing for every known gene that we could has just turned up
nothing. There's clearly something there that we are missing. Yeah. So again, we see this also with
breast cancer. We see women in whom breast cancer runs in the family up and down sideways, and they
test negative for every known gene associated. But you've got to tell that woman, your daughter's at
risk, even though we can't identify what the genes are. Yeah. Which makes it really challenging as a
provider because we love looking at genes because it gives us a clue to what the possible underlying
pathophysiological mechanism that may be driving the disease that they may be at risk for. When
we don't have that to grab onto, we're really grabbing at straws and just throwing everything
under the kitchen sink at a person because we don't really have a good clear sense of what
pathway they're on. So what would you say to that person who's 40, who's having these sleep
disturbances? But while they're awake, everything is totally fine. So the idea here being that those
sleep disturbances are the canary in the coal mine for this problem occurring in their brain.
What do you say to that patient as far as steps to take to maximize the odds of avoidance or at
least maximal delaying? So again, there's no one size fits all here. So it really depends on the
person. And the first thing I would want to do is definitely check out their genes. But besides that.
So let's say you do this and they don't test positive for either of these two genes.
And yeah, let's just let's say you have access to everything. What do you want to know? What else
do I know about this person? What toxic exposures could they have? Or did they grow up? Were they
drinking well water? Were they drinking city water? All those things matter. So let's say
they grew up on a farm, but now they don't live anywhere near it. So their exposure is in the past.
It's no longer present. And let's assume that there's nothing that's actively contributing
to it from a from an exposure standpoint. And now you're just kind of going on defense as far
as what you can do. Okay, so first and foremost, a movement assessment is absolutely key. So
the one thing that I think is so fascinating about this disease is that we see abnormal
movement patterns in these patients years and years before tremor, slow movement start. And
the patterns that we see are very similar among people. So most frequently, and maybe we should
rewind a little bit here. So our bodies are naturally asymmetric, just like our brains are
naturally asymmetric, we have despite the way they look, our bodies look symmetric, our brains look
symmetric, but we know that the right side of the brain has certain functions and the left side of
the brain has certain functions. So the left side is really a language, verbal side, and the right
side is more of a visual side, emotional side. We have a dominance for one hand and one leg. So in
people who are right handed, which is most people, we'll see the symptoms start of Parkinson's disease
start in the dominant hand and be most severe in the dominant hand. So taking into account someone's
handedness, the pattern of movement that we usually see is patients don't really load the
left leg and they won't spend time on the left leg. So most of their time is spent on the right leg
and they can't really sense or get a good sense of grounding through the left leg. And the right arm
is stiff and not swinging very freely when they're walking. That is something if you see
REM sleep behavior and this abnormal movement pattern, I want to deconstruct their movement
and make them sense on the left side and free up the right side, which often starts with breathing
because they're also not really breathing into the right apical lung or the right lung at all. So
first deconstructing that into what is their abnormal breathing pattern and how can we get
them to feel on the left side and move the right side more freely. So obviously this overlaps a lot
with stuff that Beth Lewis and I talk about and you and Beth, of course, are very close and work
together with patients as well. Is the idea here that you can start to train out the pathology,
if that makes sense? Yeah, I think I like the way you put that, train out the pathology.
I think that everyone has asymmetries in their body. The problem is when that asymmetry goes
too far in one extreme and that can happen for a lot of different reasons. It may be triggered by
an orthopedic injury. For me, for example, I actually noticed this. So I had a spinal fusion
when I was just a teenager and I thought I was totally fine until my med school boyfriend took
me skiing and I realized I could not control my right leg. No matter what I did, I couldn't
get my brain to talk to my right leg to make my right leg internally rotate. And that showed me
that there is some poor control between my leg and my brain. That neuronal circuitry is just not
developed appropriately and that's what you're trying to reinforce because by building up
stronger circuitry between all aspects of your toes, your fingers, your breath, that's how you're
training out these abnormal movements. But in a sense, it's not really training it out. It's
reinforcing the movements that you may have neglected because you just swung so far in one
direction, either left or right. Let's assume that you proceed through that. You do the
assessment. You find some of these early warning signs. You begin to work on the training.
What else can you do to, again, let's not necessarily even use the word prevent,
but delay the onset of this. So in association with the REM sleep behavior disorder,
patients aren't getting a lot of REM sleep. So I think sleep tracking is really huge in these
patients. So you know better than I do even that different sleep stages affect different functions
in the body. REM sleep is really important for not just memory formation, but also dealing with
your emotions. That's how our bodies handle anxiety, depression, stress throughout the day.
These patients often have a lot of anxiety and a lot of depression and often aren't getting
enough REM sleep. So optimizing their sleep with simple sleep hygiene is huge.
One of the things I tend to worry about with sleep trackers is that they can create more anxiety.
And so my fear with that is you take that patient who's probably by now pretty nervous and you say,
we're going to start tracking your sleep and lo and behold, oh, your REM sleep is quite
interrupted. Is that a good piece of information to have? So I think it's a good piece of information.
I agree. There is a person for a sleep tracker and there is a person that should not have a
sleep tracker because they're just going to enter a vicious cycle. But knowing that they aren't
getting enough REM sleep is really huge specifically for Parkinson's disease. So we know that the
melatonin signaling pathway in Parkinson's disease is off and they've actually done studies
where they put people in front of bright lights. So light box therapy for Parkinson's disease
early in the morning, 20 to 30 minutes a day, 10,000 lux. And that actually helps regulate the
melatonin signaling cycle and helps improve REM sleep in these patients. So knowing that,
I think it could change outcomes. Yeah. I'm going to be having Matt Walker back on the podcast in a
few months and we're going to go into much, much more detail about both the pharmacology and the
supplement side of how you can augment various sleep stages. Matt's helped me a lot with this
kind of stuff. So the other question I suppose I have, you mentioned anxiety. How do we know which
one's the chicken, which one's the egg here? You know, by the time somebody is even told this
information, even if they're completely asymptomatic, it seems to me that that would
produce anxiety. And so how do we know that the anxiety was playing a causal role versus
it's just the response to what's happening. So from personal experience, if you just talk to
patients, a lot of them will tell you I've never been an anxious person, but in the last five years,
my anxiety is just through the roof. And I think it has something to do with the dopamine signaling.
So if you think about, is it a chicken or the egg thing in terms of sleep, that's another question
because yeah, that's the sleep is promoting anxiety. If you're not getting enough REM sleep,
you're not dealing with the anxiety. So that's a whole cycle. But-
And again, we know that, again, whether it be dementia or Parkinson's disease,
these things disrupt sleep. Of course. And disrupting sleep maybe makes them worse.
Exactly. Exactly. But knowing that you may be at risk for one of these diseases, I mean,
this is what we see every day, whether it's a risk factor in terms of a genetic risk factor or a
prodromal symptom in terms of REM sleep behavior. I think knowing the data doesn't tell you anything
in terms of what's going to happen to you as an individual. We haven't ever tried to do anything
for people who have REM sleep behavior disorder. Just like previously, we didn't try to do anything
for people who had an APOE gene, an APOE4 gene. We just kind of thought, well, they're at a higher
risk for dementia and we're just going to let them be at that risk. Well, this is our opportunity
to do something about it because ultimately our treatment options once 50% of your dopaminergic
cells are dead aren't so good. We're just giving people back levodopa. That isn't going to change
the outcomes that this person ultimately is facing. But maybe starting earlier, knowing that this is a
red flag, maybe we are going to delay onset of full-blown symptoms or maybe we're going to slow
the loss and maybe at that point the dopaminergic cells could be reversed. We could repair the
damage that's done or at least if we can't, we can stop any more from happening and they may never
get the disease. Well, that last one is certainly interesting if we believe that we have a sense of
what the environmental trigger is. Of course, it seems to me that, well, I don't actually know how
the NIH is allocating resources to the biology of this disease. I can't comment as to whether
it's adequately funded or inadequately funded, but it would seem to me until we have a very clear
sense of what's happening at the cellular level with the dopamin-producing cells, that's the thing
we want to be able to halt. It's great to now shift our mindset from diagnosing breast cancer
when it's metastatic to when it's a one centimeter early lesion, but at least with breast cancer,
we know what to do when it's early. You cut the damn thing out, done. We knew that 200 years ago,
probably longer. Certainly in the 17th century, 18th century, we knew removing and by the 19th
century, the late 19th century, we actually had perfected the sterile way to do this.
That's what we're still missing, I think, here is. Step one is we now think we can figure this out
20 years before it's happening. Step two is removing the causative agent.
Right. There's no way to cut this out. We're not looking at a tumor that we can cut out, but
we also haven't ever studied doing anything this early, which is a huge loss in my opinion,
because we know that these people are at risk. We should be doing things. Even if we're only
moving the needle a small amount by certain lifestyle interventions or supplements,
which we know also play a role in disease risk, specifically B vitamins, then we're moving the
needle maybe just a little bit, but maybe a little bit at the right time actually moves the needle
a large amount. Yeah. Again, and I think we can think about that, like how do we do that clinically
with our patients? It's one thing. I think the challenge is how do you scale that up to being
the standard of care where without a biomarker, it's very difficult to do that because prevention
is too long a study. It's actually the one thing that has made our progress for ASCVD so great.
There's really two things. One is we have a really good biomarker in APO-B and LDLC.
LDLC being not quite as good, but still decent. Right. We have this causative agent. We have this
thing that is necessary, though not sufficient to cause the disease. When you have something like
that, you know almost without exception that lowering that thing will lower the incidence of
disease. Then it simply becomes a question of how long do you need to study it in your given
population to see the reduction. We don't have that biomarker here. Now we're going to talk about
Alzheimer's in a minute and we're going to talk about other potential biomarkers there. I'm very
curious to understand from you the utility that we think of, for example, serum amyloid or TAL.
Is there anything on the horizon with Parkinson's that we can even point to, be it radiographically,
be it certainly a blood biomarker would be the most desirable? Are there people working on this
sort of thing? We didn't really talk about the difference in terms of histopathology for these
diseases. Alzheimer's disease is what we call a tauopathy. You see a lot of amyloid and tau
proteins. Parkinson's disease, Lewy body, are called alpha synucleinopathies. A different toxic
protein builds up in these diseases. While we've advanced a lot in terms of our ability to develop
blood-based biomarkers for amyloid and tau, we haven't done so well in terms of alpha synuclein.
You can biopsy different parts of the body and get a good sense of alpha synuclein deposition.
There is a school of- An alpha synuclein being this other protein deposition.
Is it a misfolded protein? Yep, exactly. It's very similar to amyloid. It's analogous to amyloid. It
develops into little Lewy bodies that go into your brain cells, but also other parts of your body,
which is what I'll talk about in a second, and cause degeneration of brain cells.
Do we have the contrapositives? We know that there are lots of patients on autopsy that have
amyloid and tau who were cognitively normal. Sounds like we don't have the opposite. We don't
have people with Alzheimer's disease that are missing amyloid and tau. Is that correct? Yes.
Suggesting that amyloid and tau, if anything, are necessary, but clearly not sufficient.
What about on the other side with alpha synuclein? Do we know that there are people who live a normal
life with this present in old age, and at the time of their death, it's there as an incidental
finding? It's a good question, and I think there is a threshold before symptoms will present.
When we're looking at how much alpha synuclein, which will correlate to how many dopaminergic
cells have been lost, what is that number? How much deposition do you need for clinical symptoms
present? Yes. In answer to your question, there are studies that show there is alpha synuclein
deposits in this person's brain, in this person's gut, in this person's skin, in this person's
salivary glands, but this person didn't have Parkinson's disease. What if that person lived
five more years? Would they have Parkinson's disease? I don't know. Maybe.
Lots to unpack there. Is the alpha synuclein accumulation directly proportional to the
death of dopaminergic cells? Yes, pretty much. That means patients with Parkinson's presumably
have more of it than Lewy body? Not necessarily, because in Lewy body, you primarily have alpha
synuclein, but you can also have amyloid and tau accumulation. In Parkinson's disease, although
it's still considered an alpha synucleinopathy, you could have tau deposition. I like to view
these diseases as a continuum. I think the way that we have been trained to view these diseases
is just wrong. They are neurodegenerative processes, and the underlying mechanisms are
shared between all of them. That's why we really have to start viewing them as such related
diseases. Whether one person develops an alpha synuclein process or an amyloid tau process
is really less relevant in terms of what is the pathogenic mechanism that's driving that
abnormal protein to actually be deposited. Yes, that starts with adequate risk stratification,
risk assessment for a person, because it's clear that this person may be on the path to developing
an alpha synucleinopathy, but what's driving that? Well, it's still all a neuroinflammation
autophagy problem. Let's dial back and start more basically with what are the commonalities
between these diseases, and can we target one and affect the outcomes of many?
Let's not talk about Alzheimer's disease then. This is the elephant in the room.
At least 6 million people in the United States have it. That incidence also seems to be rising
disproportionately at the population. You always run into the question, are we just diagnosing it
more? Are people getting sicker? What's at the root of this? Let's not pick it up at the pathology.
Again, this is not really a movement disorder, therefore it's not really something where we see
the alpha synuclein accumulation. Everybody thinks of this as the lens of being an amyloid tau
problem. Maybe just let's explain to people again, what is amyloid? What is tau? Let's explain what
the APP protein is, and how does it get cleaved, and how does it turn into amyloid, etc.
Toxic proteins, what are we looking at? Amyloid protein. Amyloid can be misfolded into things
called amyloid plaques. If they're not cleaved properly, they are sticky and they fold up into
cells in the brain and can cause a whole slew of problems including neurodegeneration. Tau is
something that will develop into an equivalent called a neurofibrillary tangle in cells. Alpha
synuclein on the other hand does the same thing, it develops into Lewy bodies. Basically, these are
physical structures. These are actual proteins that due to misfolding end up in, and do they end up
inside the neurons themselves? Do they end up adjacent to the neurons? Where do they actually
accumulate? Inside the neurons. Inside the neurons. I assume that the critical problem is the
relationship between that protein and the inflammatory state that comes with it, or does
the protein by itself interrupt the neuron minus the inflammation? That's a great question. Does the
protein change cell signaling? Is that what you're asking? Correct, by itself. Or is it the inflammatory
process that's triggering all of the problems? I'll give you the analogy. We know that cholesterol
by itself, when the ApoB particle carries the lipid, the sterile, into the sub endothelial space,
that's really not a big problem. When it gets oxidized there and the inflammatory response
comes to repair it paradoxically, that inflammatory response is what leads to the tissue damage
that results in atherosclerosis, that results in the plaque formation and ultimately the plaque
rupture. In that sense, our bodies are doing the damage to ourselves. I'm curious as to whether
that's the case in neurodegenerative disease. That's what I believe the case is. Whether or
not there's some contribution that is directly related to impaired cell signaling once these
proteins build up in the neurons, that's possible. But I think the bigger problem is what you just
pointed out, which is once these proteins develop, the whole inflammatory cascade that drives
neurodegeneration is the big problem. It's essentially our body's reaction to these proteins
being built up in the brain that are causing a problem.
Okay. Now, historically, this was something that you only got to figure out on autopsy.
Person had dementia, you clinically thought they had dementia. Nobody was trying to distinguish
between frontotemporal, occipital, those are all details. This person was normal,
they're no longer normal. Maybe we'll do an autopsy on grandma and we'll figure out that
this is what she had. But a lot of that's changed recently. What's an amyloid PET scan
and how does that shed light on this? Let's even rewind it to just a regular PET scan.
An FDG PET scan, which is really helpful when we're thinking about this whole frontotemporal,
parietal, occipital pattern. Because if you get a FDG PET scan, you're looking at glucose
hypometabolism in the brain. Well, where is the brain hypometabolic?
Maybe I'll even just tell people what's going on. So FDG PET, you label glucose
with a radioisotope and when you inject it into them, the PET scanner is not an anatomic image
like an MRI or a CT scan. It's a functional image. It's just looking for glucose uptake.
Typically, when you do a PET scan, the brain really lights up the most because you're seeing
so much glucose trafficked to the brain relative to its size. And so what you're saying is hypometabolism
shows up as less signal in that area, which says, hey, there's less metabolic activity,
less glucose went to this part of the brain versus this part of the brain versus this part of the
brain. Correct. And that less glucose correlates to neurodegeneration in that part of the brain,
or at least eventual neurodegeneration in that part of the brain. So looking at patterns of
hypometabolism in the brain can be rather helpful in differentiating between things like Lewy body,
Alzheimer's disease, frontotemporal dementia, because you see different patterns of glucose
hypometabolism. So that can be helpful, but it's not perfect. It doesn't tell you what the underlying
protein deposition is and if there's underlying protein deposition. And you can see abnormal
patterns, quote, abnormal as a part of normal aging. So metabolism in the brain changes as we
age, and that's not necessarily a pathology. It could be just a process, normal process of aging.
But an amyloid PET. So amyloid PETs, there are three different tracers that are available and
FDA approved now. Essentially, they all have the same sensitivity and specificity, but what you're
looking at with an amyloid PET is completely different than metabolism. You're actually
looking at a tracer that is tagging onto amyloid deposition in the brain and you're scoring what
that tracer looks like. So how diffuse is that uptake in the brain? And here it's the opposite.
You expect to see the area with pathology being the big signal as opposed to the lack of signal
being the pathology with the glucose PET. Correct, correct. So amyloid PETs can be helpful in terms
of showing us is there amyloid deposition in the brain, but there's a caveat there because
we can see amyloid deposition in the brain in cognitively normal people. And in fact,
amyloid is abnormal, but in many ways it's normal. I've read an interesting study and this is sort
of unrelated, but I can never get this fact out of my brain where they looked at young, healthy people
and young, healthy 30 or 40 year olds and they made them sleep deprived. So they said you couldn't
go to sleep. And then they did amyloid scans and CSF biomarkers for amyloid and found that after
a single night of sleep deprivation, amyloid deposition increased by 5%. Well, that's because
amyloid is present in everybody, but we just are able to clear it. Exactly. So say it, looking at
an image at one point in time and saying that there's amyloid building up in the brain,
does that mean that that person is on the path to Alzheimer's disease? If they're cognitively
normal, does that, what does that mean? Is that reversible? It doesn't really tell us very much
more information. Yeah. To me, this is the thing that I'm most intrigued by is what, what does it
mean that there are people, nevermind just having amyloid pet positivity, there are people who die.
And when you biopsy their brain, you can't really distinguish their brain from somebody who had all
simer's disease, from the amount of amyloid that's in there. There's, it's very difficult for a
pathologist to look at this and tell you what this person looked like when they were alive.
And that's different from the heart, right? A pathologist can look at your heart on autopsy
and can clearly distinguish who was healthy from who was not, which is not to say a pathologist in
a blinded fashion can tell you that this person had a heart attack. Because if they died quickly
enough, you might not see the damage. But it's, it's a stunning indictment of our ignorance of the
brain. And of the fact that the, not this, not to oversimplify the heart, but the heart in some ways
is an easier organ to understand. It, it behaves in a more mechanical way than the brain. But this
makes it very difficult then to really stratify risk in an individual. That's, that to me is like,
this is really less a philosophical discussion for me and more of a practical one, which is where do
we need to act and how do we need to act and how do we measure progress? Yeah. And like along the
same lines there is looking at amyloid in terms of what does that tell you about cognition? Because
the two could not be related at all. So someone could have a ton of amyloid deposition in their
brain and be cognitively normal, as you said, but does that mean that they're in this weird delicate
balance of if there is any more neurodegeneration or any more amyloid or any more tau, which we'll
talk about soon, build up that they're going to just fall off a cliff and symptoms will present.
Or does that mean nothing in terms of cognition? And this comes up a lot more recently with all of
the new studies. What are we looking at? Are we looking at amyloid deposition, amyloid biomarkers,
are we looking at people's cognition? What markers should we be following? And I think
you and I both agree that it really should be cognition. Yeah. And I want to, I've made a
note to actually come back to cognitive testing because I think it's super interesting. Let's,
let's go on to tau. Talk about these, these neurofibular rectangles and, and, you know,
where do we see them being distinct from amyloid? And then I want to come back and talk about
amyloid serum amyloid as well. And the advent of that in the past few years. So right at the start
of COVID sometime in 2020, they FDA approved a tau scan. So there isn't a tau scan. It, again,
both amyloid and tau scans are not covered by insurance. So the clinical utility of these
scans is pretty low just because the cost of them is so high. It costs several thousands of
dollars to get these scans to pay out of pocket, but tau scans are. And there are a ton of radiation.
So these aren't scans. You just want to be doing willy nilly. Like it's not like,
Hey, I'm going to go through McDonald's drive through, get a burger fries, and then go head
over and get a tau scan. I mean, that's, I want to say they're in the 10 to 20 milli-sieverts.
Yep. Yeah. Yeah. So that that's an insane amount of radiation for shits and giggles.
It's you need a real reason to do that. Yep, exactly. So understand, there's a school of
thought, let's rewind a little bit here. So there's a school of thought that says that,
and I don't necessarily subscribe to the school of thought, but you first have amyloid, then you
have tau, then you have neuro inflammation, and then you have neuro degeneration. So amyloid is
thought to be one of the first markers, but I don't, I don't really agree with this a hundred
percent. And I think every person is different. So you can't really make this a hard and fast
rule. But looking at tau scans in the setting of also having an amyloid scan could be helpful.
If you're just looking at tau scans, you're looking at, does this person have tau accumulation in the
brain? These tau scans may be more sensitive, may, may, may be more sensitive at detecting
Alzheimer's specific tau versus other tau related to other tau opathies like frontotemporal dementia.
But the utility of the tau scan is that it tells us more about the progression or the likelihood
that someone will develop cognitive impairment. So if someone has positive tau on their tau scan,
the likelihood that they'll ultimately develop cognitive decline is higher than just amyloid.
So looking at them together, although we would never do that because of radiation and cost
concerns, like you said, if you had the amyloid and tau simultaneously at the same time, you could get
a pretty decent snapshot of what someone's brain looked like and where they are.
Is tau also this thing like amyloid where it's there all the time and we're clearing it and it's
potentially our impairment of clearing it that leads to the pathology?
So you're asking, is tau reversible? Actually, I wasn't asking that, but we should discuss that.
I guess what I'm saying is, look, we know that amyloid is present all the time, but we, again,
using sleep as an example, sleep is a very powerful tool to clear amyloid. Is the same true of tau?
I don't think we have a good answer for that. We don't really know because we really haven't
been looking at tau for that long. Yeah. And so is there no serum biomarker on the horizon for tau?
So there is. We can talk about serum biomarkers now because I think it's a good leeway. So C2N,
if it's okay, if we talk about the Perciviti test, came out recently and that's actually a great
marker for amyloid. So it shows you the amyloid beta 40 to 42 ratio. So it encompasses someone's
APOE status. So it gives an amyloid probability score based on someone's APOE status. And the
accuracy at predicting just from the simple blood test, a positive amyloid scan is around 80, 81%.
So super, super high when you add tau, which now is not clinically available, but is available
for research purposes. So tau 217 is a new biomarker that has been brought to this game and
looking at ratios of phosphorylated to non phosphorylated, PTau 217, it adds to that. So
you're looking at accuracy of around 90% to amyloid scans. As you know, we've got one patient in
particular who were using this serum amyloid level to track interventions in, and in particular,
one kind of unusual intervention, which is rapamycin. So too soon to really know with an
N of one, but very interesting that rapamycin is dropping his serum amyloid score. Well, this
patient is fascinating in so many ways if we want to think about just biomarkers because we collected
every single biomarker possible minus the tau scan on him. So first and foremost, the old school way
of diagnosing these diseases was to do a spinal tap and look at cerebral spinal fluid. Well,
we did that. We looked at amyloid. I was kicking and screaming not to, but you and Richard overruled
me. Yes, I know. And he was such a good sport. The patient was such a good sport. Such a good sport.
Bless him. So we looked at CSF biomarkers in him and actually they were all normal,
all negative, but we got the C2N's Perciviti test and that showed that it was positive, that
the likelihood of him having amyloid pathology was high. We discussed this with so many people,
including our neuro radiologist colleague. And she was like, let's just do an amyloid scan. Let's
get to the bottom of this. We did an amyloid scan and he had amyloid deposition in the brain. So
this brings us to another really, really interesting and exciting direction for these
serum tests because we're noticing that they may be more sensitive at detecting early, early
Alzheimer's disease pathology, even better than amyloid, even better, amyloid scans,
even better than CSF biomarkers. And certainly more available. I mean, CS, I mean, it's, I don't
think people understand like, yeah, lumbar punctures are not the most invasive procedure
in the world, but if you have one patient that needs a blood patch, you just never want to do
that procedure again to somebody. Yep. Yep. But looking at that and then having the ability to
so readily repeat measures, while we don't know if we can follow amyloid over time to see if our
interventions are actually effective, in theory, it makes a lot of sense. And as you pointed out,
we put him on a slew of neuroprotective agents and tried to optimize everything possible for him
and including rapamycin and his amyloid biomarkers have gone down and now he's considered normal,
like low probability of having Alzheimer's disease, but we know that his scan was positive.
It's a really fascinating case. So let's segue then into something that I think is
the art form of this, which is the cognitive testing. And it's in some ways the hardest part,
because it's not easy to standardize. I mean, there's a reason that we have someone like you
in our practice, because this is not something that me or Eve, Suzanne, Abhi, like the rest of
us can't learn to do this. We can't outsource it to a computer. We can't tell our patients to go
take a test that will give us the results. There's real subtlety to this in terms of
everything from movement to vision to olfactory to these. So give people a sense of what a cognitive
test looks like. What does a gold plate cognitive test look like if you're really trying to probe
the earliest leading edge of these types of diseases? So I will also correct you that some
of it can actually be self-administered, but some of it needs to be administered by a trained
professional. You can get a lot of information by having patients do some things by themselves,
but paying attention to them gives you a lot of clues. Yeah, I think that's what I meant. I think
it's like it's the, well, by all means, correct me and point out what can be completely done
automated. But yes, I think part of it comes down to the art. I mean, Richard has done a great job
of sort of helping me understand what you learn by watching somebody take the test as well. Yes,
that's the art of this assessment. So first and foremost, getting a sense of their olfaction
is key because olfaction is- That's why I can't do this test today. I'm so congested. Yes. I'm
going to go, there's like nine things that we make them smell, right? Yes, yes. There's nine things,
although we might be elaborating that battery to include a lot more, so stay tuned for that.
Great. I'd fail that test today. So what are those things that we make people smell and why
does this matter so much? Yeah, well, I can't tell you what they are because then there are
patients on the call that may know the answers to the test. Very well, very well. Okay. So there
are nine things that you're going to have to smell. Yes. And the idea here is, you know,
cranial nerve number one is your olfactory nerve. Correct. So you have basically from your nose,
a cranial nerve that goes straight to the front of your brain that presumably is like that leading
edge of immediate access to a cranial nerve that could be degenerating. Is that the thinking? Yeah.
And if you think about just sense of smell in general, it feeds directly into the amygdala
and the hippocampus. So the whole memory circuit, if you think about odor is actually one of the
strongest sense that relates to memory. If you smell something that you smell before,
you just get very nostalgic for whatever that experience is. Positive or negative? Yes. It's
very, very ingrained into memory. So it's one of the first nerves, for lack of a better word,
first parts of the nervous system to degenerate in these diseases. And it happens not just in
Alzheimer's disease. It happens in Lewy body. It happens in Parkinson's disease. When it does
happen in these cases, we actually note that those patients are more likely to have cognitive
decline. So it really does relate to memory. So yes, first and foremost, olfactory testing.
Has COVID changed that with people?
COVID has made this so, so difficult because the earlier strains of COVID really did impact
sense of smell. And for some patients, that sense of smell has taken months to a year or more to
recover. And for other patients, it still hasn't really recovered. And what are the implications
of that long-term? I don't know if we know yet. Does it relate to later likelihood or higher
likelihood later of developing a neurodegenerative disorder? I don't know, but it's something
interesting and something that only time will tell. Okay. So they get these little sticks,
these little cards, and they have to go through that exercise. Okay. What else do they, what other
types of things do we test for in cognitive testing? So memory function is another one,
but there are so many domains to memory. So there's registering the information, reading,
registering, auditory, and visual registering of information, which go into memory. Then the
encoding process. So just to be, when you hear something, do you remember it? When you see
something, do you remember it? And does it matter how you report that you remember it? Is it, is it
reporting it by writing versus reporting it orally? Do those things matter as well? So for most people,
auditory processing is more difficult. And when you're doing auditory processing, all of it has
to be done auditor, through auditory. So I would ask you, I'm going to read you a story and you're
going to tell me everything you remember from that story. And that's your immediate one learning of
the information. So I'll read it to you three times. You'll try to remember as much as you can,
how much did you learn over those three trials? That's all auditory. And then in 20 or 30 minutes,
how much do you remember? That's delayed memory. So you're looking at immediate learning,
working memory and delayed memory. Now, how do we
ferret out the people who underperform these tests because of distraction?
Yeah, so that's why we do attention tasks. So there are a whole slew of different attention
tasks and speed of processing tasks. Usually you have to get people in a quiet room,
undistracted, make sure their cell phones are off, make sure they're not doing anything on
their computers to really focus on the test. But you have to add in these other cognitive
exercises, which are looking at their attentional capacity, because often you will see distraction
is a huge, huge confounder when you're looking at memory. If you're not paying attention to
something, you're never going to remember it. Yeah, I can think of, imagine me trying to take
this test at home, like would be a disaster compared to if I woke up in a quiet place and
got to take it under those conditions. Yeah, we tell people get a good night's sleep. If you didn't
get a good night's sleep, we're not going to do the test for you because you're just not going to do
well on it. Make sure you do it first thing in the morning is really better. Or sometimes you feel
relaxed. Don't try to squeeze it in between work meetings because you're going to rush and again,
not really focus on the test. So there are things that you should do to optimize your chances of
giving this your best shot. Yeah, treat this like it's the one shot you get at the SAT.
Exactly. Your MCAT. Yeah. Okay, so those sound really stressful. What else?
Visual spatial processing and episodic memory, which is really, really difficult for a lot of
patients, actually, it's one of the ones people struggle with. So trying to see where an object
is and remember the sequence that you saw that object. So you're given a series of objects.
When did you see this? And what order? And what order? Put them in the order that you saw.
So like a series of cards, for example. Yes. So you got to remember if you saw the car before
you saw the garbage can. Very difficult. And it's easy when you're only shown four or five or six
objects, but when you're shown 10 or 12 objects, it becomes very, very challenging. So that's really
testing your working memory, but also some visual spatial. Visual spatial skills are tested a lot by
writing and drawing, copying cubes, drawing clocks, old fashioned things from med school that you
probably remember actually give a lot of information and there's still things we use today.
What about horsepower, like executive function, problem solving? Yeah. IQ test stuff. IQ test stuff.
So verbal learning and being able to pronounce very tricky words is actually a really good proxy for
IQ and is one of the ways that we look at that. Just showing us an understanding of what this
person's cognitive reserve is because having that foundation is really important for understanding
what, how you should interpret the results to follow. Because if someone's IQ is much lower
than you expected, then you really have to interpret the rest of the results in the setting of that.
So there's obviously a language bias then. So how are you testing? Like if you're encountering
a patient for whom English is their second language, how are you able to administer this
test and not be misled by it? Yeah. So there are different versions of the test. And if English is
not your first language, it's just something that we note because we could get access to all different
versions of the test, but it is challenging to do that because the norms are all different and you
have to just purchase a bunch of different forms and norms. Ideally, you would do this in person,
but I know since COVID, it became more possible to do this remotely. Do you still feel that's the
case? Yes. There are certain pen and paper tasks that we send to patients because you do need to
do some of the motor activities by writing, but pretty much we can do everything remotely now.
How long does the test take? An hour, an hour and a half.
Okay. That's less than I thought. I thought it was longer. Yeah. Other things that we test for.
So executive function is really, really broad and really cross-cutting on a bunch of different
tasks, but without giving away too many secrets, thinking about naming certain categories of
objects or naming certain words that start with specific letters. That's how you look at
executive function. Now, how do you retest people? What's the frequency at which you can retest so
that you don't sort of run the risk that they're learning the test and improving because of
getting better at the skill of the test as opposed to getting cognitively better?
You change the forms first and foremost, so you don't really administer the same test multiple
times. Interestingly, APOE-4s are immune to the learning effect, so they actually don't learn as
well. So you can retest them in about six months and learning isn't really a factor to consider for
them, but there are equations to correct for that when you're looking at normative values.
How often does the FDA use the performance on a battery of tests like this as an endpoint?
Oh, I mean, when the FDA is using things, they're looking at
things like mini mental status and the Montreal MoCA test.
Tell folks what these two helpful tests are.
Yeah, so one is the Trump test. So if people have heard of that, how Trump aced a very difficult
cognitive test, well, yes, that was one of these where you have to name, this is a lion.
These are a sequence of numbers. Just repeat them back to me forward and backwards. So they're
basic 30 question tests where you're asked what the date is, where are you?
Who's the president?
Who's the president? They're very basic and rudimentary.
Yeah, these are tests we would use in the emergency room when we wanted to know if someone
was psychotic or heavily under the influence of alcohol, drugs, things like that.
Yeah. And to be fair, they do give you a very good sense of if someone is very cognitively
impaired, they're going to do very poorly on this test. But for most people who come to you and say,
I just noticed I'm forgetting things, they're probably still going to ace the test and it's
not giving you a good sense of, well, is it an actual memory problem or are they distracted?
Like we pointed out before, is it an attention problem? There are so many things that can go
wrong when someone says that they're forgetting that you really have to dissect that problem more.
The potential risk here is that we're not using a sharp enough outcome tool to measure
either drug efficacy or timing. And that kind of gets to another question, which is,
are we looking at intervening too late? So I think most people are familiar with the notion that
the track record for Alzheimer's treatment drugs is pretty abysmal. How many FDA approved
drugs are there for treatment of Alzheimer's disease?
Well, if you count, we have denepazil or Airecept, we have, so there's a couple in the same class,
I think there's three of them. And N amenda, those are the big ones and Aducanumab, I mean,
that's all we're looking at. Aducanumab being the most recent one approved about a year and a half
ago. Yeah. Which now has had a lot of backlash and Medicare is not paying for it. So it's been a
whole big mess. Yeah, which is, and I think we've discussed this on a previous podcast,
so I won't rehash it, but the gist of it is basically this was a drug that was
targeting amyloid directly. It really split the FDA. And I think members of the advisory panel
even resigned over its approval. If you're in the bull camp on that, you'd say that drug is
misunderstood, that drug would have efficacy if used early enough. And if you use the right
metrics to assess its performance, if you're in the bear camp, you'd say it's an incremental drug
that if it has any benefit, it doesn't come close to justifying its cost. Yeah. And I think this
gets back to, I don't know the answer to that question, but this gets back to we need to do
a better job at identifying what stage someone is in the disease process and where, when and how the
disease can be reversed if it can be, which I think that it can be. I think the breast cancer
example is really apt here, which is my fear with all of these neurodegenerative diseases
is we are acting at the wrong time. Exactly. And it's exactly like saying,
we take a bunch of women with stage four breast cancer and we do lumpectomies on them
and they don't live any longer. And we think therefore the lumpectomy has no place in the
treatment of breast cancer. When in reality, the lumpectomy has no treatment in the place of women
with metastatic breast cancer. And it is the standard of care in women with stage one breast
cancer and it will save their life. Exactly. And that's my fear is when it comes to neurodegeneration,
we don't know what the, as you said, we don't know the stages. We don't know the difference
between stage one, stage two, stage three, stage four. And we certainly don't know what treatments
to apply when. And most of the treatments that are being applied are being applied at what would be
the equivalent of stage four. Exactly. So by that time, what can you really do? Because
you can't reverse the neurodegeneration once it's already happened. You have to start earlier and
another large target for these drugs and new biotech companies are the inflammation process,
the neuroinflammation, which is a huge factor. And I do think plays a huge role. But again,
the question is in who and when, and without having a plethora of biomarkers that you're
looking at to really handpick patients appropriately, I don't know how we'll show
efficacy of these drugs. Let's go back to something you alluded to very briefly earlier,
which is the role of the visual and auditory systems in these diseases. So I think it's
generally well accepted that there is an association between hearing loss and dementia.
Is it Alzheimer's specific or all forms of dementia? It's all forms of dementia, but most
of the literature is surrounding dementia as a broad term, which they usually mean Alzheimer's
disease. I've talked about this with Richard quite a bit. And he's really of the mindset that
there's a causative relationship there. And that's a big deal because again, if you can just say,
well, there's an association between hearing loss and dementia, it's like, well, okay, yeah,
I mean, that makes sense. But if you think that that relation is causative, and that's why it's
just so important to understand causality, it means that treating hearing loss will reduce
the risk of dementia. It means that screening for hearing loss early and treating it aggressively
will improve outcomes. And that's totally different from just saying,
yep, they're just highly associated. So Richard's view is that, yeah, we should be doing this. I
think you share that view. Why is that? Yeah, we should be doing this. So there are a lot of
schools of thought on how this is related to neurodegenerative diseases and Alzheimer's
specifically. But the one that I think I like the most or the two that I think I like the most are,
when you can't hear, you're increasing cognitive load to the brain, which is taking cognitive
function or taking cognitive abilities away from other processes of the brain. So for example,
memory function, working memory, because your brain is focused on trying to hear or trying to see it's
using all of its power to do that. And it's diverting resources away from building memory
function. But the other factor, which I think really relates to the movement aspect is our
brains need sensory input. And when you aren't giving that sensory input to the brain, you lose
that function. And hearing is so important for verbal processing, vision is so important for
visual spatial processing. These are all cognitive functions that if you're not giving the sensory
input that the brain is craving, you're probably not building those pathways anymore. You're not
diversifying your brain, your brain's experience. I think both of those are, they again, I don't
know if those things are right. But if, if, if there is a causative relationship between visual
and hearing loss, those two mechanisms make a lot of sense. I want to make sure I understood them.
The first is, if you were becoming deficient in those areas, you're wasting, quote unquote,
more of your cognitive energy on the acquisition of those inputs to the system. And in doing so,
you're detracting from the capacity to do other things. We have a finite amount of this reserve.
The second thing is you're now deficient at gathering inputs that foster the neuro development,
plasticity, formation creation of better outputs. So you're going to process information worse if
you can't hear, you're going to process your environment worse if you can't see. Correct.
Correct. So you'll move worse. You'll think less. And there's just clinical evidence to support this.
So there's something called recurorescence in stroke. When someone had a stroke a while ago,
it might have been a small stroke, it might have been a large stroke, but they pretty much recovered
from their stroke until their body's under some sort of other stress. So they have a urinary tract
infection or an ammonia, something that puts any sort of stress. That stroke, those symptoms that
once were a part of their old stroke come back out called recurorescence. It's like the brain
can't handle doing too many things at once. It can only divert, it can only deal with that wound
in its brain by having all of its brain power focused on it. If it doesn't, then it's diverting
some of its resources someplace else, then those symptoms come back out again. It's sort of similar
to that. Wow. Let's talk about oral health. This is something you're interested in, something you've
spent a lot of time thinking about. It certainly makes sense. I've, as you know, become more and
more interested in this idea that the health of your gums, the health of your teeth is
actually quite a strong predictor of the health of you as an organism.
It's hard to have very poor health in your mouth and have very good health in the rest of your body.
How do you think this pertains to the brain specifically? 100%, I could not have said that
better. So there are certain red complex pathogens, three bad guys in particular, one Trepanema,
Dendicola, P. gingivalis, and T. forsynthea. These microbes are associated with a higher risk of
amyloid deposition, tau deposition, and inflammation. So knowing if you have these
red complex bacteria, which drive periodontal disease, these are all gram negatives, gram
negative bacteria. Right. So when you have a high colonization in your mouth with these bacteria,
your peripheral inflammation is driven way up. And when you think about somebody who has an apo
E4, for example, a 3,4, or 4,4, why would you ever want them to be under any more inflammation?
If you know E4 is priming my greglia activation, then adding any layer of something that's going
to trigger more inflammation is just a bad idea. So focusing on oral health, especially in high
risk patients is huge. And I think really an overlooked part of this whole picture,
there is some debate and there is some evidence for this that potentially these bacteria can
ectopically migrate either through the blood or through cranial nerves to the actual brain
because they've identified them in autopsy specimen. But I don't know if that's true. I
don't know if it's the bacteria going to the brain themselves that's causing damage.
I think it's more of the inflammation that's triggering part of the damage and it being in
such close proximity to the brain, having all of these cranial nerves kind of right there,
right by the mouth. I think that's the bigger issue.
And do we know if the greatest driver of that risk is simply poor oral hygiene?
Poor oral hygiene, but also which comes first here. So dental implants, root canals,
just external hardware in your mouth. Those are just, they're just night is for these bacteria
to form on. And we notoriously don't clean them as well. People who wear retainers at night after
their braces or a mouth guard because they grind their teeth at night. They aren't really cleaning
these specimen very effectively and they're just loaded with bacteria and often flossing is
overlooked. And it's not just flossing. Flossing is great, but really using a water pick or an
interproximal brush or something that goes in between the teeth that has a little feather at
the end that you're really scraping away. The bacteria is what you need.
Okay. Let's return to AD and double click on the genes. Again, I think most people listening to this,
if they've spent any time listening to this podcast, they're very well familiar of the APO
E4 situation. We've got these three isoforms for the same gene, APOE. You've got the two,
three and four isoform and they can combine in every possible way. So there's six combinations.
The normal one is the three, three combo. That's 50 to five, 55, 60% of the population, correct?
Yep. The high risk gene is the four. High risk isoform is the four. The low risk isoform is the
two. The two seems very rare. I don't think I've ever seen a two, two. We have seen one person with
a two, two. I've never seen a two, two, but two, three is two fours and it's 5% less than 5% of
the population. But let's talk about the four fours and the three fours. These are your higher risk
populations. Your three fours are probably 20 to 25% of the population. Four fours are one to
2% of the population. In our practice, it's four or 5% of our practice is four, four, but I think
we have a selection, a little bit of a selection bias. Maybe more than that actually. Obviously,
when you were still at Cornell, you saw lots of four fours. That was probably a quarter of your
population. Yep. You've often said, and Richard said this as well, you don't get that stressed
out when you see a patient when you have a really clear sense that their risk is predicated through
their E4-ness. Yeah. Not to make light of E4, but you talk about it like it's the enemy you know.
Easy peasy. Piece of cake. Yeah. So first, expand on why you would make such a statement and then
two, I want to talk about the things that are able to either make the E4 worse or potentially
even make the E4 better. Meaning reduce the risk or amplify the risk of E4. We know what to do when
we see an APOE4. It's when somebody doesn't have an APOE4 and has a family history. That's very
notable for dementia Alzheimer's, some neurodegenerative disease. Also,
Lewy body E4s are at risk for Lewy body dementia too, which is something that we frequently
overlook. So when we see a three three and we see a family history, then we start scratching our
heads. Like what is the pathogenic mechanism that's driving this person and this family to
develop Alzheimer's or a related neurodegenerative disease? When we see an APOE4, we kind of
understand more about how that impacts the body. We understand its role in peripheral cholesterol,
which also relates to its role in central or brain cholesterol. We know how it impacts their
ability to metabolize carbohydrates. We understand kind of what we're up against when we see it. And
I just want to emphasize because so many people come and they're so afraid once they found out
that they have an APOE4 or they're just so afraid because they have a family history and they don't
want to know what their genes are, but your genes are not your destiny. There are ways that we can
intervene to mitigate some of the detrimental effects of these genes. So what are some of the
other genes that are cousins of E4 that travel with E4 or that frankly don't, but add independently
to risk or subtract independently from risk? Yeah. So APOC1 and Tom40 are two genes that are
located right around the APOE4 upstream downstream. That's two M's in Tom, right? Yeah, Tom with two
M's 40. And they are tightly associated with APOE4, meaning they're linked. Most people, if they
inherited the quote harmful copy of APOE4, I'm going to say quote because I don't know how harmful
it is anymore now that we're better at managing it, but they'll also inherit the quote harmful
copy of Tom40, harmful copy of APOC1, most cases 90% of the time. But in some patients, they don't.
Are these protein coding genes or are they in the non-coding regions that Tom40 and C1, APOC1?
They're protein coding genes. So when you don't inherit them and you're looking at someone who
is a 3, 4 or a 2, 4, 2, 4s are really great examples because if you see that they inherited
the lower risk variance in Tom40 or APOC1, then I'm thinking, well, they're less likely to behave
like an E4 and more likely to behave like a 2, 3 versus the other way around. Then I get very
worried about their E4 expressing themselves. And I start thinking we need to really hammer down on
their cholesterol. We need to do much better with vascular risk factor control. Yeah. So the Tom40
APOC1 can swing the balance. Yes. Yes. So it does provide a huge piece of information for a small
portion of people, but for that small portion, it's really, really life-changing and changes
management. Yeah. So what about genes that are less tightly linked to APOE4 that either up or down
turn the risk? So Clotho is a big one. And I know you're a huge- It's my favorite gene. Yeah.
You love Clotho. Love you some Clotho. So Clotho seems to offer a protective role against APOE4.
It doesn't completely erase the harmful effects of APOE4, but it really does lessen it. And it has
an effect on the rate of cognitive decline. So if you have Clotho heterozygosity, then we're more
optimistic about how we look about your- And just so people know what we're talking about,
we say heterozygous, meaning you have one wild type, and then you have one of the protective one,
which is the KLVS SNP. Yes. Yes. And this is- We were talking about this the other day. In the
literature, this is like, I don't know, one in six people would be heterozygous. It's actually pretty
hard to make this diagnosis because there is no off-the-shelf test for this SNP. No, there's not.
You need whole genome sequencing. Yeah. Which again, for the listener, that is a real impediment
to this work right now. It is. We have some E4s in our practice, E4E4s, who you and Richard have
looked at and you don't even think they're worth talking to. They're so uninteresting, which is a
good thing. If you don't want to talk to them, that's a good sign. E4E4s, think about that. And
I remember the first time Richard met some of these people two or three years ago, he's like-
Nard. This person has nothing wrong with them and will have nothing wrong with them.
I'm convinced that they are cloth OK LVSs, but it's not just that you got to spend all the money
on the whole genome sequence, it's that you got to get somebody to go through the data and pull
out the sequence. Yeah. Richard and I are working on a process of streamlining this. It is so labor
intensive. It's a little back of the napkin mom and pop right now, but you have to manually go
through the genome and pull out all of the relevant SNPs. There's no SNPs, meaning portions
of the DNA that pertain to risk. There's no fast way of doing it. And more than that, you have to
do it in a logical way because if someone has an E4 versus an E3, you're going to look at a
completely different set of genes and a completely different set of SNPs or variants than you are
going to look at for someone who is a three. It's so frustrating that this is such an easy
problem for AI to solve. Yes. And it doesn't need that many resources. It just needs somebody to say,
you know what, we should just automate this once and for all, spend a few million dollars on the
process. Yes. And everybody can drop their whole genome sequence in there and you can get the
answer. That's what we're trying to do a better job and work on because I think we can develop
a software that is able to do this more rapidly, but right now it is so labor intensive and so
expensive. Yeah. I also think that the KLVS clotho mutation would be a great CRISPR target one day.
Yes. Yes, it might be. Yeah. I think the longevity benefits of that transformation would be enormous.
But going back to, I mean, just teaching a software how to do this, part of it is, and thinking about
the example that you pointed out that there's E4 fours that we're just not interested in,
part of that is you have to understand that person's risk factors. So if they have no family
history of Alzheimer's disease or a neurodegenerative disease whatsoever, they're a lower
likelihood of getting this disease later, even if they're four four. Yeah. Okay. The other one I know
we've talked a lot about is mitochondrial haplotype. This is a bit more complicated because it's not a
gene per se. So explain what the mitochondrial haplotype is and what it tells us about risk and
how difficult is that to measure? So the mitochondria going way back to evolution. So
they were once thought to be their own organisms that the body devoured and developed a symbiotic
relationship with. So they are one of the few organelles in the cell that have, the only organelle
in the cell that has their own genome. So the mitochondrial genome has genes that relate to
oxidative phosphorylation or how the body makes energy. So the Cox genes and NAD genes,
all of these genes are encoded in the mitochondrial DNA. Mitochondrial haplogroups are labeled based on
what different variants are found in different genes in that mitochondrial DNA. And there are
more than 4,000 mitochondrial haplotypes. So there are a ton of mitochondrial haplotypes. And again,
they're based on what variants are common among all members of a shared group. So for example,
there is a risk snip that I wouldn't say risk, there's a snip that is associated with
mitochondrial haplogroup H and all members that are categorized as haplogroup H have this variant.
So two things, one, how difficult or easy is it to determine your mitochondrial haplotype? Is it as
complicated as, is it more clotho or more Tom 40 E4? So it's very, very difficult. 23andMe
generates their own mitochondrial haplogroups. And the way that they do it is they have a few
markers that they pull out of the DNA that pertain to each specific haplogroup. So that's how they
identify someone's haplogroup. It's actually not perfect. If you really wanted to know someone's
haplogroup, you have to sequence the entire mitochondrial genome and use specific software.
No, I don't think 23andMe can do that, right? No, 23andMe cannot. But you can do it through
whole genome sequencing, adding on mitochondrial DNA sequencing and analyze the mitochondrial
genome, but you need specific software to do so. And it's really much more challenging than the
whole genome or the. So why does this matter? Why do we want to know the haplotype or haplogroup
of the mitochondria? How does it tell us less? I mean, let's just assume it tells us risk is up,
one, one enough. But even if it's telling you risk is higher, what insight does it impart as far as
preventative strategies? So super helpful and understanding risk, especially for APOE4s,
but also for other neurodegenerative diseases. And interestingly, the same haplotypes that
put you at risk for Alzheimer's also put you at risk for Parkinson's disease. So for example,
haplotype H, if you have this haplotype and you're in APOE4, it seems to enable the E4 or act
synergistically with the E4. So when we see that combination, we become a little bit more concerned
about this person versus somebody who is a haplogroup K because K seems protective,
especially for APOE4s. Okay. If you have someone that's a type H, do you have any sense of what
preventative measures are more important than others? So just knowing what type of haplogroup
they are gives us insight into how their mitochondria are behaving. So if we know someone
isn't an efficient energy producer or their mitochondria aren't acting efficiently,
let's rev up their zone too. Let's try to get them as many mitochondria as we can. Let's increase
their density of mitochondria because that might circumvent some of the negative effects of their
mitochondria, just not working as efficiently at generating ATP or energy. So talking about that,
talking about exercise, my view has largely been that there's probably no activity that you can
participate in that will have a greater impact on your brain's health than exercise. Now, obviously,
you have to take that with a caveat. All the exercise in the world won't help you if you're
sleeping four hours a night. It can't offset that much damage. But in terms of additive activity,
it seems to me exercise matters more than anything else. It certainly matters more than
the finicky nuance that someone might make in their diet of like, oh, I'm going to take out
nightshades and all of a sudden that's going to fix all my problems or something
sort of idiotic like that. Would you agree that exercise has the most potential to
improve brain health? And that's not just in the healthy, but obviously in the preventative
strategy. Wholeheartedly. I think exercise has the potential to move the needle the most.
So what is it about that? Because exercise does so many things. What do you think are the levers
that it's pulling? So when I think about exercise, I kind of break it down into categories in my head.
So there's the coordination proprioceptive balance type exercise, which you can include dance under
that, for example, which some people don't really think about dance as an exercise, but it's an
incredibly powerful exercise for the brain because you're not just getting the physical heart rate
elevation. You're getting the cognitive training, which is involved in the coordination and the
choreographed movement. So you're trying to process the visual information and make your body do that
activity or do that movement, which is both a cognitive workout and a physical workout. So this
is a way of increasing cognitive reserve, increasing neuroplasticity that has probably a different
effect than something like zone two, for example, which is involved in improving someone's energy,
metabolism and inefficiency, which is very different than strength training, which is equally
important for building muscle mass and metabolic health and so on. So you have the metabolic
component, right? You have the vascular component. You then have like BDNF. What role do you think
BDNF plays here? So I think BDNF plays a huge role, but it's hard to say how much that plays versus
how much just higher intensity cardio exercise is increasing cerebral blood flow, which is
increasing nutrient oxygen delivery to the brain. But BDNF is what we call a fertilizer for the
brain. So it helps protect new brain cells, but also helps grow new brain cells specifically in
the temporal lobes or the memory centers of the brain. So stimulating BDNF is a potential one of
the potentially large benefits of exercise. Does anything stimulate more BDNF than exercise?
I don't think so.
What role does hypertension play here? There are certain organs that are so clearly related to
high blood pressure negatively, right? So the kidney and the heart, there's just no ambiguity.
More blood pressure is just bad for the kidney, is bad for the heart. Once baseline perfusion
levels are met, obviously every organ suffers if blood pressure is too low in a pathologic sense.
So if somebody's hypovolemic in shock or something like that, but 120 over 80 is all you need to
perfuse the kidney and to perfuse the heart. And we now know that 135 over 85, that's going to start
causing damage. What do we know about that with respect to the brain? So the sprint mind study
looked at this and lower is better. So 120 over 70 more strict blood pressure control seems better
for cognitive outcomes long-term. I will also circle back and say that what we see in some of
these diseases, especially the Lewy bodies and Parkinson's is autonomic instability. So blood
pressure fluctuations, which is very tricky to deal with because what we'll see is at night,
someone may have higher blood pressure when they're laying flat, but when they're up and about during
the day, when you're actually measuring their blood pressure, it's not very high. So you could
be misled living a fool's paradise, thinking that they're actually norm intensive, which
we'll consider less than 120 over 70 or brain, but they're not. So you really got to check what
their blood pressure is at night when they're laying down or first thing in the morning before
they get out of bed. Yeah, it's funny. So I'm just going to get back up on my soapbox,
climb back on it. So I was on my soapbox a minute ago, pleading for somebody to do the AI work to
figure out, so we can figure out everybody's clotho status and mitochondrial haplotype like that.
This might even be a slightly higher soapbox. People know how much I'm a fan of continuous
glucose monitors because that type of information, whether you only choose to wear one of these
things for a month or you choose to wear one for a year, even if you're not diabetic, the insights
are profound and they will forever change the way you think about eating, exercise, stress, and
sleep. 100%. They just show you that in your play. As much as I'm a fan of that, I would right now
get rid of CGM for the non-diabetic, if I were Czar for a day, if in exchange I could have a
continuous blood pressure monitor that was perfect and seamless and you could stick a patch on and
have real time continuous blood pressure monitoring, that would be even more valuable for the reason
you just stated. 100%. This is one where I just lose sleep over it for myself and for my patients,
which is I really don't know what my blood pressure is most of the time. Even if I check my
blood pressure twice a day sitting at my desk, it tells me nothing about what my blood pressure is
the other 23 hours, 59 minutes, and 30 seconds of the day. We don't have a tool to do that yet well.
I've tried every supposed continuous blood pressure monitor out there. The ones that work
are so cumbersome that you can't use them. The clinical grade stuff where it's a cuff
attached to a big battery pack and you're walking around, it looks like you've got an LVAD.
Those work, but they're not practical. Then the little wrist bracelets and stuff are total garbage.
We're just waiting for some technology to change the game. I just can't wait for this and I hope
it occurs soon because it's such an urgent need. Not just in terms of everything we're talking about,
but when you start to think about cardiovascular disease, we're really missing. It's like imagining.
Imagine not knowing if you were a smoker. As dumb as that sounds, you can't tell if you
smoke or not, but you might. Yeah, no. We have no data. What's worse is it's very difficult to
think of how you could develop a device that isn't interfering with your sleep because if you want to
check it when you're sleeping, you don't want it to cause another problem, cause you not to sleep.
But then you start thinking about, well, even if you did have just high blood pressure at night,
well, there probably are things you could do because there's short acting medications that
you could maybe just dose before bedtime. During the day when your blood pressure is fine, you're
up and around great. But at night when you're actually hypertensive, which is half of your day,
essentially, you are treating that. But right now we're just living in fool's paradise because we
have no idea what your blood pressure is doing at night. Okay. So good to note that, or bad to note,
but good to note that we got to keep our blood pressure low here as well. Yeah.
We all know that Alzheimer's disease disproportionately affects women two to one.
My belief personally, which is not unique, is that I think it's the hormone reduction that's
doing that. I don't think it's, I think very little of that is explained by women slightly
outliving men. I really think it's the sudden loss of estrogen in particular, and maybe testosterone
that feeds into that. What do you think, what do you think is driving this two to one gap between
men and women in Alzheimer's? Well, so something that's interesting and recently discovered in
nature, I think it was published in April or maybe May, but we can link to it in the show notes.
The MGMT gene. So the MGMT gene is a very powerful DNA repair gene in both men and women, but
it seems to, there are certain variants in this gene which seem to independent of ApoE influence
Alzheimer's risk specifically in women. And this gene is related to breast cancer as well.
So what is it about women that put them in a different category, even in terms of what
genes matter than men? It's more than just hormones, I think, but I don't know the answer.
I do think hormones play a huge role as you pointed out and the menopause transition,
which is a huge area of research right now and something that we really focus on in our patients
is something that has to be a high priority in women specifically because of this role of hormones.
But I think there are other factors at play. And just thinking of the counter argument to that,
when you think about Lewy body Parkinson's, well, that's much more common in men to a two to one
prevalence in men versus women. And is it sex and hormones that are driving that? Probably,
but in what way? I don't know. Yeah. Well, that's actually where I was going to ask you is what do
we think is explaining the opposite, which is why are men getting Lewy body and Parkinson's two to
one more than women? I don't know. I don't know what it is about the male sex that's really giving
us a higher risk or a lower risk for disease. But it's easy to point to hormones as the answer,
but I don't know if we have the data out there to actually say that. I think one day we'll be better
at really pinning down someone's risk in terms of incorporating biological sex and genetic risk
to give someone a more accurate understanding of what their individual risk is and then be able to
give them lifestyle and preventive strategies based on what we find there. But I don't think
we're there yet. It's hard to know what to do with hormones, especially in men.
So kind of thinking about this in terms of a wrap up, right? It seems that there are two big
themes that have come up here. One is the higher your cognitive process, the higher your cognitive
reserve, the more likely you are able to weather a storm here. So similarly, in a recession, it's
easier to weather a recession if you're not living paycheck to paycheck. It sounds like if I've
understood you, the same is true on the movement disorders that maybe the more facile you are with
movement, the more reserve you have to combat and delay the progression and or onset of the
alpha synuclein based pathologies as well. Yeah, I think which might, by the way, be the kind of the
other reason why a diversified portfolio of exercise matters. Yeah, I think when you think of
brain health, it's not just the cognitive piece, but it's the movement piece too, because there
are nerves throughout our whole body, not just our brain. So when we think about how do we optimize
our brain health, it has to be, yes, diversifying your cognitive experiences and managing your
vascular risk factors, but also bringing in the movement piece is such a huge piece of the puzzle
and something that I don't think people have really come to realize because we've been so
hyper focused on looking at what what's the blood work show. Let's look at what the movement
patterns show too. Yeah, this is something we're really excited about you and Beth working on
together with our patients. And then hopefully we can sort of figure out a way to share this more
broadly, which is, you know, using adding movement to cognitive testing to identify these problems as
soon as possible. Again, on the movement side, you know, we've been doing this for a long time. And
you know, you can sort of say, I know you're not in pain now, but because you move that way, you're
going to suffer an injury at some point might be a year from now, might be 10 years from now,
but you're on you're on the wrong path. If you make these changes now, you're on a better path.
When we can start to make that same relationship between movement and movement disorders. I mean,
that's fantastic. That's taking it to the next level. And that's where we need to be. And for
all the people that are listening who may be at risk for one of these movement disorders, or have
a loved one that is suffering from it, getting to the crux of the movement problem might be the
key to answering the question of how to prevent the disease. So I don't want you to overstate it.
But my final question for you, Kellyanne is with ambition, but not wishful thinking.
Where do you think we can be in five years with respect to everything we've talked about today?
So I will say that no one has incorporated exercise and movement the way that we're looking
at it now. I think just that alone is going to push the needle so far in the direction of making
it advance in the world of movement itself. In the world of Alzheimer's, like I said, they're so
related. Whatever we learn about one disease tells us so much about the other disease. We have to
stop thinking about them as so separate and more think about them as a continuum. I don't know what
the future holds, but I think if we start changing the way we're viewing the diseases and put them
more broadly under the term of neurodegeneration, identify what the problem is from the get-go,
not look at amyloid, not look at tau, not look at alpha synuclein as the ultimate problem,
but scaling way, way back. I think we can get much further than we've been.
And you think we will be able to do that with a better attention, a finer tooth comb,
on cognitive testing, which includes all of the dimensions you've talked about,
plus movement assessments. You think that those together, even before biomarkers, can start to
give us that very early indication of where someone might lie on a spectrum?
And genetics. I don't think you can do this without understanding genetics and family history.
I think with those pieces of information, yeah, we can move the needle pretty far.
And you're confident that we can then target preventative strategies.
Yeah. Once you understand what someone's at risk for and understand what their baseline is,
you can curate what strategies there are to prevent it in a particular person.
Yeah. We were talking about this last night. I just don't think there's any set of diseases
that are more frightening than this. I think when you look at all the big buckets on the
death bars that we so fastidiously keep track of.
Totally.
Yeah. Heart disease is the number one killer. Cancer is the number two killer.
I think we accept those risks. I think we kind of get it. And deep down, I think we all kind of
hope we're going to die of a heart attack in our sleep when we're 96 and that's that.
And nobody wants to die that way and nobody wants to die period, I suppose. And certainly
nobody wants to get cancer. But there really isn't any of these neurodegenerative conditions
that doesn't just leave you feeling completely petrified yourself and then completely at a
loss for what to do to help somebody who's suffering from it. So I applaud you for being
able to go into the world's one of the three most depressing fields of medicine and then somehow
carve out an optimistic piece of it.
Honestly, our waiting list at Cornell was more than five years long. And what one patient actually
said, I was told by my doctor that it's harder to get into this clinic than it is to get into
college, which is really, really sad. But that just goes to show the tremendous need for people
to start reevaluating how and when we're looking at disease. So, so much need. And the first thing
that patients would say when they would come to see us is how petrified they were. They saw their
family member go through such a disease that robbed them of essentially the person that they were.
They're no longer able to communicate. They don't recognize them like that's a terrible thing
in so many ways, so much more terrible than a heart attack. At least you still have your cognition.
I mean, granted, none of these things are good, but just losing your whole person is just so,
so hard. And that experience for so many people really drives and empowers them to do everything
that they can to ward off the disease. And most people would leave in tears just because they feel
like for once someone is listening and there's something that they can do to anything that they
can do to just change their fate. And their fate may not be what their parents fate was or their
grandparents fate was. It's huge. Well, Kaelianne, thanks for sitting down with us and walking
through all this stuff. It's super interesting and I'm excited about what we can do together.
Yes, me too. Thanks for having me. I'm looking forward to more discussions in the future.