Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Bill, thanks so much for coming by. I've been looking forward to this for a long time.
I have too. I'm really honored to be on your podcast.
So, I don't know, a little while ago I made a video on Instagram where I talked about
sort of three books I've read in the last 12 months that I didn't expect to sort of,
A, have such an impact on how I thought about things, but also B, even though they're completely
different books, they strike me as having kind of a unifying theme in this sort of thing
about quality of life. So, the three books are, one of them was From Strength to Strength,
one of them is 4000 Weeks, and the other one is Die with Zero. Now, what's interesting
is I know exactly who suggested I read 4000 Weeks, and I'm really good friends with the
author of From Strength to Strength, so that's why I just read that knowing it was coming
out. I still don't remember who recommended Die with Zero to me, but I remember just thinking,
okay, well, cool, sounds interesting, ordered it, and then kind of just couldn't put it
down. And as I think I mentioned in the video, immediately made my wife read it, and then
immediately just went out and bought many copies of it, along with many copies of the
other two books. So, I basically started handing them out as like a triplet copy. Like if someone
was over and they hadn't read them, boom, they were leaving with all three copies of
the book. So, that speaks to kind of why I wanted to sit down with you, and I guess I
just ... Let's give people a sense of who you are. So, you grew up in Jersey, right?
Yeah, I grew up in Jersey City, New Jersey. You're an engineer, we have that in common,
right? Yeah, except I don't want people to be impressive as an engineer. We had a saying
on the football team, Ds get degrees until later I found out, wait, you can't graduate
with a D in engineering, you have to at least get a C. So, I barely graduated. I was just
super slacker. So, I don't want to be like, I'm an engineer. What position did you play?
The bench. I played the bench, but I was a defensive back, a cornerback at the University
of Iowa. But did it pay for school? No, no, I was actually a walk-on. I was trying to
get a scholarship, I had a partial scholarship, which means they just give you some food.
I basically broke my leg at the growth plate, was pretty much has been before I ever was.
But when you love football, you love the sport, you never want to let go, right? You're not
like, oh, I'll just dive into my studies and pick up this hobby. You're kind of like
football is life at that age. So, what took you straight? So, you graduated college with
the degree in engineering, maybe you're not first in your class. You decide though, you're
going to go and instead of going to grad school or something like that, you're like, I'm going
to go to New York. Is that your first job? Yeah, I mean, I love that. Not first in my
class, the understatement of the year. I was kind of like lost, didn't know what I
wasn't do, really was pretty much a slacker, underachiever at the time. And my Godfather
calls me with one of those, like, what are you going to do with your life at the point?
And I knew I didn't want to go into engineering. It was kind of this cookie cutter life. You
don't really have any kind of entrepreneurial spirit in it. You work on like a subsection
of a chip, here's your career path, etc. It was all kind of laid out for you. And that
was unattractive to me. It kind of seemed like death to me. And at the time I saw this
movie Wall Street. And I was like, Oh, that's what I want. I want to be rich. I want to
go work in stocks. So, when my Godfather called me, I go, I want to be a stockbroker or a
stock trader. And he goes, I don't know anything about equities, but there's this firm. And
mind you, I didn't know what a commodity was that's looking for screen clerks. Go check it out.
And so, I got an introduction. Came with my resume.
This is what you're like, late 80s, early 90s?
Like 91. And takes my resume, tears it up, shows me, walks me around the floor. People are yelling
and screaming. And, you know, they're kind of casual wear. And it's like trading places. And
I'm like all this energy. And I'm like, Wow, that that guy can be rich. So can I. And so,
they didn't want to hire me, actually. They were looking to give the job to someone else,
another friend of the firm. So, I like kind of hung out downstairs waiting every day calling like,
can I come up? Can I get this job as a peon? Can I get, can I become a peon here? Can I become a
peon? And finally, after three days, they let me become a peon.
So, what did that job entail?
It's checking trades and sneaking sandwiches on the floor for traders. It's like literally the
version, the worst version of the mail room. Right. But the system, the old days where guys
would yell and scream across the pit and write their trades on a pick card and also in their
trade book. They throw the pick cards into the center. There's a guy with glasses and a giant
net. And all these cards will go to him. They would catch him, put him in the, down the chute,
and they would be entered into a computer system. Okay. My job was to check the traders log versus
the computer's log. Right. Your name becomes your trader. So, if your trader was why not or SMM,
S&M, that was your name. So, clerks are running around the floor going, why not? S&M, why not?
And then, you know, if you're, if you're why not, you're like, why not here? I got a, I got an
error here. I know selling five lots at 5480, not three lots at 5480. What do you know? And if you
know the same trade, then it's a simple process to correct it in the system. Right. And if you don't,
you're like, no, no, I definitely know only three lots. Right. Then you go to the traders immediately
and they kind of reconcile it. And that was a system like running around all day, you know,
checking trades. So, this is, this job is down on Wall Street. This firm's on Wall Street. Yeah.
So, back when the World Trade Center was there, this was in for World Trade Center.
And how much were you learning the business? Because I imagine one could take a job like that
and not actually learn what's happening, like what the machine is doing. Yeah.
That's when I decided to turn it on. You know, I always tell people like, hey,
I was pretty much a, can I say fuck up? Yeah. I was pretty much the fuck up of fuck ups, right?
For given what I had before college. But then I decided to turn it on. And like that poverty,
that like being a peon and not, and that desire to make it forced me to be like, I'm going to
learn every single thing there is about this business. I was reading books at night about trading,
about the oil business, about options, about whatever. I was a sponge. And I really turned
it on and said, I'm going to be diligent. I'm not going to mess around. And as much as I possibly
can as a 20 year old, right? And really, really trying to make myself invaluable no matter where
I was. So, where were you living at the time? What part of the city? Did you actually live in
Manhattan? No, no. I mean, when I first got there, I had to live at home with my mom, which was
completely cramping my style. And so I was like, I started driving a limo at night, the company
limo at night to make ends meet. What were you getting paid in that first job? Oh, geez. I think
it was sub $16,000 a year. I have to have to go look. Sub 16. Yeah. I think it was like 16,000,
but I was getting raises very quickly because I made myself valuable and I would work at night
and I would make more money driving the limo on a daily basis because traders would like take me
here and be drunk and they tip you. And you weren't there necessarily for your current
income. You were there for your future income. And so I had another clerk named Jason Rufo,
who had a studio on the Upper West Side. And what he did was he put up a wall by the kitchen and
kind of made this small room in the studio. And I eventually got an apartment with him on the
West Upper West Side living in like a pizza oven type of space. But it was great because I was in
New York City. I was out of my mom's house. I could have girls over, you know what I mean? And that
pride that goes, well, I live on the Upper West Side. Everybody wants to say they live in New York
City. And so as I was getting raises and kind of moving up, you know, I gradually got into that
life of, you know, what I call a Buppy, black urban professional, you know, Buppies and Yuppies.
And that was kind of the beginning of my journey.
Tell me, was your dad in the picture at this time?
So my dad is now older in poor health in Jersey City. So during this time, he'd had multiple strokes.
My dad is kind of like me, which is he's fairly stubborn, but he was stubborn to the extreme.
You know, doctor says, don't do this. All the things you would tell him not to do and you
need to be doing. He's like, ah, the hell with that. You know what I mean? I guess. And so
he's in the picture. My parents are divorced. He's in Jersey City.
And had your parents gone to college?
My dad did. So my dad got a scholarship to the University of Iowa. Like he was a real bad ass.
He had no intentions of going to school. He walked by a football field when he was a kid
in high school. He's like, I want to do that. And coaches like you don't know anything about
football. And he says, it seems like it's about hitting people. I know how to hit people. So they
give him some raggedy uniforms. And next, you know, he comes out for a practice. And in the
next practice, he has a brand new uniform. He winds up, you know, he's all everything gets
recruited to go to University of Iowa to go to college. And so there he is in college in 1959,
the University of Iowa, you know, all bad ass from Jersey City. So he had gone to college.
And then my mom went to college, finished college while I think it was like young teen early
preteen or late teens. But so they I had the benefit of two college educated parents.
And how much were they understanding your call it hunger, your drive, your aspirations in this
new role? I mean, because presumably they had seen you in high school and college,
not achieving at your potential. And now all of a sudden, you're hustling, you're working two jobs,
you're reading, you're learning, you're doing everything. Were they were they, you know,
purview to that sort of metamorphosis in you? They saw it later. You know, I'm the kid that
like didn't take out the garbage, right? Like it's I always say don't tell your parents your
dreams because they'll just piss on them, right? Because they've seen you at your worst, at your
failures as you're growing, right? It's like they they they have this kind of image of you
when you were the caterpillar, not the butterfly. And so, you know, you weren't necessarily like
advertising to them. No, no, no, it started it started, you know, they started seeing it,
right? Like, I remember the time when I finally made more than I got a raise and I was like,
did the calculation, just like, Holy shit, I make more money than my mom. Like, I've made it. Like,
it was one of the happiest days of my life. I'm like, I'm real. I'm legit. I'm a puppy. You know,
me with my badge, you know, used to wear around as a badge of honor. Like, I get onto the New York
Mercantile Exchange, etc. But, you know, they'd see like, I'm going out or I'm flying here or I'm
doing whatever. And it's like, oh, the kid, kid must be doing okay. You know, it wasn't until I
got recruited to go to Houston, you know, started buying the assets that adults start buying.
And and I paid my mom back for something that I did when I was a teenager that she didn't
know that they're like, okay, what was that? So when I was younger, I, I, I had a stick Toyota that
my mom had. It was her car. I was driving it. And my friend Pete Theibel, it's like, I want to drive
the car. I want to teach him how to drive the car. I'm gonna drive the car. I'm not supposed to really
drive the car. So anyway, long story short, he hits the gas instead of the clutch, spins the car out,
the back of it spins around hits a telephone pole. Trump pops up and has this big giant dent. I'm like,
holy shit, what am I gonna do? You know, so I tell my mom the story that, you know, we went to go get
pizza and parked it and then, you know, truck must have hit it on the side or bumped it and went on.
And that was my lie to my mom about this car that I felt guilty about. I said, one day I'm gonna
pay for this car in spades that that happened to my mom. And so one day I, you know, I get my mom
$40,000 and I said, Mom, you know, that time the car had that brown mark on it and we told you it
was a truck. Well, this is what really happened. So how did she react to that? She started laughing.
She was laughing. She says, I knew something was strange about that. You know, it, it, it,
the story fit, right? But, but there was something strange about that. You know, she just kind of
laughed and was, was thankful that, you know, one, you know, it was a great investment, you know,
having that car beat up, but, but she's kind of laughed and we just reminisced about it.
So let's go back to when you're on the Upper West Side, because you, you, you write about this in
the book, which was you and your roommate kind of had a slightly different, I don't know, call it a
point of view on future earnings and what that allowed you to do with your time. You told a story
about something you did that seemed kind of bold. Oh, that he did. That was kind of bold. You're
talking about when Jason took the, the trip. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, yeah, sorry. Sorry. Yeah.
So, so Jason, you know, I don't know if our views were very thought out or just wired in,
right? But like I was head down, like I gotta make it, I gotta become a trader. I gotta have
my head down. I'm, I'm, I'm saving money. I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm really at this point in my life,
like super diligent, like, you know, trying to convince my boss to get the, uh, on the bus
program to save money, you know, not, you know, writing down every single nickel that I bought,
et cetera. I'm really focused on my, my career trajectory. And Jason is like,
does Jason work in the same firm? Uh, he works at another firm right in a, if you look at the
old pictures, all the phone booths are right next to you. He's like right next to me, even though
he's not at the same firm, we're all crowded into one area. Uh, and Jason's like, I'm going to go
backpacking for your, for a couple of months. I'm like, wait, what? And I'm like, wait, how,
how are you going to do that? Well, I'm going to borrow money from, from this guy who was a loan
shark. And I'm like, wait, wait, what? You're going to borrow money from the sky and you're going
to go, and you're going to go backpacking in Europe. I'm like, this is insane. I'm like,
this is insanity. My head is about to explode. I'm like, you're going to miss out. And what if
they hire another screen clerk and your job's not there when you come back and how are you going to
pay this guy back? If you don't pay him back, this is not like, Oh, penalties and interest. This is
like, you know, knees and ankles, right? Uh, uh, and so I, I just didn't get it. Like, I just didn't
get it. Like that experience and that, you know, I wasn't thinking about like die with zero and
certain experiences belong in a certain period of life, et cetera. I was just like, ultimately
on this autopilot of trying to be successful and make money, right? At that time in my age,
that time of my life. And Jason was like, I'm going backpacking. So he went, I stayed,
he came back, had a screen clerking job, you know, different firm or same, same firm, same firm.
Wasn't that much noticeable, different. Like I moved up a little bit, but it wasn't that
most noticeable, different, but he came back richer. But he came back with stories and experiences
and romance and lifelong friends. And I was like, you know, in the beginning, I was kind of, Oh, wow.
Maybe I missed out. Maybe I could have jumped in for a week, you know, that type of thing. And as
time went on, I really, really regretted not joining him on that trip. I was like,
that when I, that when it finally came time where like, I'm going to go Europe, right? I'm going to
go, I'm going to have this backpacking experience. I was too bougie. I had money. I wasn't going to
go stay at youth hostels. I wasn't going to capture these trains. I was going to have
an experience, but a different experience. The type of experience he had was for that time in
your life and a type of experience, even though it was wonderful, it was not as rich as his
experience. Right. Because the time had passed me by and it's one of my, it's one of my big,
big, big regrets in life. So how did you start to formulate this understanding about these
different types of resources, be it time, be it money, which is the resource. I think a lot of
people think about experiences themselves as, you know, for lack of a better word, an asset or a
thing, the actual experience, the people you're meeting, all of these different things. When did
you start to coalesce around some of the ideas that, that ultimately, of course, would go on to
become the thesis of this book? It was slowly over time. You know, even when, you know, I got to
the exchange, I was like in this hurry to get rich. Right. And the reason why I was in a hurry,
because I had this bias, I just believe I was like, yeah, there's rich guys here, but they're old.
Like, what can he possibly do with the money? Right. Like I'm young, I'm 21. Like, I'm ages,
I can't imagine, you know, the use of a million dollars when you're 40. Right. Like, what are you
gonna do by a nicer car to drive your kids around? Like, you know, it just seems like loss on them.
Right. Like, they don't get to do fun things. Now, I was wrong about that, but I was right about
the utility of money over time. Right. And I was also read this book at this time called Your Money
or Your Life. It kind of transformed my understanding of what money is. Right. It's a very
detailed book that has these exercises that has you look at how you spend your hours
from going to work, getting ready for work, the things you spend on work and really figuring out
what your true hourly wage is. Right. Like after tax, this is what an hour of your time,
of your life is worth. And then it has you not think of everything in money, but in time.
So instead of going to the movies and say it costs me $10 is like that cost me one hour and 15
minutes of my time to go to this movie to buy this shirt. It cost me three hours of my time.
And so you get this idea that I'm exchanging my life for certain things. Right. The experience of
buying a shirt, going to the movie, going on a trip. And that hit me hard. And where were you
at this point? This is before you went to Houston. This is where I went to Houston. Before I did
Houston. That hit me hard. And that's what really turned me into like, I'm going to save. Right.
The two things I got out of it is I want a lot of money and I'm going to like become this very
frugal person. You know, there's this movement called fire, which that book is kind of like
the Bible, the precursor to the fire movement, which is financial independence, retire early.
And that was kind of like an early fire guy. Like I'm going to save my way to riches. Right.
I'm going to save and then retire early. And I had. And sorry, did you know what you wanted to do
when you retired? I just went on. I went on to another autopilot. I went on another version of
autopilot. I read a book. I got these concepts out of it. Right. And I was like, this is what I'm
going to do. Right. I didn't think about the big picture of everything, but some certain concepts
are coming to me. Right. Like I exchange hours in my life for money. And then that money is used for
the things I want. Let's take the abstract of money out of it and look at what I'm what hours
of my life are being exchanged for. Right. That was a great concept for the sink in very viscerally.
The idea that it's also just to double click on that bill. It's also visceral when you start to
think of the difference between using money for activities or trips versus things. So, you know,
I buy a shirt and this shirt basically works out to three hours of what I make per hour. So,
this is a three dollar shirt. I mean, a three hour shirt. Right. Conversely, like I take my daughter
out overnight. We do like a daddy daughter date night, go out to dinner, stay at a nice hotel,
have a fancy breakfast the next day. That's, you know, that's five hours of my time in terms of
work. Right. But do you see those sort of differently at the time that one of those is
like an experience and one of them is not in a way that you're properly analyzing it, but in more of
an intuitive way, my value because when you start to think about things in time, it's like, wait a
minute, three hours for a shirt versus, you know, our, you know, going here and having a sandwich
and hanging out with my friends or whatever it is, your values start to you really get in touch with
your values. Right. Because it's not an abstract plan. It's like when you're in a casino and they
give you chips, it's one of the greatest things to do is give you chips, not money, tip in $25,
you're thrown, let it all ride because it's so abstracted from money. So it's an abstraction on
an abstraction. Right. By removing that abstraction, right. You get closer to your values. Right.
Right. Imagine that you have $25 chips, you figure out your hourly after tax all in wage is 25 an
hour. Every time you flick a chip, it's like I gave an hour of my life. Right. Boom, boom, boom.
So when you start thinking about things in terms of hours of your life and you have finite hours,
you start to really get closer to your values. You can still be on autopilot, but you're closer.
And so things like this were happening. And, and, you know, at that time at the exchange,
like most people had like, what is it all for? Like, what do I want? You know, I'm here to get rich,
but, but why are you having that discussion with other either people who are your peers,
who are presumably on the same treadmill or the people who are already rich, but still presumably
killing themselves, trading their health for wealth? No, I'm generally having it with myself
and reading books. Right. And I'm just, but I'm still asking myself, but why? Like, what do I,
what do I want? You know, and I'm remembering conversations that maybe I've had throughout my
life where people like there was a college football player named Dwight Sistro and I was like
trying to do engineering and we were debating something. It's like, look, listen, you might
want to picket fence and a wife and something like that. And that life, I don't want that life.
I don't want that cookie cutter life. That's fine for you, but that's not my path. Right.
I thought about it and I was like, do I really want that? Right. And then, you know, certain
things that he said that he didn't want that I was actually working for, you know, thinking that
this was my path. I actually realized, no, I don't want that. Right. And so, you know, I'm pretty
hard headed. It takes a while for these things to seep in. Right. And so, you know, I saw, I
would argue a little different, Bill, I would argue that at this point, you're 22, 23, 24.
I think that's remarkably early to be having that thought, don't you? Yeah. I guess it took a while
for it to finally percolate into some sort of action plan, right? To like, kind of like, actually,
I'm thinking about these things, but they're not resulting in the proper behavior changes yet.
Right. So I'm still, I'm still formulating it. Yeah. Right. So, you know, everyone says, I want
to be rich before I'm 30 or I'm rich before 40. No one's out there saying I want to be rich before
I'm 86. Right. So intuitively in there, there's something about the utility of money. Right. That
it's not as valuable to you later on in life. Right. Yeah. It's one of the games I often play
with my patients. And I always, I sort of, or you'd see, it's anybody. I could play this game with
anybody, which is, listen, if right now, and you always do this with someone who's younger,
obviously, I say, like right now, would you trade places with Warren Buffett or Charlie Munger?
And they're like, everybody says, of course not. And I was like, what do you mean, of course not,
like Warren Buffett's worth a hundred billion dollars. I mean, how would you not trade places
with him? And they're like, I mean, he's 90 years old or whatever. And I say, okay, so would you
rather have not a penny to your name and be 20 or have a hundred billion dollars and be 90? No other
difference. Right. Like I'm not going to stipulate anything else. I've never met a person who wouldn't
take being a completely broke 20 year old. Right. And that, I think, speaks less to health because,
look, ostensibly Warren still appears somewhat healthy. Right. He's cognitively intact. He
doesn't, you know, it's not like he's like a frail 90 year old or whatever he is,
but it's about runway. It's about, yeah, but maybe Warren might have 10 years of life left,
that 20 year old could have 80 years of life left. And so when you face it in such stark terms,
only then I think does the average person start to realize how precious time is.
And I think they also see that, you know, Warren can't sprint, dunk a basketball, you know,
go wakeboarding. Like there's a lot of other things that they enjoy. And that's what I thought
about. And, you know, I thought to myself, if, you know, after reading this book, like I'm
spending hours in my life to acquire these experiences and I mean, experiences in the
broadest sense, whether it's like, you know, going on a walk or being able to choose to go on a walk
or go get a sandwich or buy a shirt or whatever. If I'm exchanging hours in my life and I don't
go acquire these experiences, I pretty much wasted hours in my life. Right? So that thought
hits and it's like, okay, you don't want to leave anything on the table, right? In the game of life,
when I die, you don't want to leave chips on the table, right? Like you want to use all your
resources before you die, right? And that, you know, inherent in that is like your choices,
your experiences, those experiences are what make you you. Those are the things that fulfill you
and everybody's going to be different. And so, consequently, having more of it
and enjoying more of it will lead to a more fulfilling life. So that if I'm solving
for fulfillment, right? This is, I don't care about the money, I care about the things I want,
the experiences I want to have. If I'm trying to solve for that, one of the things you come quickly
to is that you need to use all your resources up before you die. Okay? The second thing you come
through with the fact that your resources, particularly money, are less valuable to you
when you're older, then you start to think, well, there must be a curve,
right? Because if you're going to end at zero, is it, you know, this kind of rectangle shape
that just goes down? Is it a 45 degree angle of sleep? Or is there some sort of curve? And so,
what I like to do to understand certain things, it doesn't always work, is think of zero and think
of infinity, right? So when you're like, all right, let's run it all the way back to one,
you know, one years old, how useful is money? Not that useful to you, right? Let's run it all the
way forward to 96 on your deathbed. How useful is money to you? Not that useful, right? So clearly,
there's like some sort of ramp up of utility and then a decline of utility, right? And I became
obsessed with finding what that curve was. Because I was like, this is it. If you're making
more money for delayed gratification later in life, you approach infinity, you're actually
wasting your time, you should be spending down your assets at a certain point. There's an
inflection point where not a number, but a date where your wealth should be going down in order
to get the most fulfillment. Now, let's pause for a second, Bill. Is that standard thinking slash
teaching within the wealth management community? No, no, but it is a standard problem. If you look
at kind of JP Morgan or other wealth managers, one of the biggest problems they have is the
accumulation, getting people to spend down their assets, right? They've been saving, they got their
money, they've hit retirement, and it's like that net worth is going up in their 70s, you know? And
we're like, when's the party? That's what I always ask. You just tell me when the party is. Like,
you know, I have conversations with older people or other people. It's like, listen, it's okay that
you're saving. What are you saving for? And when's the party? I just want to know when you're going
to use up all your resources, right? Now, let's also pivot and talk about, because I remember one
of the stats that always stuck with me was during 2008. So a really good friend of my name, Jim
Lambright, who was at the time the president of the ex-in bank, when the TARP program kicked on
because he was close with Hank Paulson and had already spent so much time in China and had
government clearance. Basically, Hank brought Jim Lambright and Neil Koshkari, who was with him
already at the Treasury, I believe, to run TARP. So basically, Jim and Neil are doing all the deals
for TARP. And Jim is getting steeped in how bad is this going to be, right? Like, what is this going
to mean for the average person? And I remember one day he called me with a stat that I couldn't
believe. And I forget the stats, so this is only directionally it, but it was what fraction of
people in the United States could not produce $1,000 with three days notice, meaning they didn't have
that excess liquidity of $1,000. Again, I don't remember the number, but it was in the ballpark
of like 30%. It was a high number. And so I don't know what those stats are today. I've tried to
look some of them up and they're not maybe quite as dire as that, but they're not that much better.
No, they're not great. It's not great.
What's the natural history of that person who's 40 years old, whose total net worth is $50,000,
and their available liquidity is $1,000. And they're thinking, I'm going to work till I'm 65
or 70 or whatever, and then I'm going to collect my social security. Does this thinking still apply
there? Yeah, it applies in different ways. So what I've come up with this book is there's three
variables, your wealth, your health, and your time. And we're taking those three variables and we're
solving for net fulfillment, right? So we're not solving for maximum wealth. We're not solving even
for maximum health. We're solving for net fulfillment, right? I'm saying that's your
purpose. If you're with me, we're solving for net fulfillment. And so one of the things we look at
that the total arc of your life, given the resources you have, how do we allocate them?
We definitely want to focus on the money, right? Everybody wants to talk about the money and the
resources, but there's decisions that you make even without money. Whether you go on a walk with
your daughters, you play cards with your friends late at night. Do you tuck them in at night or
are you going to hang out with the boys, right? And so in the book, we talk about the seasons of
your life. Certain activities transfer nicely to the next season in your life from 20 to 30 to 30
to 40. And some of them don't transfer well. They're less enjoyable. And some of them don't
transfer at all. It's impossible. So one of the things, when the 40 year old who has $50,000,
one of the things I would say is, what's your survival number? Have you calculated that at
retirement? Are you surviving retirement? Are you in serious negative dire straits? And once we've
calculated that, okay, I need to work and save this much and plus social security, I've had my
survival number. Now the rest is for experiences, things I want to do, an allocation of my time.
How do I allocate it? Right? Is it the cruise at 70? Or is it the ski trip right now? Right. And
that's going to be different for every single person, right? Or is it a shirt or whatever
fulfills them or to go play in this chess tournament and pay the entry fee. And for people with zero
money, you still have an allocation game to play, right? You still have your health and your time,
right? You can still decide, hey, I'm going to sit down and watch Friends, you know, or I'm going to
go hang out at my mom's house and make a meal and spend time with them because I'm only going to see
them 20 times before they're gone. Right? So this type of thinking about allocating your resources
at the proper place, getting off autopilot holds at all wealth levels. It doesn't hold at all health
levels because if you have zero health, you have zero, you're done. It's over, but it holds at all
wealth levels. So that type of thinking to maximize fulfillment and knowing that you have seasons of
your life, that your body decays, your attitudes change and they pass that type of thinking and
that I need to get things in the right order and use my resources properly, that's going to help
you have a more fulfilling life, whether you have zero money or a hundred million dollars. Right?
There are many people with zero who are having a way more fulfilling life than Warren Buffett,
I would say. Yeah. I think one of the things about the way you framed it, Bill, that I really like
is the, it's a very nonlinear problem, right? So let's look at those three variables.
At the surface, one might suggest, well, wait a minute. It is a min max game with one of them.
You always want max health, but technically even that's not true because if I told you,
Bill, I have the secret for you to have max health, I can preserve your health span and lifespan
indefinitely, but here's what it's going to cost you. Every minute of the day, you have to be
working on your health. So from the moment you wake up from sleep, you have to do a two hour
meditation. We then have to go and do this yoga. We then have to go and do this workout. When you're
done that workout, you have to go and do this, and then you have to go to bed. You'd be like,
well, Peter, that sucks because yeah, I'm going to live for a hundred more years and I don't get to
spend any of that time doing anything other than improving my health. Correct. It's a glib example,
but it factors, I think it illustrates the point. It gets the point across. I usually say, you know,
there's no amount of money you can pay me to do 10 years in Sing Sing.
Not at this age. There's no amount of money. I say that to certain people who are just always
delaying gratification. I'm like, you're kind of in a jail. You're basically doing a version of
I'm doing time, and maybe you shouldn't be doing time at this point in your life.
Right. And so these are kind of just ways, you know, people absorb information in different ways.
You can say it in all kinds of different ways, and then they finally go, aha, I got it. That really
spoke to me the way you said it. And so I try and hit people with different versions of this. You
know, one of the things I like to say to people is life is like Tetris. You got to get the order
right in order to get the high score of net fulfillment. So let's say you're in heaven.
By the way, Tetris is the only video game I enjoy. Okay, gotcha. I go through periods
like where I won't play it for a year. And then I go through periods where I'll waste 30 minutes
a day, which is a lot of time for me. For me, 30 minutes in a day is an inordinate amount of time.
And when I'm sometimes in those phases of playing it a lot, I dream in Tetris. I literally dream
that everything I'm seeing in the world, I'm trying to optimize the shape and interaction of.
We got to think about getting your life in. So in the book, I talk about this thing about time
buckets, basically that you take your life in segments, in any kind of segment you want,
20 to 25, 30 to 40, 50 to 60. And then you think about, you know, leisure, job, career,
what experience you want to have in each of those periods, right? And as you're doing that,
you realize that, wait a minute, they're going to the clubs and strip clubs and hanging out
probably should be before I get married, not after, right? They're reading books to my kids
when they're children, right? That must be in this book. This must be in this bucket.
And so I give them kind of this- Right. Because they're not going to want me reading to them in
college. Exactly. Or even when they're 13, 14, they didn't even want to know you, right? And,
you know, that's one of the errors I made. Like, you know, you always do it wrong as a parent,
right? Like you don't want to spend too much time with them, et cetera. It's like, wait a minute,
maybe I should have been doing this activity instead of that activity, right? Kind of the
die with zero thinking, right? Optimize your life. And so the way, you know, the thought experiment,
I says, listen, you're up in heaven. You have the bucket of experiences. These are all the choices
you can have. And God says, take as much as you want. You're thrown in here, you're like,
I want to have sex 30,000 times and I want to climb, come out, kill them in Joro. And I want
to play hockey. I want to be in a high school team and I want to do, you know, and you're just
throwing them in, right? Everything. I want to meditate and yoga, right? And then God goes,
great, I'm going to let you have all those experiences, but there's one trick. You got
to get the order right. And what's it saying is, is if you don't get the order right, like if you
save certain experiences to the 80 to 86 bucket, you don't get it, right? If you, if you, if you're
not climbing Kilimanjaro. Yeah. If you're like in like nightclub and road trips with your buddies
before you're married and you have two kids or whatever, you don't get that. If you don't go
back pack it with your friend and youth hostels, et cetera. When you're 21, when you get the shot,
he don't get that experience, right? Or it's, or it's a bastardize, you know,
not as fulfilling experience. So you don't get the net fulfillment points.
And so it's kind of tied with zero. It's like, what do you want out of your life?
Get off autopilot. What do you want on a life? Where does it, what resources do you have?
And how do we optimize? How do we get the most out of it?
So how do you think about your own risk tolerance? Now, again, this is, I guess there's a,
maybe a caveat the listener needs to understand at this point, which is what you do for a living
today. Yeah. So you are an energy trader among other things, you know, you do many things, but,
but is it safe to say that the majority of the wealth you've created came through your ability to
understand how natural gas moves and trade on that?
Yeah. The majority of my wealth came from predicting the future. And that's generally
the future of natural gas prices. John Arnold, who is, you know, one of your closest colleagues,
someone who I've had on the podcast, nicknamed the king of gas, the greatest gas trader of all time.
Do you look at a guy like John and say he has a high risk tolerance? Do you look at someone
like yourself and say you have a high risk tolerance, or do you not feel that way at all
and feel like, nope, I'm completely in control of calculated risks. And that's why they net out to
be positive. In other words, I'm less swayed by short term volatility because my methodology,
you know, doesn't feel like I'm gambling. I think the best traders I've seen have been
pretty stoic about, about things. They think about very robotically about expected outcome,
and they don't seem to be disturbed about negative outcomes as much as-
Tell folks what expected outcomes mean because they want to understand the
probabilities and how these work. Right. So if you place a bet and the payout is one and four,
but the odds are 50-50, right, you're going to get half the time you're going to get four times
your money and half the time you're just going to lose one times your money. So that's positive
expected outcome, right? You're going to make money. This is a great trade. But remember,
70% of the time you're going to lose. Or in this scenario, no, the payout, half the time
you're going to lose. Half the time you're going to lose the payouts one and four. So half the
time you're pissed. You're upset, right? And a lot of people can't deal with that. They need
four or five or seven positive events emotionally, psychologically,
forever, every negative event. In trading, that just doesn't exist.
Yeah. In trading, if someone is right half the time-
They're pretty good, right? If their right's 55%, 60% of the time they're right. Think about the
casino's edge in Blackjack. It's like- It's going to be 51-
Yeah, yeah, 0.07 or 0.09 in Blackjack. In craps, it's like 0.03, right? They're wrong a lot of the
time, right? But ultimately, the law of large numbers, they make a bunch of money. But if your
emotional calculus is different, where such that you need a greater being right ratio,
then you're not going to make it because stress clouds your thinking and your judgment, right?
So with that said, if someone says to you, Bill, you just have a really high tolerance for risk.
I don't. I'm very risk averse. I don't like to take big risk. I never want to have the chance
of losing something. Loss aversion is a greater motivator for me than gain. How do you talk to
that person and how do you help them think through the difference between fear and risk tolerance?
Well, the first thing I do is just try and break down what are they actually afraid of? A lot of
times when people say the bad thing is not as bad as they imagine it in their head. And a lot of
times, quite frankly, it's really the fear of judgment more than the actual thing, right? They
find out that they can survive the potential negative financial hit. What they can't survive is,
oh, my friends, my colleagues, my spouse, my mom, my dad, the shame, the I got it wrong,
the I told you so, etc. There's a lot of that fear baked into disguised as I can't risk these
dollars. I'm like, yeah, you can, you know, you make more, you know, that type of thing.
Then the other thing is, I trying to think is get them the focus. They always focus on the monetary
costs of losing. But what about the cost of inaction and the opportunity costs? Right. And
by talking about the opportunity costs, I get them to see the asymmetry of the risk, right? So I don't
think I'm maybe I have a greater tolerance for risk. But what I do is, is that I fear, you know,
my fear is reversed. I fear missing out on the opportunity costs. I fear not getting the max,
you know, a lot of people fear running out of money. I fear wasting my life, right? I am more
worried about looking back and being like, shit, I wasted my only ride that I had, then running out
of money. Right. One of my patients said something to me once. He was about to do something that I
just thought was really risky. Now, it was a very unique opportunity. And he said, you know, Peter,
I'm going to go and do this thing. And I said, I think there's a, I think there's a significant
risk to you in doing that. It wasn't a financial risk, it would have been a health risk, a physical
risk. And he said, I you're right, Peter, I acknowledge that risk that that that is the risk.
But I'm optimizing in a risk, pardon me, a regret minimizing framework, not a risk minimizing
framework. Yeah, that and that's pretty much for me, it's risk reward, right? If I really love
cigarettes, like love them. I'd smoke cigarettes. You know what I mean? If I really love skydiving
all the time, I went twice, but it was diminishing returns. I go skydiving, right? It's what fulfills
you. Right. And so I'm, I'm a risk reward guy. Is the reward commensurate with the risk? Some people
like to ride motorcycles. I don't get my, for me, it's not worth the risk. Like I have a physical
risk tolerance around one in 10,000. Right? Like if it's more dangerous than one in 10,000, I,
the reward really has to be worth it for me to do it. And so, you know, I think that's the way I
think. Right. And then that, that helps me in this kind of like counterfactual regret minimization
algorithm. Right. Because, so the algorithm of the book, right, the mental models in the book,
right? You know, when a chess computer plays you, it has a regret minimization algorithm. And what
it wants to do is a solving to win. Right. AlphaGo is solving to win the game. And the game of life,
what I'm solving for the regret minimization I'm solving for is net fulfillment. I want the highest
score in net fulfillment. I don't want the highest money. I don't even want the highest health.
Right. I'm like, I don't want to run three hours a day to be in the top 0.5%. Top 3% is great
enough. I'll give up the tail end of my life. You know what I mean? Or, and, and time, like how do I
optimize my time? Right. And so everything for me is like what I'm solving for in life,
what this book is solving for for you is net fulfillment. It is relentless about net fulfillment.
And so if that entails take for you in your makeup, like taking nerves risks, going hella skiing,
skydiving, riding motorcycles, then so be it. Like, as long as you're off autopilot and you've
thought it through, then that's fine. How variable do you think people are in their
kind of stratification of what encompasses net fulfillment? And maybe a better question is,
do you think people are even understanding about and deliberate about what that means?
Like that's that doesn't strike me as something that the average person could articulate very
clearly what it is that will be their fulfillment maximizing function in terms of experiences. And
also, I think I want to reiterate a point you made, which is it's not just the experience,
it's when they occur. Correct. Right. So, so the combination of which experiences and when they
occur and who they occur with, do you get the sense that the average person can actually
articulate that? I think they, they, they had the ability earlier in life and then they get
habituated out of it. So we all go into autopilot, right? Like we have this default
mode network. It helps us survive. It helps us drive without thinking, oh, I gotta return, you
know, when you first learned to drive, like it's, everything's happening fast. You have to deliberately
think about everything you're doing. And then all of a sudden it goes into default mode network. And
it's easy. That happens with work. Right. And you're like, I need to work to survive. And I need to do
this. And you're panicking, whatever. And next thing you're in the groove and you're just constantly
working, right? Constantly working. And it's some long along the way, somewhere along the way with
the abstraction of, you know, going to work to make money, to survive and get the things we want.
We forget about the things we want. We just go to work to work, to just make more money,
to go to work, to make more money. And the things we want either get pushed for our head or forgotten
about because we're on autopilot. Right. It was a good thing because it makes us good at our jobs.
It's like, I can do this job with my eyes closed. I'm going to do this and I'm getting promoted and
you're getting rewarded. You know, certain things about the jobs that you like, but you're forgetting
why you did this thing in the first place. Right. People aren't like, I really wanted to be a plastic
salesperson. I really love selling plastics, more and more plastics and piling up numbers in a bank
account. Those numbers in a bank account were really meant for, I want to hang out with my buddies
and I want to go skiing and I want to get married and I want to donate to this charity. And I want
to do X, Y and Z. Right. But we kind of forget that. Right. And since we forgot about it, we're
not even thinking about when the best time it is to happen. Right. It's just completely like, oh,
I'll eventually do it or when I get more. So we're completely out of touch of what we want,
what's enough, the concept of enough, what that means for us and the concept of when.
Now I had a discussion with a patient just yesterday. So runs a hedge fund and not
surprisingly given the economic climate we're in, hedge funds aren't doing particularly well,
especially long hedge funds. And this guy doesn't need to be working. Even though he's
now having a down year, he could certainly return all the capital to his investors and
manage his own capital indefinitely or do nothing, literally do nothing. Right.
But he said, what would I do? I mean, what would I do? I'd sit around for three months and it would
feel really nice to have no stress for three months and then I'd be bored out of my mind.
So he's like, no, I got to keep going. Yeah. I've had this, you know, amongst my friends,
you know, it's one of the things like people ask the question, why do people do this? And
I've had direct conversations with my friends and, you know, with a friend and I'm very,
very aggressive with them attacking their walls they put up. And what I tell them is, is that
you have made your work your God. It's who you meet people. You eat around where work is. You've
learned, you've given up learning how to socialize and meet your neighbors, all the people you know,
or some kind of work or work related. You haven't exercised those muscles for years, 10, 20, 30
years. Right. Sometimes that people have their whole life revolves around work and all the other
muscles. And I mean, I'm using muscles as an example, have atropied, like, how do you socialize
without a job? How do you meet people without a job? Where do I go eat without my job? Like I eat,
obviously somewhere within five miles of this place and people recommend all the things I get
recommended, the camaraderie, everything that, you know, they, when people list what they like about
work that used to happen without work. Right. And they've atrophied those muscles. So when you take
that away, they're like, they don't know what to do. They don't know what they want. And their
dreams have left them. Right. The ski trip, they haven't thought about that or hang out with their
buddies or whatever, all that stuff has left them and they haven't worked those muscles out. And I
say, listen, just let's start working on those muscles and building them up. And you'll have
plenty to do. Right. You have plenty to do. You've let autopilot and habit put you in poor health
in these other activities. Right. You're in poor health on how to meet people and socialize
outside of work. You're in poor health on where to go eat lunch, you know, except for the places near
work or wherever you go. Right. You're in poor health on trips that are not business trips.
Right. You're in poor health about thinking about what fulfill you and discovery, just plain old
discovery. Because you don't know what you want. You discover what you want. Nobody comes out of the
womb like I don't like onions and I love chocolate and I want to go to Japan and I love
F1. Like you get exposed to it and you discover what you want. So a lot of life is discovery.
I think my kids did come out of the womb. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Well, they didn't have a choice, but you didn't have a choice.
But but these people are out of discovery. They're in the familiar habituated routine.
They are a rat in a wheel that doesn't even need cheese anymore. It just runs in the wheel.
Now, how do we differentiate that from people who and I would put myself in this category
truthfully, where, you know, a big part of their work is their fulfillment and they do feel a sense
of purpose in what they do beyond just the making money part of it. Correct. And I suspect that,
like, again, just to make caricatures of things, right. So maybe the person who works in the widget
factory that makes the widget that they don't even know what the widget plugs into, but they
need a job like and if if they, you know, inherited a big lump sum of money tomorrow, they would
happily quit the widget job. Right. But maybe they'd get bored and they'd want to go back
and start volunteering and doing something where they don't actually get paid, but they're really
enjoying what they're doing. And then, of course, you have the group of people whose job is doing
two things. It's providing money for all the things that you need, both in approximate sense
and distally. But also it is a sense of purpose and therefore it fits into their fulfillment.
But there's but but these things can be very slippery. And I would certainly put myself
squarely in that category, right, which is I still work harder than I should. Right. And I
absolutely know that I'm failing in the equation, even though I'm fulfilled by this and I wouldn't
want to not do this, but I'm doing too much of it as an example. Yeah, I really push back hard on
my friends on this. And in the part like I can't know only they can know, right? Like the heroin
addict is happy. I'm happy on heroin. You have you have a problem with my hair and I don't have a
problem. Right. And that's kind of the argument I push towards them. And I say, listen, really
think about what in your job fulfills you. And is that outside in the world? Right. And the purpose
of that. And do you have balance? Are you balanced according to what you want to life in this time
period in your life and the future time period in life? Now, I can't tell somebody what their
balance is. Right. That's a very personal thing. But what I really want them to do is be honest,
off autopilot, really like unplug for a moment and think about it like, OK, I got one life.
I only and I have only this period once. Right. I only get to be 50 between 50 and 55. I only get
this level of health at this time. Is are these the experiences? Is this really how I want to
allocate my time at this period? Is this really the maximum? Is this the optimal thing for me to do?
And if they do that and they come up with the same answer like, hey, no, I want to work at the widget
factory or I want to work at this fulfilling. I can't argue that. Like how am I going to tell you
how to live your life? What I'm here to tell you is how to optimize your life. What thought process
and what steps you should go through things you should be considering in order to get the most
fulfillment of your life. And then if you come to the conclusion that, hey, I'm at the perfect
balance of work. Right. And the money is piling up, but I'm going to use it later and I'm going
to go on, you know, a senior's cruise and that's what it's for. Then that's your life. But maybe
you might go, you know, I can dial it back and you know, my daughter's are only going to be or my
kids are only going to be this age at this time. Maybe I should, you know, take a family trip and
unplug and go on safari with them. Right. And enjoy my success because that's going to give me
a lifetime of memory dividends and discussion points and connections, et cetera. Maybe,
maybe, you know, I'd rather have that time with them now and not have them in a hospital with me
when I'm old and stinking can barely, you know, and see me this way. I want, I want the memories
and the time they spend with me doing this and not at the tail end of life. Who knows? Right. Like,
I just want people thinking about it. And if you just get off autopilot just a bit and you start
thinking about it, you're already optimizing your life. You're already going to have a more
fulfilling life. Right. Well, I think that that's probably the part of the book that most
kind of resonates with someone like me, which is especially when it comes to kids, right? It's
that you have, and I have, I guess the, maybe it's an advantage, maybe it's a disadvantage, but
my kids are sort of separated in age by a bit of a gap, right? So my daughter's 14 and then the
boys are five and eight. So in other words, I now know what it's like to have a teenager. I now
understand all the things that you kind of give up when your kid's a teenager and our daughter's an
amazing kid, but the reality of it is like, she doesn't really want to be around me. No, they
don't want to know you when they become teenagers. I didn't want to know my parents when I was
teenager. Yeah. Whereas conversely, the boys can't leave us alone. And it's tempting to sort of say,
I wish they would just leave us alone. But now knowing that, oh, actually in like six years,
you'll kill to be back in this situation. Correct. Makes it infinitely more easy to appreciate.
So that's kind of one thing that I think is helpful for people to understand the seasons
and this idea of seasonality. Like you, I probably think back to things I didn't do for
different reasons. So when I was in college, I mean, I couldn't have worked harder. I mean,
I was out of my mind how hard I worked. My night off, there was one night, which was Friday,
when I only worked till 9 p.m. It was my break. And from 9 p.m. till 11, I would go and do laundry
after 9 p.m. on a Friday. That was my way to just take a little time off. But other than that,
it was six hours a day of work outside of class. And I think of all the things I didn't do in
college. So first of all, my only memories of college are pure misery. I hated every minute of
college. I didn't have many. I didn't have this experience. Yeah. Yeah. Now, you know, I could
say, well, a lot of good came out of that because I did really well and did well. That set me up for
the next thing and the next thing and the next thing. But like I could have traveled. Right.
I didn't, having a college experience didn't mean I had to get drunk every night. No. It meant that
I could have saved all that money I was making by tutoring and done something different. This
reminds me of, you know, the college paper had this kind of like my senior year opened up and
had the 50 things you need to do before you graduate. And I just had the biggest regret when
I read that list. I was like, and you read it at what age? Like how much I was like just about on
my way out. Like on my way out. Like my life. I was like, never going to be able to do this. I'm
not going to do this. You know, it's like in some of them were simple, like write an angry letter to
the newspaper, you know, go skinny dipping at Lake, whatever. I actually actually did that after
I read that, you know, you know, there were, there were a lot of things. Do this college prank,
do whatever, like things that would be fun than necessarily costing money or whatever,
but like things to do to have a college experience, not necessarily do them all. And I was like,
maybe I did three or four. And I was like, why was I so on autopilot in my way? You know,
I didn't think about like, okay, you got four years here. You should get, you know, good,
good grades, good study. But like, you know, you want to get this out of it. You want to do this
out of it. You want to have this college experience, et cetera, right? We just kind of like,
don't really think about things going autopilot so much that we don't think about periods in our
life. Even, you know, this year, what experiences do I want to have this year with this person,
with myself, with my, with my spirituality, with my health, with my, my travel, my leisure, my job,
you know, how am I going to optimize? And how does that fit into the jigsaw, the Tetris game of my
entire life? Right? Am I doing it right? Maybe this experience that I'm saying goes here,
actually goes further out in my life. Right? When I was trying to get the book published,
one of the publishers said, I do exactly what you're talking about in the book. I really like
hiking. I have an, she did, she explains she had an injury and she likes running, but now she does
like hiking. And she really likes concert and music. And she goes on a vacation with a friend
every year. They pick what they're going to go do. And she, there's this very expensive opera
that she wants to go see and et cetera. And she said, what I and our friend decided is that the
hiking trips and you know, this mountain, et cetera, we're going to pull these forward. And the sitting
in operas and these types of trips, the set in a church, we're going to push forward.
Push, push to the future.
Push, push it in the future to, you know, maximize. It was like, if they get that order, right? If they
get that order wrong, right? They go all the opera and then they turn around like, holy shit,
I can't hike this mountain. Right. And so this, this fits in every aspect of your life, right?
College, you know, first job, pre-married, married, before kids, kids that are toddlers, not kidlers,
not toddlers. That type of thinking is really helpful. And you've been lucky. Experience has
taught you about the seasons with your kids. And I learned the hard way too. I was like, you know,
people tell you like, oh, your kids don't want to be with you when you're 13. And you're like,
you kind of forget when you were 13, right? Like you forget like, oh yeah, I didn't want to be
your own parents. And then, you know, it really hits you when you're just like, dad,
nobody hangs out with their dad that much. Come on. You know what I mean? Like, yeah.
One of the other things that you talk about and you've mentioned it already today, a couple of
times is philanthropy. So there's a story in the book about a woman who dies and leaves a large
gift. Tell that story again. Yeah. So there's a woman, she, it's one of those, you know, secret
millionaire stories, right? They're all out there. Like there's a secretary and then when she died,
you know, she had, you know, $10 million at Tootsie Roll Stock or whatever, right? And so
this woman was, I believe, a, a worked at a law firm, you know, saved her money, lived a,
by all, by all accounts, a very frugal life. And then when she died, she gave a, a multimillion
dollar gift to education. It was a charitable education. And, you know, everybody was like,
you know, that's so charitable and that's, that's, that's such a great thing. And, you know,
I had a different perspective, right? Like, you know, my perspective was when you're dead,
the money isn't yours, right? And so, and also that the, the target for her, you know, her bequeath
after her death would have been much better off receiving the money much earlier, a lower sum,
much earlier, and that the return on her charitable investment will be greater than any
of her investment returns, right? And so, you know, I can't really get into her head to determine if
it's charitable, like, like, like I'm knowingly thinking I'm doing the right thing. I'm going to,
to save all this money and it's going to grow to a bigger pile and I'm going to give,
give it to a charity. But to me, it appears to be a tip on the way out, right? The money's got to go
somewhere. It was going to go either to the IRS who, you know, the government or redistribute,
redistribute the money the way they see fit, usually into wars and stuff. But I'll, I'll,
I'm all going to that subject, right? Or, or, or, or, or, or hairs or et cetera. But it's,
it's going somewhere. It's not yours, right? It's, it's gone. So the fact that it just wound up
into this educational charity, you know, I didn't see it as charitable as much and it is impactful
as just giving the money earlier. Like life is urgent. Life is now. And I argue that the return
on investment in your charitable endeavors is greater than any return in the market you can get.
Well, and this is sort of interesting because, you know, think about what our mutual friend,
John Arnold did 10 years ago, which was before he even hits the age of 40.
It's great.
He decides I'm no longer going to do this full-time. My full-time job is now giving this money away.
Right. It was, it's, it's, it's great. John's great. And we've had a lot of conversations about this,
about like, you know, making sure the money actually gets distributed, gets, gets, gets into
the purpose, you know, the helping causes. But John decided that I've been solving the problem
natural gas long enough. I have more money than I'll ever spend or need. And I really want to
dedicate my neurons to solving other problems. Right. So he takes an analytical approach,
a database driven approach to solving some of society's ills and solving some problems and
trying to get ahead of some of these intractable problems, which is, which is awesome. And, and
the fact that he's doing so young, I even argue with John, like he did it too late. He's still
late. You know what I mean? Because he was on autopilot too, in my opinion, trading, right?
Like, it's like, what are you working for? You know, like, you know, like, you know,
have this conversation to John's like, what's the money for? What can't you buy? You know,
and to a certain extent, the money became a detriment, you know, based, based on your value
system, right? Like, if you're like, Hey, and I mentioned this book, it's like, yeah, I can have
Maroon 5 play in my backyard every day, etc. But you don't want to ruin your kids by spending the
money and consuming it that way. And I'm using the Maroon 5 as an exact, as like an exaggerated
example. But like, there's all kinds of consumption that you don't want to have, because you don't
want your kids to have that, then the money became a negative, right? Like you really work too low for,
because you're working for money that you cannot spend, you cannot consume,
right? And you could start giving away and having an impact on the other things you want to do now.
And I think one of the things that John exemplifies is how to give money away thoughtfully.
Correct.
And what you realize when you spend any length of time within which you've spent more than I have,
it is really hard to give money away strategically and thoughtfully, which is why I suspect John and
Laura set themselves up with 50 years of a runway to give. Yeah. And I don't know, there's a pretty
good chance they still won't be able to give it all away, right?
Well, I think, I think what they're doing is like, effectively giving away, right? Like, they want to
solve problems, database decisions, like there's, there's-
But it takes time. I mean, that's the other point.
It definitely takes time.
You have to invest the time to try something out, see if it works, if it does double down,
if it doesn't learn why it doesn't pivot. And, you know, you can't do that if you say,
look, at the end of my life, I'm going to give away a billion dollars.
No.
Like, it won't be effective. So there's a double issue here. There's the issue you already said,
which is the compounding issue. No. If you give a billion dollars away in 50 years
versus giving away half a billion dollars or, you know, a hundred million dollars 30 years sooner,
that money will do more good. But there's another layer to that, which is you have a chance to learn
from what that money did and make corrections that themselves allow for more thoughtful giving.
Yeah. They're immediately jumping into the problem and let the experiments run the course
and they have the time to do it. So, and they're doing it, you know, I can't say enough about the
Lauren John Arnold Foundation about the way they're going in and helping people and solving problems.
But the other thing that you talked about in the book that really, probably, this is probably the
reason I had my wife read it right away was the idea of, you know, we sometimes think that there
are people in our lives that we want to give money to at some point, you know, and you sort
of think like, God, this, you know, that's a person that was, you know, really important in my life
or in our lives. And, you know, maybe we leave them X amount of dollars at some point. Right.
And then you sort of realize, well, why don't you finish why that's maybe not necessarily the right
strategy. So the same laws of physics that govern my body and the utility of money over time for me
applies to my kids. Right. Maybe they have a little bit longer lifespan or health, man,
or relatives or anybody else relatives or anybody, anybody, right. Like the utility of money to them
falls a curve, right, depending on how healthy they are, et cetera. You can just kind of draw it.
Right. Like, you know better than I muscle decay rates for people in shape, not in shape, working
out, you know, et cetera. So this curve applies to them. So, you know, a lot of people like, oh,
when I die, I'm going to give, you know, I used to have people on my will that are like close to my
age. Right. Like I'm going to give money to them when I die. And I'm like, wait a minute, I'm going
to give my money to a 72 year old. Like, wouldn't it be better if I gave them less money now, like
let them spend it and apply it because the utility of money for them is drastic. Right.
Like the day before you die, I cannot pay you anything. I cannot get you to delay gratification.
Right. That's what savings is, right. You're delaying gratification. Right. And so like,
there is no gratification the next day. Right. And so like, if you take it from the day before you
die, two days before you die to right now, right, there's this curve, right. This compensation you
need for delayed gratification. And it makes no sense for me to be leaving money to 65 year olds
and 62 year olds. It's give it to them where the money has the most impact. Right. Where they'll
have the most utility of that money. And so when you're off autopilot and think, yeah, that's what
everybody does. They break down a well and when they die, et cetera. Now the will has a purpose.
If you die early, you've got to distribute the money. But really before you die, if you live a
normal, a normal life, there should be nothing left to give. You should have already given it away.
Again, when I read your book and you articulate it that way, it's such,
I mean, it's such a gut punch of this realization. And one example is kids, right. But I, you know,
I think like my wife and I have people in our lives that we're not related to that we
value so much. And we've always said like, yeah, you know, like we want to give them X number of
dollars at this point in time. I've had that. I had a good year and you know, there was people that
I would, you know, give money to if I had a good year or I'm not going to wait till I'm dead.
Are there people in my will? And I just went down and listened, you know, the
maximum tax free gift you can give per year per person is $15,000. And I had a, I think a
30 to 50 person list of $15,000 to, to, to give to people. Right. Because I was like, I need to
apply and this was me reading my own book. Right. Like, so a lot of people like, why'd you write
the book? I wrote it to save my own life. Right. I didn't want one waste my life. I wanted to get
the most net fulfillment. And after I wrote the book and I, you know, mainly I talk about children,
but I thought about that applies to everybody. Right. If I'm going to do something nice and
give something or leave something to somebody, it's like, it's now. Yeah. Absolutely. It's right
now. Well, especially when you think about exactly what you said, which is that person will do much
more with that in applying it to their fulfillment curve. Correct. In real time. Right. Because when
you, when you, when you're really giving somebody money, right, you're giving them life energy,
you're giving the ability to make choices, right? Like you're, you're giving them fulfillment,
right? So, you know, waiting till they're 96 on a deathbed, right? They can't really convert that
into fulfillment. You really didn't give them what you wanted to give them. Right. So when you look
at their, their curve of their life, right? Like, wait, Oh wow, here's the maximum insertion point.
And as a matter of fact, wow, $5,000 right now at let's say 33 is like 150,000. And
like 86, you know, it's actually more and more impactful, right? There's more going in life,
more choices, things going on. And then the cumulative effect, the fact that when they have
that experience, not only do they enjoy that experience at that point, whatever that experience
is, they get dividends from that experience, right? They talk about with their friends,
they become more interesting. They recall that and they get enjoyment out of it. It's like,
Oh, remember that ski trip we went on, we had a great time with the kids. Yeah, that was great.
They get fulfilled from that. So they get memory dividends associated from that experience.
Whereas if you give it to a 96, they do it once they consume it, if they can even do it,
and then they die. Right. How do you help a person do the math? Because we've talked about this
quite a bit, and you've alluded to it, there is really a curve. And, you know, this is where
both your background primarily as an engineer and a trader come into solving what becomes a
mathematical set of equations, where you have certain variables you need to understand, right?
So let's say we're solving this for me or for you, or an arbitrary person who's sitting here,
who's 50 years old. Okay. So 50 year old person is listening to this or 30 year old person,
I mean, we should do it, maybe we do a few different scenarios. So let's start with the
kind of 50 year old who is firmly planted on the treadmill of autopilot. Okay. So their kids are in,
you know, middle school and high school. They're, I mean, they realize how much money they need for
college for their kids. They've got a mortgage payment, they've got a good job. And they have
a fuzzy notion that they're going to work another 15 to 20 years. And they come to you and they say,
Bill, I read the book, I buy the thesis, I don't know how to implement it for my numbers
and for my fulfillment curve. How do you help them think about it?
The main thing is, it's very individual, right? It's like, what do you want? Like,
if you're sitting there, like, I just like working and going in and that's all I do.
No. Okay. So I'll be the guy. So I'm going to say.
You'd be the guy.
Yeah. So, Bill, no, I do have interests, but I got to be honest with you, man, I've backed away
from them. You know, I've kind of let them go. I've let myself go a little bit. So I before my
wife and I had kids, we loved traveling. And before our kids were born, we hiked the entire rim of the
Grand Canyon. We went down to the Colorado River back up for the greatest thing we ever did. And
then once the kids came, we were kind of head down and work. And I just want to make sure that my kids
don't have debt when they go to college. So what I what I do is like, okay, will your kids have
went in debt? I get what's reality and what's what's what's, you know, just fear, fear based
thinking. Okay. So we try and get on that. And one of the things I'd look for is like, why don't you
go traveling with the kids? And you're like, well, it's a pain in the ass. Whatever. I was like,
well, no, it's also so expensive, Bill. I mean, do you understand what it costs now? I mean,
right now, if we wanted to take, I mean, you know, one of my kids has a friend who did this African
Safari a year ago. They said it was amazing. But I, you know, to price that trip bill today,
$30,000 to go do that African Safari now with the airlines with the Safari. I mean, it's,
that's a lot of money. So what I say is, is when you die, we like, will you have $30,000? Are you
in track to die with $30,000? $50,000? Yeah, I hope so. Okay. So then would you rather
consume that $30,000 now? Or and and have this experience with your kids, etc? Or would you rather
have $30,000 left over when you die? And then I just want to be safe. I mean, how do I know?
Then, you know, we can sit down and go down the hard numbers is like,
do you have insurance if you lose your job? What is safe? What do you need? What do you envision
yourself doing in retirement that you can't afford? Right? What bad thing that will happen
that we can't buy an insurance policy for? Is it long term care insurance? You know, if you get
that while you're young, it's actually pretty cheap. It's very cheap. Right. You know, I look
at what risks they're, they're having and I look at ways to mitigate them. Right. So a lot of people
who are conservative, like, Oh, I'm worried about something happening. I'm like, what's the something
happening that you're worried about? Right. When you do that with people, Bill, how often are they
able to articulate clearly what they're afraid of versus it being kind of just a fuzzy notion of
a lot of its fuzzy notion. And we just keep pushing and pulling it out. What if this happens? What if
I get sick? What if, or whatever, right? Like we go over like medical insurance, like then it's worth
basically what happens is people try to act as their own insurance agent with a client of one.
Right. That's very difficult to underwrite.
So, so, so they have a client of one. They really don't understand the odds of the bad things
happening. Right. And so what they tend to do is put it in this big, giant fear bucket of insurance
premium. And they just work and save and save and save to think that they have the notional to cover
all these bad things happening. And a lot of times I'll point out two things. I go, one, some of these
bad things that you're saving for, you'll never get the notional. Right. You get some, you know,
maybe you will or whatever, but most of the people I talk to, I was like, do you know, it was like
$25,000 a night for my dad in the hospital. Like if insurance didn't cover that,
console, doesn't matter. Right. Like I'm not, you know what I mean? He's only got x days, right?
Like you're not, you're not saving. Some of these things are like, you shouldn't be the insurer,
right? If you're actually afraid of that, and that's important to you, you need to buy the
insurance policy where they have the lower large numbers and their edge is 6% or 8%. You are going
to be woefully inefficient. And on top of that, you don't even know the odds. Like some of these
things are like, you know, robot alien space insurance. Like, wait, you're worried about this.
Like, and then I also like to do a, you know, a comparison. Like, okay, here's the risk of the
scenario happen and this bad thing happen and it's bad. Right. Well, accept it. And here's the risk
of you not doing the thing that you want to do now. Right. Here's the risk of you not doing the
trip. Like, what does that look like on your deathbed when you know you couldn't have gone
on the safari and had this wonderful time with your kids and, and connected with them and something to
talk about forever and expanded your worldview. Was it worth the $30,000? Was it worth the insurance
policy that you're trying to, was it worth you trying to play insurance agent? And so a lot of
these are thematic conversations and not like hard number conversations, but you have a model. Yeah.
Yeah. We have a model, but the problem with the model is it's an abstraction, right? The variables
we're talking about are infinite. Yep. Right. And we have to have track them, extract them, extract.
So what the model does, it really tells you the direction and it's very good on the direction,
but the magnitude, it may be off. Right. And so for you as a person, it's like, what's your survival
number? We have that model, like really think about like, okay, just survival, not I'm hanging
out. Yeah. Not thriving, but surviving. What do you need? Then after that, right? It's all your
choices, right? And depending on who you are, right? Cause there's infinite choices and what those
choices will cost and the experiences you want to have in your life, plus the discovery, the, you
know, 20 to 30% discovery, you know, maybe all your experiences go into 50 bucket, right? You didn't
realize it and you're actually inadvertently pushing them in the 70 bucket and you're not going
to have them. And so that's kind of what I try and get people to do is like, are you going to
have $30,000 trips in your lifetime? And they'll go, yes. When is the optimal time for you to have
$30,000 trips and with whom, right? If you're ever, if you're never going to have a $30,000 trip,
I'm like, okay, let's think of a different type of activity that you can do that doesn't come,
that will get you the same fulfillment or close to it. That's not a $30,000 trip. Right. I mean,
to me, that's the interesting distinction, right? It's like maybe somebody listening to this says,
are you freaking crazy? Like I'll never take a $30,000 trip ever, ever in my life. Yeah. The
bigger point is, is there a trip that you think you will take near the end of your life and you're
holding back on taking it now? I mean, to me, that is one of the big aha insights from this philosophy.
And if you're, you're, you're in that thing, well, I'm, I'm saving because of just in case,
it's like, guy, you're not the best insurance agent. You're actually the worst insurance agent.
You don't know the odds. You can never have the notional and the, the, the edge, the premium that
you're extracting from yourself. And that edge is your own life, right? Like you have to give up
hours of your life to have this insurance premium is way, way more than just paying the insurance
company. Right. So people worry about running out of money. I'm like, get an annuity. You're worried
about long-term care health, long-term health. And what if I'm sick and I can't move and I need
nurses, get long-term care insurance. It's really cheap when you start early. It's really, it's
surprisingly cheap. You know, what about this? Like there's an insurance product for a lot of
things people are like, quote unquote saving or worried for, et cetera. And I'm like,
let's mitigate the risks with the professionals. Let's get you living your life.
So how do you get through to somebody when you confront perhaps an even more illogical problem?
Because the problem that we just discussed is actually quite logical. Like it's easy to
understand why a person would think I have to save for a rainy day. That's been pretty ingrained
into a responsible person. To me, there's a far less logical reason that people forego
doing things when they're young. And by young, I mean kind of like middle age, like in their
work. Or right now. Young is right now. Yeah. And it's because they're so busy making money.
Yeah. So this is probably the one. That's the rat in the wheel with no cheese, right? Like,
you know, they got habituated. That's right. They got a habituated, like you take a rat, you,
you know, get them to run the wheel, you give them the cheese, you give them the run wheel,
they do the cheese. And pretty soon you don't even have to give them the cheese. They see the wheel,
they just start running. Right. And, and, and the reward is no longer the goal. It's just to do the
thing, right? To do the thing. And so how do you help somebody break that? That is that, that is
the hardest one to break because they've been brainwashed into thinking that this is what I
want to do. And it's one of the hardest things to extract somebody from. And so I have to explain
to them, like, where do you socialize? You know, we just go through it. Like, where do you eat?
Where do you eat lunch? Well, I like the people at work and like hanging out, you know, I get,
I get this. Like, I don't want to quit work. I like hanging out with the people. I'm like,
you can quit work and take the people on a trip with you. You can vacation with them. You can
still visit them at night and play bingo games. Like the people don't go away just because you
don't show up at work. You can still spend time and you can actually spend more quality time with
the people at work if you exercise that muscle, but they don't know how to invite people over
their house or, Hey, we're going to go see the Chris Rock show tonight, which I'm going to go do.
It's Chris Rock in town tonight or is in Houston. No, here in Austin tonight.
I didn't even know. See, there you go. A new experience you might have, but anyway, like
they don't know how to do that. Right. And so I try and like, it's a very long conversation. Like
you can do this, you can do that. You can actually, everything that you're getting out of work,
that social benefit, all these little excuses, the mental stimulation. I'm like,
you know, John was like, these real life problems are more mentally stimulating than,
than the natural gas puzzle. I still like the natural gas puzzle, but these are more mentally
stimulating, more purposeful, more fulfilling to me. Right. And so I have to break down brick by
brick, right? How and show them how they got habituated and how they haven't exercised these
other muscles and how they can replace it. You realize it's not work is not the unique thing
to get the things you're getting out of work. Right. It's actually a bastardization of it.
It's minimizing those experience. You're not actually getting the most quality time
with your coworkers in the working environment. You're actually not getting the most mental
exercise. That's not necessarily the best mental exercise for you in the work environment. Right.
It's just, you know, nothing else. Cause you've been stuck in this lab, running on this type of
wheel, you know, and it's really hard because people will be extremely, extremely resistant.
Right. Like change is painful. Right. If you, if you, if you, if you get somebody who hasn't
worked out forever and you're like, Hey, let's go into the gym. We're going to work out. It's like,
Oh God, why am I here? I don't like this. You know what I mean? Like just to develop the muscle
to do the thing, to play the tennis, the fulfilling thing. It's, it's a process. Right. And, and, you
know, you have to show them the reward that life is rich. It's fat. It's wonderful. It's, it is one
of the biggest cliches ever, which is the person on their death bed who says, I wish I didn't work
so hard. And yet we all know this cliche and yet many of us still work too hard. Habits are powerful.
Like one of the things I took away from like, you know, the habit books like Tiny Habits by B.J.
Fogg is a great book is that they're powerful. They're extremely powerful. And so we have,
we get habituated in many different ways, right? For good or bad, right? Like if you,
if you have the snacks in your house and you eat 200 calories a day, you know, and, you know,
two years, you're like 40 pounds heavier, right? 200 extra calories, right? Like how did that happen?
Right. You know, how did I forget, you know, how did my life pass me by? How did I not go on these
trips? How did I not have these experiences? How did I not call my mother? How did I not say I love
you to these people even pick up the phone because my habits took over, right? They took over towards
this purpose and it just absorbed my life. And so, you know, I, you know, outside the book with my
friends, you know, I really talk about, you know, the good of habits, right? You can form good habits
that keep you healthy. But some of the habits, you know, the consequences of some of our habits
to be successful and how it takes away from other things. Right. And so. So how has that been a
struggle for you? Oh, I wrote that book for me. I wrote it to save my life. People think I didn't,
you know, the first life I wanted to save was my own. Put your life mask on first. You know, I am
just as guilty as the next person is being on autopilot. I constantly have to remind myself
that I'm going to die, that life isn't forever. This period ends. These seasons, what my daughters
end these seasons, what my startups and all these things. And I have to think about like, what do I
want? How do I balance them? What's optimized? Right. And I don't get it exactly right. But I do
it better than if I was just completely on autopilot. And then sometimes I was like, Oh, shit,
I was on autopilot. Why didn't I think about this? You know, and what do you use to help jar you out
of autopilot on these things? I mean, the first macro thing is, is the death clock. Or right now
I have this, this, this calendar up and it's, it's, it's a 4,000 weeks and you mark off each week
and it's a very visceral representation about like life is finite. You know, this period,
not only will you die somewhere around here, but this period is going to end. Right. And, and
a lot of times when people go on vacation, right, knowing that the vacation ends on Friday,
snaps you up. You're like, Oh, shit, I'm going to go here and do this and I'm going to stay out. And,
you know, we only have a couple of days. So let's do the cafe and let's, you know, do X, Y, and Z.
And you actually get more out of the trip knowing it's going to end as opposed to living obliviously,
you know, and all of a sudden time to go, wait, it's time to go. I forgot to do this or go see the
Eiffel Tower or go whatever it is on your trip. And so same thing with life. When, when, when you
know life is going to end, it becomes more urgent, right? And even, even the segment in your life,
when you know, you know, your early fifties are going to end, you're like, it becomes more urgent.
You become more deliberate. You get off autopilot. So that's the first layer of, of, of, of,
so each week you do check off a box on the calendar.
I've been in Austin and traveling, but when I come back, I see it, I see it's in my closet. So I
walk by it every day. It's a constant reminder, right? Where'd you get this calendar? By the way,
online, there was like some sort of stoic reflections out there. A memento, Maury,
remember death, you know, and so I saw it and I used to have it on my phone and you just count
down backwards to my estimated death date. That app no longer works, but the, the, the,
the seeing it every time, you know, is, is, is great. You know, if they get, if I get another widget
that counts down, we'll have both of them. Right. And I used to do it for other things like till
Christmas to your daughter's 14 till, till, till the job, the 15 year anniversary, right? It's like,
wow, my daughter's going to be, you know, 16, she's going to be driving. What, how am I going to
pry experiences out of my daughter? Cause your daughters don't want to know you right
before she's really gone, right? She gets a car and she's Sia deuces, you know,
that type of thing. So that really helps me, you know, it gives me kind of an alarm that wakes me
up out of autopilot. Right. And, and, and, and that's the thing I personally use.
How do you help somebody think about when their net worth should peak? Because a clear,
uh, implication of everything we're talking about is net worth probably needs to peak a lot sooner
than it currently does. As you said, I think the default for most working people is that net worth
peaks sometime after retirement or certainly around the time of retirement, even if they're
thinking about drawing down. But again, for most people, given the age of retirement, there's a,
a mismatch between when they're hitting peak net worth and when they're hitting peak capacity
to utilize net worth. There's a massive, it's a massive mismatch mismatch. You know, uh, you know,
one of the things I wanted to do, and I wish I knew you back then because you can, uh, you could
have helped me as I was like, I want to know about all these frailty curves, like bone,
density, lung capacity, what activities become less enjoyable first and then unable to do. Right.
Because that determines a lot when your net worth should peak. So I estimated it somewhere in your
fifties. Wow. Right. Like, like, and the data kind of shows that like when I, when I went to
St. Petersburg and climbed the 200 and I'll think it was 11 steps to walk around the Bannister,
all these tour buses coming, St. Petersburg, Asian, whatever, not one person over those tour buses
that was elderly climbed the 211 steps. So St. Petersburg was a different St. Petersburg for them.
They didn't have the same experience. I got more out of St. Petersburg for them. Now I'm not saying
it wasn't a wonderful trip and a nice trip for them, but they probably pushed St. Petersburg too
late in life. Yep. And so, you know, there's so much hidden data and data out there and reports.
If you read it where, you know, we talked about it earlier, like trying to get people to spend
their money down. Right. And one of the things, answers I give, you know, they say, well, why do
you think people are still, their net worth is still going up into 72? And, you know, part of it
is, you know, asset appreciation and going faster than they can spend it. But the real answer is
they can't. Yeah. They cannot spend it down. Life has passed them by. They no longer have the attitude
or aptitude, you know, to do this. Like they can't do it. You'd be surprised how many people die on
those cruise ships trying to swim when they get to St. Thomas. It's, you know, I'm going to do this
and, you know, they think their life's going to be like a carnival commercial. And I'm like, that
carnival commercial will kill most Americans. Right. They're having heart attacks going down those
slides. Right. Yeah. And so. And that, of course, just speaks to the imbalance between the three
variables. It's like if you spent a little bit more of your time on your health, you would buy
yourself a bigger runway to utilize your wealth on the experiences. Right. So particularly for
Americans like this book, my book is most successful in Japan, which is which is strange. Yeah. Say why?
I think one, you know, you I believe you'll get value out of this book in the way of thinking,
even if you have zero wealth. But Japan has a savings problem. Like, you know, Japan saves,
saves, saves, then they die and they give the money to the next generation. They save, save,
save. And I'm just like, well, what generation actually has fun? Right. So I'm really counters
to the culture there. Right. We hear, you know, one of the criticisms of the book will be like,
well, there's so many people that have zero and trying to make ends meet. I'm like, I get it. They
can still get value out of this about getting the Tetris of their life. Right. But maybe, you know,
a wealth building book or like how to make dollars book might be, you know, more useful to them at
this time in their life. Right. And Japan is the opposite. And also Japan, Japanese, they're
healthier. Like when I walk around, they're healthier longer. Yes. If you walk around Japan,
like the old people around, you know, it's an older country, but they're around, they're moving,
they're doing things or having activities, etc. They're doing, they're enjoying their life. For
Americans, looking at, you know, the obesity epidemic and the lifestyle of Americans, that
their ability to consume experiences way deteriorates way, way faster and way earlier than say the
Japanese. Let's go back to risk again. You, we were talking before about how, what's the mantra
of the energy trader or the gas trader? Yeah. Yeah. The name of the game is the standard game.
Right. Like sort of like Simon Sinek's book, The Infinite Game, right? It's not about winning. It's
about being able to keep playing over and over and over again. So inherent in that is never making
a bet or a trade that can completely wipe you out and take you out of the game. I mean, by the nature
of the business, even the smallest position can take you out of the game. It's really about taking
prudent risk reward and then stopping out when you can. Right. Life is risk, right? You can get hit by
a bus, a meteor can hit you, you know, you can get some sort of crazy infectious disease. Like you can
get a bum deal, right? Just going out, but you're not going to live in a bubble. You're going to
take calculated risks. So in trading, we're optimizing for profits, right? You're going
to take risks that in a tail scenario can blow you out. The key is taking prudent risk reward
decisions, right? Like, you know, I don't smoke. It's not a, it's not, it's not the rewards not
great enough. I did go skydiving the first time the reward was great. The second time it was
half as great. I didn't do it the third time because the risk was the same and the reward wasn't.
Right. The reward was going down and the risk was still the same. And so this is the same thing in
trading, right? Like we look at everything on a risk reward basis and the likelihood of dying,
right? And if things go awry, can we get out, right? Have I sized my position? Can I get out?
Is the liquidity there? And all these things are going on all the time, right? You have to.
How do you think about that in a person's life? I mean, I like the example of skydiving.
How do you think about this now in terms of the seasons of the person's life? Where are there,
are there certain seasons where certain risks make sense? Be it financial risks or.
I'll give you, I'll give you a great example of physical risk. Yeah. Okay. So I have a, a
cartilage disappearing in L3, L4, right? Bones are hitting each other. So I'm, they, I'm,
I'm wise against doing impact things. And I was 50 years old in the islands and guys were going
to go wakeboarding. And I was like, I don't want to go. I don't want to go. I'm going to hang out
in the beach. I'm going to love. And I thought about it for a second. I said, I don't have many
wakeboarding times left. Like I'm not going wakeboarding at 60, right? I have, I have this
to journal back thing, you know, Carlos, you know, it's going to be more dangerous for me, et cetera.
If I am to wakeboard, it has to be that it is now it is in this time period. And then I thought,
okay, it's in this time period. I'm like, okay, how many times am I going to be in warm water
with my buddies where there's a wakeboarding boat ready to go in the next two years?
I don't know. This is it. I don't foresee it happening, you know, like I could make a special
effort for it, but like, it's just there in my lap and I don't have something else to do,
et cetera. And I was like, I'm going to go wakeboarding. This is probably the last time
I got on a wakeboarding. That was the last time I went wakeboarding.
How much did it hurt? It didn't hurt. It didn't hurt. I actually jumped the weight too. I made
a nice jump of the wake. I said, I'm going to send it. I sent it, you know, it didn't hurt that much.
It wasn't like that. But afterwards, like there was a little tension in my back, et cetera.
And, you know, stretching and trying to like, you know, but like I was very conscious, like, okay,
I got to be, you know, careful, right? Coming across it. And now I wake, sir. Right? Like I
do the low impact version of the sport, which I absolutely love until, you know, there's some
technique to like put cartilage in my back and restrengthen my back. I, you know, I'm waiting
for the technology to catch up. So maybe I'll get my backpack. But right now, it's the last time I
went wakeboarding, you know, that was the risk was worth the reward. There was no other time that
I'm, you know, now as I get older, wakeboarding is much more dangerous. Right. And so I've gone
to a sport where the speed of the sport, you know, a lot of people think, you know, well, you know,
if you're going 10 miles per hour versus 12 miles per hour, it's only two miles per hour difference,
but it's a 44% difference in force, right? Because force equals MV squared. And so, you know,
people don't realize that, well, I'm acutely aware of it. And I'm like, okay, I want to be in this
something I can get fulfilled where the risk is not as great. Right. And so I have
a 44% reduction in, you know, force, which is great, you know, great for me when I fall.
So what year was it that you had that incredible birthday?
Gosh, I'm pretty sure it's 45. Right. But I've had an incredible birthday since then. But like
the one in the book is 45. And I'm pretty sure it's 45. I think it's, I think it, well, how about this?
Uh, it was 2008, right around 2008.
Okay.
No, no, no, there was a second one. I had two birthday parties. It was 45, 45. Let's say 45.
All right. So at the time you spend a lot of money, was it for you enough money that you were like,
am I crazy doing this? Like, did you have second thoughts about it?
I had second thoughts, like, you know, the events and the things I was planning.
Remind me what was the, it was down in the Caribbean.
Oh, so, so, so I, I, I, I, I went to St. Bart's. I love St. Bart's. It's, it's where I had my honeymoon.
It's a great island. I think it's one of the best islands in the Caribbean.
I, I obviously not everybody can go to St. Bart's and, you know, I tell people that become successful.
Um, you either get new friends or you scholarship your friends. Right. Because you want to do
experiences. A lot of times a lot of people want to do shared experiences, right? They want their
friends to come. They can't afford to just pop up and spend thousands of dollars to go to St. Bart's
or do X, Y, and Z when you're, you know, and it happens in various levels of success, right?
Whether it's on a trip to Chicago, you know, super, like I can't do that, you know, like some people
can and can't. And so as you become successful, you know, one of the experiences you want to have is to
be around your friends and have shared experience with your friends. And so I, I, I coach people,
I say, you have to lose this attachment that they have to pay, right? Or they need to pay or whatever.
Like you have to think what's most important to you. Get off autopilot. It's to have shared
experiences. And is it worth it for you to have them around? For me, I've had good friends throughout
the years. It's, it's, it's unequivocal. Yes. Right. Friends and family. So, but it gets expensive.
Right. And you have this, you know, you got to run out the hotel rooms, et cetera, and entertainment
and plan this thing. But I was like, some of these people, you know, they have their own lives
and own complications and conflicts. You won't get the time to do with it. Some of these people
won't be alive. Right. May or may not be alive. You may drift apart. This is, this is the time.
Right. I want to do this. And so as I was, you know, adding these people in and having my mother
down and all this stuff, I had to just like a heavenly experience, you know, like walking on
the beach, my mom's coming out of her beach house. My friends are hanging on the balcony, looking down.
It's beautiful. The birds are out, et cetera. And hi, all the people I love. And we're going to do
this fun activity. And we're going to listen to music, et cetera. You know, I imagine that that's
what heavens is like, right? Like you're just, just having this experience. And what I did was I
convert, you know, I realized that that's what I was working for. I was working to create these
experiences. These are the things that fulfill me. Right. When I was planning it, it's like, oh,
shit, there's a lot of goddamn money. You know what I mean? Like, what am I going to do? Is am I doing
the right allocation? Right? Like, you never know if you get it exactly right. Right. Nobody gets it
perfectly balanced, but this was the right direction. Right. You know, it reminds me of something. So
when my wife and I got married in 2004, it was, I remember looking, so, you know, we got married at
a golf club, you know, we didn't have two nickels to rub together, right? So it was like, I think
the wedding, the ceremony, the reception, we're all at the same place. The whole thing costs less
than $20,000, but it was obscene amount of money for us at the time. Right. And, and it was amazing
because everybody we actually cared about in our lives was there. We were really fortunate that,
hey, almost everybody could make it who we invited. Right. And, you know, there were almost 200 people
there. So at one point I grabbed my wife and we kind of walked out onto a balcony and could see
everybody. And I said, do you realize that this is one of only two times in our life that we will be
surrounded by everyone who's meaningful to us, who's alive. And the only other time it's going to
occur, we're going to be dead. We'll be in the casket and be at our funeral. Correct. So we got
to really take this in. Yeah. And I realize now there was a, there was a huge error in my logic,
which was that was totally untrue. That didn't have to be true at all. You can create it. You
can create that any time you want. Right. You can decide for no reason, I want to bring everybody in
my life who matters. So a birthday party to a, to a, it could be a birthday party. It could be just
a party. Correct. And most of my life is, is finding excuses to throw parties. You know, we,
we autopilot waiting for certain events like weddings or funerals or, or, or special anniversaries
or things like that. We autopilot like, Oh, that's when we get together. Right. So we, we,
we allow autopilot to dictate when we do these things, instead of thinking, Hey,
I really want to hang out with so-and-so, so-and-so-and-so-and-so let me design a trip or let me
have a bowling alley or something. It could be low cost. It'd be like, let me have a picnic
with a ball game talking shit. You know, one of the things that I want to do,
which I guess the startup costs will be, will be something expensive. But like,
I'm getting some laser tag guns and I put it in my group. I have this group called cool Austin
people. I'll put you in it if you want to be in it. And I'm like, it's on. I'm going to get laser
tag out best ass laser tag things. And we're going to, there's going to be some senior for
and everybody's like, yes. You know what I mean? Like I'm creating this experience. Like, yeah,
I'm going to kick some ass on laser tag, right. And shit talk, but I'm also going to connect and
have a good time with people. Right. And I can do that. Once I put the initial costs, we could do
that all the time. Right. We can have a league. We can have do all kinds of things. And it's like,
you know, it doesn't have to be laser tag. It could be with a ball at the park. You can have a
with Paulie low, low, low costs, you know, dollar store, pick up a pick up a whiff of all that.
And then you're, you know, you're creating memories and somebody brings sandwiches and
you can do that. Right. And that's getting off autopilot. So I'm sorry to interrupt you about
but you really hit the nail on the head about that. It's like
design your life. Think about what you want out of it and make it happen.
Now, let me ask you a question at that birthday party when you're 45, how many people were there?
We took out the Taiwan hotel and some of the other one 80, 180, 100 or something.
And how much time did you get to spend with each person?
We were there for a week. So I got to spend time. Whoever wanted to spend time with me,
they got to spend time with me. Um, some people, you know, I have this thing. This is just me.
I don't, I don't know if this isn't like some people I want their presence, but not saying
anything. Just, I know you're okay. I get to see you being happy. Maybe I don't talk to you as
much, but I get to enjoy you enjoying yourself. That's one of my favorite things at a party.
When I throw a party, they're like, are you having a good time? It's crazy. Whatever. I'm like,
I'm having the best. I'm watching the best fucking movie of my life right now. I am in an immersive
theater of people. I love doing the thing they want to do now. I'm kind of antisocial. Like I
don't like to talk that much when people like I get awkward sometimes. You know what I mean?
Sometimes I grab my wife and I'm like, talk for me, talk for me. We'll go to a party and I'll be
like, you got to talk for me, babe. I can't take it. I can talk to a million people. No problems.
The stadium or whatever. But sometimes I get awkward. But what I really, really do enjoy and
what really fulfills me is watching people I love have a good time. Yeah. So, so that's funny.
That's, you know, I think after my wife read the book, that was one of her first thoughts,
which is I've never had a birthday party. Uh, so last birthday party I had was, I was seven years
old. And after that, I just decided I never wanted to have a party and I never have. And she's like,
like, I really want, you know, I know how much you are obsessed with your friends and how much
you share with them individually, but wouldn't it be great for everybody to be under one roof for,
you know, your birthday. And I'm resisting it to, to know, and she's, she'd never throw a surprise
party for me. She knows that would just kill me. So she won't do that, but she's really negotiating
with me to sort of have a party. And my view is like, it won't be enjoyable for me because I'll
be the center of attention and I'll feel an obligation to give everybody the same amount
of attention. Whereas like having dinner with five friends is infinitely more enjoyable. Right.
So I'm trying to balance her. It's just a different experience. Like, yeah, yeah. But I guess what
bums me out is like, I feel like I wouldn't even know how to appreciate a party.
Yeah. I mean, I get that. Like I walk around and I just really enjoy people meeting and socializing
and connecting like at my wedding, people like, you know, they're friends that didn't know each
other and they're like, they're great. Like, you know, great people. And like, of course I do. Like,
you find somebody who's great. Love you keep them close by. I don't care if you dated them or
whatever. Like you, you, you keep them close, man. Like the people that vibe with you is very
important to me. And me seeing them succeed. I'm a person that roots for people to hit the long
ball. Like I'm not a hater. I'm a natural. Like I hope you crush it. I hope you become a trillionaire.
I hope you whatever it is. Right. And so seeing people at a party and like, you know, I like that
there were parties and make people have fun and create environments for them. Loosen up, enjoy
each other, have a good time and watching that success and watching them interact is enjoyable
for me, even though I might be just sitting there smiling, right? Like not really talking.
So you can enjoy a party as much if you're the host or it's your birthday as if you're at somebody's
party. You know, it depends. It's not always the same because, you know, you got to solve problems.
Someone can't get in the ice maker's broken, whatever. Like there's that type of things.
But yeah, I, I'd rather watch that movie than go to the movies. I'd rather be in that immersive
theater than, you know, McKittrick Hotel and Sleep No More in New York, which is an immersive
theater. That's the best theater. Right. And even so what? I only got to have a small conversation,
whatever. Like the feedback there was like, I met this person. We had a great time. It was awesome.
Like very fulfilling to me. Very fulfilling. What year did you finish writing Die with Zero?
Ah, let's see. It had to be, it's supposed to come out in 2020. So it's probably 2019.
2019. So 2019. In the, in the three years ish since you've written the book. Yeah.
Has your thinking changed in anything? Have you evolved? Are you more nuanced in anything that
you wrote about? I'm more, I'm, you know, it's kind of like when you write a formula, you know,
and it's not like I like came up with this formula, this life cycle hypothesis thing,
which is basically the book, right? This counterfactual rep minimization algorithm,
and I'm solving for net fulfillment. It's not as if these ideas weren't out there. Right. Like I
always say, like anybody could have like just thought about it and wrote this book. It's,
it's, it's how I present it so that it hits the widest audience and so that it hits them viscerally.
So they actually apply it. Right. And so I think about it deeper and deeper layers of it. Right.
And sometimes I go deep into the subcatter because I use these variables, wealth, health, and time.
And I'm like, what's the maximum level of health I should be? There's tons of health books out
there, right? Tons of health. Like I'm not writing a health book, but I'm like, how can I optimize
this? Right? How these two interplay the time and health, how much time do I really want to spend on
the palaton? How much time do I really want to like regimented eating all the time and being a
pain in the ass? You know, how, or, and how much time, how many chocolate chip cookies don't want
to eat before I die. Right. And just suffer. Like, you know, I have to think about that. Like,
if dying one year early means, uh, you know, living one more year, but I don't get any chocolate chip
cookies, I'll take the chocolate chip cookies. I want a fulfilling life. Like thinking deeply about
these things, you know, that's kind of a cartoon version of it, but you know, and I hear other
people think about like, I wrote the basic macro formula, but there's like, you know, it's very
fulfilling to see other people. Like they've set up spreadsheets. Like this is how you doubt. This
is the optimal way would die with zero. They've done it better than me. Right. These, these
financial planners and they built these spreadsheets and your returns and these are the things you
like to do, et cetera. It's, you know, I'm like, this is great. You know, so they've taken the
ball and run with it and I've taken the ball a little bit and run with it a little bit myself.
And the way I'm applying it mainly is, um, more socially, more, more of these things like,
you know, at my wedding, I said to somebody, I said, probably no one in this room will see
each other more than 50 times. And most of us will probably only see us 20 times in the
times of our lives. Right. You know, how many people were, this is the recent wedding. 117.
117. 117. Um, and so, you know, that's, that's, you know, kind of hit people. They're like,
yeah, you're kind of right. Like I put the over under at the max at like 50 for any,
any pair that's not, you know, married and, and, and, and probably 20. And so then that,
that made me think like, I don't, that made me think I don't want 20. I'm gonna throw parties.
Like my whole, I've taken throwing parties and social things very seriously because
I thought about what fulfills me. So the last party I had, which you were invited,
but you didn't come. I was throwing a party that night.
You were throwing a party that night at F1. Um, I went all out. I'm like, this is, this is, this is,
this is what, this is what I'm going to work for to have these types of experiences. Like there's
other things, right? But this is in the category, in the top of the category, socializing, seeing my
friends, happy, having a good time, et cetera. Travel is a big one. Charity is another big one.
You know, my kids' money is their money. It's not my money. It's in a trust. It's already
taken care of. They'll get their money turned over when somewhere between 25, 26 and 33.
Right? Because that's the optimal time for them, right? When they're mentally mature
and at physical maturity, pat, you know, not in decline.
And how much will you talk with them about, you know, what you think or don't think they
should do with that money? Is that one of those things where you feel it is your responsibility
to say absolutely nothing and let them figure it out on their own?
No, no. I feel like you, I want to give them a roadmap, you know, I want to teach them that
it's a tool, right? A lot of people, one of the biggest mistakes they, they make is,
is assigning some sort of good or bad to money or what it is, et cetera. It's, it's not money
that's good or bad in the Bible. It's the love of money that is good or bad. Right? And, you know,
I, I use this analogy. I used to say like money is a tool that much like a hammer and saw
and nails and rail guns, right? Do hammers and saws build houses? No. You need to know how to
use those tools. People build those houses, right? So do, does, does, uh, money make you happy? No.
But if you know how to use the tool of money, it can make you happy, right? Or it can make you
miserable. So some people who give hammers and saws, they build a house and build canoes. This
was wonderful things. You're like, how the hell did you build this? Right? Some people give ham and
saws and they're just sitting there to cut their arm off. Right? And so what I'm trying to do is
not tell my kids what they should do, but teach them how to use the tools. Now, once they know
how to use the tools, if they decide to build houses or canoes or cut their arms off, that's up
to them. Right? But I want to make sure that I gave them the instruction manual and, and got them a
little bit proficient on how to use the tools. And that's it. Then, then, then my job is done. Right?
Like I have so many friends that try and control people from the grave that use the money as a
control mechanism. And, you know, I'm very big on like, that's my dream. My dreams are my dreams.
You're my dad always tried to get me to be an attorney. Get the hell out of here. I'm never
doing that. Right? But, but, you know, you try and push your dreams onto your kids and, you know,
I want you to be a doctor. I want you to be this. I want you to be that, whatever. And that's not
necessarily what they want to do. They have their own life and it's their adventure. And what I want
to do is set them up to, with the tools to choose their own adventure. Now, I might not agree with
that adventure. I probably won't because I come from a different era and a different culture and
all kinds of things. Right. But I will be rest assured and happy that if they're fulfilled, great.
Well, Bill, I want to thank you very much for writing this book because as I said at the outset,
it really is one of a handful of books that has caused me to rethink a lot of what I've been doing,
how I've been thinking about the problem of optimizing these variables. And I'm,
I'm really confident that people are going to pick this book up and, and, and find similar value,
at least in magnitude. They might find different things that speak to them more or less than me,
but I believe that from a, from a, from a valence and magnitude perspective, people will across the
board find this valuable. So thanks so much for writing it and also for coming today. Thanks.
That's great feedback. I mean, you don't, you don't write books to get rich, right? You write
books to get your point across. And for me, you know, I see it as saving lives, right? And a lot
of people like, you know, I've said this before, they're like, what do you mean saving lives,
Perkins? You're fucking crazy. Like, what do you mean saving lives? You're not saving lives. And
I'm like, well, listen, when, when, when somebody's drowning in the river, right? Or Lake, Lake Austin,
you pull them out and you mouth the mouth and you save their lives, guess what? They're still
going to fucking die. Just not that day. Right? So what did you do when you saved their life by
pulling them out of the river? You've given them more choices, more experience, more life. Right?
So when you read my book and you get off autopilot and you get more choices, more experience,
more life, isn't it the same? At least in my mind it is. And that's the way, that's what motivates
me. And so when you say it had an impact in you and you're going to, you know, have a more fulfilling
life, I, I'm, it's like, I fucking did it. You know what I mean? I feel very happy. So I appreciate it.
I, I, I think the, the example you gave there is a great one. And I would agree with you completely
because I too fall in the camp, despite my profession, of believing we are all absolutely
going to die and in relatively short order. And therefore, anything that changes our experiential
existence for the better is part of living. Yeah. So thank you. Thanks for having me. It's been great.
Bye.