Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Well, Andy, it's wonderful to see you here on video. We were supposed to do this in person,
but we got a good laugh as to why that didn't pan out, but that's okay. Perhaps there will
be an in-person chance the next time.
Yeah. Yeah, I'm excited to be here this way. It would have been more enjoyable in person,
but we'll make it work.
I've wanted to speak with you for quite a while, and I think listeners to this podcast
are not strangers to the idea of how much of an emphasis I place on exercise. I've said
it many times before. I'll continue to reiterate it until the data suggests otherwise that
there's really no more potent tool to improve longevity, meaning extending the length of
life and improving the quality of life than exercise. That includes nutrition, that includes
sleep, and that includes the entire pharmacopeia of medication, supplements, drugs, hormones,
et cetera. It's probably for that reason that I would say that exercise makes up a disproportionate
amount of the content on our podcast. Of course, within exercise, I tend to divide it really
down into these different pillars of strength, stability, and cardiorespiratory fitness,
which of course then gets further subdivided by the metabolic state and energy state of
it. Of course, what we're going to probably talk a lot about today is strength, but also
all of the things that stem from that, like hypertrophy and various things like that,
which I think are of huge interest to people. Maybe for folks who don't know you, can you
give us a sense of your path, even frankly out of high school college, what was your
athletic background and what made this be something that you have dedicated all of your
time to?
Sure. I guess initially I need to state a conflict of interest, which is I'm going to
actually have scientists. If you want to start giving more credit to exercise for ongoing
wellness, I cannot be a little more biased into that lane, especially with then actually
assigned strength training. I've been waiting for 30 years for this to happen in the field.
Now I get to prove that all my preconceived notions are actually holding true. I will
refuse to change despite what you said. I will refuse to change despite what the data
suggests. No, for really, I grew up in a very small town in Southwest Washington. So I played
everything in high school, football, basketball, baseball, track and field, the whole thing.
I went to a small school in Oregon where I played college football and got my undergraduate
degree in exercise science. And then after that, I made some stops in Arizona and worked
in a facility training professional athletes. I went back and got my master's degree in human
movement sciences, which is just another fancy way of saying kinesiology or exercise
science, and then got my PhD in human bioenergetics. So in 2011, I got that came out here
to California and I've been working at Cal State Fullerton ever since. So I've been for a
while now the director for the Center for Sport Performance there, as well as my lab,
which is a biochemistry and molecular exercise physiology lab. So that's the condensed version
of the academic path. Now, I think one more pertinent question was college football, and
then training professional athletes started at that point as well. And then I started
competing in weightlifting, which locally is Olympic weightlifting that version of it,
and then combat sports a lot of that. So I've continued to work with athletes the entire
time. I'm still over the last 10 years, you know, running my labs, running our research.
I've worked with professional athletes in just about every sport with exception of racing,
I have yet to get into Formula One. But Cy Young winners MVPs, all pros, you know, the
whole whole thing, Olympic gold medalists, etc. So my research actually, and my interests
really come back from the exact same point. And if someone returns at the very beginning
here, which was, I was a decent athlete, but I actually feel like I was in the perfect
spot because I wasn't so good that these details didn't matter, I was going to be in all pros going
to, you know, go to the next level no matter what that wasn't the case. So when I did things
better, was more effective with training, more effective recovery, it mattered, I saw differences
on the field, right, it was the difference between me being a starter and being not a starter or
whatever the case is. I also was good enough to know where I got rewarded. So if you're not good
enough, then it's just like doesn't matter what you do, you're not gonna play the next level. So I
was in that perfect scenario. And so I was totally obsessed with making sure I gave myself every
advantage possible to have some success. I knew I was never going to be a professional level caliber
or even division one. But I was like, the difference is, do you want to play college football or not?
That's going to be the difference. So if you can do these things, you might be able to do it. If not,
you're gonna have no chance. And where I'm from, people don't, don't really go to college in general,
and they certainly don't play college sports. There's no advanced degrees. And so to me, I was
like, wow, you got a chance to do something really special here. And do something that no one else
you really know has done that often. So that's that initial passion came from. Additionally,
the town I grew up with, my parents and everybody I knew, it is a very working class place. And so
losing was always fine. There's always better than you. But losing because you didn't prepare was
totally unacceptable. We all most of the kids I grew up with, we worked on farms,
we cleaned stalls, we did something before school. My parents worked in construction,
like building. So that whole idea of like, you fend for yourself, and you get what you earn,
and all that sort of stuff was just something I grew up with. And so moving that into sports
academia was like, if you want a chance, like this on you and nobody else. And so do the work or
don't do the work. So that's what all pushed me to get here. And then, as I'll finish up,
the background is, then when I started moving past my athletic career, and I started
started finding athletes who wanted to pursue these tremendous goals like go to the Olympics,
but in a sport like women's wrestling, like no one's going to help them, they don't have funds.
And so I just became very interested in these people, because I'm like, man,
I can help you a lot. No one else cares about you. There's no money on the back end here. There's no
fame. There's no social media at the time. I just want to get help you here in this journey,
because that's something that's going to reach my soul of, let's give everything we can have to do
something really special that no one's going to care about, besides you and I, and like your team
and your family. And so that's what drove it initially. And that's what really put me in this
position. And that's what put me in a position to continue to go get my master's to get my PhD was,
you got to learn more, there's more things going on here, you've got to find all the answers,
that you can. And if you're doing anything less than that, what are you doing? You're just giving
up. So that's the background of sort of how I got here and what I do now.
Now you mentioned briefly Olympic lifting. We've had Lane Norton on the podcast several times.
Lane obviously is a very successful power lifter. I think folks are kind of familiar with power
lifting, having the three lifts. And it's really about these three lifts and what your total is
in those three lifts. Can you contrast that a little bit with what Olympic lifting is? And
I think more importantly, what are the physiologic differences between those two? And I'll preface
the question for the listener by saying, again, even if you never plan to power lift or Olympic
lift, this is going to be germane to our discussion. Yeah. So this is very, there's actually a,
a fairly recently we published the most in-depth analysis of muscle composition of Olympic weight
lifters. So we can actually come back to that and we can talk more specifically about muscle
composition. But in general, as some background, if you think about power lifting, it's tricky
because we're about to run some loops on your brain here. So technically you have force production,
which is in the case of lifting, it is one rep max. So it's the most amount of weight you can lift
one time. Period. Not repetitions on how many times you can do it, not how fast you can do it,
just what can you get up. And the sport of power lifting, like what Lane does, it is three exercises,
the deadlift bench, the squat, and it's how much weight can you lift one time? You get a couple of
tries at it, but it's, that's effective what it is. Right. So it's really an expression of pure
strength. It's not really an expression of power at all because the speed component is very poor.
In fact, the deadlift can take as long as you want. It doesn't matter. Did you get it up or did you not?
Squat, et cetera. So we're already at the gates, which confuse people because the name of the sport
is called power lifting. Despite the fact that it is not a power exercise, nor is it determined by
power. When you move over to Olympic way, that thing, it's the same basic idea. There are now
two lifts instead of three, one left being called the snatch and the other one's called the clean
and jerk. It's called the clean and jerk because it has two parts. You clean it to your chest and
then you jerk it over your head, but it's still considered one lip. Name of the game is still one
rep max. So whoever can lift the most amount one time is the winner. Man, there's no repetition
method to it. The difference is though, this is now more expression of power because although it's
all about one rep max, it's difficult to lift something over your head as high as possible
slowly. So there's a speed component required to the movements to perform, whether it's the clean
or the snatch. And so it is an expression of tremendous strength, but there's a force or
velocity component to it. So when you multiply force by velocity, now you've got power. And so
technically the weight lifters, Olympic weight lifters are significantly more powerful than a
power lifter, despite the fact the power lifter is in a sparkle power. So the confusion there is,
and this gets worse when we start roping in things like strong man. So strong man is fantastic
because again, you think of strength and you think that must be the biggest expression of strength.
Or in fact, it's not because strong man is contested over multiple repetitions.
So it is an expression of very, very high strength, repeated several times, very, very high strength,
but it's not technically a true one rep max that actually goes to back of the power lifters. So now
you've already confused powerlifting, weightlifting and strong man. And none of those three things
are actually explaining what they do correctly. We can keep going on with multiple sports here,
but this is the gen, the core, the problem. The reason you're, I think you're bringing this up is
this also explains training adaptations. And it's exactly, it's a perfect way to outline
to understand what's happening. So if you train like a power lifter, that's probably represents
the best way to get truly strong. If you train like a weight lifter, it represents the best way
to get powerful. If you train like a strong man, it represents a fantastic way to get very, very
strong and more, what we'll say, life functional movements. So walking, carrying, lifting objects
and doing it probably multiple times. So the only difference between all those three, the last part
I'll add to is with Olympic weightlifting, the amount of coordination required, because you're
going to take away from the ground, throw it over your head and catch it over your head in a full
squat. So when it comes to things like balance and proprioception and eccentric catching, it is
the advantage goes to weightlifters, you know, big time there. You're not going to see that
powerlifting is very controlled. It's a very specific foot position, hand position. There's
no movement ideally. And it's very, it's typically you're minimizing range of motion intentionally,
because you want to minimize work, right? So working force times distance. And if the game
of the game is who can create the most force, you can minimize the distance you're going to win.
That's why they take those funny positions. That's why Lane has both of his feet,
six miles apart. And does it, he calls it a deadlift, even though it's a fake movement.
Just kidding. And Lane and I go back many, many years. So he would laugh at that joke, I promise.
So that's the basic foundation of the difference here. You have a very sports specific application
for powerlifting. Weightlifting is very sports specific, but it's a much greater range of motion
has those other components. And strong man is kind of addition. I didn't know, I know you didn't ask
about strong. No, no, no. I love that you brought that in. Before I go on to my next question,
let's put one more little bow on that. We've talked a lot about who's the strongest, who's
the most powerful, who has the most functional strength. You want to throw in a little bit on
hypertrophy within that trio? Yeah, great. So you can actually add a couple of more scenarios here.
Hypertrophy would be more of your bodybuilding, which Lane has also done. Holly, I think you just
have Holly on, right? So Holly can smash with physique, whether you want to call it bodybuilding
or general physique or any stuff is simply improving generally leanness and total muscle
mass. And then there's a component of symmetry and shape, things like that, that don't really
matter for this conversation. So if you add that on top of it, now you're talking about who can
optimize muscle size as well as leanness, which is really, really important with no consideration
for function. Doesn't matter if you're strong or fast or athletic or any of those things.
And so there, in fact, this is so interesting that you started the conversation like this, because
this is day one of my strength conditioning courses, the academic semester. I spent the
first week actually just on going over these different categories of sport, because it does
exactly like what you're setting up here is it outlines exactly how to train. And the last two
pieces just to throw this in there would be actually, if you think about the competitive
circuit training sports, like CrossFit, for example, totally, no offense. I'm just meeting
it as a sense of they are very strong. They have a lot of muscle, but they're not nearly as strong
as power lifters, as a general statement, and not nearly as strong as world's strongest men,
but they do a lot more repetitions. And so a world's strongest man is going to win
an event doing something like five to 15 repetitions, like something, you know, kind of
depending. And CrossFit, you might have to do 90 reps in a given workout, like way more. And so
it's way higher up that scale of number repetitions. They do some, of course, that are one
repetition, but you get the point. It's just like a very crude explanation of what's happening.
A lot of function, a lot of different movements, and a lot of workouts repeated in the same day.
And so it's a very different test of recovery over three or four days of just brutal on-salt,
and asked to do things in a lot of different areas, in a lot of different energy systems,
and movement patterns, and things like that. So it's a really interesting test of total physical
fitness. And the last one that I like to throw in there is either, is basically track and field.
And now you have the truest expression of velocity. These are the people who are going to be the best
at getting you truly fast. And so if you think about this now, what do you need to have as a
functional human being for lifespan, longevity, or sport? And if you want to think about this in a
spectrum, how do I get absolutely fastest? How do I get the most powerful? How do I get strong?
How do I add muscle size slash lose body fat? How do I improve my muscular endurance?
And now how do I improve my cardiovascular metabolic endurance? This is now occupied in
all of those sports. And so we can just look at them as a model for training and saying the best
in the world at getting stronger have been doing this. The best in the world are getting faster,
peak speed. The best in the world at getting able to recover multiple days in a row.
Okay. So we have different models of that. So that is a nice foundation for all training, really.
Yeah, I love it. And there's a matrix brewing right now in my head as you go through that.
So we're going to come and kind of start to fill in some of this matrix as we go.
So let's simultaneously go back to the fundamentals, but do so with
without any remorse for how rigorous we need to be.
That's the greatest setup ever.
So let's talk about muscles. What is a muscle? What is the functional unit? How does it generate
force? What are the metabolic demands? What makes these cells that are so ubiquitous in our body
different from say the cells in our liver, the cells in our gut, the cells in our brain, you
know, what, what are these, what are these cells that we almost take for granted sometimes?
All right. Now you're asking me to do like a two semester course in 20, 20 minutes.
Look, I did ask you to do a week in seven minutes. So by that logic, we could be here a while,
but yeah, let's see what we can do.
All right. Hopefully you're ready for part two, three, four, and five of this
podcast. I'll give you what I can give you and then we'll come back. Let's think about it this way.
Number one, I like to play a little trick. You ever asked people to kind of like that
jeopardy question of what's the biggest organ in your body? And people generally are going to say,
scan. Yeah, exactly. That's what I would have said actually.
Yeah, right. Well, us again, exercise scientists. And if I didn't give you enough of a bias earlier
about being an exercise scientist, I'm also a muscle physiologist. So I'm going to give
all the credit in the world, the muscle and none of it to anything else. So,
So basically the brain, the heart, the liver, the lungs don't give a shit leader,
but they're just there to support the muscles.
A hundred percent. And if you start talking my worst enemy, the nervous system,
I'm probably going to hit and record and go off. Those neuroscientists just take credit for
everything. It's garbage, hot, garbage, right? Give it all the muscle. So you've heard my biases.
If you want to stop listening, now you can, if not understand that that's really going here.
And so in general, if you think about it this way, again, muscle is, is going to be the largest
organ in your body. And you've talked about this a number of times on your show, but it's doing
everything from supporting function. And so locomotion, getting you throughout the world
to being your biggest reserve for amino acids, what you need for building any cell, any functional
cell in your body, your brain, your liver, the immune system, all that has to come from somewhere
to regulating glucose being your biggest dump and reserve for regulating metabolism, controlling
function. I could go sort of on and on and on about the, the physiological, the practical,
general health benefits of, of skeletal muscle.
And don't be bashful. This is a good time to, to, to say those things and to expand on them,
because I've said everything you've said, but I think there's more to it. And I think one of
the things you've said, I don't think probably is as appreciated, which is the storage depot for
amino acids, because we don't really think of it that way, right? We, we sort of, you know,
Elaine did a great job talking about this in the podcast, which is we're constantly breaking
down and constantly adding new. So there's this pool of turning over amino acids. And it's very
difficult to study them from a flux perspective, but clearly some of those things getting spun off
in the moat, you know, if you're working out, it's at least a plausible scenario that amino acids are
being broken down, meaning proteins are being broken down, amino acids being released. They may
not be resynthesized right back into that same piece of skeletal muscle. They may be used for
another application. Well, it's not even a maze. Like, it's a pretty much guaranteed, like that,
that's going to happen. If you kind of think about it this way, if, so I'll give a quick energetic
analogy here. So the, I have like a cheesy video I did 10 years ago, or a set in my backyard and
shot this and put it on YouTube. So we'll, we'll link to it if you, yeah, you'll send it to us and
we'll link to it in the show notes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. That's, that's, we'll find that
somewhere buried eight year ago, YouTube land or something. So if you think about the very basics
of energy, if you were going to be out camping, you're an outdoorsman, right? Yeah, you're a,
yeah, you and I. Okay, great. So if you're out, if you're out hunting, which I am actually even a
couple of days from my hunting trip. So this is front of mind is why this analogy comes up.
And you want to, you know, you may need to create a fire. You have a handful of, of options. And the
very first one being, if you had a match, right? A match is very easy to light. And if anyone lights
a match on fire, it's going to give you instantaneous energy, the fire, and it's going to last some amount
of seconds before it burns out. I don't know what those seconds are. Five seconds, 10, 12, doesn't
matter. So some, some short amount of seconds. Worst case scenario, you need energy. Great.
The downside is you have limited supply of them. They're kind of finicky, and you better hope they
don't get wet. And they're just not reliable. At best case, if none of that happens, you're still
going to get some amount of seconds. If you need that energy right now, though, that's where you
start. In terms of your tissue, that's going to be ATP. That's going to be your fossil creatine
energy system. So the stoichiometry is one to one there, you break down one fossil creatine,
you're getting one mole of ATP out of that. That's great. That's stored internally in your
muscle. So that's already right there. In fact, it's generally loaded right up on the myosin head
or close to it. And so it can contract tissue and we can come back to what all that stuff means.
Yeah, we'll, we'll talk about actin myosin in a minute, because I want people to actually know
what this physically looks like, but let's go back to the 100%. Great. So that's your little energy
boost system. Now, if you had a little bit more forward thinking, you would say, okay, let me use
that mask and then actually just light a newspaper. If you had a newspaper or some of the other
if you had newspaper or something like that, and if you're in the woods papers, same thing, you get
fairly quick light, not as fast as a match. And it would give you some few minutes of energy. It
doesn't matter what these numbers are. It's just conceptual stuff here. And that's great.
That's going to be carbohydrate, right? So carbohydrate is stored both in the cell as well
as outside the cell in three major areas. But in the cell, it's going to give you a lot more energy
that is the most direct fast stoichiometry is a little bit better, but not much actually. And so
you're going to get a couple of moles of ATP per molecule of carbohydrate. And that's not,
it's better, but it's like, you're sort of splitting hairs here a little bit.
If that gets low, you can now pull glucose out of the blood. And for a little bit of terminology
here, glycogen in the tissue is what it's called. Glycogen in liver is what it's called. If we put
that in the blood, that's called glucose, blood sugar, roughly talking the same things here.
So we can pull that out of the blood. And then we can actually, if that gets low,
we can pull that out of the liver. So that's the basic like energy pathway in the liver then
functions as kind of your backup storage system for glucose to make sure that you can regulate
blood glucose while you're changing concentrations of glycogen in tissue. That's really what it's
doing. Cause you don't want, obviously, as you've talked about a million times, a bunch of instability
and blood glucose. That's a bad thing. It's one of the four things that your body will regulate
almost over almost anything else in addition to pH and blood pressure, et cetera, and electrolyte
concentrations. Like they don't like to mess with those things at all. So everything else will move
around those things to keep those stable. All right. So if we're in the tissue now and we've
got past our newspaper, the next thing it would be a giant piece of wood. So if you had firewood or
something like that, lighting firewood in the wild is very difficult to do. It doesn't happen in
seconds. You need to kind of know what you're doing, but it's going to give you exponentially
more fire length than you could put a log on a fire. And that could literally be on going the
next morning when you wake up and give you hours. Think about that as fat. Now, I like this whole
analogy is if you know a little bit about the chemistry of fat versus carbohydrate, they're
both big, long chains of carbon. Just like a paper is actually made of wood. It is sort of just a
separate piece of the same thing. So you get a small six carbon chain from glucose.
You can get any number of lengths of chains of fat, right? 18 carbon fatty acid chain. You can
put three of those on a backbone of glycerol and you've gotten yourself 50 carbon molecules per
triglyceride or something like that. So stoichiometry gets better here. You're going to get
something like 300 or 400 ATP per molecular fat. And that's where things get actually better.
The fat is actually coming mostly though from outside of the muscle. So energy from fat
mobilization comes throughout the body somewhat evenly. Glucose comes mostly from the muscle
itself. And then a little bit from the backup supplies, if it gets low, fossil creating comes
directly from the muscle. All that energetic background is safe. When you start moving and
you start trying to create exercise, where's the last piece we forgot here? Oh, that's protein.
So protein actually in this analogy would be functioning more like a piece of metal.
So if you had metal in the woods and you needed a fire and you had absolutely nothing else,
you can in theory melt metal with the fire. You're going to get some, but it is a very,
very low end proposition. If you absolutely have to do it, you can do it to survive.
But if that's your fueling strategy, you're in a big, big problem because you're going to run out
of metal very quickly in the woods. You're out of it. It's also the only thing you have to create
shelter and stability and to fend for food and everything else. And so it is a plausible way
to provide energy. It's just a terrible one. It's mostly there for you to reconstruct new tools.
And so if you're in the woods and you have metal and you need to make a knife, you can fashion that.
Okay, now we need to melt that thing down and make a roof. We can fashion that. Now we need to melt
that back down and make a shovel. It's meant to be kind of broken back down, recreated in the same
and different forms of the same basic item. And so that's really what we're looking at. The ability
to play back and forth with carbohydrate and fat as different fuel system. That's really like,
probably we don't have time to get to that today. It's not really the best thing, but the ability
and the need and the point of protein in tissue, it is not fuel, although it can be for what I
explained. It's really that. It is taking it and saying we need it mostly for this task right now.
We need it mostly for skeletal muscle. We need it mostly for immune system. We need it mostly for
these other functions. And so one of the ways to quickly lose muscle is to put yourself in a
compromised position because it's going to say if we're choosing between keeping that 24-inch bicep
or clearing up something we need immunologically, it's going to go towards that. This is also why
we see protein redistribution across muscle. So if you see, like say you spend a bunch of times on
your bicep and your biceps get really, really big and then you don't train your calf and your calf
is actually, and let's just say your protein intake is insufficient. You will start redistributing
proteins from the calf up to the bicep to actually enable that growth. And so you're thinking you're
getting bigger, but you're really just taking it from other places if protein intake itself is
not sufficient. And so it really is a cornerstone. And if you look at the research, like you're going
to see this bear through like very clearly as something. If you ever wonder why some of these
people are just like so diligent about protein intake and why this has become such a big deal is
is this is it's the raw material you really can't get anywhere else. And you can get carbohydrates
and fat and you can go through that whole thing in a lot of ways. You can't fake protein though.
It's just very challenging to do so. And the last little piece I'll say there is why this is so
important to me is you can't fake muscle most specifically without the protein. And when we
start losing muscle, now we enter a whole cascade of problems from physical performance. You know,
your interest is more of like aging and longevity. That whole cascade, it becomes a problem. And then
we can certainly talk about the specific changes in muscle and pass some of the details you've
actually covered before with that. But yeah, those are things like it just becomes a really big deal.
So it just doesn't make any sense to skimp on that one as a place to go. Yeah, I'll just stop there
because I can keep going. But yeah, no, I think it does. It's worth repeating, right? That when you
look at people across their lifetimes and you evaluate for muscle mass and you, you know,
divide people up and categorize them by the amount of muscle mass they have. And we should talk about
this because of course, my interpretation of the data is that once you normalize for strength,
the strength wins, but it's sort of easier to measure muscle mass. All you need to do is put
somebody in a DEXA and you sort of can figure out their ALMI. And so we tend to look at survival
curves based on ALMI, which for the listener just means the amount of lean muscle you have in your
arms and legs normalized to your height, appendicular lean mass index. You know, there's no
ambiguity about the fact that more muscle means a longer life. It's, you know, it's as clear as high
VO2 max means a longer life. So let's now go back and make sure people understand the structure
of a muscle because I want to talk about different fiber types as well, just to round out some of the
physiology. So in an effort to understand the difference between a fast twitch and a low twitch,
fast twitch and a slow twitch muscle fiber, which has a metabolic difference. I'm curious as to what
the structural difference is and maybe just kind of explaining how myofibrils work and things like
that. Yeah, sure. So let me go back just a little bit to understand whole human function movement.
I won't go as deep into this one though. If you just think about how you actually create movement,
it really has three core functions. So number one, you have to have some sort of direction or signal,
and this is going to be coming from your nervous system. And so whether this is central peripheral,
whether this is autonomic, whether this is a controlled somatic action response, it doesn't
really matter for this conversation. The nerve has to tell it what to do. So nerves, you get that
one. That's it. Don't take anything else in nervous system. You get that control. Now that nerve then
has to go into muscle fiber and tell the muscle fiber to contract. Okay, the muscle fiber then is
part two. So the cell actually has to contract itself, but that actually doesn't cause movement.
Muscles are not attached to bone. That's not how it works. So muscle fibers are surrounded by
connective tissue. All those connective tissue are bundled together in like a package. So if you
imagine buying a bunch of strips of bacon from the butcher and they would wrap that up and kind of
saran wrap together, that's actually kind of what a muscle looks like. So you've got that
saran wrap connecting it. So if you pulled on one piece of bacon, you'd notice the whole package
moves. And that's, that's sort of the point. You're transferring force from muscle through
connective tissue. That connective tissue comes together into a tendon and that tendon then
attaches to bone. And so the third part for human movement is actually connective tissue.
And so you have to have a signal, you have to have a muscle contract that has to make connective
tissue pull on a bone. That actually is what generates human movement. Well, if you look at
the front end, we'll leave the neuroscience to other people. You look at the connective tissue
and it's very difficult to understand what's happening there for a number of reasons, but
mostly it's, it's, it's not plastic. When we look at muscle, it's tremendously plastic. And what I
mean by that is it adapts. It changes very quickly, quickly and rapidly in response to a
lot of things. Connective tissues doesn't have a blood flow supply. It doesn't have an energetic
demand. It's just, it's kind of just there. It's, there's more to that story, but we'll just kind of
leave it like that. The core of the issue of adaptations, whether they are pro or negative,
is going to be in skeletal muscle. And so here's what that actually looks like. A nerve will come
down and actually attach and innervate to a whole host of muscle fibers. And so you can imagine
skeletal muscle fibers are some of the largest cells in all of biology by diameter. They're
tremendous in humans. In fact, what's actually very interesting about humans that makes us special
is our muscle fibers are what's called multinucleated. And so you probably remember this term from like
med school or something like that. In fact, I, whenever I talked to biology people about this,
like their head is blown because I forget how lost in exercise science I get,
but like us nerds, but it's very uncommon in nature to see cells that have more than one
nucleus. And the nucleus is the, is the core of the cell. If you will, it's what holds your DNA.
That's what controls and tells you when to replicate proteins, to grow, shrink, die, repair.
So the whole control center. So the fact that skeletal muscle has many of them per cell.
In fact, it's not a few, it's not two or three, it is thousands per cell. So skeletal muscle
can be extraordinarily large. You can actually, I have a video of this somewhere. I can't remember,
actually, there might've been a picture in a men's health thing we did. There's a video somewhere.
We're actually, we'll find that and we'll also put that in the show notes.
Okay. I can actually pick up a single muscle fiber from the human with tweezers and you can see it
with your naked eye. So we could hold this. In fact, I could do it right now. If I had one,
I could hold it in front of the camera and you'd be able to see an actual whole muscle cell.
They're that large. In fact, they can be very, very long. So they can be several inches.
And let's help folks understand what defines a cell because normally outside of the muscle,
we kind of define a cell by a cell membrane has a single nucleus. I mean, we kind of know what the
constitutive elements here. This is defined also by a cell membrane, but it's a sort of a longer
looking tube as opposed to a sphere. Oh, yeah. Just sort of. Thank you. Yeah. Yeah. Good distinction.
All right. Sort of, again, get lost in exercise science here. So yeah, if you remember,
you're back to high school biology and you think of a cell as like a circle or an oval.
It's like that. It's circular, but it's a tube. So it's a very long tube. The way to think about it
is like a ponytail. So if you think about a ponytail, you think about it as one thing. It is a ponytail,
but it's made up of a whole bunch of long tube individual hairs. And they all wrap together to
make a ponytail. That's what a cell, a skeletal muscle cell looks like, which is actually quite
different than a cardiac cell. Those are more rectangular, if you will, that they're shorter
and wider. Skeletal muscle fibers are very long or in error, but still circular. They still have
a cell membrane. They have a bunch of nuclei. Most of the organelle are the same as any other
thing that contract all units we can get to in a second. But yeah, that's the basic setup of them.
And just give me the typical length of a skeletal muscle cell.
You can't really give a typical because depending on what you'll see, a skeletal muscle is structure
as function. So if you can contrast this to cardiac tissue. So cardiac tissue is actually
quite interesting because it is what we call the ultimate slow twitch fiber. And so all the
cardiac tissue is slow twitch. And in fact, the slow twitch are even more slow twitch than the
skeletal and there tend to be fairly uniform. So you could give specific numbers and cross-sectional
area and diameter length on those skeletal muscle. If you look at like you're sartorius,
which is that kind of muscle that goes from that pointy part of the front of your hip down to the
inside middle of your knee, theoretically, those fibers could run the whole line.
A single cell. Correct.
Can run that whole length. Yeah. Even if it runs half that length, that's, that's extraordinary.
You go back though, and you'd go to like an ocular muscle and it's going to be mining. It's going to
be extremely small and like, if you go to muscles in your digitize your fingers, they're going to
be very, very, very, very short. So it's sort of, there is no like classic range. It could be from
millimeters to literally inches and like. So what, so presumably the reason that these cells have
multiple nuclei is, you know, basically to decentralize the actions of cellular construction,
right? So you've got DNA making RNA in the proximity of that nucleus coming out onto the
Golgi making protein. And if you had, for example, you know, even a one centimeter long cell,
which is enormous, outrageous, you couldn't simply make all of that work with one nucleus. So
the question is, does that mean these nuclei act independently?
Like what's the, where's the central command on this? It seems like a remarkable problem.
Okay. Boy, remarkable problem. Remarkable advantage, right? It's the same.
Hard to control, but amazingly adaptive. Exactly. This is exactly right. So if you want to dive
down the entire nucleation question, this gets very, very interesting because a handful of things
we've actually shown in our lab that a lot of professional athletes have more nuclei per volume.
And so this is one of the things that I posit is maybe this is why they can adapt so well.
My, what's why they can handle the volume that they can handle is they just simply have more of
these nuclei around. And you believe that that is how much genetic and how much adaptation to
training? Boy, I would love to give you an answer there. We have like anything that's going to be,
okay. So there's going to be a component to both. We actually know of numerous
lifestyle factors or your influence these things, but the more recent data are showing this.
In general, we have thought that nuclei have a couple of things. So one, it's not just nuclei
count that matters, which is what we previously thought the shape matters. And so there's
different, there's like spheres, there's ovals, they're all kinds. And it looks like the shape
determines the function, the location determines the function. And so it looks like there are
subtypes of nuclei that surround, for example, the mitochondria. And they're going to be very
specific to mitochondria repair. And then there's other types that are more specific to periphery,
that'll do cell wall damage. And then there are some actually that are regulating injury, specifically,
this is what it looks like right now. And so there are subtypes, and this is very, very recent
understanding. And this is probably why some folks recover and respond to injury more than others is
they just simply have more of the subtype. Now your question nature versus nurture, that's
challenging about that is the measurement fidelity here is difficult and attack is moving quickly,
but it's sort of like every couple of years when the microscopes get better, we sort of realize that
a whole three previous years are now invalidated. And so there's just a lot of movement back and
forth. And in fact, if you look at this related to cell growth, other words, hypertrophy, there
seems to be tremendous confusion about the role of these things in growth or not. So there used to be
a thing that we referred to as a myonuclear domain limitation. So in other words, a cell would only
grow. So this would be your fiber, it would only hypertrophy or grow in diameter, to the extent at
which the nuclei could control it. And so in order to gain more growth, you actually have to get more
satellite cells to come in and add nuclei. And then when you detrain, that cell goes back down
in diameter, but you preserve the amount of nuclear number. And so then now retraining is easier than
it was the first time. So I mean, this is unbelievable, but this is the old adage of
muscle memory, quote unquote, it's easier to regain muscle you once had than to put on muscle you never
had. And I've never heard a molecular explanation for that. But that's a very plausible mechanism,
right? Which is, you retain the nuclei. It looks like that's not correct. Interesting. So there's
like, it's very, it's very back and forth, is the way I'll say it. So something is there. The story I
just outlined to you, like, it makes intuitive sense. I got really hot on it for a number of years.
And then it was like some more challenging data came out and it's like, well, we don't think so.
I'm just gonna have to say like, this is like a like, every week, another paper comes out and it's
just like, okay, now we're back on it. And now we're back off. And now we realize there's subtypes of
land and play. And they're like, oh, shit, okay. But it will lend itself obviously to a longitudinal
type study. I mean, in an ideal world, you would take relatively young, presumably pliable athletes,
you know, in their teens and study them over time under different training demands.
You know, obviously the dream case is doing it with with identical twins. So that which we've done,
you have. Yeah. So I could just totally interrupt you and go to that.
Yeah, well, actually, let's put a pin in because I want to come back to making sure people still
understand how these things work. So we've now established that muscle cells are kind of unlike
any other cell in the body. How hungry are they for energy? Yeah. You know, so for example,
when we look at the liver, you know, I always think of a liver as a beautiful organ, maybe not quite
as cool as the muscle, but but it has a special place in my heart. Because I've always argued
that the reason there is no extracorporeal support for the liver is we simply can't replicate its
complexity. Right. So for listeners, extracorporeal means outside of the body. So dialysis is
extracorporeal support for the kidney. You know, a vad or an ECMO is extracorporeal support for
the heart or heart and lungs combined a ventilator extracorporeal support for lungs. We can't do that
for a liver, right? If a patient tragically overdoses on Tylenol in an attempt to take their
life and they reach a point of irreversibly damaging the liver, you can't put them on liver
support until they get a transplant. That patient will be dead in about two days if they don't get
a transplant. And I think it comes down to a lot of the stuff you already talked about. I mean,
glucose homeostasis, one of the most important bits of homeostasis in the body, is controlled
with a level of precision. I can't fathom. I can sit and talk about the liver with the same
level of excitement that you talk about the muscles. And yet here's what's interesting.
The liver is not a metabolically greedy organ. It really doesn't on its own consume much energy.
The brain, by contrast, a very complex organ, an incredibly metabolically greedy organ,
which is probably why we need the liver to support the brain without the liver being so
good at maintaining glucose homeostasis. Our brain would have either needed an adaptation
strategy away from glucose, or we wouldn't have brains as large as we do. Where does the muscle
fit into this hierarchy? Where is the muscle a high maintenance organ? Yeah. So, you know,
what's cool about the liver is it's kind of like a professional fighter where like you can beat it
up a lot. That's right. You can't do much to the kidneys. That's right. They just don't have
sustainability. Right. So I have like a secondary level of liver because it's the closest thing in
the body to skeletal muscle in terms of like fact that it is listening and it will respond and it
can change. And as you said, very adaptive, right? I mean, you'll appreciate this if you didn't already
know it. When I was in my residency, we would do quite a number of live donor liver transplants.
So this would be an operation where an individual would donate a third to a half of their liver
to another individual where there was a really good HLA match. Well, here's what was really
interesting. The speed with which that portion of their liver would regenerate was so staggering
that if you didn't anticipate it with inhumane doses of intravenous phosphorus, they would
have an enormous metabolic crisis. Oh yeah, totally. That makes sense. Yeah. So basically,
there was no amount of food you could give this person to allow them to have enough
phosphate backbone to go and make, you know, for the DNA and RNA and protein synthesis that was
going to be necessary to reproduce their liver. So yeah, you just had to basically be giving them IV
FOS nonstop because they could say, it's like what we have to do to fibers when we're doing our
single fiber experiments, like you have to bathe them. You just have to have a permanent path of
phosphorus. That's right. And they could regenerate a third of their liver in two weeks. Yeah. It's
simply staggering. And now, of course, the caveat for the person listening is this only works when
the architecture of the liver is preserved. So once you cross into the path of cirrhosis and
inflammation, it's over. So unfortunately, that person whose liver has been so beat up, for
example, status post-naphal D, NASH or alcoholic liver disease, you get to a point where it no
longer has that capacity to regenerate. Yeah. You know, the kind of the nice part about the story is
if you fix it before that, you have a good chance. Absolutely. Like so you can mess up for a long
time. But if you do take that action before you hit that level, you can get, I shouldn't even say
this way, but like you can almost get back to scratch. Like you can get a lot of regeneration.
Yeah, you're right. And the kidneys, you know, being so sensitive to blood pressure,
so sensitive to the damage of high glucose, the lungs being so sensitive to smoking and things
like that. Yeah. I don't know. For me, I just think the liver is an unsung hero of the body.
Well, it's the thing that keeps you like, it's the bonk, right? Like you know,
there's some endurance towards like when the liver is finished, it doesn't matter how much
mental strength you have. Like it's a wrap. You are going down. If you get hit in the liver,
if you watch any sports, you get hit in the liver, instantaneously, you're crippled.
Doesn't matter. You could be like mentally, you're there, but your body will seize and shut you down.
So it's a very same thing doesn't happen. Yeah. I feel like that. Isn't that what happened to
Oscar de la Hoya against Bernard Hopkins? Do you remember that fight? I don't remember that fight,
but I've seen it 50 times. I've seen it 500 times. I work a lot with UFC fighters and a number of,
I have actually a headline fight this weekend for one of my guys. So yeah, I've seen it in those
sports a ton. I've seen a little toe, just the tip of a toe click the liver and world champions
just get locked up and fall to the crown. So it does not like being aggregated like that,
but it will handle a beating. You know, for the most part you can, you can beat it up pretty good.
And if you see like any blood chemistry stuff and you're looking at ALT, AST stuff and you're like,
ah, you're free. It'll come back to you. Like if you take the right steps, the kidney is the one
you see when you're like, Oh, like we're not coming back from this one. So anyhow. All right.
So going back to muscle. Yeah, it is. It's a tremendously
responsive to everything you're doing and it's listening. So your question of how energetically
demanding it is. Well, there's a couple of things to say about this. People will talk a lot about,
Hey, if you add more muscle mass, then that's going to base, that's going to elevate your
basal metabolic rate. So you'll burn more calories just sitting up. That is true, but it's not to a
level that you actually think it's probably like you're, I think the numbers are something like 30
calories. With how much increase in muscle mass? Like per pound. Per pound. Okay. If you think
it's like something like that, it's like, it's not actually level and you can make the argument
hold after three or four years. That is that extra five or 10 pounds. Okay. Like sure. But it's not
like, I feel like some people think it's going to go from their basal metabolic rates going to go
from 1500 calories a day to 2,500 because they put on five pounds of milk. So like that, that's
way outside the realm of what's going to happen. There are many reasons you probably want to put
some muscle on, but like adding the metabolic boost. And that's because the question is how
energetically demanding are they actually think about it the opposite. Like scallop muscle is
pretty lazy. It wants to be as efficient as possible because if you think about functionality
of physiology, you want your brain running full course as often as you possibly can, right? You
want continual interception of what's happening in your outside world, as well as introspection
going on. It's also making decisions, et cetera. Skeletal muscle is simply like a backup system.
It's think of more about it was like, what do you need done boss? You need something done to elevate
your function or on it. If not, we're going to sit down and shut up and wait to be sort of
pulled a little bit. And so what that means is if you need energy now, muscle will jump to action.
It'll get you going. We see this from everything from meat, right? It's like if you have this
energetic need to burn 200 calories, your photos start tapping, you'll start doing sort of
amazing. That's skeletal muscle going to tell folks what need is. This is non-exercise energy.
So it's energy you're burning that's not physical activity or exercise or the energy needed to
survive, to breathe, to digest, to go through basic stuff. So it is that other 10 or so percent of
energy throughout the day that accounts for people losing weight or not losing weight or gaining weight
that fluxes pretty well, depending on your metabolic health, depending on your total size,
depending on your other stuff. So if you ever see those people who are like, man, they just can't sit
still. Those are like colloquially the people that probably have a pretty high need. So they're just
burning energy kind of sitting here. Other people are more stoic physically are going to have sort
of a lower thing. This is also one of the things that explains how people can maintain the same
amount of physical training, like exercise performance, as well as health at tremendously
different levels of calorie intakes. Because we can adjust neat very quickly and your body is,
it's kind of like a, it's the last bit of polish, last bit of paint. So it's a huge, huge buffer in
there where you can increase mass. Yeah. Yeah. And depending on what you need to do, right. And
so we can kind of change our metabolic set point, if you will, to keep you at the same body size,
irrelevant of going up and down in calories. And I'm sure you guys cover that a thousand times with
land. So that's generally where we're at. So let's talk about contraction. How does a contraction
actually work and why does a contraction require ATP? What part of the contraction needs it?
Yeah. So if we go back, nerve is coming into skeletal muscle, right? And it would,
in some instances like the eye actually, we have what's called a motor unit. So we have a motor
unit across all these things. So motor unit is the nerve that's coming in, as well as all of these
single fibers that that nerve is innervating. So what that means is in the eye, for example,
you have motor units as small as almost one to one, which means there's a single motor unit coming in
and activating a single muscle fiber. That gives you extraordinary control of dexterity, right? And
so you have a lot of nerves coming in to control a very small number of fibers that makes you have
real high precision with exactly where you're controlling. You contrast that to muscles like
the glutes. You need a lot of strength, force production of the glutes, but very low fidelity.
You don't need accuracy of hip extension. There's basically just one thing. It's contract,
not contract. I mean, do it with as much force as possible, but... Or not. Yeah.
That's basically the only dimension you have to regulate is what is the force and speed of
contraction? Whereas with the eye, which is a great example, I'm glad you made that contrast.
Our eyes have insane fidelity too. And of course you have multiple interocular muscles. So it's,
you know, you have all of these muscles above, below on the side of the eyes and the amount of tuning
that has to happen to allow humans to be able to do what we do so well, which is very subtly pick
things up with our eyes. Yeah. If you contrast that to like your fingers, which we need to have,
it's the second highest level of fidelity we have to have. The eyes are still in order of magnitude.
Higher in terms of fidelity and accuracy. It's not even close. Like I need to be very precise
with my fingertips, but my eyes are on a whole new level of precision of where we have to be.
So if there's one to one or one to two in the eyes, it could be thousands per motor unit
in the glutes on off, on 50%, 20%. So you can stand erect while having some sort of like 20%
level of glute contraction to full hip extension, vertical jump explosion, squat, deadlift.
God, that's so, that's so fantastic. Okay. Continue. So nerve comes in.
So nerve comes in and does that. Now here's a couple of other layers. Without going too far
into nerve, you're familiar, I'm sure, with said principle. So you have specific adaptation for
close demand. There's another principle in here called Henneman size principle. So Elbwood Henneman
is one of my favorite scientists. And his principle basically says there's low threshold and high
threshold motor units. And what that means is there are some motor units that are very easy to
get turned on and some that you have to just aggravate the shit out of them to get them to turn on.
Let's make sure people understand what that means in terms of what's an action potential. How does
a nerve actually deliver its signal? Yeah. So it's, we have this fun interplay between chemistry,
electricity and chemistry. That's exactly how contraction works, right? So you have to go from
a life, electrical signal to chemical signal back to electrical signal. So what happens is you've got
sodium and potassium and chloride are your main players, right? And chloride is a negative charge.
Potassium, of course, is positive and sodium is positive. The fun way to look up this and pay
attention to this, if you ever forget here is, Peter, you're probably more familiar with this
than I am, but look at patient assisted suicide with Dr. Morrachian, right? You give a giant
bolus of potassium to somebody and they're just going to slowly stop. Their heart's going to
slowly stop protracting. Why? Because the amount of potassium intracellular is going to become
fairly equivalent to the amount of extracellular potassium. And so the change in gradient
electrically between the outside of the cell and inside of the cell becomes neutral. And so no
action potential is what this thing is called. No, no exponential curves. And so what you need to
have happen is a change in electrical volt from outside the cell to inside the cell. And typically
we're talking like negative 30 millivolts intracellular is kind of a number. And once enough of
the sodium potassium start moving in the correct directions, then the electricity changes because
our positives moved more negatives and you get the idea. And boom, we hit this split of this switch
and this is what we call all or none. And so skeletal muscle fibers can't contract at different
levels of force. What I mean is once you flick them on, they go on fully and that's the only way
they can contract. And so the analogy we use here in our undergraduate classes is the light switch.
So once you hit that certain threshold of millivolt, the muscle fiber contracts as hard
as it possibly can. There is no weight. There's no dimmer switch here. You can't go 80%, 85, 50.
It's a hundred percent once you get to that action potential, right? You actually see
the millivolts just rocket back up and there's this whole cascade of recovery. This is what your
sodium potassium pumps are doing to try to reset that gradient, put them back in the right direction
so you can have another contraction. Again, this is actually what explains tetany. So if you contract
that fiber multiple times in a row before it gets back to reset and it just feels like it's in an
isometric contraction or it's not actually how it works, but it's going to feel like that.
What actually totally off the top of it, but what actually happens is you have so many muscle fibers
and they're contracting and relaxing at such a fast rate to your muscle, it feels like the whole
thing is just locked up, but they're actually flicking on, flicking off just at a really high
rate of turnover. But anyways, so that's in general how you're getting a muscle.
By the way, just so folks understand, explain to folks how despite an all or none action potential
and an all or none contraction of a single fiber, you can still get variable degrees of strength.
Again, whether you're talking about at the level of the muscle.
Yeah. So this is the next part. This is why we had to bring up Henneman's size principle.
So within these motor units, you have sizes. Now what's interesting is most of the time in
normal situations, all the muscle fibers in that motor unit are of the same fiber type.
So all your, if you had, let's just say we had two motor units, one of those motor units is slow
twitch and one of those motor units is going to be fast, rich fibers at interface. So if we had five
fibers in that motor unit or 500, it doesn't really sort of matter right now. We have a couple of
factors actually coming on, but they're going to be of all like type generally within that same
motor unit. So the only way that we relegate force production is this. We have to know that all five
of those muscle fibers, once they get turned on, are going to contract at full speed. So the only
way we actually change how much force we're creating a whole muscle is by altering how many
of these motor units get turned on. So the size principle tells us we're going to turn on the low
threshold units first. And so if you go to do what you just did, so you reached over and
grabbed a glass of water, it's probably best we don't turn on our high threshold, high force
production, generally larger, not always, but generally larger motor units that have generally
fast rich fibers that are generally bigger. Number one or two reasons why you don't want to do that.
Number one is we produce unnecessary force. So instead of slowly touching that glass of your lips,
you'd smash them off your face because there's no way to, you can't go down. So if that motor
unit can produce five pounds of force and you need two pounds of force, there is no way to go
backwards. So you always start at the smallest unit possible and turn on more motor units,
give more force production required. Secondarily, it just burns energy. So fast rich muscle fibers
are more metabolically demanding than slow rich muscle fibers. And so you're going to waste gas
doing that. And this is exactly why your car starts off in first gear, second,
et cetera, et cetera. We lose efficiency as we go up, but we gain performance. Yeah. Yeah.
So, so cars actually, so let's let's get, yeah, yeah. So let's use that example when you're
talking, just going back really quickly to the athlete. So, um, how quickly is that response
modulated when I want to deadlift something. Yeah. So you can, you can see this in real life.
You can actually see this. I have a video of a deadlift actually from a friend of mine
doing this where, um, so the initial stuff that's going to happen here, are you going to activate
slow, sorry, lower threshold motor units, which are going to be almost exposed to the slow rich
fibers. The only way that we really know to increase that is through force production demands.
And this is going to, like, we're going to come back to this when we get to fiber type stuff
eventually for aging. Uh, and some of the stuff that came out even this week that you may have
not seen yet, but, um, the challenge with fast rich muscle fibers is they are only then based
on this logic activated under high threshold demands, which are high force demands. You can
do anything to activate and then the data will show this on aging. You see virtually no reduction
and slow to its fibers with aging. You see no reduction in size. In fact, there is some,
more than a few papers showing a hypertrophic effect of slow, slow to the fibers of age.
There is no loss in VLO. There's no loss in specific tension, which is like force per unit
of size. There's no loss of power. So it just appears to be very easy with any level of activity
to maintain and preserve health of sulfate fibers. But because fast rich fibers require
force production and you generally don't get high force production and activities to daily living,
then those fibers go unutilized for long stretches of time. Eventually they go away. And so what we
see happen is this really interesting thing called fiber type grouping, where the nerve will basically
say, okay, that fiber is being like not used. And so that, that whole motor unit will decay and the
fibers will be preserved. The other neighboring motor units will actually grow new extensions,
activate some of the previously gone motor units, and then convert those fibers into whatever fiber
type happens in that previous motor unit. So in general, what we see happening here is slow
to fibers start absorbing or slow to motor units start absorbing fast, which fibers and bringing
them to their own motor unit. And so we see these large patches of single fiber types throughout
the muscle. And so the last part of that puzzle is in a motor unit, those fibers are connected by the
same neuron and they're the same fiber type, but they're not laying next to each other. You don't
want them in the same spot. They're sort of dispersed throughout the muscle. And so that gives you
smoothness of contraction. And so one of the things that happens is if you start punching like
the entire right side of your bicep is one motor unit, the entire left side is when you contract
that motor unit alone, you get super spastic out of control and you get twitchy and unregulated
movements. And so when we see this fiber type grouping occur with aging, it's almost exclusively
a problem of fast-traged fibers and not loss of slow-traged fibers. And so that also explains lack
of fidelity as well as potentially some problems with fine unit movements. And what is the
heterogeneity of fast and slow twitch mixtures within different areas? So presumably the eye is
all slow twitch. It doesn't particularly require much force and it- It doesn't require much force,
but it does require a lot of speed. Yeah. Interesting. So you need to be able to dart back
and forth quickly. So I actually don't know the- Okay. Well, let's look at a big skeletal muscle,
like the lats or the glutes. Is there- So we have two things you have to pay attention to here is
we have a huge amount of person-to-person variation. So you and I- Within what bracket though? Give me
a sense of like presumably everybody has at least 20% of each. I'm making that up, but is there-
Yeah. So let me do the second part and we'll come back to that first part. So there's actually,
as you're alluding to a second ago, there's also tremendous difference between muscle to muscle.
And so some muscles, if we look at it, like if we compare my soleus, your soleus,
you might be 90% slow twitch in your soleus. I might be 70. And that would be a large variation
in that muscle. If you look at animal models, cell culture, any murine, like you're going to
see a hundred percent slow twitch in a soleus. And the reason is because we walk, the soleus has
got to be a majority slow twitch muscle fiber. We just spend too much time ambulatory to risk
any inefficiency in that system. A hundred percent. If you look at the shank in general,
you've got two primary muscles of movement there. The soleus being the smaller one,
they both attach at the bottom of your foot. That's your-
The two of these.
The one that goes through there. If you were to take your foot and your toe and like point it
towards your face and you reflect your calf, that one that pops up, that has that kind of U shape,
if you have a nice calf anyways, that big one that pops up to the middle, that's your gastroc,
the one that kind of sits behind, it's underneath the very bottom where your calf stuff kind of
ends and it goes in that long piece. That's the soleus. And the gastroc is almost the opposite.
It is almost exclusively fast twitch, but not nearly as exclusive as your soleus is. So the
soleus is what we call postural or anti-gravity for the exact stuff you mentioned. It needs to stay
up and it needs to be on. And in fact, you can actually have a soleus contracted for hours
and be totally, totally fine. And you won't even realize it for the most part. It's actually good
metabolically, but you would not realize it. If you contracted your gastroc for more than a few
seconds, we're probably going to feel the burn pretty quickly. So the variation in something
like a soleus could be that. I think probably if you saw somebody who's 30% fast twitch and a
soleus, that's a very, very high number. I wouldn't be surprised if I saw somebody 95 though.
If you contrast that to a muscle like the VL, so the vastus lateralis, the outside quad muscle,
as you know, but throughout the audience, now the variation gets extraordinarily large. So in
general, the VL is like what we typically say is 50-50 fast-twitch flow twitch. And to the record,
it gets far more complicated than fast-twitch flow twitch, but we're just kind of keeping it at that
level for now. We have shown actually in our lab a couple of things. So one, we biopsied a whole
bunch of people who are Olympians and world caliber, national caliber in our lab, men and women.
And some of those individuals are 80 plus percent, 85% fast-twitch. And by the way,
just did you also do VM and why is there a difference between VL, VM and intermedius?
Yeah, just due to access. Generally access and safety. A lot more potential things to hit
in the medial. Nothing out the outside. By nick, anything, we have problems.
So you could be up to 80% fast-twitch on your VL if you're... And by the way, is that true
across all sports? Like if you had the Tour de France champion, would you expect him to,
even though he's the best of the best and his VL is a monstrosity, would you expect him to have
that high a fast-twitch? So in some of the folks we biopsied in the modern space,
they are as high as 90% slow-twitch in the VL. Okay. So that's, yeah. So that's...
That's what I was like, it's basically zero to zero. You can run the whole gamut of composition
in the VL. And we're back to the same question, which is, if you had a time machine and you
could go back and biopsy them as five-year-olds, we really don't know what they looked like then.
Well, this is what our twin study did. Rather than biopsy them, five-years-old,
we got monozygous twins. Who presumably had enough differences in what they were doing that
you could see a signal if there was... About 35 years difference of training. And what did you see?
So, and if we compare this now that I can go back until... Please, you've been in labs,
you'll appreciate this. One of our graduate students who'd been in our lab for probably
three or more years was sitting next to my colleague, Jimmy Bagley, and they're pulling
muscle fibers, right? And sort of like the things that come up when you're staring at a microscope,
pulling out individual muscle fibers with tweezers for hundreds of hours on time, like your brain
goes into weird spots. And so she was sort of just telling him, oh yeah, like my dad's a twin or
whatever. Oh cool, whatever. And he's like, oh yeah, like monozygous. Like yeah. So monozygous
means their DNA is exact. So not just brothers that got born at the same time. So you have genetic
replication. So we have that kind of relocked. And Jimmy was sort of like, oh cool. Did they exercise?
And she's like, oh yeah, well like, I think I can't remember which one. He's like, well, my dad
does an exercise, but my uncle has been competing in Iron Mans for 35 years. And Jamie was like, what?
It's a dream experiment.
Wait, wait. So let me get this straight. You have identical twin parents or father. One of them has
been 30 plus years of documented endurance exercise. The other, what's he do? She's like,
no, he's never exercised. And we're like, and you've been in my lab for three years.
And this is the first we're hearing about this.
This is the first we're hearing about this. Like you're, you're fired. You're not graduating.
So we were able to pull them in the lab and bring them in. And so he was one of these classic
endurance nerds. Every workout had been documented for 30 years. He's got 50 journals
written down. So we knew the caloric expenditure. We knew that miles. We just had everything.
And phenotypically, how different did they look?
Almost identical.
Even with all the training, they still looked, I mean, I'm saying not in the face, of course,
but just muscularly, how did they appear phenotypically?
No, I know you're saying they're almost identical. The only exception was
the, the non-exercising twin was a little bit less lean. I think he had,
I can't remember exactly, something like three or four more kilos of body fat.
I said, no, maybe that kind of amazing too. Just, it really speaks to the hereditary
nature. Well, yeah, yeah. So I want to come back to that because that's what's important.
But at the surface, think about that, right? You have these two guys that are genetically
identical, presumably both looked good, right? And one is, by all intents and purposes,
a fanatic around exercise. The other is a couch potato. But on the outside,
they look relatively equivalent. Tells you a couple of things. One, body habitus is remarkably
hereditary. I mean, it is, I believe, more hereditary than, it's certainly on par with
height and eye color in terms of how hereditary it is. The second is what you're about to tell us,
I suspect, which is that the outside is but a fraction of the story.
So here's what we did. I got super excited and I was basically like, I'm going to take every
measure possible. It's this DEXA scans, this is vertical jump, VO2 max, blood chemistry,
muscle biopsies. We did psychological evaluations, we did IQ tests, we just did
everything we could possibly do. By the way, you created just a random IRB to do this?
Oh, yeah. I mean, we did it. We took time to design the study, put an IRB through the whole
How long did it take just so people understand the pace at which science moves from the microscope
discussion until you've got these guys in your lab? Maybe eight months. Oh, wow. That's really
fast. You already had the funding, I assume. Yeah, I didn't care. I'm like, I'm paying for this.
You're paying yourself good. We're going to pay this out of my pocket. Yeah, like this is for sure.
100%. In fact, I literally did pay for their plane flights out of my pocket. I didn't want to deal
with the stuff. I was like, just book the flights right now. We got to schedule the work. Put it on
my credit card. I don't care. I'm not missing this chance. So what did you see? So the what's
interesting was that again, body composition wise, the untrained personess again, five, six pounds,
more fat masks, something like that, maybe three kilos was too high. I can't remember. So I'm like,
oh, that's interesting. What was the difference in on decks? So what was the difference in muscle mass?
Like a hundred grams.
You're at the detection limit of DEXA. So they're essentially way beyond. They were almost identical
and totally muscle mass. Right now, interesting. The endurance guy did not lift at all. No
strength training was strictly running cycling. So like a very classic. Can you imagine just the
the Gedanken experiment of triplets where you had a third guy here that only lifted weights
and you just imagine I can like this was like an hour of her thesis defense.
This was that question right there. Okay. All right.
We we actually did a another study in Stockholm, Sweden with lifelong skiers.
I don't get to do around here, but these are people who are world champions, the 1940s and
50s and cross country skiing, Olympic gold medalists and didn't stop competing. Now they're
in the age of 85 plus up to 92 years old and we're still competitive skiers and compare them to
age matched healthy folks over here in America. So I've spent a little bit of time in this like
aging athlete. Yeah. And I actually wrote a little bit about that, that cohort in my book.
The ski. Yeah. Yeah. No, it's insane. I could tell you a lot more behind the scenes on that.
I'd love to. Yeah. Let's come back to it. Walking into the hospital across the street and just like
jumping off the curb because there was ice and you're like, Oh, you're in 90. And you just
decided to jump that curb for fun. Like when no one was watching you, because we could like see
them from the window coming in. I'm just like, just so just like, uh, one guy finishing a video
to max sitting on the chair, taking like two breaths and goes, I didn't understand the test.
Let me try it again. I'm trying to get back on the bike. This is like 12 seconds after
you had to max and a whole bunch of other stuff like that was incredible.
Okay. So back to the twin study. So that was, that was identical. In general,
you could categorize some things. So I'll kind of make this a little bit shorter.
If you looked at muscle quality, so this is echo intensity and an ultrasound,
this is vertical jump. This is leg extension strength. It was either identical or it favored
the non-exercising twin, right? Everything else that you would classically associate as an
exercise adaptation favored the exerciser blood lipid panel, blood pressure, body composition.
Certainly VO two max was significantly higher resting heart rate. Like all the classic
textbook endurance exercise as a B and C it stacked up exactly as you'd think the neutral stuff,
total muscle mass. That was basically on point. And then blood glucose was favored for the
exerciser, like all that stuff you'd predict. But just to make sure I understand the non-exerciser
was stronger, stronger, better jumper, higher quality muscle, more power. Again, go into,
go into the higher quality against make sure I understand that beyond the metric driven stuff.
Was that, is that, is that a subjective assessment of muscle quality?
No, no, no, no, no. So there's a, you can actually measure this via ultrasound.
Okay. And so this is like a measure of, it's called echo intensity. It's a measure of,
it's akin to measuring how much intramuscular fat is inside the actual tissue. That's what,
that's what echo intensity is kind of basically telling you. So you're saying the exercising guy
had more intramuscular lipid. Right now, but just to play devil's advocate, isn't that an adaptation
to his endurance training where he wants to have more intramuscular lipid because he wants to have
more logs near the fire. He's burning those logs. Totally. Yeah. And you wouldn't have to
dig hard to find support for that. And I think that's different from the intramuscular lipid
we see in the diabetic, for example, or in the insulin resistant. There's a level when you cross,
right? When there, when there's no exercise there, then there's a different reason that that happens.
Yeah. But in terms of functional output, but still what's interesting to me is that the
strength metrics also favored the non-exerciser. Yeah. It was all favored to neutral. Yeah. Like,
like either some of the metrics were similar or not statistically different, but like
they hedge towards a non-exerciser. So you could say at best they were neutral to favoring
the non-exerciser is I think the most fair way, but there was not a metric there that favored
the exercise on that side of the house. So what is your biopsy related? Yeah. Let's talk about
the biopsy. It gets very different. So I'll give you the quick version. There's a more interesting
version. The non-exerciser was almost identical to what you'd see in the literature and what we've
done a ton of times where you have something like it, you're fairly mixed in terms of phenotype.
So you've got some percentage of fast, which some percentage of slow twitch, but in fact,
he had about, if I remember correctly, something like 20% of his fibers are in what we call this
hybrid format. And so I sort of loaded this earlier. There's fast rich fibers and slow
rich fibers, but the story goes much deeper. That's not really how the whole thing plays out.
So these hybrid fibers are a single individual cell. So one muscle fiber that co-expresses fast
and slow twitch. And in fact, it'll express that in different areas of the length of the fiber. So
it'll be exclusively fast, which in one portion, fast and slow in another portion and exclusively
slow twitch in another portion, et cetera. Let's make sure people understand what the
difference is between a fast and a slow twitch fiber. I want to come right back to where we are,
but I just want to make sure we haven't lost that thread. Yeah. In general, there's a lot of ways to
describe it, but the easiest way is to describe it by the name. So fast twitch means that the
twitch or the speed of contraction is higher. And so those, these fibers can contract and
squeeze together through the mechanisms. We haven't got to yet. We'll get there. Myosinactin
at a much faster rate. Having said that the fast rich fibers tend to be larger, though not always,
and certainly not in endurance training individuals and definitely not with aging,
that they tend to be almost, they almost always are more glycolytically driven. And so they're
going to have more of the enzymes responsible for anaerobic glycolysis. They're going to have more
glucose in the cell. They're going to have less intramuscular triglycerides,
and they're going to be having, they generally have more phosphocreatine. Slow twitch fibers
are fatigue resistant, which means these are the ones that they can contract kind of all day long
because they don't use as much glucose. So they do use quite a bit still. They are much better at
using fat as a fuel. They tend to have more and larger mitochondria. And the downside is they
don't contract with as much velocity in general. So that's the functional, that's why we call them
twitch. And just to be clear, the force difference between them is, it doesn't matter. It's just
velocity or is there a force difference as well? So the, yeah, no, so a couple of things. In
large part, force production from muscle fibers is determined mostly by size cross-sectional area.
So getting the fiber bigger is the play to get it faster. Having said that, power is markedly
different. And so if you're talking about- Because power is based on velocity as well.
That's yeah. You times multiply the force by the velocity. So if you use this metric that we'll use
in single fiber experiments called specific tension, which is sort of like relative strength.
So you take the size portion out of the equation. What you're going to see is a true slow twitch.
So these are also called type one fibers. If you compare those to a type two A, so that's a fast
twitch muscle fiber, you're going to see something like five to six X power between these two. So it's
not- When you normalize for size. Yeah. And you normalize for cross-sectional. If you go to the
two X fibers, which is a special class of fast twitch fibers, now you're talking 20X, that power curve.
And that is mostly explained by more metabolic apparatus. What's enabling the speed? Why does
the two X fiber go faster? Yeah, it's all has to, in fact, the way that we differentiate muscle
fibers in a laboratory is we measure what's called the myosin heavy chain. And so to kind of actually
come back to micro anatomy here. So the way that muscle fibers work is this is all in a 3D sequence.
So you can imagine that cylinder. I'm going to explain it to you in 2D to see you understand,
but this is actually occurring in 3D. And so what happens is you've got two of these microfilms
called actin and myosin. Now, what happens is they're overlapped, so they're not touching each
other. And you've got myosin kind of laying in the middle and it's this big thick tube. And it's got
these heads that flick off the top of it. Right now, these heads reach up and they extend again
in 3D, but if just think about it 2D, they reach up and grab on what's called actin. All right. And
so the idea when you contract the muscle is the myosin will reach up and they're going to reach
out sort of outward. So if you're watching this video, you're seeing my hands kind of reach up
and away from my body, like I'm stretching my arms, like I'm doing a big T, if you will. And my hands
would then grab onto the actin. And then if I were to squeeze my hands and bring my hands closer to my
face, that's the myosin is actually then pulling the actin closer together. So what actually happens
in real life is those start stacking on top of each other. And that's why when you squeeze your
bicep, it actually glows larger vertically because those muscle fibers are stacking on top of each
other and that's actually elevating the size. And so what determines force production versus velocity
is what we call cross bridges. So the amount of time that these myosin heads grab onto actin,
that little place of connection is called a cross bridge. The more of those cross bridges you have,
the more effectively you can pull the actin closer to each other. The more effectively you do that,
the faster the contraction, the more forceful the contraction is going to be. So primary thing
explaining force production is the amount of cross bridges. So the thicker your myosin, the
more likely you are to grab actin, the faster, the stronger the hold, if you will. So the better
connection your hand has to that thing it's grabbing onto rather than you can imagine like a
couple of fingertips on it and trying to pull something closer to you versus having your whole
hand wrapped around it, a strap on it, chalk on it. And like you're going to be able to rip that thing
down quickly. Now there are six actin that surround in a circle each myosin in human
skeleton muscles. So again, a picture of that 3D structure. So you can imagine if I'm standing up
in a room and I'm myosin and six people are forming a circle around me, like they're going to
jump me or celebrate me or whatever, that's what it looks like. And my arms can sort of reach out
and no matter where my arms are, there's going to be somebody that I can grab. And you only have two
arms still in this. You only have two myosin filaments. You have a time. Okay. Okay. So you
have one myosin. I'm sorry. You only have two heads or how many heads do you have?
The jilly. Okay. So you have billions of heads to grab onto six potential targets. So you're always
going to grab a target. You're going to grab one, right? Now you can't increase the amount of those
actin that are around you, but we do see that in other animals. So this is one of the reasons
that explains why like fruit flies, spiders and things like that can contract with so much more
force relative to humans is they might have eight or 10 or 12 or 20 myosin or actin per myosin.
And ants, which we always think of as like further size being insanely strong. Totally. They'll do
that. So, so evolution's tool to make things stronger is give more actin because you already
have an infinite number of myosin heads. The more things I can give you to grab onto the stronger
you are, the stronger you're going to be. Yeah. You realize there's somebody out there using
CRISPR right now trying to figure out how to double the number of these things in humans, right?
So I'm not going to say this officially. All I'm going to say is, well, officially the world knows
about the bare muscle studies that we've worked on. So there have been bare tissue come through
and under my microscope, put it that way. Bare tissue is actually quite unique. So they actually
have a, so humans have that 2A and they have that 2X. Which is formerly 2B, right?
Incorrectly identified as 2B. That's correct. Most other animals do actually have in fact 2B
and the 2B is even faster than the 2X and bears have a lot of them. So this is one of the other
reasons why not only do you have that, they simply have a fiber type that is much faster
than any of the fastest ones we have. Cheetahs and other cats like that have like 20 to 60%
of these 2B fibers. It's extraordinarily high amounts. And in those, do they have more actin
targets? I think actually, I think cats are pretty close to six to one, but we could fact check that
one. But I'm pretty sure that part of it's fairly, it tends to be fairly similar, similar kind of
mammals. It's when you get to the insects and things like that, I think when that number jumps off.
But my comparative physiology is not the sharpest. So don't trust me there. So
that's a great description of the micro anatomy. And I want to remember. Let me finish the speed
thing. So what determines the speed? So on those little myosin, there were kind of connects to the
actin, it's called the myosin head. Okay. Now, part of that is a bunch of stuff that you guys
don't need to know about. But a part of that is called the heavy chain. So there's a light chain
portion and a heavy chain. All right. Now, on the tip there, the way that we get a muscle to contract
is ATP. So what happens is the myosin are kind of loosely connected to the actin at all times,
but in order for it to grab and pull, you need a strong connection. And for that connection to
happen, and for that to be able to pull it together, it requires energy. So pardon the somewhat crude
analogy, but the way that it kind of works is if you imagine cocking a pistol. So in order to
actually cock the pistol versus fire the trigger, the squeezing the trigger actually produces, it
takes a lot less energy than cocking it back. If you've ever cocked a thing like it, actually,
you have to pull pretty hard. So the energy that we need actually for muscle contraction is not the
pulling together. That's actually almost passive. It is the cocking back part that takes energy,
right? And so that energy comes from ATP. So on the little tip of that myosin head is an enzyme
called ATPase. As you know, you hear ACE, you think kinase, like you think like something enzyme
that's going to work. That's the molecule that hydrolyzes ATP. That splits ATP rather, right? So
to make that simple. So what you have to do is actually invest in ATP.
That gives you energy, use that energy to cock that myosin back into place. And now it's kind
of sitting there, but it can't bind strongly until calcium comes into the picture and gets released
from the sarcoplasmic reticulum. That has to come to the equation. It has to cause this
conformational change and act in and move these T tubules or that comes from T tubules and you have
some other things around. Once those things get moved around by the calcium and the myosin is
like, oh, boom, it connects to something. And then it just almost subconsciously snaps as hard as it
possibly can. And that's why you can't regulate force production is like, it's just going to catch
and snap, catch and snap. In order for that to go back, you actually have to invest more ATP.
This is also a side note, what explains ritamortis. So this happens, it gets contracted,
you don't have the energy to then pull it back in. So then you stay in this locked
sort of skeletal muscle contraction position. So now the speed at which you can do that,
that ATPase thing, that's what determines single muscle fiber contractile speed.
That's also that myosin heavy chain is what we measure in the lab. And that's how we determine
fast switch versus slow switch. So if you were to use a technique we use called gel electrophoresis,
basically you put a gel between two pieces of glass and you just pour gel in there and it gets
like solidified, just like hair gel, like a little bit thicker. And then you put each individual
muscle fiber in its own vertical lane. And then you put a little bit of positive charge on the top
end, a little bit of negative charge in the bottom end or inverse doesn't matter. And then you
actually put a little bit of chemical bath around muscle fiber that has a charge. You turn the
electricity on, positive goes to negative, et cetera. And so those fibers run down vertically
through the gel. We hit stop at a certain time point and the smaller ones have gone further
because smaller molecular will go through the gel faster. And so we stop, basically we put it,
we develop it like you would develop a picture, like old school photography stuff, literally the
same silver nitrate, et cetera, that you use. And we can see the ones that have gone further down
are slow to it's the ones that once say up higher are fast switch. And of course we use molecular
weight markers to confirm all that, but that's effectively what we're looking at. So what that
means is the myosin heavy chain molecular weight determines fiber type and that regulates its twitch
ability. The more, all of those and the faster those heavy chains work, the faster ATPase can
operate, the faster the whole thing can contract, the faster the muscle fiber contracts. And there
you go. And that's why muscle fiber type is not predicated on signs. It is specific to either
metabolic abilities in the old days, or now more specifically twitch velocity. So I guess all of
this now brings us back to a better position in, in, in which we can understand the biopsy studies
in these identical twins. So if you, if you look at the fiber profile of the untrained twin, it lines
up very close to what you'd seen a textbook, right? So it was around 50% slow twitch and about 30% of
these fast twitch 2A form, but then about 20 or so percent is hybrid 2A or 2X. 2A. So here's one of
the things that's interesting. When you get into the 2X conversation, there are clearly humans have
the ability to express 2X. It's just extraordinarily rare. And so what tends to happen is this.
If you find somebody that has what we call pure 2X fibers, so these are single fibers that are
expressing only 2X, a couple of things have happened. They've, number one, they've probably
had that muscle fiber de-innervated for decades. That's really the only time we see it. In fact,
if you look at spinal cord injury folks who, you know, had a denervated thing for decades,
they're as high as 50 or 60% of their total fiber type being 2X. And so this seems to be the
default strategy of if you don't activate or utilize a muscle, it eventually is going to fall
to 2X. Why? We have absolutely no idea. I could guess. We don't seem to know. We see it sometimes
in older folks. And again, 2X, sorry, 2X is the hybrid, single fiber hybrid.
2X is a pure fiber type. It is the ultra fast. Oh, okay. Okay. It is the one. So any hybrid is
going to be called something like there is a one 2A hybrid. There's a 2A 2X hybrid, and there's
even a triple hybrid, one 2A 2X. It has all three fiber types in the same cell. Those are, those are
fairly uncommon. A one 2A hybrid and a 2A 2X hybrid are very, very common. A pure 2X by itself,
though, is extraordinarily rare. In fact, we've done hundreds of thousands of individual fibers
in my lab and have probably seen in total 20 or 30. Pure 2X fibers, you're talking generally
something like 0.1% of fibers, something like that are pure 2X. Now, if you dive in the
literature here, you're going to get confused very quickly because a lot of people don't use
detailed enough laboratory methodologies to differentiate these. And so they're going to
see, oh, there's all kinds of 2X fibers. They're really not. They're very clearly 2A 2X fibers.
They just didn't run high fidelity enough to actually differentiate between hybrids. And so
you'll pick up 2A 2X fibers as having some portion of 2X. And so it's a difference between,
does that fiber contain 2X versus is that a purely 2X fiber, which is sort of a semantic
difference. But in all world, it's a big deal. If you find somebody with a high percentage of 2X fibers,
something odd is going on. The only exception here is there's no data really on truly fast
people. We have a lot on powerful people. We have a lot on kayakers and bodybuilders and
weightlifters. But as we discussed at the beginning, that's actually not true.
Meaning we don't have data on sprinters?
No.
Why?
Great question. It's hard to get these folks in the lab, I guess. People haven't been interested in
it. It's not a thing. We just don't have them. The only thing we have is there was a case study.
There's a case study done on a guy who I think he still owns a world record.
It's not hard to figure out his name, though. I can't technically say it. 110 meter hurdles,
I think, and 60 meter hurdles at the time had a world record of both, I think. Still has one of
them. He's the only one I know. And I actually, I was a graduate student at the time, so I didn't
run the study, but I certainly had my hands on fibers plenty of times. And he had something like
24 percent pure 2x fibers. I'd like to see that replicated.
So the untrained guy was 50 percent slow, 30 percent 2A, 20 percent hybrid AX.
2A2X.
2A2X, yep. And then what was the trained cardio only trained twin?
About 95 percent pure slow twitch.
Okay. So right there, you have the explanation for why he was weaker. He just couldn't generate
the force. It's a couple of things. So it answers the handful. Number one, do they change?
Yes. We know this is highly malleable now. Yeah, not even close. We actually know that
there's data on nutrition. There's nutritional aspects that will alter fiber type composition.
Anything that's going to go activate PGC1 alpha and that whole cascade is going to activate
increase a switch of fibers. Like this is going to happen, right? There's actually a study that came
out very recently on resveratrol doing it. Not in humans, but like a very reasonable dose 5 grams
of resveratrol, I think in cattle. Just like not that much at all for a 2,000 pound animal.
Cause significant changes in fiber type profile. And there's a whole host of nutritional interventions.
The question of, okay, does it change the physical activity? Like it's been answered so many times
for so many decades now. It's just like very clear. And in our case, okay, how much, how much
can it really change an important amount? Well, I don't know what these people's default is. Because
one could argue the untrained guy was actually in a, in an adaptation state. He would have,
yeah, he had a higher state. Yeah. And he, he, he deviated away from his potential.
Right. Because one thing that seems to be very clear is these two A2X fibers are generally associated
with four health. And so we see this concentration go up. Whereas any kind of physical activity or
space flight. A 2X by itself is not. A 2X is basically irrelevant because they just don't exist.
Okay. Got it. And if you have some, if you have them, it's generally bad news. So you don't want
to train into them. So the ideal scenario here is two A, those seem to be the place you want to
train into. Um, if you do any sort of physical training, those hybrids tend to go down, especially
two A2Xs, they kind of go away. And so I'm not surprised that that the trained individual had
none of them. Um, and also not surprised that the untrained one. So it lined up pretty textbook. So
the magnitude of change is meaningful. Um, so the case study, all that. What's, what's your hypothesis
if you had a third brother, a triplet who was a, um, let's see who was a weight lifter.
Or a power lifter. The distinction actually don't think would matter a ton. You're going to get the
same answer. I would not be surprised if that third was 70% pass switch to a, um, and 30% type one.
Yeah. With probably very few hybrids. If they're trained now, the one distinction is the two A2X
fibers tend to be a little more responsive to a little bit of workload. And so you have to hit
sufficient audience to really get them to go all the way away, but it's not that much. So if you're
just like kind of like a laissez-faire lifter, you'll still have some there now, but if you're
training seriously, um, those things are going to be going away. Yeah. So, so I don't really think,
given enough time and exposure, I don't really think that there's a limit to the plasticity
among fiber types. Um, even within a normal human condition. Now this was 35 years.
Yeah. Yeah.
So like, you know, do we have a sense about the window in which you are maximally susceptible
to it? So if someone listening to this is 50 years old and they've kind of been sedentary a lot of
their lives, but because they listen to this podcast, they've now got the motivation to
become big time exercisers. How much can they, you know, bend the arc of their fiber curve?
So fiber type is actually really quite cool because it doesn't seem to matter what age you are.
So training studies in 70 year olds, we see dramatic changes in fiber type in six weeks,
eight weeks, certainly. And the magnitude of change doesn't seem to differentiate. In fact,
the way that you want to think about this is it's kind of like an asymptote.
The less trained you are, the faster things, the faster the initial adaptation,
the closer to your edge. So if you're a weightlifter, in fact, we saw this differentiated.
So with our world caliber lifters compared to national caliber lifters, the world caliber
lifters had been lifting at a very high level for like eight or so years, but the national
caliber had been lifting more like four years. They were close to fiber type, but the national
calibers had more fast-rich fibers. So what this tells you is initial changes happened very quickly,
but getting from that last few percentage up took years for that second group. But we will see this
again four to six weeks to see a demonstrable change in fiber type composition is, and it
doesn't seem to matter with age. In fact, as you age, it probably gets easier because your level of
untrained is so high if that situation is there. One other thing I want to ask you about on the
microanatomy side, Andy, is explain, you sort of have talked about it indirectly, but if a person
hasn't maybe caught it, can you just explain how hypertrophy fits into this? So when a person wants
to have bigger muscles, what's happening at the cellular level with their muscle fibers?
Right. So there's an interesting discussion here. The easy answer is when we generally say
hypertrophy, what we're referring to is diameter or cross-sectional area. And so if you remember,
if you think about the muscle fibers being that cylinder, the width of the cylinder just expands.
And so that circle gets larger is the way to think about it.
And a crude analogy is getting fatter means each adipocyte is getting bigger. It's taking on and
storing more triglyceride. Yep. Yep, exactly. So from a skeletal muscle perspective,
the diameter gets larger. There's actually interesting work. We actually have some tissue
on its way to Auburn right now. Because one of the things that's been interesting is like a
bro science thing for years of sarcoplasmic hypertrophy versus contractile hypertrophy.
And so what this is really positing is, is the change really coming from fluid retention,
basically? Or is it actually enhanced of the contractile tissue, which in this case would be
active in myosin? Seems to have some initial work there. That's a little bit of both. And it happens
the different phases of training. So sorry, is the question, do different types of training
increase sarcoplasmic versus contractile hypertrophy? Or is the broader question, you know,
hey, is a bodybuilder a bodybuilder because their sarcoplasmic reticulum is huge, but their
contractile units are not that much bigger than the average person? I'm not sure I want to make
sure I understand the question. Yeah, so it's close, not the sarcoplasmic reticulum. It's what
we call sarcoplasmic hypertrophy. So this is just being increased in diameter with additional
fluid. So it is close to what you're saying. Okay. So in other words, does this thing even exist? In
other words, or is all increases in muscle size through strength training, assuming it's like a
normal positive adaptation. That's sort of weird thing. Is it actually happening because myosin
actin are getting thicker? I see. I got it. You can't add. That's amazing. We don't know the answer
to that question yet. We don't. More data have started coming out. Wow. But even a few years ago,
the idea that sarcoplasmic hypertrophy was a thing was thought of as like garbage rosines. Meaning
the idea, the sort of assumed belief was anytime muscles got bigger, they were getting bigger in
the contractile units. Correct. By the way, I'm not shocked that that was the default hypothesis.
I'm shocked that it wasn't definitively known. It was a technology issue. Okay. It was an assay
problem. Like figuring out how to actually measure this. When you take a muscle fiber. Even with an
electron microscopy, you couldn't do this? That's not the problem. It's the standardization of fluids.
That's the issue. When you sample the tissue, it's how do you lock the fluid into place,
basically? Correct. How do you take this cell out of it, living human? And preserve its fluid
architecture without contaminating it. I got it. And you couldn't do that with liquid nitrogen
immediately. That flash freezes. So if you get crystals in there, you actually lice.
You screwed the whole thing. Got it. Beautiful. Just because I'm such a freaking nerd, I can't
stand it. How did you guys solve this problem? Well, I didn't solve it, first of all. Mike Roberts,
out of Auburn, has produced a lot of really interesting work in this area. His lab is
extraordinary. But they just figured out they were able to take an assay from a colleague of
his, figure out how to preserve it, and liquid nitrogen is actually fine. But then from there,
you have to thought correctly, and you have to do it. So he troubleshot this whole thing for a
couple years. I see. So you accept the crystals that'll blow up the size because of course they
don't. If you freeze them correctly. Yeah, but it's how you thought that... Yeah. Okay. So cool.
Like this. So it gets very detailed. And I hope there's some high school college kid listening
to this who's studying chemistry, who's realizing just how cool and interconnected all of these
worlds are. Chemistry, biology, physics, they're just so linked. Yeah. Yeah. I always joke that
there's only one thing in this world. There's only one science. It's just math.
As much as I hate math, the chemistry is math. Energy is math. It's all just biomechanics is
math. It's that. Math and reductionism. But that's it. Those are the two things.
Yeah. So to go back, what the question is, and here's where the exercise scientist
came up comes in. Why is it a bodybuilder can have more muscle, yet they're not stronger than
a strong man or a weightlifter? How does this actually happen? This is where this whole thing
comes about. How is it that my hypertrophy can exceed yours but somehow your strength? And the
easy sophomore answer is, oh, neurological adaptations. Okay. Fine. Sure. But there's
nothing happening intracellularly? Well, I don't think that's correct. And in fact,
it doesn't look to be the case. And so there is some sort of combination because here's the
juxtaposition. There's a thing called lattice spacing, which is there's an optimal distance,
between that myosin and actin. In other words, if I was trying to produce a powerful contraction,
but I was buttered up next to each other, I can't actually squeeze that hard because there's nowhere
to go. If I'm too extended, then I actually can't. Yeah. So it's the same idea as preload in a heart,
right? Which is 100, 100%. Preload is going to determine stroke volume, like everything
incoming in, right? So this spacing, if you're going to start adding contractile units one way
or the other, you have to preserve spacing somehow. So the kind of the idea, yeah, the idea
is it will exceed, it will expand hypertrophically. But if it actually compromises your, because
they're going back to math, I promise you, there's a mathematical optimization for the exact strike
distance between actin and myosin to not be overextended or under extended and to have that
perfect preload for maximum contraction. And if your hypertrophy train, this is now,
I'm totally making this up, but if your hypertrophy training interfered with that and compromised it,
you might gain size at the expense of potential strength. Right. Or if that hypertrophy was coming
simply from excessive fluid and not actually contractile units, then you would actually have
a larger muscle. And when I say fluid retention, I'm not talking about like acute fluid retention.
I'm not saying like you're bloated today, you've water loaded. I mean, just there's enhanced fluid
in a homeostatic balance inside the tissue because diameter has gotten larger, but it wasn't met with
an equal amount of increase in contractile units. So if that number gets off. Yeah. I think another
physiologic point that's worth explaining to people is how much people are familiar with the idea that
two thirds to 70% of our weight, right? I stood on the scale this morning,
like that number on the scale, two thirds to 70% of it is H2O. Yeah. And then people say, okay,
well, wait, how can that be? Because I get that my blood plasma is water. That can't be where it
all is. No, most of it is in the cells of our body. And the muscle is of course, no exception,
given that it's such a ubiquitous cell. Totally. And in fact, given that it occupies the vast
majority mass in your body, giving the fact that in order for it to store its primary unit of
energy, it needs to bring water with it being glucose. Right. And just tell folks how that
differs from like what the, again, going back to bodybuilding, you know, I love following Jay
Cutler on Instagram because I was just such a fan of his as a bodybuilder. And he's just one of
these guys who in retirement is still like training hard, paying attention to his nutrition.
And it was an interesting video. So he went into like In-N-Out Burger and he was like,
it's my cheat day today. I'm going into In-N-Out Burger and he places this monster order. But what
caught me was how much he said no salt, no salt, no salt, no salt. So he was like,
two burgers here, fries here, but no salt, no salt, no salt, no salt. Clearly this guy knows
something about the effect of sodium on fluid retention. That's a different fluid than what
we're talking about now. So yeah. Well, yes and no. In the sense of like, he probably has
an either direct or indirect understanding of if you smash down seven grams of salt right now,
like bad things are about to happen in a lot of areas. Like more specifically,
if you just look at, we're getting sort of maybe after it, but if you look at hydration
and dealing with the athletes that I deal with, a weight cut is a huge deal, right? Like managing
a 15 or more pound reduction in water over a course of 48 hours and then putting that back in.
If you don't understand being hypoosmotic or hyperosmotic or isosmotic, like you're going to
cause a whole host of problems from kidney issues to diarrhea to bloating to all kinds of problems.
So you have to actually understand what you put back in them has to be the same thing as what's
intracellular or you're not going to drive fluid. You're not going to drive fluid into tissue. And
you get it in a situation where guys are peeing and girls are severely dehydrated. They're peeing,
yet they put very little fluid actually back into tissue because blood volume got so large and
expanded so quickly. They have a sense to excrete because total volume gets too high,
quote unquote, but they didn't actually balance electrolytes. And so nothing goes intracellular,
which is where you're trying to get it to outside of organs once your organs and functional organs
rather. And are there any rules of thumb on that? So, you know, we were talking before the podcast
started how, you know, I had food poisoning and in a span of like two days, I lost seven pounds.
And my weight is about the most stable metric in my life. It just doesn't fluctuate a pound. So
to lose seven pounds in two days, basically due to the fluid losses of being sick and having to go
to the bathroom about every seven minutes, coupled with not really wanting to eat during that period
of time. What is your best guess as to how much I mean, let's just posit that much of that seven
pounds, six and a half of it is water. What's the ideal strategy to replenish that in terms of
hyper, hypo or isosmotic? If I'm going to try to replenish that in the form of liquid.
Yep. Handful of things. Number one, you need to go slowly. Yeah. Right. So you got to make sure
that you don't get excessive. So I don't want to pound four liters of worth of four grams of sodium
in the first six hours. I'm feeling better. Yep. So number one, you want to shoot for something
like the neighborhood of 110% to 125% of fluid, what weight like that's cause you're going to
lose some to your, what's going to happen. So let's say you lost seven. Like my brain is like,
okay, we're going to go to eight and a half, nine pounds, like something like that. Like you want
to round this and call this a gallon. Okay. Like we're going to go down. All right. We're going to
bring that in over the course of three hours or two guys before I've lost much. Is a pound,
a quarter gallon. Well, four liters in a gallon ish. Yeah. A little over a couple of gallons. Right.
So you're going to be, you don't want to bring that in. Well, yeah. I mean, a gallon is,
you got a gallons, four liters, a liters kilo. So you're talking four kilos.
So, and so you would do that over how many, you could do that over two days. No, no, no, no,
like three hours. Oh, you could, you can, you can, you can bring it once, once your GI system
settles down. So you would have fighters that would, I guess they have to, if they're going
from a way into competition, they've got to bring that in. No, no, no. Yeah. We for sure, like,
for sure, last week guy in Abu Dhabi, a hundred, weighed in 136 pounds,
there's 152 pounds within probably five hours. And what was the osmolarity? With no urine,
like no, no diarrhea, no GI. What was the, what was the osmolarity of the fluid he took in?
Um, so it depends the guy going through it this week as well. We actually measure that. So we
actually will measure, run a basic sweat test and you can figure out sodium concentrations.
And then the amount that they get back is actually dependent upon them. So that number can fluctuate
depending on if they're a high salt, low salt sort of sweater. It also depends on how much salt
we've had to pull out the week of or not. So obviously if we don't pull out salt five or six
days away or like anything bananas like that. But if you have seven to 8% of your body fat,
you have to lose or sorry, seven, 8% of body fluid of your body weight and fluid you have to lose.
Like we're going to take some salt out for a couple of days just to get a salt out.
Tell me how many grams per day they're down to in sodium zero. You're going to get down to zero
on those last couple of days. So you're going to get down to like a classic example is we might
have them at like, uh, two and a half grams, kind of like fight week per day. It's like not
unreasonable, but the day before like water cut day, it's zero. It's as much as like you're boiling
chicken to get as much possible stuff out of there. Um, you're eating as much like as low as,
as close to zero as we possibly can for that 24 hour period. And that's, that'll have,
ideally you don't have to go that low. But sometimes you have,
that's a bigger impact than cutting calories, which you don't really want to do at that point.
Yeah. Yeah. I don't care about calories. The calories are irrelevant at that point. It is
simply physical weight of food. And this is a fluid manipulation here. Uh, if we can keep them
at like a gram, cause I last say like cool, but a lot of the times you're staring on the barrel of
an eight to 15 pound water cut on a day, like you just need every advantage.
I'm sorry. Eight to 15 pounds of water you can cut in a day.
Oh yeah. Yeah, for sure. In a guy that starts out as little as like 160 pounds. Like if you're
taking, if you're trying to get 160 to 147, you're doing that in a day. You can't, it's not ideal,
but you can. Okay. Let's make it ideal. If you did it, would two days be ideal to do that?
Now. So ideally in the situations you start off, um, you, you come into fight week in the proper
situation. So you need to come into fight week hydrated on normal or like even maybe slightly
higher salt, normal or higher carbohydrate. You need to come in healthy. You need to come in
recovered, not over-trained all that stuff because you have, like you have to play a whole bunch of
games here Monday through sort of Thursday, you're going to start getting as much of this off
passively as you possibly can. And so you're going to typically keep carbohydrate very low,
50 or less grams, sort of depending on what they're doing. And you're going to complete
glycogen that alone is going to start helping you pull some water. And so you've got to passively
do it. You can play games with fiber. And so you have these low residue diets last couple of days.
And so you can make sure you're not holding on to food in your gut. That can buy you a couple of
kilos, depending on the size of the person. And so ideally, for example, if you came in Monday,
a fight week at 170 pounds, hopefully we can kind of get you down to like 164, 165 by Thursday
with like very, yeah. And now you're, you're talking like we've got nine to do over 24 hours.
Well, you're going to float a couple throughout the day, just urinating and stuff because you're
being very hydrated. You're going to float one or so overnight, this because of that. So really,
there goes three right there. So now you're talking like we've got to do six or seven
of like active water dropping in that situation. So that really is a 15 pound week, but it's not
that bad. Okay. But where do those six come? Those six come just from taking straight water pure. So
that is the sodium complete sodium restriction. Well, you're going to have to, you're going to
have to add in some sort of sweating component. So you're going to have to do
sauna or cardio. Yeah, something like that. If you're already down, the ideal situation is you do
a little bit of physical activity, maybe to burn any last little bit of glycogen without getting
like too terrible feeling. And then from there, ideally, it's sort of like, well, you'll see a
lot of what's called a mummy wrap. So you basically lay down and you put a bunch of blankets on
yourself. It's like very easy to regulate blood pressure and make sure you're okay. You know,
the risk of passing out and you'll sweat like a pretty good amount. And then weigh in is Friday.
What time? Morning. So nine o'clock in the morning. Okay. Usually. A lot of times if we
actually do this best, you don't do much of that the night before you wake up the next morning and
you're say four pounds over and you can actually sweat out four pounds pretty easy in a sauna,
20, 30 minutes. Like something like that. And then fight is Saturday night. So you've got,
you know, 18 hours plus to put it back on. Oh wait. Yeah. More like 30, 36 because you're
going to, yeah. Yeah. And typically if we do this again, correct. Um, it's that all these,
all these scenarios don't always play out, but it's, it can be a quite chaotic. Um,
but yeah, you would, you would ideally be back to your normal Monday weight within four to five
hours after that weigh in. And so you're only touching that final scale number for a very
short amount of time. Um, so you're, you're kind of faking the scale. So you're back to that normal
fight neighbor. Uh, and then, um, by the next morning, like you're certainly well back normal.
Now the only difference, the only thing here is like recovery muscle glycogen in 36 hours is
close enough. Like you can get, if you, if you do this correctly, you can get a pretty good way.
You can actually get body weight back. No problem. The difficult part is getting brain fluid back.
Um, I'm not totally convinced that gets all the way back in 36 hours.
So that's the like little bit of a challenge that you have, but there's just no way around.
So is there an advantage to be made for a fighter who I'm just making up the weight of 147,
but just pick a weight, right to live, train and show up at 150 instead of 160. So that,
okay, the drawback is he's going to be in the ring at less weight. But the advantage is he went
through less metabolic fluid shift in the two days prior. And maybe he's actually just
physiologically better. So there's actually a good amount of research on that, uh, of looking
at exactly what happens then doing performance testing, um, pre and post. It's not that bad
actually from a performance perspective, as long as you stay within certain ranks, uh, if you get
excessive, then yeah. Um, there's been a number of folks look at, uh, if you follow the UFC, look
at Frankie Edgar. Um, he's won multiple world championships, significantly undersized. Right.
So that, that works in general though. It starts to become challenging because in the sport of MMA,
the, the weight classes are so large in boxing, you've got a weight class every four to seven
pounds. So if a guy is really six pounds, everything use of that big deal on boxing, you know,
if a guy is 15 pounds, however, you know, grappling sports, it's, it's, it's just,
and then you'll see this, like he held me against the cage. I couldn't, she just held me down. She
didn't. Ideal situation is nobody cuts weight. I did situation is that's all gone,
but how do you ever do that? Because somebody will be like, well, I'll take that advantage.
So ideally if you do it right and you can come into fight week at 6% over fight weight,
it should be no problem. Um, performance-wise you should get there other than like the pain and the
acid is to deal with you start getting to 8% fight week. Okay. You it's 10% fight week. Like,
all right. I guess it's going to be really, really challenging. Um, but yeah.
All right. Let's bring this all back. Cause I, I know I'm guessing, you know, that, that
we've gone probably a lot deeper into the physiology, the anatomy, the micro anatomy
of the muscle, but I think it's worthwhile. I think this was an investment that was worth
making because now it becomes a lot easier to talk about some of the things that are effectively
the application of this. And I really want to kind of go back to, um, how we started talking
about this, which was through the lens of different types of athletes that are effectively the beacon
of excellence in anything that has to do with muscle. So we talked about a power lifter,
power lifter, despite the bad nomenclature is ostensibly the strongest athlete at the
all out max one rep. Don't care how long it takes movement. You then go to that weight lifter who's
also doing a one rep, but boy, he or she is also got to be incredibly coordinated. And therefore,
by definition, because of the nature of the movement, incredibly explosive, but it's just one
rep, the strong man, um, he's, you know, throwing boulders and having to pick them up and throw them
again and again, again, insane amount of strength, but you, you're not just relying on one energy
system. You've got to also have a little bit of endurance, both muscularly, cardiovascularly,
the CrossFit, you know, athlete, also very strong, also agile mobile has the explosivity, but not,
you know, basically isn't as good at anything as those first three, but has something that none of
them have, which is a greater degree of endurance. I think we looped in the bodybuilder, which
aesthetically looks like, you know, better than all of them has bigger muscles than all of them,
but has to meet no other requirement. And then I think I like that you brought in finally the
Sprinter, which is the pure, you know, you could argue the highest ratio of power to weight and
locomotion optimized. Okay. I will never be half as good as any of those six. I think there's six,
right? One, two, yeah, there's six of them. Um, and most people listening to this don't need to be,
but we probably want bits of each of them in us. Right. So let's now talk about hypothetical
ways to train. And let's, I did this with Lane and people really liked this approach. Um,
so maybe we'll try to do the same thing. Let's go through some hypothetical case studies, right? So
person comes to you and says, Andy, I want you to design a training program for me. Here's what I
look like now. Here's what my goals are. And the goal is a no holds barred approach to what they
need to do. In other words, don't, don't, unless I specify it as part of the problem, don't hold back,
you know? All right. So we'll start with the easy one, which is the untrained individual,
who comes to you and says, okay, I bought it. You know, I'm, I'm all in on this. Um,
I'm willing to, to go to the gym. You know, Peter's all we already got me doing a couple
hours a week is zone two on the bike, but I don't even know how to approach this strength training
thing. I'm willing to, I don't know, put three hours a week in the gym. I want to get bigger
because I, you know, I had a DEXA scan and it really showed that my ALMI was about the 40th
percentile. And I really, you know, I looking at the literature, I think being at or above the
75th percentile for lean mass is a better place to be. So that's where I'd like to be in a year,
two years, three years. Um, but I also want it to matter. You know, I want to be stronger. I want to
be able to do stuff when I get older. I don't just want to get bigger. I want to be able to, um,
never enter a competition. I'm not here to enter the strongman competition, but like I never want
to hurt. I want to be able to chop wood in my backyard. I want to be able to carry stuff around.
I want to be able to travel with a backpack on. Any, any other questions you have for me before
you designed my program, Andy? How many days per week did you say? Um, I, I could be up to going
into the gym like three days a week, an hour at a time, three days total. Okay, cool. So you've
basically described every one of our executive clients and our rapid health optimization program.
So like, so I can nail this one. Um, I obviously spent most of my career with professional
athletes, but we deal with this problem all the time in rapid. So here's what I would say. You've
already got zone two stuff. Yep. We got to study state. Great. Copy that. Um, here's what you need
to pay attention to. You described muscle was insufficient. So we got it in our brain,
right? A macro thinking we've got to put on muscle mass. You also said they're untrained though.
And one of the things you're going to see quite clearly. Oh, sorry. I sort of left out. Um,
like I, I was active in high school and college. Like I, it's not like I've never done anything,
but you know, I've been working really hard at my job, started a family. And so the last 10 years,
my only exercise has been, um, like activities of daily living, which includes sometimes hiking and
playing with my kids. But yes, I haven't been in the gym. I haven't been in the gym in a decade.
Perfect. Yeah. You still describe everybody in rapid health optimization. No problem. So the way
that I'm just going to walk you through sort of, I'm going to break the fourth dimensional wall
here. My brain and maybe thinking, all right, we need hypertrophy. This is a base and foundation
of everything. You're going to get stronger by doing hypertrophy at this stage of your training.
Like we talked earlier, those are not always coupled. You can get stronger without getting
more muscle mass very clearly. And you can get really a lot of muscle without optimizing strength.
We talked about that at the end of those spectrums. You're not, you're at this end of the spectrum,
the opposite. Those are going to be basically linked at this phase in your training.
So we don't have to do both. You can do one and get both adaptations at the same time. Because
I'm so low on the curve. Anything is going to give me a bit of both. In fact, we can get that
from not even lifting weights. Because in fact, of our training studies, you'll see that you'll see
equal adaptations and muscle size, hypertrophy from even steady state cycling. Initially,
for six to eight weeks, you'll see equal all of our concurrent training models and studies show
same thing. Like not only is there not interference and interference effect at this stage, it's a
complimentary. In fact, a study came out more recently showing six weeks of endurance exercise
steady state cycling prior to hypertrophy actually enhanced end result muscle growth.
So spending time initially getting physically fit before trying to add muscle mass for someone like
this, it's a very fruitful investment. Great. So the fact that I've been doing my zone two for
two months actually has you pretty happy. Super happy. Okay. Okay. I'm also thinking,
all right, you mentioned longevity, physical function as we move down. You also mentioned,
you said three years from now or something, which tells me your mind is really thinking about long
term investment. That's right. Peter has me committed to, this is not about looking good
in my bathing suit in six weeks. I'm not in a rush. Copy that. Right. So one of the things
that you'll see very specifically with aging is a loss of physical function. And that's more geared
for power. In fact, the rate of you've probably covered this before, rate of loss of muscle mass
as you age is something like a half to 1% per year. Loss of muscle strength
is double the triple that loss of muscle power is triple that. And so what are you saying? You see a
very precipitous drop in muscle power. And why is that happening? So a little bit of loss of speed.
Aha. So preserving the fact that you can do this, you can go look at the world records
of all sports across age groups. So if you look at like track and field, what's the world record
in the a hundred meter dash and what's the world record for the 30 to this, what's the world record
for the 40 to 50 year old range, 50 to 60. And what you'll see is strength sports like powerlifting,
the world record through age, it doesn't go down that much. The world record in speed and jumping
sports just falls off a cliff. So it's preserving speed. In addition, my friend Greg Grisicki
just published a paper this week and a journal of physiology, a blue ribbon journal in our field,
right? So high as you get. And this was actually looking specifically at single fiber contractile
function changes with aging. And the data here are extraordinarily clear, have been along with that.
You see very little loss of function in siltered fibers through aging, regardless of exercise or not.
I sort of mentioned this earlier, but you see a dramatic reduction in fast rich fibers,
and you actually don't see a drop of power. And so there's nothing internal to the muscle fiber
that's going down. So what other way to say this is if you take a loss, that's the problem.
It's the fiber size. The atrophy of fast rich fibers is the almost exclusive.
The problem with aging and muscle. You have got to maintain fast rich fiber size.
Now there are some loss of total fibers, but that is actually very difficult to find scientifically
counting total amount of fiber fibers in a live human muscle is extraordinarily difficult.
So what really what we're after here is anytime I'm thinking
longevity, I'm thinking primarily absolute force and power
has to be preserved. And this is a faster fiber atrophy issue. This is a target. So these are
the things spinning in my head. So how is this three day a week combination interlock? Okay.
And sorry, just to make sure we translate that Andy, because I think that was so important,
what you just said, you're basically looking, I'm 50 and you're looking down the barrel of my life
saying you want to live another 40 years and you want to be functioning.
The most important thing I can do for you in the gym is not focus on the things that you're going
to get for free. It's focus on the things that are declining so rapidly. And I will as a corollary
to that, get a bunch of other stuff for free. But I have to focus on the atrophy of your fast
twitch muscle fibers because it's already happening and we need to save that off. And we need to put
in the gym systems to support the reversal of that process. Because if I just ignore that,
you know, I might as well be that highly exercise twin guy who's, you know, doing all his cardio,
but at the end of the day, he can't jump off the curb. He can't, you know, he's going to be this,
the hyper cardio athlete who's still a decrepit person in the last decade of their life.
To make it even better or worse, those fibers require specific types of training.
Unless you specifically do that, you just don't have any chance of those tissues. The other tissues
aren't as like hypertrophy. Hypertrophy is pretty non-specific in terms of your training
application. But if you want to make sure that you're targeting fast twitch fibers, like this,
this requires very specific protocols or like, have no chance faster, slow twitch fibers are going
to get activated with any activity of day to day. They're going to get activated with any amount
of physical strain, whether you're doing intervals, zone two, zone six, that doesn't matter, right?
Tone 28, pick whatever you want. So that you're good. It's the fast twitch fibers that require
intention. And that's why I, I, makes a big deal of it because you can't accidentally get those.
Yep. That's right. It's sort of like what we say in fighting is like, you can sometimes accidentally
knock somebody out. There are fluke punches. There are no accidental submissions. Like there's no
fluke arm bars. Like you have to know what you're doing there or not. So coming back to our avatar.
By the way, I love that line because I often say that to especially my female patients who are
completely untrained, borderlining on cactic, afraid of lifting weights, you know, they just
want to do yoga all day. And when I say, look, we have a problem here, you're osteopenic,
and you're so weak, I am worried for your life. And they say, I just don't want to lift weights
because I just don't want to get too big. And it's like, I have good news for you. The myth,
the myth of accidental muscle has been fully debunked.
Me and every other guy out there can tell you we're waiting for it to happen. It hasn't happened.
The odds that you're going to wake up and think, God damn it, I'm too muscular. It's just,
it just won't happen. The vast majority of us sitting around hoping and praying and devoting
most of our waking hours and not waking hours to this goal that you think might accidentally happen.
You're good. You're totally safe here. All right. So we know we have to preserve
past which muscle fibers for the longterm. We know we have to take care of VO2 max.
This is another, I'm sure you covered this in depth, important thing for long Kevin.
All right. But we got some constraints. We also have to be considerate of, I have not trained in
10 years. I'm going to get very sore very quickly. And if I become too sore, that it dissuades
further training. Now I'm going to lose you. I bought in, but that shit was too hard. I was so
sore. I couldn't even walk. Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. Right. I think in your show with Holly,
she talked about making sure you start with a very low volume, like, like way lower volume than you
think. We have time. Like we just need to move. I'm going to be very cautious of eccentric movements
because they will, they will generate more soreness than relative. And the last part before I give you
some direct answers is we want to start building movement patterns that we're going to need over
time. And so this is an investment. We can get all that done by doing the same sort of training.
We're practicing movement patterns. We're getting that stuff grooves. So we don't pick up injuries
later. We're not getting excessively sore. We're building some muscle mass because we're going to
get that anyways. And we don't need that. So if this was a six month program, because you can't
write the same program for the next 50 years, right? What's the first six months, I guess is,
if that's your question, right? So who's out of the way. I would probably stick to fairly similar
to what Holly said initially, which was, okay, something like one to three working sets
of probably four exercises a day, something like that. We want to spread those across upper, lower,
and kind of some different movement patterns. And we want to practice the compound movements. I'm
not going to isolated single joint movements yet. I'm going to, let's learn how to do a goblet squat.
Okay, this is a squat. You're going to hold the dumbbell sort of in front of your chest. Great.
We're going to learn to do a hip extension. We're going to learn to do a basic overhead press
or some bent rows, things like that. And I'm going to spend 30 minutes on those things. I don't even
really care about tracking progression at this point. We're going to track. Did you get to get
the movement pattern down? Right? Did you brace as our spine in the proper position? Are you breathing
through your nose and through proper positions? Is your neck in the right spot? Great. All this
foundational stuff that feels like not a big deal at all right now, because it shouldn't be.
But we're making sure boxes are checked so that when we start progressing low later,
that neck doesn't start getting irritated. We're just being in that position. We're going to do
that, right? Okay. So we're basically completely optimizing movement patterns. We're making sure
we don't hurt ourselves. We're learning new skills, right? We're learning skills of exercise.
Let's now go to the next six months. So I come back to you, Andy, and I say,
you know, this has been great. Like this is not as difficult as I thought it was going to be. I
really, I've kind of enjoyed going to the gym. And honestly, like I even see a little more
definition in my arms and my legs and I'm a little hungrier. So I've been eating a little bit more.
I haven't lost any weight or anything, but my pants fit a little bit better. I'm, I'm, I'd like
to take this up a notch. I can't commit more time though, Andy. So I'm really kind of, you know,
three 60 minute spots is all I can get. Cause I still got to, you know, get my kids from school
and work is just as demanding as ever. But how do I increase the desire to be even bigger and even
stronger and even more functional? Great. So now we have to start investing that 60 minutes in the
three workouts into different sections per workout. So we need to start doing something
to start addressing power and speed. I'm going to give that the first 10 to 15 minutes though.
We don't need to go nuts now, but we need to introduce those movement patterns
and those velocities and those that tissue tolerance that we call it. So your ability to
land and absorb, it's not creation of power, but it's the backend. How did I stop that movement?
How did I land from it? We're going to continue to invest in, in the muscle growth. Now we can
start pushing the pace a little bit. And then we're actually at the end, starting investing in
either muscular endurance and or interval stuff. So if we're still continuing to do zone two,
that's great, but we haven't worked on getting heart rate up coming back down and regulating
that whole piece. So what's that look like? The first 10 or so minutes of all three workouts per
week, we're going to do something in basic movement patterns. So let's imagine a box jump,
right? We'll do a box jump. We're going to jump from the ground and land on a box that's say 18
inches in the air, right? We're going to practice that movement pattern. I want you landing on the
box, not on the ground that reduces the eccentric landing because you're going to be absorbing way
less. So you're not going to get out of sore, but you're going to have to pop a little bit. You're
going to have to jump to get up there and we're bracing that movement pattern. I'm going to
probably do something. How are you determining that height Andy? 18 inches seems really high to me.
How do I know if I shouldn't be 12 to start? What, what level of fatigue? How many times would I do
this so that I can gauge how high it needs to be? There should be no fatigue. This is simply about
high. This is load tolerance. This is load tolerance then. Low tolerance and it's introducing
power. So you're going to start learning how to move fast, but you're going to do it and it's
the safe thing where you're not going to pull a hamstring. And just to be clear, Andy, I, you know,
I, I don't, I don't need to compete in sports. I don't play basketball anymore. I'm not,
are you sure you need me doing this? Cause all I'm trying to do is I just want to be able to pick
up my grandkids in 30 years or 20 years. Yeah. A hundred percent. So in order to pick up your
grandkids, you need to not be in the hospital, right? You need to be not living in an assisted
living home. Do you know what puts people in assisted living home? Falling and breaking the
hip. The connection between morbidity and mortality with a hip break is extraordinary after the age
of 60. It's not even 90. It is 60 ish. Um, reason, large reason people fall is they actually don't
have foot speed. What do you mean? If you catch yourself, your toe on the corner or you slip,
you have to have the foot speed to be able to put your other foot on that foot back out in front of
you in the proper position. Then you have to have the eccentric strength to stop that fall. And so I
need foot speed to get there and I need eccentric strength to brace the fall. So you don't land and
break your hip. That's what's going to keep you playing with your kids when you're 60. Got it. So
even though, yeah, so it's not, even though I don't want to be a quote unquote explosive athlete,
I still have to kind of train like one in some part, and I'm asking for 10 minutes of your workout.
Okay. Right. So I want to keep you there. Um, you can imagine the, I can continue to give you examples
and analogies, but this is, if you want to go for a hike again and you, you trip, or you need to be
able to get up and do a little scramble, you know, your, your, your 10 year old grandkid is going to
want to go up that rock. Like you got to have a little pop to get up there too. I'm going to be
able to pull yourself like all these things, right? That's what's going to keep you from going. So what
are some, I'll just sit down here and wait. You go. Yeah, exactly. Exactly. Uh, I had a patient once
say something that I loved. Um, I asked him kind of what were his goals for aging and he said,
to always be able to go to my kids and grandkids. And he meant it both micro and macro, right? Meaning
I never want to be in the position where I can't get on an airplane and travel and go wherever they
are. And I never want to not be able to go physically in the moment to where they are. I,
I thought it was just a very elegant explanation. The second part is brilliant. Yeah.
That's so good. Because that's the example there. I'll wait here versus no, I'm going to come with
you up that little rock. Yeah. It's, it's the water slide. It's, I don't want to climb up those
stairs. It's seven of them, but like, it's all the little stuff, right? Um, I have two little kids,
so I'm very, I'm very in the world of like what a four year old will do. So what are some other
things that we would do in that first 10 to 15 minutes? So I love the idea of the box jump with
landing on top. So you don't have that huge eccentric de-ce, massive deceleration. Um,
what about the bounds, skips, things like that would all be in there. Yep. Yep. Medicine ball
throws are great. Medicine ball slams are great. Medicine ball tosses up in the air high as you can
go as far as you can go behind you. Um, these are re-informing reinforcing movement patterns. You
built the previous six months, proper hip extension versus low back extension, et cetera. It is also
doing what we call triple extension. So you're simultaneously explosively extending the hip knee
and ankle. And this is a very important human movement pattern. Um, you can do that without
jumping and landing by throwing a medicine ball. If you go to, to, to plyometrics, um, you have to
be a little bit careful here. Plyometrics are totally safe for all ages, as long as you account
for volume. You just can't do too many of them, uh, at too high of an intensity, in this case,
eccentric load. So, um, jump rope, a five minute jump rope is just plyometrics right now. When you
go single leg to single leg, you start increasing risk. Like, so if you're gonna jump from your right
leg and land on your right leg alone risk, but two leg to two leg is very easy. I mean, for
for Pete's sake, you can play hopscotch. Hopscotch is just two-legged plyometric to single leg to back
forward progression lateral. I can say it's a wonderful little exercise. Isn't it interesting
when you go to a playground and watch kids play to realize the, they're not being told to do this,
just the inherent ability that they have to be explosive. And as you said, how that deteriorates
with age. Like you just can't imagine watching a group of 40 year olds sitting around just deciding,
let's go play this fun game where we jump around. I mean, you do that if you're playing a sport,
you do that if it's part of your pre-programmed workout, but it's not the equivalent of neat,
right? Where you just, yeah, it's not spontaneous. Last one I love is actually,
don't get thrown off by this word, but I love sprinting. And I just, just, just give me 70%.
You would be surprised of like, whoa, it feels like great slash terrible. But if you can get on
like a wood way or a controlled situation like that, and you can just do some like 70%
for just getting through the motion, kind of a temple is what you've, you're a runner. Like
you've caught that type of stuff for very short distances. I'm talking like a 15 seconds,
just kind of stride it out. Okay. Slowly come back down. Wait a minute or two, fully recovered here.
Okay. Ready? Roll back into it. Two, three, four seconds. And then give me, pick it up for five
seconds, six seconds. Okay. Slowly back down. Just getting used to handling movement and being
an athlete and moving and not being, everything is locked into a position where it's structured
and secure and all that stuff. So I really, really like movement, athletic movement and,
and multiple planes for people. The last example I'll give you is just back to like high school
and middle school sports. Give me, we're going to play 10 minutes of basketball, go to the court,
we're going to shoot, grab it up and down. Like we're going to play racquetball as our warmup today.
We're going to play badminton. You go over there, I'll get over here like two and two bad, like you
can do a lot of little different things that are going to be multi-planar. It's going to be speed,
agility, quickness at this point. So you're going to get change of direction. All this stuff is the
foundation piece you need to get to when we actually do some speed and agility drills next year,
or wherever we're going to get to, right? Like, which is going to be part of your plan.
So those are all a bunch of examples. I would recommend doing a different one each day of those
three. So it's Mondays, we're going to do med ball stuff. Cool. Wednesdays, it's going to be
pickleball. And then Fridays, we're going to do, you know, some, some, some jump stuff and some
medicine ball horizontal throws. Like whatever the case is, maybe, or it can be jump rope. It's going
to be hopscotch, you know, things like that. Some, I'm not against bounding broad jumps.
I typically want to start here two on two. So two leg leave, two leg land for this person,
but they can be, you don't have to be forward. They can be lateral jumps. They can be combinations.
They can be all kinds of things. You honestly be surprised. Like I want to say this too loud in
case somebody hears, but that stuff's actually kind of fun. Like it's pretty fun. You're going to
get a lot of giggles. Like I haven't jumped like this. Yeah. Like it's like, they're going to feel
weird and it's going to be way different than what they're thinking. This is like training
thing is like you'll get some giggles. So that would be my, that's your opener. That's 10 to 15
minutes. Okay. Now we're hot. Now we're ready. Okay. Now we're going to move into a strength
training. And so what I would still do is keep the same structure, total body on all three days,
because here's what's also going to happen. Once a month, you're going to miss one of those days
for more. Your kid's going to get sick. I got too busy at work. Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
If you do body parts splits, you'll start missing all day. You're going to miss chunks. So I like,
in these situations, these people, I want whole body every day. You're going to recover just fine.
I would do a different rep range. So I would do something like Monday is going to be say three
to four sets of five to seven reps. You're going to be able to go heavier. You're going to have a
minute and a half rest between each one. Wednesday. What RPE do you do there? Seven to eight. Okay.
So meaning just for folks listening at the end of that, you're finishing with maybe two reps left
in the tank. Yep. Yep. Like I want to like for the working sets. For Wednesday, let's go 15 to
20 reps per set. Right. So now you're actually going to have less, you're probably going to
drive less soreness because you're activating probably less faster drivers. You're going to
get more of a pump. You can actually like push the repetitions and you can work harder and probably
get a little bit less sore and you'll feel more of an acute satisfaction for a lot of people. Right.
Like you feel the feeling in your wrist has gone down a little bit. And then the third day,
you could go really wild and you could do something like isometrics where you're just holding
positions. Very good for joint, very good for connective tissue and very good for just doing
something different. All three of these are equally effective for hypertrophy. So your gains
and muscle size are going to be identical across the board. And now you've introduced three different
elements. Let's talk a little bit about isometric. I'm now going to deviate from my patient into back
to being Peter and interviewing. We didn't talk about it, but everybody's probably heard of an
isometric. It's force generation or muscle contraction without movement. Big part of my
recovery from shoulder surgery. I had a labral repair a while ago and this was the first thing
I was permitted to do was begin humoral extension inflection without movement. And interestingly,
I hadn't really spent much time doing isometrics outside of that with a few exceptions. There were
some dedicated a lot of isometric deadlifts I was using as a precursor to deadlifting, just a great
way to sort of warm up. But I don't think I was actually aware that isometric training could
generate or elicit the same hypertrophy response as isotonic or movement based contraction.
Why is that the case? How does one know where to be in the range? So for example,
if I do a bicep curl, I can get every range of the bicep. But do I know if there's an isometric
benefit to being here versus here versus here? Yeah. So are you 10% flexion, 30% flexion,
110% flexion? I have so much to say on this one. We're good for two and a half,
three, we go into the three hours. I will say this, we're clearly going to do a part two of
this podcast. So we'll think. There's a whole show on this area because of this. So you actually
sort of invertedly asked what's actually driving muscle hypertrophy. And it's not the workout per
se, it's the stimuli, right? So then what are those stimuli? That's a whole conversation. And the
reason hypertrophy is training wise in terms of what reps to do, what type of exercise I consider
to be the least scientific interesting is because it takes the least precision. Because the mechanisms
are so spread across different areas, that it's sort of like you can go from A, B, or C. You don't
have to have all three, you can also have A and B, or you can have A and C, or you're going to get
there. The muscle is very much listening to that signal. It's not so much for other things. And so
it's very easy to kind of land accidentally in hypertrophy range, as long as a couple of things
happen. As long as sufficient overload occurs, like you're going to get there. So this overload
can happen over time. It doesn't even matter how you achieve the overload, more volume, more reps
per set, more weight, extra range of motion, like all these things are different strategies for
progression. And if that happens, you're going to be in a pretty good spot. So barring the
mechanism session is we're just going to get so far down the road here, we're never going to come
back and answer your patient question. But that's one thing to think about. So isometrics,
the shorter answer is they're going to be activating a number of those same mechanisms.
So you're going to cause the same amount of hypertrophy. Where do I be in that range of
motion? Well, there's no answer there. This is the primary downside.
Presumably.
Certainly mix it up. In general, muscles respond best to being at the highest stretch.
So if you can have that thing at the highest level of extension generally, but it kind of
depends on the muscle, you're going to generate that you're putting more effect. You can actually
take a muscle fiber and hang it vertically and hang a weight at the end of it, and it will grow.
So being stretched that long is a very strong signal to grow. And so when you generally train
a muscle over a large range of motion, you're putting the muscle on a larger stretch. And so
that signal alone activates that whole anabolic cascade for hypertrophy. So my default, if you're
going to do an isometric is to do it closer to the end range of motion of, of where it feels the
most tight, if you will, not the finished position, but it very much depends on what,
what you're after, because the thing that gets tricky here is many muscles are single joint.
And so if you look at the soleus, as we talked about earlier, that crosses the ankle joint only.
But if you look at things like the gastroc, it crosses the knee and ankle joint. So putting the,
the, the soleus in the right position is only dependent upon the ankle, but in the gastroc,
the right position is dependent upon the ankle and the knee. And so if the knee is flexed,
you're never going to get the, the gastroc to contract properly. You can't get a full contraction
of the gastroc and reflects knee. You have to have an extended knee and extended ankle,
because it's going to just get short on one end of that spectrum. And same thing happens with
So translation, a seated calf raise only works the soleus, a standing calf raise works both
gastroc and soleus. Correct. The same thing with like a tricep push down versus an overhead tricep
extension behind neck, right? Now you're talking to triceps muscles across the shoulder joint
are not going to be put on stretch when you go behind the neck. And so that's why I recently
saw a study that looked at tricep extension in a flexed versus extended humoral position. And
the difference in muscle mass was significant when the arm was up, when the humerus was flexed.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Right. We see this at the hamstrings. We see this at the glutes,
like muscles like to be put on stretch. Well, they don't like it, but they respond to it. Yeah.
You get the better, you get the better compensation. Now that changes in a situation like what you were
dealing with because like example I use oftentimes, like imagine somebody who's kind of
getting like a nagging elbow pain. They're like, man, like every time I do a lot of bicep curls,
this stuff, my elbow just gets me like, Oh, okay, great. Hmm. Can we actually train the biceps
without aggravating the elbow? Hard to do because no matter which break your radialis,
my sister's break, like they're all going to cross the elbows. What if that's a nagging shoulder
problem? Aha. Well now if we do like a preacher curl, which is when your arms out in front of you,
you're shortening the biceps part that crossed the shoulder joint and you can still work across
the elbow joint and it will not aggravate your shoulder. If you were to do like an incline curl
where your shoulder and arm was behind you, you're putting it on stretch across your shoulder joint.
Now those bicep curls are going to aggravate your shoulder, like theoretically. So going back to
isometric question, it depends on your specific surgery and whoever you're obviously talented
therapist or whoever was running that had you on, I'm sure they were putting you in a position
to get a little bit of activation in the joint that they wanted, but not actually aggravate
and let the thing recover. So that that's the angle you pick is dependent upon a number of factors.
It could be sports specific. So if you take the case of like a power lifter,
like you may just want to train in your final position of your squat and get very used to being
strong there, going extra depth is only just going to make you worse as a lifter because you're now
traveling further distance and you got to do more work. So there's no easy answer. That's one of the
reasons why we generally frown on isometrics is they just take a lot of intention where if I
generally just say do a normal full range squat, then you don't have to guess. So if you were,
but if you had an athlete who said, look, even at this stage, I'm really willing to do a little bit
of isometric. Let's say using the squat as an example, you're going to load the bar in a low
position. They're going to stand under a weight that is much heavier than that they could ever
lift and basically push up against the bar. I mean, how are you doing an isometric squat, for example?
So you can do this in a number of ways. So you can do a bench, you can do squat. So typically what
we'll do is you'll put the barbell in the rack. And so you can imagine like a squat.
But when you raise the arms of the rack, yep.
Yep. And you have safety pins that run horizontal or perpendicular to the ground, right?
So instead of putting the bar on top of those, you put the bar below them. And so you just lift up
against the rack and nothing moves. So you can set your position, whether you're putting it behind
your neck, the squat, whether you're putting a bench below it, and you just push up on those.
We actually have these built in the lab and on the bottom is a force plate. And those allows us to do
an exercise or movement called... Yeah. So that's how you can tell how heavy they're pushing.
Right. And so we can measure force produced into the ground at various positions.
Does isometric offer any other advantage over safety?
Yeah. There's a ton of advantage to it. The advantage is you have less degrees of freedom,
less moving parts. So if I get you in a position, say in a squat, and your spine looks good,
and everything looks good, there's a very low likelihood you're going to get out of position.
If I ask you to do a... the back squat is extraordinarily complicated.
There's a lot of moving parts. We have degrees of freedom at the ankle, knee, hip, low back, ribs,
shoulder, neck. And an isometric, nothing moves. All we have to do with is compression.
Sometimes compression is aggravating, axial loading being specific, but axial loading is also
fantastic for moment of mention. So the reason I threw isometric in for our client, kind of
running back to us, you were talking about... You mentioned that as one of the problems. It's like,
okay, great. We know we can smash actually on these people with very low risk and get a lot of
stimuli there and not have to worry about getting in position at different parts. And we have this
thing called the strength curve. When we do a typical isoponic movement, so same with like a
normal lift of a normal dumbbell or something. You're only going to be challenged in the areas
in the range of motion where you're the weakest. So if you look at our study on lifting with bands,
like heavy bands from a deadlift, you're going to lift at the very, very bottom and you're going
to have very low load. In fact, like you could have as much as a 40% reduction in load at the
bottom, but when you come up and you start crossing the knee joint and you start gaining mechanical
advantage, it becomes extraordinarily easy, but the bands start getting heavier. And so the actual
tenicity that happens without the entire thing is fairly equal, if not, well certainly greater at
the top. So you can train that whole area of the strength curve with things like this is why people
use bands and chains and things like that is to be able to produce more resistance in areas where
they're stronger and they're not being held back by the weakest position that they're in. To wrap
that up, then you can actually then train that. So then you can go into that weakest position and
do an isometric in that weak position without having to put a whole bunch of load on your body
like you would need to get. Getting to and from it. Yeah. Right. So it's nice because with people
like this, you could put her in like an RDL position, like a hinge position, which is a kind
of a complicated movement and just be like grab and pull and nothing moves and they can pull as
freely and as hard as they want. It's very difficult for people with a low training age
to truly express maximum force output on a free range motion because there's too many variables
and in the right position is my back safe. Am I losing my balance? If I just say grab this par,
pull on this bar as hard as you possibly can and nothing's going to move, people can just go. So
walk me through how you do that for an RDL, for example, you're going to do kettlebell, dumbbell,
barbell, RDL. Barbell. Barbell. Yep. Set the barbell in the squat rack, put it underneath
and set the height of those safety pins to whatever height feels comfortable for you.
And so you'll then get in there and do that RDL and you'll pull up against that bar and nothing
will move and your back will feel comfortable wherever that range of motion is for you.
Your glutes can be there. Your feet can be in the right position. We get total foot,
big toe activation. You're doing this two foot down.
Yeah, you do one like it, but you would most likely start the same two footed. Just to develop
for this person. In this goal, we're trying to let them express peak force output and feeling
comfortable. And how long do they need to stay in that isometric position?
Three seconds to, some of the times with our athletes, we'll go up to five minute isometric
holds. Up to what? How much? Five minutes. You can do like, we'll do rear foot,
elevated split squat, hold isometric hold from up to five minutes,
which presents a tremendous neurological challenge. Yeah. Yeah. I'm generally up for
things that are ridiculous. I don't know that I could do it isometric hold for five minutes.
Yeah. You've probably done like, you've ever done like super high volume lunges or split squats,
like hundreds. Yeah. Like I did a four minute set of split squats the other day.
Yeah. Okay. So just get into that position for your foot, elevated just a little bit.
And just hold it for two minutes to see. It's a fun task. You'll enjoy it.
Yeah. No, I'm sure I will. What are they, where are you creating the resistance for them? You're
just, again, same thing, bar over shoulder. In that particular scenario, you don't need any.
I see. Time will be your resistance. Oh, in other words, it's isometric only in that you're
just holding a position. Yeah. Correct. Yeah. Yeah. Because you're holding, it's like doing a wall
squat. It's like a better version of the wall squat. So you can go for a long time. So to kind
of come back here, you're replacing here. That's what's interesting. Yeah, this is interesting
because I never, so I can really see now how you could create a full day of isometrics. It's
if that's, if you want it to go down that rabbit hole, it's easy that one of those days is purely
isometric. Oh, yeah. I mean, in this situation too, even holding, not that I'm, you could hold a plank.
Yeah. That is an isometric exercise, right? It's the one that people love.
Holding a hip extension position and just making sure you can actually continue to have your glutes
on utilize. You mentioned the squat earlier. So you can do this in a couple of ways. You can
actually go all the way down and truly hold that bottom position. That is challenging though,
if people don't have the right position. If you do, it's a, or you can close, it's a great way
to build it. So I wouldn't be opposed to that if they're close and doing, okay, 30 seconds,
but here's the difference. I would cap that as failure, not when they quit or get fatigued,
but when they break position. Yeah. When their form changes, that's exactly right. Yeah. We,
this is one of the tests we do with our patients and the, the, the, the excellent grade is two
minutes in a full 90 degree squat. 90 degree. Yeah. Or no, better than 90, lower than 90,
right? So like parallel, thigh parallel squat. Sorry. So why is like parallel? That's just the
standard we picked and, but the failure, as you said, if you, you know, the goal is two minutes,
can you go two minutes and you, you fail not when you give up, you fail when you basically
shoot your butt out, lunge forward, you know, make a compensatory movement that is beyond that.
Yeah. But we use that as a really nice, we use that as a great test of strength without having to
put people at risk. Totally. Yep. Yep. So you could, you could easily generate that day. You can also do,
so one of the things we haven't talked about yet is it's important that you're moving in multiple
planes. And so there's, there's three major planes of movement, which is frontal, sagittal,
and transverse, right? Which basically means you need to be moving like up and down, like a squat,
or you need to be moving things away to you and towards you like a bench press.
And you also need to be moving things laterally. So like a lateral lung, as well as twisting and
rotation. And so you want to pick a few things in these areas. The other thing you want to keep in
mind is single leg versus either split stance or unilateral. And so there's no perfect number you
have to hit here, but you would want to select something across those three days where you're
not doing everything is two foot supported. So you mentioned one footed already else, you could do
step ups, you can do split squats, you can do rear foot elevated split squats. There's a single leg
press, single leg extension. There's just a lot of ways you can do that. So you'd want to keep kind
of an eye. I'm not going like, all right, it's everything I'm using barbell and everything I'm
using to like, okay, maybe that's not a deal. So maybe I'm going to use a kettlebell over here,
because I can actually do this. This is moving over here with the rotation or press. Okay,
great. But now I'm going to pick dumbbell for this movement and this movement over here,
I'll use a machine. Lovely, great. And now you're in a really, really nice position where you're not
getting held back so much by technical demands. This person is only six months in a train.
You don't want their whole day being learning how to do a movement. And then boom, that 60 minutes
goes down. But you also don't want to be like, well, these are too hard to let's just stay on
machines the whole time. That's right. Like, it's not a long term investment, right? So we want to
invest a little bit in growth. You know, 20%, 60% isn't what you need to be here. 20% long term
development. 20 other percent is fun. Like, that's how we generally think about that 60-20-20 split.
So that's how we split it. So the last piece here to wrap this thing up is I would finish every
session with something that either gets close to a max heart rate or is a personal pain point.
So this is where I always close off with Katsu and there's some intense pain. But my last thing
is always two minutes of BFR on the air bike, which combines two beautiful personal pieces of pain.
Yeah. So it is, what's the thing that they love to hate? What's the area that they want to grow?
They hate their triceps. Okay, great. Like we're going to finish the session with a tricep blast.
We're just going to smash it. They did just feel like, yep, okay, I got the thing done. One thing
people hate is when they're not listened to. And when they come in, they're like, I want to get my
glutes in to get stronger or whatever. And you're just like, they're working them, but they're not.
So it's the double down concentrate on that. Yeah. And it's one little session. It could be whatever.
We used to do this on Saturdays with the NFL players because Saturdays were mostly a recovery
regeneration day, which means they would never show up. And so it was like, hey, Saturdays are
a gun show. We're doing nothing but biceps and triceps. Like we would just do, and we would put
who showed up to you pick one, you pick one, you pick one, you pick a tricep. Like everyone got to
pick one and we just do these ridiculous made up circuits, just like things. And then it would all
just get super pumped in their arms. And it was like, all right, now go to your 45 minutes,
go see your PT, go see your athletic trainer. And like, yeah, you're working on it. So like,
people are people. Give them a little bit of what they want.
And just make sure in one of those days we touch high heart rate, one way or the other.
And when you touch high heart rate, a classic way that one might do this would be a Tabata type
exercise where it's basically four minutes of, you know, intense work. What are some, what are
some ways that you might recommend getting high heart rate in there? Do you do it? Do you want to
do it with jumping? Do you want to do it on a bike, on a rowing machine? What do you like to use?
We typically want to keep away from eccentrics. So, you know, I don't love, this is where CrossFit
is done very poorly, right? It's just like you're putting your in a position of fatigue in very
risky situations at a lot of times, right? So something that's for this individual,
again, I'm going to clarify that comment was regarding this individual, he's probably not a
great thing. Like, rather individuals, it's fantastic. You should totally do it. Yeah,
air bikes are fine, rowers are fine here. If you really want to, you can actually do specific
breath hold manipulation. So if you just alter breathing, so this is CO2 tolerance, CO2 can get
very, very high. You can deal with the suck without doing any physical work. This is all the stuff
we've done at XPT Live in the pool. You know, we've done like you can do a lot of stuff with
with weights underwater and just changing what you're doing with ventilation. And you can get to
a level of pain very quickly that requires very little physical trauma. So, you know,
there are lots of ways we can play that. Simple examples would be do a 10 second sprint on the
bike and then go into a breath hold. Like you want to see your heart rate shoot up incredibly fast.
And then you're going to come back out of that. You've got 30 seconds, but you're going to go
nasal only recovery breath. How long breath hold, by the way? Well, you're going to see the goal is
max. Okay. In other words, yeah. So go 10 seconds all out breath hold until failure. 30 second
recovery nasal only. How many rounds of that? Let's see if you can get three. Okay. Like one
might be the answer though. Like you might go like I'm not even close ready to do this again.
Two might be there. You can also do that inhale hold prior to the sprint. So you can do an inhale
hold breath in hold and then hit that sprint. Yeah. I mean, there's just a ton
of ways you can get to playing with CO2 tolerance, if that's part of the equation. And again, you'll
see your heart rate get up to damn near maximum. That doesn't require much physical work. So if
you need to spare joints, you can do spare soreness, you can do spare energy, but you want to get that
signal soon. There's lots of tricks that way you can play. So Andy and listeners, I think we have
some really bad news and some really good news. The really bad news is we've probably been talking
for three hours and I think. We've got one case study. Yeah, we've got one case study done and
we haven't talked about a ton of physiology that I had in my 10 pages of notes here. What's really
sad is I had 10 pages of single space notes that I wanted to talk about and we got into the first,
I'm not being facetious, we got into the first half of the first page, at which point I threw it
over and totally rerouted everything we were going to talk about based on your answer. And we have
nine and a half pages of notes plus a whole bunch of questions that we got that we didn't get to here.
So the bad news is there's zero chance we're going to finish this podcast now. The good news is I hope
you will come back and we can do this again relatively soon so that listeners can have a part
two of this discussion, hopefully within a month or two months of part one. Is that something you're,
I'm going to put you on the spot and ask you this, you're willing to give us another episode here?
Well, I think we can. I'll talk to you. People talk to my people and then we'll figure it out.
All right. Andy, this has been super interesting. I literally will be putting a few of these things
into practice tomorrow for me in the gym. And if I'm putting things into practice that are in just the
purview of the guy who's never exercised, I can't wait to get into kind of more my phenotype,
which is, hey, I do exercise, but how do I take it to the next level?
Yeah, there's a lot of interesting things we can do when we get to that fun conversation.
Everything from like, if you want to see behind the veil of professional athletes, you want to see
what they really do for sleep. You want to see if they really do for nutrition. You want to see if
they really do for training. We can go down that route too. Yeah. Well, Andy, this has been amazing.
Thank you very much for your time, your expertise, and I'll see you again in hopefully a month or
two. That was good, man. Thank you. All right.
Bye.