Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hi, everybody.
Welcome to the fifth and final episode in the week of Tom.
This is the Tour de Force Magnum Opus course on Lipidology.
As we round this out, we talk about a number of things.
We talk about LPa, inflammation, oxidized LDL, remnants, red blood cells and cholesterol,
a biomarker called LPPLA2 that you've often probably heard about, another biomarker that
you may have not heard of called ADMA or asymmetric dimethalarginine and SDMA, symmetric dimethalarginine.
And then we kind of bring it back to what is one of the more tragic stories in Tom's
life, which is a friend of his who unfortunately probably had FH, wasn't treated and in many
ways is sort of one of those patients that still kind of haunts Tom.
And I think, you know, we open this back in part one by talking about Tom's passion for
two other things, firefighting and hockey, and how that passion is what really got him
into or basically allowed him to apply himself to this new field once he became obsessed.
But also I think most physicians listening to this will have a similar story where there
are certain patients or there are certain personal relationships where a loss of life
stays with you for a very long period of time.
And in many ways it colors what you do over time.
So I hope you enjoy this fifth and final installment of the Lipidology Advanced Course.
And next week we'll be back to our regular scheduled programming where we're just doing,
you know, one podcast a week.
So I hope you've enjoyed this and I hope you find the show notes very helpful.
I can't express how much work has gone into it.
So without further delay, here is the final episode with Dr. Tom Dastman.
This will be a nice way to dovetail niacin, statins and PCSK9 inhibitors.
What lipoprotein have we not discussed today that would tie in a discussion of those three?
Well, the astute listener realizes it's our good friend LP little a.
All right.
Why do I bring this up?
So LP little a, there are some people who still argue, hey, niacin makes sense because
it lowers LP little a.
I'm going to save everybody on this podcast the brain damage of listening to us discuss
that for the next 20 minutes and just bypass us to the more interesting question, which
is why don't statins lower LP little a?
Well, first of all, we need a better understanding of LP little a clearance and personally of
the belief that it is the L L receptor.
There is a plasmidogen receptor that could clear some things and there are macrophage
receptors that depending what else is going on might internalize some LP little a and
get rid of it that way.
But it's the L L receptor that clears it.
And also let's pause for one second because I realize even though we've already done an
entire podcast on what is LP little a, there's someone listening to this who hasn't heard
it.
You'll go back and listen to it.
I'm sure I'm going to do future podcasts where I interview the world's expert on the topic.
But Tom, can you give in two minutes a description of what LP little a is?
Yeah, it's an LDL like particle to which is it here in another April protein?
It shouldn't be there and it's called April protein little a and you must pronounce it
as little a.
That means small case rather than capital A.
Lipoprotein capital A is April protein A1.
That's the main April protein on an HDL particle.
So if you tell me you got lipoprotein A, how do I know what are you talking about?
You got HDL particles?
Are you talking about little a, which clearly identifies to me this potentially pathogenic,
atherogenic LDL particles.
So use the correct terminology with everything.
And Peter's got that nice podcast on it.
Our metrics of is that present in you or not is most labs will run an LP little a mass,
which is the weight in a deciliter of plasma of the weight of your entire LDL particles
and everything that's in them.
They're triglycerides, they're cholesterol ester, they're phospholipids.
Meaning any lipoprotein that is carrying an apolipo little a and you weigh the entire
LDL density.
So but you're weighing everything.
You're not weighing apolittle a.
You're not measuring apolittle a per se.
Yes, that has a molecular weight, but the molecular weight of apob is way higher than
the molecular weight of apolittle a.
But you're measuring that too when you do an LP little a mass.
But the molecular weight of apob is known because it's pretty much the same, whereas
the molecular weight of apolittle a is very variable.
So that's another reason LP little a mass becomes a useless metric.
And how do I know how many cholesterol triglyceride, phospholipid, 10,000 other lipid
moieties, other proteins are on that particle?
I don't.
And you have heterogeneous mixtures of particles that would have variable amounts of all of
those constituents.
So you can see there's going to be a weakness to measuring LP little a mass.
Now, if it's really high, you probably got too many LP little a particles.
But since there's almost no more debate that the best metric for our LDL particles is low
density lipoprotein particle number, there's no debate among those who will truly understand
that HDL particle number is your best metric available metric on quantifying the number.
And that is a better metric than guessing that using HDL cholesterol or LDL cholesterol.
Wouldn't you rather have a really nice finite count if LP little a particles are dangerous?
Wouldn't you like to have a excellent, accurate concentration in them?
Well, the only way you can do that nowadays.
NMR provides those other HDL and NMR cannot assay LP little a particles because NMR assays
lipid content of particles, not protein content.
So the only way I can give you an LP little a particle count is I have to separate all
lipoproteins electrophoretically and they all you'll see little bumps on the electrophoretogram.
The LDLs congregate here, LDLs congregate here, HDLs congregate there.
And what's that little bump that is in this person, but it's not in that person?
Oh, that's LP little a because that's due to its surface charge where it migrates between
the cathode and the anode and the gel that you separate them on.
So if I then take that LP little a hump and I immunostain it with a antibody that binds
to ApoB, you've just counted the number of particles that are in the LP little a distribution
range.
I theoretically should not call that an LP little a particle count.
I should call it LP little a ApoB.
It's too much of a mouthful.
It doesn't fit on a request form.
So of course it's abbreviated LP little a dash P. And to me, the downside of that is
most people think it's an NMR measurement, which it absolutely is not.
Basically if you want that metric and we've already announced I do work for true health
diagnostics.
I was working with a different lab before that, the lab that actually did the development
of the LP little a ApoB assay, which true health absorbed and got proprietary rights
to when he did it.
So that's it.
And believe it or not, there are people who are going to have discordance with LP little
a mass, the weight of the whole kitten caboodle versus the number of LDL particle counts in
generally Carly.
But if you really want to know, and also I find it useful, those at least those of
you are doing LDL P by NMR, you have your total LDL particle count.
But what does that really include?
It includes LDLs that don't have a pallet a attachment includes LDLs that do have a
pallet attached.
Now I throw a statin at you and we started to talk about this.
That statin is not going to budge your LP little a particle count at all, but the statin
is going to dramatically lower your LDLs that don't have a pallet a attached to it.
So your LDL total particle will get down a little bit.
But part of that is your LP little a particle count.
But this shows you you are getting benefit when you give a statin to somebody with high
LPA.
You're going to have to go after residual risk.
You know, one of the best examples I saw of this was an unusual case where a guy had an
LDL particle of 1600 ish nanomole per liter, but he had an LDL P little a of 600 nanomole
per liter.
So even though it's an apples and oranges assay, directionally speaking, he's got 600
LPA particles are nanomoles of particles per liter and a thousand non LPA little A's.
But when you give him that statin, you're really only targeting the thousand.
And so you'll be surprised at the lack of response you might see because you're not
getting to target those.
But you'll still get your 3040 here, but your total LDL P may still be higher than you wish
it to be.
And unfortunately, that is LP little a particles.
Then you can get into the theoretical discussion right now that if I could get rid of them
and basically the only way you can do that now is the maybe try niacin, which is a weak
lowering of 20% or a PCSK9 inhibitor, which seems like 30 to 50%.
Well, it would be an individual response.
But it's in that range.
So if somebody could at least afford that drug, you can't get it covered by third party
because they don't have that indication to help you manage LPA little a patients.
So and that'll never come because could I ever prove to anybody that the PCSK9 inhibitor
because it's lowering LPA little a is reducing events.
No, because they're going to turn around and say, ah, all its event reduction is they're
just getting rid of the remnants and the LDL particles.
That's nothing to do with lowering.
And how would you argue against that?
We need a drug that only lowers a po little a or LP little a and does nothing to LDL particles.
And that drug is under investigation right now.
It's an APO a synthesis inhibitor where your liver is going to stop making the vast quantities
of APO a that these people who genetically inherit that propensity.
This is courtesy ISIS.
Yeah.
Again, not to be confused with.
Let's hold our breath.
But so until then, are there people in the lipidology world who would say, Tom, until
then I'm going to continue to use niacin because lowering it has to work.
I've been around too long.
Things seeing lowers this and lowers that and they don't work.
So is niacin going to have the same toxicity that I think it has in other people and LP
little, I don't know.
But if you want to use that because you want to make a patient happy because you're improving
some metric, be my yes, I would not.
I know many lipidologists who would not.
But there are ones and look, Sam Samikas is probably the world authority on this.
Sam uses niacin in his practice too.
And I hope Peter has him on one day with a podcast.
He would tell you until we get our dad on his other drugs.
I'll try and lower it a little bit.
If nothing else, I'm he'll hash to it.
I'm lowering April be a little bit too.
And I'm if I don't know if it matters, but I'm raising whatever HDL metric.
By the way, although fibrates are probably our best available drug now to raise HDL particle
count niacin, which blows away fibrates on raising HDL cholesterol, there's nothing to
HDL particle counts.
I didn't mention that before.
And because nice and makes the HDL bigger.
I was just about to say that could actually suggest it's worsening LDL HDL function.
Yeah, you're right.
But the niacin people will convince you that the big HDLs are protective.
It's laughable.
And the small HDLs are harmful, whereas the VA has really got to show you the opposite
because the lipid poor HDLs are the ones that can accept the most lipidation.
So you're never going to have definitive answers on any of that.
But there's a lot of BS around.
So what's the best explanation for why a statin, which causes the liver to upregulate
LDL receptors, does not lower LPa, whereas a PCSK9 inhibitor, which also net results
in more or longer transiency of LDL receptors, seems to lower LPa, even though that's not
its primary objective.
And by the way, the data certainly tells us now that the main determinant of LPa mass
or LPa particle concentration is APOA production in the liver, not clearance.
So until we can really inhibit production of APOA, who knows what you're doing.
Until then, let's see.
So how do LDL receptors clear these particles?
Well, earlier, I think I mentioned that LDL receptors looking for APOE or a section of
the APOB that it can latch onto.
There's a very specific area on the APOB protein on any of the APOB particles that, because
of surface charges, will bind to a specific part of the LDL receptor.
That area on APOB is called the LDL receptor binding domain.
So here comes an LDL particle, and that domain is sticking right out.
It'll stick right to any expressed LDL receptor.
But what if there's something camouflaging that APOA or that LDL receptor binding domain
on APOB, such as an interloper like apoprotein little a?
I could see where that would slow the clearance of an LPa particle, because it's not going
to bind as rapidly and as vividly to an LDL receptor.
So most of these people have way too many LDL particles.
We express whatever LDL particles we want.
We try and express more with the statin.
What are they going to grab first?
The LDL particles that don't have APO little a attached.
And only then would they maybe then start even grabbing APO little a particles or so.
Do we all really have enough LDL receptors?
Most of us, for a variety of reasons, do not.
Other things retard the clearance too.
You know, with the APOC3, I talked about other proteins that may be affecting clearance too.
So there are just other factors at play.
But right now, my guess is APOA is affecting totally efficacious binding to an LP little
a particle.
It's camouflaging the LDL receptor binding domain on APOB.
And therefore, I better learn how to inhibit synthesis of it.
So Sam will obviously, hopefully we do get Sam on the show and we'll talk about this,
but that any sense oligonucleotide is basically going after the jugular issue, which is you
inhibit the synthesis of APO little a.
Yeah.
And hopefully you do that.
You know, the million dollar question has always been why do we even have APO little
a to begin with?
Did it ever serve some physiologic function or is it important in any other aspect of
human life?
I guess we'll know it if we eliminate it and there's some bad outcomes in that trial.
And obviously, it absolutely will be looked at for every safety aspect anybody can ever
think of right now as they're developing that drug.
So right now, I don't think there's anything they're worried about.
Sam would no more than I.
But yeah, so if we can reduce that in, I don't know that we can shut it down completely,
but he can drastically lower APO little a and LP little a levels too.
So you know, everybody thinks either or you don't, there's a lot of people who have what's
considered a physiologic or a non adversarial concentration of LP little a in your system.
So you don't have to make it go to zero, you know, where risk is concerned.
In fact, the only people that are ever going to study this drug is in people like you just
mentioned have an LP little a mass or particle count up in at 600 range or something.
They're not going to take people with borderline LP little a's and risk a clinical trial on
them.
Just like the first statin trials were done in sort of FH type people or so.
Yeah.
They're enrolling for phase three on that trial, aren't they?
And is it secondary prevention or primary prevention?
I'm pretty sure it's secondary prevention.
Yeah.
And remember, there is some data in the aphorhesus world that if you pull out LP little a particles,
there is event.
They're not randomized by the trials because how would you do that with a phoresis that
aphorhesus for the non-physiologists, your it's a dialysis where you're clearing your
blood of you take the blood out, you get rid of the LDL particles and you give the residual
blood back.
So and for at least a week or two, they have less.
But there's so many other things you're clearing the regular LDLs, all sorts of rheological
things, all sorts of other hyperosmotic proteins and things that who knows what the why a phoresis
really works.
You know, I don't want to get us too far off our main theme of lipidology, but because
they're both quite recent, let's just really, really briefly talk about two other interesting
drug trials, which look at a completely different component of the atherosclerotic mechanism
pathway, which is the inflammatory pathway.
So there was an agonist to IL-1, I believe, or maybe it was that was it IL-1 around the
second.
And then there was also a trial that looked at using low dose of methotrexate.
But you're still ongoing.
There was some preliminary words that it had.
This is looking good, but it's not been definitively released.
But there is the theory this hey, reduce inflammation and you will certainly help vascular health
in capacities.
Maybe even I have nothing to do with lipids or so.
And so what's a great anti-inflammatory drug?
Well, we've been using low dose methotrexate in people with inflammatory disorders without
a lot of toxicity for a long time, rheumatoid arthritis, et cetera, et cetera.
Cultucine, very powerful anti-inflammatory.
There's a big outcome trial undergoing with that.
And I believe within the next year, we're going to have data on both of those trials.
So in the problem that this IL-1 inhibitor that Peter talks about, which has already
published nice outcome data by inhibiting that, but it's a $30,000 drug.
And there was downside to it because by seriously inhibiting the inflammatory system, there
was a slight increase in cancers in some people.
Your immunological system has uses in the body.
So you better be careful how much you knock it out.
Because of course, and because of that downside, it will never get an indication to, for me
and you to use it.
Again if you're some multi-billionaire, it's already been approved for certain type of
conditions you could use.
Yeah, no, I think the bigger issue is really as more and more of these drugs become available,
hopefully it leads to a more and more personalized type of intervention where look, if you got
somebody who's walking around with a low C-reactive protein and a low fibrinogen and their issue
is elevated, you know, LDL-P, I don't see why you'd want to use an IL-1 agonist on that
or antagonist rather on that patient.
So yeah, it comes down to basically stratification of what's the driver?
Again this comes back to this idea of necessary but not sufficient, sufficient but not necessary,
neither necessary nor sufficient.
Inflammation is necessary but not sufficient.
You do need an inflammatory response but you can have an inflammatory response and that
by itself doesn't necessarily.
No, and a certain degree of inflammation is critical for you to get rid of certain pathologies
yourself so you never want to stop the immunological system.
Yeah, look, I believe like Peter does, these are multifactorial diseases.
We've spent a lot of time on April B. E
but there are many other contributors that go into this.
So I believe the better we can evaluate using biomarkers, the better we can identify many
of the known existing pathologies, I'm sure there's many we don't fully understand yet.
And then perhaps we can better individualize our therapeutic suggestions to these people
and know what we have to do both nutritionally and pharmacologically if that's necessary
to normalize whatever you're trying to normalize.
Yeah, it's a complex world out there and you got to look at a lot of things.
So we've already discussed many biomarkers on the lipid front and we've alluded to some
of the biomarkers on the inflammatory side, C-reactive protein, fibrinogen.
But what are some other biomarkers that you find helpful as far as understanding even
more diffusely endothelial dysfunction or other markers of oxidized states that can
give us more of an indication and say, look, you might have two people with the same degree
of dyslipidemia, but one has a greater burden of oxidation going on than the other, which
would be presumably worse.
Presumably, yes.
And the problem is going to be when you even start expanding and I can throw some markers
at you that you might want to measure it.
It would tell you there's a pro-oxidative state going on.
If your mission is to reduce atherophromatic events, trials that show, oh yeah, if we
improve this oxidative marker, it add oxidative matter, people do better.
They've never ever been adjusted for APLB or LDL particle count.
So even though you may show some nice data on them, if you really just normalize APLB
and LDL particle counts, would it even matter?
And don't tell me what common sense suggests.
And look, I'm all for it.
I use oxidative markers now mostly to try and convince people to do certain nutritional
therapies rather than I got a wonderful drug for you to reduce inflammation because right
now I really don't.
I know if I lower APLB, I reduce inflammation.
So that's one perhaps.
That's your first therapeutic initiative, lowering APLB by nutrition or if the risk
category is high enough a drug, fine.
But could I measure something that tells me you have a pro-oxidative state?
Yeah.
And people do ox LDL levels in the blood.
They have no idea what they're measuring.
Remember an LDL part, our truly oxidized LDL particle, which is the only type that a macrophage
in your arterial walk can internalize is oxidized in the wall of the artery.
And what is oxidized?
It's the phospholipids on their surface.
Or maybe some free sterols, beta-phytosterol cholesterol.
That oxidized surface lipids is what the scavenger receptor on a macrophage is going to pull
that particle into it and then you start accumulating cholesterol and you have a sterol
laden foam cell.
Bingo, you got the disease.
But can I measure oxidized LDL in the plasma?
No, LDLs don't get oxidized in the plasma.
There's too many natural antioxidants in plasma where they don't occur.
So what you can measure in plasma is what's called minimally oxidized.
All right, there's a little bit of oxidation occurring.
But it's not the phospholipids.
It's some of the struck the proteins on the Apo-B segment are being changed into aldehydes,
which is what the monoclonal antibody picks up.
It picks up aldehydes on Apo-B. But those aldehydes wouldn't have formed if there wasn't
a little bit of a pro-oxidative state.
So when you're measuring ox LDL, it's really Apo-B, a measure of aldeo-Apo-B oxidation.
But where is Apo-B?
It's on remnants and on LDL particles.
So just understand what you're measuring.
But of all the LDL particles that are floating around, if you get an abnormal ox, you're
looking at maybe 5% of the total particles.
Now you might make the case that when they do enter the artery wall, force them by the
particle number, they're going to be even further enhanced.
So maybe they got a leg up on an oxidized LDL particle.
OK.
I would use that as a measure of a pro-oxidative state.
And I'd try and give you whatever nutritional things I believe might fight oxidative states
or so.
I'm not knowing that I got a drug, including a supplement, that ensures me I can do that
or not.
Other than if I had to reach for a supplement, it might be an omega-3 fatty acid.
But it's another story.
So that's what you're measuring with the ox LDL.
I think there are better markers of pro-oxidative states.
And look, a lot of oxidation is the granulocytes oxidizing a variety of tissues.
So myeloperoxidase is a granulis-secreted pro-oxidative enzyme.
We can measure that easily in the blood.
That would be a signal of a pro-oxidative state.
And I think the best of all is as fatty acids get oxidized, derivatives form.
They're shorter chain fatty acids.
And they're put in a big group called isoprostanes.
And you can easily assay something called F2 isoprostanes, which have clearly been linked
to pro-oxidative states.
Now, it's a urine test.
It's not a serum test, but it's a small urine sample.
It's not a 24-hour urine.
So I like to do F2 isoprostanes.
So whatever you like to do, be it ox LDL, be it myeloperoxidase, or be it the F2 isoprostanes,
I can use that as useful information and maybe even convince you that nutrition is important
here.
And that is the best way to try and change them around or so.
So those are some of the pro-oxidative marks.
What I would not use is a pro-oxidative biomarker that way too many people are is lipoprotein
phospholipase A2.
First of all, the data is pretty poor.
Most people don't even know the only thing the FDA has given that approval for is as
a screening test in primary prevention never ever for anybody on a lipid modulating drug
or on who has known coronary atherosclerosis.
For the simple reason that Mendelian randomization has shown that your level of LPPLA2 activity
or mass has nothing to do with outcomes, sort of like the HDL cholesterol story.
And even more important, there have been two mega trials where pharmaceutical industry
has developed LPPLA2 inhibitors, gave them to patients, shut down LPPLA2 activity, drastically
reduce LPPLA2 mass, levels plummeted, no outcome reduction whatsoever.
And LPPLA2 is an enzyme made by the endothelium?
No, it's made by macrophages.
It's a macrophage.
It's just like myeloproxys is made by granulocytes.
The MPO data are equally unimpressive, aren't they?
If you want to come down, depends what you're using it for.
I stopped using MPO like two years ago.
So look.
And I agree with you.
I think I don't do it myself.
I do the, look, OXLDL I do it.
It's easy to do.
It's there and it's more linked to the process that I can see.
MPO, I don't know, you could have some other vasculitis going on or something.
Yeah, my take on MPO is I found it to be unhelpful and I agree with you that LPPLA2, it's one
of those things you only really need to check once.
Where I find that actually somewhat helpful, and again, I could be just diluting myself,
is you take the patient with an elevated LPPL who has an elevated LPPLA2 and not only
do you have a tongue twister, but you also have a patient that might be a little higher
risk.
And I wondered if I whispered that into Peter's ear over the years or so.
You may have.
But anyway, I tend to agree with him.
So here's why.
LPPLA2, which is an enzyme that does oxidize those phospholipids on an LDL when after that
LDL enters the arterial wall, is exposed to reactive oxygen species and some of the
fatty acids on the phospholipids start oxidizing, then LPPLA2 activity kicks in and it de-esterifies
the fatty acids from the phospholipids.
So now you've got oxidized phospholipids floating around and a byproduct called Lysolacetin,
which is a pretty pro-atrogenic molecule.
So LPPLA2 is involved with the production of them in the arterial wall.
That's not where we're measuring LPPLA2.
But hey, if it's on the particle when it goes in the artery wall, whose artery is wall in
today's nutritional environment doesn't have reactive oxygen species sitting there waiting
to attack something.
So boy, what particles entering the artery wall are going to have the most LPPLA2 mass
on it when that's where you're going to turn on LPPLA2 activity.
And by the way, the new assays available everywhere, they no longer measure the mass, they measure
the activity.
We were the last company who finally ran out of reagents, so we're going to activity now.
So across the board, the studies show either LPPLA2 mass or activity are identical in predicting
risk if that's what you're using it for.
But believe it or not, the activity assay is so much easier technically to do, less
costly.
That's what all labs are doing nowadays, the activity.
So back to LPPLA2 jumps on LDL, it's a little bit on HDL particles, but most of it is on
HDL particles.
But HDLs are heterogeneous species of normal size, big and small LDL particles.
You'll find way, way more copies of LPPLA2 on the smaller LDL.
Perhaps one of the reasons if people believe small LDLs are more atherogenic than larger
sizes, I don't know, once they're in the artery wall, which is driven pretty much by particle
number, but everybody with small LDLs has probably got too many LDL particles.
So they're very prone to oxidation when they do go in the artery wall, not that a big LDL
can't be oxidized, it could be, but it would have less LPPLA2 on it.
But if I really wanted to know the number of copies of that enzyme, LPPLA2, where would
I find it in the blood on LPPLA particles?
That's where it's all carried.
So I think Peter hinted on it in his LPPLA2 podcast, that there's another attribute to
LPPLA other than quantifying it or weighing its mass.
We do know there are people with high LPPLA who do not get out, and they may be a minority,
but they're out there.
Just like not everybody with FH is going to have a heart attack, some go through life
without it.
Most get some events, but many do not.
Clearly there are people without LPPLA who get heart attacks for other reasons.
So if you came to me with a very high LPPLA, whatever, do I just say life's over, get your
will in order, I got no drugs that can really help me with this, and you can't afford a
PCSK9 inhibitor, I can't even experiment there.
Maybe the ones who are at most risk, part of the functionality, part of the atherogenic
potential of an LPPLA particle is one of the functions, perhaps, of APOLITTLE-A is
it's a garbage truck that scavenges oxidized lipid moieties, phospholipids, sterols, and
it brings them back to wherever, maybe it's macrophages that clear them and detoxify them.
So it's some sort of a little rescue truck, garbage truck of clearing it.
What happens if you've got way too many LPPL particles, too many LDL particles, so some
of them are going in your artery wall, now you have an LPPL that's not only got a potentially
pro-atheregenic APOLITTLE-A protein on it, but that thrombotic, if it is a pro-thrombotic
protein, there's plenty of evidence suggesting it is, by the way with arterial, not so much
venous thrombosis, many people have dismissed LPPL as being linked to venous thrombosis,
I don't know the sort of, but if you talk to Sam on it, he will tell you.
Oh, that's interesting.
I stand corrected because I think I was probably quoting some old data when I said that the
VTE hazard ratio is about two.
Yeah, but it's just weak sort of data, so when you talk to Sam, talk to more about that.
So maybe it is, maybe it is.
Atherobut aortic stenosis.
You're wearing aetherro first, yeah, aetherotic stenosis, yeah.
And part of the pathology, maybe it's just trafficking these oxidized lipid moieties
into your particle, which is going to just stimulate this whole inflammatory mess that's
going on your arterial wall, and maybe it's a pro-thrombotic mess if that's a pro-thrombotic
protein too, the double whammy going in with it.
So, and I think Peter covered it nicely in his discussion there.
There are already segments on APOLITTLE-A called Kringles, and there are a couple of
Kringles that have a large essence of lysine amino acid that is like fly paper for oxidized
lipid moieties, so they really bind to these lysine-rich segments on APOLITTLE-A.
So if we could start measuring oxidized phenomenon and tying it into LpL-A-
Now Sam has written about this in his papers.
And Sam has published the data showing that's who you worry about with LpL-A.
If they have oxidized APOB phospholipids elevated, Sam's got an assay for that.
Yeah, so the OxPO-
It's not available widely.
Yeah, that's a shame.
And heaps Sam will tell you that yes, we're measuring it on APOB particles, but the APOB
particles that carry the vast majority of these oxidized are LpL-A particles.
Yeah, it could be a renminatory, oddball LDL particle, but mostly it's your LP.
So that is, again, a double whammy.
So I think maybe in the future we're going to be screening with whatever you want, LpL-A-
mass, LpL-A particle count.
I hopefully never LpL-A cholesterol.
Like all cholesterol metrics should be.
And the only way you can assay it is a poor assay nowadays anyway, is all right, you do
have excess LpL-A, whatever in your system.
Let me now do this follow-up test.
And if that's also up, let's discuss everything we can possibly do until that miracle drug,
hopefully miracle drug comes along and we got a cure for you.
And maybe it'll be covered in those people because the data will be strong because like
all these new antisense drugs, it's going to come with a price.
Yeah.
Before we leave biomarkers, anything you want to say about asymmetric or symmetric dimethylarginine?
It's a very interesting biomarker also where we talked about endothelial function, perhaps
even some of the antioxidant function is this miracle molecule every endothelial cell
makes extremely transiently makes and it's gone.
It's nitric oxide.
Nitric oxide is a powerful regulatory molecule that regulates vascular reactivity, bioxidation,
the thrombotic potential of an endothelial surface initiating a thrombus is highly dependent
on nitric oxide.
So when endothelial cells make nitric oxide, which is by far the most important molecule
they make, where does that come from?
Arginine, the amino acid arginine.
So arginine gets converted into nitric oxide.
So last thing I want is things that are going to screw up arginine pools, which is needed
to make nitric oxide.
And two proteolytic molecules we know byproducts of basically catabolism of nuclear proteins
is something one is called symmetric and the other one is called asymmetric dimethylarginine.
They're isoforms of one another.
So if you, you know, they're mirror images of one another, but they're actually different
molecules.
One directly and the other indirectly inhibits the synthesis of arginine.
So if I measured ADMA or-
The synthesis of nitric oxide, you mean?
Right, yes.
Well, ultimately synthesis of arginine, which results in the synthesis of nitric oxide.
Oh, see, I always thought that SDMA inhibited the synthesis of arginine, but ADMA inhibited
NOS directly.
I should correct what I said.
One inhibits the synthesis and the other enhances the catabolism of arginine.
So at the end of the day, you're going to have less arginine-
You're going to have less nitric oxide.
And less nitric oxide.
And they're both markers that we can easily measure.
So and if we measure them and they're high, you might presume, hey, maybe that's a blood
test that actually tells us something about endothelial function.
I don't think we have another that has anything close to at least that hypothesis.
I think the nice thing about the ADMA, SDMA is it creates a biologically plausible mechanistic
explanation for why we see an association between high homocysteine and greater disease.
Because homocysteine really inhibits the clearance of ADMA and SDMA.
That's very clear when you correct it.
Which would therefore screw up nitric oxide production.
Correct.
So it brings even oxidation into the process, would disturb that process too.
So if pro-oxidative state, if hyperhomocysteinemia is adversarial to the vasculature, that's one
of the pathways in which it is.
So what can we do?
Well, we can measure it.
So who would I measure, ADMA?
So if you came to me and you're on your third bypass or fourth stent, I think it's a pretty
safe assumption you have screwed up endothelial function.
So I don't know.
And of course the bigger question is, what do we do about it?
So one thing is, look, if they have impaired renal function, hypertension, those are things
that you go after.
The homocysteine, especially in the MTHFR mutation patients, you give methylated B vitamins,
which is still controversial in sort of mainstream circles.
Because even though it lowers homocysteine, some will point to that and say, well, you
have no outcome data on lowering homocysteine.
But you have plenty of data that in people with hyperhomocysteineuria, lowering homocysteine
drastically improves their vascular outcome.
So it's plausible at a certain threshold of homocysteine that there's probably makes sense.
And if you really understood the pathway of catabolism of methionine, you'd understand
this better.
And remember, in that pathway is going to be the production of a lot of neurotransmitters
too.
It's not going on if you have the genotype that's going to screw up methylation or the
enzymes involved with that.
That's another story.
But perhaps the best use of ADMA, SDMA is in the primary prevention setting where, all
right, you got a little borderline, APLB, LDLP, you're not going to do lifestyle.
Do I really want to throw you on a drug or something?
If those markers are up, that tells me whatever is going on in you, you have endothelial
dysfunction.
So you're down the road towards vascular pathology.
So it might be a marker to kick you in the rear to at least be super aggressive nutritionally,
even, hey, I'm sorry, whatever nutrition we tried, you still have abnormal endothelial
function.
It's time for us to, here I would rather improve these markers that will take a drug to get
them to where I want them to be.
So maybe we can use it in that setting.
If you also want to tell it to me, Tom, you said, hey, if you've been through a bypass
or a stent or something, why do it?
But what if I have such a patient who I've maxed out on a statinazetamide, I've done
everything I else to homosistain or insulin resistance and they're still up?
Should I lower APLB even further with a PCS?
Because I mean, you use it for what you want to use it for, but as a marker of endothelial
function.
And very interesting of the two, you get both.
You also get an arginine level in the same assay and SDMA is cleared by your kidneys.
ADMA is catabolized in the cells.
So kidney function has nothing to do with ADMA.
But SDMA, one of the things that will elevate it is renal disease.
And when SDMA goes into serum, it can back flux right into the cell and decrease nitric
oxide production, probably part of the pathology and people are renal failure.
I was just about to say the thing I like about the ADMA, SDMA stuff, even though we don't
have all this great long-term data, is it's one biochemical pathway that provides very
clear evidence for two observations that are undeniable.
Elevated homosistain and renal function.
The SMA, not the ADMA.
But you get both out of the...
You get both.
It's not like you're ordering selectively.
You order, you get them all three of those markers.
And they're addressing both sides of that equation.
So it's a very interesting little biomarker there.
And hey, who doesn't want another renal function test?
You're using creatinine, that's kind of a poor, you should be using such statin C.
And SDMA will be further enforcement.
And mild degrees of renal impairment go ignored in this country.
And if you're even in the early stage, even stage two, but certainly by stage three, which
could be a clearance of 70 or something or 60, people that gets ignored, even though
EGFR is being reported to people, and that's a major risk factor that you ought to say
you're a vascular path, you're at risk for vascular disease.
I got to see what I can do to you therapeutically to lower your risk.
But it gets ignored until a creatinine clearance is 32 and you needs dialysis or something.
Yeah, this is one of those things I do talk about with a subset of my patients, especially
these young patients in their 40s, 50s who buy cystatin C and creatinine and maybe even
a touch of microalbumin.
Their GFR is 80.
And I say if you're 40 and your GFR is 80, there's a problem if you want to live to be
100, because I don't know where you're going to be at 80.
Yeah.
And look, if you've got albumin in your urine, you've got a serious vasculopathy someplace,
maybe it's just your glomerulus and you've got a kidney disease, but you probably have
some other vascular disease too.
So albumin is just asking something else about something as big as a protein's escaping in
your urine.
You've got some membrane problems that are aligning some either glomerulus or a blood
vessel someplace.
The other ones are, and it's interesting because Peter in his little world sees a lot
of these people who are well-trained athletes take care of themselves and some of them in
Peter probably encouraged him to build up muscle mass and which can influence creatinine
and makes it far less usable as a marker of renal cystatin C has not influenced by muscle
mass.
So that's where it picks up some of the imperfections, the weaknesses.
We check both.
Yeah.
And if you do both, which is, by the way, if you read the kidney guidelines, they've
actually developed a nice equation where your clearance, and we provide this at THD and
I don't know any other lab that does, we give you a clearance based on creatinine.
We give you a clearance based on cystatin C and we give you the best clearance of all
based on both of those parameters.
And then you segregate by African American, non-African American.
Because creatinine is very different in African American.
So there's a lot more to those EGFRs if you haven't studied it lately, they might be going
on.
And if I'm going to do a biomarker, if there's no other restrictions and what that might
be a third party payer or somebody else, I'd rather do the most informative biomarker.
And that would be the dual EGFR and maybe some ADMA or SDMA thrown in as a renal marker
anyway.
And that SDMA ADM marker, I really wish we could take you through just be five or six
PowerPoint slides and you'd see these pathways and maybe I'll tweet them in the next week
or so individual slides.
Yeah, we can just attach them here easily to the show notes.
And you'll really, it's not a high, highly mechanized, it's staring right in the face
how they work and what they're doing.
Now we touched on something earlier that I know you wanted to come back to and we were
deliberately short on it, but I'm trying to kind of think about how to land this plane
here.
You want to go back and talk a little bit about what a remnant is?
It gets so much confusion about remnants.
They're talked about like they're one homogeneous entity.
Yeah, like there is a...
First of all, every known lipoprotein class, including LP little a, has remnants.
All a remnant is, is a smaller part of its sister particle that's in the same density
class.
The LDLs come in multiple sizes.
You got the big ones, which are only found in people with triglyceride abnormalities.
If you don't have a triglyceride disturbance, you will never have a big VLDL particle.
You'll have medium size and very often just small LDLs.
But if you look at your LDLs, there's a normal size particle.
There's a big LDLs and they're small LDLs.
Everybody has a heterogeneous mixture.
There's no human on the planet who has 100% exact diameter of every single sub-fraction
of a lipo HDLs very widely in their density, in their size, in their diameters.
Even IDLs, there's a certain diameter range or density range where here's the upper limits
of what you would call an IDL and here's the lower limits of when do you not call it an
IDL or it's an LDL or when does a small VLDL, I can't call it a small VLDL anymore.
It's called an IDL.
But wait a minute, wouldn't an IDL be a remnant of a VLDL?
If that LDL has a VLDL or IDL origin, is it an LDL or remnant of an IDL or maybe a VLDL?
Chylomicrons as they lose their triglycerides and phospholipids, they become smaller chylomicrons,
chylomicron remnants, which are for the most part, if you're lucky, cleared by APOE receptors
somewhere but there's chylomicron remnants floating around.
So what is the only particle I really care about?
An APOE particle, it can wind up in your artery wall, get oxidized and deliver the
sterols and you oxidize them and then you got plaque.
So what forces them in?
It's particle number.
Now I've also explained, all right, if that's APOE particle number, LDL-P is your first biomarker.
APOE is simply an LDL-P biomarker.
You're not counting VLDL particles because there are so few of them.
You're certainly not counting chylomicrons because there are even fewer of those.
So APOE is identifying to you way too many LDL particles in this person but there is
absolutely no doubt.
Even though you have way, way more LDL particles than you do have VLDL particles, because VLDL
particles are two or three times bigger than an LDL, the volume of a spear is the third
power of the radius, they do carry more cholesterol molecules per particle than an individual
LDL particle.
But of course you have so many more LDL particles than even VLDL or whatever you think a VLDL
remnant is.
Most of the cholesterol getting into your artery wall is still LDL delivered but I am
not denying that VLDL particles cannot deliver cholesterol and get oxidized when they are
into the artery wall.
They can.
So what has been the classic definition of a VLDL remnant?
Well they've always said well do that conversion factor we told divide triglycerides by five,
if that's high the VLDL cholesterol is high, they have too many VLDL remnants.
And no doubt if we really had a VLDL remnant test that's true.
But it would not be true in other people.
So there aren't some poor man's perhaps estimate of remnants.
I'm trying to clarify what you're saying because I think it's a bit confusing to the listener.
You can estimate VLDL cholesterol in two ways.
You can take triglyceride and divide by five and the higher the triglyceride level
the less accurate that becomes.
You can take non-HDL cholesterol and subtract LDL cholesterol from it and you'll get an
estimate as well.
Those two don't often agree by the way but nevertheless you have two estimates.
But that still doesn't answer the question.
Which of those go on to become pathologic remnants?
Correct.
So all you're identifying there is you have increased cholesterol content in VLDL particles
and because the ones we fear the most are remnants we're just presuming oh boy there's
got to be remnants.
There's got to be remnants here.
So whatever therapy you're thinking of doing in this person you better get rid of some
remnant therapy too.
Well all of the FDA approved drugs that lower APOB, whether it's statinazetimibe, fibrates
which are approved to lower LDL cholesterol even though they don't really do it that much,
you see it's clear all APOB particles including remnants.
So your ultimate solution, now your first solution might be nutritional if it's not
somebody coming off their bypass who is in the nightmare risk range classification where
I think you need a lifestyle and pharmacology day one.
You just don't have too many decades have passed.
You shouldn't be putzing around.
On a real short time you know the nutritional therapy if I think you have remnants is going
to be.
I'm going to address insulin resistance in you.
So I'm being an advocate of some degree of carbohydrate restriction and certainly a clear
advocate for a lot of reasons apart from even APOB would be the fasting is part of your
diet and too.
So great if you want to use your VLDL cholesterol and it makes you think there's remnants and
you're going to suggest the therapy.
I would tell you if your total drug guy did I out of a drug then that's the person you
give a fibrate to with your statin because that's what the fibrates really do well.
But I can show you that.
At zetimite the statin clears as many remnants as that combination too but I think fibrates
bring other things to the table that perhaps Zetia does it in people with triglyceride
rich lipoproteins.
And one of them is going to be so it's how I really think we're going to have to identify
remnants.
So just even tell there's a laboratory that produces they separate VLDL particles by ultra
centrifugation.
The NMR people used to report total VLDLP but they would also give you large VLDLP plus
medium VLDLP plus small VLDLP.
And we used to say well the small VLDLP those are the remnants that's the mark.
Well they don't do that anymore they only give you the large VLDL-P anymore those NMR
generating labs that have the proprietary ability to release VLDL particle data and
that's not all in them.
Is that liposcience or lab core now?
Well there is no more liposcience it's lab core.
So you will get a large VLDLP and it has one reason and one reason alone.
It's a lipoprotein marker of an insulin resistant state.
That's it.
It's not a goal of therapy it's nothing.
There's no data that of what you do to VLDLP affects outcomes although I'd make the case
that maybe it does.
But it's just an IR marker.
I can measure small dense LDL cholesterol, HDL2 cholesterol, just small LDL particle
concentration I can do an insulin level and 10 other tests that tell me your insulin resistance.
So I don't need any VLDLP marker.
I mean they were using that as part of their IR algorithm squad.
If you don't have that and they use the effector in VLDL size here because the big triglyceride
rich VLDL is a marker of insulin resistance.
But if you're measuring insulin levels and other insulin biomarkers they're no better
than that.
I don't know is there any better than just measuring small LDL particle concentration
at least in a drug naive person.
So fine it is a marker of insulin resistance.
But this other lab the Cenofusion they tell you look at our smaller VLDL cholesterol those
are remnants.
How do they know?
All they know is that person has extra cholesterol in their small VLDL particles.
But VLDLs depending on two things.
It's APOE content and it's APOC3 content is going to be virtually instantly cleared.
So if your small VLDL particles are being rapidly cleared by your APOE, APOB100 receptors.
So in other words if you took a bunch of small VLDLs and some of them had lots of APOE and
very little APOC3 those aren't remnants.
They're not pathological.
They're not sticking around.
If they're small VLDLs that's what they are but are they disease causing VLDLs?
Right.
Look some of them probably get in but very few compared to LDL particle number.
And also remember.
And very few relative to a small VLDL that would be high in APOC3 and or low in APOE.
Yeah which is never going to be cleared.
APOC the main down there's a lot of downsides to APOC3.
It's a pro-inflammatory protein.
It really enhances VLDL production in the liver.
But it just retards their clearance and it probably interferes with the hydrolysis induced
by lipoprotein lipase.
So you're increasing half-lives of all triglyceride rich lipoproteins which let's CEP exchange
occur longer.
And what is CEP exchange doing?
Bringing more cholesterol into your VLDL particles enhancing cholesterol enrichment.
Those VLDLs are losing triglycerides of the other in cholesterol.
So these are all the pathologies that might go on if you have delayed clearance.
And C3 is going to delay the clearance for multiple reasons of these particles.
So I want a blood test that tells me the APOC3 content of your APOBs.
LDLs that have APOC3 cannot be cleared.
In one of the early Pravastatin trials, the care trial, they went back and they who would
have had high triglycerides gets coronary events.
And this is Frank Sacks up in Boston and they've been able to measure this in sophisticated
lipid labs for a long while.
If your LDL had CEP APOC3 on it, Pravastatin was a useless drug, didn't reduce any events.
It still reduced APOB but it didn't reduce events?
It would clear some LDL particles.
It didn't reduce events in people who had high triglycerides.
So the APOC3, it's not measuring triglycerides that matters, it's APOC3.
And a lot of people with APOC3 might only have a triglyceride of 110, 120.
Wait, which trial was this?
A care trial, cholesterol and acute.
It was the second secondary prevention trial.
Simbostatin 4S was first and that was Swedes with super high LDL cholesterol and heart
attacks.
And that was done in Boston at the Brigham where they enrolled people with unremarkable
at the time LDL cholesterol 130 or lower who had heart attacks.
And they gave them Pravastatin and got pretty much the same event reduction as they got
in the 4S trial.
But the ones that had high trigs didn't have the reduction?
Yeah, so they went back in a post hoc analysis and those who had high trigs, Pravicle lowers
triglycerides, does it matter?
That's one of the benefits of Pravastatin.
The only people that got event reduction where Pravastatin lowered triglycerides was those
who had APOC3 enriched LDL particles.
So APOC3 becomes your biomarker.
Is Sam's company also working on?
I believe, yeah, in production is an anti-sense molecule that's going to stop APOC3 production
because Peter, I believe you also know the Mendelian thing there is gain of function
loss of function of APOC3 is tied into longevity also.
Actually, I think this is of all the major longevity genes.
I do not believe, and I could stand corrected, but I'm in the process of writing for the
book now.
I don't think there is a longevity gene on cardiovascular disease that is a stronger
predictor of longevity than hypo-functioning APOC3.
Yeah.
So in very interesting, and we just got tweeted about it, I'm sure within the last week, a
very interesting trial that if you're going to use an omega-3 fatty acid, when they compared
DHA versus EPA, DHA is the one that lowers APOC3, not EPA.
So all of these mega advocates of EPA, I don't know if APOC3 is involved there, maybe you
better find some DHA.
Well, I got to be honest with you.
I used to see myself as more of an EPA guy.
And then my focus on DHA, I think became more something I saw in the mild cognitive
impairment literature, which was the importance of DHA in the brain.
But I didn't realize this DHA C3 relationship.
Yeah.
So there, look, from my mind for years, it's been omega-3s are not lipid drugs.
Ignore them.
Don't use them to putz around with lipids because you don't know what they're doing.
That's changed now.
Clearly, high dose prescription strength EPA can be a helpful adjunctive therapy to
lower APOB.
And whether it's with remnants or whatever it's doing, it's lowering APOB an additional
8%, 10%.
Great.
And it's a pretty innocuous therapy.
I always worried about those who might not be able to convert EPA to what I believe is
the necessary DHA also, especially in the brain.
So, but I can measure that in the plasma.
I've been thinking about, I'd like to have Bill Harris on the show as well to have a
discussion about this because at least at the time of our recording today, I would
say that the mainstream view of EPA and DHA is that they're useless, right?
That's the press for today.
That's the mainstream view.
Yeah.
The mainstream view is abandon all of these dumb sort of supplements.
But as is often the case, when the mainstream says something in a declarative fashion, they're
usually wrong.
Especially on a nutrient, you know, where they're looking about what you're eating,
not taking pharmacologically, where you might have a real serious trial.
Yeah.
They're confused by supplements versus pharmacologic grades.
Most of the trials that they would quote is Omega is being useless.
They're using some miniscule, not a pharmacologic dose of these things.
And they're not measuring even who's deficient in Omegas.
And if you're not deficient in it, why would I even give you an Omega's re-pros?
And measuring fatty acids in the blood, I would encourage you to measure red blood cell
Omega 3's that are like a glycohemoglobin out of a 30 or a 60, 90 day half life, rather
than a plasma free fatty acid Ome, which might be what did you eat for lunch?
Yeah.
And also there's other intricacies involved.
But nonetheless, just all things to think about there.
So in this DHA with APOC3 is kind of interesting.
Now look, some people, if you're just going to drown them in EPA, do convert it to DHA.
So it's not an issue.
But we can measure that.
And I think we'd know.
Oh boy, and you, you got to have some of that either eaten or supplemented.
Are you pushing patients towards closer to 10% red blood cell EPA DHA level these days?
Or are you?
Well, I don't see patients anymore.
But if you want to ask me, yeah, that would probably, you know, there's no, you know,
Bill Harris would tell you, why not make it 14%?
But we don't have any data that would show, hey, that's harmful.
But we don't have any data showing you can even make it that high or so.
Not even epistaxis and things like that.
Easy for using.
So far anything with it, they've never turned anything from an omega three into coagulation
disturbance.
I mean, I definitely have to add that, hey, some Eskimos had a bloody nose one day on
and what else they're eating EPA and DHA all day long.
So I don't know that would have to be tested.
By the way, Tom, I just have to take issue with that as a Canadian.
I think we refer to them as Inuit now.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Eskimos is an old New Jersey term.
They're culturally insensitive.
I'm not going to.
I'm not going to stand for that.
You're right.
I know I insulted him.
But I really do need to get Bill on the show because he's always, Bill's one of these guys
who is, and again, many listeners won't know who Bill Harris is, but I hope to change that.
Just this is a guy who is as devoted to understanding the entire body of literature and science of
omega fatty acids in general, especially omega three and sixes.
You are to lipids.
Way more than me.
And he was a colleague I worked for three or four years with.
I love the guy.
We'd lunch all the time.
We'd go out.
So he has taught me so much.
And he is the guy who developed the red blood cell, phospholipid fatty acid assay.
So he knows what he's talking about.
And it gets so intriguing because even for those of you listening who may be taking an
omega three or prescribing an omega three, be it a supplement or be it a prescription
product, what vehicle is that?
It's just, is it, are you prescribing a free omega three fatty acid?
You're not.
There is an FDA approved product that the company who developed it is not brought to
market yet.
So you're either prescribing a starified omega three fatty acids or it's a starified to something
else or it's a starified to glycerol as a phospholipid or it's a starified to a glycerol
back bone where it has three fatty acids, but only one of them is an omega three.
Or are you buying a super enriched that all three fatty acids are starified to an omega
three?
You wouldn't need very small.
So what is the vehicle in your favorite supplement that's carrying the, all of that comes into
the pharmacodynamics.
You know, I just realized like I don't actually know the, cause there's only two supplements
over the counter that I fancy.
One is Carlson's, the other is Nordic Naturals, just based on some of the toxicology stuff.
But I don't know the answer to the question you just asked.
You can't get that information unless your brother works there and is privileged to that.
The companies won't even tell you what they are starified and look, you hear about these
krill products, they're phospholipids and that means there's one fatty acid on them.
So you got to prescribe a lot of krill pills to achieve a certain omega three way less
than you would if you had a die a starified or luckily enough, a triesterified triglyceride
my vehicle.
I'm always, I'm always happiest when I see my patients just eat enough salmon.
So listen, at the end of the day, that's all cool.
It's good to know, but at the end of the day, whatever way they're somehow getting omega
threes into your body, if you're normalizing the omega three index, does that even matter?
All that other stuff.
So it all depends, but I would implore you to follow up, please.
Yeah, I want to dig into this a little bit because it never occurred.
I gotta be honest with you.
I'm ashamed to admit this because I hate being the guy who makes dumb assumptions and is
too lazy to follow up.
I've always assumed that the high quality EPA DHA supplements were triacylglycerides.
Almost none of them are.
They're mostly monoglycerols, but it's glycerol with two other fatty acids plus one omega
three fatty acid.
And what are those other fatty acids?
If nothing else, they're calories that you may or may not need or they're a harmful fatty
acid even or so.
Interesting.
We'll get to the bottom of this.
And there's no pharma grade DHA to your knowledge.
No.
But here's what there is, and it's already FDA approved, but the company that developed
the product is not brought to market, but I think they're going to, because this November
at the American Heart Association, you are going to get the people at risk who are on
statins and half of them are getting statins plus EPA and the other half are getting statins
plus EPA placebo, no EPA.
And we're going to get outcome.
What dose of EPA?
It's high.
It's three, four grams.
It's the prescription strength.
So are we going to see cardiovascular?
All indications and we're all optimists are it's going to be a positive trial.
They haven't stopped it, at least for futility.
They certainly haven't stopped it for toxicity.
The trial is over.
They're generating the data now.
Wouldn't they have just stopped the fertility and gone away if it didn't work?
So we're all expecting that it's EPA added to the statins going to work.
Why wouldn't it?
It's an EPA.
It probably has other physiologic attributes that can reduce certain inflammatory markers
here, and it's an ICA-POB additional lower.
Now the company that has developed free omega-3 fatty acids, so they're not as terrified to
anything.
That means they're very bioavailable.
You just swallow it.
Remember, anytime you swallow an esterified omega-3 fatty acid, you have to secrete pancreatic
enzymes to deesterify it because it can't be absorbed without that.
Even phospholipids, krill oil, has to be deesterified by a specific lipase coming out of your panther.
Right, but a free fatty acid is easy to use.
A free fatty acid is going to come right in, but we don't eat them.
You might in certain foods, but even most of the foods you eat, it's triglycerides
that are delivering.
Don't free fatty acids taste horrible?
I don't know.
Maybe that's why they're not there.
I think most of the time they're stored as energy and as not free fatty acids, so they've
got to be deesterified.
But anyway, this company that has them, why didn't they?
Because this is a company that manufactures a statin.
What they were hoping was they thought that people make an EPA.
The FDA was going to give them an indication based solely on additional LDL cholesterol
lowering or APOB lowering.
That will let you come on the market pending your outcome data because non HDL is better,
whatever the FDA didn't.
FDA even told me they couldn't do it.
The company, which is Amarin, actually took the FDA to court and the Supreme Court says,
no, even though you don't have an approval for it, you can at least go share this with doctors.
And that Amarin EPA product, the SEPA, has skyrocketed in sales because doctors believe
this, hey, additional data with the SEPA.
So the company that, and so you would add SEPA to your favorite statin of choice and
then you're taking it to trial.
Which statin do they make?
No, they don't make a statin.
They make EPA.
So they want you to add SEPA to whatever statin you're ordering.
Oh, I thought they also made a statin.
No, they don't.
So you can pick your favorite statin, but now you have like a Zetimibe you might add
to a statin.
You can now add SEPA.
If you're evidence based, you're going to follow the trial.
I'm going to wait till November.
Oh, I would too.
Yeah.
And not that I wouldn't be using EPA, DHA for perhaps other reasons, cognitive or whatever,
just cell membrane health.
But the other company that makes a statin called Resuvistatin, the pretty, and that
would be called AstraZeneca is the one that owns this.
So what they were clearly hoping that had Amarin got an indication to add it to a statin,
they would have released a combo product called Resuvistatin, their EPA product or
so.
And you would have in one pill your statin plus your proper dose of Omega threes and
they would be free Omega three fatty acids, which would zoom right into your body.
I got a feeling if, and by the way, they are completing their own big outcome trial with
Resuvistatin plus the non-aestarified free fatty acids.
So they'll wait for their trial too.
But if this first trial works, why would there's not even work better?
Cause it's combining it with the most potent statin.
So all these people who've been bad mouthing Omega three is with no trial data may have
to change at least some of that talk come November at the American Heart Association.
It's the biggest trial going to come out of AHA this year, at least in the lipid world.
So pay strict attention.
Still a month or so before.
Normally they don't leak out that data cause that somehow prohibits publication in prestigious
journals, but some companies do cause it just means so much financially to them that it'll
get published somewhere.
So I don't know one way or another, we're going to have it in November.
Now we've danced around this idea of red blood cells for a while.
They keep coming up.
So let me redirect us to another topic, which is you've already said red blood cells per
molecule carry many, many more molecules of cholesterol than any lipoprotein does.
Why don't red blood cells cause atherosclerosis?
Because they're not invading your arterial wall and not subject to oxidative forces where
a macrophage is going to ingest the red blood cell.
Do they not invade the artery wall because they can't penetrate the sub endothelial space?
Yeah, they're gigantic.
Now, listen, can a red blood cell get into plaque?
Yeah, through the vase of a serum.
So could there be some in there that are, so the vase of a serum meaning from the other
side?
Or you remember artery walls get arterial supply.
They need oxygen.
Even plaque has little capillaries and stuff.
Are there red blood cells in expanding plaques?
Sure.
So not to say they're not a tiny little part, but that's not your primary delivery of oxidized
phospholipids and sterols into the artery wall.
Red blood cells are not being entering the artery wall and being oxidized, you know,
like the APOB particles are.
Yeah.
So this kind of gets back to sort of the causality issue of low density-like approaches.
Although also red blood cells carry way more cholesterol molecules, you have bazillions
more APOB particles than you have red blood cells also.
So yes, quantity-wise, they're carrying a lot of cholesterol, but not red blood cell
number-wise versus LDL number-wise.
So the size of the LDL particle obviously is what enables it to easily get into and
do that now though?
Oh yeah, number and size, but as you know, I've taught you this a long time ago, any
VLDL or under 17 nanometers can work its way into an endothelial gap or an arterial wall
through a scavenger receptor, whatever.
So not to say remnants aren't at their jet, they can't get in because remnants are way
bigger than an LDL.
No, they could.
But there's just more of the LDL particles.
So if this is a diffusion gradient for sitting an end, there's a hell of a lot more LDL troublemakers
than there are remnant troublemakers.
Not to say some big tough guy isn't a big troublemaker by himself, he is, but he's,
which would you rather have?
A thousand guys coming at you?
You're one guy.
I take my odds that I could beat one guy rather than a thousand guys, you know?
Yeah, yeah.
You know, I figure it's hard to believe we've been going out this for almost seven hours
and I feel like there's at least another hour or two we could go.
But at the same time, I want to be sensitive for the listener.
Normally I say I want to be sensitive to the guest, but I know you and I can keep talking
about this for six hours and we're going to go have dinner with Jamie Underberg tonight
and just continue this discussion.
I wish I had a microphone for dinner because I have a feeling that's going to be equally
interesting.
One of the things you talked about at the very outset was a really close friend of yours
who got you into hockey.
Took you to your first game at Madison Square Garden, got you hooked.
You were both obsessed with being firefighters.
He went on to become a firefighter.
You went on to become a lipid educator.
Yeah, so let me just pick up that my, you know, if you look back in life, who are some
of your absolute best friends, your high school buddies, who you really spend all that enjoyable,
the type of enjoyment you can have at that age that you never can have at another age
and you can do things.
And especially when we grew up in, we were in high school, 59 to 63, you could get away
with a lot of junk in those days.
Whereas today we were in the expelled real quickly or so with some of the shenanigans
we do.
So, and look, I, I joked with Peter when I was telling this story, I think he really
wanted to be my best friend because my father was a fire chief in the town of Patterson,
New Jersey, where we went to high school.
But even if that was true, I love firefighting.
What do I care if he loved firefighters?
We used to get on our bikes and write the fires all the time together and watch fires
and stuff or drive the firehouses.
So we were really tight for a million reasons and we just got along personality wise, but
he is the guy who invited me to my first ice hockey guy, which was certainly impacted my
life and my son's life in mega ways.
My son's a very successful guy and he would tell you would never be half as successful
had he not played ice hockey and developed the teamwork and the camaraderie.
Speaking of a fire engine.
It is perfect timing to have a fire truck going down.
But I'm going to just keep talking about this fire truck because it's not high lipid science.
So my buddy there, he went and became, and I knew him all my life and I went and became
a doctor, but right in, in that same city or in a suburb of that city.
So it's not like he didn't know where to find me.
But at a certain point earlier in life, I knew my buddy, a, a, you're a doctor now,
I got this cholesterol problem.
They tell me my cholesterol is up in the blood and you know, I was probably at the point
where we were really taking cholesterol serious and we could do something about it.
They're all, you got to come and see me.
Come on.
You know, and I was probably even the days before I was just solely dwelling on lipoprotein
ology and lipidology, but I was very aggressive with understanding cholesterol and knowing
look who I evolved into.
So it would have probably been a smart choice for him to come up.
It's not like I was going to charge him and he couldn't afford me.
He's a fireman in a big city.
He had as good a health insurance as you could ever get.
So it's not like it would have cost him 10 cents.
A lot of firemen did pick me as their doctor because of who my father was.
And they knew he was a guy who likes fire engines.
We used to see him as a kid in the firehouse.
I want him to be my doctor.
He knows what I do.
Earl just is one of these people who thought the farther I stay away from doctors, the
better.
I don't want to hear what they got to tell me.
I don't want to be on a medicine.
I don't want to do anything.
And Earl got buried in his mid fifties with a sudden acute myocardial infarction sitting
at home watching TV.
He could have been climbing a ladder out of fire.
By the way, if he did die to fire, his name would be on the Memorial Monument up in that
city.
But he died at home the next day.
So not that I want his name on.
I really wish it was because he's just such a debt.
But there is such a needless death.
And I think across America all the time, there are many young age needless deaths occurring
with a very preventable, treatable disease that's being ignored totally because they
don't go and get it checked or they're getting bad advice based on the wrong metrics.
So my buddy there is the perfect example.
But what a tragedy.
Had he made the right, I like this guy.
He's my best buddy.
He's not going to screw me or do anything wrong.
Let me go to him.
He didn't.
Every time I saw him, I'd remind him, Earl, come up, come up, please come up.
Yeah, yeah, Tom.
Never did.
Well, in many ways, that's a reasonable and sad way to kind of end this discussion.
But it also brings it kind of back to why we why do we get so animated about this topic?
Well, I think, as you said, we think of this as, you know, one of the big three diseases
that kills most people in the civilized world once they get out of childhood.
And by civilized, I really mean developed.
People know what I mean.
But of the big three diseases, this is the one where I think we know the most about it.
And therefore, by extension, it's probably the one that's most delayable.
Never want to say preventable.
Right.
We use that term.
But in reality, what does that mean?
It means delay.
And so if Earl died in his early 50s, maybe with the right care, he could have died in
his late 60s.
You know, again, if a guy's dying in his 50s of heart disease, he's probably got really
bad disease.
He needed therapy at a real young age, but he could have hung around for a while.
He's got grandkids and children and stuff who really wish he was still here at a fire
department.
He was a beloved fireman.
They all wish he was still on.
He'd be retired by now.
But he's just one of these people that God sends to earth that do nothing but good while
they've been here through their whole life.
He had saints, his parents, and he was so tragic that he left us at such a young age
and got driven to the graveyard on the back of a fire truck with a flag on a Vietnam veteran.
And so, but just so, so sad.
And listen, I want to wrap this up myself.
And I used to wrap up a lot of lectures I did with this.
And you know, because I my lectures were all high science, no matter what group I was speaking
to.
So I always wanted that you ought to come out of this lecture that I give and maybe
with all the things, if you really sat through everything we talk about today to say, guy's
an idiot or he's onto something and I thought I understood this topic, but maybe I need
to understand it at a higher level.
So everything is study, study, study.
I didn't learn this stuff overnight.
My life has been sinned in this field.
Yeah, well, I'll say a couple of things.
I'll say a couple of things on that.
So first of all, I obviously want to thank you for the influence you've had in me.
And I, I don't know, I just feel really lucky.
I think that I got plugged into you and Alan and Ron just out of the gate to have met the
three of you so early in my interest in this topic saved me so much time because it's one
thing.
I mean, no one can substitute the amount of time you have to spend obsessing over this
topic and learning it.
But boy, when you can have that curriculum curated for you, you shortcut it by, you know,
3X I'm sure.
It's a gift and I'll just extrapolate on that because Peter named three guys he can get
in contact with pretty quickly and get answers.
As I evolved in this world, I had 20 guys around the world who liked me a lot because
of what way I explained things, what I could illustrate for them.
So I've been blessed by, I've mentioned a few today.
It would take me another 15 minutes to list them all.
But so many of the, I call them the lipid gods out there, the people who have spent
their real life in research laboratories and clinical trials and taking care of people
in the worst clinic, lipid clinics, see, and they still are available to me.
But that's who I use.
I don't go on the internet and read something or make stuff up.
I try and ask experts about a lot of things.
Not that you'll ever get consensus on anything, but those of us who do have those avenues
open, which many do not, but they're not afraid to still pontificate about something
that's kind of sad.
I can't remember if I made this, this'll be my final point on the topic and I can't
remember if I made this point on a previous podcast or not.
And if I did to the listener, I apologize.
I started out in mathematics and engineering and really loved those things.
I excelled at those things, took great pleasure in being a first principles thinker.
One silly story at the end of my freshman course in dynamics kinematics, like Newtonian
physics, you take a final exam and you are allowed one piece of eight by 10 paper that
you can write on both sides as much as you want, whatever formula you want.
Because there were just so many equations you would have to know to go in and ace one
of these exams.
Now I was cocky B on words and I was really lucky as a freshman.
I used to study in this dark part of the stacks where I met a real upperclassman guy.
His first name was JP.
I don't remember his last name, but I'll never forget him.
He was the only guy I'd ever met who decided to take two engineering disciplines and finish
them both in four years.
So he did electrical and mechanical engineering in four years.
The price he had to pay for that was he studied every minute of every day, but he also had
told me he didn't have the opportunity to learn everything.
If you wanted to take all of electrical and mechanical in four years, you had to accept
that there were certain things you couldn't know.
All of his study focused around first principles inference.
He taught me this early.
He saw me studying for one of my exams and I was writing out something called the Coriolis
equation which basically explains centrifugal forces under the condition of a changing radius.
He said, you don't need to memorize that formula.
You know how to derive it.
And I was like, what are you talking about?
He goes right out the formula for angular position and take the derivatives of it.
You know calculus.
So I did and sure enough, I was getting the same formulas.
To make a long story short, I've become totally inundated by JP's reasoning.
I go into my final exam and oh, you have to turn in your cheat sheet at the end of the
exam.
And I, this is again, I'm not saying this to brag about how cocky I was, but so I just
have to stay.
But the point is I wanted to show the professor how well I understood this material.
The only thing I wrote on my cheat sheet in big block letters was the sum of the forces
equals mass times acceleration.
Because I was like, if you know the simplest of Newton's laws, you can actually derive
everything at this level of physics.
We're not talking quantum physics at this point.
And I remember JP said, look, on every question, write it out.
Show them how you can go from one to the other.
Because if you make a mistake, at least they'll see what you're doing.
I ended up acing the exam and that lesson sort of stuck with me.
And it served me very well through the rest of engineering and mathematics, including
when it got really, really complicated.
That in the end, if you truly wanted to understand something at first principles, you could derive
so much.
Okay.
Fast forward a few years.
Now I find myself in medical school.
Now I was not a pre-med.
So I'm in medical school, not as a pre-med, but as a former engineer math guy who based
barely squeaked into medical school, meaning I took the MCAT having not even taken a course
in biology yet.
I had to take my bio class after.
And I'll tell you that first semester of med school was brutal for me because I learned
the hard way that you couldn't first principles your way through biology, at least not at
the level, at least not until you gained a certain amount of familiarity with the basics.
I couldn't walk into my histology class, look under the microscope and on first principles,
know the difference between the Golgi apparatus and the endoplasmic reticulum.
You just have to know that stuff.
I couldn't go into anatomy and physiology and pathology and just first principles my
way into stuff.
Eventually you can, but you have to have an enormous basis.
So I sort of forgot all about that pain.
You know, you get through medical school and by the end it became, you know, it was very
enjoyable, but it wasn't until I got to the lab to NIH where my mentor told me a great
story.
Now he's probably one of the most brilliant scientists I've ever known and did a PhD in
biophysics specifically for the purpose of wanting to make sure he was never in his words
intimidated by a differential equation, despite the fact that he was an immunologist.
And he told me a story, which I need to get the details of it because I don't remember
the physicist he's referring to, but he told me the story of a physicist turned biologist
who lamented once that the moment he switched from physics to biology, he could never again
take a bath in peace because as a physicist, he could sit in the bath and wax philosophically
and think about lots of things on first principles and be very theoretical in his understanding.
But as a biologist sitting in the bath, he always realized there was one more fact he
needed to remember before he could draw a conclusion.
And so he had to keep getting out of the bathtub to go and look up a certain fact.
And that obviously disrupted the beauty of taking the bath.
And I think that long rambling story is a way of saying the following.
I find this subject matter to be as complicated as any I have ever tried to learn.
And unfortunately, every time I have a brilliant idea, just based on first principles, I still
have to go and check if it's grounded in the foundation of science.
And sometimes it is, but many times it is not.
I come up with an idea and I'm like, this has got to be right.
But oh, they're physiologically impossible.
And there's even an experiment that one day suggested this or it's, you know, I made an
assumption but I can clearly see that it was not the case.
So I understand your frustration and I share it.
And I think unfortunately that is the nature of biology.
Yep.
And I remain an eternal optimist.
I continue to teach lipids.
I think clinicians know a bit more than we knew in 1995 when I started this journey
teaching.
And so that's all if I have to do it one at a time with people, I try and teach them what
I know and hopefully you'll do your continuing education.
And that's one of the nice things about medicine.
But you got to do it.
None of this comes easy.
It does.
And there's a lot of complexities in medicine nowadays.
We're talking because it's a highly pathologic state and leading cause of trouble.
But there's so many other things to boy take to the much higher level nowadays.
Well, Tom, people I think will certainly by the end of this know where to find you.
But on Twitter, which is where you spend the most of your time, you're at Dr. Lippit, correct?
That's me.
So, yep.
And this will, I mean, we're generally in our brief existence as a podcast already known
for probably producing the most thorough show notes ever.
I'm suspecting that this episode, which will probably break into several parts, will have
the most robust show notes that we've done.
And I love, by the way, that there's another fire truck going down.
It's perfect.
It's totally appropriate.
But also, if there's anything else that you think of, let's just talk about it where offline
even we can just get to it.
Where there are other resources you think people ought to go to.
Again, I will steer people away from your 2000 to 2004 writings.
But I think there's going to be a number of people who listen to this who say, you know
what, look, I might have missed half of what those guys talked about.
But there's something there I want to make sure I understand better because in the end,
every doctor wants to do the best by their patient.
I mean, that's just, I believe that wholeheartedly.
I get very frustrated when I hear people say that doctors are in the pockets of pharma
companies and they're just in it for the month.
And that's sure there's going to be some of those people.
But I haven't met those guys.
You know, the doctors that I meet, the men and women I meet who take care of patients,
they all want to do the best by their patients.
And I think that those are people who are going to want to invest a little bit of their
time in understanding this problem a little better.
No, I can't say it anymore.
As you listen to seven and a half hours, even hopefully piecemeal market, clearly for, depending
on the list, there's going to be things over your head.
Even if you are a super skilled lipidologist, there's going to be some things you said,
what?
Let me read about that or so.
But it's just trying to open your mind and understand there's a lot going on here.
The field is infinitely more complex than you ever imagined.
It took me a long and I'm a, as Mike Davison calls me, Tom's a self-taught lipidologist.
I mean, I didn't spend two years down at the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute,
but I don't know the director of that NHLBI, Alan Romali, and I just authored a 70 page
chapter in the Teats book of molecular and clinical biochemistry, all about lipids and
apoproteins.
So I think to be an invited author with a guy named at Magnitude.
Yeah, you've sent me a preprint of that.
That's a remarkable treat.
So I mean, it's an expensive book.
I don't expect you, if you're not a lipidologist or somebody seriously into this clinician,
that's what you go out and buy.
There is a lot of information out there.
So just be careful on what you, that's ridiculous.
Or my cockamamie theory based in no clinical trials or science is what I believe.
Fine, believe it.
You know, this is America here.
I can't lock you up.
I'm not the lipid police.
Yeah, well, on that note, Tom, thank you very much.
It's hard to believe this has been seven hours of discussion today, but it's been worth every
minute to me.
I've learned a lot in this discussion.
So that's to me, that's always a, I mean, for selfish reasons, that's sort of my primary
objective is to learn as much as I can.
And then along the way, if others can learn too, that's a bonus.
And without a year of my intermittent fasting and program from Peter at TIA, I could have
never had the energy to say it.
Even to use my tongue.
Or brain.
So thank you again, Peter.
Yeah, my pleasure, Tom.
Thanks.
You can find all of this information and more at Peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at Peteratiamd.com.
What's a nerd safari you ask?
Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week
email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeteratiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the
practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving
of medical advice.
And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own
risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical
advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they
have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit Peteratiamd.com
forward slash about.