Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of the space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Dan Rader. Dan is a professor of molecular medicine at the
Perlman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, where he conducts translational
research on lipoprotein metabolism and atherosclerosis. The particular focus on the metabolism and most
importantly, function of high density lipoproteins, HDLs. Dan has received numerous awards and has
been elected to the American Society of Clinical Investigation, the Association of American
Physicians, and the National Academy of Medicine. He also currently serves on the board of directors
of the International Society of Atherosclerosis, the board of external experts at the National
Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, and the advisory board for the clinical research of the NIH. In
this episode, we focus our entire conversation around high density lipoproteins or HDLs. Now,
as any listener of this podcast will know, we have no shortage of content around lipids. We
focus a lot of that energy on the ApoB side of the family. That is, to some extent, VLDLs and,
of course, LPLitLA, which is a subset of LDL. However, this is the first time we're doing a
dedicated podcast on HDLs. Now, the reason for that, in other words, the reason for that disparity
is largely because HDL biology is so much more complex and we know so much less. I mean, at the
highest level, I think people generally think of HDL as, quote unquote, the good cholesterol, but
you've no doubt heard me rail on the stupidity of such a designation. But there is clearly something
good about HDLs as in the lipoproteins, not the cholesterol. And in this discussion, we really
talk about everything from the biology of the HDL, its genesis, its origin, its metabolism, its
life cycle, and, of course, its function. We also talk about why it has been so complicated to use
pharmacologic interventions on the HDL side of the equation to impact atherosclerosis. Conversely,
of course, it's been the easiest thing, I would say, in medicine and perhaps the greatest success
of modern medicine, especially as it comes to cardiovascular disease, has been our ability to
manipulate the ApoB side of the equation as opposed to the ApoA side of the equation. That's one thing
that's going to be important here when we get into the terminology. When we talk about ApoA in the
context of HDLs, we're talking about ApoA as in a big A, which has no bearing whatsoever to Apo
little A, the thing that, of course, defines an LP little A. But I digress, that is simply one of
the many details we get into. So, as I said, we're going to talk here about the genesis of the HDL,
the structure, its metabolism. We talk about the differences between HDLs, LDLs, the difference
between the HDL measurements. So what exactly is HDL cholesterol versus ApoA concentration versus HDL
particle number? We talk about the idea that having a high HDL means you don't need to worry
about cardiovascular disease and how that's obviously going to be bunk. I'm just going to
let the cat out of the bag on that one. We speak about CTEP inhibitors, which are a class of drug
that have been repeatedly used to try to increase HDL cholesterol with the hopes that that would
reduce cardiovascular disease. And finally, we end the conversation around some of the new thinking
around HDL and neurodegenerative disease, something again, I learned a lot about. So,
without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Dan Grader. Well, Dan, thank you so much for
making time to join us on the podcast today. Tom Dayspring really recommended you highly. And
anytime Tom Dayspring says to me, you should have so and so on the podcast to talk about anything
that has to do with lipids, I immediately pay attention. Tom's an amazing guy. Now, in particular,
the subject matter I want to explore with you today is probably the area of lipidology that I
personally am the least familiar with. And that has to do with kind of one half of the lipid family.
I explain this to patients as they're broadly speaking two families, the ApoB family and the
ApoA family. We spend obviously so much more time talking about the ApoB family based on, I think,
two things. One is our clearer understanding of it and two, the direct and causal relationship to
pathology. But I often sort of waffle a bit when I'm talking about the ApoA side of the house.
That's really why I'm excited to be sitting down with you today. But perhaps for the person
listening to this who doesn't even understand what a lipoprotein is yet, never mind what the
two families are that we're talking about, can you take it back to the beginning for where do
these things fit into the broader architecture of our existence? Lipoproteins are these big complexes
that really are evolved to transport lipids within the blood. Lipids are like oil. They don't mix
well with water. Oil droplets float to the top of a puddle. We wouldn't be able to transport lipids
in the blood if we hadn't evolved a mechanism to do that. And lipoproteins are basically the
mechanism to do that. As their names suggest, they're lipoproteins. They have lipid in the core,
and then they have proteins that dot the surface. That allows them to be transported in very
complex and sophisticated ways within the bloodstream in terms of how they're metabolized,
in terms of the receptors they bind to, and in terms of the specific proteins and lipids that
they carry. You've talked a lot about ApoB lipoproteins. I've listened to several of those
podcasts. They're really fabulous. And of course, the ApoB lipoproteins really primarily transport,
or evolve to transport triglycerides as a source of energy, both from the gut to adipose and muscle
and heart, as well as from the liver during times when we're fasting. You've talked a lot about that
and, as you pointed out, they are very important in terms of causal relationship to atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease. HDL, which we're going to be talking about today, is also a lipoprotein.
It's a very complex lipoprotein. It doesn't have this key protein, ApoB. That's what differentiates
them. That's why we often refer to the ApoB-containing lipoproteins, and then HDL is the
other half, as you said. And HDL really is characterized by a different protein called
ApoA1. HDL also transports lipids, especially cholesterol and some other complex lipids,
and we'll be getting into that more. But essentially, lipoproteins are lipid transport
vehicles within the blood and really evolve to do that function.
A couple of things I'll just throw in for folks, again, maybe new to some of this,
which is all of this stuff we're talking about is so important in terms of these lipoproteins,
because unlike glucose, electrolytes, things that we kind of take for granted that are water
soluble, we use our circulatory system as the freeway to move these things around.
And unfortunately, as you said, because of the insolubility of both cholesterol,
triglyceride, lipids, et cetera, we have to come up with this more complicated system.
I think the second thing I'll throw in just for folks, because it could get confusing with the
nomenclature, when you talk about ApoA, I want to make sure people understand we're not talking
about LPa, which has another ApoA, so maybe just clarify for folks the difference between those two,
because we'll do our best to not talk about ApoA today at all.
Yeah, LPa is really important, not the topic of today's discussion. I think, as Peter already
said, the main thing to remember is that that A is lowercase, whereas the A we're talking about
today is uppercase. I know it sounds crazy, it's just the way things evolved historically,
but we're talking about ApoA, uppercase A, and the most important one has a 1 after it, so ApoA1.
So you're going to hear us refer to ApoA1 a lot, totally different than the LPa, which is also an
important topic, but not for today. Yeah, it's a shame that the lipid community back in the 60s,
70s, and 80s didn't hire kind of a PR firm to sort of help with the naming of this stuff, because it is,
hands down, some of the most complicated nomenclature, and if they realized back then,
I'm half joking, that it wouldn't be a bad idea for patients to actually understand this stuff,
I think we could have done better. Okay, so you've already alluded to kind of different
ApoA's and ApoA1, again, that's Apo capital A dash Roman numeral one is the most important,
but let's go back even further than that. So again, not to draw the ApoBs into this again,
but we kind of technically now have these two lineages of ApoBs, right? We have the ApoB100,
and virtually all of the time that we say ApoB, we really mean ApoB100, and that's to contrast it
with ApoB48, the one that you kind of alluded to very briefly as transporting chylomicrons from
the gut for the use of energy. Can you talk a little bit about the, or not a little bit,
maybe a lot a bit, about the genesis of the high density lipoprotein? What is its parent?
Where is it formed? And how does it move through its evolution such that, you know, when we're
measuring HDL cholesterol, something we'll talk about in a minute, we have a sense of where it
came from in the same way that we understand the LDLs, IDLs, and LDLs. With all due respect to the
ApoB community, and I'm part of that community too, I would say the metabolism of HDL is perhaps
an order of magnitude even more complex. And that's obviously what we're going to be working
our way through today. So I'll start relatively simplistically, and then Peter, I know you'll
lead me to increasingly more detail about the process. And by the way, I don't think anyone's
going to disagree with that, Dan. I don't think anybody who spent even a modicum of time looking
at this literature, it is hands down the most confusing stuff in the lipid space.
Again, I'll start with ApoA1 as the key protein with HDL. The analogy is to ApoB, as Peter alluded
to. Although one big difference is ApoB, as your listeners know, ApoB stays with that particle
throughout its lifetime. So it gets made by the intestine as B48, or the liver as B100. It stays
with that particle. There's one molecule of this huge ApoB protein, and that it basically then
ultimately gets taken up mostly by the liver after its time in the blood. ApoA1 is also made
by the intestine and the liver. There's some parallelism there. It also is a core protein,
essentially, of HDL. But unlike ApoB, there are several molecules of ApoA1 on any given HDL
particle. We'll probably talk more about that, but anywhere from one to four, maybe in some cases a
little bit more. And also ApoA1 doesn't stay with the particle. It can exchange onto other types of
mostly HDL particles, but even sometimes onto ApoB containing lipoproteins. What we've really
learned in the last decade or so is that ApoA1 is put into the blood by either the intestinal
enterocyte or the hepatocyte in the liver as more or less a free protein. So it's secreted as a
protein. One of the first steps that has to happen for HDL to be formed is that HDL, once it comes
out of the cell, engages with a key transport protein called ApoA1. And Peter, stop me if I'm
already getting too detailed. ApoA1, we'll come back to that. Which its role, ApoA1's role, is to
take lipid, cholesterol and other types of lipids called phospholipids, from the cell and export
them to the newly secreted ApoA1. So ApoA1 has to acquire lipid, particularly phospholipid and
cholesterol, soon after it's been secreted in order for the so-called nascent or early HDL to start
forming. We'll come back to this when we talk about genetics, but we know this because humans
that lack ABCA1 have virtually undetectable HDL. And that is because they cannot, they make plenty
of ApoA1, but they cannot protect that ApoA1 with lipid once it's secreted and it goes out like a
rocket from the blood. Basically can't, almost can't measure it in the blood. So that's the first step
in terms of HDL biogenesis, if you will. What other phenotype do those patients have? So in the absence
of cholesterol accumulating in what would be an HDL, does it end up where more of it ends up in the LDL
or back in the liver? Where does it go? This is the value of studying these very rare human genetic
disorders. And it just tells us a lot about what specific proteins or genes are doing. This disorder,
which we can talk about the history, it's a fascinating history, it's called Tangier disease.
It's named for a small flat bizarre island in the middle of the Chesapeake Bay, where the first
patient was discovered. This disorder is primarily associated with accumulation of cholesterol in
macrophages throughout the body. So tonsils, spleen, places where there are a lot of macrophages,
the cholesterol really builds up. And they have huge sort of orange colored tonsils, they have
big spleens that sometimes rupture, they have big livers because there are a lot of macrophages and
macrophage-like cells in the liver. And they also have some neurologic type issues, especially
neuropathy, which maybe we'll leave to later when we start talking about HDL and its relationship to
the nervous system. They may or may not have some increased risk of atherosclerotic cardiovascular
disease, but as we'll talk about that relationship between HDL and atherosclerosis is quite complex.
This disorder has helped to inform that a little bit. Another sort of structural question, Dan,
if you were to take a quasi-mature garden variety HDL particle, and again, it's more complicated
there because of what we're talking about, and put it next to a comparable LDL particle,
what's the difference in size and can you explain a little bit why they come up with this different
name of high versus low density? What specifically is that referring to? That's a great question.
Again, this is a historical artifact of how lipoproteins were discovered and named.
First of all, HDLs are much smaller, I would say, in the neighborhood of 1 5th to 1 10th the size
of an LDL, and of course much yet smaller than triglyceride rich lipoproteins. Lipoproteins have
lipid. As I mentioned earlier, lipid floats, so lipids create buoyancy to particles. The way
lipoproteins were discovered is that when you subject plasma to spinning, the lipoproteins spin
to the top. They spin to the top at different rates under different forces. The low density
lipoproteins have more lipid or bigger, more lipid. They spin to the top more easily. The
high density lipoproteins still have lipid. They do spin, but they don't spin quite as quickly or
easily, so they're higher density than the low. Then in another artifact of the history, Peter,
after low density was discovered, something even lighter that spun up even more easily was
discovered. Of course, if low was already taken, so that had to be called very low.
There's the very low density lipoproteins that you've also talked about at length.
Then finally, the chylomicrons, the huge ones that come from the intestine, they're just so light
and so buoyant that instead of calling them very, very, very low, they were just given the name
chylomicrons. How long does an HDL particle last? Does it mean the same thing given that it's
transferring its ApoA in a way that makes it a little different from, as you said, the way the
VLDL to IDL to LDL always stay with one lipoprotein ApoB that allows us to track its life.
Before we get into how HDL is removed from the blood, could I take a little bit more time to
explain what happens after that? Absolutely.
ApoA1, quote unquote, nascent HDL particle gets formed because there's actually a bunch of stuff
that has to happen first before we start talking about how the HDL then gets removed from the blood.
The ApoA1, or what we call the nascent HDL, has ApoA1, has phospholipids, and it has what I'm
going to call free cholesterol. This is a concept that you may or may not have addressed before,
I can't remember, which is cholesterol itself as a molecule can have a fatty acid attached to it.
When you attach a fatty acid to a hydroxyl moiety on the cholesterol molecule,
you create what we call a cholesterol ester. The cholesterol ester is even more hydrophobic
or oily than the free cholesterol because it has this additional fatty acid sticking off it,
which is obviously oil. It's absolutely critical for the HDL maturation process to have this fatty
acid attached to the cholesterol after the nascent HDL has been formed. There's another key enzyme
that is responsible for that, so-called lecithin cholesterol acyltransferase. It's the last time
I'm going to say that, I'm just going to call it LCAT, that's its nickname, LCAT, L-C-A-T. So LCAT
rides on the HDL particle, on that nascent particle, it takes a fatty acid from one of the
phospholipids on the particle, and it transfers that fatty acid to the cholesterol and creates
the cholesterol ester. Remember, that cholesterol ester is more oily, it actually then moves to
sort of the center of the particle because it wants to be by itself and not interacting with
the water, and it starts to form the core of the HDL particle. So the core of the mature, what I'll
call the mature HDL particle, is basically cholesterol esters that are entirely dependent
on LCAT for their formation. Another rare condition are people who lack LCAT genetically,
and as you might maybe expect from what I just said, people who lack LCAT who can't do that
process of esterifying the cholesterol, have extremely low levels of HDL, not quite as low
as Tanger disease, but very low, and simply can't form the mature HDL particles that we see in most
people. So again, we learn very important things about the key role of that enzyme. That ultimately
leads to the mature particle that then is really what we're measuring as HDL cholesterol in people,
is this mature HDL particle where most of the cholesterol we're measuring is the cholesterol
in the core. Just to make sure we're clear on semantics, when you say that those folks have
very low HDL, you mean low HDL cholesterol or a low concentration of ApoA1 or any of the ApoAs?
They have low HDL cholesterol. So again, Tanger disease, HDL cholesterol is one,
virtually undetectable. LCAT deficiency, HDL cholesterol is 10. Also, as we'll talk about,
quite low compared to normal. They also have low ApoA1 levels. And part of that is because
part of the metabolism of ApoA1, which is where you were going, is that it's affected by the mature
HDL and the cholesterol in the core. So when you don't make that cholesterol ester, that ApoA1
is much more rapidly removed from the blood. It's not the normal metabolism. And it basically,
the kidney sees that ApoA1, which doesn't have much cholesterol on it and actually filters it
and degrades it. Not surprisingly, the biggest issue with L-cat deficient patients is they get
renal disease. There's a serious progressive chronic kidney disease in these patients that
leads usually to kidney transplant related to something around the lipid metabolism in the
kidney as a result of the lack of L-cat activity and esterification of cholesterol.
Before we go deeper on this, I just want to ask if there are any insights we have or how parallel
is this system in other mammals, whether it be primates, dogs, mice, et cetera. Because obviously,
a lot of these animals have a very different ApoB side of the equation. I'm curious as to how
similar they are on this front. No, it's a great question. ApoA1 is pretty highly conserved
certainly among mammals. In many lower level mammals, the primary lipoprotein is HDL.
That clearly includes ApoA1. I'll just take mice, obviously a major model system for human,
for biomedical research. Mice, I'd say 90% of cholesterol in the blood of mice is in HDL,
even more than 90% in a normal mouse. That is the primary lipoprotein in mice. It's true for dogs.
It's true for really all mammalian species. Once you start getting below mammals, things change a
little bit in terms of the lipoprotein metabolism. Probably we won't get into that today. There's
even HDL-type particles in much lower species leading to one of the thoughts that HDL is like
the primordial lipoprotein and that the ApoB system evolved subsequently, but that HDL probably very
early evolved as a transport mechanism for lipids within circulatory systems in lower level species.
This to me is one of the most interesting teleologic slash evolutionary questions, which is,
was God just pissed off at us? Is that why we as humans have ApoB? I've never really heard a
convincing explanation for why humans have ApoB when it seems that every other species
gets away without it. As you said, if a mouse or a primate or a dog who clearly have similar
energetic requirements can use their ApoAs, i.e. HDLs, for lipid transport and energy mobilization,
why did we need to evolve with this particle that in the short term really doesn't cause us any
trouble, of course, but long enough it doesn't. One answer might simply be that evolution had no
concern for the longevity of our species, which is pretty true, but there is some other short-term
benefit from ApoB that maybe outweighs the long-term death that it brings our species via ASCVD.
I do want to be clear. Mice, dogs, pigs, rabbits, they all make ApoB in both the gut and the liver,
so it's not that these species don't have ApoB. The differences in terms of looking at the steady
state plasma levels is that their ApoB system is just really markedly revved up. They take care of
their business. They just must clear it up a certain way. And they make it, and it serves a
similar role in terms of transporting triglycerides as a source of energy to tissues in the body that
need energy and to adipose tissue for storing it. It's just that the rate at which they do that is
much more efficient, whereas in humans, for reasons we could talk about but aren't totally clear,
but certainly have to do partly with our lifestyle. Humans are not nearly as efficient
at clearing the ApoB containing lipoproteins, and they hang around, especially as LDL,
as a byproduct of this metabolism in a way that then ultimately leads to, of course,
atherosclerotic vascular disease. We do need ApoB. Honestly, mammals evolved ApoB because,
one, we have to be able to efficiently capture fats in the diet for energy purposes,
and very efficiently. That's what the chylomicrons allow us to do. And during fasting, which, of
course, in evolution sometimes lasted a long time, we have to be very parsimonious about
parceling out that available fat we have in our adipose stores back out to heart and muscle to be
able to have as a source of energy. That's what ApoB 100 in the liver does. We need these,
especially in evolution, the latter. We need it very substantially. But now, unfortunately,
in the modern times, the ApoB system is mostly a problem, not something we need.
I think the way you stated it earlier is obviously more accurate, and perhaps I want to just make
sure I'm restating it without being quite as tongue-in-cheek. It's really not that we don't
need ApoB. It's that we could be clearing it at a much greater and more efficient rate
than we are, and we could more mimic primates and other mammals and walk around with an ApoB
concentration of, call it 20 milligrams per deciliter instead of 100 milligrams per deciliter,
a five-fold difference, which is about, that's the difference between getting atherosclerosis
in our lifetime and never getting atherosclerosis in our lifetime.
I agree with that.
And that's the interesting thing, because even absent the, quote unquote,
lifestyle things that will raise ApoB, it just occurs with aging. Peter Libby has written about
this very eloquently, and children neonates have ApoB concentrations that are just like those of
these other animals. And all things equal as we age, ApoB just goes up, that concentration goes up,
as you say. We're less efficient in the way we clear ApoB from circulation. Anyway, it's a
fascinating topic, and I know not what we're going to talk about today because it's one of speculation,
and we could speculate, but there are actually lots of things today that we don't have to speculate
about as it comes to ApoA and HDL. I want to go back to kind of the nomenclature a little bit,
because I know I'm still kind of confused on some of this, and I think it's going to be a little
challenging because we're sometimes talking about Roman numerals, and we're sometimes talking about
numbers. But is there just an ApoA1 and 2 in the Roman numeral lipoprotein, Apo lipoprotein cover?
No. So it goes to two, three.
The two other ApoAs that at least we know about or we talk about are ApoA4 and ApoA5.
Don't ask me what happened to ApoA3. That's a mystery I've never been able to solve.
But anyway, it's another one of those. ApoA4, we don't really know what it does. ApoA5,
I can't remember if you've talked about, but ApoA5 has a very important role in stimulating
lipoprotein lipase and in the metabolism of triglyceride-rich lipoproteins. It rides on
HDL, but it also rides on triglyceride-rich lipoproteins. And people who lack ApoA5,
have really high triglycerides and are also at major risk for atherosclerotic vascular disease.
So anyway, again, maybe not the topic for today, but it does illustrate one point, Peter, maybe
that I'll make, which is that HDL as a molecule, as a lipoprotein, I think of as a platform.
It's a platform for all sorts of proteins and lipids that get transported by HDL in the blood
and then transfer off HDL to other things, to ApoB-containing lipoproteins. So my example of
ApoA5, it's named ApoAA because it was discovered on HDL, but its primary role in metabolism is
triglyceride-rich lipoprotein metabolism. ApoA5 is basically kept within the blood and stored,
if you will, on HDL. But then when we eat a fatty meal, it transfers off to the triglyceride-rich
lipoproteins and it serves a role of promoting the hydrolysis of the triglycerides. So I think
that's a general concept for HDL that maybe we'll keep coming back to is this platform for all
sorts of things that are doing different things that involve not only lipid metabolism, but
host defense and other things that it evolved to do as a platform for transporting things within
the blood. Which I think explains, at least in part, the complexity of this system is
it's much more dynamic than what we see on the ApoB side. The ApoB side, as you said,
it's a very monogamous relationship, right? I mean, you sort of get your ApoB in the liver and
it's with you for life and you're not swapping, you're not trading, you're not increasing or
decreasing, you're just marching through life. And the HDL is maybe the monogamy wasn't the best
example because now I don't know what to come up with here because it's not just polygamy,
it's even more complicated than that. As you said, it's swapping, it's moving things around,
it's carrying things that it doesn't really use, but loaning them out. It is indeed a complicated
system. The next thing that seems to add a lot of confusion, at least to me, is some of the
nomenclature around the numbering of the HDL particles. And I bring this up in part because
various commercial labs, someone listening to this goes out and gets a really fancy,
fancy blood test. We use Boston Heart Labs with our patients. I know that this is something you
see with a number of other labs. It might say things like HDL1, HDL2, HDL3. What's the relationship
between that nomenclature and the ApoA1, ApoA2, ApoA4, et cetera? This is ridiculously complex.
The short answer to your question is actually, believe it or not, there's no relationship. So,
the numbering of the Apo-Lipar proteins or the ApoA-Lipar proteins, 1, 2, 4, 5, is totally
independent of the numbering of the HDL particles, like especially HDL2 and HDL3, which are the
classic two main, quote, subclasses of HDL. These are different sizes and different densities of HDL
that, again, were isolated by centrifugation and by their flotation properties. HDL2 is bigger. HDL3
is a little smaller. HDL2 has mostly four molecules of ApoA1. HDL3 has mostly three
molecules of ApoA1, but those threes don't have anything to do with each other. Then,
to make things more complicated, there are other ways of subfractionating
lipoproteins. I know you've discussed, like the NMR type methodology, that don't use HDL2 and HDL3,
which frankly is a little outmoded now, but use things like very large HDL, large HDL, medium HDL,
small HDL, very small HDL. HDL certainly comes in a whole series of sizes and densities
that can be isolated by these different methodologies. There's been a cottage industry,
as you know, Peter, of trying to relate these different fractions of HDL to cardiovascular risk
in a way that might give us some advantages in terms of trying to predict risk. We can come back
to that, but I would say in general, I'm not very compelled that fractionating HDLs gives much
clinically valuable information that allows us to predict risk. In contrast, I just want to say,
in contrast to the ApoB-containing lipoproteins, whether it's ApoB, but I think the smaller,
denser LDL particles do have a relationship to increased risk, as you've discussed in the past.
But I think the HDL fractionation is fascinating for understanding HDL biology and metabolism,
but is relatively unimportant from a clinical relevant standpoint.
I'm actually glad to hear you say that because I was wondering if I need to be changing
our clinical practice. In about 2016, we basically stopped paying attention to any of the HDL
fractionation metrics. Really, it had to go out of our way to make sure that the lab was not running
those because in some areas, we're running complicated labs. We were saying, look, we don't
want any of this stuff. A, we don't want the additional cost of it, but more importantly,
we don't think it's clinically actionable. We still get labs from other doctors who
might've seen our patients in the past and they're chock full of these things,
to which I don't know what to do with them.
While we're on this topic of HDLs fractionation, unless you want to ask me another question.
No, no, go ahead.
I wonder if I could use this as a springboard to continuing this complex saga of the metabolism
of HDLs once they're formed and once they have cholesterol ester. The reason we have this whole
set of different size and density HDLs is because of the complex metabolism that occurs on the HDLs
once they're in the blood, once they've been made mature HDLs. I want to give you maybe a couple
examples of that. One is that HDLs are acted upon by so-called lipases and you've talked a
lot about lipoprotein lipase. It's critically important for triglyceride metabolism and energy
metabolism. Lipoprotein lipase has two other very close cousins that I don't think you've talked
nearly as much about appropriately because they're more HDL related. One is called
hepatic lipase and what is called endothelial lipase. We actually first reported a long time
ago endothelial lipase as a member of this family. Both of these lipases, they're made in different
places as their names suggest, but both of them fundamentally chew on HDL, specifically the
phospholipids on HDL and result in modification of the phospholipid composition of the HDL particle
in a way that does different things. It certainly changes the sizes of the HDLs and they contribute
to this distribution of different sizes. It changes the protein composition of the HDLs in
ways that we don't fully understand and almost certainly has other important biological effects
that we don't fully understand, but of course these evolve for some reason, one of which I'm
going to get back to later when we talk about the central nervous system. So that's one. The
lipases are really critical for HDL metabolism. There's also this protein that I know you've had
some discussion about, cholesterol ester transfer protein. Happy to go into more detail and I'm sure
we will because it's very relevant to HDL, but just for the metabolism part of it, this so-called
CETP, cholesterol ester transfer protein, essentially transfers cholesterol esters between
apoB-containing lipoproteins and HDL and it's a major modifier of the HDL particle in terms of
its size and composition. We know this because people who lacked CETP have hugely elevated HDL
cholesterol levels, big time, like over 100. That really told us that cholesterol ester transfer
protein siphons cholesterol out of HDL and when you don't have it, you have a lot more cholesterol
in HDL and just point back to our previous discussion of mice. Mice don't have CETP.
So among the differences, one of the things is that mice have a lot more HDL cholesterol relative
date would be because they lack this CETP protein. I mean, I know we're going to come back to this,
but I just, I worry that for the listener, this would be an opportunity missed if we don't dive
into CTEP a little bit because of the following. If we take a step back, a listener is going to be
saying, Peter, Dan, what the hell are you guys talking about? Like I am so lost. The only thing
I know is when I go to the doctor, the doctor says my good cholesterol is high. I'm in good shape.
So let's do this. Let's hit pause for one sec and acknowledge that a standard lipid panel spits out
a bunch of numbers, total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, HDL cholesterol. And if you're lucky,
VLDL cholesterol, non HDL cholesterol and triglycerides, that's basically the standard
metric. If the lab is competent and they're using direct measurements, your HDL cholesterol,
LDL cholesterol and VLDL cholesterol should sum to your total cholesterol. And of course, your
non HDL cholesterol should be the same number as your total cholesterol, less your HDL cholesterol.
Want to pause and also insert that with nomenclature, HDL is not a laboratory metric. It is a LIPA
protein. The laboratory metric is HDL cholesterol, HDL C, or if using NMR, HDL P, HDL particle number.
Or APO A1, an analogy to measuring APOB. Exactly. The units that you've been throwing around,
of course, are the HDL cholesterol. A moment ago, you said, hey, people who are deficient in CTEP
could have HDLs over 100. Of course, that means HDL cholesterol over 100 milligrams per deciliter.
Now, there is an observation that goes back probably to the late 70s, right? I mean,
it probably goes back to late 70s, early 80s, which is in some of the earliest Framingham cohorts,
which observed the risk of ASCVD in five cities. We don't need to go into what Framingham did in
the first cohort. But what came out of that was higher HDL cholesterol was better than lower HDL
cholesterol. In fact, that was four times greater if my memory serves correctly as a predictor of
ASCVD than high LDL cholesterol was a negative predictor. Am I remembering that correctly?
Yeah, that's about right. Yep.
By now, we're talking about 82, 83, 84. This has been a long time since I've looked at this stuff,
but it emerges that, hey, high HDL cholesterol seems to be positively associated with outcomes.
And obviously, that's a big part of why HDL cholesterol became known as good cholesterol
and LDL cholesterol became known as bad cholesterol. We'll obviously talk about why those terms are
inaccurate. But it wasn't long until companies, drug companies were saying, hey, wait a minute,
we know that if CTEP is inhibited, this enzyme is inhibited, HDL cholesterol goes up. That must
be a good thing, right? That led directly from this observation I mentioned that people who lack
CTEP genetically have these hugely elevated levels of HDL. One directly from the other. Well, gosh,
that must mean that if we could pharmacologically inhibit the CTEP, it would be a way to raise HDL.
And of course, as you know, that absolutely turned out to be the case. But the story goes beyond that.
So the first company to do this was Pfizer, right? Wasn't the first CTEP inhibitor?
The first CTB inhibitor, Torcetribib, was from Pfizer, correct?
And that was, you could take a skeptical view of the trial, which was Lipitor was about to go off
patent. And so they came up with a trial that was Lipitor by itself versus Lipitor combined
with the CTEP inhibitor. And I remember actually, this was probably early 2000s, right? Thinking,
oh, this is super, I mean, this was back when I was in my surgical residency. So I was
only tangentially interested in this, right? It wasn't my field. But interesting in that I knew
my family history for ASCVD was high, so I was paying attention. And I remember thinking, well,
God, this has got to be great, right? You got one drug that's going to lower LDL-C,
one that's going to raise HDL-C. This is a can't miss drug. And then in September of 2006,
lo and behold, not only did it not get better, it was slightly worse, right?
Yeah, bombshell. So first, I want to emphasize, the genetics did predict what happened. That is,
pharmacologic inhibition of CTP is extraordinarily effective at raising HDL a lot. In fact,
putting people kind of over 100 HDL cholesterol, like the folks who lack CTP. But you're absolutely
right. There's a lot of excitement about that. A lot of excitement about HDL is the good cholesterol.
And that trial, the first of several with different CTP inhibitors, not only didn't show benefit,
but showed an actual adverse effect. Now, it has to be said that in retrospect,
we're pretty sure that adverse effect, more people, literally more people died.
That adverse effect was due to off-target effects of the drug, not due to CTP inhibition itself.
So that drug, of course, was discarded, but it didn't kill the field because the idea was, well,
that was just a bad drug. Let's get a clean CTP inhibitor and see what that really does. I don't
know if you want to ask me questions or I can continue the story. Yeah. Let's go down that path
because it's still a little, it got progressively less murky as time went on, but let's go down the
path of the evolution of CTP inhibitors, which let's be honest, it's for what, we're almost
15, well, actually 16 years post the halting of that trial and the discarding of that drug.
And we still don't have a CTP inhibitor on the market, right?
We don't. There is still a CTP inhibitor that's in development, which I'll get to,
but there is certainly not one on the market. As you know, Peter, and certainly probably many of
our listeners do, three additional CTP inhibitors were then taken into late-stage clinical development,
including large cardiovascular outcome trials. To summarize the results of that, one of them was just
flat, didn't do anything, didn't hurt people, but didn't help. A second one was stopped early because
it really didn't look like it was doing anything, helping. And the third one was followed through
and did show about a disappointing 9% reduction in cardiovascular events. But I also want to point
out that it lowered LDL and ApoB pretty well also. 9%, given that you also lowered LDL and ApoB
was not exactly exciting and that drug was not taken further in terms of approval. I have to say
one other thing that's just fascinating for sort of our field and maybe in general. One of these
drugs, dalcetrapib, that failed in its clinical trial, a detailed genetic study was done post-hoc.
And there were individuals who were found to have a particular genetic variant that looked like on
post-hoc analysis that group actually benefited from the drug. And that led to a subsequent attempt
to do another trial focused specifically on people of that genotype with the CTP inhibitor,
which was just reported out really within the last year as a negative trial. That CTP inhibitor
actually had two different trials, one in kind of a very focused precision medicine way, but it still
didn't produce any benefit. This has been a long saga of using CTP inhibition to raise HDL
as a way to reduce risk. And as we're going to be talking about more, it really is one of the key
planks that has led to, I think, what is now rock solid, which is HDL cholesterol itself, the HDL
cholesterol itself is not directly and causally protective against atherosclerotic cardiovascular
disease. There's a lot of nuances there, which we'll come back to, but I feel pretty confident
making that statement. And I just think there's a great opportunity to also talk about why it's so
important to have hard outcome trials in the field of cardiovascular medicine. I think it's true in
all medicine, but let's go back and think about the first lipid lowering drug introduced in the
United States in, God, about 1950, right? Maybe 1959, something like that, right? So try Panerol,
which I can never remember the name of the enzyme, but it's the enzyme that converts
desmossterel to cholesterol in the cholesterol synthetic pathway. Believe it or not, this is a
sign of my aging, Dan. I used to know the names of these enzymes. It was like, and it's not delta-24
desaturase, but it's a cousin or derivative, isn't it? But anyway, so you had this drug,
triperinol, that inhibited that enzyme and lo and behold, it lowered cholesterol. Now, this was
for the listener, this is back in the day before we knew anything about the sub fractions of
cholesterol. So we just knew from some of the early work of Ansel Keys that if you looked at
very, very high levels of total cholesterol and compared that to people who had very,
very low levels of total cholesterol, there was a difference in outcome, cardiovascular outcomes.
This was an observed finding. There was no intervention to test that. So this drug came
along and it really lowered total cholesterol and it likely would have been lowering LDL cholesterol
and APOB. It basically got approved on the basis of that without of course the hard outcome. So it
gets approved, it goes into circulation and it's really only after it was approved, gosh, probably
what, eight to 10 years later that they had enough post surveillance data to say, you know what,
this drug is lowering cholesterol all right, but it's actually increasing mortality, cardiovascular
mortality. Drug was pulled off the market. I don't know what is known about the why, but I
know Tom Dayspring and I have speculated that it was probably the desmosterol spike that was causing
the problem. So you might've been trading one problem for a worse problem. Are you familiar
with that drug or that story? Only peripherally, but of course there's been a ton of research in
desmosterol really over the last several years. We now, based on that, that the plausibility of
the fact that the adverse effects were related to increasing this nostril I think is quite real.
That very well may be the explanation. By the way, this is a totally tangent off-topic point, but
it's become quite in vogue to use clomaphene or clomid for testosterone replacement in men. And
the reason for it is A, it's quite effective. So if you give clomaphene, you are telling the
pituitary to make a lot of LH and FSH, which of course is telling the testes to make a lot of
testosterone. This would certainly in the short term have the advantage of preserving testicular
function, unlike giving exogenous testosterone, which suppresses testicular function. And I think
for short term use, it probably isn't a bad thing. It's an off-label use of course for clomaphene.
And we used to do it for this purpose, right? So if a guy was still considering reproduction
or we were considering this a ridge treatment between testosterone, we would use it. But
because we always measure desmosterol, lithosterol, compensatorol, cytosterol, these sterols when we
measure our patients' cholesterol levels, we noticed how high the desmosterol levels were getting in
those patients. And we figured out pretty quickly it was the clomid that was doing this. And it
would reverse, but it could take a year to return desmosterol levels to normal after you stopped the
clomid. So about four years ago, once we put two and two together, we stopped using clomid. But it's
interesting to me that the use of that hormone has gone through the roof. There are now like
clomid clinics opening up. And I don't understand why someone, and we've done a lit search. I don't
understand, we just need to write this up. I think at some point. Yeah, it's fascinating.
Because I don't understand why someone hasn't put the two and two together, especially long-term
use. Again, I don't think using clomid for a couple of years is going to be problematic. And
I certainly don't think it's problematic for women using it for IVF. When I think about a guy
being on this for 10 years, and I'm talking desmosterol levels going up by 20 fold,
that would be concerning. And we went back and tried to see if we could find out how high the
desmosterol levels were in the triparinol trials, not trials, but in the levels that if anybody had
pulled serum or saved serum from those subways, we couldn't find it. So we don't really know how high
it was, but the assumption has to be that that drug and clomifene both interfere with the same
enzyme. Really fascinating. I would encourage you to write that up. So what's the point of that
whole long-winded story? The point of that long-winded story is things can make a lot of sense
until they don't, right? That's for sure. Before we leave CTP inhibition though, I do want to just
remind your listeners that there is still one CTP inhibitor, obocetrapid, that is still in clinical
development. What differentiates it, it's much more effective at lowering LDL and ApoB. We now
no longer think that raising HDL cholesterol with CTP inhibition is going to help you. We don't think
it hurts you, but we don't think it's going to help you. But we do think that there's still merit.
Of course, we know there's merit to raising LDL cholesterol and ApoB. You mean lowering. I'm sorry,
lowering. Perhaps this CTP inhibitor could be part of the armamentarium to do that. So we'll see. Stay
tuned. Now, Dan, maybe this was naive of me, but after the third failure of a CTP inhibitor,
my very crude interpretation is not unique. I'm sure a lot of people have speculated this,
is that if at least part of the benefit of HDL involves stuff we're going to talk about, right?
Delipidation, reverse cholesterol transport, all of those things. And you slap a CTP inhibitor on
one of those particles, thereby making it harder for the particle to efflux its cholesterol to get
rid of its cholesterol, which is why you now measure much higher HDL cholesterol, which on the surface
looks good. That could actually be problematic. In other words, if you see a lot of people in a room,
it might be tempting to conclude that there's something awesome going on in that room.
But what you don't know if you can't measure all the ins and outs is it might be that those people
are all stuck in the room because the door is locked. I know that's a bit of a crude analogy,
but is there any merit to that sort of thinking around the different ways in which one might
boost HDL cholesterol and how some of those could actually be deleterious if they prevent function?
There absolutely is, but I think it's probably not relevant to CTP for reasons we can return to,
but it is relevant to another protein that I think now's a good time to introduce,
which is another key protein, a receptor that is basically the major HDL receptor.
Essentially the equivalent of the LDL receptor, but for HDL, and it's known as SRB1,
another unfortunate nomenclature. SRB1 is a receptor that basically is on a lot of cells,
but the liver is the most important with regard to HDL. It essentially binds the HDL particle,
basically sucks the cholesterol ester out of the HDL particle, and then releases the
cholesterol depleted HDL back into the circulation to go back around and do whatever it's doing.
So the analogy I like to use, Peter, is that of garbage trucks. So a very simplistic view of HDL,
which we're going to return to because it's much more nuanced, is that HDL to a certain extent
functions like garbage trucks that are picking up things trash in places where you don't want it,
and returning it to the liver, dumping it off via SRB1, and then going back now empty to do more
of its role. Again, it's more complicated than that, but that's an analogy. So this brings me
back to SRB1. So there are humans who lack SRB1. What do you think the problem is? Very high HDL.
They have very high HDLs. They have very high HDLs because they can't unload the dump trucks,
but they actually have increased risk of heart disease because they are not efficiently
unloading that HDL. So very similar to your analogy of the locked room, you're not clearing the HDL
and doing that normal process of recycling the trucks back to the periphery to do what they
need to do. And so that's, I think, our best example of this concept of constipation of the system,
leading to high HDL but paradoxically to increase risk. And of course, the analogy would be that,
not the analogy, but the interpretation that would be, you would never want to develop an SRB1
inhibitor. Yes, it would raise HDL quite a lot, but it wouldn't protect against heart disease and
probably would hurt people. Yeah, I remember the first time Tom shared a case study with me of a
patient with presumably defective, not necessarily completely absent, but SRB1. And
this was one of those things where you could tell just reading the journal, it must have been 40
years old, but her LDL cholesterol was whatever it was, 100 milligrams per deciliter. Her HDL
cholesterol was like 150 milligrams per deciliter. So she had quote unquote high cholesterol,
but initially people assumed it was not of concern because the fraction that was HDL cholesterol was
what was contributing to it. And of course, on further exam, I mean, she had very, very advanced
atherosclerosis for a woman her age. Yep, exactly. We don't see this often. I can tell you that I
have not yet seen a case of that. Now, admittedly, my practice is not large, but we're certainly
looking for it when we see people with high HDL cholesterol, typically north of 90. I guess we
should talk about this as well, but we can do that in a moment after this question, which is why is
there a sex difference between these two? Because there is quite a significant sex difference
between men and women in terms of HDL cholesterol. But at what point, Dan, as a clinician, do you
start to worry about that? And if there are doctors or patients listening to this, when would you
recommend that somebody go and get checked out for a genetic deficiency there? SRB1 deficiency
is not common. I completely agree with you. Huge project we've had for a long time now is
essentially collecting people or consenting people with extreme high HDL with the goal of trying to
find what the underlying genetic cause is. And I will tell you that that's how we found a few of
these SRB1 folks, but most of them don't have any identifiable gene that we can point to and say,
here's the smoking gun. Here's why your HDL is high. HDL is very heritable, meaning that there's
a lot of genetic determinants of HDL, but it's more about so-called polygenic inheritance where
multiple different genes, including SRB1, but not major genetic defects, just sort of more common
variants, but many others, like some of the things we've been talking about, including a CTP and
ABCA1, all contribute to the heritability of the HDL cholesterol. But to get back to the clinical
implications, my view at this point, we can talk more about the data. It's pretty clear that
high HDL is not uniformly associated with protection. And there are certain circumstances
where that's true, especially if it's extremely high. Perhaps we'll get back to this, but there's
a fair amount of evidence now, including a recent paper that individuals of African ancestry who
tend to have higher HDLs anyway, that the high HDLs are not as protective or maybe not even HDL is
that well associated with risk. So my clinical advice to anyone with high HDL is not go get
yourself sequenced to find out if you're deficient in SRB1. The odds of that are extremely low,
but never use a high HDL as a reason for not using a statin or some other LDL lowering or
preventive therapy. That is, you should never be dissuaded from doing what you would have
otherwise done in that patient just because their HDL is high. Does that make sense?
Yeah, absolutely makes sense. And I have a very short paragraph in my book that'll be coming out
in a while where I cite two Mendelian randomizations that really look at this in some detail. I think
I've explained Mendelian randomization before on the podcast, but it's always worth, I think,
a short explanation again, in case you haven't heard it. This is basically a technique where
you look for genes that impact traits that you are interested in. So in this case, because as you
pointed out, HDL is very genetic. That means that there are sets of genes that we would identify
that predispose people to having very high versus very low HDL cholesterol. And because those genes
are randomly occurring, you can look at that as though it's a natural experiment. And you can look
at based on the natural occurring spreading or scattering of those genes, how are outcomes
effective? And it turns out that low HDL cholesterol is not causally linked to atherosclerosis,
and high HDL cholesterol, genetically high, is not causally linked to protection from ASCVD.
So I think those are very important findings, and I think it speaks to why, as you say, you can't
use high HDL cholesterol as a reason to not treat in the presence of other risk factors.
I completely agree. It's interesting, though, that that persists, isn't it? I do find this to be
probably top three most vexing discussions I have with other physicians, which is, I know his LDL
cholesterol is 140 milligrams per deciliter, but God, I mean, his HDL is 80. I mean, his ratio,
I mean, that's when they say the ratio of total cholesterol to HDL or LDL to HDL is such and such,
and therefore I don't need to treat. I mean, it makes me wish I had hair to pull out.
You're absolutely right, and I'll just reiterate, high HDL is never a reason not to treat someone
who would have otherwise merited treatment. I do want to make clear, though, there are lots of
people who are on the fence about whether to start a statin, who have LDLs that are kind of borderline
or even not that terribly high. And of course, we look at the whole patient, we look at the risk,
we look at their calculated risk, other risk factors. But I'll just say that a low HDL
in the setting of someone who you're generally on the fence about treating,
perhaps could contribute to tilting toward, yes, I'm going to treat this person. In other words,
a low HDL, at least in most populations, again, I think individuals of African ancestry, perhaps
we have to be a little bit more careful about using HDL as a predictor. Maybe we'll come back
to that. Otherwise, I think a low HDL can be used not absolutely, but relatively to tilt toward
being more aggressive, but only in the context of the overall risk profile.
And obviously part of that, Dan, has to do with the relationship between low HDL cholesterol,
if my memory serves me correctly, it's the HDL two fraction and the association with that and insulin
resistance. So there's no question that a phenotype, and as you point out, and we should come back to
this, we don't even do this calculation for African-American patients because we've long observed
it's not helpful, but in non-African-American patients, the ratio of triglyceride to HDL
cholesterol when both are in milligrams per deciliter is reasonably associated with insulin
resistance. And the higher that ratio, the more insulin resistant they are. And obviously that
ratio is driven up by an increase in triglycerides and a reduction in HDL cholesterol. Why is it that,
I mean, we've spent hours on this podcast talking about why insulin resistance would lead to or be
associated with high triglycerides. We haven't done the opposite or the reverse of that. What is
it about IR that drives down HDL two? I'll just say first though, that one of the other analogies I
like to make is that HDL cholesterol, while not causally related to disease, is sort of like an
HBA1C for cardiovascular risk factors. It's an integrator of information related to insulin
resistance, related to triglycerides, related to inflammation, that in one number, in most people,
when it's low, it's telling you something about cardiovascular risk, even though itself it isn't
directly impacting on risk. So in answer to your question, I think one of the big issues with HDL
cholesterol is that it's an inverse barometer of triglyceride efficiency of triglyceride
metabolism. And again, we talked about efficiency earlier. You can only learn so much from measuring
a fasting triglyceride after a 12-hour overnight fast. It's useful. It's the way we do it in terms
of lipid panels. But a lot happens after a fatty meal, and a lot of that action is basically over
in most people by 12 hours. Some people are extraordinarily effective at clearing their
dietary fat and even their liver-derived fat, like mice. Others are not so effective, but their
fasting triglycerides may not necessarily even reflect that. The HDL cholesterol does reflect
that. There's a complex, as we discussed earlier, complex frequent interaction and exchange between
triglyceride-rich lipoproteins and HDL, with the net effect being the higher the triglycerides at
any given time, the lower the HDL is as a result of the complex interactions. So if you can picture,
we do a lot of these experiments where we bring in people and we give them a high-fat milkshake.
We draw blood multiple time points after that milkshake, and we measure triglycerides and all
sorts of other things. People differ a lot in their response to that high-fat milkshake challenge.
The higher that triglyceride goes, the area under the curve, the lower the HDLs are. That relationship
is extraordinarily strong. So just like HbA1c, that HDL cholesterol is sort of reading out
the 24-hour triglyceride metabolism much better than the overnight fasting triglyceride
measurement is. That's sort of why HbA1c is better than fasting glucose. That's the analogy.
First of all, I've never heard that before, and that might be if I learn nothing else on this
podcast, Dan. That is hands down the most amazing thing I have learned, not just today, but I'm
going to go out on a limb and say this week, potentially this month. That is super fascinating.
First of all, people on this podcast have probably heard me gripe over the lack of integral
functions in biology. My background, of course, in math and engineering, we love integrals. As
imperfect as the A1c is, as you said, it is an integrator, and it's so hard to find integrators.
Ferritin sort of does it a little bit for iron, but not nearly as well. The holy grail, of course,
would be to find an integral of something like mTOR activity or something like that.
I've never before been presented with or confronted with this. I want to make sure
we all understand this a little bit better. There's a couple of things that you've said there. One is,
if you stick an IV in a person's arm, let's just do that to go easy on them. We're going to just
be able to draw blood continuously or call it every five minutes without poking them. You bring
them into a lab fasted. You measure their HDL cholesterol. You measure their trigs. Let's just
say they show up in the morning fasted. Their trigs are 100 milligrams per deciliter. HDL is
50 milligrams per deciliter. Most people would look at that and say, oh, that's great. Person
looks super healthy. You give them a high fat shake, and 30 minutes in, you just start measuring
every couple of minutes the concentration of those two things. I think most people somewhat familiar
with metabolism would not be surprised to learn that the triglycerides will go through the roof.
As an aside, anybody who has accidentally done a blood draw with their doctor after eating a meal
when it was supposed to be fasting will be familiar with this. We see this from time to
time when patients make mistakes. They have a big fat breakfast before the blood draw and you get
their trigs back in their 400 or 500 milligrams per deciliter. Highly variable from person to person,
just to be clear. Highly meal dependent as well. Exactly. Very much depends on what the meal is.
In this experiment though, you're specifically giving them something to elicit the biggest
triglyceride response. In the example I gave Dan, let's say triglycerides go 100, 125, 150,
all the way up to 400 before they start to come down. That generates an area. You could integrate
that on the curve. Can you give realistic ideas or values for what the HDL cholesterol would do
during that period of time? The HDL cholesterol definitely dips during that time in a way that's
proportional to, roughly proportional to the triglyceride levels, but not anywhere near the
same degree of magnitude. Right. Simply because it's starting lower and you have a constraint
bottom versus no constraint top. Starting lower, but also the dynamics of its turnover are very
different. I think the key point here is HDL is not just an integrator sort of acutely over that
meal, but chronically in your example, the HDL cholesterol might go from 40 to 38 or 37,
which doesn't sound like a lot after that one meal, but the repeated meals that that individual
is eating that are high fat and that repeated triglyceride excursion has a more chronic effect,
a little like glucose and HbA1c that keeps taking the HDL down over time until you get to kind of
a new steady state. So the cute effect on the HDL is real. It's modest. The chronic effect on the HDL
of that abnormal postprandial triglyceride metabolism is quite substantial. And that's why
HDL is a good, as you say, integrator of this effect. And actually what you just said, Dan,
is kind of what I was hoping to go to next, which is if everything I said were true, that might not
be enough to explain the full integral function because it probably captures some of what's
happening outside of the meal. Just as hemoglobin A1c doesn't only reflect what would be captured
in an oral glucose tolerance test, it captures what's happening over 90 straight days when you're
eating, when you're not eating. Exactly. And that's also why there's a very strong statistical
relationship between fasting triglycerides and the HDL. So the fasting triglycerides themselves
are still affecting HDL metabolism. It's just that the postprandial part is also a key component.
So let's then again, just one more time, sort of reiterate the lagging nature of HDL cholesterol
through HDL biology to what's happening with the efficiency of maybe for lack of a better word,
lipid partitioning. The lagging nature, meaning the integrating over time? Yeah, exactly. Let's
use an example. So you've got a person who is exercising. And so you have two people who are
similar except that one is very insulin resistant and one is quite insulin sensitive. The insulin
resistant person is going to have a higher level of insulin. All things equal, they're going to
have a more difficult time oxidizing free fatty acid. So as energy demand goes up from the muscle,
they're going to be more likely to utilize glycogen as opposed to utilizing triglyceride.
So at any point in time, you might measure differences in glucose, differences in lactate.
You might, well, you would see lactate as well, but differences in triglyceride level. You might
also notice more fat in the liver or some fat in the liver of the insulin resistant person,
none in the insulin sensitive person. Into that situation, even when they're not eating,
they're quite different physiologically. What is the HDL discerning or doing in those two scenarios
that's being reflected in the ongoing integral function of it? The simplest, most direct model
is that the HDL is reflecting the 24 hour excursions in triglycerides, like we were just talking about.
I think what you may be getting at is there are almost certainly other components of metabolism
that the HDL is integrating and reflecting, particularly in the complex insulin resistance
world. We know insulin resistance has a lot of effects other than affecting triglycerides.
And insulin resistance, I'm sure, has effects that are affecting and are reflected by
a lowering of HDL. What I can't tell you is exactly what those are. That's an area that is
still a topic of investigation. I will give you one hypothesis though, and one that maybe I think
has some merit. As you know, adiponectin is an adipokine secreted by fat that has an inverse
relationship to insulin resistance. So basically people who are insulin resistant have lower levels
and people who are more insulin sensitive. And adiponectin itself appears to have some direct
effect on HDL metabolism in the right direction. We could talk about it possibly by tweaking the
liver in ways that then the liver affects HDL. So where I'm really going with this, although I have
to say the data still are not completely solid, is that another way that insulin resistance
is impacting on HDL is through adiponectin secretion affecting HDL metabolism in a way
that's completely different than the triglyceride hypothesis that I just put forth. You follow me?
Yeah. And it's funny. We used to measure adiponectin and leptin levels.
Again, one of those things I sort of stopped measuring. Do you think that that's a helpful
biomarker independently? And should that be something that's back on our plate?
Absolutely fascinating to try to put together these metabolic pathways
in terms of its utility as a clinical marker? I guess I'd have to be a little bit skeptical.
I'm not quite sure how I would use it in terms of guiding clinical care.
I mean, I think that was sort of where we ended up, which was, look, we get more actionable
insight out of other metrics. Okay. That was really interesting. And again, before we leave
the pharmacoside of this, can we talk for a moment about niacin? Oh, sure. It's been a while
since niacin came up on a podcast, but this is an interesting drug because it clearly raises HDL
cholesterol and it lowers APOB, doesn't it? It does. It lowers triglycerides. It lowers APOB.
It lowers LDL. All modestly, but really. Peter, niacin, I just chuckled because niacin is one
of these areas where we as lipidologists and me personally have to really eat a bit of crow.
There was a time when I prescribed niacin to a lot of patients with primarily the idea that it was
the only thing we had to raise HDL. This was in an era where HDL is the good cholesterol and raising
it must be good, right? I also told myself, well, niacin does lower triglycerides. It lowers APOB.
It lowers LDL. It also, as I'm sure you know, modestly lowers LP little a as well.
About 15% lowering of it. Yeah, 15, 20%. It basically was like, this is a nice broad spectrum
lipid lowering drug that, you know, not in place of, but on top of a statin for certain people who
had certain lipid profiles, mostly high triglycerides, low HDL, it has to be providing some benefit,
even in the absence of, as you pointed out, the clinical trials that really are a cornerstone of
cardiovascular medicine. Well, the clinical trials, you know, got done. The high trial, which
was a very well done trial, which frankly just didn't show much benefit of niacin, a blow to us,
but the field comes up with reasons why that trial may not have been right. Bottom line is,
one more trial run by Merck with a drug that also helped to potentially address some of the issues
with niacin was done. Very large trial, very well powered trial. And that also had really
minimal or very disappointing effects on reducing cardiovascular events. Essentially those two trials
killed niacin. So over the next, you know, year as patients would come back, I would have the
discussions that maybe you've had discussions with patients too like this, you know, that niacin I
put you on, you know, eight years ago that you've been taking religiously despite the question that
it causes when you take it. I really think I have to tell you that I'm not sure you need to take it
anymore. And it was a humbling experience to basically have a drug that I had prescribed
quite a lot basically to tell patients that I don't think that in retrospect, this is helping
you much. I do have a subset of patients who are so wedded to their niacin that despite that,
they haven't wanted to stop. But the vast majority of my patients have stopped their niacin.
And what's the mechanism by which niacin raised HDL cholesterol?
I think one is certainly triglyceride lowering, like we were talking about earlier,
but probably not just that because the increases in HDL were somewhat disproportionate to what
you'd predict from the triglyceride lowering. Although again, with the complexity, it's a little
hard to make that calculation. So there probably is some other mechanism. And to this day, I don't
think we really understand it. We tried for a while to try to figure that out. Niacin is a
very complex drug. Of course, we're talking about niacin here in pharmacologic dosing,
not in the kind of vitamin dosing. We don't really know. I think it's fair to say how niacin raises
HDL beyond its triglyceride lowering effect. It's not a drug we used much, if at all. But
the few times we did, I was actually really amazed at how much it raised HDL cholesterol.
I mean, it wasn't uncommon to go from 50 milligrams per deciliter to 90 milligrams per
deciliter on a strong dose. Let's shift gears for a second and talk about something that we briefly
touched on, but I think we now want to go into a little bit more detail. If everything we've
talked about so far is somewhat complicated, I actually think for me at least this next part,
especially the RCT stuff, gets complicated. So let's talk about what HDL lipidation,
delipidation, and reverse cholesterol transport are, because this is really where we start to
get into some of the sophistication of the HDL and even the interaction with other cells like
macrophages and things like that. I'll start and then you can kind of lead me along because this
can get quite complicated. Maybe just to orient you, Dan, why don't we start with, unless you have
a better way to do it, I'm totally open, but if you're looking for a goalpost to start in,
do you want to start with a foam cell stuck in an artery wall or is there a different place
you'd want to start the discussion? That's a good idea. So many of your listeners know that a core
concept in atherosclerotic vascular disease is the macrophage that's taken up lipids and is now a
so-called foam cell, meaning it looks foamy under a microscope because it has all this lipid and when
you stain tissues, the lipids become like bubbles within the cells and they look foamy. The foam cell
the lipid loaded macrophage is a core pathologic feature of atherosclerotic vascular disease.
It's also the first thing you see. So careful studies that have really looked at vascular
tissues in children and teenagers and young adults on the way up, you basically see lipid loaded
macrophages accumulating in the sub-entimal space, in the intimal space in the large vessels,
before you start seeing some of the more complex features of infiltration of other leukocytes and
extracellular matrix and all the stuff that ultimately comes to complex atherosclerotic plaque.
There's been a strong belief for a long time that this is one of the core initiators of the process
and I think that's probably true. An analogy would be like with Alzheimer's, the A-beta being kind of
the core initiator of the process leading to much more complex pathology. So macrophages have very
well-established mechanisms for ridding themselves of cholesterol. Keep in mind, no cell except the
liver cell has the ability to metabolize cholesterol to other sterile species. Only the liver can do
that. Cells can make plenty of cholesterol but the only way cells can deal with their cholesterol
is to quote efflux the cholesterol, to push the cholesterol out of the cell and get rid of it.
So if you think at the whole body level, all of the body is making cholesterol but that cholesterol
ultimately has to come out of those cells into something. This is where HDL comes in and ultimately
get back to the liver where the liver then can metabolize it or directly excrete it into the bile
then it goes out the intestine in the feces. So all cells have to be able to do this and all cells
in fact have the ability to push cholesterol out of their cells but macrophages really have to do
it. That is because macrophages are like kind of the dump truck of the body. They're picking up
not only LDLs and lipoproteins with cholesterol, they're scavenging cells, dead scales,
apoptotic cells and of course all those cells have lots of cholesterol. So macrophages need very,
very effective ways to rid themselves of cholesterol and they do have effective ways of doing that.
When those pathways get overcome or less efficient, the macrophage then builds up
cholesterol and becomes the kind of foam cell that we're talking about. Macrophages have
transporters. They have a very abundant amount of this ABCA1 that we talked about earlier.
Earlier we talked about it in the gut and the liver. Now I'm saying that macrophages have ABCA1.
ABCA1 is one of the, not the only, way that macrophages rid themselves of cholesterol.
If you recall, the main acceptor of cholesterol via ABCA1 transporting out of a cell is APOA1.
This led now quite a long time ago to the general paradigm that macrophage foam cells
are building up cholesterol because they're not getting rid of it effectively and that one of the
best ways to get rid of it would be to promote these efflux pathways via ABCA1 and other
transporters that are being driven by APOA1 to HDL, which then by my garbage truck analogy,
the garbage truck, i.e. the HDL, is picking it up in the periphery like the blood vessel
and returning it to the liver, dumping it off in the liver, and then going back and doing its job
again. This process of quote efflux, cholesterol efflux from macrophages and frankly other cells,
particularly in the blood vessel wall, has been for a long time now thought of as a key
process that would help to protect against the early initiation and progression of the
atherosclerotic plaque. Peter, that was long, but that's the start.
Well, and I think that's, look, let's just make sure everybody's interested in what we're talking
about here, which is when we really talk about the positive valence of HDL as a particle,
it's because of this, right? In large part, this is a big piece of the positive association,
presumably, or negative association, depending on the direction of HDL. We might see,
as we've been talking about it, it really now speaks to function. Part of the problem it would
appear is that very crude metrics like the amount of cholesterol in an HDL or even the number of HDL
particles or the size of an HDL particle, those are basically the only things we can measure,
clinically at least, those are so crude and so far removed from providing any quantification
of the process you just described that I suspect in part, that's why we are stuck in a way that
we are not on the ApoB side of the ledger because so much of the damage caused by ApoB is simply
captured in the number of them, given the stochastic nature with which they enter artery walls and get
retained. Would you agree with that assessment? I would absolutely agree with that. So this process
of cholesterol reflux, as the ideas evolved, is, if you will, the first step in this broader
physiologic process that Peter briefly referred to that we call reverse cholesterol transport,
or RCT, different than a randomized control trial. If forward cholesterol transport is basically the
cholesterol coming out of the liver into VLDL and LDL and then depositing in tissues like the
artery, the reverse transport is the picking up of the cholesterol, putatively via ApoA1 and HDL,
and returning it back to the liver. This process of reverse cholesterol transport, plausibly,
and I think some data, at least in animal models, is related to protection against atherosclerosis.
That is, the more effective you are at the integrated process of not only picking up the
cholesterol via efflux, but effectively returning the cholesterol to the liver for excretion,
the more you would protect against atherosclerosis, as the theory goes. I'll just remind you about our
example with SRB1. That's the terminal, sort of one of the terminal steps where the HDL is dumping
off the cholesterol. If you interrupt that process, your HDL goes up, but the process of
reverse cholesterol transport is being constipated, and therefore there's increased risk of atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease. One of the great goals of the field has been, can we promote that first
step of the process? Can we figure out a way to promote the driving of the efflux process
from the macrophages and maybe other cells in the atherosclerotic plaque to acceptors like HDL
in order to protect or maybe even regress atherosclerotic plaque, shrink it, as a way of
trying to reduce risk? I'll just say that as we move into this next phase of complexity,
I think what's pretty clear is it's not the mature HDL particle. When we measure HDL cholesterol,
that's what we're measuring, is the cholesterol in the mature particle. That's almost certainly
not the particle that is driving this first step of the efflux of the cholesterol from the foam
cell and the macrophage. That's maybe why simplistically raising HDL cholesterol, like with
CTP inhibition, doesn't actually reduce atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease events.
But are there other ways more creatively that we might be able to drive that process? Also,
to Peter's earlier functional point, might it be that different people, even with identical HDL
cholesterol levels, have different function of their HDL? One person with an HDL cholesterol of 50
might have something about their HDL pathway that is super functional at driving efflux,
whereas another person with the same HDL cholesterol doesn't do nearly as well. If we
could measure function efficiently, might we have a better way of assessing risk and maybe
even targeting interesting therapies more so than just measuring this fairly not so dynamic measure
of HDL cholesterol itself? There's more to say there, Peter, but I'll turn it back over to you.
Well, no, I mean, I think you illustrate the very important distinction between static biomarkers
and dynamic biomarkers. We have very few dynamic biomarkers, an OGTT and old glucose tolerance,
dynamic biomarker in a sense, but most things are very static and static things allow us to miss
flux. So that example you gave of two people whose HDL cholesterol is both 50 milligrams per
deciliter. We have no clue what the velocity through the HDL is. In one of those cases,
it could be a bump on a log and the HDL is not really doing a heck of a lot. And in the other,
that could be the busiest beaver on the face of the earth, just transporting lipid
out of foam cells right back to the liver back and forth, back and forth, back and forth. And
that could be the most industrious little guy on the block. And you could be in a totally different
risk situation as a result of that. So going back to the RCT, how often is it happening
that an ApoB, white-bearing lipoprotein, let's just call it an LDL, is floating around, so not
yet in artery wall, but on his way there, presumably. And an HDL come along and they collide
in the artery itself and delipidation takes place. So the HDL says, hey, I'm going to take some of
your cholesterol away and take it back to the liver now, which by the way, LDLs do as well. I
mean, LDLs are obviously carrying cholesterol back to the liver. But not as a reverse cholesterol
transport process, but yeah. The scenario I described, does that occur often? No, I don't
think so. In fact, as we discussed earlier with CTP, the directional flux of cholesterol in the
blood is more from HDL to ApoB containing lipoproteins rather than the other way around.
So I'm pretty comfortable in saying, I don't think that what you just outlined is a way that HDL,
HDL doesn't directly delipid, ideal. No, no, I think it's more about if it's happening at all.
I want to say all this is couched in, this is the paradigm that we're dealing with,
but where there's still a lot of uncertainty about it. But if it's happening at all,
it's really more that something about HDL or something, ApoA1, is more interacting with cells
to promote efflux of cholesterol rather than with other lipoproteins like ApoB containing lipoproteins.
What do you think the future could look like here in terms of commercial assays to measure
HDL function? I know that we're a long way away from that, so maybe I should start with something
even more basic, which is, what would it take in the lab to measure HDL functionality
if resources were unconstrained? No, that's where I wanted to go. So first, I want to say that
several years ago with this concept of reverse cholesterol transport as a dynamic process,
we developed an assay in mice that simply speaking involved taking cholesterol loaded macrophages
with labeled cholesterol, injecting them into the mice, and then following that label all the way
through the HDL to the liver to the gut to the feces. And we called that integrated reverse
cholesterol transport. And we showed in a variety of different genetic and pharmacologic approaches
that when you tweak that process either up or down, it mirrored the effect of that process on
atherosclerosis. What I'm really trying to say is something that promoted that process and made it
more efficient also reduced atherosclerosis, something that constipated that process,
increased atherosclerosis. It gave us a lot of confidence, frankly, it gave the field a lot of
confidence that integrated measure of reverse cholesterol transport is actually relevant to
atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease, at least in mice. So that brings me to humans. We can't do
the type of experiment I just described in humans. It's not feasible as a research or as a clinical
assay. So we thought long and hard about how can we start to think about doing this in people and
developed what I'll call an ex vivo cholesterol reflux assay, where the concept is we took
someone's blood or plasma, we isolated the HDL specifically, we got rid of the ApoB-contained
lipoproteins, and then put that on cells that were labeled with cholesterol and we measured the
effectiveness by which that HDL removed cholesterol from cells. What kind of cells did? And what we
found, as I think you know, is we were really struck with how different individuals HDLs were
at their ability to extract cholesterol from cells, even with the same HDL cholesterol level.
And it sort of affirmed this concept that HDL cholesterol is not really telling us or informing
us on the efficiency of the function of HDL, at least in this case, the function defined as the
ability to extract cholesterol from cells. And so we went on to use that in larger numbers of
individuals and showed that actually that was much more predictive of risk of coronary heart disease
than just measuring HDL cholesterol, even when you controlled for HDL cholesterol statistically.
And many others have shown the same thing. So I think it's pretty well established at this point
that this so-called cholesterol reflux capacity measurement of HDL is a better marker or predictor
of risk than just measuring HDL cholesterol, consistent with the idea that function is
important and that perhaps if we could increase function, we could maybe have a mechanism for
reducing risk. Now, Peter, you asked about the clinical apoligibility of that assay. You know,
I get asked all the time by patients and referring doctors, can you measure my patient's HDL function?
There's a lot of effort in this regard. Full disclosure, I was part of starting a little
company now several years ago called Vassar Strategies. And Vassar Strategies does do
this measurement in a very reproducible sort of way, mostly related to biomedical biopharma research.
But there is a lot of interest in trying to bring this clinically. And there are other
assays that are being developed. You know, when you're using radioactivity, it's a little,
you know, it's cumbersome for a high throughput clinical assay. And others are developing assays
that are cleaner and simpler and faster and cheaper. I think there's a chance we could have
a more widely available clinical assay to us for this purpose within the next, say, two to three
years. Right now, it's still under development. Two follow up questions there, Dan. One is just
a technical question on the assay. What type of cell are you using to measure the efflux capacity?
Well, when we first sort of pioneered this work, we used a mouse macrophage cell line
called the J774 cell. We have done it with human macrophages as well, and so have others. We like
to think that the macrophage is the most relevant cell type for reasons we discussed. Yeah, that's
the answer. And then I guess the second question is using the hypothetical, but probably somewhat
real example of we'll take 100 people that have an HDL cholesterol that's about the same. We do this
assay and we rank order them in effectiveness. You're saying that that rank order of effectiveness
correlates directly to risk. Are you saying directly related to risk by proxy, i.e. other
measurements like insulin resistance, ApoB, or are you saying actual outcomes? The first study we did
and published was cross-sectional with clinical coronary disease. So basically it was calcium
scores or things like that. An association cross-sectionally with prevalent disease. Then we basically said
we need to know if this is predictive of incident disease, events that occur. So we went to colleagues
who did the Eric Norfolk study, which you're probably familiar with, a very large prospective
study in the UK, in Europe. They provided samples and we measured this in a very large number, many
thousands of samples in a baseline in people who had been followed for 10 plus years. And we showed
even in that setting that the efflux capacity was predictive of incident cardiovascular events. So
yes, these are hard events, not just proxies like measurement of coronary calcium, for example.
Which is, again, fascinating. How well does that prediction hold up if you corrected for other
things that could be measured in the blood, such as insulin resistance, triglyceride, or ApoB?
We did do these statistical analyses correcting for clinical risk factors, including, of course,
HGL cholesterol itself. We corrected for things like BMI and presence of diabetes, dichotomous
presence of diabetes. If memory serves, we didn't attempt to correct for a sophisticated marker of
insulin resistance, like HOMA or anything, because I'm not sure we even had that data.
So your point is well taken. At some point, is this causal or is it still associative,
but just even better associative because it correlates with things even better than HGL
cholesterol? And I think that's why we need, of course, interventional studies that actually test
the hypothesis. Well, or even could we use it, there could be a hybrid there, right? Which is,
it's absolutely causal, but because it's so difficult and complex to initiate at scale,
what if we use AI to figure out that it's equivalent to a new metric that is a composite
metric of things that we can measure as biomarkers, if that makes sense. I hear what you're saying,
and that would be a great thing to think about. In our paper in Epic Northfolk, we did correlations
of the efflux capacity with lots of different things. Frankly, I have to go back and look at
that and remind myself if we had like fasting insulin or anything, because I think that starts
to get more at the insulin resistance component. But you're absolutely right. We may be able to find
markers that in composite would predict efflux capacity rather than having to measure the efflux
capacity itself. I'm not convinced we'll be able to do that, but I think that it's a good thought.
The analogy that comes to mind is certain labs use a series of NMR metrics to predict insulin
resistance, which I've always found not that interesting, frankly, because we can measure
insulin resistance so easily that using NMR to add another insulin resistance metric,
it seems a bit backwards. But the idea was they were able to basically look at the NMR spectra of
all the lipoproteins and impute a composite metric that came back. So if you could do that
in the other direction, which would actually be the valuable direction, it could be amazing. In
other words, if there was an HDL function score built out of X, Y, and Z, anything else before
we leave the topic of kind of measurement, we haven't really talked about the NMR side of the
equation. That's probably a bias because we don't use NMR, but clearly there are labs out there that
will count the number of HDL particles and spit out an HDL P. Anything you want to say about HDL P
or anything like that? Yeah, the overall number of particles is obviously correlated with HDL
cholesterol, but is a different measure because HDL cholesterol is just that amount of cholesterol
carried in the HDL, whereas the particles are more analogous to sort of measuring APO B,
the meaning total particle number. I think the data on balance suggests that HDL particle number
is a little bit better than HDL cholesterol at predicting risk. We haven't formally compared
HDL particle to cholesterol efflux capacity, the functional measurement. Fundamentally,
it's another static measure though. And so while it has maybe some limited predictive value,
I don't think it takes us that much further in terms of trying to get at where we're really
trying to go, is better predictions of risk, particularly in a setting where we might want to
intervene to actually try to reduce risk. Let's talk about something you mentioned
kind of in passing a couple of times. Peter, before we leave this topic though,
I do think it's important to remind your listeners that this concept of promoting the efflux and
reverse cholesterol transport pathway is being tested with another intervention called CSL112.
It's a form of APOA1 that's been complexed with lipids in a so-called recombinant HDL particle
is being tested for impact on cardiovascular outcomes in the setting of acute coronary
syndromes. So people have come in, been randomized to four weekly injections of this APOA1 containing
recombinant particle, which is very effective at promoting cholesterol efflux based on all the work
that's been done, with the idea being that this may directly impact the plaque and impact on
cardiovascular events. So this is, I would say, the closest thing we have to a formal test of the
cholesterol efflux hypothesis as an intervention in terms of whether it will reduce risk. Those of
us in the field are on the edges of our seats, it'll be a little while to really see what this
trial shows. I do think it's going to be interesting either way. So earlier, Dan, you mentioned kind of
briefly the association of plasma APOA1 and HDL cholesterol with neurodegenerative diseases,
such as dementia or Alzheimer's disease. I don't know if it extends to Parkinson's or Lewy body.
What do we know about that? Well, this is, I think, a fascinating new area of HDL biology
that has a number of components and that's still being investigated. I want to maybe
start by bringing in APOE. We haven't talked about APOE. APOE clearly has a role in APOE
containing lipoprotein metabolism and mediating the uptake of those remnant particles into the
liver. Can you actually explain this a bit more because most people hearing this are going to
think of APOE the gene and of course the gene for APOE people are going to be familiar with. It
exists in three isoforms, two, three, and four, but of course these things combined. So you have
six combinations of an APOE genotype and of course the gene codes for a protein. So I mean, I assume
everybody has the same APOE protein. You're going to have different amounts of it and different
potentially functionality depending on the combination of which gene produced it.
Exactly. APOE is possibly one of the most fascinating genes and proteins in human biology
in terms of its roles and the isoform issue and its relationship to disease. So as you point out,
there are three common isoforms of APOE, APOE3 being the so-called wild type or the most common.
You know, in lipidology we focused a lot on APOE2 because if you inherited two copies of APOE2,
that form of APOE is defective in binding to the LDL receptor and the other receptors that mediate
uptake of remnant lipoproteins, both chylomicron remnants and BLDL remnants. And therefore, if you
homozygous for APOE2, you're at risk for so-called, again, the terminology is bad, type 3 hyperlipidemia.
Which is basically a remnant clearance disorder. These individuals can't clear their remnants
appropriately. They get high triglycerides and cholesterol. They also are at increased risk of
atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. It's a classic lipidology thing.
And these patients require Fena fibrates to bring down the LDL and triglyceride?
They respond to a lot of the standard LDL lowering therapies like statin and azetamide. They even
respond to PCS-G9 inhibition. But sometimes we have to add on fibrates as well to maximally
control them. Depends on how severe they are. And yet those people, and by the way, that's the only
genotype I've never seen. It's much more rare than the 4-4 homozygotes. But the 2-2 would come with
about a 20% risk reduction, relative risk reduction in Alzheimer's disease. But paradoxically comes at
this higher risk of ASCVD. Exactly. So comes at higher risk of lipid disorder in ASCVD. But that's
exactly why I brought up APOE in response to your comment about neurodegenerative disease.
So as probably a lot of people know who are listening, the APOE4, as you just pointed out,
the APOE4 form, which is present in about 25% of people. So it's quite common. And even in the
homozygous form, certainly plenty of people out there who have both two copies, is in a dose
dependent way the major genetic risk factor for Alzheimer's disease. No question about it. And as
you said, Peter, APOE2, which is bad for your lipids in the blood, is actually protective against
Alzheimer's. It's absolutely fascinating biologically. There has been so much work to try to understand
how APOE is interfacing with Alzheimer's disease. So APOE is made in the brain. It's made by cell
types like microglia in the brain. And it's a lipid binding protein that transports lipids.
And now we know from genetics of Alzheimer's that there are lots of other lipid genes that are
related to Alzheimer's. So the story starts with the fact that APOE made in the brain is somehow
impacting on Alzheimer's risk. And if you have this form of APOE4, and especially if you have
two forms of APOE4, you are at very substantially increased risk of Alzheimer's for reasons that
we still don't fully understand. But as a lipidologist, I think it has something to do with
lipid transport in the brain. So that brings me to HDL. The APOE in the CSF and in the brain
is mostly made there. The newer developments that are relevant to APOE1 and HDL are that
there is clearly APOE1 in the brain and in the CSF. APOE1 is not made in the brain. So APOE1
gets there somehow through the blood, which I'll come back to. But there's now quite a lot of
observational data that strongly suggests that APOE1 is protective against neurodegenerative
disease. Now this is associative data. It doesn't prove causality. But the reason I think it's
plausible is that two of the major genetic risk factors for Alzheimer's that are expressed in the
brain are ABCA1. Remember that lipid transporter, that rid cells of cholesterol, and that APOE1
interacts with and promotes? And ABCA7, a very close relative of ABCA1 that structurally looks
very similar and that we don't know exactly what it does, but I think it's a safe bet that it's
transporting some sort of lipid to something in the extracellular space, whether that's APOE1 or APOE
or something else. So the plausibility of APOE1 being protective against neurodegenerative disease,
particularly Alzheimer's, is quite high. And frankly, there's a lot of work to be done to try
to figure it out. There's one other point I'll make, which is the blood levels of APOE1 and the
CSF levels of APOE1 and the relatively small number of studies that have measured both in the
same people are not that well correlated. So it's not simply a matter of if you have a high level
of APOE1 in the blood, that's going to generate a high level of APOE1 in the CSF. So what that
probably means is the processes that are happening that get the APOE1 across the blood-brain barrier
are highly regulated processes that, a little like the cholesterol efflux story, probably differ from
person to person and aren't directly being driven by the level of APOE1 in the blood.
Where I'm really going with this is this concept that if we could figure out how that happened,
if we could somehow promote more APOE1 going into the brain, into the CSF,
the data suggests that that might be a very interesting opportunity to blunt or reduce
risk of Alzheimer's. I find it fascinating, as you can tell. Dan, do we know if this relationship is
stronger or weaker as a function of APOE genotype? Is the effect more pronounced? Do we have enough
data to parse out that type of relationship? So I'll give you an example. Yeah, that's a really
super question. And I don't think we have big enough data sets yet to be able to parse it out
in terms of by APOE genotype to figure that out. But I have to go back and look for that, but I
don't think we know that yet. Do you have any idea why labs have not developed what would be very easy
to do, which is just a commercial assay for APOE concentration? There's certainly some data to
suggest that APOE concentration might be more relevant than APOE genotype, although of course
it's highly influenced by APOE genotype. But you could almost think of it as a gene expression
measurement, a crude measurement of gene expression for APOE. Is that something that you've seen or
used even in the lab? You're talking about APOE in the blood, right? Yes. Not in the CSF, just to be
clear. There are automated assays for APOE. We run one routinely in our lab. I think it's not a
clinically used assay. No, I've never even seen a CLIA-based assay for it. Right. I think mostly
because it isn't that helpful in the limited studies that have been done, which admittedly
maybe aren't as voluminous as they should be. It isn't that really helpful in terms of predicting
cardiovascular risk. Total plasma APOE. Oh, I was thinking more for neurodegenerative disease.
Has that been looked at? Oh, well, I didn't say it, but the levels of APOE in the CSF and the
levels of APOE in the blood for the few studies that have measured both in the same people also
do not correlate much at all. You would need CSF APOE if you wanted to do anything with this.
Exactly. That's what I'm getting at. You would need to be able to do it. I would not be surprised if
someone develops an assay for APOE concentration in the CSF as a clinical tool, because there I
think that might be highly relevant. Interesting. So here we have basically HDL potentially being
protective in the brain and presumably doing so via APOE1 potentially offsetting some of the APOE
problem, APOE being, as I think one of our previous guests referred to as kind of the
general contractor of cholesterol in the brain. Does HDL do anything with nitric oxide? I think
I remember reading something about promoting sort of endothelial NOS activity, nitric oxide
synthase activity. Is that a major issue? There's been a variety of other quote functions that HDL
has been reported to do, which I think are absolutely real. Their relevance to human
disease and pathophysiology I think are less clear. But one example is what you just said. So
a couple of investigators, most notably Phil Schall and Dallas has shown very clearly and
beautifully in cells and mice that HDL can promote nitric oxide production in a way that would be
expected to be beneficial, both in terms of blood pressure lowering and maybe protection
against atherosclerosis. And that SOB1, the receptor we've been talking about, is also
present on endothelial cells and mediates at least part of that effect of HDL. It's a fascinating
observation that is absolutely, I think, solid. Translating that observation to relevance in
humans I think is challenging, but I think plausible. Another, we've been talking about
insulin resistance. I'm sure you're aware of the data that suggests that HDL can interact
directly with skeletal muscle in a way that promotes insulin sensitivity. No, I'm not.
Fascinating work. Again, I put it in the same category of solid in terms of what it's been
able to show. Mechanistically, a little bit unclear and relevance to human disease and
physiology I think is still a little bit unclear. These are just two of the other types of things
that HDL has been shown to do that would be putatively beneficial but are of uncertain
relevance to real human disease. It's even more sort of removed than that because even if we knew
mechanistically that this were sound, we're still back in the same area we are with ASCVD. In ASCVD,
there's really very little ambiguity about the utility of HDL, the beneficial utility of HDL.
Yet we're standing here with our hands in front of us saying, well, what can we do about it
clinically as a physician, as a patient? What do I get to do about this knowledge that HDLs
are helpful particles when I can't measure the manner in which they do their job? The only
things that I can measure are as useless to me as my eye color basically. Then we're expanding into
and look what they can do in muscles and look what they can do in insulin sensitivity and look
what they can potentially do in the brain. It really comes back full circle to how we open
the discussion, Dan, which is this is such a complicated area of biology that I would guess
it has to be considered the next frontier of the lipid space. When we take a step back and put
ASCVD in the context of cancer and neurodegenerative diseases, so these are the big three
killers in the modern world. We know so much more about ASCVD and we have so many more tools to
effectively treat it. We know a bit about these other diseases, but in the case of Alzheimer's,
we don't have a single tool to do anything about it. In the case of cancer, most of our tools do
nothing. 90% of the tools do nothing, i.e. they barely extend median survival but don't cure
people. But in ASCVD, we can really move the needle. Yet you could argue half of the field,
we still know nothing about. Is there going to be a renaissance, you think, or are we up against
some technical limitation on this inability to measure function? I say that in a practical way.
I mean, yes, I think you're already measuring function in the lab, but is this a bridge too
far for the clinician? Well, I'm going to separate that into using a measurement of function for risk
prediction and then the implications for intervening therapeutically. I think that HDL
function, say, cholesterol efflux, has the ability to allow us to more specifically assign risk
better than just measuring HDL cholesterol. I think realistically we need a good reproducible,
easy to run, automatable assay that then is tested in large numbers of people and shown to predict
risk better than HDL cholesterol itself. I feel like knowing what I know is going on in terms of
developing those assays, that there's a decent chance that we're going to get there. But it's
not just the development of the assay, which actually there are several assays now that are,
but it's the proving that the measurement actually enhances risk prediction enough,
not just incrementally, but enough to make it actually worth doing in clinical practice.
I think there's a, I'm not going to say 100%, but I think there's a more than 50% chance
that we're going to see at least some assay come out that will allow us to do that. And then it
will be, frankly, physicians like yourself and like Tom Dayspring who pick up that assay and
start using it in their patients and start trying to get a sense for whether it's useful in the
context of a sophisticated preventive clinical practice. I think with regard to intervention,
the study I talked about is huge in terms of this. Let's just assume that that study is
positive. Four infusions, weekly infusions, significantly reduces cardiovascular events
in patients with ACS after 90 days. If that study is positive, if you think about that,
the implications for that product, but more importantly for the field that showing that
actually triggering cholesterol efflux via infusion of that particle, that type of particle,
that will rejuvenate the field of cholesterol efflux and reverse cholesterol transport as a
therapeutic target for intervention. I think if that trial is not positive, I think the concept
of intervening around HDL and reverse cholesterol transport for purposes of ASCVD is probably past
recovery. That would be my view. And even that CTP inhibitor that I mentioned that's still in
development, it's really more about reducing APLB than it is about raising HDL. When does that trial
read out, the function trial? I should have refreshed my memory on that. I just can't remember.
Where is it being done? How many centers? Roughly. It's a global study. There are centers in US and
Australia and Europe. It's a classic global large cardiovascular outcome trial. I think the leaders
of the trial I think are in Boston. Remind me, does it have a fancy acronym yet? Yes. And I'm
embarrassed to say that I'm not quite coming up with that either. We will figure that out and it
will be in the show notes. If I could just follow up on your next frontier comment. I don't think
HDL per se is the next frontier, but I do think lipid metabolism in the brain is one of the next
frontiers. I really do. With regard to neurodegenerative disease, but also other brain function, I say that
as a long-term lipidologist who is focused primarily on the blood. So I admit my biases
and looking for things that we can apply as lipidologists our expertise to. But I do think
understanding lipid metabolism in the brain and its relationship to disease, the brain is of course
the most lipid rich organ of any organ in the body, has been an under investigated area that we have
a lot to do. But where I think we're going to be uncovering some very interesting things that
with luck have implications for therapeutic intervention to prevent neurodegenerative disease.
Dan, it's hard to go anywhere from here. That is, I mean, both exciting and important in ways that
are rarely captured even in the subject matter. So I want to thank you for taking a subject matter
that is so complicated that I've largely shied away from really doing anything on it in the AMA
series that we do and so eloquently describing it and really using if someone's listening to this
and this is the first podcast they've ever listened to of ours, they might think, oh my god,
that podcast is too technical. But I think for regular listeners, they will appreciate that
you really did a great job simplifying a very complicated subject matter and certainly did a
better job than I would have ever been able to do, not simply because I don't know as much,
but because the ease with which you were able to speak about this is impressive. So
thank you for taking the time. Thank you for doing that. And most importantly, of course,
thank you for your work in this field. We, I think collectively, look forward to seeing how
things shake out over the next decade. Thanks very much, Peter. I really enjoyed it.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is
nobody's show notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing
these episodes completely access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything
without having to listen to spiel's like this. The qualities, which are a super short podcast
that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics and
tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
Peter Attia MD. You can also leave us a review on Apple podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise. Please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up to date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.