Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Rick, great to have you back and great to be spending time with you. Obviously, we had
dinner last night, which was wonderful. Thanks for coming to Austin.
That was such a treat last night, getting to see you in full dad mode and beautiful
family and great meal and lots of protein.
Indeed, lots of protein. Although we're in touch constantly from the standpoint of the
listeners, the last time they got to interact with you was probably almost exactly three
years ago, 2019. Sometimes when I have folks back on, especially if it's a technical podcast,
I want to talk about, okay, well, what's new information since that time? Well, this obviously
isn't very technical. Hopefully, folks remember a lot of the story that we talked about.
But nevertheless, what do you think of as the highs and lows for you of the last three
years? Because I know there have been both. Gosh, Peter, go back to that time. We had
a specific conversation about leadership. We were talking about leaders are only leaders
in a time of crisis. We had talked about how the last decade had been super benign and
how do we show up in crisis? And then 60 days later, 90 days later, boom, COVID hits.
So a lot of change, if you think about it, the last three years have been the most tumultuous
three years, no matter where you are in the world, not in any one country. And then you
layer that with lots and lots of changes. My kids have gone to college. My mother, which
we talked a lot about in the podcast, and my father-in-law and my aunt, which was, I
guess, like a mom all passed in that window. Our business went aggressively into offense
when the market changed because we saw some opportunities. We bought some very meaningful
businesses and then everything kind of further imploded in one way. And then now we're living
in the middle of a war, in the middle of uncertainty and all of that. But so the world always keeps
changing and surprising us. We tend to project kind of today's reality into the future, but
it's always changing. And how much of your even keel around all of these events, personal and
professional, do you attribute to what happened in January of 2009? In terms of perspective, I mean.
Yeah, yeah. A lot. You know, I really, I don't have a lot of lows. I, you know, I don't have a
lot of high highs. I just, to me, it's this understanding that this too shall pass and
really doing what you can in the moment when you can is all that you really can do. And if you
don't tie yourself up to the outcome as much and you're just really trying to stay in the process,
I really am able to navigate this in great part because of that experience.
One of the things we spoke about in the first podcast that, you know, you always have these
moments of podcasts that sort of stick with you. And that's probably true for a listener. It's
certainly true for the person doing the interview. There were handful of moments. One of them was
this image of raising children is playing a game of tug of war that you eventually lose. Now, you
can't lose it immediately, right? You can't just say, ready, go, let go of the rope. Right.
But by the time they're, you know, off to college, they've pulled you over the line metaphorically.
At the time we had that discussion, you were still engaged in that tug of war that your kids
were not yet in college. Now they are. I'm in the middle of that game. But I think about that
constantly. Maybe start by retelling a little bit of that and explaining kind of if at all
your thinking has evolved or what you've learned about that game in the last few years. Yeah. So
that was probably the last meaningful lesson I got from my mom. She had, you know, onset of
Alzheimer's and, you know, we would have moments of that. And I came and I was having coffee with
her and I asked her some advice about our daughter who was in plenty teenagerhood. And what she said
was she said she looked at me and said, my son raising teenagers is a tug of war. And then there
was this silence. And then she says that you ultimately must lose. And it is, you know, like
you said, you know, such a such an insightful, you know, all encompassing statement about parenting.
And it's really the transition from really being there will always be your kid, but you will not
always be their parent. And is that transition from no longer being their parent and maybe being more
of a coach, maybe being more of an advisor, a friend, all of that, they'll all you will always
treat them like your kid. So in our example, we're on the other side of this. I don't think of myself
anymore as, you know, the parent. I will always be that, but I'm not the parent. So the conversations
are very different and I love it. There have been times where both of our kids have looked at us
and said, I really appreciate your opinion, but this is what I'm choosing to do. And to me, that's
a sign of, you know, really good kind of sense of your own decisions. And we disagree with them,
but it is like good to see them in their journey of, of adulting now on their own.
Yeah. I don't know why I'm not looking forward to it, but it's one of those things that you know
is healthy, good, important, but, you know, but have you noticed a difference in teenagerhood and
how they start pushing away? Oh yeah. And I've always believed that the reason why teenagers are
such a pain is so that you don't miss them when they leave. And I tell you, we love our kids and
we're lucky that our kids love us back, but we were, we high fived each other when we dropped them off.
We did not cry. We were like, you know what, they're ready. We're ready. And, and empty nesting is,
it's a beautiful thing. You know, you still talk to them all the time and you still see them and all
that. So nothing, you know, but it's a, then the funny part is that they're doing the same things
that drove you crazy. You just don't see it. So it doesn't feel as, as intense.
So let's talk a little bit about, well, I want to bring up something that, that happened kind of
recently over the summer that I thought was spectacular. So early summer you, you, you call
me and said, Hey, I'm, I'm having a get together in July, you know, a couple of days and I'm inviting,
you know, you gave me a bunch of details, none of which meant anything to me, right? What I took
away from it was you wanted me to come out for a couple of days to your home. And there was going
to be a bunch of other guys there, at least one of whom I knew, but most of whom I did not. And
you, you prefaced it by saying, look, I know it's a big ask. I know how much you hate to travel. I know.
And you will have, I had just come back from traveling. I was just leaving the next day. I
would have to fly back and then hop right on a plane. But you really urged me to come. And
interestingly, I thought it was a birthday. Yeah. And so I sort of committed that I would think about
it and then talked about it with my wife and said, you know, I think this is special to Rick. I'm
going to go because I have a feeling it's one of those things where I'll spend the entire flight
there kicking myself for going. But if I don't go, I suspect months later I'll kick myself for not
going. So there's an asymmetry and regret. Yeah. So I ended up going and it had nothing to do with
your birthday, which I think was like five months earlier. So I don't know where I got that from.
Tell us about kind of what was the motivation for that and why do you think that ended up being
a really special time for, were there 40 of us there or something? About 30. Yeah. Okay.
You know, when you go back through your year and you go back and ask yourself what was truly
memorable of the year, at least in my case, there may be eight or 10 things that you will remember,
you know, well into the future. And what is universal about those things is they're usually
experiences and their experiences with people that you have a deep connection with. So I have
become very, very focused on creating experiences with people that I love as a way to create
memorable moments of the year. Because I think that really is what we grow old with is the
memories. But the memories alone are not enough is the memories with people and the more that kind
of the richer. So I wanted to experiment with the concept of, you know, let's create a friend summit.
Let's bring 30 super interesting friends. The uniqueness of it is everybody's been curated by
me. Everybody there was a friend. So I think immediately everybody showed up with like, okay,
if they're Rick's friends, I'm going to be open-minded. I'm not there kind of doing like, what do
you do? Who do you are? Is more around how do you know Rick and then what is interesting about each
other. And then, you know, we had a lot of the same participants speak and, you know, that we curated
the that we don't over-orchestrated, but we curated the agenda. And then we had all sorts of things
around food and magician and all this other stuff. And the greatest thing happened, which is one of
the things that I love most is when my good friends become great friends. And I know for a fact,
because I was with Rick Hendrick a week ago and we spent 15 minutes talking about you, about Matt
Walker, about other people that you guys all have become friends. And what greater currency in life
than, you know, spreading love through friendship. And it was a huge home run because everybody there,
even those who came as a gift to me, I think left with the gift of new friends. And at our age,
it's not easy to make good new friends. And it is something that we can do by leveraging our
own friendships. And you've been good to me in this regard. I asked you when I heard, you know,
your interview with Matt, I say, hey, would you introduce me? And we had, we become dear, dear
friends. Like I talk to him all the time. So I don't know, it's all around this currency that
friendships really matter in life, memories, you know, memorable moments really matter. And how do
you bring all that together? Yeah, no, I was surprised by the number of guys I walked away
from that meeting with who I couldn't wait to see again. And, you know, it's like, hey, look,
when I'm in LA, I'll give you a call when you're in Austin. You give me a call. What, what did you
learn that, that during that summit, because there were, you know, there was some structure to it as
well, where there were folks that, you know, it was kind of like a bunch of fireside chats, effectively.
Did anything surprise you? Did you learn anything?
I learned don't schedule something like that right after a vacation, because I spent my whole
vacation thinking about, because I, in essence, kind of interview most people, including you.
So that was a lesson, which is, you know, create some gap between something in your relaxing time.
I learned that, you know, I think all of us, no matter what, need moments like that, were
no matter who you are to the outside world, you are, you know, you're the one and the same in that
group. So, you know, there were professional athletes, there were governors, there were CEOs,
there were, you know, true people, like, are exceptional in their field like you, but everybody
there was the same. So I think that this knows, this essence of like, you know, the guard can be
down from everybody. And never be, I got to like hang out with 30 of my best friends and give lots
of hugs and catch up and have moments and create memories. And, you know, relationships take a lot
of effort. And that was a really efficient way to like, make huge deposits into a bunch of important
accounts. I'm blanking on his name, but he was the older gentleman on the very last day that spoke.
Yeah. Walter Green. No, no, no, no, I remember Walter. Marshall Rush. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Walter was amazing in his own right. And actually, Walter's someone I want to have on the podcast.
You should. Yeah. So, so we know it's really funny. We used to be neighbors in San Diego and
didn't even know it. Oh my goodness. Lived in the same neighborhood, like lived a mile from each
other. I love Walter Green. You know, Walter mentors, I don't know, a hundred people like us
and we're all better because of it. Yeah. So, so that's, that's someone on our, on our, on our hit
list for, for podcast guests. But yeah. So Marshall, who's like, I don't know, I guess 200
years old. 99 actually. Yeah. And I think from Marshall came one of the most interesting lessons
that you drew out and it's a lesson about looking forward versus looking backward and how that ties
to age. Do you want to, do you want to recount that story? Yeah. So I've known Marshall about 20 years.
I've had, I don't know, a hundred lunches with Marshall. And so when I met him, he was probably
81, 82, and he was still driving and he'll come in and, and there was something about Marshall.
There is something about Marshall that is incredibly appealing and attractive. And is that
every time you see him once a month, every other month, he has a list of things that he has learned
that he wants to talk about. He has ideas about things he wants to do. He's constantly evolving
and thinking. And what I've learned from Marshall is that your age really can be told by what you
think about aging of our spirit, not of our bodies, not of our mind, but of our spirit.
It's really about which mirror you're using. Are you using the rear view mirror or the windshield?
And he is like, you know, I told a story there, right, where he's like completely worried about
one of his kids and really thinking about giving them a tough lesson because it is time. And,
you know, he's asking for my opinion. I said, Mark, I said, Marshall, how old is your son? And he goes,
72. So it was a point of like, you know, he never stopped thinking in doing that. And that's how he
leaves. Listen, he turns 100 in February and we're going to do something super special, I hope.
The other story I like about him was I think when he was 96, he came to you with a with a
pretty serious business idea. And it was really predicated on trends over the next 10 years.
Correct.
And it was like, look, today, this isn't necessarily an enormous opportunity, but
here's all the data for why 10 years from now, this is a home run. We need to act now and make
sure we build this business. And you're sort of thinking, you're 96 years old. Why are you
thinking about a business opportunity that's going to, you know, mushroom in the next 10 years?
You know, and he was a senator for North Carolina for 26 years. There's a highway name after him.
His uniqueness, he's Jewish, but he made all his money selling Christmas ornaments,
like all the things that are so unique about him. And he's incredibly close to his kids and
his grandkids. And, you know, he sees the world so clearly, even when you talk about current events
and politics today, he has a wisdom about, you know, he literally played basketball at Duke in
1939, I believe. Right. And, you know, he went to World War II, like this guy and all of that,
you know, and he's had tremendous hardships. He lost his wife. He's lost some kids. And, you know,
he's the dignity by which he handles it is just distilled in a wisdom of life that I find super
attractive. I really think, and again, this is one of those, there's like the soft science and
there's the hard science, you know, I spent most of my life thinking about the hard science of
living longer, the things that we can measure, the metrics we can measure, the biomarkers we can
measure, how we can predicate our assumptions of risk based on X, Y, and Z. But there's simply no
question that there are these soft metrics that we can't quantify, but they must matter. And I look
at my dad as an example of this. So my dad, who is 85 years old, not the healthiest guy in the world,
but he has outlived everybody in his completely unhealthy family by more than two decades. And
this is a guy who came from a family where there were, you know, nine kids, one died as a child,
the other seven have all died. Again, nobody came close to his longevity. And to be clear,
he's not remotely a beacon of health. Like, even as your dad, huh? No, no, no. I wouldn't listen to
a thing I've said if my life depended on it, nevermind the fact that his life depends on it.
And look, he probably doesn't have that many years left on this planet. But I deep down believe that
his relatively modest longevity, again, relative to what I think his genetic capacity comes down to
exactly this phenomenon, is everything he never is looking back. He is planning, he is planning,
he's got an idea. I mean, you know, when he should have been retiring, he was
you know, he bought quarries, he bought like swaths of undeveloped limestone land, you know,
in his sixties with the idea that this is going to be, you know, there will be a demand for high
quality limestone dolomite and granite in the next 30 years. And that's what he's out there in
a quarry every day, barely able to walk because his knees are so, you know, messed up. And I'm
convinced to my greatest sadness that one day he's going to fall on these rocks and smash his
head or something. But it's like the idea of just sitting around couldn't possibly occur to him,
let alone, you know, relaxing. Now, again, we could talk about whether I think there's some,
maybe one should enjoy life a little bit more. But for him, I think enjoyment is building and
is thinking about opportunity like, well, you know, there's this niche for this market of
limestone that nobody has really appreciated the value of, and that's where he's going to
pour himself into. And that reminded me of that story with Marshall.
Yeah. And I have, I've studied a lot of people that are finishing life well,
seventies and eighties, because I think we're all pretty predictable. We just got to find patterns
that we relate to that relate to us. And I have lots of friends like, you know, Henry Kravis
is a very, very good friend. Henry's in his, you know, mid to late seventies. And you know what,
he is a complete stud. And I'm sure he's changed and evolved a lot as, you know, as one of the great
leaders in Wall Street. But he is, you sit down with him and he has more energy and more passion
and he's thinking more about the future. And I think there's something to be said by staying
in the arena. You know, even if you downshift, I think there's something to be said to,
you know, your brain stays connected, you stay relevant, you don't feel old because you don't
feel irrelevant. Have you read Arthur Brooks's book, From Strength to Strength?
I've read experts and experts. I listened to your podcast. I talked to him. Okay.
I don't know him as well as you do, but we know each other. But, you know, I think a lot of what
he says is it's around this and this crystallized intelligence that he talks about. I think it's
interesting because I am definitely, I lack about 30 points of IQ vis-a-vis the two of you.
Like literally I listened to the podcast and I'm like, all right, I had to pause and go look at
some stuff in the dictionary. But I wonder if the, you know, to me, the crystallized intelligence
is more to me of the evolution of our brain and the aging of our brain, but a way that we stay
productive for the tribe, for the society, more than a elevation of. It is an evolutionary of.
But that notwithstanding, I thought your podcast with him was tremendous.
Thank you. I really enjoyed speaking with Arthur. I enjoyed his book. I read it twice. And I really,
it hit home a lot because even though, you know, I'm not yet 50, there's simply no question. I don't
have the horsepower I had when I was 20. I mean, it's, or 25, like where I feel like I was really
at my cerebral peak. And I think, you know, as he talked about and wrote about the transition
from fluid to crystallize intelligence, it really gave me some comfort in accepting this transition.
So that to your point and why I brought this up is, yeah, I think it is important to stay on the
field, but I also think it's important to understand that it's okay to move to a different position.
Well said. Well said. And I think that replacing this notion of like, I don't have the horsepower,
is redefining what that horsepower is. And that gives us continued feeling of growth. I think the
importance of life is really not necessarily the looking forward is constantly growing.
I think the day that you stop growing is the day you age.
Yeah. Yeah. I agree with that completely. And, you know, this kind of brings it back to what we
talked about a minute ago, which is, I mean, I am sad when I think about my kids not being little,
and I'm not sure what that's about. But, you know, we talked about it very briefly at dinner yesterday,
because you got to see both my boys in complete action, which we're not shy about, right? Like,
we don't make any apology for the fact that they are high energy and we totally love it.
You were so physical. I really was so reminded me of my relationship, but I also felt your joy
and love. But what Jill and I often say to each other, and this is it, you have to say this in
the bad times. So yesterday they were well behaved, but, you know, there's equal number of times when,
I mean, you'd think that they're psychotic. I mean, you can't believe how poorly they behave,
you know, like, literally, Jill will kill me for even telling this publicly. Like the other day,
she walked by the youngest one and out of nowhere, he just took his pencil and stabbed her in the butt.
Unprovoked. It's not like she said, go to your room. So it's like, but in those moments I say,
I know it can be really hard. I will be, I would, if I could freeze time, I would, which is a totally
irrational thing to say. Why do you think that is? Why did you feel that way when you and your
kids were at this stage, which is you are their world. You're still daddy, not dad.
I think this is an amazing stage and I feel fortunate to be going through it a little later
in life when I think I can appreciate it. I think had I been presented with this 20 years earlier,
I wouldn't have had the maturity to embrace it as much maybe. No, I think that's right. You may not
have the same energy you would have had, but you have plenty. And especially, you know, and I think
that's straight up that we have when we have kids younger or older. You know, I think the great thing
about having kids is we get to kind of almost relive life. And I think there's something very
subconscious about, you know, rediscovering things or seeing things through their eyes
that brings the child back in us. You know, I think that child is a safe place in all of our
kind of personas. I also think that there's this notion of this is how we are relevant in the world.
This is how we are going to stay here when we're no longer here is through them.
Because a lot of us will live through them. And that's why we are so committed to it. I just
think that it's and it's such a powerful job to have and responsibility that is heightened in
every sense and the good and the bad. And the reality is that, you know, all the things that
they're doing are just normally growth moments of, you know, their own brain development and all that
good stuff. And, you know, we talked a lot about it the last time in the podcast, but, you know,
and I think we weigh over parents.
Eric, the youngest is he's just obsessed with math right now. You know, he's five. He's starting
to learn how to add. And the other day we were sitting there and he he's he's sitting with me on
the couch. Reese is who's three years older is sitting at his desk doing some coloring. And he
goes, you know, when I'm 100, Reese is going to be 103. And then he looks at me and he goes,
how old are you going to be? Wait, 70? Then I go, no, I wish, buddy, I'm going to be long dead when
you're 100. But if I were alive, I'd be, you know, 140, whatever. But it's just first of all, that's
an amazing thought to me, because I do think that kids today will quite easily be 100 years old.
Right. Like I don't, you know, today to be 100 to make it to 100 right now is a pretty remarkable
feat. You know, centenarians are exceedingly rare, about 0.004 percent of the population.
I tend to think that kids that are born now will reach that level at a far greater frequency.
And so it was a bit of a sobering thought. Right. It's like I'm looking at this little chubby,
cute kid that I can't stop wanting to squeeze and hug and kiss and realizing he's going to be a
hundred year old man one day and I'll be probably long gone. It's all of that stuff is sobering.
I guess it brings me to the to the idea of how do you I mean, you strike me as a person for whom a
lot of purpose came from your kids. Yeah. And so as your kids are older, do you feel less of that?
And has that caused you to put more of your sense of purpose into something we'll talk about later,
like philanthropy, which is also very important to you? I know I actually I'm very challenged by
this notion of how do I help evolve our relationship into more of a coaching relationship
in a way that, you know, I can be still their father, but also be a sounding board amongst,
you know, many others. And this morning I had a conversation with my son, a lot around something
he's dealing with. And I said, I'm going to talk to you as if you were a mentee of mine. And I gave
him what I thought as an advice. I said, you got to do whatever you want, but I want you to know
that I am a resource for you. And then you're not alone in solving these problems. And just like you
have other people. And I've really enjoyed kind of this this morphing of the relationship. It's early
for us. So I don't I, but by the way, I think that's why people enjoy grandkids so much. It's not that
I can give them back when all that. Yeah, yeah, that kind of really matters. It's a chance to
almost do it again. Right. And do it again with lower expectations of like, oh, is it reflecting
on me as a parent or is it all this stuff is just, you know, we have this innate desire
to perpetuate ourselves and we do that through our kids. Yeah, you've probably heard me talk about
the centenary in Decathlon. And for me, one of the greatest motivations personally, and I do
find that for many of my patients, because we talk about this in such detail,
I think it's true for them also is what they want to be able to do with offspring and more
importantly, the children of their offspring. And you've probably seen me do this, but we do an
exercise where you kind of build a timeline. So you'll, you know, you put your age down and, you
know, you're you're these are your kids. And then you start to estimate the bracket, you know,
my kids will likely have kids when they are this age, this age, this age, I will therefore be this
age. And you don't need to spend too long doing this to come to the realization that the things
that you want to be able to enjoy doing with your grandkids will will range from kind of the really
extravagant, like I want to take them on the greatest vacation. We're going to go to Egypt and
we're going to scale, you know, the great pyramids and go down the Nile. Okay, well, that's great.
Alternatively, it's going to be the really mundane. Like I want to be able to play catch.
You know, it's interesting. I wanted to share with you a story that I haven't sure yet,
which is, you know, in the end, the after the plane crash couple of weeks later, I was watching
my daughter perform in kindergarten. It was a really important moment of the realization of like,
for now, this is my most important purpose, which is to really kind of help my kids become adults.
And it came full circle without me knowing it. I was at her graduation from high school.
She's a sophomore now in college and they're coming down and it was outside because of COVID.
And they're coming down this kind of hallway in the same emotion that had not happened for,
I don't know, 11 years happened. I started bowling uncontrollably as I saw her. I didn't expect it.
It came out of nowhere. I'm not a crier. I'm not afraid to cry, but I'm not walking around.
And it was a realization that I had lived to the moment where she had become her own person.
And the graduation from high school was a lot more meaningful than just the graduation,
at least in my experience. It was a realization that she can fly on her own now. And it was
a moment. It was a moment for me and that realization, but then also realizing that,
I now have more capacity to broaden purpose. I think we're all seeking purpose. So it's not like
you finish it. It's just you evolve it. And I was very grateful to have had that experience because
seldomly in life do you get to see the end of the circle come back. It's usually a line that goes
somewhere or nowhere. So when we last spoke, I think you talked a little bit about
any follow up or interactions you've had with either the crew from that flight or
Captain Sullenberger himself. What's the latest on that? I imagine that that's it. I don't remember
how many people were on that flight, 150 plus the crew, 158. So there's 158 of you that
I'm sure some people have passed away due to natural causes since, but that's a very tight-knit
group. I'm guessing. Do you all collectively celebrate that anniversary together?
Yeah, there's always something and there's Facebook groups and all that stuff. I've been more on the
fringe. I've participated in a couple of things. It's just time for me. And I got a lot of what I
needed, especially at the time from my closest friends and family. But you asked me at the last
podcast because we were presenting him that award at the points guy event that I had,
I had, you know, have I seen him enough and why not? And I told you that I was planning to do
something. Well, it is happening. And I don't know if you know this, but the plane itself, which
it's worth seeing because it is banged up like a plane will be banged up if it hit a wall at 150
some miles an hour. So it really is not the plane. It's just a shell of the plane sits in Charlotte.
And for a bunch of different reasons, the all hangar and museum, we lost all the facilities.
So the airport, they were going to move the plane to Dallas because it ended up in Charlotte because
that's where US air was based on. So just by total coincidence in your backyard.
And then there was a lot of risk that we were going to lose. And there's a bunch of other planes
there, but that's the anchor plane. So a number of us rally in the community. Is that normal,
by the way, after a plane wreck that I would have guessed that they normally scrapped planes.
I think this one because they wanted to keep because of the significance.
Right. And so a group of people in Charlotte rally and I made a donation with, you know, asking for
the naming rights. So the thing that I'm going to do to honor Sully and the crew and perpetuate,
you know, kind of this notion I was doing my job, remember that statement, is we're going to name
the museum after him and the museum will be in Charlotte in Charlotte. So we the Sullenberger
Aviation Museum of the Carolinas or something like that, but it will be his name. And I called him
to ask for his permission. And he was interesting, hesitant at first. And then he called me back and
you know, said, OK, let's do it. And the the naming and all of that will happen in January.
So we'll be a big 14th anniversary. Yeah. And it'll be a beautiful day. But, you know, I just
I wanted to find something that, you know, will outlast both of us as a way to
honor his commitment to doing his craft and to saving our lives.
Yeah, it's by this point in the podcast, I think most people, if they haven't familiarized
yourself themselves with this story, should probably go back and listen to that. That section
of our podcast is the way I think you you tell that story. It's probably the longest version
you've told of it, because obviously you have a TED talk where you go through it in
in some detail, which is really moving. But I think also just the
you know, I'm still. So remember how I said from our first meeting, there are a couple of things
that stand out. The other thing that really stands out from our first podcast, which is something you
sort of said in almost passing. Do you know what I'm about to say? No, because I've shared this
with you. But it's when the plane is coming down and you're going once you realize there's about
10 seconds until you're going to die. You said a couple of things. One, it's very calm. Like it's
you weren't scared. You were sad. You're very sad. And you put your hand on your leg or on your other
hand on your arm and said, I love you. That's the last thing you said yourself before you would have
died. Close my eyes. Yeah. And I was and I just couldn't believe that. I was like, that's the last
thing I'd ever think to say. What would you have said? I don't know that I probably would have said
nothing. I probably would have just been very sad and and and yeah, I don't think there would have
been any gratitude or anything like that in me. Have you have you actually asked any of the other
people on the flight what they did said thought in the last 10 seconds? No, but I have and and
and I will because I think it would be interesting. I would mean there's a whole book there. Yeah. Like
that is for sure. And remember that we had no suffering. I imagine if you're dying, you know,
in some level of distress, it's a different, you know, your mind is in a very different place.
But that's what makes this such an interesting quote unquote control experiment is yeah, you weren't
on fire. And it's 90 seconds. So it's not all it's not it's not it's not a lot of people have near
death experience. It lasts a second or two seconds. Right. But I've reflected a lot, Peter, on kind of
the the TED talk was, you know, a moment in time and it was all around, OK, here's kind of the three
regrets I felt as as the plane was coming down. And we talked a lot about them in the other podcast
but, you know, we should revisit them, by the way, just so that folks can see it all in one place.
So it was this notion that everything changes in an instant. So time really, really matters.
It was this notion that relationships are the core of the richness of life. But yet we spent a lot
of time with our ego, you know, kind of leading the charge. And then this notion with around my kids,
which is I wasn't living true to kind of what I, you know, discover was my true purpose at the time
or my main main purpose, which is seeing my kids. And it was the regret that I felt at the time of my
look like death to have missed it, to have not being clear that that really was the I don't know,
the map or the or the or the you know, the key to living a better life.
You know, as I reflected all of that, what's interesting is nothing has really changed,
but it's not around regrets. You know, I think more. Yeah. So, you know, for example,
I think instead of it being around everything changes in an instant. So, you know, living the
moment, it is that but it's wrapped around around a notion of having true intentionality
about how we live our life and true intentionality about how we live a lot of life is a really big,
deep bucket that I've spent lots and lots of time thinking about. It has a lot to do with time.
Right. And the reality with time and I've heard this and I love it is like the problem with time
is the same problem that we have most things that are free. We don't value it.
Right. If we like how to get up and like really spend real money on time,
I bet you we will behave differently. Right. And the problem with time is, as we have learned about
sleep, is you have to do a lot of things to extend your time, some so that you're more productive
the next day, like sleep and some like nutrition and exercise so that you have more time. Right.
So a lot of what you are really trying to do is, you know, convince people that there are things
they can do to have more quality and meaningful time. But it is a lot more than that. You know,
to me, to live with intentionality is around kind of combining a lot of things into where we spend
our energy and what the things that we stop doing and how do we kind of reverse things that we don't
want to do. So I really think that this notion of having complete intention is really a decor of
living a more rich life. So I feel my life to be very rich because I do I have like, for example,
I have two hundred and forty two weeks left until I turn 60. And, you know, I have all this little
exercises where I'll say, OK, you know, what are my big intentions this week? Because, you know,
at 60, I'm in a different energy level. I'm probably paying a bunch of physical debts back.
Like there's a lot that will come back. And, you know, and I live in chunks of my life with just
great intention. It is because of that, because I realize that everything really is, you know,
fleeting, but it's not just around time and time only. And that manifests itself in the second one,
when you talk about when I will you talked about relationships. What I realize is that, you know,
a little bit of the event that we were talking about. I. I want to continue to meet new people
that I can learn from. I am addicted to learning and growth. And the best way to do that is through
other people. So the amount of energy I put into friendships, because it's not relationships. You
know, the good news is when you're in business, you have a lot of deal friends. The key is how do
you convert them into real friends? Who do you want to convert into real friends? And to be a real
friend, talk about a skill to be learned. Like talk about it being a never ending journey. And then
how do you approach that? So I'm really, really, I have an enormous amount of great friends more than
most because I spent the bulk of my time on that. Now, if you go back to time, there's only three
things you can do with it. You can waste it, which a lot of teenagers do. You can use it in things
that are, you know, value, and then you can invest it. There's nothing else you can do with time.
So the ratio of what you do with those three components has a lot to do with it. So guys,
like you and I, at least we don't waste a lot of time. The question is, how much are you using it
for things that gives you pleasure or things that you want to do and how much are you investing?
And that will ultimately continue to pay dividends in life. So like, if you look at your time, you'll
know how much of that it is. And if you're using too much in something, at some point becomes
wasteful, if you may. So relationships are super rich. And then the last thing is, you know,
this notion of purpose is how do you kind of expand it? So I spent a lot of time trying to
continue to evolve the gift and not look at it as a moment in time, but as a some level of a map
into the future and as I continue to age. What do you think the next decade holds for you in terms
of Red Ventures? So maybe give us a bit of an update on, well, maybe again, remind people what
Red Ventures is because it's not an easy thing to explain. It's not like we make a widget.
No, you know, it's funny because I explained it in the last podcast three years ago differently
that I'm going to explain it now. It really is basically a private equity platform of companies
that we control. So instead of investing as a passive investor, we control a bunch of companies.
And we have about 17 companies. But, you know, those companies, the fact is we don't own 100%
of them, but we control all of them. And they're all over the place. They're in Europe, in Brazil,
we're starting the first bank in Puerto Rico in 26 years. And then we own a bunch of brands in the US,
mostly digital brands. We own services companies. So it's just really a platform of kind of tech
and data and digital and a really, really strong culture and a purposeful place to work.
How many employees do you have now? We are up to 4,500 employees.
And when I came out to visit you for a business review circa 2014, 2015, how big were you then?
1200. 1200. Yeah. Beautiful campus. Thank you. It's still the same? It's still beautiful. It's
just people are not going in as often. The world has really changed. Our relationship with world,
with work has really changed. And for both, like anything in life, everything has pros and cons.
I think COVID did a lot of good for society. I think COVID realized that this fixed way that
we thought about our relationship with work didn't have to be, and that those rules got established
way early in the industrial age for control. And control is a false premise in every regard.
But at the same time, I'll tell you my reflection on this and what I worry about a little bit,
and I know a little bit of a different topic. But I think that one of the unique things about the US,
and you don't see this in a lot of other countries, having studied a lot of Latin American countries,
is that the decade between 20 and 30 is a decade of true apprenticeship. And that all these
companies and corporations and hospital systems, they're really training people into their second
third of life. So you spend the first decade of your life. Hopefully, if you're lucky, you have
good enough parents where you learn a lot, then school becomes a place you work, and then whatever
your profession is, that third decade of life is incredibly important. And that's where you really
built a lot of depth and learn on someone else's nickel and all this stuff. And I worry that we're
going to look back in 10 years in the US will have lost a sense of competitiveness, because a lot of
these people coming into the workforce are getting a fraction of the tutoring and coaching and
experiences and intuition that they would have had. And 30, 40 years from now, we will have lost
a lot of our edge because we stopped investing in the people and their creativity and their skill.
Meaning that's a downside of not being in an immersive culture.
At least for that segment of that age of the population. Now, I would argue that, I think
what we learned in COVID is flexibility is king, and we should celebrate and look for flexibility.
And we shouldn't be able to sacrifice raising kids if you're a working mother or working father,
to the sacrifices that we made, or we don't have to travel crazy like we were traveling. So a lot
of that is baked into changes in the rules of engagement. But this is all a moment in time.
If we go into a recession, some of these habits may return. I hope we never lose the flexibility
we gain. I don't love going to work every day at the same time and leaving at the end of the day.
I love having a lot more freedom. And I think most people do.
Do we know if, I mean, presumably there are certain jobs that work really well remotely versus not,
and there are presumably certain types of people who work really well remotely versus not.
I don't have, haven't spent much time sort of looking at any of this, but I imagine given
size of your company and the footprint of Red Ventures, do you have any insights into that?
I think there's two components to that. One is productivity, which is,
at least in some functions, fairly easy measured. And so we have lots of editors that write
real content. They are as productive or more. If they don't have to commute and do lots and lots
of things that are distracting in the office. There are some places in engineering where that
is also true. Maybe some of the places in the back-end engineering where you're not doing a lot
of collaboration. But by and large, and those people, net-net, you would argue that remote,
not hybrid, very different things, you know, net-net may be more positive. Now, the second side of that
equation, I think being alone or being in your home every day has a real tax on mental health.
I think we are, we're designed to be with others. And I don't think we know the real
value or tax on that. Now, a lot of the other jobs, hybrid in my opinion,
you're collaborating with people where you're learning experientially, where you're building
intuition. It's a healthier way to gain expertise on something.
Do you mean hybrid, like you come in sometimes and you work remote sometimes?
Yeah. And there's a lot of things we do during the week that you don't need to be in a place.
My hope is that ultimately work evolves into what are the things that require people to be together
versus what are not. And then depending on where you are in your career and your, you know,
your proficiency, you have even more flexibility.
How long do you think you'll be doing Red Ventures as your quote unquote day job versus
working on some of the many things that seemingly are of just as much interest to you,
but are more on the nonprofit side?
You know, I feel super healthy in great part. Thanks to you. I literally, I feel like I've
at least slowed down a lot of the aging and I'm really grateful. So as long as I feel healthy,
I love this perch. I don't, back to the Marshall conversation, I don't intend to, you know, I never
want to replace happy with happier in anything in life. And I'm happy as can be, you know, and,
you know, and, you know, would it continue to evolve? Yes. Would it continue to, you know,
change? And, you know, the one of the big ahas in COVID, you know, COVID to me was unique in so many
ways. When I got to do something for a second time, which we usually don't do in life, when something
kind of goes away, goes away, the fact that we got our kids home for like a year and a half,
it was, it was, it was wonderful. But, you know, I think the,
the, the, for me, Red Ventures will continue to evolve. But what will happen is a lot of our
companies will kind of gain independence. So instead of Red Ventures being one thing,
we will find the right outcomes and, you know, in marriages of a lot of our businesses with the
right partners and allow those people to become CEOs of their own businesses and will create
monetization and return for our investors. But our ability to stay private and stay independent
and stay away from all the other stuff that public companies have to deal with, it's non-negotiable.
So I see Red Ventures in a bizarre way, returning to its roots in the next 25 years to a much simpler
thing where most of our businesses will evolve out. We'll continue to buy businesses in the next
10 years. But my guess is when I turn 80, I'll have 15 people and we will be hoping to give all
our money away. Speaking of giving money away, you've reached a point where you've
recently signed the Giving Pledge. Yeah, about a year and a half ago.
So tell us a bit about that. I mean, I think people have heard of the Giving Pledge, but what,
what does it mean and what type of people can sign it and what are the implications of it?
You know, it was, it was not something that we did without a lot of trepidation. You know, we had,
it's something that really Bill and Melinda Gates and Warren Buffett started. And it was
around creating consciousness of the people that have had more luck than others in creating real
wealth to create a commitment and responsibility that you will give at least 50% of that wealth
back. That's what the pledge is about. And that's, that's during your lifetime as well, correct?
Yeah. Or, or when you die, it doesn't matter. But you are committing, that's, that's the pledge you
sign. And there's hundreds of people that have signed it all over the world. So it's a bit of
a community too, where you learn how to give it in ways that reflect what you want to do and all
of that. So there's real value to being part of the community. When we first, you know, met and we,
we had, we had the privilege of having dinner in Omaha with Warren Buffett and they were trying to
convince people at the time, our kids were still in high school and we didn't want this burn because
it does create negative energy around it. And there, you know, it gives a lot of people.
Meaning because it makes public the amount of wealth that you have.
Yeah, it is a threshold, which at the time we were, we were a private company, so no one had
known, but when the New York Times wrote an article and all this stuff, it kind of became public what
it was, but it's just more, I wanted to shelter them from anything that negative that may come
out of that. And it's just not, it's just, we're too young. So we waited until they went to college.
So when they went to college, they called back and said, Hey, you said when your kids work out of
college, you do it. And so we, when we did, and we're grateful we did, but you know, we, we plan,
we were planning to do this anyway. And we do it more as a, you know, as a, as a pledge that
hopefully others realize that this only works if it works for everybody. It doesn't work if it works
only for a few and, you know, putting it back into the system in the core, that's what you're hoping
to do. Did you ever hear the podcast I did with John Arnold? I did not. Okay. So definitely one
you'll want to listen to. So John and Laura Arnold, who've also signed the giving pledge
are probably two of the most deliberate philanthropists I've ever met. John was,
I think you could say hands down the most successful energy trader in the history of energy
trading. And he, he was a, he was a trader at Enron right out of college and became their most
successful trader. In fact, I, if I'm not mistaken, I think his personal book of business was
generating a billion dollars a year for Enron, just his own personal trades. When Enron imploded,
you know, he was handed a severance check of something like $5 million and he took every
penny of it, put it into his fund and went on a 10 year tear of unparalleled returns, something
like 30% per month, per month. Okay. So, you know, at the time that John shut his fund down,
which I think was 2011 or 2012 before the age of 40, he basically completely turned himself to what
he's been doing for the last 10 years, which is just philanthropy, but doing it with a level of
rigor and analytics that, in other words, he's done something that I think is really interesting
and highlights something really hard, which is it's actually not that easy to give away billions
of dollars. I mean, if you want to do it intelligently, I mean, you can obviously
give money to entities that, you know, build buildings, you know, build a hospital. Those
things are, those things are great. But, you know, when you look at the sort of projects that John is
interested in, it takes time. And I think John and his wife correctly came to the realization
that they can't wait until they're, you know, 65 to start doing this. They will run out of time
because they have too much money. How do you think about that balance? Because I know there are things
that you are really committed to. Maybe we can talk about some of those things. The two that jump
to mind, of course, are the children, you know, sort of, I forget the exact name for undocumented
kids who are born here, not born here, but brought here, young, educated here, and then can't work.
And then, of course, a lot of disaster relief in Puerto Rico, but also just infrastructure and
building up there. So let's talk a bit about these things. So first, I really think that only
governments have the muscle to really solve problems. And I think even people with the wealth
of Bill and Melinda Gates have come to a lot of that conclusion. You can attack singular problems
and maybe, you know, eradicate a disease or something like that. If you have billions and
billions of dollars, but through systemic issues, I think the role of any, you know, non-profit is
to gain momentum, to create a roadmap, to create the case for governments to really put real funding
behind things or create the systemic changes to change it. So I don't think that the illusion of
like, we're going to fix a real issue. To me, this is more around. But there is something you,
or when I say you, I don't just mean you personally, but I mean, there is something
that the philanthropist can do that the government won't do, which is you can take a risk financially
that a government can't do. You can demonstrate a proof of principle that, as you said, then becomes
a template or roadmap for a policymaker to say, well, here's a pilot study that was done that
demonstrated X, Y, and Z. This was very high risk. We never would have done it, but oh my God, look
what we learned. This is now something that could be replicated at scale and you bring in. So in other
words, the private, the philanthropist can effectively function as the angel investor or
the early stage VC and the government comes in as the PE investor. Yeah. And in that regard, I think
bringing an entrepreneurial spirit and putting real kind of business savviness behind it is
really important. So I do believe that, but I love the, I think it was Jeff Bezos a long time ago.
He said something around, you know, in philanthropy, you're not really necessarily
looking for the perfect business plan. You know, if you're helping somebody, you're doing good.
And then that's a little of my approach, like do things that are good for the world and good,
and it's good for one person, then you're doing something and trying to do it in scale and with
purpose and all of that. As it relates to what we're doing, Peter, it's, you know, it keeps evolving.
You know, we've now, we're really focused on this, you know, 16 to 24. That's our concentration on
people that are under-resourced and it is more than undocumented kids, although we just close
our applications again. And these kids are still in limbo, meaning, you know, there's still, there's
no path to anything. They just have this basically a permit that gets renewed, but no one can get the
permit anymore. So every year, about 80,000 kids are graduating high school that, you know, have
no ability to get a work permit. It's just insane. It is insane. So just so people understand, these
are kids that came here undocumented. So they're born in another country. They've come here.
They've grown up here though. They've gone to high school here. They could go to college,
but they wouldn't get financial aid because of course they're not residents. So tell me what
actually happens. What, how many of them say I have to go back to the country I was born in versus
I'm going to get in college and somehow take a bunch of debt without any financial aid? Like,
my guess is that 95% of them end up taking minimum wage shops or kind of
you know, jobs that are, you know, underground and stuff like that. Like where, where, where,
where, because you really, you know, now there was a process there where you can get a DACA permit
and there's, there's 650,000 of these kids that have DACA permits. So you can, you can work.
Unfortunately about that, you know, in the last administration, DACA got rescinded. So there's no
new DACA. So if you're a high school student and you're 17, you know, you can't get a work permit.
So at that point you were, you grew up here, your family's now here going back to your original
country, country at origin may happen, but it's really, really hard. You have no roots there.
You have no resources. You may not even know the language for that matter. Right. So I think that
that's the, that's the craziness of this. We, we're, what's the distribution of where these kids
are from? Do we have a sense? Probably 90% Latin America, probably two thirds of those Mexico,
just because of how they're, I mean illegally, but, but you see them a lot from Southeast Asia.
And other places we just, our, our yearly scholarship grant, we just got 1200 applicants,
literally close last week. I believe over 300 of them have close to a 4.0.
You're providing scholarships for these kids to go to college because they don't need to be
residents to go to college. They just need the funding.
The funding. Yeah. So you don't get in, you don't get federal financial aid and about half the
states don't get you in state tuition. So it's almost like you would have to go to school as a,
you know, to a private school and pay 60, 70 grand a year.
And is the investment you're making, Rick, that if these kids crush it in college,
they're going to get an H-1B visa on the back end, or they're going to, they're going to land in
some legitimate dual intent visa with a path to citizenship based on their education.
Well, until three years ago, because the world DACA, they had a path to getting jobs. And there's
many now that have jobs, right? We, we put, we have 520 kids in the program, about half of them
are graduating, but we keep thinking this is the last year. This is the last year because Congress,
Congress just needs to pass a law, right? And, you know, they, there's plenty of reasons why it
hasn't happened. But now the kids that are going to start graduating next year, they're literally
in limbo because they can't get a work permit. So the H-1B visa and all of that can't do it.
You can figure out a way to marry and then take that route. You can look for asylum, but those
are all really, really hard paths. I didn't realize that. So you're telling me that if a
kid goes through a scholarship, oh, because they're not doing it on an F1.
They're not DACA, right? DACA was, yeah, that, that expires. That's the argument now is like,
not only do you have the DACA kids in limbo, but now you're like, you know, this 80,000 kids every
year that we're, and the crazy thing is we invest in them in primary school and secondary school.
We don't ask the question when they go to our school systems, but then, you know, we invest all
that money. Why don't we make them taxpayers? You know, we have an issue. There's like this massive
decline of kids applying to college. We have all this college infrastructure with not enough
students today. Why not educate them and make them pay taxes and give them a path, whatever that is,
to citizenship. So to me, this is one of those things that makes absolutely no sense. But to,
what we did is we expanded that to, you know, after the George Floyd event, we, we as a company
kind of rally around, we have to find opportunities into our inner cities and have used a lot of the
same platform to broaden it. It's called Road to Hire, where Golden Door Scholars is a part of it.
But here's something really cool. We, we start teaching coding in North Carolina, mostly Black
and Brown students, mostly from Title I schools. We're going to the high schools and start teaching
there. And then we do an apprenticeship program and then we partner up with all the corporations
in Charlotte. We are graduating more Black and Brown kids with computer science expertise than
the whole North Carolina system is now. This year, we have over 220 of these kids graduating and they
all have jobs on the other end. So we give them an apprenticeship and then we have a whole of the
Sorry, these are high school or college? No, these are, these are, they're not going to,
these are kids that are 22, 23, 24, mostly Black and Brown kids that we're teaching them how to
code. We pay them to teach. So they're high school grads that didn't go to college. We give them a two
year apprenticeship where we're paying them on behalf of all this corporation. It's working
tremendously. Here's the crazy thing. This 21 year old kid who was driving over after two years of
the apprenticeship, they are as competent in technology as someone who graduated from NC State.
Now, how do you think that can be scaled? What do you think is the magic in that? That, because
to your, this is a great example of what we said earlier, you can't solve that problem across the
country, but can you provide a roadmap for that? Well, there's like, you start with the jobs,
like, and at the end of the day, there's hundreds and hundreds of thousands of jobs that are
unfilled because they don't have the skills. So pick this, by the way, it's the same thing with
high school teachers today. There's a shortage of like, I believe is 350,000 teaching, you know,
vacancies that is projected to be, but we get, we pay 42,000 in most States and you can't, it's crazy,
right? But, but keep on technology where there's, there's a big gap. The reason our system, our
model works in Charlotte and North Carolina is because it rides on the rails of the system.
It literally partners with the county and with the city. It partners with the schools, with the
high school systems, all title one, it connects to the, to the public school. So like, there is a
lot here and then the corporations all basically offer a job on the other end. The key to this is
to start with the job and then train into the job versus start with education and hope they get a
job. So go fill the job that is not getting filled. And by the way, solve the diversity
challenge that all these corporations have, solve a lot of the other issues, but don't show up into
the, you know, into, into the nonprofit arm of a corporation, solve a problem that they really have.
And that's the connection. So I think it will have to happen more at the city level. So there's a big
initiative, call 110 that a number of like high profile CEOs have built to try to do this. It just
takes a long, long time. And my concern is when the economy turns, these are the kinds of things
that get scrapped. These are the kinds of things that people stop giving that job for or investing
in. Yet we go back to this, you know, negative spiral that we tend to have. Obviously you and I
both are kind of cut from the same cloth, which is that of immigrants. And I think with that comes
a little bit of disbelief as to why the U.S. would not as a country want to embrace an amazing asset.
Do you see this changing? Do you see this as just being a season?
I do. You know, I am super optimistic on our country, you know, and that, you know, for as
flawed as we are, I would rather be nowhere else. Yeah, I agree with that. And, you know, there's
just things, unfortunately, take time. You know, I'm reading a book called Brothers about, you know,
the Kennedys. And you realize that there were real serious issues there around, you know, the mob and
like all these things that, you know, we don't hear about today. So I do believe that the trend line
is up. It's just not linear and it's not fast enough. So, you know, I think we just have more
information, much of which, if not all of most of which is noise that distracts us a little bit.
So I think back in the 60s, there was no question it was a more tumultuous era. I mean,
there were political assassinations on U.S. soil, right? Like we don't have anything like that today.
But the noise today is unbearable. It's right. The never ending cycle of nonsense, news, cable,
social media, I think makes it feel more dramatic. But that could also be the undoing, right?
I mean, you know, and these are pendulums. I think we're at a pendulum right now where
the country is super divided. I am super, I believe that there will be a series of leaders
in our future that will bring us back together. We need a common enemy. And, you know, maybe it is
this risk of China that becomes our galvanizing thing. You know, I find it super interesting when
there's a real crisis in our country, 9-11 or even, you know, COVID at the beginning, like we all kind
of are behave like Americans. And then, you know, we need something that brings us back to being
Americans and not Republicans or Democrats or black or white and all that stuff. And the common
enemy tends to do that. And I think this, these peaceful times have allowed for a lot of room for
us to subdivide. So, Rick, let's pivot a little bit to talk about health, which is, you know,
you're a very health conscious guy. But there's also been some changes, I think, in your life
over the past, I don't know, I think I've known you now for nine years. Basketball used to be
kind of the only thing you did for exercise, which was great because it kept you running around a
court. But, you know, you can get be prone to injuries and things like that. How would you
describe overall kind of your mentality towards your health, your longevity? What changes have you
made? One of my favorites, which I'm sure you'll get to is your approach to your body weight,
which cracks me up. It is. You know, I've realized that I want to be here for as long as I can and
I want to be here in as, you know, active of a way as I can. So I really am committed to that,
you know, it's this notion of time, but it's time on the other way. So for the first time ever in
the last, you know, especially in the last four years, I've gotten into the gym and I have a
trainer and we go through it. I don't do the crazy stuff you do, but I would argue that I am so much
stronger from grip to balance to all the things. And, you know, I try my version of it because I
don't consider myself to be an elite kind of athlete in that regard, but I feel so much better.
I transitioned from basketball. So I play my last official pickup game about three months ago and
I had a bunch of pros come and it was great because it's been such a great language for me.
And so many relationships came through basketball, so much self learning and self awareness. And
I now picked up tennis and, you know, you know, now why did you do that? I mean, why,
why did you completely stop playing your favorite sport? Because I watch a lot of people my age,
just blowing Achilles and a knee and all of that. And you know what, those are all signals that we
should listen to. I didn't want to get to that place. And now the more I play, the more my knees
were sore and, you know, my body's talking to me. It actually talks to us all the time. And I wanted
to leave on my terms and I wanted to leave knowing that, you know, it served its purpose.
It doesn't control me. And I love, I picked up tennis in the pandemic and it's something that
we're doing more as a family, but I love the apprenticeship, the struggle. So I have a coach,
I go twice a week. It's a great workout. I get my high rate to 130 again to zone two. I stay there
for an hour. So I get a lot of, you know, multiple values and I'm really not good. And, you know,
footwork is different. Everything is different. And I love the grinding of, you know, things. And
it's a reminder of humility. Like, you know, everything that we now take for granted that
we think we're so good at, at some point was really, really hard. So I have now a list of things I
got, you know, it's embarrassing. I'm Puerto Rican. I don't know how to dance salsa. Like, I can't die
as the only Puerto Rican who can't die. But dance salsa. So I have a list. I want to, you know,
even last night you were grilling and I'm like, I used to grill a lot more. And so I have this
notion now that I want to keep learning things. I have a list of about eight or nine things.
And eventually if we end up living part of the years in another country, that language I want to
try to engage in. And it's just this notion that I don't want to get old, but I want to get, don't
want to get old, not by my age, but I don't want to get old by stuff. So I want to talk about that
last game of pickup basketball. How sad was that? Zero. Really? No, I'm grateful for what I had now
because it ended its life. You know, I don't, you know, it kind of leads to the biggest self growth
I've had since the plane was in that middle bucket of like relationships. And what I realized,
Peter, is that the most important relationship we have, the most important friend we have is ourselves.
And that unless we get that right, everything else will have a lot of friction. Everything else will
be a version of a worse version of what it can be. And what I've realized as I study this is that
we in society, and it's, I think it's almost every religion, I want to say almost all,
all because I don't know, but most religions that I know are anchoring some level of guilt.
And guilt as a way of teaching us or as keeping us connected to something. And I've realized that
guilt is the most useless emotion one can have. And I have spent the last five years just basically
getting rid of guilt to the point that I joke that it's a complex I no longer suffer from.
I still have others, but I feel no guilt. And when you feel no guilt, what you realize is that you
can change the dialogue that you have with yourself. I am super kind to myself. I constantly
make mistakes. I constantly do things and I'm like, Oh gosh, that wasn't right. Or I don't show up the
way I need to show up. But I have, I have, I have nothing but love for myself. I would say things,
yeah, that wasn't your best. Okay. What next? Help me understand that. So, so you, it's hard for me to
imagine you showing up as poorly as I can, but let's say you, you're in sort of a pissy mood.
You come home. You had asked your wife to do something earlier. It's not done. Instead of
saying, Hey, sweetie, did you, did you have a chance to do that thing I asked you to do before
you sort of snippet her? I don't know if you've ever done that. It happens. Okay. How do you,
cause it's, I think it's really easy to feel bad and feel shame for snapping at her. And then that
actually impairs your next interaction. So how, but how do you break that cycle?
I own it. I, because it just takes a little bit of time. It's like, I'm sorry. I just took out
something on you that it was not on you. That was unfair. I hope you forgive me.
How long does it take you to man up to that? It's not long, you know, maybe 20 minutes,
30 minutes, like, like, like, like you're very self-aware and you can read body language,
you know, like, you know, you can see that what you just said kind of cut through in a way. And
then you're like, huh, what did I do? But, but more importantly is I don't, I don't feel bad.
Like I don't, I don't carry this notion of like, Oh my goodness. I just did this. Even like,
even if I do something that I didn't want to do, I just said, okay, just part of being human is part
of growing up as part of learning as part of your humanity. But do you think that that can only
happen because you're able to immediately make amends? I think it's a habit. I think we, we,
we walk around. So how do you break that habit then? I mean, guilt is a pretty strong habit for
a number of people, I'm sure. Yeah. It's like any habit. It may be worse than smoking. Smoking is
hard. I never smoke, but it's a really habit. But if you want to break it, you break it, you know,
you're 98% of your thoughts are with yourself. So first of all, you got to be very aware of all
your thoughts and you got to be able to objectivize what you're hearing and you have to be able to
evaluate and say, you know what, is this productive? Is this helping me? Or am I doing this because
I've always done it or because this is how my parents kind of relate it to it. And I think the
more we move away from the emotion of guilt and become, it becomes self-love. It becomes, you know,
a notion like the safest place for us to be is with ourselves. And the kindest place to be is in
our own heads. And there's no judgment. There's no anything like life becomes so much simpler.
And then that that you give yourself, you can give to others. Because, you know, when we talk about
purpose, you know, we're very lucky that we can impact people through your platform. You're
impacting lots of us. And, you know, I'm lucky that in my platform, I can impact people. But you
impact people every day with little things. How you show up to the coffee shop in the morning,
the type of connection that you make, the taking time, like all of that is making an impact. And
the more that you feel a piece inside, the more you want to give it. So I am now addicted really
to like good energy. And that doesn't mean it's maybe 95% of the time, but oh, I love that place.
And I give it and I give it freely. And I give it with, you know, not expecting nothing in return.
And to me, this is like the happy place. I live in a happy place.
What do you think is the relationship between happiness and wealth? Do you think they're
uncoupled? Do you think they're correlated positively? Do you think they're correlated
negatively? I think we decide what they are. You know, I think, you know, some of the happiest
people in the world have no wealth. So they cannot be coupled. Now, wealth can give you a set of
conveniences that allows you to solve for whatever your priorities are that, you know,
might, may, may heighten your ability to do that. And therefore it gives you more happiness. Or,
like in many people, you pursue wealth your whole life, because that's what our society wants. And
when you get there, you just feel so empty and then you feel so guilty for all you sacrifice for it.
And you're in the worst place, which is you got what you wanted. And then it was a mirage and
it meant nothing. And there are so many people out there that feel like, oh my goodness,
I was running the wrong race. You know, we talk a lot in life, Peter, around the best way to
run a race. No one steps back and asks, am I running the right race? And I think really
focusing on, you know, reevaluating the race you're running. So when you ask me questions about,
you know, Red Ventures in 10, 20 years, I made it very clear after my, you know, my plane event
that I was going to run a different race than everybody else. I wasn't looking for,
you know, being public. I wasn't looking for being the wealthiest. I wasn't looking for,
my race was to enjoy the race and to enjoy the race. I am crazy. So I love growing. I love being
challenged. I love competing, but I, I give no power to anybody. And I tried really hard not to
take power away from anybody. What do you think are the ways that, that people even inadvertently
take power away from people? You know, we as leaders, you know, can, can overlead and not let
other people's have, you know, kind of the, the, let them be celebrated and not take all the, all
the credit for things. Or on the contrary, take responsibility for things that may not have been
truly your responsibility. So I think, I think leaders have an ability to really
manage the, the kind of the power equation with intentionality. I think how you treat somebody,
like I think we talked about this in the last conversation, but I think the best way we can
parent is by showing our kids how to treat strangers and how we, you know, give people
respect no matter who they are, what they're doing, and how do we not give anybody too much respect
just because society made them be something, you know, everybody puts their pants on the same way.
Everybody has insecurities. Everybody has issues. You know, when you look at people as like, you
know, we all are in this like imperfect journey with imperfections, it just makes it really kind
of level field and, and, and simpler. One of the really enjoyable, I mean, there were so many, but
certainly one of the enjoyable highlights of the Friends Summit was when Simon Sinek got up and
talked about Finite versus Infinite Games, which of course is the name of the book. Maybe for folks
that aren't familiar with that, I know it's a book that you love as well. How do you implement
that ethos into both your business and your, your life? You know, when Simon sent me an early
book and said, Hey, what do you think? It was almost like he was writing what it was in my brain.
I just don't have an ability to write a book, but he wrote a book. I'm like, and he, he actually was
rewriting a book by somebody that had come before, right? He had put it in more modern terms. And it
became kind of codifying a language that I really believe in. And that the core of the Infinite Game
is that there's a bunch of principles of the game and how you play the game and all of that. But the
core of the Infinite Game is that there's no winning, that the whole objective of the game is to stay
in the game. The reality is if you really read into it, the real, real ultimate objective is not
just to stay in the game, but to perpetuate the game. So what you're doing through your podcast,
through your book that's coming out, through your kids, through everything else is you're
perpetuating the game, you know, the game that matters to you. And that's living with purpose.
Because you are now, you have a purpose of what you're doing. I feel the same way. So when you give
up the winning or losing, when you don't look at things, you give away a lot of the, you know,
the jealousy. Like I don't feel jealousy. Like I don't like it's, it's, it's an emotion that I'm
like, you know, I'm just because you have it doesn't mean I don't have it. You know, maybe a
little envious at times, like, wow, I wish I had the knowledge that Peter has about this stuff,
but zero jealousy. Right. So the infinite game, it makes it really, really simple not to get
caught up on winning or losing just makes it and like, just play the game. And therefore we give
away, we get away from back to this notion of like, Oh, you know, I came in second, I came in
third. And you and I have talked a lot about this kind of stuff. It's like, and by the way,
I don't think it affects the outcome at all. You know, I think you,
is that something that you have the luxury of playing because you run a private company,
but if, if, if Red Ventures were a public company, would you be able to, to, to, to live by that or
would quarterly earnings and other metrics that shareholders would be privy to and have an
interest in change that. In other words, do, do public markets demand winning?
I think by and large, yes. Now you could argue that Jeff Bezos at Amazon forever never made
money, even though the public markets were demanding that he did this. And he basically said,
no, I'm going to continue to lose money on you either going to like my story or not.
You could, you could argue that Mila Musk is playing the infinite game in many ways with the
decisions he's making. Even, even Mark Zuckerberg. Yeah. Like with Meta, like, you know, he clearly
has not taken a short term meeting 75% of the value of the company. So I think you can do it.
You just have to have the temperament and the stomach to be unpopular. And you know what,
the best way to be that to not be unpopular is not to read. I don't read anything about us,
about me. Like it doesn't matter. The opinion of a stranger has zero value to me. Now, if you call
me and say, dude, I heard you say this or do this, and that feels like not you, I will listen.
Because I know that you know me and you care. So like, I have no desire to be popular with
people I don't know. I want to be respected by people that I care about. That's an amazing
lesson. That to me is a very difficult feature of living in the world today, right? It's,
do you, do you look at what people are saying about you on social media? Do you read comments?
Not very often, but a little bit. Again, I would say I'm probably 95% compliant with the
notion of ignoring it. And when I do read it, I'm rarely perturbed by it, largely for the reasons
that you put forward, which is you understand that it's kind of irrelevant. But I can't imagine
what it would be like to be doing that from a real stage, right? I mean, look, I'm kind of a
nobody, but I mean, could you imagine being Mark Zuckerberg, for example? You know, I think he
doesn't care. Yeah. Meaning he's a main man at a place where whatever, you know, but I think, I
think it's all irrelevant, Peter. Like there's no stage that is different or bigger than ours.
Like there's just different stages. Just because someone is, has a bigger platform than we do
doesn't make their stage more important than our part. Like we're all the same. No, I think it just
means that the attacks are louder, potentially. But doesn't matter if you don't read them. If you
stay true to yourself, it has all circular logic. Yeah. Have you imparted a lesson like this on your
kids? I mean, we've talked about this a little bit on our first discussion, right? You made an
interesting point that I think is, I've thought a lot about actually. I think I had historically
thought of it as our kids have it so much easier than we did because, you know, we came from little,
they come from plenty, you know, got reasons going on. You made a, I think it was the, I think you
framed it this way, but this is certainly how I think about it is I feel like me from my parents,
from their parents, from their parents, there was an inevitable trend that the child would exceed the
accomplishments of the parents. That was just the nature of moving from the industrial revolution
to now. And maybe it's our kids that will be the first one for whom it's not just going to be
falling off a log to exceed the accomplishments of their parents in whatever metric we use to think
about that. And you came at that from a real point of empathy, which is I want to make sure my kids
aren't under some unnecessary unrealistic pressure that they have to do something that their parents
did. Say more about that and how has your thinking sharpened? It stems from the premise, I think our
kids have a lot more comfort, they have a lot more access, they have a lot more experiences, but that's
different. You know, if you're defining this about feeling a level of satisfaction with life or a level
of happiness back to what we've been talking about, there's two separate things. They're divorced from
one another. They shouldn't tie. I think the fact that we're starting with the premise that achieving
more than your parents financially is the objective of life is like a goofy starting point, right?
I think what I would love my kids is to feel like they were able, given the opportunity, to really find
their gift and to do it within a place of love and that they are great parents. And then as a result,
we as a family did good in the world. And I tell you, it is to me, none of these things kind of
make any sense when people are like, oh, we don't know. I just think it's hard. It's hard when
you are Peter Attia's daughter or Peter Attia's sons. And I think we should be mindful of that,
not because it's a burden that is put on them by others that they don't know how to accept. You know,
that's what I really meant by that. I saw a really interesting clip.
I'm sure we'll be able to find it for the show notes. It was Arnold Schwarzenegger, a very young
Arnold Schwarzenegger. So I'm guessing he would have been late 70s, early 80s. So I had already
accomplished a lot, but obviously had more to accomplish. Right. This is before he would have
become the world's biggest movie star and go on to become the governor. But he was being asked,
and I think it was like Barbara Walters, but it was some highbrow interview. So it must have been
the 80s by this point. What accounts for your greatness? And he sort of said, look,
to have this level, he's referring to his own level of drive. It must come from a place of hardship.
And he's much more eloquently than this described, that basically everything he has
comes from a singular focus of escaping and being better than and improving. And he said,
look, the reality of it is kids who don't come for this, if your kids don't come from this level of
deprivation, they can't be great. They can be very well adjusted. And that's really the best thing
you can hope for them, but they can't be great. And I really thought about it a lot. I was like,
that's really interesting. There's a lot to reflect on there because first of all, there's nothing wrong
with being well adjusted. It could be a perfectly reasonable goal for kids who come from privilege.
You know, kids who are never to want anything to be perfectly well adjusted. But he's arguing
that's the best case scenario. But great in what? Well, lifting weights, great at being a movie star.
Being exceptional. Yes. So that's different because you can be a great human being. You can
have a great like being the elite 1% of something has a huge amount of tax on other things.
Absolutely. And I don't think look, I mean, that's the irony, I guess, of his life is,
you know, he couldn't he couldn't see the crystal ball of the lows that would come with the highs.
And it's, you know, to me, that's the problem with hyper successful people that trying to repeat what
they did and ends up being more self destructive than not. And do you I would argue that most
people can't handle greatness because it is addictive or greatness as it's reflected by
being the best at something or the very best so for a period of time. And those who are able to
accept the fact that none of that matters and it will change and evolve better lives. What do you
want for your kid to be the greatest at something for a moment in time and miserable or do you want
him to be, you know, not self adjusted because that to me is like a consolation price. No,
no, but I think being well adjusted is is a fantastic objective, frankly. And I agree with
you completely. I wouldn't which actually, by the way, kind of is just a very extreme version
of the yin and the yang between fluid, fluid and crystallized intelligence. The more extreme one
is the harder, you know, the more extreme your fluidized intelligence is, it might be harder to
make that transition to crystallize intelligence. Yeah, yeah, that's right. And that's true in
intelligence. But I think that's even more true in, you know, what is it like to be Tiger Woods
or Michael Jordan? Yeah, that's why I think really, really great, like four perfect students
struggle to be super productive in life because they never had to deal with adversity.
They never had to be coached. They've never had to be in a place where they're they're
forced to be good at it. And, you know, like it is better to struggle so that you learn to struggle
than to be great at something because life is full of potential struggles. Well, Rick, as always,
awesome to sit down and catch up on life. Congratulations on on all of your successes
in the past couple of years in particular. And I'm really excited to hear about this museum in North
Carolina. I think the next time I come out to visit you, I hope we can make the time to go and
see it because I would actually love to see that. No, I would love that, Peter. And, you know, I
can't say enough to you. You've had an incredible impact on my knowledge of, you know, of myself
and exercise and nutrition and how I'm going to live. And, you know, I'm I hope I know that the
last 10 years of my life, I should I should name that to you because you've done you've helped me
a lot and I love our friendship and I love how we can be so honest with each other and raw. And
I'm humbled you would have me especially a second time. So great fun. Thanks, Rick.