Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Anthony, thank you so much for coming over, not just coming over, coming over on a Sunday.
The reason I'm, we're doing this on a Sunday, I don't normally record podcasts on the weekend,
but my wife and I saw you speak, actually saw a video of you speaking. We couldn't make
it to the actual event. And we were both so moved by it and thought, you know, if there's
anything that I can do to use sort of my platform to get this message out more broadly, basically
to everybody, because it's hard to say that there's someone who doesn't need to hear what
we're about to talk about today. And basically, if I had tried to slot this into our normal
podcast schedule, we wouldn't be having this discussion until about June. And I was just
like, you know what, honestly, like if it makes the life of one person different by doing it now,
we're going to record this at the beginning of February and turn this around as quickly as
possible. So this will probably give listeners a sense of why this is an important episode. But
let's just start. Who are you, Anthony? What do you do? And why is it we're sitting here today?
Yeah, well, I appreciate the invite. I'll never say no to talking about Vietnam and talking about
the dangers it presents to everybody. It's it knows no boundaries, right? It's, it's black,
white, brown, it's rich, poor, it affects anybody and everybody, not only in Hayes County, not only
Travis County, Texas, but the entire world. So that's how prevalent this stuff is and scary.
But again, I appreciate the invite. And I don't care if it's Sunday. So I really appreciate you
fitness in and getting this getting this going. I've been in law enforcement for 24 years,
I worked at the Austin police department for 23 years, I retired July of 2021.
I grew up and basically live my entire life out in Hayes County. And I wanted to get out there and
serve in the community that I grew up in, right? So I took the summer off and during the 2021 year
and started in September. I've been friends with the sheriff out there for a long, long time. And he
consistently recruited me to get out there. So I got hired by the Hayes County Sheriff's Office
September. And I've been there just, you know, 18 months or so now. I'm currently assigned to the
community outreach unit. During my time at the eight at APD, I did just APD is a large department,
right? So you're able to do a variety of assignments. Obviously, you have to start out on patrol,
but I work patrol certain several stints, I promoted twice. So each time you promote,
you got to go back to the patrol division and answer 911 calls and all that good stuff. But
I worked in organized crime. I worked in public affairs. I did internal affairs. I did some
undercover work. I worked mounted patrol, bike patrol on six streets. So in a larger department,
you're able to specialize a lot. So I was able to experience a lot and learn a lot about the
department, the inside, what makes it tick and all that good stuff. But it was just time for me to
move on. And I reached the point where I was able to retire. So I jumped out to Hayes County. And
again, I'm on the side of the community outreach unit. And all we do is get out in the community
and visit and show the citizens of Hayes County that we're human, right? We're police officers.
Yes. Or sheriff's deputies. Yes. But we're humans, right? And our job is to get out in the community
and reach people and talk to them. And we do that through a variety of ways. We have a citizens
police academy. We do junior deputy academies during the summer. We visit HOAs. But obviously
now over the last, since about August, it's all Fentanyl all the time, just because of what's going
on. So you retired in the summer of 21. And what up until the point of your retirement, how big an
issue was Fentanyl making its way into other drugs? Yeah. So at that time, Fentanyl was around
when I, at the time I retired, I was an organized crime. I was a sergeant over the criminal
interdiction unit. And that's what we did on a daily basis was battle the Mexican cartel.
Obviously I 35 runs up and down through the middle of Hayes County, through the middle of Austin.
So I had about 10, 10 officers that were assigned to me. And we had officers that
did interdiction work up and down. I 35, we had officers that worked at ABIA. We also had
officers that worked with FedEx, with UPS, with the postal service to try to interdict,
not only drugs, but money, guns, and any, any, any type of criminal element. So at that time,
I think I did about three, three and a half years in that assignment. And we started seeing Fentanyl
probably 2017, 2018, but it was more on the black market. People would order that in the dark web
and it would be sent from China. It would be sent FedEx or UPS. And the majority of our seizures at
that time were through FedEx and USPS. We would work with the postal inspectors and security folks
with UPS and FedEx. And we would intercept boxes and boxes of illegal illicit counterfeit pills.
So that's where we started seeing it. What's going on now is the Mexican cartel,
being that they're very competitive and they want to own the drug market. They have gotten into the
Fentanyl game and that's why we're seeing it become more and more prevalent over the,
over the last number of years. Now, I kind of been sort of asleep at the wheel here and haven't
paid a lot of attention to this until maybe the past six months. But back when I worked in a
hospital, we used Fentanyl all the time. It was a very potent intravenous narcotic. So you had
morphine, which you would typically give in milligram doses, right? So if a patient was having
a lot of pain, you would use an intravenous infusion of morphine, one, two, three, four,
five milligrams, right? So, you know, thousandths of a gram of morphine. Fentanyl was much more
potent, came on quicker and it was dosed in micrograms, right? So now you're, you're, you're
talking about like, it's, it's a lot smaller dose. And, you know, it was a very good drug
for pain and sedation. So, you know, if a patient was having even something like a colonoscopy,
for example, you would use maybe a hundred micrograms of Fentanyl. So that's 0.1 milligram
and say a couple milligrams of another drug called Versed that kind of, you know, makes you drowsy
and makes you forget what's going on. Anesthesiologists use this all the time in the operating
room. So it's one part of anesthesia is the, is the pain part is the Fentanyl.
But again, I never knew it existed outside of a liquid form. And I had no idea that it was being
put into other drugs. So when did that transition take place? What is it about
this drug? And I guess we could maybe, why don't you explain to people how these drugs work and why
we're even having this discussion. What's the problem with them? Is it just that they make
people high and it's bad to be high? No. So you explained it perfectly. How powerful this
Fentanyl is, right? When you're talking micrograms, and that's the difference between the Fentanyl
that you would get, you, the doctors would prescribe, right? And what the Mexican cartel's
making in their labs in Mexico, right? The difference is what they're making is synthetic
opioid, right? So the same molecular, whatever that is, molecular, whatever structures is all
the, is all the same. It's just that they don't need the poppy plant to make it right. So that's,
that's the difference. The big difference is the dosage. They don't know how to control the dosage.
And I don't think they really grasp how powerful Fentanyl is. And when we're talking two milligrams
can kill you, right? So Oh my God, two milligrams would, I mean, that's, that's a beyond lethal
dose, right? Beyond lethal dose. And that's where we're seeing more and more of that as we're
learning as we get more toxicology back from these victims. And tell, tell folks just so they
understand like, why does this drug kill you? Is it giving people heart attacks or what is the
actual thing that's killing people? Yeah. So how it works is when you, when you take the Fentanyl
and it has a lethal dose and it basically attacks your respiratory system, right? It slows everything
down that you get that euphoric high, but you don't realize that it's shutting your body down.
And once your respiratory system starts shutting down, your heart rate starts going down and you're
can be dead in an instant. And that's how powerful and scary this stuff is.
Yeah. And I'll tell you, even in the hospital, we saw that that was not uncommon in a,
in a hospitalized patient that you accidentally gave too much. You know, you, you misjudged a
person's sensitivity and you gave them a hundred milligrams, when a hundred micrograms, I'm sorry,
when they probably should have only had 50 or 75 because you didn't understand some other factor
about them. And all of a sudden they would slow down their breathing rate to the point where
you would either have to put a breathing tube in them to breathe for them,
or you would have to give them something like Narcan to reverse the effect. And again, there
were actually examples in the hospital I trained in where patients had narcotic overdoses completely
by accident, but due to the potency of these drugs, especially to fentanyl, much less common
with morphine, more common with fentanyl. And so you think, gosh, if that can happen in a hospital,
how much more likely is it if you get this dosing schedule wrong outside the hospital? And as we're
about to discuss, they're not off by 10 or 20%. I mean, they're off by an order of magnitude
in this. So, okay, so let's go back in time, right? So, and again, think about this over the
course of your career. What was the bread and butter of the DEA and law enforcement when it
came to illicit drugs? Like when I think about this, I'm thinking it's cocaine, it's marijuana,
methamphetamines, like heroin, right? Those would be your big four. When did it turn into
other drugs like Percocet and legal drugs, but being used illicitly and sold illegally?
When did that transition take place? I think when you look back at it, I think it's 2010, 2011,
when you started seeing the pain management doctors recklessly prescribing the oxycodone,
the Vicodins, the Percocets, and there was no regard for anybody. That's how powerful all these
pills are. People get addicted to it, right? So that's why a lot of people when they have
surgery, they don't like taking these pain pills because they're so addictive. They're afraid they're
getting hooked on them. And once we started seeing that 2010, 2011, people would doctor hop.
One doctor wouldn't prescribe, they'd go find another doctor. And once they found that doctor,
they would continue to go back to them and they would just stockpile the stuff, right? So
we started seeing that probably 2010, 2011, that the opioid addiction was pretty prevalent. And I
think this is where this is the fallout of it, right? So the Fentanyl game has just elevated
the opioid crisis to a whole just entire new level. And why is it that we think that Fentanyl
is being even put into these things? I mean, I guess one of the things I understood from
your talk was that once the military and police authorities kind of cracked down on Mexican
cartels, the poppy fields are getting harder and harder to grow, but you can now make this stuff
synthetically, presumably that's cheaper, less labor, easier to do.
Correct. Did that immediately shift production to China?
So when the Mexican cartels, when they found out about what China was doing over there,
they started buying the precursor chemicals from China to start making this, again, it's synthetic.
So it's an illicit pure Fentanyl, right? So they want control of the drug game. They want that.
And it's much cheaper for them to make the Fentanyl than it is to cocaine, the heroin,
the methamphetamines, simply because they don't have to worry about the poppy plants. They don't
have to worry about the weather. They don't have to worry about the labor. They don't have to worry
about a variety of things when they're trying to grow the poppy plants. So when they found out,
they can make it synthetically and make it just with chemicals. That's when they started buying
from India and China. What we're learning now and what I've heard is they're starting to make the
precursor chemicals themselves in Mexico as well, which is obviously making it cheaper. They don't
have to buy it from overseas so they can make it much cheaper and much faster. And once they get
that Fentanyl by the kilo, they just ship it across to the counter ports here in the US. Yeah.
It's the same. Maybe before we go any further, because there's so much more I want to probe on
this. Let's kind of bring it back to a story. So we'll show a video now that you shared that
night when you gave the presentation here at the school district about the parents of a boy who
lost his life. So let's let folks watch that now. Yeah. This is Kevin McConville. He was 17 years old.
And he was my baby boy, my pride and joy. Born May 9th, 2005.
Amazing kid, full life and loved the outdoors. Very creative.
Was playing a career in the military and possibly becoming a welder. He would have been a senior
this year. He has a little sister that he loves very much. The night of August 2nd,
he asked if there was any more pizza and I told him no, unfortunately, and I could make him his
tuna. And he said no. He said I'm just gonna go upstairs and go to sleep. And I said I love you.
He said I love you too.
The following day, I found him in his bed, asleep. What appeared to be asleep.
But he was gone. And I couldn't bring him back.
Later, we found out that after their investigation, they said that there was a pill found next to
Kevin in an Altoids tin can with a pill in a bag. It was a light blue colored pill with the M30
logo stamped into it. And they said they're believed to be fentanyl. These are the counterfeit
pills that are going around. I contacted one of his friends shortly after he had passed away
to let him know that Kevin was gone. He was very heartbroken. And he had told us
that Kevin confided in him that he was taking Percocet and Xanax to help him sleep.
I think one of his, I don't want to call him a friend. I can't call him a friend,
um, was doing it as well. And that friend originally gave him the pills,
because he probably confided in that person. And Kevin probably took them before and nothing
happened. And so he continued to take them. I can't tell you how many times because I don't know.
But it doesn't matter how many times you could take it. It could be your first time. It could be
your last time. And no parent wants to see their child in that position. And that
he looked like he was asleep.
Um, that's it. That's a, that's a hard video to watch. Very hard. That's, and it's powerful,
right? So, um, and that's one of the reasons I put it at the beginning of our presentations,
because I want that to be the attention grabber. I want kids specifically to sit back at their
seats and really bring it home, personalize it a little bit, because that's somebody their age
that has fallen victim. Because not everybody knows somebody that has died from the fit and
all, because it's, although it's very, very prevalent, these deaths really in the kids
hasn't been as prevalent as what we're seeing these days.
I think the other thing that you made a really important point of in your talk is we,
we really want to talk about these as what they are, right? These are accidental deaths,
right? These are not people that are intentionally taking a dose that is so high to end their life.
This is someone who thinks in the case of Kevin, that they're, they're taking something to help
them sleep. And then they don't wake up. Right. Um, let's go back to this idea of,
do we know by the way, what dose was in Kevin's system?
I don't, I don't think toxicology has come back on, on, on Kevin's case quite yet. Um,
but as you mentioned, he was taking Xanax, um, or what he believed to be Xanax, um,
because he needed help sleeping. So whatever he was battling personally, um, led him to,
to seek these pills to help them help him sleep. Um, we all battle our own demons. We all have our
own stories, right? So, um, we don't know what Kevin was dealing with, right? Personally, um,
did he have issues at home that he have, um, was he getting bullied at school? Was he,
girlfriend, just break up with him? Um, is he getting bullied on social media? Just the kids
these days battle so much more than what we had to deal with simply because of social media. Right.
So that's what I tried to relay to these kids is I want to get rid of the stigma. Like let's figure
out why you're making that decision. Why did you, why, why, why were you needing Xanax to sleep in
the first place? And why are you, you seeking this thing out? And it doesn't mean you're druggy.
Yeah. Right. And I, I, I preached that over and over because I'm not trying to do a say no to drugs
talk. I'm trying to personalize it. I'm just trying to bring as much awareness to this crisis
and it is a crisis. Um, and what we're dealing with, um, I want to be able to, um, personalize
it and not, we have to get rid of the stigma. We want kids to be able to come forward and ask for
help and whatever Kevin was dealing with, um, he led him to take these pills. His parents had no
idea what was going on, um, until his mom or his dad walked into his room the next morning and he
was lifeless. Um, and they've been very brave. Um, they've joined us in several presentations. Um,
it's very hard for her. Um, but I think it's also good for her and other parents to talk about it.
They're very therapeutic and they're very passionate about saving somebody's life. So, um,
they'll, they'll never know why, right? And that's the hard part for, for, for them. Um,
I still talk to them on a regular basis. Um, and they're actually having the celebration of life
here in May for Kevin back home in Nevada. That's where they moved from. Um, but yeah,
so that's what I really truly want to focus on for not only kids, but adults like why let's figure
out the why, you know, I did the calculation the other day with, I was with my wife and my daughter
and I just did some numbers in the back of it, you know, and does, does my calculation come out
right to you? But by my calculation, every five minutes, someone accidentally overdoses in the
United States, meaning dies as a result of an accidental overdose. Does that sound about right?
Yes. Five minutes sounds pretty accurate. I think I heard that this morning on another,
I just happened to be going to the gym this morning to work out and I popped in my phone and it was a
podcast about fit and all. Like I, I didn't pull it up. I was wicked pretty, it was really being
that I was coming here today to talk about fit and all and that stat was there. So that's it.
I mean, I basically just looked at the last 12 months of CDC data on how many people have
died. And again, it's important to understand this is not including people who overdose as a way to
end their lives. This is people who think they're taking either just a straight up recreational drug,
like cocaine or something that's laced, uh, or two, they take too much of it or they're in the
case of what we're seeing now more and more of those. Do you have a sense of what percentage of
accidental overdose deaths today are attributable to fentanyl directly? Fentanyl is in the drug that
they are taking. Uh, I think two thirds about two thirds. Yeah. And that's what we don't, um,
I catch myself because I, I say overdose a lot, but you, you bring it up again, right? It's a
poisoning. They're not intentionally tried to kill themselves. They're taking a drug for whatever
reason. Um, and they're, they're not waking up. So they're being poisoned, um, by these drug
dealers by the Mexican cartel. And that's, um, yeah, it's that, yeah, it's insane. So maybe I'm
silly for trying to apply logic to this, but if I put myself in the hands of, uh, put myself in
the head of the, the drug cartel, the goal is, I mean, they just want to make as much money as
possible. Killing your customers can't be good business. So do they, I mean, I'm asking you a
question you can't possibly answer, but just sort of thinking about this, like, uh, why in the world
haven't they figured out a way to get the doses right? I mean, cause again, they're not off by a
little when they get it wrong, they get it absurdly wrong. As you pointed out, you might as well be
giving these people cyanide pills. If I'm understanding you correctly, there are kids
that are taking two, four, even eight milligrams of fentanyl in a single tablet.
Yeah. Yes. And that's very scary. Just so people understand, like this is a hundred times a lethal
dose that you might as well have cyanide. Yeah. One of our, one of our, uh, 15 year olds that passed
away in August, August 21st, Noah, Noah Rodriguez, um, a sophomore at Johnson high school, um,
was this is Janelle's. This is Janelle's son. Yeah. We're gonna, we're gonna link. We won't
watch that video now cause it's a bit long, but it's, it's very moving. We'll link to Janelle's
talk, which we saw at the district there. Yeah. So yeah. He, uh, he took some Percocet,
what he believed to be Percocet. Um, and his mom got a call at midnight, August 21st, um,
to someone screaming on the other end of the line, say, Noah, we believe Noah's overdosed. We believe
he overdosed. So I'm doing CPR. Um, Janelle was in Buda. Um, the overdose of the poisoning took place
down in San Marcos. So by the time she got there, her mom and dad had already made it to the scene.
She got out of the car and her mom just shook her head saying he's, he's, he's gone. Um,
what she has since learned, as you mentioned, um, Noah had eight milligrams of fentanyl in his,
in his system. Um, they got toxicology back just a week or two ago. Um, and it was pure illicit
fentanyl that was in his system. That's four times the amount that, that it takes to kill somebody.
It's insane. It makes no sense. You brought up, why did they, I get, I get that question all the
time. Every press, like why are they killing their customers? And to me,
it's happening so often they don't care what they do. Um, obviously they don't want four kids to
die in a four, in a four week timeframe, because that's when they get the attention of the DEA and
other law enforcement. But if they kill a person here or a person there to me, they don't care
someone. They don't care. I mean, yeah, there's no question that they care, uh, care about the kids.
I just think even if you were thinking about this through the lens of
having a business empire, how about just floating below the radar and not killing anybody? Um,
and as you said, I mean, the numbers are exploding. So
10 years ago, if you said to me, what is the greatest threat to a young person's life?
A young person, I mean under 40. I said, it's two things. It's only two things that matter.
Everything else is noise. Only two things that matter is dying in a car accident and suicide.
You're going to take your own life or you're going to die in a car. And again,
we can get into all the wise. It's alcohol. It's, you know, a whole bunch of reasons.
But as you know, today, accidental overdose dominates those two, like they're now the
rounding errors in one decade. Yep. And those numbers have gone up exponentially since about
2010, 20. And I just want to make sure listeners understand you're not using the word exponentially
hyperbolically. No, you are absolutely correct. It is not a line. It's an exponential line. 100%.
I think somewhere here, I even have these numbers because I couldn't, I couldn't believe when I saw
it, right? Yeah. We're talking in 2018, 2019, 2020, and 2021, just looking at fentanyl seizures,
you go from 200,000 to 1.5 million to 4.1 million to almost 10 million. I mean,
yeah, and you brought it up in 2020, 2021. If you're between the ages, 18 and 45,
fentanyl was the number one killer. It wasn't gun violence. It wasn't car crashes. It wasn't
suicides. It wasn't COVID. It wasn't any of those things. It was fitting all poisonings.
And unfortunately, I think when we get the 2022 numbers back,
that it's not going to be 18 anymore. It's going to be 13 or 14 to 45. And that's,
that's strictly because I believe, and the DA believes that the Mexican cartel are specifically
targeting our young folks. And that's why that we're seeing. Can you say a bit more about what
that looks like? How are they doing that? One of the ways they're doing that is they started making
what they, what we've, what we call in law enforcement and DA calls is a rainbow fentanyl
or candy fentanyl. And it's made to look just like candy. It looks, it looks attractive to the young
folks. It looks pretty, right? So it's, it won't kill me. It won't happen to me. And they're also
targeting young folks because they want to get people addicted a lot younger. So they have that
customer base a lot longer. Tell me what the chain looks like. So you're saying like if 13 year olds
and 10 year olds are potentially now being targeted, you're going to expand your market, right?
What is the, who's the drug dealer in that situation? How is it getting its way from a
Mexican cartel to distribute these, you know, much more friendly looking drugs? It's no longer a shady
looking Percocet with a stamp on it. By the way, I think we're going to link to some photos of these
that you shared because this is the other thing that surprised me is how good the counterfeits are.
You can't tell. They're indistinguishable. Yes. It's, I would assume, I always assumed when people
were getting counterfeit Percocet, I was always like, well, they just don't know what real Percocet
looks like. And that's why they're being fooled. But that's not true. This is color matched,
printed, identical, which by the way, Anthony, you'll have to forgive me. This brings me back
to my frustration. You figured out how to color match perfectly stamp and manufacture this. And
yet you're off by a dose of a thousand on the active ingredient. It just boggles my mind.
I'll never understand.
But so back to the question, we're now seeing this in middle school. Is that right?
Yes. As a matter of fact, our most recent death in Hayes County was a middle school student. She's
13 years old. And it's all related back to fitness.
So how did this drug get into, how did she acquire this drug?
Yeah. So basically, the majority of the time, they'll make the illicit pure fentanyl in Mexico,
smuggle it across the border to their counterparts here in the United States. And then it just gets
distributed through every day.
Tell me how that happens, by the way. I'm so ignorant of this.
So the fentanyl is coming over in a powder form?
For the most part, yes. It comes in and it's blocked in a kilo, just like a brick of cocaine
would come across or a kilo of fentanyl. What is the wholesale price for that?
I'd have to look that up to be honest. I don't know what that price is.
But it's cheap compared to a kilogram of cocaine, a kilogram of heroin, a kilogram of any other drug
based on the fact that you get to make it synthetically.
Correct. And they, okay. Yes.
So your feedstock comes to Mexico now from China. They synthetically manufacture pure fentanyl.
It gets shipped and it's cheap as hell. They get it across the border. Again, walk me through that.
What's the most porous part of the border that brings this stuff into the United States?
Vehicles. I mean, in small batches?
It depends, various ways, right? So they'll load cars up, they'll load semis up,
they'll strap it to people's bodies. They'll send it via airplane. Drones are real big now,
getting it across the border. Drones that fly at what altitude?
High enough to get over the wall, high enough to not be detected. They have grown their business,
their business models. I mean, if they were innovated in other ways, we wouldn't have
traffic problems. I mean, it's insane because they're so ahead of the game of law enforcement.
Like some of the stuff's not even getting detected by X-ray. Some of the stuff's not
being detected by narcotic dogs. They're finding various ways to smuggle it in. So when I talk
about the candy fentanyl or the rainbow fentanyl, they're actually smuggling it into the country
inside Skittles, inside nerd boxes, inside. It doesn't have Skittles in it, but it's full of-
Wait a minute. You mean in Mexico, they make things that look like Skittles or they're just
putting pure fentanyl into a Skittles box and shipping the Skittles box?
They're making the fentanyl pills look like a candy.
And putting them into a real candy box.
Into a real candy box.
And then that just comes over in a regular truck.
You would never even know.
So unless you've got a sniffing dog or if you do a random inspection at the border-
You'll never catch it.
I think I heard a stat to where the folks down at the border party intercept 5 to 10%
of the narcotics that go across the board.
It's-
Again, not to get so off on these tangents, but is that a staffing issue? Is it simply
a numbers game where unless you're willing to stop and seize every vehicle crossing,
which would of course make transport over the border impossible, you just, that's all you're
doing. That's all you can get.
There's so much of it. And it is a staffing issue, but it's a variety of things. They're so smart and
how they get it across the border that we're not able to detect it. So I heard a stat this morning,
it was between 5 and 10% that they actually were able to intercept at the border. So that leaves
other law enforcement entities throughout the country to try to intercept it.
And just from a jurisdiction perspective, the border seizure is the responsibility of
border patrol or DEA?
It's the border patrol.
So the second they make it across the border, it's a DEA law enforcement issue.
It's in every law enforcement issue, 100%. Once it gets across the border,
yes, it's a DEA, it's the FBI, it's the ATF, it's local law enforcement, federal law enforcement.
It's anybody and everybody that specializes in tackling this narcotic.
And just so I understand the logic, they're going to put these things in Skittles because the idea
is a kid that tries one of these Skittles, even if they're 13, is going to get high and getting
high feels good. And they're going to want more of those Skittles. Is the impression that the
kid thinks it's a Skittle or pretty quickly realizes, this is no Skittle, but whatever it is,
I love it and I just want more of it?
Yeah, no, I think they do that specifically just to smuggle it into the country.
I see. Okay. So it's not that they're selling Skittles.
No.
So they're going to break it apart when it's a Skittle and turn it back into pills.
Yes.
Okay.
It'll be, it's a fit and all pill and that's how they'll sell it.
All right. So let's go back to this girl in seventh grade. How did she come into possession
of this stuff? Was it through an older sibling or was she the direct person who got it from a
dealer?
I don't know the specifics on her case, but how it works today in today's world, it's social media.
And that's how a lot of this stuff is sold. It's a lot. It's how it's bought. It's social media.
It's Facebook. It's Snapchat. It's Instagram. They're very blatant about, especially on school
campuses. If they bring it to school, all they have to do is put an emoji up on their
Snapchat and they, all the kids know so and so has pills today or they're downloading these
encrypted apps, telegram signal to where once these messages are sent and received,
they disappear. So it's hard for us to go back and try to trace where these pills.
That's kind of an issue with Snapchat as well.
Correct.
Yep. So anytime in Hays County that we have an overdose that's fit and all related,
our narcotic folks actually go and respond to that scene to try to get the phones,
talk to the witnesses, talk to the friends to try to figure out. So their sole goal is to try to
trace back where these pills are coming from and to see if they can find out who specifically sold
these pills to these kids to put them in federal prison.
The people who are selling pills to kids, do you have a sense of how many steps they are removed
from the guy that receives the brick of fentanyl? Is that two layers, three layers?
It's multiple. It's not a two or three. It's multiple.
There's different plugs in each city. It's just a whole enterprise on how it's distributed
throughout the country. It's pretty insane.
Let's talk a little bit about what happens to a person when they overdose.
There's another video you shared from an elementary school actually. It was a surveillance camera.
Why don't we have folks watch that now? Let's put that on.
So again, Anthony, these are hard videos to watch, but I don't think we're going to shy away
from that. I think it is important that people understand how uncomfortable this is.
There's probably a lot of mixed emotions that are going on around the person who stops breathing.
On the one level, there's the obvious fear and panic and, oh my God, what is happening?
On the other level, is there some sense that you get from talking to people who have been there,
that there's a hesitation to call police or paramedics for fear of reprimand? Because,
hey, we're obviously doing something wrong.
Yeah. I think that in this particular video, the passenger that wasn't getting poisoned,
I think it was several, 20, 25 minutes, I believe, before he even called 911.
I think that's specifically attributed to not wanting to get in trouble and not believing
his friend is dead. So I think that's the big...
What is the law with regard to that? How clear is the law on prosecution of people who are...
Let's just say someone calls the police immediately, calls the paramedics, everybody shows up.
Are they going to be prosecuted for drug use?
If they're in possession of it?
Yeah, let's say they are.
So if they are in possession of it, yes. We had a young man who overdosed on one of our
high school campuses that had, I want to say three or four illicit counterfeit percocet pills on him
at the time he pretty much died in class. And I think that's still in criminal proceedings.
So there, yes, if you're in possession of it, obviously we want to save your life and we'll
deal with the criminal part later. But when you're in possession of it, yes, you're more
likely going to get charged.
I know this is beyond both of our pay grades, but I wonder if that's... Is that the right solution
to the problem in that situation? I don't know if you heard this, I just read it this morning.
British Columbia being the latest example of, at least in this case, a province or a state
is decriminalizing from a personal possession standpoint, any drug. So this is going to be
their attempt to say, how are we going to address this problem? Now, it's not entirely clear to me
how that fixes the problem. I can see scenarios where it makes things better. For example,
it would presumably reduce any friction to someone calling for help the moment someone is down,
because you now don't have to fear that you're going to be prosecuted. But I don't know, what
are your thoughts on that? I mean, if you go back to the case of that kid, right, who basically died
in class, it's a miracle he's alive. Again, just taking off your law enforcement hat, just from a
personal sort of philosophical standpoint, do you think that's the right thing to do?
I think it's probably on a case by case scenario, from a law enforcement perspective, and there's
laws that we have to follow. Yep, we do. So if we have to end up putting that young man in jail,
it doesn't mean he's going to spend the rest of his life in jail. It doesn't mean he's going to
be in jail. We have to file the appropriate charges, right? But also our main concern
is to make sure he's alive, make sure he gets the help he's needed. So we don't necessarily arrest
him that day, right? So like that young man went to the hospital and got treated. And then we turn
those pills in, get them tested. If it comes back with an illicit narcotic in it, then we would look
at filing charges at that time. But filing charges and putting somebody in jail at that immediate
moment is not a priority. Our priority is obviously his life. Yeah. I mean, again,
I don't think I'm close enough to the data because I know that Oregon has done this.
They have. You see it now in British Columbia. Portugal did this 20 years ago, right? So Portugal,
I believe, I think it was Portugal, basically decriminalized for any personal possession,
any drug. And interestingly, their accidental overdose rate dropped to lower, I believe,
than any country in Europe. Now that said, it is on the rise again, along with this problem. So in
other words, the fentanyl is raising all boats at the moment, including even Portugal. And truthfully,
I just don't know where I stand on it because there's a part of me that still thinks that's a
band-aid. And I think what you said at the outset is the problem, even though it sounds like a cop
out, it's not. I think it is the problem, which is why do you need fill in the blank drug? 100%.
Why do you need Percocet? Why do you need Xanax? Why do you need whatever it is? And without the
answer to that question, I think it gets very difficult to think about this. 100%. I think,
again, it doesn't make you a bad person. If I have to arrest you today because you have three pills
on you, I have a job to do. But I still need to treat you with respect. And I need to try to help
you. I'm going to put you in jail today, but when you get out, let's figure out a way to get you the
help you need or find you someone to talk to you to figure out, again, why? Why are you making that
decision? Because that's without that why that person will never be able to get the help that
they need. Specifically, they don't know the why. Do you see that that side of the equation is getting
as much attention like I would like to believe that with all of the attention this is starting
to get. And once you're at the point where every five minutes one of your citizens of a country this
size is killing themselves accidentally with poison, that should be enough to get attention.
Do you feel that most of that attention is being channeled into seizure, stopping the cartels,
the law enforcement side of it? And do you feel like enough of it is going into that side of it
that you're talking about, which is the mental health side? No, no, I don't think so. I think
it's because it's becoming more and more prevalent and more and more people are starting to ask for
help. And we're starting to learn that there's not enough rehab places for these people to go to.
Several kids have come forward at HACI-SD and asked for help. They've talked to their pediatricians,
they've talked to counselors and teachers. And some of the issues they're running into is they're
being told, well, give me six weeks and I'll have you a bed or give me three months and I'll have you
a bed. That's not acceptable. Yeah. Right. So it's not just a law enforcement thing. It's not a school
district thing. It's a community that needs to collaborate together to try to figure out ways to
help everybody, to help the folks that are struggling, right? We're not going to save everybody.
We're just not. I've been a cop for 24 plus years. I've arrested many people that have
had drugs or put drug dealers in jail. So we're not going to save everybody. The war on drugs,
we're never going to win. We're just not. But if we can take 10 pills off the street a day,
that's what we're seeing now is probably six people that we've saved because six out of every
10 illicit counterfeit pills have enough fit and all to kill somebody. So if we can take 10 pills
off the street, we're potentially saving six lives. And if I can go talk to a group of 300 students
and I can keep one kid from making that decision to take a drug or if I can get one of those kids
who's struggling with an addiction to say, Hey, I need help. Then I think I can sleep well at night
knowing that we're doing something to help. So I want to talk about that because I think that's
sort of why we're sitting down here today, which is what I think one of the things that moved us
about kind of your presentation was just how much you were putting of yourself into this,
like how much you're going around, just talking to random parents like us, going to school meetings,
doing all this kind of stuff. But it's so much of what you talked about blew my mind. I want to
get to a few more of those things before I come to the nuts and bolts of it. I have a lot of
technical questions about Narcan and all that kind of stuff, but I've been hearing some other really
frightening things. So talk to a friend, I don't know, a couple of weeks ago, I was talking to a
friend of mine who goes to Burning Man every year. As you know, Burning Man is a place where a lot of
drugs get done. And he said, and maybe I heard him wrong or maybe he got his facts wrong, so maybe
someone listening to this will correct this. But he said that at Burning Man, there were at least
two deaths attributed to fentanyl in drugs that normally would never have fentanyl in them. One
was cocaine and one was ketamine, ketamine of all things. Ketamine is a perfectly legal drug. Now,
probably was being used off label, so to speak. But clearly this was a person who was using
counterfeit ketamine. What is the breadth of drugs that you're seeing this? So we've already
established it's going into every single counterfeit pill out there potentially. So that's
going to be all of your pain meds, of which I'm guessing Percocet, Oxycodone, Oxycontin, Dilaudid
are your big boys. Then you've got it going into the benzos. That's your Ativan, your Ambien,
probably is it going into sleeping pills and stuff as well? Adderall, stimulants, any pill,
anything that's a pill that kids want, they're going to, it's going to be, it's going to be
laced. 100%. Okay. That's frightening because I know that I can hear this from my daughter saying
it's not uncommon for kids to say, I need something to help me study. I need something to help me
sleep. 100%. Where else is it going? Has this crept its way into anything that has to do with
marijuana? Yes. We're talking every illicit recreational drug that's out there, cocaine,
heroin, methamphetamines, Mollie Pills, X, marijuana. We haven't seen this particular
here in central Texas yet, but DEA says, you guys know how prevalent vapes are throughout the,
throughout the country and all the schools. It's just a matter of time before we start
seeing it in central Texas, but they're starting to see vape, vape pens that have the THC in it,
also contain fentanyl. So any illicit drug, any vape pen. And again, just to be clear,
there's no reason to do this unless you're trying to get people higher than
normal. That's the only reason. Because there's no cost benefit to putting fentanyl into THC.
They're totally different agents. Correct. So they're basically saying we're going to,
we're betting that you're going to like this THC so much more because somehow it's going to get you
the marijuana high, which is totally different, right? Right. From the opioid high. And we're
going to make a more addictive product. And yet again, they screw it up and put too much in.
It's a competitive market, right? So they want people to seek them, them being the drug dealers
out for this particular drug. This drug dealer has the strongest cocaine on the market. Everybody
go to him or her. These folks are thinking they're taking cocaine, not realizing that when
the pure fentanyl gets here to the country, that the drug dealers on this side of the border
are starting to get fentanyl in all their drugs. So when they sell it, they want their stuff to be
more powerful. They want that street cred because it goes out on social media. So-and-so has the
strong cocaine, go see him or her. And that's, that's the only reason they do it is they want
to stand out about the rest. So is there any drug this has not made its way into yet? No.
So right now we're sitting here in central Texas and hasn't shown up yet, but do you think that's
just a matter of time? In the vapes it has. In the vapes, yes. But fentanyl has been seized.
Yes, yes, yes. I just mean in vapes. Correct. And it-
Is it showing up in cocaine? Is it showing up in other drugs?
100%. It's in, it's in co- to me, if you buy cocaine on the streets today, the chances of
fentanyl in it is probably 90 to 99% if I had to bet. And most of the time you probably get away
with it because it's not a lethal dose, but you're playing Russian roulette. And every day,
and I bring that up in my presentations, specifically regarding the pills,
because six out of every 10 illicit counterfeit pills has enough fentanyl to kill you. So I,
stress it to the parents and the kids, you're playing Russian roulette by taking a pill that
you don't know where it came from. And that's how, because we're seeing so many deaths and
poisonings throughout central Texas and the country that, yes, you're playing Russian roulette
and there's no other way to put it. It's just be blood. Yeah.
So let's talk to, I would guess that the majority of people listening to this podcast
are parents. That's kind of the demographic. Are they going to share it with someone who's a parent?
Sure. I got to be honest with you. I don't think there's a 13 year old listening to us right now.
I don't think there's a 19 year old listening to us. They don't like listening to cops either.
Yeah. But there are a lot of parents listening to us. So what can we do? So let's start with,
you're just talking to me and my wife. Okay. We've got a 14 year old daughter,
eight year old and a five year old boy. Yep. So that's one of the reasons I'm pretty passionate
about it. I've got kids, right? I got a freshman in high school and a senior in high school.
And I see, I've seen firsthand how it's affected my community.
But as parents, we have to be nosy, right? We have to take off the blinders and we have to say,
we have to stop saying my kid won't do this. Yep.
How many of the parents, Anthony, that you've met who have lost a child were so shocked
that it was, I never even knew this was happening versus I'm sure there are some cases where
my son has struggled with drugs his whole life. Yeah. How many are in that former category where
they literally are dealing with two complete shocks, the loss of their child and the fact that
they had no idea their child was in need or in use of this. How often is it that case? You hear
a lot. I don't have an exact percentage, but you hear it a lot. And it may not be because they
don't know. It's that they refuse to believe it. Right. And I get it. And it goes back to the
stigma. Like I don't, I'm embarrassed if my kids are doing drugs or I'm embarrassed if my kids are
druggy. So I stress the stigma. Like we have to stop with the stigma, to stop with the judging.
And we have to work together as a community to get this as low as possible. We're not going to
get rid of it. But if we can move it around a little bit, then we're doing what we can.
But yeah, I hear too much. And as a parent, I catch myself sometimes like, no, not my kid.
But I have to remind myself because I see it so often, like it could be my kid. So
social media, both my kids have phones that have social media. Actually, my freshman no longer has
social media. But you have to be nosy. How do you do like so. So luckily, my 14 year old is not on
social media. We're going to try to keep it that way as long as possible. But you mentioned it like
emote, you know, this emoji means this, this emoji means that. Is there any chance a parent
is going to figure that out? So when I when I talk about social media to the parents,
when I go talk to the PTAs or go to HOA meetings, I stress, if you're going to give your kid a phone,
and if you're going to give your kid social media, you better learn as much as you can about every
single app that's out there. Because I guarantee you, your kid knows more about that app than you
do. Right. So if you give them Snapchat, you better have it on your phone as well. And you better
learn as much as you possibly can and figure out the tips and tricks that they probably know
on how to hire things. They're always going to be more technology savvy, technical savvy than we are.
But it's our duty as parents, if we're going to hold them responsible for that we have we have
to learn about it. And I stress that so much. Because there's so many it's not only the apps,
it's the games, the roadblocks, it's the the encrypted app, signal, telegram. So I just I
try to put as much information in my presentation in regards to social media, just so it gives
parents something to think about. And I showed that and we'll link to a lot of these videos in this
as well. So perfect. We're gonna have people gonna leave all these resources in there for folks to go
to. Tell us about Narcan. So, you know, we used to use Narcan in the hospital. Mostly the use was at
the end of surgery if a patient needs to be brought back and you mistimed the opioid dose,
you know, you would use it. But sometimes you would, you know, a lot of times you'd use it in
the situation I described earlier, which is, oh, you accidentally gave that person, you know,
120 or 125 micrograms of fentanyl. But in reality, that was a bit too much for them. Their breathing
rate is slowing. We got to back that off. I've already forgotten how long Narcan lasts for.
But what is the approximate, like if you if a kid is down and you give them Narcan,
are they out of the woods? Or is there a chance that the drug they have so much drug in them,
that even though they start breathing again, they're going to crash?
Yeah, that's, that's one of the things we try to talk about. Because kids have started going out
and buying Narcan and carrying it with them and saying, hey, I'm going to pop this pill. Can
talk to their friend at home on Narcan. I'm going to snort this pill. If I fall out, can you please
shoot me up? What they're not know what they really don't understand is this fentanyl is so
powerful. It's not one, one injection in Narcan or one nasal spray in Narcan is not helping,
because it's so fast acting. And I don't think there's a set time because everybody's different,
right? Everybody, you know, is built differently, metabolism different. So there's not a set,
there's not a set time. I try to explain that in my presentation as well. But if you, the quicker
you get Narcan into that person's system, the better chance they have to live. Right. So,
but what we're seeing in a lot of these overdoses and poisonings throughout Hayes County is one,
one injection is not working. We had a kid two weeks ago, they took 15 doses of Narcan.
15 doses in the field, in the field before they were.
It's just to play ignorant. I'm sorry. Paramedics are not yet there or they're,
they're there, but they don't want to intubate yet.
Correct. Paramedics are there. They're not deputies throughout Hayes County care Narcan as
well. So usually, if we're first there and we know it's a fit and all related overdose or poisoning.
Presumably you're just giving Narcan no matter what.
Correct. The guy can drunk.
It's so prevalent.
And you're just going to give them.
Yeah. Because it's not going to hurt them if it's right or not. Right. So we, we try to, you know,
play it safe. And if we even suspect there might be some kind of poisoning, we're going to shoot
them up with Narcan. It's very easy.
And how do you do, do you do intramuscular or intranasal?
It's an asyl. Yeah. It's like, just like an afferent. If you have your battle, allergy is
the same thing. And, but the stuff is so powerful. And depending on how long it's been,
their respiratory system could have slowed down to where the Narcan is not going to get through.
So that's where the CPR comes into play. Not only with the Narcan injection, but the CPR just to
get the blood flowing again. And that way the Narcan can get in there and attach to these opioids.
So should parents, I mean, lesson number one we're taking away is be, be really hypervigilant
about social media and understand. I mean, I've read horror stories of, you know, yeah,
drug dealers on Snapchat are basically offering dropdown menus, right? It's like, do you need
something to make you feel happy? Do you need something to help you sleep? Do you need something
to help you study? I mean, it's very banal language. And then, but every one of them is fentanyl.
It's some derivative of fentanyl into some other pill. It's different. It's going to be stamped as
a different pill. And then these kids die. And, you know, the few times that kids have taken
screenshots of their Snapchat is the only way that these stories are coming to light where you're
making the clear link to, Hey, this, this, this innocent little high school kid is sitting there
studying and, you know, wanted something to help them study, you know, wanted Adderall and wanted
this thing there. And that's life is over. So that's lesson one. How long does Narcan last?
Does it have any expiration date on it? I don't, I don't, I don't think so. You don't worry about.
So, so is it something parents should have in their house? Is it something kids should be
carrying around with them in case they, if the kids at a party, would you, if your kids are going
to a party, would you, would you tell them to carry Narcan in case something goes wrong with,
with some of the kids there? I have mixed feelings about that. But I tell the parents,
if you, if you have kids, middle school or above, have Narcan at home somewhere where you can find
it under stress, we all react differently under stress. So it's very important to, to have Narcan
on hand. Don't have it in the box, in the garage, in the top corner where you need the ladder to go
up and get it. Have it somewhere where you know, 100% where it's going to be. And you're able to use
it right away because it may not be your kid that's, that's battling whatever they're battling,
but little Johnny could, could be spending the night with you that weekend and hanging out with
your son or daughter for the weekend. But you don't know that he or she is battling anxiety.
You don't know that their parents are going through divorce. You don't know if that person
gets bullied or they simply need medication to help them sleep. And they've gotten pills off the
street because they're going to go spend the night at somebody's house and they're battling anxiety.
So it may, it may not be your kid, but if somebody's spending the night at your house and they go into,
they start getting poisoned and they start, you know, showing signs over and over dose,
if you don't have Narcan on hand, you know, you're going to feel really bad.
Can Narcan be purchased without a prescription?
Yes. You can go to any, you can go to websites, the federal government will mail it to you.
It's becoming more and more prevalent. You can go to Walgreens and buy CVS.
Okay.
CVS 100.
So we should all be just going out buying Narcan, having it in the kitchen drawer where it's
under any situation you can access it.
It's sad that we have to do that, but it's, it's the world we live in.
But it's like, you almost think of this like you, I mean, we have, you know, fire extinguishers and
fire blankets in the house in case one day the grill catches on fire or there's an oil fire.
So you just sort of have it. Tell me why you have mixed feelings about if your, if your
son is going to a party and let's just assume, even though we should never assume that you feel
very confident that, you know, your son's going to break some rules, but not this rule, right?
Your son's probably going to have a beer, but he's, he's, he's not going to take a pill that
he doesn't know what it is. Do you, do you worry that that's sort of, well, tell me what your
reservation is. Yeah. To me, it's almost like you're given permission, right? But in the, in
the same hand, it's almost like the designated driver, that, that Narcan is your designated
driver. So I guess if you're going to take drugs, you're doing it responsibly, right? I guess, but
they're legal, right? Well, I'm not even thinking, I was just thinking more of, you know,
you're not even saying to your kid, like, it's okay to take drugs. You're saying,
if somebody else does and they get into trouble, you could almost do it through a selfish lens,
which is, I don't want you to have to experience this tragedy that will change your life forever.
And it will. You know, you watch a video like that one we saw and you think like,
yeah, it's, there's two lives that are lost. There's the kid who dies and there's the kid who
watched. 100%. And if you can take that away. Yep. Um, yeah. And that aspect, 100%. Yeah. Um,
completely on board with it. What I have mixed feelings about is.
Yeah. Take the, take your drugs and have your Narcan. Yeah. Hey, hold my Narcan. Like that's
where I have mixed feelings. As do I, because, and my mixed feelings aren't even ethical. They're
practical, which is how do you know your buddy's going to give you the Narcan correctly? How do
you know you have enough? Like there's a whole, I mean, to me that's, you know, that's, that's,
you're, you're really playing with fire in a dangerous way there. 100%. Um, Anthony,
anything else parents can be thinking about here to, cause I have to be honest with you,
there's a part of me that's, and maybe this is just the, the skeptic in me that's thinking,
wait, Peter, don't overreact to this. Don't freak out. Don't, you know, cause I mean,
I mean, of course you can believe it. I had a discussion with our eight year old,
right? And I'm like, okay, Reese, if anybody ever gives you candy at school, unless it's in the
wrapper, you don't eat it. You know, I'm going down the path of, I don't know how you're, you,
I don't know if you're as old as I am, Anthony, but I don't know how old are you?
47.
Yes. Yeah. I'm older than you, but I bet you still remember when we were kids,
do you remember all the panic about app? Never eat an apple at Halloween.
100% of razor blades in it.
I talk about that in my presentation because of the, the candy fit and all. Yeah. Right. It was
just right before Halloween, I would get the question all the time at every presentation.
Should I let my kids go trick or treating or can I go trick or treating? And what I told them is
like your neighbor's not trying to poison you. Go out and have a good time. Let your kid go trick
or treating. But then I referenced the eighties when I was trick or treating. Yeah. I had to come
home and dump it out because of the razor blades. Yeah. But yeah.
So you grew up in Texas, I grew up in Canada. It's amazing to think that everybody was putting
razor blades and apples apparently across the globe, right? It probably happened three times,
right? And yet it somehow created a moral panic. And I think that I guess I think about this
sometimes, right? Is where, where is the line here? And I think when I look at these stats,
it's hard to say this is a moral panic, right? Like when you think of other examples of moral
panics, things that were like, what was the most common? What was, there was a very prominent one,
right? Which was like all the satanic cults that were like killing babies all over the place.
Remember that whole thing? That was kind of another eighties weird thing along with,
turned out not to even be the case. This is different, right? This is real.
You have the bodies, the body bags there, you've got more than a hundred thousand body bags in
the past 12 months. It'll be very interesting to see what the 2022 numbers are.
I keep waiting for those to come and I'm, I don't know if I'm, I'm not looking forward to them
because I know they're going to be scary, but they're real. And this is not a panic. This is,
I'm not trying to scare people, right? When I, when I go and talk to them, I just tell them what I,
what I know and try to just to, because it's real, it's not going anywhere. It's going to
become more and more prevalent. And unfortunately we're going to start seeing stuff that's stronger
than fentanyl because they're starting to change different structures and the molecule structure to
make stuff stronger than fentanyl. We, we haven't seen it in central Texas,
but up and down the East coast, they've seen like nytosines and I think it's called isotopes or
some other stuff that's, there's another variant of it called Sufentanil that is,
Sufentanil, carfentanil. Yeah. Sufentanil is like insanely potent. I was told from somebody
on the inside that it's the single greatest regret of the FDA was that they, that they
authorized Sufentanil as a, so Sufentanil I think is technically a schedule two drug, meaning it's,
you know, highly, highly controlled, but still medically can be used, you know, for like cancer
patients and things like that. But, but I, I've been told that they have enormous buyer's remorse
at having authorized it or, or, or allowing it to, to become legal in that setting because it's,
you know, it makes fentanyl look weak. Correct. And you've sort of opened up an awful Pandora's box.
Correct. I think in that, in that aspect is they're also trying to create the Narcan,
like a super Narcan to try to battle what's coming. And unfortunately,
it's just a matter of time before we start seeing that here in central Texas.
Yeah. Anything else, Anthony, that you want to, you want to get across to, I think specifically
to parents, either for them directly or things that they can talk with about their kids. I think,
you know, obviously the most important lesson I take away from this is being very open with your
kids. I mean, the first thing that I think we said to our daughter was like anything you have
a question about, just let's just talk about it. Cause I'm not going to give you sort of like a
legal answer. I'm going to give you a medical answer. Right. Right. I'm not going to tell you
this is right or wrong. I'm just going to give you the medical, like this is the no judgment view of
what this is. Correct. I don't know if that's enough. It's something though. And that's what
I don't think probably enough parents are doing. So like I said, I have two kids, have two daughters
and I, I've seen so much in my 24 years of law enforcement. There's a ton of stuff that I want
to unsee. But I've always been upfront with them about the world and what I encounter and what's
out there on the street because I want them to know, and I'm not trying to scare them. I want them
to know exactly what's going on and how it affects you. So we need to start in elementary
school. You mentioned talking to your eight year old. It's huge. Like the schools out in Hays
County have started hanging signs and posters that are age appropriate, talking about pills,
talking about fit and all to where that conversation is starting at a younger and younger and younger
age. We haven't gone into the elementary schools and talk to the kids, but we go and talk to the
parents. We go to the PTAs. We hold public presentations because I want those kids,
the parents of those elementary school to start having those conversations at that age, because
if that's where we'll start seeing the difference, if the knowledge, the more knowledge they have,
the more right decisions I think will be made. And again, I don't try to scare people. I don't,
I don't, high school kids don't want to want me to go up on stage and preach to them.
I just try to humanize the badge as much as I can and just try to show them that I care about
you guys. And because it affects first responders too, right? Because we go, we go to these calls
and we can never unhear the mom screaming because they're kids lifeless on the ground.
And I can't unsee that, right? And that affects not only officers, but firefighters, paramedics,
doctors. That's the stuff that we don't want to deal with either. We don't, we don't have to
experience that. We sign up for it. Yes. And we're going to try to save everybody. But
yeah, just start, just have those conversations as much as possible. I never,
never not think that your kid won't do that. Right. And just be nosy. Really. You just have to be nosy
unfortunately. And never believe your kid won't do it. I just have to stress that a lot because
I've heard it too many times. I can't believe that happened. I never, I never knew my kid would
never do that. And as parents, we want to believe that, right? I don't want to believe my kid
did, did, did what they did, but they did. Let's figure out why. Right. And just, you know, your
kid better than anybody. If you start seeing the different signs, their friend groups are changing,
the grades start suffering. They're losing too much weight. They're gaining too much weight.
Um, just, you know, when your kid's off, right? Um, I mentioned my, my freshman not having social
media. Like I, I gave her social media at a too young of age because I tried to compare her to
my older daughter who was much more mature and it affected her because she battles anxiety,
depression, some other things. And, um, I took social media away from her. And probably about
a two months ago, she came up to me and she was like, dad, I want to thank you for taking, um,
Tik TOK away from me because I'm so much happier. I didn't realize how much it affected me because
all she would do is sit in her room and scroll. Right. And it's just mindless stuff that, and
it's so, it holds so much power over your kids. Just be mindful of that. And, and, you know,
you get to know your kids, you know, it sounds funny to say you should know your kids, but some
parents, they don't, right? Get to know your kids. And when you start seeing something's off,
start having those conversations. You know, the way I think about what you're doing,
Anthony is, um, I think of, um, you're a guy walking down a beach and it's not just you,
there are a lot of people doing this, but I think, you know, the, this has become your life's mission
now. And you, you're a guy walking down a beach with another guy. I'm borrowing this from a story
and there's a hundred thousand starfish washed up on the beach and you're walking with this guy
and you're picking them up and you're every few steps, you pick one up and you throw it back in
the ocean. And the other guy says to you, Anthony, what are you doing? And you said, well,
the tide is out and all these hundred thousand starfish on this beach are going to die if they
don't get back in the water. You pick one up, throw it in. Guy looks at you funny and he says,
Anthony, you can't possibly save all these starfish out here. You can't possibly make a difference.
You pick up another starfish, you throw it in, you go, made a difference to that one.
And so I don't, I don't, I don't know how many you're going to save, but if you save a hundred,
right? If, if, if through your work, a hundred lives are saved, that's a hundred lives that are
saved. Most people go their whole lives, don't save a life. Yeah. So I want to thank you for what
you're doing. I want to thank you for taking time on a weekend to come here and talk with me about
that. And we're going to put in the show notes for this. We're going to have all sorts of
additional resources based on anything that you, you tell us we should link to for other folks.
So thank you, Anthony. I appreciate you having me. Thank you so much. That means a lot.