Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Sid. So great to see you again. It's been a long time since we've seen each other
in person. The last time we sat down for one of these, of course, it was in person and
we didn't have video now. We've got video, but we're in a different time zone. Congratulations
on the success of your most recent book. For folks listening or viewing, give us a sense
of kind of where this book fits into the prior work. We talked at great length about one of
your books, The Emperor of All Maladies, but there was a book that followed that. And then,
of course, there's this. So maybe put this in the context of those books.
Well, so it's an interesting. So, you know, this is part of a trilogy and possibly a
quartet that I'm working on broadly called the Life Series. And the attempts of these
books is to try to explain and understand how we understand life and how we're
manipulating life, living things, obviously, particularly humans.
And so in an odd way, the place to begin, to some extent, the trilogy right now.
So the first book, The Emperor of All Maladies, the second, The Gene and now The Song of
the Cell, would be to probably start with the gene, the gene being the least unit or
the smallest unit of information.
And then realize as you end the gene that genes which are encoded in DNA, the
molecule DNA, are lifeless. They don't have any autonomous life. A gene is just a
molecule. It's a chemical. And it's the it's the cell that brings it to life.
And without the cell, there would be nothing. All of that code would be useless.
I liken this to the human genome or any genome to a score of music.
But a score is lifeless. There's no music in a score. It's just it's the code.
You need a musician to bring it to life. And the cell is that musician.
And hence the word, hence the title of the book, The Song of the Cell.
The cell brings it to life.
So the second book, to some extent, is The Cell.
And then the third book, bizarrely enough, is the first book.
It's sort of like Star Wars, the prequel to the sequel to the prequel, where you learn about what
happens when cells become average.
So that would be one way to read the book, read the series of books, start with the gene,
move on to the second unit, which is the cell, and finally end up with the sort of dysfunctional
aberrant cell and what happens to it when its genes in genes go haywire.
A completely different way would be to read them as they appeared.
And the reason behind that is that they progressively go downwards.
I mean, the first book was of course, a history of cancer and cancer therapy.
They progressively go downwards and delve deeper and deeper into mysteries of that history,
missing pieces. What did we not understand about cancer?
Obviously genes and genetics.
What did we not understand about cancer in terms of its cell biology when the cancer genome
atlas was, for instance, completed?
And what do we understand now?
So they can also be read chronologically from the first to the third, but you would get a
different kind of story.
And that's what's interesting about it.
You can read it by the way.
It's possible that my question slash statement here is a bit of tainted by a bit of recency
bias because I read them in order.
And of course, I've just finished reading the cell because we decided on a very last minute
basis, we were going to try to do this podcast last minute for the way my podcast works, which
is months of preparation.
So, you know, I was sort of, you know, reading the book in the period of the last week and a
half, which I enjoyed immensely.
But here's the thing.
I felt more surprised and in awe of the characters in this book than the previous books.
And that might sound crazy because you'd think, God, you know, decoding the human genome, what
a Herculean feat.
But in many ways, the characters of this story blew my mind even more because of the time and
the era in which they had to do their science.
There were fewer tools at their disposal.
Is that does that statement surprise you or how does that resonate with you?
Well, so it's not surprising.
It's because the characters in this book are enunciating things that are, I think, very
fundamental.
Now, if you take, for instance, a comparison, if you were to do a historical comparison with
the history of genetics.
So, you know, you would start potentially in the scientific world, you would start with
Mendel and, you know, Greta Mendel, of course, being the pioneer here.
And then there is an enormous period of silence that follows Mendel, almost 40 years in which
basically nothing happens.
And then, you know, his work is picked up by other people, ultimately picked up by folks like
Thomas Morgan and others.
But for a long period of time, nothing happens and nothing's relevant.
Here, what you see in this book is very different because you see a sort of continuation of
development.
And so once the microscope is invented in the 17th century, you see from the 17th century a kind
of gradual blossoming of the science, ultimately ending up with someone like Rudolf Werkau, who
can make really, really audacious statements that are missing in the history of genetics until
much later.
The audacious statement that Werkau makes is every function that we carry out, regardless of its
origin and regardless of what that function is, is a consequence of cellular physiology.
We are cells and everything that we do is cellular, is a consequence of something happening in some
cell. This conversation is a consequence of something happening in some cell.
So that's one piece, that statement one.
And then you get the other converse statement, which is equally audacious in which he says that
every illness is the consequence of some cell behaving incorrectly.
And these statements are made in the late 19th century, mid to late 19th century, they in fact,
almost contemporaneous with Mendel.
So you have enormous sets of leaps in cell biology, which is why this book might feel sort of, you
know, that these characters are doing things while sort of, you know, genetics is still clogging its
way, trying to understand sort of Mendel's first very important paper. And there's a remarkable 40
years of silence, whereas in cell biology, there isn't that 40 years of silence.
And I think also just maybe we take it for granted sometimes today, but the ingenuity that was
necessary to even build the tool to permit the visualization.
I mean, we just lost over the fact that in the 17th century, we're putting together microscopes.
But you actually describe in some detail what the process is like to grind the glass, to create the
lens, to even have the window into this otherwise microscopic and invisible to our eye piece of
physiology.
Well, it's an it's, it's an incredible I tried to make one myself. I tried to make the one of
Lewinhoek's microscopes. And I can tell you, Peter, it was not an easy task. It was a it was a
disaster. And he made 500 of them. These are single lens microscopes. And they're about, you know,
this big, it's about the size of I would say, half a sheet of paper. And the lens is literally
this smaller than the size of your eyeball. And so you have this sense in which you have an
enormous amount of labor of love put into making this thing that's mounted with tiny screws and
tiny little apertures. So that when you look through your eye, through the lens to in a droplet
of water, you can actually see these, you know, microscopic forms. So so there's a there's an
enormous sense of wonder about how people even began to, to see these and how, how they found them and
what what the consequences of that, of that finding were and are.
People who listen to my podcast are probably used to an idea that I talk about. And you have come
across this now because you were kind enough to be one of the people who read my book. But I talk
about this transition from medicine 1.0 to medicine 2.0. And then, of course, where I hope
we're going is the transition from 2.0 to 3.0. And I typically talk about medicine 1.0 to 2.0 is
two big events happened. And they weren't, you know, momentary events, they were transitions
of process. One was, of course, the way we changed about the way we changed the way we thought,
right. So it was the scientific revolution. So once we introduced the scientific method,
late 15th century, we had a new way of thinking about observation and hypothesis. And all of a
sudden, the idea of bad humors and all that stuff sort of went away. But really, the big moment
became germ theory. Once we understood microbial agents and that we had a way to treat them,
we really leapfrogged into the era of modern medicine. And if you look at the mortality rates
as a result of that, it's outstanding. I mean, there has been no bigger reduction in human
mortality than the reduction of death that comes from infectious diseases. What I had never really
thought of until I read your book was that couldn't have happened without this deep
understanding of the cell. I mean, it's obvious when I say it that way. But in effect, this book
describes how medicine went from effectively witchcraft into where we are today. And of course,
you're going to we're going to talk about this in more detail, by the way. But I mean,
does that make sense to you? Oh, absolutely. It makes sense to me in the sense that it makes sense
because the introduction of being able to ultimately see germs and connect germ theory
with human disease, as you say, took medicine from witchcraft to the modern era.
Think of any procedure, childbirth, any surgical procedure, anything that we do, and think of the
effect of antibiotics on that procedure and think of how important it is that these antibiotics are
now available and the lives saved. I mean, just childbirth alone, the capacity of saving lives
through antibiotics has been enormous and has just really been transformative in terms of, you know,
again, as you say, moving medicine from from witchcraft. And that's because what's astonishing
in the piece that I write about microbial biology and the discovery of microbes, Peter,
is that microbes were imagined in the abstract long before they were seen. So what's interesting
is, you know, people like Lister, the great surgeon who began to sterilize his instruments,
folks like, you know, I have a small biography of him in the book, folks like Semmelweis,
almost ignored by medical history now, but Semmelweis discovered that, you know, that people,
that doctors were transmitting microbes. Tell the story. You know, I have it in my book,
you have it in your book. I am really glad that more and more people are writing about him because
it always breaks my heart when someone dies without their due. And Semmelweis is the example
of that. And it's a heartbreaking story, but it's a remarkable example of this transformation.
So Semmelweis was a junior obstetrician in Vienna. It's important that he was so junior,
and he made a very important and incredibly important discovery. So Semmelweis was delivering
children, and there were two maternity wards, World One and World Two. And this is why it's
important in medicine, I think, to listen to your patients. You know, the famous adage in medicine
is the most important question that you ever ask in medicine when you're trying to diagnose a
patient is to ask the patient, what do you think the problem is? And it's the one we forget the
most, right? Doctors never ask that question. But usually the patient will tell you the problem is,
they'll say, you know, I think I have an infection in my lungs, or, you know, I think I'm, you know,
depressed because of X or Y reason, because I lost my father. So Semmelweis learned to ask people
of a bizarre aberration that was going on, which is that in World One, the maternal mortality rates
from childbirth were astronomically high. Whereas in World Two, same similarly, same people, same
women coming in, were much, much lower. And he asked the very simple, and he knew this because
he, you know, at least the story goes, whether it's apocryphal or not, the story goes that,
that in World One, people, you know, mothers would beg to be admitted into into the safer world,
while they would beg not to be admitted to the where, you know, they would have a 30% mortality
rate, or 20% mortality rate, one out of five women, which is an incredible number to think about.
So Semmelweis began to ask the question why, and he looked at all sorts of variables. He was sort
of a classical epidemiologist. So he looked at all sorts of variables. And the variable that he
found was that in, in the first world, where there was a high mortality rate in childbirth,
the, it was run by doctors. And these doctors, he figured out, were running between autopsy rooms.
So doing autopsies on probably the very patients that they had killed, and then running, and then
without cleaning their hands, delivering babies, essentially examining patients, delivering babies,
etc. were two, on the other hand, was run by nurses, nurses were not doing autopsies, not touching
any decaying or dead material. And there was no mortality. So Semmelweis made the hypothesis,
again, remember, this is a junior obstetrician in Vienna, made this hypothesis that what doctors
were doing is they were transferring some, and this is, these are his words, some material
substance from the decaying, decomposing dead bodies that they had autopsied into the bodies
of the women that they were examining internally. And thereby transmitting that material substance
and that material substance was, was the source of the putrefaction or the infection that these
women were getting. And he insisted that the doctors wash their hands with a diluted sort of
a diluted version of bleach. And he saw that suddenly now the mortality rate plummeted.
And so he made this argument. Now, remember, he didn't have a microscope. He didn't have,
it is all in the abstract. But he made this argument that this material substance was
responsible for this, what was then called child-bred fever or maternal infections.
And the transfer of the material substance could be removed by washing hands, by hand washing.
And so he, in the abstract sense, he had basically founded junk theory.
Yeah. I mean, completely prescient.
Yeah. And incredibly prescient. And the idea of a material substance, that's what's important about
it. Right. It wasn't just bad air in a vague sense.
It was not bad air. It was not, you know, bad humors. It was not, it was a material substance.
And of course, if you had, if he had the capacity to look down the microscope, he would have found
out that that material substance was in fact nothing else but germs.
And the sad thing, you know, the sort of the epilogue to the story is the guy dies in an insane
asylum, basically having been ridiculed. He's ridiculed. The doctors don't want to,
the last thing that the doctors want to do is to admit that they've been, you know,
infecting other women. So he's, symbol wise, he's ridiculed and he's sent off to an insane asylum.
And ultimately he dies in impoverished and never vindicated.
Yeah. It's again, medicine is full of these stories. But, but, but yes, this is,
this is what it was about the book that really captivated me was this thing that I've taken for
granted. So, so much, you know, of my existence in medicine is what really allowed this, this leapfrog
and frankly, far more so than the genetic revolution. I mean, we could sit and talk about
has the genetic revolution delivered on its promise? I mean, in some ways, yes. In some ways,
no, we thought, of course, in whatever it was 22 years ago, when the human genome was coded,
that was basically going to be an equal leapfrog forward. It turned out not to be. We'll come back
to talk about some genetic stuff, but I want to go back to a question that you pose in the book
that I had never contemplated and I have not been able to stop thinking about it and I love it,
which is what's the evolutionary drive for multicellular life? So like, let's talk through,
you know, kind of, yeah, we go from these single cell organisms that have all of their own evolution
built into them and then look at the complexity that we are today. You go through this very elegantly.
Well, I mean, it's the less cause for a second to contemplate single cell organisms. So they are
bacteria, you know, protozoa, yeast, etc. They're extraordinarily successful. You can't imagine how
successful they are. They live in virtually every environment that you can think of, you know, they
live in boiling water, they live in thermal vents, they live in inside volcanoes, they live, I mean,
how successful is a single cell organism? So the bizarre question that you should ask is not
why, you should ask why we exist at all. Why is, what is the reason that, you know, we have about,
you know, several trillion cells or trillions of cells. How did we, why do we exist? Why not, why
aren't we all bacteria? And people have been trying to answer the question and the initial idea in the
80s was that there was a massive leap, evolutionary leap from single cell organisms to
multi-cellular organisms. But what's surprising is that if you look at evolutionary history and if
you look at all the evidence from evolutionary history, it turns out that multicellularity
evolved from single cell organisms, not once, but independently multiple times. And it's, you know,
it used to be called a major transition. It's actually turns out to be a minor transition.
In other words, there was a great evolutionary drive towards becoming multicellular. And you can
ask the question then, well, if single cell organisms are so damn successful, why ever be
a multicellular organism? The quick answer is we don't know, but all the evidence suggests
that it has to do with several possibilities. The leading possibility is predation. So it's much
more hard, it's much harder for a predator to eat a multicellular organism for several reasons. One
of them is that it's bigger. Number two is that it has defense systems. Number three is that it can
move away from predators through specialized apparatus, apparatus. So that's one idea. The
other idea is food and resources, multicellular organisms can have, you know, can access food and
resources. And there are other ideas about how multicellular organisms came to exist and
essentially conquered the world, as we know. But that said, single cell organisms are still the
champions. We are just a minor fixture in the world. If you took by weight all the single cell
organisms in the world and their diversity, you would be shocked at how successful you still are.
Remind us what Ratcliffe's experiments with yeast demonstrated. I had never heard of that experiment
before, so I'm reading this like I'm reading a thriller novel. Well, William Ratcliffe is a
professor who studies this transition, this evolutionary transition from single cell to
multicellular organisms. And he did this actually an extraordinary simple experiment. And he sort of
just thought about thought about it over Christmas with Travis Zahn on his advisor. He said, well,
why don't we just take some yeast and culture them? And we basically allow them to grow.
And so remember yeast are single cell organisms. And we just collect the sediment. So anything
that's multicellular is obviously going to sink to the bottom of a flask. We collect the sediment,
and then we allow that sediment to grow again in another cycle of evolution. So this is sort of
Darwin in a bottle. So we allow that to evolve another cycle, collect the sediment, allow that
to evolve another cycle. And by about 30 or 40 such cycles, he found that the yeast had evolved.
And this is astonishing. I have pictures of this in the book into these sort of snowflake-like
multi-fingered, multicellular forms, really a new organism, a multicellular yeast. And what's
interesting about them is that when he let them be by themselves, so no more recollection, no more
sedimentation, they continue to propagate as multicellular yeast. So in other words, he had
basically created a new life form, which is multicellular. And what is even more interesting
is that when he looked at these multicellular yeast, they started to acquire specialized
functions. So you would imagine that one way that these multicellular yeast could reproduce is that
one cell could butt off and create a new multi-fingered multicellular yeast. That would be one way
that these organisms could reproduce. But that's not how they reproduce. The way they reproduce
is that a specialized series of cells that sit in the middle of this snowflake
commit a purposeful cellular death. And I repeat the word, they commit a purposeful cellular suicide
such that this snowflake can break into two parts, two snowflakes, and grow out new fingers.
So this organism has now, evolutionarily speaking, learned, the word learned implies that it has some
consciousness, but that's not true. This is just an evolutionary process. It has created a specialized
furrow in its middle, where these cells basically can divide into two forms. And what's more is that
he's now, that has done many versions of this experiment. He's done it with different organisms.
He's done it with algae. He's done it with various other organisms. And what he finds is that there's
even more specialization. So these new creatures, that's the only thing I can call them,
form little channels to deliver nutrients. They form pores. They form secondary structures.
So he's really sort of created a new kind of life. And just by doing nothing, I mean, just by allowing
it to evolve naturally. And remember, this is 30, 40 cycles, which may be, you know, 60, 80, 90
days. So you can imagine over the course of, you know, several billion years of history, the
extraordinary amount of diversity and specialization that could happen in evolution that leads to
people like you and me having trillions of cells, very committed to doing one thing or another thing
or many other things. You know, because my kids who were, my boys are five and eight at this point,
they're, as you can probably imagine, obsessed with dinosaurs. So we're nonstop watching every
imaginable thing. I, you know, I paleontologists are the most important people in the world at this
point. I can't help but wonder when I watch these recreations of what we assume dinosaurs to have
looked like. I mean, at least we know about their size. How did evolution allow something so large
to be, you know, in existence so many millions of years ago? And are we basically seeing a
correction now? In other words, was that just the pendulum swinging too far towards multicellular,
where, you know, boy, here you have things that can really defend themselves, that can really get
away, that can really go after prey. But of course, they're too sensitive to a reduction in food or
something like that. Or is that just totally unrelated? And had it not been for, you know,
volcanic eruptions and things like that, maybe we just wouldn't be here today and dinosaurs would
be the sentient, higher, you know, higher order creature. A little bit outside my, my pay grade
in some ways, but, but, you know, there's lots of theories. I'm certainly not a paleontologist. So
there's lots of theories about the extinction of dinosaurs. What we do know is that, that, that,
you know, that these life forms were also very successful in their environments. The problem
was, as many people have hypothesized, that, that they, they sort of reached a maximal capacity of
size. And smaller mammals, or mammal like creatures, were much became much more adapted or adaptable
to the environment. But there are a thousand theories about dinosaur extinction, including
changes in the atmosphere, changes, you know, meteors and various other volcanoes and events,
which, you know, you can read in, in, in most paleontology. Yeah. I just, I just wonder if
there's something about their size that became their downfall beyond, you know, the obvious
external factors. And it just made me think of that when I was reading that segment about,
yeah, there's a beautiful essay, if I remember correctly by Steven Gould, where he talks about
a natural biophysical limitation on size. And that's because the volume to surface area of
any creature reaches a place in where the volume to surface area becomes no longer sustainable,
because the, the, the, the surface area of a creature does, is no longer able to deliver
the oxygen and the nutrients required for aerobic living. Yeah. I'd encourage people to read it. I
don't remember the name of the essay, but it will find it. It has to do with the rhinoceros and,
you know, what the size limits of creatures can or cannot be. Interesting. So let's go back to
something in the book where you talk about the four types of cell therapy. When you spell it out,
it sort of makes sense, but I'd never considered this before. I think it's, I think it's, I think
it's an illustrative framework for people to think about the era of medicine that we live in. So what
are these four areas of cellular therapy? You know, I tried to create a typology of the four types of,
of ways in which we could use cells as medicines. The first is the simplest one of all, which is to
use a drug or a substance to change the behavior of a cell. So the simplest example would be an
antibiotic. You're using a drug to kill a microbial cell while you're sparing normal human cells.
So that's one. The second one is the use of the transfer of cells from one body to another body
without any modification. The simplest example of that would be blood transfusion. So you're
transferring red blood cells, piglets, and other cells from one body to another body for therapeutic
effect, but you're not essentially changing the cell itself. The third is the use of a cell,
either transferred or by itself in a dish, in a bioreactor, in a chamber to synthesize something.
So I remember I said that DNA is inert. It's a lifeless molecule. If you put it inside a cell
in the right context, the right cell in the right context, the cell will start making proteins out
of DNA. And those proteins could be very useful. So insulin, for instance, you can only make insulin
in cells. That's how insulin is generally made. So antibodies are made by cells. The
antibody, herceptin, that you use in breast cancer is made by cells. So that's a third
use. And the fourth and the final is the one that is coming up and now becoming more and more
prominent as we move into this new era. And that is the use of a cell where you make a genetic
modification in a cell and then either transplant it or use it for a therapeutic reason.
So for instance, CAR T cells, which I'm sure we'll talk about, are examples of a genetically
modifying T cells and putting them into a human body. I've been doing, as you very well know,
series of experiments on bone marrow transplants in which we genetically modify the bone marrow
using CRISPR and other techniques and then transferring them into human bodies
and essentially creating a genetically engineered cells. Now people, just to finish up a little bit
on that last point, people often talk about gene therapy. And I always remind them that gene
therapy is really cell therapy. If you put the gene in the wrong cell in the wrong place at the
wrong time, you get nothing. You get the disaster. So gene therapy is really a mechanism to put a
gene inside a cell and that would be the fourth typology as it were. And then the book goes through
elements of these four typologies, examples and elements of these four typologies as medicines.
Well, let's touch on a few of them. Because you and I don't have the ability to sit here for
the next three days, which is what it would take to do each of these, their appropriate service.
There are a handful that I really want to talk about. So let's talk about the story of Jesse
Gelsinger, because that is one of the earliest examples of gene therapy in a human. We could
talk about what went wrong, but let's use Jesse's story just as much to explain the state of the
technology at the time, the vectors, the vehicles, the methods by which genes were transferred. So
let's just start with what disease did Jesse have? Why was gene therapy viewed as the solution as
opposed to whatever the other three methods would have offered Jesse? So Jesse had a genetic disease.
He was a young kid, I think 14, 15 years old, 16, maybe. He was a young kid. And, you know,
I've interviewed his father, I've interviewed, I've had a very, very moving interview with his
father. But nonetheless, Jesse was a young kid, he had a defect in an enzyme, which is related
to the processing of ammonia and ammonia related substances in the body. And so the idea back then,
and we're now talking, I think, about 22 years ago, yeah, it was about 2000. Yeah, yeah.
At the University of Pennsylvania, the idea was that if they could create a virus,
which would then go to Jesse's liver and start making this the correct version of the gene,
then Jesse's disease would be ameliorated. So they created a virus that they thought was going
to be harmless. It was a variant of an adenovirus. And then they genetically modified that adenovirus
to now include the corrected version of the gene that Jesse had a problem with.
And then they infused that virus into Jesse's body, hoping that the virus would go and infect,
because viruses infect cells and deliver its cargo, the cargo would be the corrected gene,
and thereby correct Jesse's disease. So that was the idea behind that therapy.
Let's explain two things before we go on with the story. We didn't say this earlier,
so I think it's worth clarifying. We don't really consider viruses in the same category
as bacteria, yeast, fungi. Why is that? What is it about viruses that, do we consider them
living things? Are they not living things on their own? I mean, they basically just contain
DNA and RNA, but there's sort of parasites in it. They need us to replicate. So that's right.
So viruses are not, they don't meet the criteria of living things. They are essentially
a strand of RNA or two strands of RNA or multiple strands of RNA or DNA that have been packaged
usually with an envelope and with some decorated with some proteins on top. But they themselves,
by themselves, they can't reproduce. They can't make copies of themselves, which is one of the
reasons that they're not considered living. The only way they can reproduce is they go and attach
themselves to cells, let's say to human cells or any other cells, and then they use the reproduction
apparatus, the duplication apparatus and the reproduction apparatus and the synthetic apparatus
that's present in the cell to make copies of themselves. And once they've made copies of
themselves, they butt out of the cell and then they go and infect more cells and make more copies of
themselves and so forth. So that's what a virus is. And in Jesse Gelsinger's case, the idea was that
this virus would essentially infect his cells and create now, but it would insert, because the virus
would genetically modify, it would insert its genetic payload, which consisted of the normal
gene, into Jesse's liver cells. The liver cells would now start making the protein that was
defective in Jesse's case. This is gene therapy. And then by doing so, it would reverse his
relatively mild, but his disease. So what happened then? They used this adenovirus,
they injected him and it went pretty bad, pretty quick. Yeah, so a rather terrible thing happened.
And again, I have a very, very moving testimony from his father, which is in the gene, not a
little bit in this book, but really in the gene. A terrible thing happened. So in retrospect,
we think what happened is that Jesse mounted a very, very vigorous immune response. A virus is a
object, a foreign body, and you mount an immune response to it, especially if you, for whatever
reason, have been exposed to that virus before. And people now suspect, we don't know for sure,
that first adenoviruses cause common colds, they cause, in circulation, there's a suspicion
that Jesse had been exposed to that virus, the wired form of that virus before, perhaps through
a common cold or something like that. And his immune system went berserk, because it was now
recognizing not one virus particle, but millions of particles suddenly into his body, his immune
system went berserk. And when the immune system goes berserk like that, you basically have
terrible consequences because your body is recognizing your cells as foreign, the virus
as foreign, the, you know, it goes on what I call a kind of immune rampage. And that immune
rampage can kill you. And unfortunately, Jesse died from the consequences of this very hyperactive
risk immune response raised against that virus and died. And in fact, the whole field of gene
therapy was frozen for almost a decade, as we learned to slowly understand the cause of that
death and how we could prevent it in other people. And so I think in response, the field said, look,
we need to look at slightly more immune protected or privileged sites to dip our toes back in the
water. And so tell folks a little bit about what's a safer place to maybe consider gene therapy as
the field moves closer to that. Well, there are many things that have happened. It's not just
safe places. So I'll give you some examples. Again, I'll try to create a typology for you.
So one thing you can do is you can, there are safe harbors in the body. By safe harbors,
I mean places that the immune system doesn't usually reach easily. So it just by chance,
the retina turns out to be one of them. There's not a lot of immune cell infiltration into the
retina. So you have a chance to use gene therapy. And in fact, there are now several gene therapies
that have been approved that allow you to insert or inject viruses so that you can get some
corrected gene that's missing or abnormal in the retina. So that's one place. There's some other
places in the body turns out by coincidence, the testes is another place, although we've not used
that for gene therapy. So that's one thing you can do. The other thing you can do is you can
actually, there are new drugs that can dampen down or tack down the immune response. So you can
think of the immune response as a dial. What you can do is you can dial the immune response down
so that the immune response doesn't respond so briskly to the gene therapy. You can hide
the virus. So you can make a virus such that your body has not seen such a virus before.
So you can actually use a novel kind of virus that has not been, that won't raise a brisk immune
response. The fourth thing you can do is you can actually give the gene therapy in small doses.
It's called hyper fractionation. So that fractionation, big, small fractions, so that the immune
system doesn't again go berserk, seeing this massive bolus of a dose of virus. So those are
some of the strategies and they've been very successful. So that now, the number of deaths
from this hyperactive immune response still remain, but they are much, much, much more controlled
than in Jesse Jusz and his times. So you alluded to an example earlier of CAR T cells.
I think it's one of the great successes of cancer when it comes to treating CD19 or B-cell cancers.
Let's use that as an example to explain how gene therapy can work in that regard.
Well, so CAR T cells are a very special example of gene therapy. So in a CAR T cell,
what happens is that you extract T cells from a human being who has cancer. You extract their
normal T cells and you use gene therapy to recognize them so that they can attack cells,
including cancer cells. So you're essentially turning the T cell. A T cell is part of the
immune system. Its job is to hunt out and kill foreign cells, including cells that have been
infected by viruses or foreign cells that have somehow entered the body. That's their job. That's
the job of a T cell. It's a foreign cell detector built into your body. So now you take that T cell
and weaponize it to recognize the cancer cells as foreign. And then you re-inject them. You grow
them in a petri dish in the laboratory and you re-inject them into the body. And our laboratory
has done a lot of this work. We are now doing this in India. The costs of doing this are
astronomical in the United States, almost $500,000 to a million dollars per person. We're trying to
reduce that cost dramatically, 24, perhaps even 50 fold in India using new technologies, et cetera.
We've treated about 11, 12 patients already. And we've just released the data. It looks very, very,
very good. And so they're usually used in blood cancers like lymphoma, leukemia, and myeloma.
They've not been so successful in solid tumors for reasons that we don't fully understand and
we're still trying to understand. But that's what a CAR T cell is. It's a weaponized T cell that goes
and kills cells in your cancer cells in your body. Sid, what is the difference? Why is there a 20 to
50 fold reduction in cost doing this in India as opposed to the United States? Because this is,
of course, one of the jugular issues with oncology is marginal treatments. Not that I'm saying CAR T
cell is marginal. It's actually one of the few beacons of success. But cancer is full of marginal
treatments. Extend median survival by two months at a cost of $100,000. How much of that is just
a structural American problem versus sort of, you know, people that are able to go outside of the
existing channels of IP? Some of it is a structural American problem and some of it is not. So
obviously, the structural American problem is that for reasons that we are trying to still investigate,
90% of drugs, including drugs in the cancer space, fail. And pharmaceutical companies make the
argument that they are trying to recoup the R&D costs, the research and development costs of those
failed drugs with the ones that are successful. Now, that's a complicated and, I would say,
somewhat specious argument because you could ask, you could say to them, well, why do these drugs
fail in the first place? Is it because drugs always fail? Is it because you didn't understand
something about the human body that you therefore took this drug all the way to spend millions,
perhaps even billions of dollars on the drug? So that's one reason. The second reason is,
so that would be the standard argument. The second reason is that CAR T's are intrinsically
expensive to make. Their success rates are incredible. So these are not just one month,
two months survival. My book begins with the story of Emily Whitehead. She was seven when she
was treated with CAR T therapy. She's now 17 or 16, applying to college, completely cured.
So you have a situation in which these are miraculous drugs. We've seen people who've
had terrible leukemia, essentially eradicate the leukemia forever and become cured. The problem is
that they're intrinsically hard to make. To weaponize the T cells, you need to make a virus.
That virus is expensive to make. It's labor intensive. The quality control that's required
is much, much greater than making aspirin or making any other tablet. And then, of course,
growing the T cells, you have to grow them in an incredibly sterile environment,
where you have to basically put on a hazmat suit to go in. It's called a GMP facility, but it's a
highly, highly sterile environment. It has to be monitored. It has to be checked for a single
bacteria or a fungal infection in that flask of a T cell will now basically take that entire batch
away. You can't give those back. So there are some intrinsic expenses.
Now you asked the question, how can you reduce the cost? Well, we reduce the cost by several ways.
One is that we basically, we've learned to make the virus in a much cheaper way. We've reduced
the cost of the patent burden by essentially, I think, by really making successful products
and not spending millions of dollars on unsuccessful products. So we don't have to recoup all that R&D
cost. We've changed the machinery. We've changed the way the cells are harvested. And finally,
of course, hospital treatment and therapy in India is much cheaper to start off with.
So that, you know, adding them all together comes to, you know, almost a 10 fold to 20 fold reduction.
So let's now use another example of gene therapy, which is maybe the harder of the problems, which
is you have a person more like Jesse, where they have a germline mutation that results in a pathology.
And the goal is as an adult, you know, let's pick sickle cell anemia as an example.
In some ways, sickle cell is so amazing that one single amino acid difference can have such
catastrophic consequences on the life of a person. But you want to now just change that. I mean,
it's a single amino acid. It's very, you know, we know exactly what genes drive that.
How does one go about doing that? And where are we in the in the realm of approaching success there?
So fantastic new results in sickle cell anemia, published in very major journals, and will
continue to get published. So ancient disease, as you know, single the minor acid mutation,
if you inherit two copies, then you get sickle cell anemia, terrible disease.
Your blood cells in low oxygen environments form sickles, you get, you know, they basically clog up,
it's like plumbing clogging up. And you get essentially what you might consider sort of
micro strokes all over your small, the small blood vessels in your body, terrible pain
associated with this. So the answer would be in gene therapy, you know, what if you could change
the mutated gene. So there are two or three approaches that have been so far tried.
One is using new technologies, gene editing technologies, to basically change both copies of
the gene to now make them into normal. So take out your bone marrow, which is where blood is made,
change the gene from the abnormal gene to the normal sickle, normal hemoglobin gene.
And then re infuse that back into the into the patient. So that's a gene correction strategy.
There's another strategy, which is very attractive and fascinating. And I'll just briefly mention it.
So it turns out that the fetus, the human fetus, has a special kind of hemoglobin, which is different
from adult hemoglobin. And the reason it's different is that the fetus has to extract
oxygen from mom's blood. And mom's blood, when it by the time it reaches the fetus,
has already been depleted of oxygen because it's gone through her body.
So this is called fetal hemoglobin. And so basically, the fetus has a special form of
hemoglobin, the oxygen carrier in blood, that can even extract oxygen out of mom's blood.
And so another approach to sickle cell anemia is to forget about the sickle gene problem.
And basically, in an adult, somehow reactivate or express or make fetal hemoglobin.
In that case, you don't need to correct the gene, the gene, you leave the gene as it is,
you just make fetal hemoglobin, which is very, very avid as an oxygen delivery machine.
And the cells don't sickle anymore because they don't have this oxygen problem. And that too has
been successful. There have been several trials now showing that if you activate fetal hemoglobin,
you can do that. So just to summarize, then you can either do gene therapy to express the corrected
version of the sickling gene, that would be the gene is called beta globin. That has been performed.
The second approach is to use gene editing technology to change the gene back to its normal
form. And the third approach is to reactivate fetal hemoglobin in adults to essentially correct
the hemoglobin defect. And all three of them are in trials. And all three have shown various
measures of success. My impression is that during our lifetime, we'll see a cure, a permanent cure
for sickle cell anemia. So this kind of dovetails nicely into, I think, a term that most people have
heard of. But I think that the details of this are pretty important. And this is the idea of
CRISPR. Now, I haven't had Jennifer Doudna on the podcast yet. I would love to at some point.
So we don't need to necessarily go into the great depths of CRISPR. But I think some history is
probably relevant, especially as it pertains to the topic of our discussion, which is cells,
bacteria and viruses, or bacteria as the cells and how they interact with viruses and where to
protect themselves. But I now want to kind of use the story of CRISPR to talk about another tool by
which one can impart this type of cell therapy. So, you know, the world of genetics was turned
upside down in a very important way by the discoveries of Jennifer Doudna, Emmanuel
Saucon-Tier, and several others. I should mention Fen Zhang and George Church, among others. And
there's a history of this, which is in the book. For a long time, there was the question of whether
the human genome is a library. Imagine the human genome as a massive library.
If it was printed in normal text, it would contain 80,000 books, a massive encyclopedia,
stretching across a massive library. And imagine that you wanted to make a change in one word
in that library. You want to take book 61 on shelf 47 and make a change from verbal to herbal
in that library. This was a dream of scientists for a long time and no one could do it.
And then Jennifer Doudna, Jean-Puentier, and then assisted by Fen Zhang and other people,
figured out that there was a bacterial system evolved millions of years ago that could make
that precise change in one word in that entire library, either deleting that word, in other words,
erasing it, simplest change, or potentially changing the word to another new word.
That's, it's an incredible genetic revolution. So as we move forward into this new universe,
we have the capacity to change the human genome in a deliberative and,
erm, I would say a, a processed manner. So just take the example of sickle cell anemia that we
gave before. We can change that sickle cell anemia gene to a normal gene by using this technology.
We can change the mutant or abnormal cystic fibrosis gene to a normal gene, the normal
version, erm, or the wild type version using this technology. So it's obviously extraordinarily
important, erm, and there are many, many applications of this technology, erm, and it's exciting because
we can do things that we couldn't do before involving changing genes to new genes, changing
genes to their wild type, er, variants or their more common variants, and so forth. So, erm, we
now have, have the capacity to do this. We can do this with embryonic cells. We can do this with
embryonic stem cells. We can do this with bone marrow cells. We can do this with T cells,
CAR T cells. The, the, it's a revolution and all I can emphasize is the depth and breadth of this
revolution because it's enormous. So two, two follow-up questions. The first is explain using
the library analogy how this system differs from the approach that was used 20 years ago in the
case of Jesse Gelsinger that we described where an adenovirus was used. I mean, what's the difference
in scale and elegance between what you just described, which is in the 80,000 books, you can
go to one page, one word and make the change versus that other approach. Yes. So, erm, so again,
imagine the human genome as a massive library, 80,000 books, er, printed on a page, erm,
and so the old technology, Jesse Gelsinger, the technology that was used with Jesse Gelsinger
is the technology in which we, er, by analogy, I'm using metaphors and, and, and analogies here,
we would insert a new page into that 80,000 page library. Erm, so you would go into the library,
80,000 books around you, and you would take a page and insert a new page into that library.
A foreign page. The librar, the librarian could come, in this case, the immune response, the T-cell
or the B-cell immune response, and come and say, wait a second, that's on, it doesn't belong. That's
on a page that belongs. And that's what happened with Jesse Gelsinger and other people. The librarian
would come and say, librarian being the human body, would come and say, wait a second, you're
inserting new pages into a library. That's no good. Erm, and would prevent that.
And it seems to me that you didn't even, it was much harder to know where to put that page. I
mean, if you knew a priority, I really want that p2b between page 87 and 88, you might accidentally
insert it somewhere else, right? Exactly. And the librarian would say, well, why are you putting it
into, you know, Jennifer Egan's book on the Boone Squad? Because it doesn't belong there. You just
inserted that page, new page, the new gene into a place where it doesn't belong. And he or she would
say, I don't buy this. I'm not going to let you do that. That's absurd. You're reading along with,
you know, Chekhov or Egan or whoever. And all of a sudden you find a new page that's been taped in
the virus that's carried in the new gene, the new virus. And you say, well, wait a second,
that doesn't belong there. And that was where the technology sat for years and years and years.
Then Jennifer Doudna, Charpentier and others discovered a method in which you would do just
quite the opposite. You would go into a page and say, listen, I have the right page in the right
volume of the right book. And I'm going to change one word. The first kind of words that they could
change was just deleting a word. And this was using a viral system called CRISPR. And you could
just erase a word. And then more and more research showed that you could change the word.
And as I said, you could change the word verbal to herbal by changing a single letter. And for the
most part, leave the library intact. And if you were a very vigilant librarian, you would say,
that's okay. You haven't put in an extra page in, you know, Charles Dickens book.
You've actually gone to the right book and changed the right word in the right space,
in the right time from one to another. And that's the subtlety of what CRISPR allows us to do.
It allows us to make extraordinarily precise changes in extraordinarily precise ways
in a massive library, which would not be possible otherwise.
So you alluded to this at the outset of your description, which was
you could make changes to an embryo, right? You could take an embryo and you could make a
genetic change, which now has pretty significant consequences because it is now a germline change.
This is different than, you know, if you made a change in a non germline cell way down the line.
And I guess as things would have it, the first documented example of this created quite a
controversy. So maybe briefly tell the story of JK and the CCR5 gene and why that, and I guess
more importantly is what are the implications of that pretty unethical episode?
So again, I would encourage people to read the book, The Song of the Cell,
to get all the details about it. But a Chinese scientist, JK Wu,
made a somewhat bizarre decision. And I'll talk about why that is it or was bizarre.
There is a gene in the human genome that makes cells resistant to HIV infection.
There are many genes, but this is one of them. The Chinese scientists in this case
decided, Hei-Jung Khen, decided that he was going to make a change in human embryos
with gene editing technology, the technology that I just described, which would make the child of a
parent couple in which the man was HIV positive, the woman was HIV negative,
and make that change in the embryo and implant those altered embryos into the mom
so that they would be HIV resistant because of this change.
So it sounds great on paper. The problem is that the risk of these children to acquire HIV
because they were produced by IVF is basically zero. It cannot get HIV. The sperm doesn't carry
HIV. So if you produce a child by this method, you basically have a zero risk of HIV infection.
It wasn't medically necessary. Let me take a step back. Peter, the book makes a very big distinction
between disease and desire. Disease is fundamentally linked to suffering.
When we talk about disease, we talk about human suffering.
When we talk about desire, we talk about the idea or the aspiration to ameliorate suffering,
even where there's no suffering involved, as far as we can tell. Now, in this case,
there was no disease. The children had no risk of disease. They couldn't have any risk of disease.
The desire was an entirely scientific desire to create a generically modified embryo.
In this case, in particular, the desire was that they would create a modified embryo and that
his inquiry would be the first in human history to create a human embryo with genetically altered
stem cells. So he went ahead with this project and he created two girls. We don't know their
real names. Their names have been called Lulu and Nana. What he obtained was not exactly what
he hoped to obtain, which is not that precise erasure of verbal to herbal in a single book
in the entire library of 80,000 books. What he obtained was a much cruder version of that.
Scientists across the world were concerned about did he have informed consent? Was there appropriate
use of the parents even understand the language that we're using? Now, remember,
because this was an IVF procedure, the risk of these children getting HIV was zero.
So again, we come to the question of disease versus desire. They had no disease. The only
desire was to create someone who was potentially resistant to HIV infection. So we have this
situation, which is very unusual, where desire, the desire to change human embryos, the desire
to push the frontier of science overwhelms the disease where there is no disease.
And so the scientific world became extraordinarily incensed about the idea that, you know,
this scientist had really crossed the boundary between disease and desire. Now,
if this had been some disease that the children had inherited, cystic fibrosis, sickle cell disease,
Huntington's disease, some terrible thing that they would encounter in their lifetime,
the scientific community would have been much more sanguine about it.
But these children, these two twins that were born, had a zero risk, zero risk,
of acquiring HIV from their fathers because the sperm had been washed, sperm don't get infected
with HIV. So they were basically, they had no risk of the disease. So what was left was desire,
the desire to be first, the desire to be create new human embryos. And that's what was very
incensed, you know, that's what incensed the scientists and the community of scientists.
You know, there's probably no greater example of the relationship between science and philosophy.
You know, people might want a little bit of a reminder about what a doctorate degree is
formally called, right, a doctor of philosophy. And so when you think about this question,
it becomes kind of difficult, right? And I think in Walter Isaacson's biography,
of Jennifer Doudna, I think this topic is explored in your book, this topic is explored.
Where does one draw the line, right? So, you know, Huntington's disease is a great example
in the sense that you have a genetic, you have an acquired genetic mutation that is 100%
penetrable in a devastating disease that shortens life and leads to immense suffering.
Would we find many philosophers of science who would say that it is wrong to alter the embryos
of adults who have Huntington's disease or carry that trait, that gene, to prevent it from going
to their offspring, which by the way, if you play the thought experiment out, would eliminate
Huntington's disease altogether? Because these are germline mutations. Like, how does the
scientific and philosophical community merge over questions of that nature? And then of course,
just to tell you, eventually, do we move that further to APOE4, LPA, other genes that are not
as penetrant? Right. So APOE4 is a risk factor for Alzheimer's disease or early Alzheimer's disease,
just to give you an example of how devastating it can be for particular people who have
combinations of APOE4 and other genetic mutations that increase their risk early Alzheimer's disease.
But I think the scientific community would say, for Huntington's disease, the scientific community
would say, listen, this is a devastating disease with a huge penetrance. By penetrance, we mean,
if you inherit the gene, the chances that you have the disease is very high.
Sometimes that's not the case, right? So you might inherit a mutation in some gene,
whatever it might be, but you might not get the disease. Braco1 is a good example, right? You might
inherit Braco1 gene, but you never may have, you may escape having breast cancer in your lifetime.
Huntington's disease has a very high penetrance. So in other words, if you inherit the mutation,
the likelihood that you have the disease is very high. I think the biomedical community would say
that for diseases like Huntington's disease, it's probably worthwhile doing an intervention,
an intervention of whatever that intervention might be. But the biomedical community would say
that for, in this case, in HIV, it's not warranted. And I think that the biomedical community would
say it's not necessary. It's not part of the continuum of disease versus desire. It moves
towards desire without moving towards disease. I think the other examples of things on the clearly
desire spectrum are pretty obvious, right? Like enhancing intelligence or physical traits like
strength, size, et cetera. Of all of these areas, the one I find most interesting is around mental
health, right? Which is we understand, for example, autism and schizophrenia have an enormous genetic
component. On the surface, it might seem like, hey, wouldn't it be great if fewer people were
born with autism and or schizophrenia, but it's really nowhere near that simple, is it? And there's
a Pandora's box upon which we have no idea what we could lose as a society if we were to sort of
sterilize, quote unquote, some of these conditions. You've obviously touched on this, and I want to
come back to sort of mental health, because in some ways, where we're going to go next in this
discussion, I think, is to the last cellular territory, right? The cells of the brain. To me,
that's kind of like the most complicated cells of the body, in a sense. And of course, this is one
area where it's very difficult to appreciate a phenotype under a microscope or in a scanner.
And so I think part of it has to do with the complexity of these genes. But how do you think
about what might be inevitably questions that society faces around the use of this type of
precision gene editing when it comes to genetic conditions of the brain?
Well, the brain is the most complex of all organs, and it's important to understand that complexity.
What we know about diseases like autism and schizophrenia is that there are, broadly speaking,
two kinds of genes in the entire spectrum of genetics that have to do with mental diseases.
One kind of gene is what I call a shove gene. Shove meaning it pushes you really hard.
So think about height. Forget about autism for a second. Think about height. Height is a genetic,
has a strong genetic component. Tall parents tend to produce tall children. Short parents tend to
short parents tend to produce shorter children. So we know there's a genetic component to it.
Now, there are genes in the spectrum of controlling height that are very powerful
shove genes. They shove you in one direction or the other. So one example is Marfan syndrome.
Marfan syndrome is a genetic disorder, a single gene. One gene, if you inherit copies of that gene,
you will likely be extremely tall and you might have other medical and other complications,
but you will be tall for sure. There's a story that Abraham Lincoln may have inherited
Marfan's, the Marfan gene. Okay. So that's a shove gene. Those are relatively rare in the human
population of very tall people. The more common variant is what I call a nudge genes. Nudge versus
shove. Nudge genes move you little by little by little by little by little towards increasing
height. And there may be hundreds, there may be tens of hundreds of genes that may increase your
height little by little by little by little by little until you get five feet, 10 inches, five feet,
nine inches, five feet, 11 inches, six feet, etc, etc. It's not one gene, but hundreds,
if not tens of hundreds. Now, transfer that same idea to mental health. Okay. There are certainly
genes in the human genome that change your neuron physiology, the physiology of your nerves
that are shove genes. In other words, if you inherit them, just like Marfan syndrome, you are
likely to get much more likely to have mental illness in whatever form it is.
They're relatively rare. And they are inherited in families. There's a great book on this
written recently about a family that has multiple kids with schizophrenia, etc.
I think it's called Fallen River Road, if I remember correctly. Okay. But most mental illness,
just by analogy with height, is not the consequence of this shove phenomenon,
but our consequences of what I would call death by 1000 cuts, small nudges that would push you
towards depression, schizophrenia, autism, etc. And in fact, we haven't even found those
genes yet, even though we know they exist. In some cases, we haven't found those genes yet.
So the capacity to change those genes is very limited because, you know, the examples that I
gave you of gene editing, gene alteration technology are limited to one gene, two genes,
three genes. But it's very, very hard to find a way to change those genes, hundreds, potentially
tens of hundreds of genes in the mental health spectrum. So it's not as if we can all of a
sudden wake up one morning and say, I'm going to change your mental health, or change the mental
health of your embryo, based on the understanding of our subgenes, because it just won't happen.
So let's now dig into this complexity issue around the brain. You know, it's,
I've tried to explain this to people, and I've never been able to do a great job of it. You do
a great job of it in the book, describing the mystery, right? And you came up with a way to
describe it that I thought was fantastic, which was, and I want to make sure I'm getting this
right. So correct me if I'm wrong. You said there were two types of problems in science.
There are the eye in the sandstorm problems versus the sand in the eye problems. And as
the cellular biologists and neurobiologists were getting deeper and deeper into the brain,
and it really seemed like they had figured out this thing, these axons, the movement of electricity,
these action potentials, they were figuring this out, but they had a little piece of sand in their
eye. What was that piece of sand? And again, feel free to expand on this if I haven't provided an
eloquent enough setup, but it was a beautiful description. It's a fanciful description,
and it's an important distinction. And it's a philosophical distinction.
The eye in the sandstorm problem is a problem in which you encounter something in medical sciences
where the information just doesn't fit. It's being in the sandstorm. And I give the example
when we made the transition in physics between Newtonian physics and quantum mechanics and
Einsteinian understanding. So in other words, you reach a place and all of a sudden,
everything didn't fit. The bending of light, the presence of
relativity, etc. Nothing can fit. So you needed a completely new theory, a new paradigm, a Tobi
shift in paradigm, paradigmatic thinking. That's the eye in the sandstorm problem. So in other words,
there's sandstorms everywhere, and you can't make sense of the real world.
That's one kind of problem. And I'm interested in those problems. The sand in the eye problem,
as I call it, is a different kind of problem. The sandstorm in the eye problem is when everything
fits except one fact. And it's very important to understand that both of those are really,
really interesting, because the sand in the eye problem says that our theory is almost right,
but it's not right because there's something, a fact that won't fit. And the particular example
I use is neuronal transmission. So when people discovered neurons in the brain,
they figured out basically by looking at an anatomy, that neurons in the brain weren't,
that there was a space between them, that nerves weren't just wires. If you were an electrician,
fitting out an electrical situation in an apartment, right? What you wouldn't do is put
spaces between the wires so that all of a sudden that space would become a communication between
wires. You just hook the whole apartment up. But when people like Ramani Kahal and other
scientists figured out how to solve this problem, they understood that all of a sudden that nerves
have spaces in between them. In fact, they had a name for these spaces. It's called a synapse.
And that is an eye in the sand problem because you say to yourself, wait a second, if the nervous
system is just electrical wires strung together, why would you place a space between two electrical
wires? And the solution to that problem turns out to be extraordinarily important for neuroscience
because what happens between nerves is that an electrical conduction moves between, from one end
of a nerve to the other. And then, and here's the kicker, it changes from an electrical conduction
to a chemical signal between one nerve to another. And that chemical signal
re-sparks, or sparks, an electrical conduction. So you're both going chemical, electrical, chemical,
electrical. And you could say what mad person would ever devise, or what evolutionary process
would ever devise a system like this? And the answer is, the reason is very important.
Because what your nervous system is doing is in that transmission between electrical, chemical,
electrical, chemical, electrical, chemical, what your nervous system is doing is it's putting
weights so that in the chemical transmission and in an electrical impulse could come down a nerve.
But let's say there are 10 nerves or 10 neurons, nerve cells, that are impinging on one nerve cell.
You could assign a weight as to how much this one was transmitting versus another one.
And by assigning those weights, by assigning those calibrations, you could say one is louder
than the other, one is softer than the other, one inhibits the other. And it's those combinations of
inhibition, loudness, etc., etc., that allow profound things like sentience, and conversation,
and consciousness, and so forth. The analogy that's very important is this is exactly or similarly
to how, and I say it's an analogy, this is exactly or similarly to how neural networks work.
There are, there are weights put on how one layer of communication
communicates with the second layer of communication. In other words, some are louder than others,
some are softer than others. Imagine discriminating a dog from a cat. You could say that a very loud
signal in that discrimination if the animal happens to bark. You know that for sure that's
not a cat. That's a very loud signal. A very soft signal could be the weight of the animal.
Some dogs are lighter than cats. A very loud signal could be the way that, you know, the snout
of an animal is fixed with the head of the animal. Dogs have a particular snout, head combination,
cats have a particular snout head combination. So by adjusting the weights of these combinations,
we think by analogy that this is how the brain can discriminate between dogs and cats.
We don't know this for sure because this is an area of science that's still in process.
But this is a classic example in the 1950s of the idea that why on earth would you take an
electrical signal, convert it to a chemical signal and then convert it back to a micro signal?
The answer is because it was just an electrical signal, you know, we'd be a box of wires.
And a box of wires without the weight between individual signals between the wires is a useless
box because we don't understand or we cannot understand how to construct a learning network
between these a box of wires. Whereas we can understand how we can construct a learning
network between electrical and chemical stimulation because we can modulate the strength
of that chemical stimulation such that we can really actually learn a process.
Does that make sense?
It really does. I mean, another way that I like to explain it is using music, right, which is
the electrical signals that travel down the axon are digital. And maybe because I'm an engineer,
I do tend to think in terms of digital versus analog processes. But if you explain that,
look, digital means it's either completely on or completely off. There is no modulation.
And imagine an orchestra that every instrument could only play at one maximum decibel level or
not at all. You couldn't have any modulation of sound. It would be a very awful sounding music.
But if now each of those instruments can go up and down and crescendo and decrescendo and modulate,
you now basically have kind of the analog adjustment of music. That's how we make songs.
And I think that's probably a cruder analogy. But I think it kind of also gets at this point,
which is I mean, again, it comes back to how did evolution figure this out? How much trial and
error went into producing something so remarkable, so brilliant, right? I mean,
like, again, you wouldn't think to engineer this system necessarily.
Well, I mean, I think the reason evolution figured it out is, is again, learning
a purely electrical system, which is sort of like saying, you're playing some music,
but you don't have any modulation. You know, you're listening to a score,
and the score has no modulation, right? So you play everything at the same volume,
at the same tempo, at the same time. That's on music. That's not the song of the cell.
What evolution figured out, and by figured out, I don't want to put an anthropomorphic idea on it,
but what our evolution converged on is the idea that music has tempo, it has pace,
some pieces are softer, some pieces are louder. And by altering this loudness, softness,
as we move along in our neurons, that we can produce not just a mechanical
output of the score, but a real music. And your musical analysis is very interesting,
because that's what we're producing. We're producing not a mechanical output of the score,
we're producing a learned output, a mature output of the score. And that mature output has to do
very much with, you know, modulation. Some parts are louder, some parts are softer, some parts
speed up in rhythm, some parts slow down in rhythm. And that is ultimately the music of the cell,
but also the music of the brain. So there's many systems we haven't spoken about, but there's one
we would be remiss not to speak about, because it's near and dear to both of our hearts. So you
when you went to Oxford to do your PhD as a Rhodes Scholar, you ended up in a lab where you
learned immunology, which of course would come to serve you very well, as an oncologist and a
hematologist today. I want to talk about a couple of things there. First is, you spoke of course,
of your mentor Enzo in the lab. Help us understand what it is that was sort of bestowed on you
from an education perspective, from a learning perspective, as a doctoral student that we don't
really get in medical school. I mean, you know, you would go on to Harvard Medical School, you'd
get a great medical education. But I think anybody who spent time in a lab will understand that
there are just certain things that can't be taught in a classroom. You have to learn things
by being in a lab if that's the language you want to be able to speak.
What are your recollections of that period of time, especially in the beginning when presumably
the learning curve was very steep and you're drinking from a fire hose and you don't know
much of what's going on, but you've committed to this path of becoming a scientist first,
a physician second. It's a very different kind of thinking process. Peter, I like to make
medicines. And when I make medicines, I like to make medicines that are important for
human life, hopefully for saving lives. I've talked about some of them.
We've spoken prior podcasts about some of the new medicines that I've been involved in inventing.
The textbook knowledge in medicine is important and biology is important because it lays the
groundwork and the foundations of what we know and understand. But textbook knowledge only gets
you so far because when you come into the actual laboratory, you understand that there are things
that are predictable, there are things that are not predictable. And then you get into these
eyes, eye in the sandstorm and sand in the eye problems, which are very important.
You learn to recognize failure. You learn to recognize how to troubleshoot your way out of
failure. None of this is in a textbook. Open a textbook of biology, any textbook of biochemistry
biology, and try to find me a section on troubleshooting. You won't find one.
Troubleshooting your way out of failure is the most standard way that we think about medicine
in biology. Run a clinical trial. How do we select a patient? So let's say you're running a phase one,
phase one to be clinical trial. I have six open trials right now. How do you run a clinical trial?
Read a textbook. Nothing will tell you about how you select a patient for a clinical trial,
how you manage a patient with complications from a clinical trial. There is no information anywhere
in that textbook about running that trial. So similarly, run an experiment which will
set you up for a clinical trial. There is no information in that textbook about how to
troubleshoot how and where and how to do that science that allows you to make it into a human
medicine. What if, for instance, you suddenly find that the medicine that you're working with,
that you're trying to create, isn't pure, that there's a contamination. How do you remove that
contamination? There is no method that you can't find a textbook. And so what you do is you ask your
peers who've done this before you and you say, what did you do? And that's not in a textbook.
That's not in any book. That's not in a book that's ever been written. And so I wanted to write
about that. I wanted to write about that process of learning by doing, learning by being, learning
by experiencing. And that's why that whole chapter exists in the book. There is a kind of learning
that we do by doing, that we be by being, that we acquire by acquiring, that cannot be found in
any book or textbook in the medical sciences. And there's no way around it.
You know, there are a couple of really personal things I want to ask you about,
some of them for selfish reasons. I want to start with writing. For all the times we've had meals
together, I don't know how this hasn't occurred to me to ask you, but how and when did this, and
when I call it a gift, I don't want to undermine it, Sid, because I don't want to suggest it doesn't
require an obscene amount of hard work. But the reality of it is if I spent the rest of my life
writing, I would still write like a child compared to an adult in the way that you write. So at what
point in your high school, undergraduate, etc., did you realize that you had a brilliant way to
write? And I will say this, I think you are hands down the best medical writer, I mean, best writer
who happens to write about anything that has to do with science and medicine. I mean, it's really,
it's outstanding, Sid. Well, thanks for the compliments. You know, writing is not an easy
process for me, but it's also a somewhat weird process for me. And by weird, I mean, I throw in
everything. In the next book that I write, maybe this conversation that we're having, or some aspect
of this conversation, some question that you ask in this conversation will find its way into the
book. So I have this policy in which I don't make any, there's nothing that's outside my box.
It's all part of the box, all part of the whole story. So again, I find that that writing is a way
for me to think, a way for me to work through my thoughts. And the analogies and the metaphors and
the metaphorical parts of my writing are really not in service of writing. They're in service of
making me think. They're in service of making me understand why a certain phenomenon is related to
another phenomenon. I draw from history, I draw from mythology, from philosophy, from our
conversations, from interviews, and everything goes into a book. And in some ways, I feel as if
I had to invent the genre, because, you know, it was so siloed. Medical writing was about medicine.
It wasn't personal. It wasn't. There was sharp distinction between memoir and case histories.
There were sharp distinctions between, you know, deep history and an interview or journalistic
writing. And I said to myself, you know, these distinctions are arbitrary. They only exist to
serve a kind of secondary purpose. Why not erase all of them and make a new kind of writing in
medicine or in life? Because the most important thing that I think people told me about medical
writing was that when people read writing about medicine, they want to enter your cosmos. They
want to enter your world. They want to know what it's like to be like you. And so I said, okay,
I'll show them. What is it like to be like me? Well, it's like to be to experience intense,
absolutely intense exhilaration when a clinical trial is successful, absolute depths of depression
and crisis when a clinical trial fails. Absolute anticipation, absolute apprehension,
absolute admiration for people who on whose shoulders I stand. That's what it's like to be
like me. And when people said to me, show me your world, I said, okay, I'll show you my world,
but I'll show you my world in a way that's like to be like me. What is it like to be like me?
I am like you. I have terrible days. I have very good days. I have exhilarating days.
I make inventions. Those inventions work. Some of them don't work. And all of it is
wonderful and terrifying at the same time. I want to bring you into that. And that means I will
combine memoir, journalistic writing, traveling writing, philosophy, mythology, and everything.
I'll throw everything in there so that you understand what it's like to be like me.
There are two things you talked about in the book, Sid, that were completely unconnected,
but immediately in my mind were connected. And it probably has to do with my own world.
As you know, Sid, I think a lot about the end of life. I think a lot about how we can
delay and push off the end of life. And one of the things that I think a lot about is how
quickly life can vanish in a person when they fall. In an older person, I don't mean a 10-year-old.
And these two things that you write about, and again, totally different parts of the book.
Run, you talk very openly about your own depression that really kicked in a year after
your father's death, which resulted from a fall. And near the very end of the book,
you talk about the end of Virchow's life, which I was not aware of how Virchow died.
I was completely unaware of that, that he ultimately died as a result of a fall and
a broken femur. And within less than six months, he was dead, which is unfortunately far more
common than people realize. I mean, it is the leading cause of accidental death. And the
mortality, as you know, Sid, from a person over the age of 65, if a person at that age or above
falls and breaks their femur, depending on the study, it's anywhere from 10 to 30% mortality
at 12 months. And you do a very good job of explaining the why. Because a lot of people,
when confronted with that fact, simply can't understand it. And I was again confronted by it
just two days ago, when the swim coach of Stanford while I was there, and of course,
I didn't swim at Stanford, but many of my friends did. And I sort of knew him and I got to know him
later after he had retired. And he fell two weeks ago, broke his hip, and two weeks later, he's dead.
Never really recovered from the surgery. That's a very extreme example.
It's interesting to me, but
what I couldn't believe was how you tied it back to the cell, right? Which was,
here we have one of these giants of cellular biology who falls and dies, but it's actually
the result of a cellular process. One cell, it starts with the osteoclast and the osteoblast
and the matrix of the hip. And ultimately it leads to organ failure. That's not a leap that I think
is easy to make. It's not obvious. Well, it's obvious when you think about
Burkhart's own idea that the body is a citizenship. Yeah. Well said. And the citizenship falls when
one part of the citizenship falls. Imagine a citizenship in any capacity, right?
All of a sudden your bureau of transportation decides to take a leave for 20 days. The trains
in New York City stop running. The trains stop running and therefore people can't go to work.
People can't go to work and the economy collapses. The economy collapses and all of a sudden
people who are dependent on small changes in their lifetimes, wage workers collapse.
And then the entire system, the network of systems collapses, all because
the Department of Transportation closed down for two days. That's what happens in the human body.
That's the liability in some ways of multicellular existence. There are many advantages. We talked
about multicellular existence as advantages, but there are also liabilities because you depend on
your pancreas for insulin. You don't depend on your brain. Your brain doesn't make insulin.
Your brain doesn't make insulin. You depend on your brain for sensuous and consciousness.
You depend on your muscles for movement. Your brain can't produce movement without muscles.
And so there's a citizenship that bodies develop and have developed with each other
so that we together perform as organisms. Say it again, another personal question. How
much did you weigh the pros and cons of writing about such personal matters as your own depression?
I mean, we do still live in a world where it's not entirely clear to me why we view
depression different from hypertension. For example, if a person says,
I have hyperlipidemia and I take 10 milligrams of Lipitor a day. I don't think anybody bats an eye.
But if somebody says, I'm really struggling with depression and I take an antidepressant,
it just has a different valence to it for some reason. I don't, again, I don't know why that is.
I really don't. But in the presence of that knowledge, you still chose to talk about this
Why? Well, Peter, it was a very conscious choice. It was not unconscious. I talked to my family about
it. And I made the choice after that conversation. I agree with you. I think that depression is,
it can be what's called an organic disorder, a disorder in mood regulating neurons in your brain,
just like type 1 diabetes is an organic disorder, a disorder in the inability of pancreatic beta
cells to secure insulin. The reason it's different, I think, is that we associate a kind of victimhood
to mental disorders. And that kind of victimhood is punitive. It blames victims for being victims
in a way that you don't say that, oh, you're hypertensive because you
have genetics or behaviors, etc., etc., that are related to your hypertension.
But depression and mental disorders, grief, depression, and perhaps even more complex
disorders, schizophrenia, have a sense of blaming the victim and the victim being the person who's
the experiencing the disorder. That victimhood, I think, has to do with the idea of the brain
is separate from the rest of the body. It's a special organ. And yes, of course, it's a special
organ. There's no doubt about that. But on the other hand, it's also an organ that has physiology,
just like your pancreas physiology, just like your heart has physiology. And so what I wanted
to get away from is this idea of special victimhood and talk about the brain as a cellular cluster
which is just a cellular, in some ways, just a cellular cluster, like the pancreas or the heart
or the liver is a cellular cluster, and thereby remove this or defend or even challenge this
idea of victimhood and responsibility. Because most people who experience severe clinical
depression experience it as a consequence of, of course, of environmental and emotional stimulation,
the grief of dying, the grief of their situation, etc. But there are neuronal or nervous nerve cells
and nerve cell circuits that push them in biochemical and chemical ways towards the
state in which they cannot function. And I want to highlight that that absence of function,
if Virkha was alive today, Virkha would say that absence of function or that dysfunction
is not dissimilar to a person who has a failing heart or a failing liver. Because that function
is a dysfunction of mood regulating circuits and neurons in the brain, just as type 1 diabetes is
a dysfunction of insulin regulating cells in the pancreas. And that idea, again, is very important
and I think radical in this book and in all my books. I agree with you completely. I think it is
entirely radical and it's, I think, very difficult. I spoke about this with Carl Deseroth.
If you haven't read his book, by the way, it's a fantastic book as well.
I have read his book. It's incredible.
And Carl was a classmate of mine in medical school and he was equally brilliant then as he is now.
But he talks about this idea, right, which is it's this entire field of medicine,
I'm referring to psychiatry, for which we have not one biomarker, for which we have not one
radiographic finding that lends itself to a diagnosis. And so in the example of that
failing heart and that failing liver, I mean, we have a menu of things to aid in the diagnosis.
In fact, it's much easier to make that diagnosis today than when William Osler had to make the
diagnosis 125 years ago. I mean, today, a medical student can diagnose a failing heart and a failing
liver given enough data. And yet there's still this black box inside of our brains in some ways.
And I think I just, you know, I find it very interesting and I can't help but wonder
where we will be in 20 years. Like when I think about oncology today and I think about what the
wish for oncology is in 20 years, and I think about psychiatry today and psychiatry in 20 years,
I feel like there's even more potential in psychiatry. And of course, I think the potential
in oncology is enormous.
Well, I think you hit the nail on the head, which is to say that, you know,
biomarkers will help and are always helpful. But ultimately, it's a clinical decision.
When you see, I always tell people, you know, who haven't been in clinical medicine,
when you see depression, you know depression, you know that this person has a dysfunction of
the neural circuits that regulate mood, just like a patient with type 1 diabetes has a dysfunction
in the cells that secrete insulin. And even if there are no biomarkers, you know it.
This is what humans can see about other humans. There's a disproportionality or a
disconnection between the level of grief that a person experiences and the level of grief that
persists, the level of onui, the level of psychomotor inability to move that a person
experiences when they're when they're thinly depressed. So I think that there are,
even in the absence of biomarkers, I think that there is a new age that is coming.
And a respect, I think, for the autonomy of patients who experience neurological and
psychiatric diseases. And I think, as you said before, Deseroth writes about them
very carefully and very thoughtfully. There are many people, Andrew Solomon has written about
all of this. And I think it's very important because, you know, we could find therapies
for these. Some of them may be related to things that you and I are very interested in, like
alterations in diets, alterations in diets plus medicines, alterations in human physiology that
could reset brain circuits, electrical stimulation, as Helen Mayberg and others have been doing.
And to treat the problem as if it was, you know, just a problem that is sort of an epic phenomenon
is to minimize what the problem is.
Sid, there's so much more I wanted to talk with you about, but as not surprisingly, we've gone
pretty deep in a few things and there are topics like the entire immune system, the epigenetic
phenomenon and how we get into cellular reprogramming and Yamanaka factors. I mean,
we got through about half of what I wanted to talk about. So I think the only reasonable thing to do
here is to say, once the book tour is behind you, once we've both got a little bit more breathing
room, we should sit down again and do part three where we talk about some of these other factors.
You have a wonderful way of explaining complicated ideas. And frankly, I think perhaps the single
most important thing I wanted to talk about today, which was to bring all of this around
the future of science and the culture of anti-science that is propagating. I hesitate to
not touch on that now, but I don't think we could do it justice with a glib and short discussion.
With your blessing, I'd like to postpone that as yet another topic we can explore,
hopefully in 2023.
Would love to. And good luck. I love your podcasts and I love being on it.
Well, thank you, Sid. And congratulations again on another masterpiece. And I'm looking forward
to helping to spread the word so that many more people enjoy the, or experience the joy of reading
your work. Thank you, Sid.