Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
All right, Ethan, thanks so much for making time to sit down again. This is round two,
although I kind of don't remember when round one was. I think it was 2019, but it might
have been 2018, right?
I think it was 18, which is just a function of the fact that neither of us can remember
how long ago it was.
Yeah. Well, that time we spoke in person and we sat in your office at UCSF, but you're
sitting in a new office today and we're not in person, but more importantly, where are
you sitting today? And there's been a bit of a change in your life in the past year,
huh?
Yeah, so I did. It's been an evolutionary change over the past couple of years, but
I did have sort of a midlife crisis and decided that I didn't envision myself doing the same
thing I'd been doing for the prior 25 years for the next 25 years. If I should be lucky
enough to be around in 25 years. And I was given the opportunity to get involved with
the local group of investors who create biotech companies and they asked me to help them conceive
and eventually they started a new biotech company. So I closed my lab and have become
a volunteer clinical faculty at UCSF and see patients infrequently and spend most of my
time over here working to build this new company that I can at least tell you a little bit
about later on.
Yeah. Well, I know we're going to talk about some of the science that the company is interested
in because it factors in directly to what we wanted to talk about today. So there will
be a chance to talk about that for sure. But in some ways, this podcast is really just
a compilation of our email exchanges over the past couple of years. And so I think at
some point we said we should just do another podcast because we keep emailing each other
about these things. And I suspect as is often the case, there's value in sharing what it
is that we talk about with others. So let's just start with a quick recap of what a calcium
score is. And then we'll follow that up by what a CT angiogram is because I think those
two need to be understood to understand much of what we'll talk about in the next God knows
how long.
Yeah. So, you know, we talked about this the last time. I think I do remember that we spent
a lot of time talking about the distinction between calcium scanning and CT angiography.
And as we discussed last time, I think, you know, you've used the analogy before the calcium
scan that sort of demonstrates a site of a prior injury. What we know is that quantitatively
the amount of calcium that is in the distribution of the coronary arteries is correlated significantly
with adverse outcomes. So the more calcium you have in your arteries, the worse you do,
the higher the risk of both cardiovascular and all cause problems. And the reason we
suspect is that that calcium represents a healed plaque and that so the amount of calcium
you have in your arteries is strongly related to the amount of plaque you have in your arteries.
We know that the amount of plaque you have in your arteries is related to your risk of
having heart attacks and dying from heart attacks. So calcium scans are great ways to
kind of the way the analogy I use for my patients is that it's a sort of a satellite
image of your heart and gives you a sense of has there been damage there over your lifetime.
And then also gives you a nice adjunct indicator of your overall risk of dying from a heart
attack, which people like to know.
And one of the nice things about a calcium score is it's very, very low in radiation.
I mean, it's really, you know, even CTAs are now low. We'll talk about that. But the calcium
scan is a really low radiation and a very inexpensive tool as well. There are places
that are doing these scans for a couple hundred dollars nowadays.
Not all places.
No, that's the that speaks to the problem in US healthcare where you'll still find some places
charging 2000 while some will do the exact same scan for literally 200. But it needn't be an
expensive procedure. It's a low risk procedure. It doesn't require die. So it's effectively a
zero risk, low cost procedure that at least at the population level, as you say, has really great
insight, especially the first time it's done. Right.
Absolutely. And I think we talked about this the last time, but I'll just say it again for those
who weren't around back then that I did a full 180 on these. You know, when I first started
practicing as an independent cardiologist back in the early 2000s, I would get patients showing up
with these calcium scans. And I really sort of wanted to make them go away. I thought they were
annoying and I didn't know what to do with them. And it really has been a full 180. I do find value.
Obviously, there's epidemiologic value and understanding the risk of different populations.
But I do find that there is value in many contexts and even in individual patients. And we can talk
about which context I think are most valuable. It's certainly not everybody. I think, you know,
a calcium scan and a 25 year old is probably not worth anything. It's just not worth doing.
So, yeah, I think I've come around now to seeing the value of calcium scanning as a tool that I use
regularly. Yeah. And I know we did talk about this, but again, I've learned that one of the things
that makes podcasting difficult is it's very difficult for people to go back and listen to
them. There's just too much volume. So we should never apologize for repeating stuff that we talked
about more than four years ago. And the way that I kind of explain it to patients as well is that
if you have a two by two of sort of, you know, young versus old and zero versus non-zero as the
calcification, you know, there are two areas where the scan provides insight and there are two areas
where the scan doesn't really provide insight. And so one of them, as you said, you know,
if a 40 year old shows up, has a calcium scan of zero, haven't really learned a lot. And if a
calcium scan of zero in a 40 year old is accompanied by other risk factors, I would not be dissuaded
from aggressively treating those risk factors. And similarly, when an 80 year old with lots of risk
factors shows up and has a zero calcium scan, we'll talk about the false negative rate there.
All things equal, you might be less inclined to push for aggressive measures. Would you agree
with that framework? I do. Yeah. I think there's a group of very committed, whatever you want to call
them, calcium scanographers who believe in the power of zero and believe that a calcium score of
zero is meaningful no matter where it comes. But I just think that defies logic, right? You shouldn't
have any, if you shouldn't have any calcium when you're 25, I'm not sure what you learned there.
There may be edge cases where, you know, one in several million people will have some calcium,
but I just think mostly the two cases you described are where I find the most value.
Well, this gets to something that I think I've learned a little bit more about both through
personal experience and also just kind of spending more time in the literature on this is that a
calcium scan is a relatively imprecise measure. So the thickness of the slices that are used
in that scan are significantly greater than the CT, the slices that are used in the CTN geography.
And I'll give you a stark example of how I learned this in my own life. And I think I shared at least
part of this story last time, although clearly not all of it, because I just learned more recently. So
in 2008 or 2009, when I was in my mid 30s, I had my first calcium scan. Now, at the time my
doctor thought this was a crazy idea. I was 35. I was exercising at least 24 hours a week. There's
no seemingly relevant reason for me to waste insurance money and do this, but I had a horrible
family history and it didn't seem to make sense. It wasn't like everyone in my family was smoking
or anything like that. So anyway, I had the calcium scan and it showed that I had a score of six.
So I had a single foci of calcium in the proximal LAD. And interestingly, despite being in my mid
30s with that calcium score of six, nobody really seemed to care either. That was viewed as well.
I mean, look, your lipids are really not that bad. My LDL cholesterol was about 120, 110 to 120
milligrams per deciliter. So nobody took that terribly seriously. Of course, it changed my
life and it changed my interest in this field forever. Fast forward to 2016. So call it six,
seven years later, I went and had a CT angiogram and a calcium scan and the calcium scan had a
score of zero. The CT angiogram, which now is at much finer resolution, indeed found a tiny speck
of calcium in the proximal LAD. No other finding. Bob Peters, who is the remarkable radiologist that
now sees a lot of our patients explain to me, not uncommon at all. Like that little spec that you
had six years ago can easily be missed. If you had five calcium scans, half of them would miss it
because it's just too small. But now in the CTA, we can see it. So we repeated the CTA. Now I'm
just kind of partially interested in progression, more of soft plaque. I had it repeated very
recently. So call it 2022. This time the calcium score came out as two and the CT angiogram was
identical to what it was in 2016, six years earlier. So you could certainly believe that if I had a CTA
in 2008 or 2009, it would have looked similar. And you would argue that for basically the same
lesion, the score was six and two and zero in the, sorry, six and zero and two in that order.
Have you seen this yourself in patients where you've had the luxury of both longitudinal
assessment and simultaneous CAC and CTA? You know, I can't off the top of my head, I can't
think of anybody, but I would ask you, and this may be a leading question, but what were the
percentiles of those? I mean, I would imagine that calcium score of six when you were 35
was 99th percentile. It was 75th to 90th percentile at that age. That's right. Yeah.
Yeah. But there's a big difference even between six and two and a huge difference between six and zero.
Yes, exactly. Yeah. So I haven't seen it, but it doesn't surprise me.
Yeah, exactly. My guess is at a low enough calcium score, that's not uncommon. Of course,
that then got me into the literature and I realized that 15 percent of people who have a
zero calcium score have a finding on CTA that is either, as mine was, meaning a calcification
that was not picked up or a soft plaque. Furthermore, two percent or maybe it's one
and a half percent of those people who are deemed with a negative CAC have an unstable plaque on CTA.
It's not just the 15 percent that have something, but 10 percent of those people have something
that would be deemed relevant if we saw it on the CTA. Just back to our prior discussion on age and
utility of the scan, I would imagine, I don't know if they're familiar with the data, but I would
imagine that that 15 percent is largely represented in younger people or is that not the case?
I'd have to go back and look. It's a great question. I'd have to go back and look at the
study because it's been probably about six months since I looked at it. We'll find it and
we'll link to it in the show notes so that it's unambiguous and we'll include the table that
summarizes all this, which would hopefully include age. If not, it'll be in the fine print.
The other question I have for you, Peter, is over the course of the whatever it was,
15, 16, 17 years since your first calcium scan, what's your average APO-B been?
Yeah, so that's the point. It's been lower and lower and lower. That's
about the time I met Tom Dayspring and began to learn. I didn't know what APO-B was at the time.
At first, I was just bombarding LDLC and then that turned into really now targeting APO-B.
My target APO-B is between 30 and 40 milligrams per deciliter. That's where I aim to be
day in and day out. Obviously, that requires pharmacological intervention. Now, again,
I never really had a particularly high APO-B, but in some ways that actually gave me more concern,
Ethan, because I didn't have the obvious risk factors. I'm normotensive. I don't smoke.
My APO-B at the time was probably about 85 to 90 milligrams per deciliter. Very few doctors would
get phosphorylated over that APO-B in someone in their late 30s or mid 30s at the time.
But again, I watched countless men in my family die, some of them as young as in their late 40s
from heart attacks. You start to realize, A, this is probably quite polygenic, and B,
there's something going on here that's not just standard plug and play risk factor stuff.
Which, of course, is your practice. You get these really tough cases where it's not just,
oh, the LDL is too high. Yeah, it is my practice. Unfortunately, at least for now,
the only set of tools that we have are aimed at, well, I should say independent of blood pressure,
which is a different conversation we'll have later. But the tools we have now are focused
really on lowering the APO-B through any number of different means. I think we all expect that
there's something else there. There was clearly something else there in you. I mean, again,
it's hard to make the argument that you were sort of a ticking time bomb with a widow maker that
you were going to drop dead or a heart attack. You had a tiny minuscule lesion. The question
would have been what happened to you over the next 15 or 20 years had you not taken the intervention
that you did pharmacologically. Yeah, as I approach 50 now, I do find it interesting to play the thought
experiment of had I been on a different path in life, had I never looked at that 15 years ago,
had I never cared, what would it look like today? What would that CTA look like today?
How significant would that lesion be? Would there be others? Yeah. And my belief is that,
and we should obviously talk about this. I think that the epidemiology, the clinical trial data,
and the Mendelian randomization, to my reading of this literature, and I don't think there's
anything I pay closer attention to truthfully, is that APO-B is a necessary but not sufficient
criteria for atherosclerosis. And as such, removing it removes atherosclerosis. And so,
my best guess as to why there has likely been no progression of this disease in 15 years,
at least to the level that it can be detected by a CT angiogram, is that we've basically taken away
the causal agent. Yeah, I think I mostly agree with you. I think it's absolutely necessary. I
think the data really do suggest that if it's bottomed out, absent some really bizarre, probably
monogenic things that we don't see very often, that you can't get atherosclerosis. I think that's
demonstrated not just in humans, but across many other animal species. The one place where I might
quibble a little bit is that I do think it's probably sufficient in some cases, right? That
interesting, that in FH, for example, it's probably sufficient. In other words, I don't think you have
to have something else to get out through in cases where that APO-B is sky high.
The sufficiency is complicated, right? I mean, I suppose there are people with FH that don't go
on to develop ASCVD. Yeah, a lot. I mean, that's sort of the argument that the sort of, and I don't
know if we're going to get into this or if I ever want to talk about this ever again, but this lean
mass hyper nonsense, that's the argument that they make, that having a high APO-B is not sufficient.
It's definitely true that there are some people with FH who don't go on to have ASCVD. It's
interesting. I mean, obviously suggests some other genetic modifier or something else
that protects them. Yeah. I mean, so I think that one could argue that APO-B is not sufficient,
but is necessary, which is how I feel, and still take it very seriously because let's look at
another obvious example, which is smoking, right? And again, is smoking even, I would argue smoking
is even weaker, right? Smoking is neither necessary nor sufficient for the development of,
let's just pick lung cancer. Let's just pick the most smoking associated cancer, so small cell lung
cancer. Smoking is neither necessary nor sufficient, but there's nobody in their right mind that would
argue that not smoking, if in our analogy, that's the equivalent to reducing APO-B,
does not improve risk. Absolutely. Yeah. So I just think that to point to people with elevated APO-B
as an example of why it's safe has never made sense to me. And I'll tell you another reason it's
never made sense. I know I'm not going to get an argument out of you, but I'm hoping we can try to
formulate some argument here is there are other ways to treat APO-B besides diet.
And so I feel like if part of the argument for I need to have this APO-B high is because the diet
that's making it high is producing other benefits, that's sort of not necessary. One can consume a
diet that if it needs to be in a certain way and produce a high APO-B, you could still continue to
consume that diet and just pharmacologically address the APO-B problem. Yeah. It's the sort of
mind numbing in congruity of this whole discussion. And again, it makes my skin sort of want to fall
off. But yeah, no, I think you made a great point about smoking and frankly, any other risk factor
for any other disease. You know, replace smoking for coronary disease with smoking for cancer.
We all have lots of stories of people who smoke four packs of cigarettes a day.
Or even emphysema, right? You know, that where the toxicity is much more direct.
It's part of the nature of the heterogeneity of response, right? That this penetrance in this
case of an environmental factor is not 100%. I guess there are some that are, right? Cyanide
probably is. But most of the things that we encounter in our environment don't have that
level of penetrance in terms of causing risk. It's certainly not the ones that we encounter
frequently, right? Yeah. Yeah. So yeah, cyanide is a great example. 100% penetrance, carbon
monoxide at a certain concentration, 100% penetrance. Yeah. Okay. So let's go back to our discussion
and now contrast the calcium scan with the CTA. And then especially we'll use this to now explain
these other variations of CTAs that have shown up where they're more like software additions to CTA.
Sure. I mean, look, in what I tell patients is that what you get from a CTA is clarity and more
information, which in most cases is really, really good. And that comes at a small cost
in terms of increased radiation. And I guess some potential risk of the contrast,
although it's relatively small. The biggest cost and the biggest reason that I don't use it
in all of my patients in whom I'm thinking about these kinds of things is that it's hard to get it
paid for. So it is actually, in this case, more expensive if you pay for it yourself out of pocket,
which almost all of the calcium scans that I order end up getting paid for out of pocket. Almost
none of them as of today, at least are reimbursed by insurance. But as you said,
That's calcium scans, you mean, and CTAs. They're both just out of pocket these days.
No, no, no. Calcium scans are almost exclusively out of pocket. I would say 90 plus percent of them
are paid for by patients themselves. But again, as you said earlier, it's a couple hundred bucks and
almost everybody can make that leap and sort of convince themselves that it's worth, you know,
whatever it is, 10 Starbucks. So, but for CT angiograms, the cost is much higher. You know,
and again, I don't know, and this is one of the problems with their healthcare system. I don't
want to get distracted in that, but it's transparent to me what the cost is to my patients unless they
go and do some digging. And what's really annoying is that it's often not clear to them what they're
going to pay for until after they already have it. And so the cost of a CT angiogram is much
higher. It depends on the insurance that you have. And even if you pay out of pocket, so even if it's
not covered, the negotiated rate is going to be different based on whatever carrier you have. So
I would say much fewer than 50% of my patients have coverage. And we can talk about what would
justify coverage for a CT angiogram. And I've sort of gotten, I think, a little bit more
sophisticated in trying to be able to get around some of what I think are these sort of absurd
blockers for coverage. But then obviously, depending on the patient spending anywhere
from let's just say 700 to two or $3,000 on a scan may be more or less of an issue. And in some
patients, it's enough of an issue that they don't get it. So I think that's just worth
pointing out that in a world in which they were covered universally, and we could have access to
the data, that, in my opinion, at least, it provides so much more information than a calcium scan that
I'd probably just go straight there. And especially because in a lot of these cases we're talking
about, like you and your 35 year old self, these are cases where we just don't have a lot of data.
And the calcium itself is just not going to add that much.
So yeah. Yeah, I agree. And we kind of have that discussion with our patients as well,
which is that look, the IV contrast is virtually a non-risk outside of a handful of settings,
which are clearly well understood and can be, you know, we know how to handle those pretty well.
The radiation these days is so low. It's really in the neighborhood of two milli-seavers for a
person our size. So, you know, that's 4% of your annual allotment of radiation. But you're right,
the cost, I mean, we sort of assume 2000 to 2500 is pretty standard for that test.
When it's paid for out of pocket, it is, I would say that's probably average, but there are some,
for whatever reason, and I don't understand insurance in this country at all, but for
whatever reason, some insurance carriers are able to negotiate a lower rate for their members. And
so I've seen some people get, and it's very different institution to institution, right? So
you could go to UCSF and it would be $700, you might go to Stanford, it would be 1500 or the
other way around. And so I do advise people when it comes to these decisions, if the money is an
issue, which it is for almost everybody, because it's, you know, significant amount of money to
shop around a little bit. And then, you know, the question of sort of, all right, well, what do I
get for my money? And we know that right there are different scanners in different places, and those
different scanners provide different information in terms of resolution, but they also provide
differences in terms of how much radiation exposure. So that's another variable that we
kind of have begun to address a little bit. And those are the two things we always sort of say,
I mean, we have places we send people that we, because we know the answers to those questions,
but if it's not convenient for them, we're sort of saying, you've got to ask what the radiation
burden is. And it's actually, it can be a 10X difference. I've seen scanners out there that are
at 20 milli-seaverts. So now you're up to 40% of your annual allotment of radiation for one
screening scan, which, you know, personally, I think is too much. I just don't think it's
worth it, even if you're saving a bit of money. I agree. I agree. And it's just another layer of
complexity and sort of how you think about applying these different tests and getting
this information. It's just really important to make sure not to forget about it.
So every time I've had these CTA scans, you know, we get these beautiful images
and they're 3D reconstructed and then they're 2D sectioned. And, you know, we're looking at the
lumen, right? The tube of the artery. In both cases, that little speck of calcium shows up in the wall
of the artery. And then we're also looking for sort of soft plaque as well. And fortunately,
there hasn't been any, but that's, you know, soft plaque doesn't show up anywhere in the calcium
score. So you can have a significant burden of cardiovascular disease without any calcium. I
think that's the thing that maybe gets missed a lot. And that shows up in that 15% of people
who have a zero calcium score. A lot of them still have a significant burden of disease.
As you mentioned earlier, I mean, it could be that that calcification
where it's actually placed is not problematic. It's just that it's a harbinger of whatever it
took to get there. Do you look at patients with a high burden of soft plaque and no calcification
is even higher risk? I don't really, just because I don't think I buy that their data suggests that
I think a high burden of plaque period is a problem. Do I believe that a high burden of
calcified plaque might be less risky because it's more stable, I guess in theory, but it's super,
it's super, I get really nervous about sort of trying to impute plausibility and things like that
to drive clinical decision making. I think the reality is a lot of plaque is bad. I mean,
we know that people who have a calcium score of 4,000, which by definition means they've got a
shitload of calcium, that that's a high risk. And even if they don't have any soft plaque,
the risk is still high. So I don't pay too much attention. It's part of the reason why I actually,
if again, if everything else is equal, I prefer the information I get out of a CTA. Of course,
I'm greedy. I want more. And I feel like we just get so much more information and don't have to
make that distinction between soft and hard plaque. And frankly, I'm not sure we're at a point in
this field yet where we can make a compelling argument about plaque characteristics. It's been
a field that I think has evolved now since the early days, right? Since the 70s, probably when
the pathologists were doing autopsies on people who died of sudden cardiac death. And
we've been trying to understand the vulnerable plaque and different plaque characteristics and
what confers risk of rupture and ultimately of an event. I just don't think, at least in my
estimation, and I'm certainly no expert, it's not, we're not there yet. So I don't use it
anything other than as a sort of how much plaque is there tool.
Yeah, it's really interesting that we don't yet have a better tool to explain what vulnerability
means or to predict what vulnerability is, right? I mean, I think, do you think that in the research
setting, things like intravenous ultrasound or intravascular ultrasound, where they can actually
look and measure the thickness of the cap on the arthroma, do you think that in a theoretical sense,
those things are any better, even if they're impractical from a clinical perspective?
I guess, but ultimately, as a lot of things in biology, this is just so stochastic that it,
I think we might convince ourselves that it means something that it doesn't. So I think we've
learned a lot that, again, from the early days of even understanding that ruptured plaque leads to
a thrombosis over the surface of the ruptured plaque, and that's what causes a heart attack.
That was a debate until 1979, or even maybe even a few years after that. It really wasn't settled
until ISIS II was published in the late 1980s that showed that if you gave striptokinus or aspen,
you could reduce the risk. I think we've learned early on that it wasn't necessarily that 75 or 80%
or even 90% plaque that led to the big one, that oftentimes the plaques that ruptured and led to
sudden cardiac death were the smaller plaques, the 30% plaques, which kind of makes sense in the
context of how we think about, we'll all hear these stories and I'm sure you get patients coming to you
after somebody prominent dies. And I'll mention the name just because I think this is an example.
I don't know Cheryl, but when Cheryl Samper's husband died on a treadmill a few years ago,
I mean, I had probably 25 people call me that week to want to come in and get a risk assessment.
That happens a lot. I don't know anything about his case and I don't know anything about the
pathology, but my guess is in younger people who die of heart attack suddenly that oftentimes it's
a sort of relatively mild plaque that wouldn't trigger any discussion of revascularization
and wouldn't make anybody nervous at all that those are the plaques that end up causing
problems. And we can begin to weave together reasons why that might be, right? That maybe in
a person who's got more plaque burden, that there's more chance for ischemic preconditioning
and therefore the chance of an arrhythmic sort of malignant arrhythmic response to the ischemia
is lessened because of that. But I think my point is I don't think we have an understanding of,
to me, at least that satisfactorily would allow me to change the way I practice clinically based
on the characteristics of the plaque, even the volume of the plaque. And so for that reason,
I treat people with plaques, any plaque, 30% plaque, pretty much the same way that I treat people
with extensive plaque and I treat them maximally with sort of the best optimal medical therapy
I can offer. Yeah. So boy, we feel so similarly about this, Ethan, that we're going to have a
hard time coming up with some something to really clash about here because this is basically the
same discussion we have with our patients, which is I'm treating the causative risks, not the
end stage problems. If the goal is I need to wait until you have a 30% stenosis or a calcium
score of 200 to start acting, that's insane. It goes back to the smoking analogy. Right.
I want to tell someone that I want to tell somebody the second they pick up a cigarette
to put it down, not until I see that the pulmonary function tests are problematic or they've been
smoking for 20 years and their risk is significant. Yeah. And this is the sort of eye bleeding
experience that I have with insurance companies talking about adding PCSK9 inhibitors to what,
you know, sort of statins and whatever else they're on. And often they'll say,
well, they need to have an event first. And I'm thinking to myself, so backwards.
You're going to ask me to let my patient have a heart attack so that I can prescribe the drug
that's going to prevent them from having a heart attack. I mean, it's really incredible. And
hopefully we won't practice that way down the line. The problem of course is that, and I don't
want to get distracted, but all of these trials are so incredibly expensive to do that the
information that we're going to get from sort of the most rigorous randomized clinical trials is
going to be limited just because we're not going to be able to, you know, all the questions that I
want to ask and answer, I'm sure that all the ones you want to ask and answer are just not going to
be feasible to do because they're going to be overwhelmingly expensive. So we have to find a
way to be able to make decisions to treat patients independent of this gold standard level evidence.
And hopefully the insurance companies come around. Yeah. I've kind of accepted the fact,
Ethan, we're never going to have the gold standard evidence that we need in the most important
demographic, which is the demographic for whom we have the most runway to effect change. So in other
words, there will never be the study done in 40 year olds that says, what is the 30 year risk of
ASCVD in a cohort of 40 year olds, one group whose APO B is reduced to 30 because we've used a PCSK9
inhibitor plus or minus whatever other agent we need versus the group that's managed with
standard of care or some placebo or something else. And I mean, again, I feel more convinced of the
outcome of that theoretical trial than I do virtually any other theoretical trial I could
ever muster up in my brain. And yet it'll never be done. And therefore, there will never be an
evidence based case for true prevention of ASCVD. I say something very bold in my upcoming book,
which is that ASCVD should basically be an orphan disease. There's actually no reason it needs to be
the leading cause of death. It really doesn't even need to be in the top 10. It's that preventable if
you start early enough and if you're maximally aggressive. And really at that point, I think it
just becomes a question of working through the challenges of tolerating side effects in patients
who are sensitive. And I think there are going to be patients who are going to be challenging,
but with a long enough runway, this disease is sort of irrelevant. Let's talk a little bit about
these flavors of CTAs that keep showing up. So I guess we'll start with the CTA FFR,
because we did speak about it briefly. We don't have to go back into all of the detail of, and I'm
blanking on the name of the trial. There were two trials that looked at FFR in angiography.
Fame and fame too, I think.
That's right. Yeah, fame and fame too. I guess give the short version of what those trials
looked at, what the technology was, and then we can talk about the CT side of it.
Well, I mean the original FFR that was performed, that is still now performed in a cath lab is
basically a way to detect a pressure gradient across this diagnosis. So the simplest thing I
use to explain to patients is if you take a garden hose and squeeze it, that there's a gradient of
pressure. That there's going to be pressure proximal with your fingers squeezing the garden hose,
and the pressure on the other end is going to be lower. And that what they'd effectively do is
to put a wire with a pressure sensor on one end of the wire on the other end of the blockage,
and they put one on the near end of the blockage, and they can measure the delta. And that using a
mathematical formula that I've... You'll know the name of it. I'm blanking on it. You can impute
the diameter of the artery relative to the diameter of the unobstructed artery,
or the garden hose in this case. And so that gives you a way to get at the severity of the
blockage. And I guess what this stems from is a 40 year odyssey to try to take a very qualitative
measure, which happens in a catheterization laboratory, which is to measure the percent
stenosis, which is done if you've ever seen it. It's done very much by Gestalt. And the people who
are good at it are pretty good at it. But if you watch it, you understand that the difference
between 30 and 50 is probably not that meaningful. When there are severe blockages or stenosis, you
can all agree that it's really high grade. So I think of things in that high grade, modest and low.
So this has been one of a number of tools that have been developed to try to supplement the
information you get from that very qualitative assessment of visually how bad does that lesion
look. And many of these things have happened over the years. Ivis, you mentioned earlier,
is one of them. There have been a quantitative coronary angiography where they actually try and
take a cursor and electronically draw around the diameter of the vessel. Mike Gibson, back in the
old days, used to do this blush thing. I can't remember what it was called, but basically it would
count the number of frames it takes for the contrast dye to leave the myocardium. And that was
another indication of how severe the lesions were. FFR evolved as a sort of
hemodynamic way to impute the severity of this stenosis. And so I think FAME was the first of
these studies. And it showed that if you had a significant pressure drop, if the ratio of the
pressure and the sort of upstream sensor was much higher than the downstream sensor, that
conveyed that there was a bad lesion and that it conveyed worse outcomes in people
who didn't get stented. I can't remember the design of those. But basically-
Yeah. I think the idea was basically, look, there's no ambiguity in two subsets of people
who should be stented. So somebody who's actively having an MI, they show up in the
ED with chest pain, enzymes are leaking. I mean, we just go to the cath lab. There's no need to
putz around. Or I mean, what's the algorithm on clot dissolve versus stent in the active MI in the
ER? Oh, in the modern era, if there's a cath lab within whatever it is, I think, I don't know what
the exact number is in the latest guidelines, but it might be like 90 miles. It's really the
amount of time you have to calculate the amount of time it takes to get transported to a place
where there's a cath lab that does stenting, primary PCI. So primary PCI is the standard of care.
I think thrombolytics are used sparingly in this country, and only in remote places where there's
no access. Where they can't get to the cath lab. Okay. So in an ST elevation in my, it's primary
PCI is the standard of care, class one, the whole deal. And as quickly as you can get there.
And then the other indication in the non-MI setting is symptomatic, right? If you have a person who
for example, if someone has a stress test and on the stress test, you see ST changes,
is that an indication for a PCI as well? So we'll back up. So STEM, ST elevation MI is where there's
a complete and the physiology or pathophysiology is a complete obstruction of blood flow.
ST segments go up, you go in, there's no blood beyond the blockage. That's clear. Everyone
understands what we're now calling ACS, which we used to call unstable hands and our non-ST elevation
MI, which is not is same pathophysiology, right? Ruptured plaque, a thrombus sitting on the plaque,
but it doesn't completely obstruct blood flow. I think there's general consensus even among
some of the more conservative groups out there that those people benefit from going to the
cath lab early and having a stent to fix that blockage. I would say it's generally accepted
on the order of, I had to guess of 85 or 90% of people would practice that way. And what I mean
early, I mean within the first 24 hours. So it's not a sort of code level emergency where you,
you know, now most hospitals have these STEMI teams where they'll automatically, the emergency
department will page the pager and everybody comes in from the technicians in the cath lab
to the interventional cardiologists to the fellows and everybody else. They all just assemble there
to get there as quickly as possible. That doesn't happen. There's no STEMI activation for a non-STEMI
or a ACS event, but I think there's still general consensus that disease is treated best with early
intervention. And the only distinction between those people, Ethan, the only distinction is the
ST change on the EKG when they present. That's right. Yeah. I mean, that's the, that is the
distinction. And of course that is sensitive, but not a hundred percent sensitive. There are certain
lesions that are obscure, right? Where you would, you know, for example, a posterior MI,
you'd have to do posterior leads to be able to see that. So, but mostly it's STEMI is a, is a
emergency go straight to the cath lab, don't pass go. Non-STEMI or ACS is urgent. And generally
people end up in the cath lab and it wouldn't be a bad thing to have them go there, you know,
relatively quickly, depending on how unstable they are. Obviously, if anybody has unstable symptoms,
no matter what they have, in other words, if their blood pressure was labile or if they had heart
failure or ongoing chest pain that was refractory to medical management, then that would also become
a sort of don't pass go go straight to the cath lab. So I would say those things generally end up
getting stented. The, the, and this is a, this is my opinion, my read of the literature, but over the
past 15 years, what has changed is people with plaque, but without symptoms generally don't get
stented. Even the most aggressive interventional cardiologists, I won't mention names, would
probably agree that people who have a lot of plaque, maybe with the exception of proximal idea
of left mane, there might be still some people who would think, gosh, even without symptoms, I'm
going to put, I'm going to put a stent in this person. But generally people with, with plaque,
no matter how bad the plaque looks angiographically, those people are treated medically if they don't
have symptoms. Where things have gotten interesting is in these cases for symptoms, right? Because
I think most of us, when you say symptoms, Ethan, you mean symptoms in day to day life,
or do you mean under stress and provocation? Yeah. So no. So rest symptoms is unstable
symptoms and that falls into that first category. And those people would be, should be hospitalized
and they would go in that first 24 hour window. So any symptoms at rest without doing anything,
we can debate about what, what is like, what happens if you have an argument with your wife
and you get chest pain, is that unstable or stable? You know, but mostly it's the sort of
non-classic exertional angina where you're walking up a hill and you get chest pressure,
you get chest tightness or rarely pain. You stop, it gets better. You take a nitrocloser and it gets
better. Classic stable angina. So people have plaque, but do not have stable or unstable
symptoms at all. In general, these days are treated medically with some exceptions. It's the people
who have this classic stable angina, stable symptoms. So they go out and walk up a hill and
they get chest tightness, you know, feels like somebody's tightening a belt around their chest.
They stop, it gets better. It's those people who I think are kind of the most interesting today
in the contemporary practice setting. And those are the people I think that require the most
thought. And I think, you know, we, we hadn't put it on our list of things to discuss. I don't
remember if we discussed, you know, these trials the last time around, but, but obviously courage
was the trial that sort of taught us that it's okay to have a lot of plaque and not necessarily
intervene on it. There have now been several other trials to get at that question of is,
is, and this is part of the reason why fame is to me, like not that interesting,
because we've kind of already answered the question in all comers that stenting people
without symptoms, even if they have some significant lesions doesn't offer a benefit
over optimal medical therapy. There's, there's now, I think, some discussion around even patients
with symptoms, whether they, the range of opinion I think goes from anybody with symptoms should be
stented or re-vascularized, you know, in edge cases with bypass. Some people think, you know,
medical therapy in all cases. And then I think there's sort of this nuanced in between people
who think give a trial of medical therapy and see if you can get the symptoms better. It's not an
automatic take to the cath lab, but try to optimize medical therapy. And if you can make
the symptoms go away, then there's no need to go and stent that artery. And that's probably where
I land right now is I don't, I still use interventional cardiology. I certainly don't
use it as much as I did in the past, but I do use it for people who do have what I would consider to
be refractory symptoms. And then obviously for the unstable sort of emergency acute settings,
that's a different story. And if you had a patient with a really high calcium burden,
so they're north of a thousand, and they never experienced symptoms, which, and they're young,
they're, you know, in their fifties or something like that. Would you put them on a treadmill and
push them as hard as you could possibly go and assume that like, Hey, they're not necessarily
exercising that hard every day. I want to really see if they have any ST changes or
wall motion abnormality when I make them, you know, go to 15 minutes.
I don't, but because, because like I said, I sort of land in that camp of,
even if you had symptoms, I'd still medically managed them medically. Yeah, probably I would
still try to optimize medicines. Now, if somebody came in and was on great medicines and was still
having symptoms, then obviously it's a different story. But yeah, I don't routinely do anything to
people who have high calcium. In fact, if you have a high calcium score, whatever it is, a thousand,
it to me, it triggers a response. And it's the same. I don't think you need a CTA in that case.
And in fact, the CTA might not be very useful because there may be so much calcium that kind
of obscures the ability to be able to see into and beneath the vessel. So, and it's to me,
I don't automatically do stress testing in somebody like that. I often will see patients who've
been completely freaked out by the result and that, and they'll have had a big workup,
including potentially stress testing and, and a CTA engineering, but, but I don't do that. And,
and I likewise don't do any routine stress testing anymore as a way to follow coronary disease.
That was something we used to do in the old days when somebody had a lesion, you knew they had a
lesion, you'd kind of exercise them over once a year or something to see how they progress that.
I don't do that anymore either. Okay. So in light of that fame, if I recall,
basically said, or sought to answer the question, if you took a bunch of asymptomatic people
and you did this FFR on them, you measured the fractional flow reserve.
If you took the people who had a pressure drop of, I think it was either 30% or more,
I think it was a 0.7 P2 to P1. Yeah, something like that. It was either a 20 or 30% drop.
If those people automatically got stented and the others did not, and these are both asymptomatic,
would we see better outcomes in the more aggressive stenting strategy? Isn't that
effectively what the trial was? That was the design and that was the result. And,
and so therefore that became standard of care in a cath lab. In most cath labs that,
in fact, we were doing FFR and a lot of patients were, yeah, initially FFR was there for these
end cases where you weren't sure is this significant or not? Should we stent it? Should
we not stent it? I think it went through a period. I think it's now come back, but I think it went
through a period where it was being used a lot based on fame with the sort of assumption that
you're impacting people's outcome, hard outcomes based on your decision-making and that there were
certain groups of people who benefited tremendously from getting stented. And our job was just to
identify who they were. On the surface, that's not an absurdity, right? That's definitely a
possibility. But I think, you know, after however many years now of understanding the data,
I think the consensus is it's just not necessary. I think really mostly it comes from the sort of
line of evidence that we've had through, you know, courage, ischemia, orbiter, all these different
trials showing really that the take-home is that optimal medical therapy, even in a mildly
symptomatic person patient is quite effective. So all of this basically is prelude to
a CT based version of this study, which of course can't do the intervention,
but it can identify people who are getting CTAs, which are far more than the people who are getting
traditional angiography to say, hey, maybe you do need an intervention. So again, in theory,
the idea here is, well, you've got a CTA, I see a stenosis there, it's a 50% stenosis.
Is it significant or not? I can't tell. I don't have a pressure transducer in there that I can
measure, but I can run this algorithm on it and the algorithm will tell me what the pressure drop
is. So of course, question one is how successful is that algorithm? I don't know myself. I assume
that there was a head-to-head that was done where you had a whole bunch of people that actually had
cath that actually had pressure transduction and then concurrently had CTA, and then they could
actually see how predictive they were. I have to believe that was done right.
Yeah, there was a trial. I don't remember the details of it. I guess the questions are in my
mind, so does the physics, and I don't understand the physics, but does it make sense? Can you
actually really make this calculation in a meaningful and reproducible way in these people?
I imagine back in the day when the method was being validated, that there were some comparisons,
the FDA required some comparison to be able to say that this is just as they probably required
something to clear the FFR catheters themselves. They probably required something. It probably
was close enough. I don't have any knowledge that the thing is a random number generator.
To me, that's a distraction. I think there are plenty of people who go down that path. To me,
the question remains what are we doing? And really, in the way I practice, do we need to identify
asymptomatic people who are at higher risk? Is there a group of these people who
are special and might show something that no other group of patients has ever shown in the
history of interventional cardiology, which is a benefit from stenting? I know that my
interventional cardiology colleagues are going to hate what I just said,
but we've been doing this for a long time now. We've been looking for any group of people who
would benefit from outside of the Akitamai setting, which we've talked about, any group of people who
would benefit from a stent being placed in their artery. And we've had a hard time doing that.
It's not for lack of track. It's been, I mean, again, courage, which sort of was the beginning
of the end of this in some way, since that was a trial that was conceived of and executed by a
group of interventional cardiologists who wanted to demonstrate the superiority of stenting
over medical therapy. It was designed that way. And all the bias was weighted towards getting
that outcome. It did not get that outcome. And frankly, there have been however many dozens of
studies since then. And at least from my point of view, there's nothing that screams at me that,
hey, look, our job as preventive cardiologists or thoughtful internists should be to go looking for
people who might benefit from a stent in the absence of symptoms. And that's where I'm left
today is that I don't see any evidence yet that there's something magical about some group of
people where they derive that much more benefit from a stent beyond truly optimal medical therapy.
And I think, as you said earlier, if everybody got truly optimal medical therapy, like if we
didn't have barriers to using all these tools in everybody, I think this disease would largely
be controlled. Now, I do believe there's something else going on that's residual.
And you're an example, I think potentially. But yes, I think the quality of the medical
therapy we have today is so good that it's going to be really hard to demonstrate the value of
stenting people. That assumes that stenting doesn't do something harmful. And again, I think that's a
open question. Why, if you have a very high grade lesion, even before there was great PCS
canine inhibitors, they were just ZOCOR or something, why wouldn't opening that artery lead to improved
outcomes outside of the Akita mice setting? That's a question that always plagued me,
even as a cardiology fellow, I was like, well, this doesn't make any sense. It should. You're
opening up an artery that's severely blocked and restoring blood flow back to the heart.
And there are lots of explanations for why that might be. I don't think we have a good one,
but you could imagine that in going in there and blowing up a balloon inside that artery and
deploying a stent that you're elaborating the contents of that plaque downstream. And much
like what happens when you break up a beaver dam in a stream, it's just going downstream and causing
its own set of problems. That's just me speculating and making it up. But to me,
it's an interesting question. Why it wouldn't be. Has the study been done, for example,
where they take a group of individuals who were asymptomatic at the time of being stented,
or they weren't being stented in an acute STEMI, who then go on to have subsequent events, what
the location is of the plaque. In other words, when a person gets stented in the mid-LAD,
and they go and have another event, is that other event more, can we identify a pattern?
So for example, is it distal in the LAD? Is it in a part of the heart where you could say,
maybe there was some mechanical change that took place as a result of that stent,
or maybe it was, hey, you know what? The reason it doesn't work is you're playing whack-a-mole,
and this person had lots of disease. You just happened to pick the one that had the most
stenosis, although stenosis by itself is actually a really crappy predictor of future events. So
you weren't more likely to do anything here. Maybe if you stented the entire vasculature,
you would have, but of course you can't do that. So it really comes down to how lousy is
plain up stenosis as a predictor of subsequent events.
Well, I think it's a good predictor that as we discussed earlier, these plaques that end up
leading to bad things often are not the plaques that would be get stented anyway. So I think
there's that. And that's my point, right? Because another explanation, which I think you had a good
one is if you have a 90% stenosis and you haven't experienced symptoms as a result of that yet,
that's probably telling that if you throw a clot there, you're going to survive it.
That's right. Because there's collateralization and we know that, right? From seeing these,
you know, you can see that. And that's probably the mechanism, right? That this ischemic
preconditioning leads to this growth of collaterals. And basically it's like,
if there's an accident on the freeway, it's like I tell my patients that you get off on the side
streets and you wind your way through, it takes a lot longer. And it's not great when there's like
a lot of traffic, but if there's no traffic and it's relatively light flow, you do fine.
Right. But that 30% lesion hasn't been tested yet. No, it hasn't.
So you don't really know how it's going to respond.
Because you would never send a 30% lesion. Yeah. So there's that. And then the other thing I think
is that if you look at, and now with the advent of sort of high sensitivity troponins and other
more sensitive measures, if you look at say troponin or CK elevations after a long intervention,
they most certainly go up, not in all cases, but they do go up. And so the question is,
are you doing, are you basically creating a little MI in the process of putting the stint in? And
does that then cause downstream risk in the form of arrhythmias or other issues, you know, later on
in life? That to me is sort of an interesting thing to think about it. Obviously there's no
great data at this point, but I think there are data, at least observational data, looking at the
area under the curve of the troponin elevations post PCI as a predictor of outcomes. I think
obviously the more troponin you have, the worse you do, as you'd expect.
Okay. So there was this study that I don't think is published yet, but I think you and I saw it in
email to each other about, was it, was, is it the precise trial that we saw the abstract for?
Remind me. This is the one that did the, I think this is the one that did the FFR
and it found no difference in all cause mortality, no difference in mace,
but a reduction in the need for catheterization. Right. Yeah. So this has now become the sort of
value add of doing these non-invasive adjuncts to CT and geography. And it's the reason that we
at UCSF now do CTFFR on not all of it, most of the CTAs that we do, is that in theory,
you've reduced the number of people who go to the lab. You only reduce the number of people who go to
lab if you send people to the lab. If you're not sending people to the lab, you're not reducing
number of people. So again, to me, it comes back to the primary issue, which is that people
with plaque probably, you know, in the absence of symptoms, people with plaque should probably be
optometically medically treated and left alone. And that taking it in the cath lab is a very little
value. And obviously if they get to the cath lab, the chance of them getting stented goes up
astronomically, once they're there. So yes, you do theoretically prevent unnecessary stents
with CTFFR, but you can do that without the FFR. You don't need the FFR.
Yeah. I think that's really well said, right? Because to me, I don't get hung up when a study
like that doesn't find a difference in ACM, because I think that's a short time horizon.
But I do get a bit alarmed when there's absolutely no difference in MACE, right? When you see
no difference in anything related to cardiac pathology. And the only difference is an
algorithmic difference that to your point, you can make on your own. Again, I think we should
maybe reserve judgment until the final study is published. I mean, so we'll wait for that. I don't
know when that's coming out, but I found myself very underwhelmed by this and it didn't change my
thinking, which is that at this time I'm struggling for the use case of FFR. And as such, we really
don't employ it with our patients. I think that the issue is you have all these levers you can
pull. And so your job is to figure out which levers am I going to pull. And I think sometimes
people overcomplicate it, right? That there are going to be relatively low risk people whom you
could get away with statin or maybe statin and a very low dose of Zetia. I mean, in my opinion,
if you have plaque, significant A plaque, they say a 30% plaque or greater in an artery,
in your coronary vasculature, I'm pulling all the levers. I don't need any other information.
Like I don't need more. And that's a pretty good intervention, pulling all those levers.
By the way, to your point earlier, let's just assume there's something in me that's off.
I think the fact that the moment I had a six score Ditzel, every lever got pulled. That's probably
why 15 years later, it looks like a Ditzel still, nothing's changed, which means
if we just pulled all the levers all the time, we could kind of take this disease off the table
for virtually entire population. This is the mission statement of my friend,
say, Catharines' company, Verve. I mean, they want to CRISPR out PCSK9, not necessarily initially in
everybody, but he believes that if you can do that, you'd eradicate this disease. I don't totally
agree with him, actually. We disagree a little bit on some of these things. But in general,
I think he's probably right. The question is, do you need to go to that extreme to be able to
solve for this problem? And could you apply that solution to everybody, feasibly worldwide?
That's his problem to think about, not mine.
That's a very, and I'm going to, yeah, I'd love to have Seth on to talk about
many of these things. Okay, so let's talk about two other things before we leave CTA.
There's the fat attenuation index, FAI. What is that exactly?
I actually, I'm going to be totally honest. I have no idea.
Okay. You've seen it, I assume.
It's been, if to be presented to you.
Maybe, I guess. I sort of have learned in now doing this for as long as I have.
Right. I mean, so I graduated from medical school in 1996 and did my residency for two years and
then started my cardiology fellowship here 25 years ago. So I've sort of learned to tune out,
like put blinders on and to some of this stuff, just because it's something new every
like few weeks. It's been that way, like consistently. So I'm sorry, I'm not like
completely up to speed on this latest and greatest fat attenuation index. I imagine it's some CT based
way to look at the characteristics of the plaque and to see if it's potentially vulnerable. Is that
the idea? No, it looks, and I'm not an expert in this. I was hoping you were. So it basically,
it is a CTA bolt on just like the FFR is, but it looks at the characteristics of the fat
around the plaque. Yeah. So it's not trying to predict vulnerability per se. It's actually
trying to predict how much inflammation is, I hope I'm getting this right, but I think it's
looking for how much inflammation is around the plaque. I see. That's interesting. That's
interesting. I don't, not familiar. I am familiar with PET CT. The amount of it you can measure
using FTG PET, you can measure the amount of inflammation in a plaque that can be done
quantitatively. There's a group of people who've been doing that for years. And I think
certain pharmaceutical and biotech companies have used that as a way to kind of gauge efficacy
in evaluating new molecules to see if they can have an impact there.
That I don't think has been being used now clinically, at least to my knowledge and
routinely. I'm not familiar with the fat attenuation index. It kind of makes sense.
So it's, it's epi-cardial fat. That's right. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. I mean, it's an interesting
idea, right? I mean, epi-cardial fat is visceral fat and there's, it probably does impact risk in
some way. Again, what are you going to do with that information? You're already pulling all the
levers. I guess maybe you'd focus a little bit more on metabolic stuff, I guess.
Which we'll come back to. Okay. Let's now, let's pivot to another topic that seems to come up from
time to time online, I guess, which is are there subsets of people who, in whom an elevated CAC
is not a predictor of risk? So there's been some confusion about this. I think it's maybe worth
clarifying this for folks. So James O'Keefe has commented on the fact that certain athletes,
you know, who exercise a lot, so very high degrees of cardio respiratory fitness might have a higher
frequency of coronary calcification. So let's first talk about that. How robust are those data?
And more importantly, what does it mean? Yeah. Well, I think it's plausible. I mean,
we know that sort of increasing sheer forces across an endothelial surface can certainly
lead to damage and that would potentially increase calcification. We know that
in, say, patients with a bicuspid aortic valve, that people who exercise at extreme levels do
appear to have an increased rate of calcification of that valve. And I say appear to because none of
these studies are controlled. But it does seem that that's the case and it makes sense and is
plausible as dangerous as that word is. I think the same thing could be true in a coronary
artery vascular bed. The increasing sheer, as you would expect to by increasing flow, as you would
during extreme exercise could potentially lead to some damage and therefore calcification.
So I do think it's plausible. I guess I don't, I still don't think, and sorry, I do think there
is this one example where there is a disconnect between the amount of calcification in the artery
and the amount of risk and that is within people taking statins. And that's a very difficult
concept for people to grasp. And frankly, it's a difficult concept for me to explain.
And I do find myself getting tied up and trying to explain it. And I can make up explanations like,
what you're doing is healing the plaque and stabilizing the plaque, which we think statins
are doing and that that's a good thing and not a bad thing. But I think that's incontrovertible
that statins probably do increase the risk of calcification despite lowering the risk of events.
So there is this one example. So is it possible that exercise could be similar to that? Maybe.
But we don't have the flip side, right? We don't have the 40 years of really rigorous
randomized trials showing that some exercise versus some version of placebo does that. Would
I say don't exercise? Absolutely not. Would I still tell some patients not to exercise to that
extreme level? I don't know. I'm on the fence there. And the question is, what's the, so each,
let's just assume that it is the case that high, high amounts of cardiorespiratory fitness come
at the expense of some endothelial damage. Again, I don't know if it's true, but I agree with you.
There's certainly mechanistic plausibility there. The question is, if a person goes from
call it, I don't know, 50 met hours per week of exercise to a hundred met hours per week of
exercise. And let's assume that doing that increases their calcification. A, is that with
or without more risk? Let's assume it is with more risk, but is that risk more or less than
the benefit that they gain going from the 25 or 50 to the hundred met hours a week of exercise?
In other words, this is what makes exercise a bit more complicated here, which is most of the other
things that are increasing the burden of calcification are net negative, right? Obviously,
smoking more, having higher blood pressure, having worse lipids, but the correction of that moves in
the same direction as the correction of the calcification works in the same correction of the,
as the calcification of works in the same direction as the improvement of the risk
modifier with exercise is not the same. What's I think unambiguous though, and we were talking
about this earlier, more exercise is better than less and more calcium is worse than less.
I've yet to see an exception to that rule. That is according to the thing.
I agree with you. And I think that discordance is only mimicked by the statin story, right? Where
we need more spattens are better and also lead to more calcium. Look, here's the thing. If you
put it back into sort of the terms in the context of a patient comes to me and says, Hey, I got this
calcium score of whatever, let's call it 800, I don't know, whatever you want to call it 500,
300, 200, 100. But I don't think it means anything because I exercise a lot. Like that's
the question, right? That's the question that gets presented to us sort of at an individual level.
And I guess what I'm saying is that I'm not yet comfortable saying, Oh, don't worry about that.
Whereas I am comfortable saying, don't worry about that if it's because they're on a statin.
And so what I would say to that patient is we have to assume that that calcium is representative of
plaques in the arteries and that having plaques in the arteries is a bad thing.
And that we should treat you accordingly, even though you exercise a lot. And if you want to be
sure, then we can do a CT angiogram to kind of see how much plaque you actually have.
Because, you know, I don't know any evidence that this calcification is not plaque related,
that it's somehow extra vascular calcification or beyond the, it's in the intima or something
or media, I guess. But that's how I would approach it today is I just can't tell you,
I can't give you a free pass on the calcium because you exercise a lot. Exercising is great.
Keep exercising. Don't stop exercising. But I think the burden of proof is on us to show
that that is not risky. And if we did a CT angiogram and it showed you didn't have any plaque and
all the calcium is sort of extra vascular somewhere else, then sure, I'm sure you're
okay with that. But that if we do it and we see plaque, I'm not aware of any data that would say
let's not treat you. Which is sort of the subtle but important difference between the statin store,
because the people on statins are already by definition on the risk reducing therapy
that's been shown to save lives. So like, it's not like, what are you going to do to that person
because their calcium score is higher? You know, would you be more aggressive, I guess,
is one question people might ask. But I think it's a little bit of that's the difference is that
there's that lever still to pull and the exercise person is that 90.
So what percentage of your patients take statins?
I mean, it's a completely biased group of people because it's all of course, of course.
90, I'm guessing. And is the implication that the five to 10% who don't
have some side effect that they aren't able to tolerate?
Right. There's those for sure. Although I think that's less frequent now because
would you say statin or any other like or PCS-kinine inhibitor? Because I do have
a few patients.
No, I would just say statin to start because what I want to sort of explore for a moment is
what are the real world implications of the use of these drugs? What are the real world side
effects? What are the real world conditions that prevent people from being maximally
medically treated?
Small number of patients of mine who don't take them because of true side effects.
Equally, maybe even slightly larger group of patients who don't take them because they're
afraid of them. And I don't mean that to be pejorative. I think there's been a tremendous
campaign, a propaganda campaign to demonize statins that's been going on for a long time,
25 or 30 years. And it's been very successful and people are terrified of statins. And
there have been documentaries made on how statins are poison and they're killing people.
And while not everybody or even maybe most people are aware of that,
plenty of people who spend any amount of time online are. And so that is, I do spend a lot
of time with patients who come to see me because I have some openness to at least having that
conversation with them and I'm not going to force them. I have a patient of mine who came to see me
with a tremendous amount of skepticism, had every risk factor, was probably having angina when he
first came to see me. And I recommended that he start taking a statin that first day and he was
afraid to because of stuff that he'd read about how dangerous they were. He ended up, needless to
say, a few months later in the ER with an acute MI and fortunately the outcome was good. He ended
up with a stent. He's stayed on a statin ever since then. So that sort of was enough of an
experience for him to change his mind. But I have a number of people who just flat out either won't
or it takes me years to convince them to. Years. I mean, some people I've seen for years, I've had
the same conversation year after year after year after year. And some people never changed their
mind. Some people change their minds because of other things happening like this patient having
an MI and some people change their minds because finally they are convinced. But I never force it.
What's the core belief that's at the root of the fear you think? I mean, again, and I say this just
acknowledging that probably about 5% of patients are going to experience muscle side effects that
are going to warrant not taking a statin because it's going to impede in their quality of life.
But so if you just acknowledge unemotionally that there are side effects, you're going to see
transaminase elevations that are just too much, especially if mixed with Zetia. But if you
acknowledge all of those things, there's obviously some deeper seated fear in something that can't
be seen or measured or quantified. Where do you think that comes from? Why don't we see that with
other classes of drugs to the same extent? I think we do. I just think this happens to be
one of the most prescribed classes of drugs in the history of humankind. And so
it's just the denominator is bigger. I think this is sort of the same thing that gets at a lot of
skepticism around science and big pharma. And there's a whole world of people out there with
these vast conspiracy theories about the development of statins and about how Rory Collins is an evil
person. He's engineered this whole conspiracy to try to get the whole world on these poisons.
I mean, there are people out there who really believe that. And look, if you hear something
enough and you aren't an expert and don't have access to all the data that we have access to,
it can be compelling. And I've watched some of these documentaries. They're terrifying. Just as
I'm sure the documentaries were made after the Wakefield experience in the late 90s were
terrifying to young mothers who were worried about giving their kids MMR vaccines or whatever,
any other. I think it's very easy to convince people to be scared of something.
It's a lot harder to make people unscared of something. And this is just an example,
I think, where there's a group of people out there who just don't believe in this whole
enterprise. They're, for whatever reason, very skeptical of big science and big pharma. And
don't get me wrong. Obviously, there are plenty of things that big pharma has done wrong. And
we can go through the examples of that. This happens not to be one of them. The sad thing
about how demonized statins have been is that it's one of the most profoundly important interventions
that we have in modern medicine. And it's astonishing to me that this is being compared
effectively to smoking, right? To cigarette companies. I haven't heard that comparison,
but certainly people will quickly point to Purdue and the opioid crisis has proved positive that the
pharma entities are evil. And it's again, it's there's no question that Purdue pharma is indeed
evil. And again, I've said this before on the podcast, I think it's really difficult for us
as a species to think dialectically and to hold seemingly contradictory truths simultaneously that
pharma companies can do good things and bad things. And that seems to be true across the board. That
seems to be true of every person as well, right? Any given individual can do something good and
something bad. The exceptions would be those that are universally good or universally bad
as people. Right. Yeah. I mean, I think there are people out there who just
are clearly bad. And yeah, there are people who are probably clearly always good. And yeah, again,
I'm not even I'd like to meet I'd like to meet them. Yeah. Okay, let's let's talk about blood
pressure. Because I think this is one of those areas that I've personally become more and more
interested in over the past year. And it's actually become more of a concern to me maybe
over the past two years through the lens of the kidney. So we have this organ that just doesn't
get much attention. I'm trying to think outside of my podcast with Chris Sananday, where we talked
about kidney and liver transplantation. I don't think I've got a single podcast that deals with
the kidney. And it's a really special organ. And I sort of explained to my patients that
in our bootstrapping approach to living an extra few years on this planet, a lot of it requires a
phase shift in time. Right. So if you're 50 years old, you really need to be held to the standard of
a healthy 40 year old, if you want to live an extra 10 years, that's the way you want to think
about it. You want to think about that in terms of your mind, you want to think about that in terms
of your body, you want to think about that in terms of your coronary arteries, want to think
about it in terms of your bone density, but you got to think about it in terms of your kidneys.
And so when we look at a person and estimate their glomerular filtration rate, which we use,
you know, cystatin C to measure that we've largely abandoned creatinine.
It's really tempting to say, well, you know, this guy's 55 years old, his EGFR is 70 mils per minute.
That's good enough. But in reality, it's not actually. It's far from good enough. And
the kidney is not uniquely, but exquisitely sensitive to high blood pressure.
Again, I'm not a nephrologist and I never really, I don't think I remember much from nephrology, but
I certainly remember that something about its vasculature is incredibly sensitive, right? It
probably has to do with the fact that it's such a tiny organ that takes such a high amount of our
cardiac output. And I suspect just like the heart and the brain, it's very sensitive to pressure.
And so that really is the lens through which I think about this first and foremost with the
meaning even the slightest amount of elevation in blood pressure is going to interfere with
long-term kidney health and also with heart and brain health. So really, there's a win across the
board if we just normalize blood pressure. So I'll posit that and have you just kind of explain
from the ASCBD perspective, the importance of blood pressure and how it stacks up with
smoking, APO-B and some of the other heavy hitting risk factors.
Yeah. So I guess I just want to acknowledge how strongly I agree with you about the neglect,
how much we neglect the kidney as an organ and nephrology as a subspecialty of medicine.
I actually used to give a lecture on hypertension in the first year of medical students at UCSF.
And I did that in conjunction with a kidney pathologist who interestingly had been at Hopkins
when I was a medical student was my advisor, very interesting woman who's now retired named Jean
Olson. And she and I co-gave the lecture, she gave the pathology part and I gave the
clinical part. And I learned so much about the importance of the kidney and regulating blood
pressure in that, in giving that lecture with her for however many years it was, 10 years.
So it's both an important cause of blood pressure. And in fact, I think if you go back and look at
Rick Lifton, who's sort of one of the premier human geneticists in history, member of the National
Academy, some probably should win a Nobel Prize. He characterized all of the single gene mutations
that lead to extreme increases or decreases in blood pressure. I think at the time,
and this is 20 years ago, there were like 10 single gene mutations that led to people who had
really, really low blood pressure had to constantly supplement salt and do things like that. And then
10 that led to extremely high blood pressure. And I think like 19 out of 20 of these things
were located in the same location in the proximal collecting doctor in the tubule. It was like,
you couldn't have picked a place that was more important evolutionarily for how we handle volume
and salt and solute. So it's an incredibly important organ both as a cause of high blood pressure
and also as a consequence. And those experiments, you know, Jean showed these beautiful slides that
I'll send along sometime, you know, pictures of what happens to your kidney after it's exposed to
increased levels of blood pressure over time. So it was interesting because I was giving this
lecture as a cardiologist during the kidney block. It always felt, I felt out of place.
So most people kind of know that when they go to their doctor and they get their blood
pressure checked, normal is about 120 over 80 millimeters of mercury. What do we know about
how much that changes in a healthy person across the course of the day? So when they're sleeping,
when they're ambulatory and walking around, but not under stress, i.e. not exercising,
when they are exercising vigorously, when they're, you know, under stress, physiologic stress,
psychological stress, all of these different things that we do every single day, surely our
blood pressure must change. And yet most of us, myself included, have virtually no idea of how our
blood pressure is changing under those situations, even if under perfect optimal conditions, i.e.
sitting down, legs uncrossed for five minutes, it reads 120 over 80. So what do we know about the
rest of the time? So I guess it's, we don't, I don't want to get too distracted, but I think
it's fascinating. I've thought about this a lot. And the question of what's normal is, you know,
we all assume 120 over 80 is normal. If you look at blood pressures across different animal species,
it's mostly in that range. There are some that are outliers. Obviously a giraffe is,
is the best example of an outlier species with much higher blood pressure that it needs to have
to be able to pump blood up to that very, that head that's sitting way up high. It is weird to me
from an evolutionary perspective, why we would have the same blood pressure as a mouse,
right? It's a little tiny creature who walks around on four legs. Why should we have the same
blood pressure? It speaks, I think, to the conservation of this sort of vascular system
that we have. I think most people when I was a medical student, I'm sure you were the same,
were taught that 120 over 80 is normal, but that's just normal. Whether you're,
you know, 7, 17, or 75. I don't think we have a good understanding of, well, we have an understanding
of what is epidemiologically normal as we age. And so we know that blood pressure does go up with
each decade of life. If I had access to that lecture I used to give, I could show you what
happened, but certainly with each decade of life, your blood pressure goes up on average. If you're
looking at a population of people, is that normal? Is that part of normal healthy aging? Or is that
just a function of pathology? Is it a function of something going wrong over time? To your point,
is it something about decreased kidney function or maybe as an increased vascular stiffness
over time? I think all those things are possible and probably probable. So for a long time,
it was assumed that a blood pressure that was normal for somebody in their 20s and 30s
was probably too low and not normal for somebody who was in their 60s, 70s, and 80s. And so we
had this permissive hypertension in elderly people because we thought, well, gosh, they
required. It's just part of the aging process. And it really hasn't been until the past
really 10 plus years that we've begun to ask specifically in really well-designed clinical
trials, is that the case? And is it the case when it comes to looking at important clinical outcomes?
And I think my take on this now is different than it was 15 years ago. And that is that
120 over 80 is normal no matter where you are in life. And that anything above that is abnormal.
And just to kind of get to the punchline, what I tell patients is that my aspiration is that we
can get you as close to 120 over 80 as we can without harming you. Because there are certainly
potential harms that are associated with treating people to these low numbers, they can be in the
form of side effects or impacts on lifestyle. They can be in the form of real toxicity. Hyperkalemia,
risk of death, I mean, there's all kinds of potential issues. It's not just a simple intervention
like treating LDL or APOB lower and lower and lower. There's really no consequence at all.
There is a consequence of lowering blood pressure too low in this case. So that's my overall kind
of philosophy of how to think about blood pressures. I do think there's now evidence from
good clinical trials that 120 over 80 is normal and that we should try to get there
as best we can without making a mess. So through that lens, basically we're saying that the amount
of float that we see in blood pressure, again, we're talking about blood pressure in a very
narrow instance, which is seated, resting, et cetera. We'll come back to the other point, but
just to build off that, that when that drifts up to 125, 130, 135, 140 in an aging population,
we're actually calling that pathologic in the same way that I think we would all agree that the
reduction in glomerular filtration rate, the reduction in ejection fraction, the reduction
in pulmonary function, okay, yes, that occurs with aging, but that doesn't mean that it's not part of
an aging process and therefore part of something we want to minimize, correct? That's right. We
lose muscle mass as we age. Is that something we want to accept and that's normal or do we want to
try to do it? We can't have preserved the muscle mass that we had it younger in life. And again,
I think here the, the crutch that we fall back on and is good, high quality, well done clinical
trials. And in this case, we have now have them and it's not just sort of an opinion-based thing
that says, oh, we'll really get closer to 120 over 80. We actually have evidence that being closer
to 120 over 80 impacts mortality and that permitting people to run higher to a level
that we used to consider to be just basically prehypertension or just normal, even an older
person 140 over 90, that leads to a significant increase in risk of dying. So to me, I think
we've learned a lot and I don't consider it to be a normal function of aging. I think
there may be a process, there's obviously a process that goes along with aging that there's
a decrease in function of a lot of different things that lead, combines to lead to this increase
in blood pressure, but I don't leave it alone. Okay. I think that makes sense to me as well.
Let's ask the second question now, which is the one that vexes me the most,
which is how much of a given day, let's assume I sit down three times a day for five minutes,
relax, don't look at my phone, don't drink coffee, don't cross my legs and perfectly Zen.
I put the cuff on my arm, I measure the blood pressure, it's 120 over 80. Let's assume I do
that three times a day and I get that number. How reflective is that of what my blood pressure is
when I'm sleeping? Let's say I'm sleeping eight hours. When I'm exercising, let's say I'm
exercising for an hour, 90 minutes a day. And when I'm sitting at my desk stressing out over email,
how much variation am I getting? Tons. So the first time I ever was in the cath lab,
it was really amazing to me to see the variation in blood pressure just in a patient lying on a
table based on before they were sedated and after they were sedated. There are all kinds of things.
So there's no doubt that there's a huge amount of variation from second to second, minute to
minute, hour to hour, day to day and beyond in blood pressure. And I think it's very easy to get
distracted by that. And I do all the time. And obviously when I'm sitting in traffic,
my blood pressure is not 120 over 80. When my kid spills coffee all over the computer,
it's not 120 over 80. When I'm exercising, it's not 120 over 80. There's physiology and there's
pathophysiology. So physiologically, our blood pressure does go up and it's meant to go up
during some of these cases. It's a function of increased cardiac output, which is one of the
components of blood pressure. So I think it's understandable. The question then is what do you
do about that relative and sort of how best do you measure blood pressure? And so again,
and this is a broken record, I'll just keep doing this, but I fall back on the clinical trials.
And just as we try to practice as best we can with some sort of fidelity to the way the trials are
done, I go back to sort of how are they measuring blood pressure in these trials and therefore how
were the decisions made to adjust medications and how did that influence the practice of the trial
and therefore how should that influence our practice? Because those are the outcomes that we
look at. So this got a lot of attention. When Sprint was first published, which was I think
2014 or 15, I can't remember the exact date, but it got a huge amount of attention. There was all
kinds of pushback from almost every angle you could think of. There were a lot of people out
there who felt like this is just yet another example of medicine trying to do too much.
The Less is More crowd hated it, right? That this is just over medicalizing normal aging, right?
There was a significant amount of attention paid on how they actually measured the blood pressure
because it wasn't the way that we typically measure blood pressure. And it was the way that
we probably ought to measure blood pressure, but it certainly wasn't the way that we typically
measure blood pressure. So if you go back and you look at the data, if you look at the methods,
what they did was they had people in a quiet room, then automated cuff, one of the sort of standard,
you know, sort of best in class at that time, automated cuff, they put the cuff on the person,
they had them seated and relaxed in a quiet room by themselves. And they had the blood pressure
measured three times, five minutes in between, right? So total of once, five minute break,
one more, five minute break, and once more. And they took the average of those blood pressures.
And that's obviously much different than having somebody rush in after parking their car and run
into the office in a sweat and show up and somebody slaps a cuff on them and measures the blood pressure.
But my point is that that optimal way of measuring blood pressure, even if it ends up
yielding numbers that are lower than what we typically get, that led to the result in that
trial, which was so spectacular, the trial was stopped early. And this is not to all the,
you know, conspiracy theorists out there, this was not a pharma sponsored sponsored trial. This
is an NIH sponsored trial, the government sponsored trial, and was agnostic to different
agents, right? I mean, it was not about the physicians who enrolled patients in the trial
had had access to almost any therapy during that trial. So this was not about sort of proving the
benefit of one drug over another. This is purely about testing the hypothesis that getting as close
to 120 over 80, rather than letting people sort of float up to 140 over 90 was better or not. And it
turned out that it was with caveats. So let's talk about that methodology. And then let's talk about
the algorithm agents and then the potential downside. So I have started testing my blood pressure
six months ago. And the reason for it, so I shouldn't say that I have always checked my
blood pressure, because both my parents have hypertension. I'd always attributed to the
fact that I had low blood pressure to the fact that I was super healthy and did all these other
things. But I realized, look, there's genetics to this as well. So I'm just going to start checking
my blood pressure every couple of days. And I did. And so for a couple of years, I just take my blood
pressure, three, four times a week, just when I'm sitting at the desk working, never attempting to
relax or rest or do anything. And it was pretty low, you know, probably averaged 110 over 70
was sort of a typical reading of while I was sitting there working. And then something happened
in August, it was consistently a little bit higher than that. Not a lot higher, but it was 125 to 130.
And it was, you know, more or less 80 in the denominator. This made me get a little more
serious. I got another cuff. And now I started doing the full sit protocol three times a day
with both the Amron cuff and the Withings cuff. And what I realized were two things. The first is
I can always breathe my blood pressure down to normal. In other words, there's never been a
five minute window when if I don't sit there and really focus on breathing, I can't get that blood
pressure to come to normal. But most often than not, that first reading the second I sit down,
especially in August, it got better in October and September was kind of a transition month. It's
kind of normalized now. But it was not uncommon for that first one to be as high as 140 over 90.
If I just, you know, was literally doing something, not exercising, but if I was, you know,
doing something active, and then I went and sat down like the equivalent of the guy who
shows up from the parking garage, you know, just parked the car, had to walk up one flight of stairs,
sits down 140 over 90. Five minutes later, it's, you know, it's 117 over 74. And, you know, I've been
in sort of a back and forth discussion with my doctor and with my colleagues about, is this
something I need to care about? Because now if you look at my spreadsheet and all of my phone data,
my blood pressure looks perfectly normal. For the last six months, I've averaged below 120 over 80.
But I kind of feel like I'm cheating, Ethan, because to guarantee that it's low, I have to
take five minutes of being calm, which then makes me wonder, I know that that's in line with how the
sprint study was done. And you could argue, well, Peter, you're simply, you're actually doing
something that's less extreme than what they did, because they did three measurements over 10 minutes.
But I think, but deep down, I know my blood pressure is not 120 over 80 when I'm sitting
at my computer, you know, writing, because when I check that blood pressure straight away, it's
it's above that. So I hear your point that it's okay. I mean, what I think I'm hearing you say is,
based on the way the trial was done, we have to assume that the other people,
when they first sat down, might have been higher as well.
Yeah, so here's what I would say is, I think, sounds like something changed in you.
Yeah, a book deadline is definitely what changed in August. So there's no question that was that.
Well, so if that's the case, then that's understandable. And that's, that's okay. I
think, in your case, it sounds like what I was going to say was, if it was truly a change,
and there was no explanation for it, like a lot of things in medicine, then I probably
would have paid more attention to it, even though it was going from what was normal to normal,
right, that you just, that it sounded like something did change. But in this case,
it sounds like there is an explanation in that you had this stress in your life in the book.
So I guess the cheating thing reminds me of my daughter, who I think I told you before,
is my younger daughter is legally blind, and she plays basketball, and we were discussing
a potential. This is such a crazy little side, but I thought I'd tell the story because it's
kind of cute. She, we were discussing a potential procedure she could have to improve her vision.
Because part of her decrement of visual acuity is that she has pretty bad nystagmus,
lateral nystagmus. And the ophthalmologist was saying that if you can sort of make that better,
you'll improve, understandably, you'll improve her visual acuity. And that they,
somebody stumbled onto the idea that if you cut the optic, the extraocular muscles,
and just reattach them, don't do anything else, but just sever them and reattach them,
that nystagmus can go away. And that people's visual acuity can improve a lot. So we thought,
well, gosh, that sounds really interesting. We should do that. It's fascinating how that
might happen. But she said she didn't want to do it. Because she was like, that's cheating.
This is a kid who runs around with a visual acuity of 20 over 200. And she was like, that's cheating.
So we haven't been able to convince her to do it yet. We'll see if she changes her mind someday.
But I don't think you're cheating. What you're doing is optimizing the measurement. I think
what you could do if you want to, and maybe you've already done it, if you really want to get a sense,
and it would be great to have this over time, serially, is to do a 24 hour ambulatory blood
pressure monitor to really get a sense of what is the average blood pressure you're seeing over
a 24 hour period, because there is a difference. When you're sleeping, your blood pressure should
be low, right? That's physiology. When you're out and about and doing these, it's going to be higher.
What is the survival? They can quantify all the spikes. It's actually a really nice tool that
I'll use, especially in people who have some degree of what's commonly termed white coat
hypertension, which is what white coat hypertension is real life. White coat hypertension is
living in the real world. How does an ambulatory BP cuff work? It's presumably a cuff that sits
on the arm and then it straps to a device like a halter would. It's funny, I don't think I've
ever seen a device, I've ordered a bunch. It's a cuff, so it's really old school, right? It's not
like this is new technology where they can measure blood pressure without doing the old sphincter
monometer. It's a cuff, I think it's got a self, I would imagine it's got some hardware attached to
it that tells it to inflate and measure blood pressure, just as you would with a one that you
have in your office. It does that once a minute or whatever it is over the course of 24 hours.
So it's constantly inflating, deflating over the course of a day. Patients who have
mine who've warned them say that after a while you get used to it and just you can ignore it.
It seems to me like it would be really annoying to have this thing like inflating and deflating
all the time, but that's what it is. What it does though is it buys you sort of a distraction from
real life. It buys you sort of when you're not thinking about things, when you're clearly not
stressed or you shouldn't be stressed, i.e. when you're sleeping, what is your blood pressure? And
we know that blood pressure, that hypertension during sleep is abnormal. It should really be a
time when your blood pressure is the lowest. So it's just another tool that we have to kind of
get at that question. It is always interesting to me that we measure blood pressure not just once
a 10 or 30 second interval in a 24 hour day, but that we do that on average once or twice
a year. And that we assume that this very variable number is actually meaningful. And it's remarkable
to me that it has been even meaningful the way that we've been measuring it because it is such
a poor sample. I mean, we in our patients will ask them to do twice a day checks at home, same
method that I'm using for at least two weeks once a year. And if we have reason to believe that
that suspect will do it more and yet, so even though that's much more than they would be asked
to do normally, it still feels woefully inadequate. And I've tried a bunch of devices that's supposed
to measure, supposedly measuring blood pressure like little wrist based devices. I've never found
them to work. Is there anything on the horizon that's closing the gap on that?
You'd think so. There was a period of time where people were using a cell phone camera and you could
press your finger on the camera and that it could basically detect the pulsation. It could almost
calculate a pulse wave and then could give you a sort of imputed systolic and diastolic blood
pressure that never made it. Obviously we're not seeing those around. We're not seeing any other
devices that people can wear that can accurately measure blood pressure. So I do think it's a
interesting question. You'd have to think that at some point, even if it's an intravascular device,
that you could put a miniature device, much like we're now using, I don't know how much you use
them, but I use them a lot, these implantable event monitors, these loop recorders. We use them to
detect arrhythmias. It sounds bad, right when you think about it, but it's really not that big of a
deal. There has to be a way to get a pressure transducer into an artery safely that you could
leave there for some period of time. It feels like that's going to come, but I haven't seen it. And
then non-invasively would be amazing, but I just again, haven't seen it. So yeah, as you know, I
find CGM to be kind of a remarkable tool. I would think this is even more important because glucose
in many ways is less variable than blood pressure, or at least its variability is more
predictable. In other words, you could, I think much more easily get by with just spot checks
of glucose than you can with just spot texts of blood pressure. To have a true continuous
ambulatory BP monitor, I mean, that would really be a game changer in medicine.
Again, when you think about the heart, when you think about the brain, when you think about the
kidneys, it's such an important thing. I agree with you. I think that said, the intervention
that was used in sprint still showed a remarkable benefit. And so we can't exist with the tools we
have. Yeah. And while they're not optimal, they're probably adequate. And they're definitely better.
If you go back and look, and this was part of this lecture I used to give, if you look at the
percentage of people that have either diagnosed blood pressure, so how many people are known to
have hypertension who actually do have it, how many people are treated at all, even have on any
medicine, and how many people are controlled. If you look back in time, when this was first done
in the first Indian survey in the whatever 1975, 76, whatever that was, only 50% of people who had
hypertension were even aware of it. Only 30% were actually ever treated, and only 10% were controlled.
And I don't know what the most current numbers are, but the awareness has gone up, it must be
north of 80% now. Treatment is probably 75 or 80%. And control is probably somewhere around 50%.
So we're still missing the opportunity to treat 50% of people with this disease.
So let's go back to Sprint. This trial was drug agnostic, right? Is this the one that basically
said, start with a thiazide, move to a calcium channel blocker, and then an ACE or vice versa?
No. Actually, I don't remember the algorithm for Sprint, but I think it was relatively agnostic.
Allhat was the first NIH sponsored blood pressure trial. That was in early 2000s, like 2002, 2003.
And that tested five different classes of medications, two of which were discontinued.
So I believe it was calcium channel blockers, ACE inhibitors, and the calcium channel blocker at the
time was amylotopine, ACE inhibitors, diuretics, thiazide diuretics, the cortilidone, beta blockers,
and I don't remember what it was. Oh, it was alpha agonist. Because at the time,
they were being used for blood pressure. And both the alphas and the betas were stopped early
because they were harmful. And so what the result of that trial was that using any of the other three
classes was first line and primary hypertension treatment, a primary hypertension.
And that was lysinopril, amylotopine, and ethiazide, correct?
Yes. And I believe the thiazide they used was cortilidone. And we can talk a little bit about
the difference between cortilidone and hydrochlorothiazide, but in general, cortilidone is more potent.
And that's the one that was, I think, used in the allhat trial, but I'd have to double check.
And if I recall, the amylotopine, lysinopril, and the thiazide all ended up having similar outcomes,
which were all better. Yeah, no real differences. Yeah.
Yeah. And I think there were maybe some stroke, it's been like so long since I've reviewed it,
but I think there might've been like a minor difference in stroke risk and the amylotopine.
But the take home of that and what became contemporary practice was use any of these
three agents as first line and primary hypertension. And if you need more, you add another.
And the target was 120 over 80.
Well, that was, yeah, I mean, it was the target. It certainly wasn't
a, the emphasis was not, the definitions definitely changed, right? Because there was
this sort of category in, I don't remember which JNC, so I think it was JNC six or something.
There was a category for normal. Ah, that's right. So it was normal was actually 120 to 130
over 80 to 85. Borderline was 130 to 140 over 85 to 90. And it was only then hypertension,
if you were greater than 140 over 90, and then they called it stage one, two, and three.
So then when they redid it JNC seven, it was normal was less than 120 over 80. Prehypertension
was then at 120 to 140 and hypertension was then above 140 over 90. That was the difference
in between JNC seven and JNC six. JNC eight, I believe, gosh, I can't remember what happened.
There was some controversy and they stopped after that. There was like basically the, and NHLBI said
we can't do this anymore because there was too much controversy over these.
So what was the impetus for sprint? The impetus was to test the new hypothesis that was,
should we be more aggressive in the management of hypertension?
So the impetus was that there were epidemiological observational studies,
and I can send you one or two, that showed that it appeared that the risk of
bad outcomes, mostly coronary cardiovascular disease, was lower, step function lower in
patients who had optimal blood pressure. This is, you know, according to the old classification,
people whose blood pressure is 120 over 80 or less optimal, and then a small step increase in
people who had what was then classified normal, and then a large step increase in people who were
considered high normal or even early stage hypertension. And so, but this was all
observational. It wasn't, you know, there was, it was, it was not a prospective study. So the NIH
designed a study to prospectively evaluate whether treating people to these two different goals,
and these were aspirational goals, whether that resulted in a change in outcomes. And so
they randomized these people, again, the doctors were given leeway as to which agents to use,
and you can look through the supplemental tables and see which ones were used, but
there was really nothing, at least to my recollection, there was nothing about the
different agents that was that meaningful. Clearly, people got to the two goals that they were
assigned to randomly. It was obviously not blinded because you couldn't be blind to your blood
pressure. But they got to the two goals. So the people assigned to the more aggressive 120 over
80 got to like 123 or whatever it was, 82. And the people into that 140 over 90 were more like 137.
You can look at the curves in the New England Journal paper, and they separated.
Yeah, it was 121 versus 136.
It was something like that, but it was a significant difference. And obviously,
the amount of medication usage was much higher in the people who were assigned to that more
aggressive arm. And there are some questions there was, well, is it a benefit of the medicines,
or was it a benefit of the blood pressure? Look, I mean, we can ask all these questions
forever and ever. But the reality is this was a really striking difference such that the NIH
stopped the trial early because of benefit in that lower group. And I think it was one of the
most important and practice changing trials that we've had. I don't think that it came without
some cost risk. It would be silly to just completely dismiss this. There were real issues,
right? There was a greater increase in the risk of falls and syncope. And I think even in the risk
of significant kidney dysfunction, it was all reversible, but it was all there. And so what we
took away or what I took away from that trial was, it looks like you get a mortality benefit for
getting closer to 120 over 80. So let's get there if we can without creating one of these problems.
So obviously, if you're falling all over the place because you're dizzy, or if your kidney function
deteriorates because your kidneys aren't getting enough blood flow, or whatever, something else
bad happens, then we're not going to do that. But we're going to get you as low as we can,
as close to that target as we can without making a mess.
Yeah. And I think that's sort of why my doc has been relatively unexcited about doing anything in
me is he still remembers a year and a half ago or less than that, just over a year ago, when under
my normal set of relatively low blood pressure, I stood up in the morning, too quickly fell,
face planted, split my head on the table. And that was an occurrence like once,
maybe twice a week, I'd get up and need to sit back down again in the mornings. And so
understandably, his appetite for trying to correct an average blood pressure of 120 over 78
is pretty low. And I'm not keen to take any medication either, clearly.
Well, and there is no doubt in blood pressure, unlike in cholesterol, if we want to go back,
there is a U-shaped curve, right? But too low is definitely bad. And I think your body was telling
you that your blood pressure is probably right about where it ought to be and maybe even a tad
too low. Maybe you're just like a little dehydrated in the morning or have some orthostasis. It sounds
like your doctor made the right decision in you. I don't think there's any evidence that I'm aware
of that treating you to below 120 over 80 is advantageous. No, it was more just my question
was, should we treat such that I never have a reading above 120 over 80? And again, I think
that's probably too aggressive based on these side effects.
Well, I don't think it's even feasible. I mean, the way you exercise, I would be shocked. There's
just no way. I would imagine if you wore 24 hour ambulatory blood pressure when you're exercising,
especially doing isometric resistance training, your blood pressure is going to go way out.
Yeah. No, actually, I think that's a great idea. I've wasted a little bit of time in the last
two years looking for new technology to measure blood pressure in a continuous ambulatory way.
And every device I've tried has failed. So I think I just need to bite the bullet and do the old
school low tech way. If some smart engineer out there wants to figure out a great important
thing to work on, this is definitely at or near the top of my list. I would agree.
I haven't been solved. So go for it. It would be great. Right. As you say that there isn't
really anything now other than the old school old fashioned single manometer just attached to
your arm. So what about the step trial last year? Did that sharpen our thinking at all?
I think it just assuaged any fears that people had that there was something unusual in that
sprint. And of course, there was this concern over the trial being stopped early, which does risk,
you know, does risk what is it? You know, this stuff better than I do, but it does risk the
possibility that the result of spur. Yes. Yeah. So I think step does sort of is a nice confirmation.
Because I think that I think sprint was stopped at like three and a quarter or something, three
and a half. Yeah. Something like that. It was definitely stopped early. And again, that was
because it was pre specified and there was a DSMB and the whole deal. And again, it was an industry
that stopped it. It was the government that stopped it. And because of overwhelming benefit.
And you know, you could have made the argument to keep going. A lot of people did.
They felt like this was an important, you could calculate the number of people who are
under treated, and that they could calculate the impact on mortality, even here within the United
States for every day that you didn't get this result out there. And so they made the decision
to go ahead and stop the trial and report the results. And like I said, there were a lot of
reasons people didn't like the trial. Lots. And that's fine. There are lots of reasons that we
can all find fault with a lot of different things we do. Anyone who's done a scientific experiment
knows that there's plenty of people out there to find fault with all of the things that you did or
didn't do correctly. So I think that what I took away from step was that it was a nice confirmation
that that sprint was probably not spurious that the result of the sprint was real and robust and
repeatable. I think the other thing step had going for it over sprint is it included patients with
type 2 diabetes, which I believe were excluded. So you had a longer trial, you had a more
representative population. And yeah, again, so I'll tell you, and we can leave this after we're done
with this, because I want to make sure you have some time to talk about the metabolic stuff. But
do you have any thoughts on the specifics of various agents? So you have these two really
good trials that were largely drug agnostic. Yeah. And yet I still, when I'm hanging out at
the bars at night talking to, no, I'm kidding. This is not bar discussion. I was going to say that.
You hear this little bit of ARB versus ACE versus calcium channel blocker. And basically the question
is independent of the effect on blood pressure. So if you have two agents, an ACE inhibitor
or an angiotensin receptor blocker, for example, or throw in a calcium channel blocker that can
equally lower blood pressure so that they can get everybody down to 120 over 80 and they can,
the symptoms and side effects become non-issue. And each of those will have a slightly different
set of symptoms we know. Do we have one reason to prefer one over the other, for example,
when it comes to renal protection? Okay. So my first answer is because of the conversation we
had earlier about the sort of lack of awareness and lack of treatment and lack of control of blood
pressure. My first advice to people is get the blood pressure control. And that's what I tell
patients, right? That let's just get the blood pressure control. And then if we want to try to
optimize and find out what the right combination of things is for you, given your other circumstances,
the NIH used to use this term, extenuating or special circumstances. For example, if somebody
had angina, even though beta blockers were no longer first line for true in the primary
hypertension, if you had angina, you'd have, you'd include the use of a beta blocker in that
hypertensive regimen. It was really an anti-anginal, but it lowers blood pressure. So I think the first
step is just get to goal. I do tend to do things differently in some contexts. So age to me has a
big deal in both directions, right? Young people don't like taking diuretics. And in old people,
diuretics can be a little bit more challenging, right? So there are more electrolyte abnormalities.
I see a much greater incidence of hyponatremia and other electrolyte problems. And of course,
the kidney issue, right, is there too. So while I think if I had to pick my favorite agent,
that I think probably among the three classes is the best at managing sort of all comers of
high blood pressure, it would be chlorthalidin or thiazidyridic. I don't use it as much just because
it's harder to use. I think amlodipine is a great drug because it's the easiest to use.
It doesn't require any monitoring, right? You don't have to monitor electrolytes, you don't have
to monitor kidney function. It's a benign drug, super easy, very few side effects other than
a not super infrequent amount of what's considered to be swelling in the ankles. It's not really
edema, but it's the sort of non-edema ankle swelling that people just don't like, especially
women don't like having. So aside from that, it's a very easy drug. For ACE inhibitors or ARBs,
I mostly don't make the distinction between the two. I probably should, but I don't. There are
data, I think that do suggest that those drugs may be more indicated in certain subpopulations.
So for example, there was the HOPE trial, right, which was, I think, you know, mid 2000s.
And so it suggested there may be a benefit in people that have atherosclerotic coronary disease
to have an ACE inhibitor on board. So maybe in people with, you know, with
ASCVD or ACVD risk, I'll use that one over the others as a first line. It's also, you know,
there's the whole ARB and aortic diameter thing, right? So people who may have a little
increase, whether you want to call it an aneurysm, but just an increase in aortic size,
that there may be a benefit to ARBs. You can start begin to weave together all these little
things. I like ACE inhibitors and ARBs probably the best. They do require monitoring, right? So
they do require that you get, you know, electrolytes because there can be in some patients, there can
be issues, especially with potassium. And they can impact kidney function. So it's this weird thing
where the benefit to people with kidney disease is high, but then kidney doctors are also very
nervous about the potential kidney toxicity of ACE inhibitors and ARBs. So it's this weird thing.
To answer your question, I think in people with existing kidney disease, that that's probably the
drug. The other place that I use ACE inhibitors ARB first line is in patients with diabetes,
because that's been shown to, they've been shown to reduce the progression to diabatic nephropathy.
Again and again. So I think. So somewhat renal protective again.
Renal protective. Yeah. So I think they are probably the most renal protective beyond just
getting the blood pressure lower, which is not, is still to me primary. Yeah. So really what you're
saying is, look, the first, second, third order term is take that 50% up to 100% in terms of
effectively lowering blood pressure. And when everybody's at 120 over 80, we can, and we're
doing it without causing ancillary side effects. So that's the third, fourth, fifth order term.
The tail end of this polynomial is the nuance around actual class of drug inside that. Yeah.
I think that makes a lot of sense. And tolerability. Because I do think,
you know, we probably don't pay enough attention to that. It's probably the biggest reason for
non-compliance. Yeah. I kind of include that in the second bucket, right? Is anything,
whether it be ankle swelling or a dry cough that obviously tends to occur in some people with
ACE inhibitors. Older people who tend to get more orthostatic, right? I'd stay away from that. Again,
staying away from direct for them. Because falls in older people, I mean, you're not old and you're
obviously not at risk for having a significant injury from falling, but it's a huge source of.
Did you see my face after I fell? Well, you had a good story about the bar you were in the night
before. Yeah. No, it's, look, I think falling is an enormous risk for an elderly population. And
it's, I mean, between the head bleed and the femur fracture, I mean, these are devastating
consequences for someone in their eighth decade and beyond. I mean, absolutely life-changing and
sadly often life-ending. Yeah, they are. Yep. Yeah. And I say that with an 81, almost 82-year-old
father who has unfortunately fallen now several times and it's a bad thing.
So let's spend a minute, Ethan, talking about one other thing,
kind of bringing it all the way back full circle in the atherosclerosis world.
I generally tell my patients that there are four big pillars of risk in ASCVD.
Smoking, hypertension, APO-B and metabolic health. And that last one is kind of squirrely
because, you know, I can't point to one number that tells me like I can point to your APO-B,
I can point to your blood pressure. You're either smoking or you're not smoking.
But here I talk about the sources of fat that exist outside of your subcutaneous,
you know, depose of fat. And I typically talk about five of them, but I know you tend to focus
on a couple. So I want to double click on those, but just for folks listening, right?
I think the generally accepted principle of this is we as a species, one of our remarkable
advantages in evolution was our ability to store energy. You know, without this capacity,
we wouldn't exist. And so we have this vast network of subcutaneous
adipose tissue, white adipose tissue, that is incredibly adept at storing triacylglycerides.
And I think what appears very clear is that different people have a different genetic
capacity for how much they can store. So I kind of liken this to a bathtub. Everybody has a
different size bathtub. And the water coming in the bathtub is how much you're eating and the
water leaving through the drain is how much energy you're expending. And if you're accumulating
fat, you are, you know, obviously consuming more than you're expending. But at some point,
you could fill that bathtub up and water can escape the bathtub. And that's when really
bad stuff happens, right? That's when it gets into, you know, the floorboards, the electrical stuff,
and that's a disaster. And you don't need to get a lot of water out of the tub for really bad things
to happen, right? Ask anybody who's gone through a leaking, a leak in their house. So you can,
you might have a hundred gallons in the bathtub. If two gallons escape in the wrong place,
it can be a disaster. So talk about the places where it escapes. So around the viscera,
within the muscle itself, in the pancreas specifically, which we can talk about maybe
why that's so problematic, pericardial fat. Tell us a little bit about why this is so problematic.
Well, first of all, I'm so incredibly impressed at how you tell that story. Because it's exactly
how we tell the story. And we learned it from Steve O'Reilly, who I think is the sort of godfather
of this concept. I think we've all appreciated for some time that there's a relationship in terms of
risk and weight, that that's imperfect. And BMI, right, that their BMI is not a great measure of
risk. It is in epidemiology, it is in large populations. We also know that how much fat
you carry. So overall, adiposity is important. But what we've learned really in the past 20 years is
that, as you've said, that it's not so much even how much fat you have, it's where you carry it. And
that we are evolutionarily programmed to store energy in these places around our hips, and our
butt, in our legs, and not as much up here in our bellies, and definitely not in our organs, right,
that's a bad thing. And that has been shown to be a very potent predictor of risk. And that there
are a number of genetic alleles that predispose to both these differences in body composition,
but also to differences in risk of developing diseases like corn
Why does that so bad? The answer is not one I can give you, but I we started our sort of process and
thinking about this problem, and thinking about extreme the extremes of biology, in particular,
these rare genetic diseases that are called lipodistrophes, where people are born with the
inability to store fat at all in generalized lipodistrophy, or with just an isolated inability
to store fat in the gluteofemoral and subcutaneous regions in the legs. So they have a selective loss
of adipose tissue in their butt and their legs, and therefore a huge overabundance of fat in the
abdomen, the viscera, in the liver, and the pancreas, and the heart, as we talked about.
And those people have tremendous metabolic disease and extraordinary levels of risk, right? I mean,
there's small numbers of people that have rare diseases, and all of these studies are observational,
but there's a beautiful paper from Canada from 20 years ago, showing that people born with these
sort of congenital forms of severe insulin resistance, be it either lipodistrophy or type
A insulin resistance, have astronomical coronary artery disease risk. There are women who are
having bypass operations in their 30s and 40s, which is basically unheard of. And
you know, in women. So I think the question of why that is remains unanswered. I think there are lots
of different potential hypotheses. You know, I think the role of insulin and its impact on different
organs and tissues and cells is interesting. We don't have an answer yet. What we do know is that
there's this very strong now association between these different shapes, body shapes, right, the
apple pear thing, and risk of developing these diseases. And so I think if you look at the
epidemiology curves of say coronary disease over the past 30 years, we've done an amazing job of
reducing the risk of coronary artery disease events using all the tools we have at our disposal,
whether that's, you know, blood pressure, smoking cessation, lipid management, etc, etc. Yet, as you
mentioned, at the very beginning, it's still the number one cause of death in the world, and even
in the COVID era. And so it's still a huge problem. The question then to all of us is what
is what is what is what is that? Is that just that we're adequately using the tools we already have?
Or is it that we're missing something else? Or is it a combination? And I guess I would sort of
probably bet that it's some combination of sort of we're just not doing anything.
And I think that's a combination of sort of we're just not doing a good enough job with what we
have. And there's probably something else there. And so that's the focus of sort of what I want to
spend, like I said, the rest of my life thinking about. Yeah, I would agree with you. I think it's
really a combination. I think we start too late and don't go low enough on lipids. We fail to
recognize and don't get enough traction on blood pressure. I mean, I still think nearly 20% of
that is the case. And then I do think that this pillar of poor metabolic health is so improperly
understood. And I don't think we're identifying people at risk because I mean, I think about how
little I know about my own state here. I mean, I have a pretty good sense from any blood test you
can do. I can do a DEXA scan. It tells me how much of that I have. My transaminases are adequate.
I assume and based on last test, no liver fat. But I don't, other than that, it's a real blind
spot. I mean, I don't have the clarity that I would have about my ApoB, for example, or my blood
pressure. And that's I think because we're sort of increasing our very poor resolution of this
problem starting with the most blunt tool of all, which is BMI and then moving to other things.
Even what you just said, I think it still represents probably a very low resolution
image into this, right? Just focusing on that. We know that's bad. But so here's a question right
up. Just a thought experiment is what is, is the problem with that? Is that a defect in the ability
to store fat where it should be stored in the gluteal femoral depot? And is that just a
manifestation of that? Is there something different about that? Is there truly a benefit to having
more fat in the gluteal femoral? So in other words, to your bath of analogy, if you could make
a bigger bath, would you be more metabolically healthy? Well, certainly there's one experiment
that Gerald Shulman did that, you know, obviously it's a contrived experiment, but it would certainly
suggest in the model. So he looked at a mouse model where the mice had profound insulin resistance,
and he would just put more and more subcutaneous fat into those mice, and they got fatter and they
got less insulin resistance. They actually got paradoxically fatter and healthier. So in at least
that intervention, allowing them to get fatter, making them have a bigger bathtub, improved them.
But it's not clear that that's the same thing, right? In other words, that doesn't answer the
question, is that bad simply because it's not in the subcutaneous space? Or is it doing something
fundamentally different? And I think that's where we want to sort of eventually understand, right?
Are there cytokines that are coming out of those cells that are different from the cytokines
coming out of the other cells? And how does that interact with it?
Yeah, I mean, there are all kinds of things that we're learning about the difference in
life, basal lipolytic rate between the two depots. And again, we're just describing these
depots based on what we can see and how we can describe them based on a DEXA scanner and MRI.
I think-
Right, it's just so low resolution.
It's very low resolution at this time. I think what we can say is that in a patient
with bipolar dystrophy has an extreme who has normal lipids, right? Not normal triglycerides.
So maybe a modest elevation in APOB, but APOB triglyceride, that those people have
extreme increases in risk independent of their traditional risk factors. We think
that there's a group of people, and I've now, as I've been thinking about this, begun to see
these people all over. And once you see them, you can't not see them. But we think there are group
people here who represent probably some polygenic version of this where there's a relative decrease
in fat in the legs. I can think of patients now who come to my practice who may have a tiny little
pot belly, but their lipids were not that bad and their legs are super skinny and they had a bypass
at 38 or 40 or 41. And the number of people I can think of like that keeps getting bigger and bigger.
And I think what we're going to learn is that gluteofemoral storage capacity is going to be
an important driver of risk in this context. And finding ways to change that, if it's possible,
would be of great benefit. I think it remains to be seen if it can be changed. There is some
very poor evidence, right? If you talk to the plastic surgeons, they've begun to understand
that there are metabolic consequences to taking fat out of places like the legs and the hips
that are very different from taking fat out of the belly. And so I think, again, we're just
getting it sort of something. It's like Jerry's experiment of putting in more subcutaneous fat.
It's just helping to guide us towards this idea that there's something there.
And especially where it's... Oh, go ahead.
No, no, it's fine.
No, I was just going to say where I think it's really going to be interesting, Ethan, is when you
start to look at this in the much larger and less extreme population of those without lipodystrophy.
So the cases you're describing are profound. But the question is, this is probably also playing a
very big role in people who aren't the ones showing up for bypass at 38 years old, who don't have the
complete lipodystrophy where they have no ability to store fat on their legs and hips. And so the
question is, are there targeted and directed therapies that can be aimed at the metabolic
tip of that spear?
Well, that's what we're doing. So my answer to you is we think so. We need to do the experiment
to demonstrate that. But using human genetics as a guide, there are a number,
large number of alleles that seem to confer this concordance of changes in both directions. So
for example, people who are born with alleles that confer more gluteal ephemeral. So really,
what's important is not so much the amount of visceral fat you have in an absolute sensor to
amount of gluteal ephemeral fat. It's really the ratio. It's called in DEXA terms, and maybe on
your DEXA reports, it's called fat mass ratio. And there are different levels that are normal
or abnormal for women and men, but having a high fat mass ratio, meaning having more fat up here
and less fat down here is bad. And there are alleles that confer that, and that they do also
confer a bunch of changes in the other things that we know are bad, including lipid-based biomarkers
and then diseases, like coronary disease.
And how concordant are these alleles? So do you have enough data to look at identical twins
and say that the genes are completely concordant between them and the phenotype?
I don't know of any twin data, but I do know that there are certain of these that are common enough
that you can find heterozygotes and homozygotes, and it looks like there's a dose response.
And again, it's not just one, right? It's not like there's just one of these things. So I do
think there will be targeted therapies, and we'll test one sooner than later. We'll probably begin
by testing it in patients with lipodystrophy. But the hope and expectation is that we'll move
beyond that and to eventually try and target other metabolic-associated diseases in the
ultimate way than most metabolic-associated disease, which is coronary disease.
What percentage of the patients with a phenotypically appreciated lipodystrophy
have an identified set of genes or gene that results in that?
Oh, it's probably on the order of 50%. It's a great question because we don't really look
at the recognition and diagnosis of lipodystrophy as abysmal. And Steve O'Reilly, who at some point
if you ever can convince him to come on, he's one of the most entertaining human beings I've ever
been around, and I love every moment I spend with him. And Reed is banting metal lecture from 2019,
which was just astonishingly brilliant. He gave it at the ADA, which was here in San Francisco
that year. But Steve will say that the problem is that we don't take our patients' clothes off,
and that if you don't undress your patient, you'll never see it. And actually, we have some patients
with lipodystrophy who are big in the advocacy groups, and they've been incredibly helpful to us.
And they often tell the story that their own personal diagnosis of lipodystrophy happened
by accident because it happened to be a warm summer month and they were wearing a skirt,
and a doctor was able to see that their legs were super skinny and muscular. So I can't
answer your question because we just don't know what the denominator is. There is this
form, so partial lipodystrophy is characterized or classified in how it's been
defined historically, and there's familial partial lipodystrophy 1, 2, 3, 4, and beyond.
FPLD1 doesn't have a monogenic cause. It's by far, in a way, going to be the most common.
But there's not an agreed upon way to make that diagnosis today, which I think is a major problem
and is going to need to be addressed because a doctor, if you talk to an average doctor,
will never have heard of lipodystrophy, would clearly never even be thinking about it. And
I'm saying this having had the experience myself where I probably just never thought about it.
We're conditioned to think that leanness is good. Leanness and muscularity are good. And if you see
leanness and muscularity, if you haven't even see it, it's a good thing. You never would think,
oh, this is a problem. Yeah. I mean, look, to me, this is interesting in that it becomes the index
upon which you can build a far greater set of insights because, again, while I think this
population experiences such an extreme consequence of this, I think I share your belief that this,
even absent a lipodystrophy, this is still a problem.
Yeah. And again, the lipodystrophy patient has a broken bathtub. Of course.
It's not like a normally shaped bathtub. It's a jagged bathtub that is more quick to overflow
because it's simply smaller and therefore they show up much sooner with this problem. And to your
point, if the clinician would simply walk in the bathroom and go, how come that's not an oval? Oh,
I need to be looking harder. And I think that's the expectation is that they represent a very rare
version of what happens when the whole thing goes awry, but that there are going to be
more common versions of this that exist. And it's very similar, I think, to the distinction between
familial hypercholesterolemia and run-of-the-mill hypercholesterolemia. And we've learned a lot from
rare diseases. I think this is a case where we'll learn a lot. In this case, we already have
an abundance of human genetic data that suggests this sort of polygenic version of this thing.
And there'll be some papers coming out soon with collaborators of ours that will show that the
FMR itself conveys more risk even than smoking status. And that's a pretty amazing finding,
right? That if you have a high FMR, I mean, you have a lot of fat up here and not very much fat
down here, that your risk of significant bad things in the form of coronary disease events
is higher than it would be even if you smoked cigarettes, which is astonishing. And I think
none of us would have believed that. Yeah. And I do like the analogy of FH because FH is also
a very, very heterogeneous wastebasket of genetic things and more than 3,000 different genotypes
that produce this phenotype. But interestingly, at least one of them has now become, I think,
the most powerful drug we have on the market, right? Which is the PCSK9 mutation. So it'll
be interesting to know if how much the genetic insights will also form therapeutic options for
the people that don't have lipodystrophy. Yeah. I think for in this case, at least what I can say
with some confidence is that the rare genetics are probably not going to be as informative.
Certainly not as informative as PCSK9, which is, I think, stands alone in terms of the quality of
its informativeness, both as a rare disease mutation, but also as a common disease variant.
But the genes that underline a common variation in these phenotypes are, I think, going to be very
interesting. And so I think that's where we're focused because the rare disease, the single gene
mutations, one of the most common, the disease underlying FPLD2 is a mutation of lamin A.
I mean, we know that this leads to progeria, leads to cardiomyopathy, leads to muscular
dystrophy, leads to lipodystrophy. It's a complicated mess of a protein that's expressed
in the nuclear laminar. It's hard to kind of imagine that common variation in that gene is going to
lead to problems. It might, but it's not obvious. Well, Ethan, this has been really interesting.
We've covered a lot of ground. Some of it we repeated from before, but I think it was necessary
both because I just don't think everybody has the capacity to go back and listen, but I also think
we have a couple more years of insight. So thanks again for making time. And for me personally,
this whole getting deeper down the rabbit hole on blood pressure thing, I'm hoping that enough
other people are equally becoming interested in this because I just worry that there are too many
people walking around out there who have no idea what their blood pressure is. And even if they're
just 10 millimeters of mercury above normal, as you pointed out, the consequences are significant.
And again, it's just such an eminently treatable thing. It's a tragedy.
Yeah, it's been that way. This is not a new problem. And I'm glad that you're latched on
because it is one of these, in terms of things that probably are lowest bang for the buck
in public health these days, maybe short of vaccines. This is at the top of the list.
If we could just raise awareness and treat this, because I think we've done a really good job on
the lipids. Excuse me, the lipids, the lipids, what's left over now is probably, it's not awareness.
But blood pressure is one of these funny things. For whatever reason, it's just not sexy. And it's
very hard to convince somebody to do something that doesn't make them feel better. And in some
cases may make them feel worse. And we've known that for a long time. And this is one of these
things where you're trying to get somebody to understand that it's not going to have any
impact on positive impact on them for years, decades. Yeah. All right, Ethan, thanks very much.
Thank you, Peter. I look forward to seeing you. Yeah, I look forward to seeing you in person
someday. Hopefully I'll hook up. Sounds good, man. Thank you. All right. Yeah. Thank you.