Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Peter, Bill, how are you guys doing?
Doing all right.
Doing good.
This is the first time we've ever done three people in person, so we'll see how it goes.
But it should be fun, and I think what we're here to talk about is the book. So by the
time this comes out, the book will be out, which is still kind of crazy to think about,
more so for probably both of you who have been much more involved in the process than
me. But I think what we did is we collected a ton of questions from the audience on wanting
to understand the process of the book, who Bill is, what the cover means, what's talked
about, all of that stuff. And so we collected those questions. We're going to cover them
today, and it should be kind of a fun way to learn more about the book, what's involved,
kind of that inside baseball story about it. So with all that said, I think the first thing
we should start with is Peter, how's the voice doing?
I would say it is like 80% of the way back to normal.
Do you want to tell people who are maybe unfamiliar how the book tried to kill you through your
voice?
I think the book has tried to kill us in many ways, but I think most recently, between reading
the book for the audio book and then getting some virus and then having a hectic travel
schedule to try to do some podcasts, I basically just developed the worst case of laryngitis
and had a pharyngeal abscess that caused my vocal cords to stop working.
Oh, yeah, which in your profession you kind of need. So it's good that they made their
way back.
Yes, but I will say this, I really enjoyed not speaking for two weeks.
Sort of a vow of silence kind of thing.
It was just amazing. I was like, it was amazing how many things I got to tune out. I'd hear
people call my name and I'd be like, I can't do anything about it, so I'm just going to
sit here.
How did the family take that? Did they set it to their advantage?
They absolutely loved it. The boys were, what was really funny was the first couple of days,
everybody else got very quiet in response to me being quiet. So actually it's very interesting.
One of the few times social media turned out to be insightful and helpful. After I posted,
I think the second video of the direct laryngoscopy, someone, a very astute, actually several
commenters said, hey Peter, by the way, don't whisper. Because that was basically all I
could do. I could go like, I can sort of do this. And they said, don't whisper. Whisper
is a bad form of phonation. It's actually teaching you the incorrect movements. Either
don't speak or speak normally, but at the lowest volume possible. I was like, that really
makes a ton of sense because my throat was actually starting to hurt from all the whispering.
It was utilizing muscles incorrectly and stuff like that. So anyway, so I'm talking very
quietly and my boys who as you know are not, you can use a lot of words that describe them,
quiet would not be on those lists.
Definitely not one of them.
They got so quiet in response to me being quiet that I was like, I got to figure out
a way to just do this enduringly.
Yeah. Next time you have people over, you need to just be under control. It's just going
to, I can't talk to you.
Yeah. So you learned the parenting hack.
Yes, totally. The quieter you are with your kids, the quieter they are about treatment.
One of the questions that we'll get to later is, will you ever write a second book? Which
you say no, I'm curious what Bill thinks, but maybe if you do, that could be the parenting
hacks 101. Just lose your voice.
So I think we'll kind of get into it and we have a lot of questions to get through, but
the first one, which I think makes the most sense and which to start with, which is relevant
to the book sitting in front of us and the cover is, I think people would ask, we understand
how to outlive and what that means, but where does the science and art of longevity come
from and why was that so important to include in the title?
Well I mean, the title was actually an evolution. So the first title I had in mind when I wrote
my manifesto, which was an awful title, but it was the longevity manifesto, which of course,
obvious reasons got scrapped immediately, but the working title during, call it 2016
when we were shopping, the proposal around was the long game. So that was kind of the
working title that pretty quickly got replaced by outlive for I think obvious reasons and
I think I've talked about why I like that title so much and why, I don't know, we never
really even questioned it, right? I don't think there was ever a point where we thought
of something else for the main title. Yeah, I mean, I think there was a moment when I think
a previous publisher questioned it, but I think it's just very evocative and it's very simple.
And it's an action. Yeah. And you think, it could mean different things to different people,
but I think of like, you're going to outlive your expectations or outlive your parents or
your grandparents. Your fate is not set in stone is kind of the idea. So to your question
about the subtitle, art and science is a pretty common term. People understand that this is the
art and science, this is the art and science, but I felt that there were two things that needed to
be communicated. One, the study of human longevity is part science and part art, but the science
should come first. So that's why I wanted to flip that order and say it's the science and art of
longevity. And I think in the book, we make a pretty good case for where the application of each
comes, right? Why this is not, if this were a book about mouse longevity, that could just be the
science of longevity. Because in mice, you can do all of the definitive experiments and answer all
these questions. And in humans, as is readily apparent, we will never know definitively what
the answers are. And therefore we always have to have some art involved. So Peter, another question
we got is you often talk about longevity having two components, the lifespan piece, which is how
long you live, and the health span piece, which is how well you live. The lifespan piece is kind of
covered a little bit with the outlive. But we did get a question to someone wondering, was it purposeful
that health span didn't make the title? Or kind of what was the thought process there?
I see, I think outlive encompasses both truthfully, I think, you know, to Bill's earlier comment,
outliving is more than about the chronological years of life. It's about the quality of life as
well. And so I think next, the most common question we got, as it related to the cover is,
can you explain the cover art? And I know for those listening or watching, it went through a
lengthy process of a lot of different iterations. So do you maybe kind of want to talk about that,
why you ultimately settled on this and kind of to you what it means?
Yeah, I think the cover is interesting because there were two things that in the back of my
mind were enormous stressors as we got closer and closer to the finish line. And by that,
I mean, basically by about the spring of 2022, so about exactly a year ago, you know, we had a
manuscript that was, we knew it was too long. It was probably about 190,000 words at that point.
So we knew it was going to get a big haircut, but we knew we basically had the book at that point.
But these two things that kind of nagged at me and kept me up at night were, how could this be
represented in a cover? And who is going to read this book for the audio book? Those two things
just created such a low level anxiety for me. I can't even talk about it. And so as the spring
turned into this summer, and our publisher is like, okay, like, we need to get on this cover
thing. And they've got kind of a checklist of, okay, for the book to come out in March,
we have to have this thing designed by here and da da da da da. I just didn't even have a sense
of what one does because I couldn't, you know, as Bill can say, I have very strong opinions about
everything. I couldn't even offer an opinion on the cover, right? All I could say was, I want it
to be elegant. I want it to be kind of timeless. I don't want it to be too busy. Like I had vague
ideas of what I wanted. And as you know, I'm a font fanatic, so I kind of understood the fonts
I wanted, but no sense artistically of what was wanted. So then Bill sent, this is probably August,
right? You sent over an email of a guy named Rodrigo Carell, who I'd never heard of before,
but you sent over, I think his website. Yeah, my sister is a book designer and he's like a big,
he's revered in those circles. And we looked at some of his designs. Yeah. And I really
kind of popped. And I was like, yes, this is elegant. And while that's happening in parallel,
the publisher is churning out designs as well. And I'm kind of like, okay, there's a couple of
these that I could see iterating on. And basically we weren't really making a ton of progress until
we, I think just collectively decided. And really, I think Bill has contributed a lot of things to the
project. But if I was going to say the single most important thing Bill contributed was being
adamant that we engage with Rodrigo. And this was late in the game. This was October, if I'm not
mistaken. And I remember where I was, I was on a flight and I got an email from Bill and it was
said something to the effect of, cause we were looking at something that I was almost going to
capitulate on. It was a design. I remember what the design was. And I basically was saying,
it's a solid seven out of 10 and I'm too tired to do anything about it. And Bill was like,
this is bullshit, man. We've worked way too hard on this book to have a seven out of 10 cover. I
think we just, we just, we just, we go and get Rodrigo and it doesn't matter how much it costs
and it doesn't matter how much it slows the process down. We do it. And I was like, yeah,
Bill's right. I don't want to regret this. I don't want to, I don't want to be sitting here in 10
years going, why did we do that? So then we reached out to Rodrigo, had a long call with him.
And I guess this is what makes great artists, great artists is even having this call, just
talking with him about the book. He didn't have a chance to read the whole book cause it's long.
And I mean, within three days he threw up 30 covers. And they're all different, totally different,
all sort of evocative. I mean, there were some, there were some images that I liked and that you
liked and other people liked and but different ways to kind of evoke this concept of longevity
and outliving and living better and all that stuff, which I mean, it's really easy to also
get that wrong visually. Like the, I was telling Nick about the Korean cover of my book,
Spring Chicken, that portrays a fat guy on a beach chair, like frying an egg. And that's
supposed to mean longevity. So there's many ways it can go off the rails. So I think there was
something about this and I think, I don't think this was your favorite at first either.
It was, but it was in my top six. So I remember he sent over 30 and I think we each decided to
pick our top five or top six. This was on for all of us. It had a very different font. There
were a number of things about it that were different at the time. And I think the font
threw me off the first time around. Font guy. Yeah. Font guy. I'm very particular about my fonts.
And to make a very long story short, we ultimately decided this was the one we were going to make
the winner. And, you know, I wish I could sit here and tell you that the blue, green, yellow,
pink all signify something. I can't tell you that. What I can tell you is it signifies a bunch of
things to me, right? It signifies kind of a keyhole that you're walking through. It's a passage,
but it also looks like a target. And that's a big part of this. There's a very subtle theme
in this book about lots of metaphors that revolve around archery. Anyway, I could talk
about it length. I'm not sure, Bill, what you're saying. Well, it's different. I showed it to
different people, like my partner, Martha, and various other people and everybody kind of liked
it, but they had a different reason to say, I like it because it's like an aura. I like it because
it's like you're going into the beyond, into the future or, you know, the little guy there,
let's not forget him, is an important part. That was an important addition. So it was different
things to different people. And that spoke to the art side of it, science and art.
And I think that that's, I think that it speaks to what art is, right? Art means different things
to different people. And in that sense, I think the cover, I just wanted a cover that I would
like to look at. And I have certain books that I love looking at their covers. And so I wanted
this to be one of them. Yeah. And it is interesting too, as you kind of mentioned, like what makes
Rodrigo so good. And when we saw that list of 30, you were just every time you would look at another
one, you're like, this could easily be it. There literally wasn't a bad one on his list of 30.
That's the thing. Like every one of those was reasonable. And there were a handful that were
exceptional. And there was one that was perfect. Yeah. Yeah. It just shows people who are experts
at their craft, how good they are and how they can think so differently. And this cover, yeah,
it turned out really, really well. And I think I drove everybody absolutely insane with all the
font changes I made. I was going to say, I think to say you're fanatic about fonts does not do it
justice how fanatic you are about fonts. Yeah. One little inside baseball thing here. If you go with
this font, the commas work out to be much cruder. And so I was like, nope, we can't do that. We have
to use a different font for the comma because the comma, I really wanted to be serif to a sans serif
font otherwise. And everyone was like, I mean, only Rodrigo was like, yeah, that totally makes
sense. Everyone else was like, Jesus Christ. Yeah. Everyone else was like, this comma is going
to cost this book, not actually getting done because the cover won't be done on time.
So I think it kind of pivots to the next question and Bill, you hinted at a little bit, but a lot
of people were kind of curious, you know, who is Bill Gifford? Like, what's his backstory? How did
he get involved in the book? So do you kind of want to give a little rundown of kind of who you
are, your story, and then ultimately how you initially got connected with Peter and the project,
which was six years ago now? It was end of 2017. Yeah. Yeah. I got an email out of the blue.
For me, right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And I knew who you were because I had read your, you know,
I knew you were, and I think in particular, I had read your insane 13 part series about cholesterol.
This is epic. And I had read that in the course of researching my own sort of more personal book
about longevity spring chicken, which came out in 2015. I thought I was done with longevity,
honestly, but this seemed interesting, but sort of to reel back, I'm, you know, like where other
kids' dads were throwing the football, passing the old baseball around, like my dad took me to
the library. So I became a writer eventually, and I just love writing and words. And I thought I
would be like a poet at one point when I was in college, but then I realized I like writing
to people and sort of connecting with people and evolved from sort of general journalism into
writing more and more about sort of scientific and medical topics and writing about like sports
performance and doping and cycling, and then more general health related topics. And then
got interested in, like Peter did, you know, you reach a certain age and you're like, huh,
what is happening here? You know, I'm not the guy I was 10 years ago. And there's this interesting
process going on. It's this big sort of biological mystery. It's super fascinating.
And it has not been solved. It still has not been solved. So yes, so I ended up writing about
longevity and I ended up writing, I write a lot about athletes too. So I found myself writing
about older athletes as well. Like Phil Mayer, the skier came back to racing when he was 50.
So I followed him around and he was competing against 22 year olds. So that kind of longevity
kind of fascinates me as well. And Peter, I actually don't know if I know the story,
but you mentioned you first reached out to Bill. So what caused you to do that
throughout the writing process? Well, so in 2016, I was working with an agent.
This book got sold to a different publisher. And, you know, I was the author of the book and I'm
working on it nights and weekends, you know, while I'm doing my day job. And I finally have
kind of the first part of the book to submit. It was just under 40,000 words. And I submit it to
my agent who then submits it to the publisher. Now, by this point, the editor who had bought the book
had left. So there was this woman who was at the publisher and I seem to like her and I thought
she really got the concept of the book. But unfortunately, and I guess this is not uncommon
in publishing, within a couple months of me coming on with the publisher, she gets a better job at
another publisher. So she's gone. So now another editor basically comes on. It's now her book,
but she doesn't really have as much invested in it. And so I submit this first section to them.
And it is met with a very lukewarm response. And they really had two huge criticisms of it.
The first was, it's too technical. And I, you know, I can see why that's the case.
The second was there was no story in it, right? There was no narrative. It was mostly just a
scientific treatise on the subject matter. And so then my, I guess both my agent and the publisher
said, look, we think you should bring a co-author in who can help massage and smooth this out and
make it, you know, a better book for the lay person to read. So I said, okay, how do we go about
doing that? And they said, we've got a long list of people to introduce you to. I said, great.
So sure enough, the courting began and every, this is back when I was in New York constantly,
because I was, you know, this, you know, this is back when I traveled a lot to work there.
And so basically every week that I'm in New York, I'm meeting another author. And usually what would
happen is they would send me one of their books. I'd, you know, read as much of the book as I could
get through or skim it or something and then sit down with them. And I kind of went through five
or six of these. And it just, I was like, there's no way this person gets it. Like this person has
no clue what I'm trying to write about. And this is not going to work. So then I talked to Bob
Kaplan and I said, Bob, here's the problem. What do you, do you have any ideas? He goes, yeah, let's,
let's go find somebody who's already written about what you find interesting and see. And the very
first thing that I remembered, what year did you write that Bloomberg piece on Rapamycin? Was that
2015? I think that came out, um, 2015. Yeah. Early. So it's actually interesting that you wrote it
back then, because this was still sort of pre hype of geoscience. Yeah. But there was an article in
Bloomberg, yeah, I guess 2015 that, you know, because I was obsessed with this stuff, I read
everything that came out. And this was the first one that I read that I was like, this is a very
good article. Most of them were so simplistic. They just missed the point, but this was a very good
article. Um, and so I said to Bill, I said to Bob, I said, this is the guy, because he already
gets it. I'm not going to have to like, you know, explain to him this, that or the other thing, or
at least I said, like, my intuition is that he will get it. And I don't, did I contact you through
Twitter? How did I, I do remember reaching out to you, was it through your website or through
you just emailed me? Yeah. Yeah. So somehow I just got Bill's email. Maybe it was on the article
and I, I don't remember what the email said, but I do remember we met for dinner on the upper east
side one day in late 2017. Yep. And I think I probably just said everything I just said now,
which is, you know, and, and, and by that point, so what did I send you to read? What was the
version I had sent you at that point? I think it wasn't the 38,000 words. It was more like,
I think I probably by that point, it was kind of the proposal. It was like 5,000 or something.
And you know, some interesting, I was just thinking about it. Like I think some of the
DNA of that is definitely in part one. Yep. Like if you did a, you know, text analysis,
you'd probably find some bits of that sprinkled in there. You know, it had the sort of the central,
central ideas in part one. Yeah. So you had to start, but you know, starting is super hard.
And then keeping going is even harder. And then figuring out that you're done is the hardest of
all. So you had to start. I had no idea how hard this would be. I mean, I, I, I'm sure every first
time author says that, but this was so much more difficult, so much more time consuming
than, than anything I could have imagined. I do remember in the early days, we spent a lot of
time in front of a whiteboard in my office. Yes. And that was the easiest way for me to communicate
kind of broad strokes was, you know, this is how I think of these as pillars. This is how I think
of these as foundations. This is this, this is that. Yeah. We had a lot of pillars and foundations.
Yeah. Frameworks. Lots of frameworks. And I feel like that was kind of the easiest way, I think,
to get us on the same page about how I was thinking about it. But the structure that emerged
in the final book, which is basically, you know, three big sections that communicate, you know,
each important and builds on the other. I feel like that didn't really crystallize until,
gosh, I mean, 2019, I don't, 2018 is a blur. Right? Like I don't, I don't remember
the difficulty. I mean, I do in some ways, but, but clearly there was a, so if version one of the
book was what we just talked about, the sort of pre-bill, then there was version two, which was
the book that got written basically from the beginning of 2018 through the beginning of 2020.
Yeah. Yeah. And it, even in that period, so the two things I remember, first of all, I remember
you ordered about half the menu at that Turkish restaurant and the waiter was like all for you.
This was back when I was eating just one meal a day. So it was like, I would fast all day and
then basically throw down 3000 calories at dinner. Yeah. So I was like, this is whatever this is
going to be, it's not going to be dull. And then the other thing is sort of, we had a basic template.
We kind of outlined, okay, what's the book going to be? It's going to be, you know, 25%
kind of this part one, this kind of the manifesto stuff. And then it was going to be basically a
biology of aging book. I mean, that was kind of where we were going, the Rapamycin stuff and the
kind of mechanisms that, the hallmarks of aging, almost like the molecular cellular level stuff.
And then we were like, you were like, 10% tactics.
I didn't want any tactics in it. I want to do that.
Yeah. Maybe 5% tactics.
We were making appendix with a couple of tactics in it.
Yeah. We had 200 pages on tactics.
What did the publisher say when you said, I'm actually not going to tell anyone what to do in
this book? No, they were apoplectic.
And what do you, you mentioned it was so hard to kind of write and it obviously took a very long
time. What do you think was so hard about the process? Was it translating the science into
something that was more of a story? Was it figuring out how to verbalize the frameworks?
Was it just getting what was in your head cohesively on paper?
I think there are a couple of things. So first of all, I love writing. I've been, you know,
been blogging for, for as long as I can remember, but that's a very different style of writing.
You know, Bill was talking about my 13 part cholesterol series.
You don't have any constraints when you're blogging. You can go as deep as you want to go
because you are attracting an audience of similar weirdos who are going to go as
far down the rabbit hole as you will take them. And so I think the biggest struggle I had
switching to this kind of writing, and it's so funny for me to look at this version of the book
now and compare it to what I was writing in 2018. And I remember Bill really tolerated a lot of my
stupid things that I was writing and what the basic, basically how he tolerated it was he made
a lot of footnotes. He was like, all right, I really want to delete all of this, but we're going
to make it a footnote. And of course, four years later or three years later, I was the one deleting
those footnotes. And I was like, this is so gratuitous. Like it doesn't matter that much.
And that to me is a remarkable evolution, I guess, that everyone has to go through.
You know, Bill presumably went through this 30 years ago, right? But for me, that was new. That
was like, no, but I do need to explain the extracorporeal circulation of the liver in this
section. And Bill is like, I don't think that's really important. And I was like, no, no, no,
Bill, you don't understand. If the reader doesn't understand portal blood flow here,
they will never understand why glycogen gets there. And he's like, Peter, I can assure you there are
seven people who give a shit about that. And I was like, no, no, Bill, it's important. He's like,
all right, let's make it a footnote. Fine, let's make it a footnote. I was pissed. And then of
course, two years later, I'm like, that's so goddamn irrelevant. Get rid of it.
But you have to know it though, to be able to write intelligently, like you have to know it and you
have to know what's going on. But then you also have to decide, you're talking about getting in
the weeds, right? And you have to know all the weeds to write well about science. But then you
also have to, and I think ultimately we both got pretty good at this, get pretty harsh about what
you're going to leave out. And we left out a lot of stuff. I mean, so much. It's like, it's the,
I mean, I think I've told this story before, but I remember when I was writing probably my first
or second scientific paper, you do a lot of experiments, most of which don't make it into
the paper. And I forget who it was that told me this. I think his name was Dan Powell. It was one
of the postdocs that I was in the lab with. And he said, you just have to learn how to kill your
babies. You're going to throw out 90% of this. And I just think that that for me was hard,
getting to that point of, but will the reader, if the reader doesn't know all of this, you know,
stuff below the surface, can they appreciate the piece of the iceberg above? And I think ultimately
the readers will determine if we've struck that balance correctly. I think we have.
And I'll tell you why I think so. I think it became readily apparent when I read the audio
version of the book, because when you're reading it out loud, it's very different from when you
read it the way one edits their own writing. Cause you're, you're, you're obviously reading it much
slower and you realize the unnecessary interruptions of endless footnotes that are
you know, incremental in what they're adding.
Yeah. It's kind of, it's interesting to hear you talk about it because I can't imagine,
I haven't read the first iteration, which I think you said practically none of it made the
final version, right? Certainly in direct content, absolutely not in spirit, some of it, but yeah.
I just can't imagine what it was is if you handed them a whole manifesto, zero tactical advice.
And literally explaining every little nuance of the liver, like I would just love to see the face
of the person who came in after that publisher left and read this and just was like, what the
hell are we going to do with this thing? I'm sure they were freaking out. So I think it makes sense
to kind of talk a little bit. You mentioned it there, but there's three main parts of this
book, right? So let's talk about what ultimately made it into this final version. Do you kind of
want to walk through what the structure of the book is, kind of some of that content? We don't
have to get into detail, but just kind of what people can expect to read about.
Yeah. I mean, look, there's three parts. I think the first part sets up the structure of the book.
It gets the frameworks across. You'll certainly as a reader understand the problem statement,
right? And again, I think you can't solve or even attempt to solve complicated problems if you
aren't asking the right questions and you don't have the right frameworks. That's something that
we posit very clearly here. And that's really what part one is about. And that's not just explaining
what longevity is and isn't, but it's explaining something called medicine 3.0, which is the
vehicle through which you pursue this thing. Then part two, sorry, I guess the other thing
in part one is I'm blanking on where the delineation occurs, but I think part one also
includes kind of some of the scientific underpinning, doesn't it? Or does that all get lumped in part
two? I think that's part two with the horses. That's part two. Yeah. So then part two is
probably the most technical part of the book where we get into the scientific underpinning
of everything coupled with get to know your opponents, basically, right? So there's no denying
this. A big part of this book is trying to figure out how to live longer. Now, not in terms of
science fiction living longer, but I mean, I think we argue very convincingly that a person reading
this book who puts these principles into practice is really thinking about elongating their life by
five to 10 years. But to do that, you really have to understand what are the things that are coming
to take your life. So we kind of go through all that in part two. And then part three is how do
you put this into practice? It is that which I initially didn't want to write about, but ultimately
think, I don't know, I think that section just turned out better than I ever could have imagined
it. It kind of organically evolved and kept growing and changing. But going back to part two,
I think we were looking at, because we're both fascinated by centenarians, we were looking at that
chapter and kind of hammering out that chapter. And we kind of had a little bit of a revelation
where it was like, wait, it's not like a big mystery how these people live to a hundred when
most people live to 80. They get heart disease much later, if at all. They get cancer much later,
or maybe never. And they get neurodegenerative disease later or never. And so that's the ball
game. You've got to figure out how to delay all of those diseases, which you call the horseman.
And we didn't even contemplate writing these chapters at the beginning. And then we decided,
no, we have to, because we have to, like you say, know the enemy, know the opponent.
That's right. Yeah, the first version of this, which is the first version that we wrote,
which is the second version of the book, was way heavier in the molecular science of aging.
So we came at this much more through, let's go really deep into autophagy. Let's go really deep
into nutrient sensing pathways. Let's go really deep into all of these things, which of course,
I found super interesting, but ultimately we pivoted much more towards this insight,
which is there are two completely different strategies to live long. One is figure out a way
to extend the period of time you live once you have a disease. And by the way, that's everything
medicine 2.0 does. We're going to wait till you have a disease and we're going to figure out a way
to just drag you through that and keep you from dying. Okay. That strategy has worked a little bit.
Strategy two, which is medicine 3.0 is no way we have to figure out the time. We have to figure
out a way to drag out the time you live without a disease. And to understand, you can't enter,
you can't play that game if you don't know everything about these diseases. You have to
become so intimately familiar with each of the horsemen. And, and of course, therefore, each of
those horsemen has a very robust chapter. As I'm listening to you talk, I'm curious, do you think
for as tough as it was to write the book and all the pain to go through that process over the years,
do you think how you practice medicine with your patients, what we talk about on the podcast,
weekly newsletters, how all that structured, do you think it would evolve to what it is
if you didn't write the book? I mean, I think they help each other for sure. I think,
I mean, you can't write well if you don't think well. And you could argue it's hard to think well
if you're not able to write well. So I think the relentless process of streamlining and figuring
out how to get to the point sooner, all of those things would absolutely force me to,
to reconsider how things were happening. By the way, I think a lot of what's written in there
comes out of just the conversations I'm having with patients. I do, I don't, in fact, I know there
were certain times when I even asked patients, hey, do you mind if I record our Zoom today?
Because I, I just want to be able to go back and listen to how we talked about it. And they'd be
like, sure. And so I would walk them through all of their cardiovascular disease risk and then go
back and listen to it after and go, okay, yep, this is the way I would, this is a good version
of this talk. Because I give the same talk to patients constantly, but sometimes they're,
sometimes they hit better and sometimes they don't. And so having some recordings of those
was really helpful to kind of go back and remember how, what worked.
I think the, when you started the podcast, I think it was about six months,
it was about six months into the book writing process. I think that gradually that made you
more cognizant of how to communicate science and medical topics. I think maybe by nature,
you're a very data-driven kind of mathematical guy and you'll want to maybe just present like,
numbers and, you know, facts straight up. And I think doing the podcast, you kind of learned how
to, how to, how to kind of speak and, you know, introduce these subjects in a more sort of user
friendly way. It was an interesting progression. Yeah, that's true. We did start the, we started
the podcast in June of, or yeah, June of 2018. And I remember in the summer of 2017, so before we
were still working, when I was still working on version one, I was effectively podcasting,
but without podcasting. And in other words, I was flying around interviewing people, you know,
going up to Boston to meet with David Sabatini, meeting with Matt Caberlin, meeting with the
postdocs in their labs, sitting down and recording these interviews with them. And it was effectively
my foray into podcasting without, but it was all for the book. You know, these were all just
interviews that were used to sort of drive the book. And yes, what an evolution in that. That's
another, save that for another discussion. But boy, how difficult podcasting is too.
Yeah, it's kind of funny because some of those initial interviews ended up being some of the
first podcasts we released. That's right. I think we did end up using at least three of probably a
dozen of those as actual podcasts. And I think too, the interview, the first interview we did with
In You Go and Rick Johnson, that stemmed from you wanting to go talk to them or the book.
And we just kind of double dipped. So it is kind of funny to think about.
You know, a lot of those interviews, you'd come back and you'd be like, you gotta listen to this,
Billy, you gotta listen to In You Go. And so those fed into the, not only the writing of the book,
but sort of the evolution of thinking behind the book.
And it kind of fits in with a question we got asked quite a bit, which is,
it took you six years to write the book. There was a lot that changed in those six years as it
relates to science. There's a lot that's going to change in the next 10 years. And you, when you
announced the book, you kind of wrote about your goal with this book is it would still be applicable
in 10 years. So kind of people were curious, you know, how do you think about one writing a book
that can stand the test of time to, you know, what changed a lot in your mindset and where did
you evolve in that whole process? I mean, I think a lot of things changed in me in the six years.
Some of them just obviously very personal things, some of which I've written about in the book.
But I think more it has to do with emphasis, right? So there were things at the beginning
that were much more the emphasis in my mind and other things became more important over time.
So for example, at the outset of the writing of this book, I probably placed more of an emphasis
on nutrition than exercise as one of the important drivers, one of the important leavers we have at
our disposal. And I would say that my views on that have flipped. I think that exercise
has a bigger impact than nutrition. And certainly on the positive side, nutrition can have a pretty
big negative impact. But once it's corrected, it doesn't have this enormous upside, whereas exercise
has an enormous downside in its absence and an enormous upside in its presence. So that's,
you know, that's a, you're reading a different version of this book than you would have read
six years ago with respect to that. Or two years ago. Yeah, exactly. One year ago. Obviously,
you know, a book, this book written five years ago would have not had anything about emotional
health. There's not a lot on it, but there's something on it and I think it's relevant.
I think it's very framework focused, which I think lends to a more timeless piece.
Because frameworks or scaffoldings are there upon which to place information and substitute
information. So if the framework says delay the time that you do not have disease,
that's relatively timeless as a strategy. Now we're going to learn different things about these
diseases. I've been 10 years. My hope is that, you know, one, taking one example, liquid biopsies
should be a heck of a lot more valuable in 10 years than they are today. That's going to
completely change our approach and our efficacy of screening. So you'll have a different tactic
that you'll use in a toolkit to go about the strategy, but the goal is still the same.
So you're talking about liquid biopsies for cancer detection. Yeah. So if you can detect cancer
much earlier, it's treating, it's a whole different thing.
Yeah. And it's interesting because anyone who's listening to podcasts for a long period of time
will know, like hear you talk about things in a different way as you learn more information. And
I think sometimes a natural reaction from people is to be frustrated at that. And like, well,
why did you say this one time? And then you kind of change your mind. But I think to what you just
said, which is really important, it's probably worth spending a few minutes on it is you will
focus heavily on objective strategy tactic. And that's probably the reason why in the initial
version, it had zero tactics, which a lot of people are probably like, how do you write a
book that doesn't tell people what to do? But for you, it's how do you write a book that tells
people it's all about objective and strategy? Because as new information comes in, the tactic
may change, but the objective and strategy doesn't. Do you kind of maybe want to talk people through
how you think about that objective strategy tactic? Because I think it is applicable
for anyone who's going to read the book to really understand that for knowing how to take this
information and still make it applicable years down the road, not just months down the road.
Well, there's a whole chapter on it in part one, right? Which is like, why is it that we spend so
much time hammering this idea? And it's a simple concept, but it's amazing how often it's ignored.
So for starters, you do have to define the objective. And I won't say any more on that now,
but again, the objective, you'd be amazed at how many people would struggle to define their
objective, you know, oh, I'm taking this 27 different supplements, because I'm hacking my,
you know, whatever. And it's like, okay, what is your objective? And if you can't clearly state
that, then there's so much fog around this. The strategy is very important. And again, you know,
we open each chapter with a quote, but of the quotes, my favorite has to be the one that opens
that chapter, which is the Sun Tzu quote about strategy. What is it is the objectives,
sorry, strategy without tactics, without strategy is the noise before defeat or something.
That's right. That's it. And so we go to great lengths using lots of examples to really help
a person understand the difference between a strategy and then the tactics that they employ.
And we do this because we say the tactics are the most valuable things here. They're the things
that are going to change the most. And to your previous question, those are the things that have
already changed the most, right? So give you another example, right? Like how much emphasis
did I used to place on fasting? How much emphasis do I place on fasting today? Totally different.
I am positive that there is some set of drugs that I am either not taking now or don't even know what
they are now that I'll probably be taking in 10 years. And similarly, there's probably something
I'm taking now that in 10 years, I'm going to say the evidence for this sucks. I'm not going to do it.
So, you know, if I can't take that and anchor it back to a strategy, which is the reason I would
take this or wouldn't take this is because it feeds into one of these three overarching
principles that guides the subjective. Then I'm really just doing a bunch of random things
that aren't in concert. But you're also able and open to changing your mind. So, you know, one of
the things I noticed early on is like, you're not like a dogmatic person. If you get information or
a new interpretation of the existing data that kind of causes you to see something differently
and fasting is a big one. And Frank, I was a little bit relieved actually, because I knew I was going
to have to do it myself just to be able to write about it. But I wasn't looking forward to it. But
then you kind of got off the fasting. I think it had served a purpose for you.
Yeah. And again, there's still times when I think it makes sense, but yes, it just is one
specific example of this isn't something that everybody needs to be doing.
And one of the questions we got was, what areas of a book do you think within the next 10 years
will evolve the most? You mentioned there like liquid biopsies and cancer detection. Is there
anything else that you kind of think about when you write this book? If you're like, if I was
going to update this in 10 years, I had to make a guess on which sections I would want to refocus
on. Is there anything that you would think? Another way to think about it is, what in this
sphere are you kind of really excited about progress in the next 10 years?
I do think that we've taken a very aggressive posture on cancer screening for the reason
that Bill alluded to a moment ago, which is certainly in doing research for this book and
getting really deep in the weeds. There simply is no ambiguity that the earlier you catch cancer,
the better your odds are at treating it while it remains local.
Given the exact same histology of cancer, treating it when there are a billion cells versus treating
it when there are a hundred billion cells with the exact same therapy has such dramatically
different outcomes that there should be no question about that. You basically have to
put yourself into different camps. Are you of the mindset that we will come up with systemic cures
for cancer regardless of size and stage in the next couple of decades? Or do you think it is
more likely that we will get better and better at finding cancer when it is smaller and smaller
and treating it with existing therapies? Now, those don't have to be mutually exclusive,
but the question is which one of those you think is more likely. I think the latter is much more
likely. We present it as such. Goal number one, don't get cancer. Goal number two, if you do get
cancer, catch it as early as possible. And then, and only then, goal number three is we get into
what are the most promising things. So I think that's another area where what we're seeing right
now with immunotherapy is so exciting. And I think we are right on the verge of unlocking the next
layer of immunotherapy, right? Which is once, and by the way, I think this gets to another part of
your question, which is what else would I be excited about in 10 years that is not in this
book? Because I think it's too soon for prime time. But if we could reprogram immune cells,
so you've heard a lot of talk about reprogramming. Well, reprogramming gets talked about nonstop and
there's so much nonsense there. But there is one subset of the human body that if it could be
reprogrammed would change the game and that's the immune cell. And by the way, that's much easier to
reprogram than like your heart or your liver or things like that, in my opinion, because of how
easily we can access those cells. If we could epigenetically reprogram T cells, I think it's
a totally different game when it comes to cancer therapy and cancer incidence.
I think, yeah, I would say maybe neurodegeneration.
Yeah, that's a good one too.
But that's someplace where we're nowhere in terms of effective treatments for Alzheimer's
disease or Parkinson's disease. Hopefully better data on prevention. Right now, we've taken,
and we do this in our practice as well, we're taking very much a kitchen sink approach,
which is there are a handful of things that, especially for dementia, less clear for the
movement disorders, there are a handful of things that unambiguously reduce your risk of dementia.
There seemed to be at least three, four, if we were going to be right clear, exercise,
management of lipids on the AD and dementia side, sleep, and not having diabetes.
Those things you can take to the bank. We talk about 27 other things for which the data are
not clear yet. To have more clarity around that would be great.
And as someone who's not in the scientific field, how you talk about cancer makes a lot of sense
in the idea of if the goal, like if you have better treatment, the earlier catch it,
you want to screen as early as possible. But you talk about in the book, kind of the difference
between medicine 2.0 and 3.0 and how that's not the case now. Why do you think that's,
I don't want to say controversial approach to it, but why is that not the norm? Because from the
outside and looking in, it's hard to poke holes in that idea. Do you mean why is the traditional
view of cancer screening different from kind of the view we present? Yes. I think if I'm going
to be fair and charitable to the outside view, it would be that it's being, we're basically
asking two different questions. Okay. So I think the question and the solution that we're proposing
is at the individual level. The outside view, I think is at the population or societal level.
So there was a recent study that got a lot of attention in Europe. I think it was published in
the New England Journal of Medicine that looked at colonoscopies. The study took a large group
of people and they were randomized into two groups. So one group was standard of care. Don't
do anything. The next group was suggested that they should have a colonoscopy in the next decade.
Okay. At the end of the decade, they were compared for rates of colon cancer and colon cancer
mortality and all cause mortality. And while there was a slight benefit to the group that were
recommended to get a colonoscopy, it was nothing to write home about. The relative and absolute
difference in colon cancer and colon cancer deaths, while statistically significant, didn't seem very
clinically significant. And opponents of colonoscopy said, look, this is proof positive that
colonoscopies don't save lives. The route of it is no, it's proof positive that telling people
to maybe get a colonoscopy once every 10 years, when by the way, I think less than 40% of them
actually did, probably doesn't save lives. That's very different from the example and the approach
that we take. I mean, I'm 50, I've already had three colonoscopies. I get them every three years
and I will continue to do that until my life expectancy is so short that it becomes irrelevant.
And again, totally different approach. So we have to, and am I suggesting that
everybody get a colonoscopy every three years? Of course I'm not. What I'm suggesting is,
that everybody think about their own risk reward trade off and decide what's the cost benefit
analysis. So there's an enormous cost to doing that. My insurance company doesn't pay for most
of those. They've paid for one of the three. There are risks of bowel preps, right? You do a bowel
prep in a person who's significantly older, who runs risks from the electrolyte abnormalities that
come from those things. All of those things have to be, I certainly wouldn't want my 86 year old dad
getting a colonoscopy under any circumstance. That ship has sailed, right? The bowel prep alone
could injure him, let alone the sedation of it. So one has to be very thoughtful and measured in
how they think about doing these things. And I think the long answer to your question is, I think
when people talk in blanket statements, like cancer screening is bad, they're generally speaking
through the lens of policy and population. And it kind of leads to another question we saw come
through quite a bit, which is, sometimes on the podcast, it can get technical, can kind of get in
the weeds. A lot of people were curious, how is the book compared to that in terms of technicality?
Is it something that obviously if you're an MD, PhD, you're going to be able to understand?
But what about for just the layman? Do you think they'll be able to get as much out of the book?
And was that kind of the hope and how you wrote it? And my guess is we can get Bill's response to that.
I was actually going to turn this question over to Bill first and then I'll chime in,
but I'd like to hear Bill's thoughts on that. I have a strong thought on this.
Well, I think we're both fascinated, probably more than me, but we kind of go down these rabbit holes
of the technical details, which I call the alphabet soup. Once you start streaming together,
a lot of acronyms like APOE and PSAN and all this stuff turns into alphabet soup.
And I sort of think of the podcast as like your playground to go deep with these scientists.
And it's tremendously valuable, right? Because they don't have really a lot of other, you can't
go on fresh air as a scientist and get into that level of detail. But I would say it's
considerably less technical than the podcast, but the basic message and the kind of the...
We cover a lot more ground, so we can't really go too deep on any one particular topic. Like I was
listening to the episode about HDL. It's super interesting, but like mind bogglingly complicated.
And we just didn't have the time or the need to go that deep. And I do hope that
they figure out how to enhance the function of HDL, but yeah, we can go that far.
There were probably some sections, actually, that's interesting. The cardiovascular section,
pretty detailed actually. We go pretty detailed in that section.
But we have to. And again, I think part of it is we're trying to add enormous value in writing
this. There's a lot of kind of me too books out there on this subject matter. And by me too,
I just mean it's just another book that is literally adding no value.
Saying the same thing.
Yeah, it's just saying the same thing. And our goal here was like, there's no chapter in this book,
none, that should ever just be another version of checking that box. And so on the chapter of
atherosclerosis, I mean, yeah, I think we do go probably deeper than certainly our editor would
have wanted. I think she was kind of to her credit, just accepted the fact that she might
not understand every word of it, but you don't need to necessarily understand every word of it
to understand what to do about it. And if you do want to go deeper, because we do get into HDL,
and we do comment on the fact that HDL functionality is not captured by HDL cholesterol and HDL
particle number and APOA concentration and all of those things. And we do have to talk about the
Mendelian randomizations and what they've taught us with respect to HDL cholesterol and what they
haven't taught us and things like that. So that's probably, yeah, that's probably a little more
technical than maybe the average person would want. But I think that overall, this book is
very readable by a person who is curious. And I agree that it is definitely a notch below the
technical depth of what we often do in our podcasts.
It's not it's not meant to be a textbook either. But kind of the way I think of it is you want
people to learn more than they expected without even realizing that they're learning, kind of
package it in a story or a metaphor. And the atherosclerosis chapter is a good example of that
because most people know, everybody knows about good and bad cholesterol. And I think Peter got
a little triggered by that and we're just going to go to town. And in the writing process,
what was it, how was that like between the both of you in the sense of,
were you often trying to keep Peter in check in terms of the scientific aspect of it, trying to
bring stories in kind of how, how would you both do that throughout? Because obviously, the book is,
I mean, it's a good chunk now, it clearly could be four times as long if you went into the detail
that you could go. So kind of where in the writing process did you decide, okay,
like this deserves to go deep, this doesn't, was there ever disagreement about that? Or kind of
how did that work? Yeah, I mean, I think Bill always thought about it through the lens of the reader.
And I think there was a very healthy tension between us on those things, for sure. And I say
healthy because it was never, I don't think, I think both of us would sit here and say,
never once did we have a disagreement that was about ego, right? We had lots of disagreements
about content. But it was like Bill saying, I don't think a reader needs to know this. And I'm
saying, Bill, I think a reader does need to know this. And it wasn't about like, I want to put this
in because it's mine. It was never about that kind of stuff. So yeah, I think there was always a great
and healthy tension about that. I think once, you know, there's a backstory here, which I,
we didn't really get into, but this book basically got killed in 2020. And then it died, like it was
left, it was left for dead. And it only got revisited with a whole new publisher and a whole
new editor and a whole new process. And so that process, which went, which was now 2021 into 2022,
introduced a new player into the mix, which was our editor at Penguin. And
I don't have anything to compare Diana to as far as other editors, but she struck me as
relatively hands off. I, I, would you, would she be described as more of a hands,
more of a conceptual editor as opposed to a line editor?
Yeah. And she gave great sort of, you know, guidance and, you know, she had some give and
take, but I think between you and I, like we, it took us about six months to kind of get the right
voice and register, right? Like how, who are we writing this book for? And I think you weren't quite
clear. No, I think initially I was, I'm writing this like I would write a scientific article.
I'm writing this like I would be writing in a journal, a scientific journal.
For people who know.
And I think Bill initially was like, no, no, no, we're going to write this more like I'm making
this up. It's not what was actually said, but like, we're going to write this for USA today.
And I think in the end, we probably settled on, you know, the New Yorkers slash the New York
Times slash the wall street journal. Like it's, it's halfway in between and it's the right voice.
It is. And again, I go back to, I finally realized it's absolutely written the way it should be based
on how it sounded when I finally read the book out loud, which by the way, we dodged a bit of a
bullet because I was given this advice by Sam Harris a couple of years ago and I didn't follow
it because I never had the time. But Sam said to me, do not do your edits silently. When you were
editing this book, read it out loud. And yeah, that's good writer's advice. Yeah. And I was like,
I mean, I acknowledged what he said and I never had the time to do it. Because when push came to
shove, this is like nights and weekends. And if I got to get through a 5,000 word section,
like I don't have the fricking time to sit there and read that out loud. And so as we got closer
and closer to that reading, my anxiety was peaking because I was like, I haven't actually sat here
and done this exercise. And there were a lot of last minute edits that came out of that. Probably
many more than anybody would have been comfortable. I mean, I think you said 400. Yeah. You pushed it
to the very end. Yeah. And also not only like line edits, but also like, Hey, we just saw the
study about Tao deposition. Oh, in women. Yeah. Can we put this in? Bill's like, oh my God,
we're going crazy. But I think just kind of going back to something you said, like a lot of times
you didn't kind of come up with something or some idea or there'd be some new study about Tao. Can
we put this in? It's like, well, we'd find a way to do it. Right. That worked and kind of weave it
in and massage it in. Yeah. But a lot of times it would be, you realize like something so significant
might only warrant a sentence in a book of this nature. And yeah, I think that was just a general
process of getting comfortable, but it is the way these things need to be done. And I really,
I'm glad, I'm really glad with the way this turned out, because if this had been written in the voice
that the first version had been written in, it would have been accessible to so many fewer people.
It just would have been returned off to people. I mean, I think, you know, the feedback again from
that first version was not just that it's so technical, but there is no story in here. There's
no protagonists. There are no journeys. There's nothing to follow. And that was one of Diana's
insights. Like what's the thread that pulls the reader? That was her big saying, what's the thread
that pulls the reader through the book? And they were there. We just had to kind of expose them,
let them kind of shine. You know, one of the questions we get asked a lot, which is,
you often said this is the only book you're ever going to write. And a lot of people are like,
there's no way. And I think even Bill joked that he doesn't think this is the only book you're
going to write. And whenever people would ask that, I always be like, oh, there's not a chance Peter
writes another book. Like, there's no way. But as I'm hearing you talk now, kind of thinking to
myself, how do you not write another book in 10 years on an update to all this? So how do you,
because I know you, you went into this being like, look, I want to write one book. I want it to
contain everything, which is why you did the objective strategy tactics. Like we talked.
What makes you think that you'll actually never write another book?
You know, again, I think if we're being reasonable people, we could never say never, right?
I just think a couple of things would have to be true for me to write another book. So I say that
one thing that would have to be true is I would have to have something to say, like you, you, I
think this process is so difficult. At least, I mean, I see these people that write a book a year.
I don't understand how they're doing it. So again, let's just put those people aside. But for someone
like me to do this with the unbelievable inertia that's required to do it, the desire, the drive
to need to say something must be so great that that you have to be able to overcome that pain.
So so that's that's condition number one, I would have to have something so overwhelming to talk
about. The second condition is I would have to be at a different place in my life than I am today.
I would not want to repeat what I have done for the past five years, which is work on something
so difficult on nights and weekends. This has been I think it's just been it's just it's I've
paid a price for it that is probably higher than I would like to have paid. And I don't want to do
that again. So so I think the second equally important condition is I will need to be at a
point in my life where I'm not working 24 seven. And writing this will not kill me. Meaning, it's
not something I have to do nights and weekends, I can write it during the daytime. And that just
means my life looks different than it looks today, right? That means my kids are a lot older. That
means I'm not working as hard on my practice or other things as I am today, where those are my
jobs. And this is my hobby. So I think if those two conditions were met, if I had something really
amazing to write about, or update or tweak, and I could do it in a civilized manner, I would be open
to it. One of the questions that we got came through, which I thought was really interesting,
fits well with thread you just went on is, did you want or need to write this book? Because
you mentioned it there, there's obviously no shortage of books on health, books on longevity,
whatever you want to call it. And so what, going back to the framework you just laid out,
what do you think to you was so important to say that you were like,
I need to get this out there. And I need people to have these insights.
I think it's hard to speak to the motivation at the outset, because when I started this in 2016,
it was two years before having a podcast. So it never occurred to me at that time to have a
podcast, where I probably would have had a podcast. And maybe if I did have a podcast,
I wouldn't have thought to write a book because in some ways, a podcast is an easier way to
communicate. It's less formal, but it's easier, right? And you can communicate much more through
a podcast. So I think the more interesting question for me to think about is, let's go
back to where we were in December of 2020, Bill. So basically in February of 2020, this project is
nuked. It's dead. We're done. Publishers fired me. And nobody wants a book about longevity in
the pandemic anyway. Yeah. Yeah. It's over. And I'm over it. I'm so frustrated that, and I feel
bad that I've wasted so much of Bill's time because he's put in two full years at that point,
and he's going to have nothing to show for it. He's not going to have a book to show for it.
For me personally, I don't care. I don't need a book, whatever. And so I don't know,
Bill and I probably didn't talk for nine months. It was sort of done. I felt bad, and Bill didn't
make me feel bad or anything like that. That was just the nature of things. So that was the end of
it until late, late, late 2020 when Michael Ovets somehow asked me about it. I don't know
what brought it up. We were talking about his book, which I love. And somehow it came up that,
oh, I'd kind of written a book too, but it sort of got scrapped. And he was like, oh, send it to me.
And so I called Bill and I was like, hey, Bill, do we still have the G-Doc that has like whatever
the last version was of that thing before it died? And he's like, yeah, I could probably find it.
And I was like, do you mind sending it to me? So he did. And I sent it to Michael. And I remember
this was around Christmas of 2020. He read it in two weeks, which is saying something because it
was a pretty long ass thing. And he said, look, man, this has got to be published.
And I was like, well, we don't have a publisher. And I explained how much hair was on this dog.
And then the rest is kind of history. He just said, well, yeah, yeah, yeah, no, no. He goes,
look, we'll get this published. So that's really the question then becomes why at that moment in
time did I go back in the ring? Because I was clearly out of the ring. And by that point,
we had a podcast. I mean, this was not like I wasn't looking for things to do.
And honestly, I think it kind of comes down to some of the stuff I write about in the very
last chapter of the book. I think there was a coming to peace with some of my demons and a
realization that I wanted to do it. I really did have a I really had a strong desire to put
this material out there in basically the form it's in now, which turned out to be such a blessing.
Had it not been for getting fired by the old publisher, had it not been for COVID, had it
not been for all of the crises that emerged. This book looks a lot different. And truthfully,
I think it's not as good. But to answer your question, I think it was want more than need,
but I don't think that want really found its why until the end of 2020, the beginning of 2021.
Yeah, Bill. So hearing that, I mean, what are your thoughts on that process? And also during
that nine months of silence to you, did you ever think the book would see the light of day?
I think deep down, I knew that it would because there had been so much work that went into it.
And there was so much that's original and interesting and amazing in it that I felt like
it would be a tragedy if it wasn't published. And I was kind of depressed and sad for a while that
it wasn't. So I was very glad to get your call about your friend, Michael Ovets, wanting to see
it. It was yes, this is going to happen. And I think it was kind of interesting watching Peter
kind of like become a writer in certain ways. You're talking about like working on nights and
weekends, and you're just kind of tortured by this thing that's like hanging over your head.
And it won't go away and it has to be good, it has to be perfect. And so one of the
stages of that process is deciding that the whole thing sucks. And there's all kinds of
stories about writers throwing all their manuscripts in the fire and like, ah. And it's a process you
have to go to and go through. And especially in science writing, there's like a first draft that
we call it like the shitty first draft, and you have to write it. And it doesn't mean you're a
shitty writer or a shitty thinker. You're just getting it all out there. And then it's like,
what do we got? And then the process, you think you're done, right? Because I remember finishing
the first draft, it's like, okay, sweet, I'm done. And I think at about that point, you had sent me
an espresso machine. It's like, this was nice of Peter to send me this espresso machine now that
we're done, but we weren't done. We weren't even close. You've got the first draft. It's like you
run the first half of the marathon. Like don't put the sticker on your car. You got to run the
other half of the marathon before you're done. So yeah, it was a marathon.
And like a marathon, anybody who's run one or swum one or done these things, you know that the
physiologic halfway point is not the actual halfway point. My wife just ran a marathon recently and
we, you know, in training for this, I mean, it was all about the training for the physiologic hits.
And in that 26 miles, you don't physiologically hit the half point till 20. So you'll hurt as much in
the last 6.2 miles. You will, it will be as difficult metabolically and physiologically in
the last six miles as the first 20 were. And I think the same as I exactly the same for this
writing process, right? The, yeah, what we did in the last nine months
was more valuable than the previous five years.
Right. And I, I kept telling you that through the process, like,
you got to trust this process. Yeah, you got to trust it. And it's going to get a lot better in
the last six months than in the first however many, many years. And that's just the nature of the beast.
I remember this summer, sorry, last summer. So it was July of 2022.
We were on a pretty tight deadline at this point. So this was when Penguin said this book has to
come out in March. And if you reverse engineer that the manuscript needed to be final by the
first week of September, and we were six weeks away from that. And there were gaping holes in
this thing. Like you could drive a tractor truck through some of the holes in this thing. And
I had a feeling that I have not had since I was on a very difficult swim in 2008, 2009,
where I was in the water and nothing was going well. This was actually early on after I tore my
labrum and I was in so much pain and the current was moving in the wrong direction. Everything was
going wrong. And you know, these things are very psychological. You know, you, you, you, it's just
like running. It's like cycling. I mean, once your brain is hurting, like nothing, nothing goes right.
And I remember at one point realizing I still had seven hours to swim. And every stroke,
I felt like someone was sticking a dagger into my shoulder. And there was just a part of me that
was like, I don't want to do this anymore. I just don't want to do this. And I remember thinking
for at least an hour, all I thought about was quitting. All I thought about was just getting
out of the water. All I had to do was put my hand up and touch the boat. And I was disqualified and
the swim was over. Um, and I didn't, you know, for better or worse, I kept swimming. I don't think
it changed anything in my shoulder. I'm still going to need shoulder surgery regardless.
But I came back to this in July of 2022. And I remember talking about this with Jill.
And I remember thinking in the next six weeks, we will have to work so hard to get this thing
submitted. And we don't have a choice now, meaning we can't stretch that out for six months.
It's you have six weeks to finish. Do what you can in six weeks. And I remember saying to Jill,
I'm so torn right now because I am so tired. I don't want to do anymore. And I know that for,
I know that our publisher would accept this right now as is because it's good enough.
Yeah. But in my mind, it's not good enough. And the only way this thing is going to be good enough
to what we think it deserves is I'm going to have to kill myself for the next six weeks.
Everything I do will revolve around this and I will have to rewrite and rewrite and chop out and
do and do all these things. And I just, I just remember saying to Jill, like I want to quit right
now. I've never wanted to quit so bad and quitting. This is a soft quit. It's just a saying,
I'm going to back off. It's not that I'm not going to finish. I'm just going to back off.
And I'm glad that I didn't. I don't know how you felt at that point, but that's, I really was
like, I'm done with this. I don't even know if I care anymore. Nobody, most people won't notice
the difference between this version and the version we might be able to get to in six weeks.
Yeah. I think one thing we share in common is, maybe you're more than me, but like a kind of
a perfectionism. And to me, that goes to the sort of the level of the writing, right? Is this,
I would be going through every single sentence, like, is this the best way that this sentence can
be cast or are these in the right order? How are we structuring this? I was doing that constantly
and spent that most of that summer doing just that. And it was, yeah, it felt like in a pretty
deep hole and the deadline is looming, but deadlines are good, right? Because like,
nothing would be finished without a deadline. So at a certain point, you have to like,
take your hands off it and say, all right, this is what it is. But it did get a lot better,
even between then and when they finally yanked it out of our cold dead hands,
it got better, got a lot better, more readable.
Yeah, that was the proverbial darkness before light was that August, September was really hard.
And that's what I think every person was trying to tell me before, which is,
you have to trust how much this is going to converge at the end.
Yeah, it's kind of funny hearing that timeline, because by the time this comes out, we'll have
released a podcast with Ethan Weiss and you guys were talking about blood pressure on it.
You're like, you know, Ethan, my blood pressure has always been normal, but in August, I started
taking a reading and it just was higher, but I could calm down. And he was like, well, did
anything change during that time? And you were like, yeah, I had a book deadline. So it's kind
of funny to just see how much this book is trying to kill you along the way of not only the blood
pressure, the voice, just every little bit of stress. Yeah, ironically. Yeah. Let's talk about
the audio book. You kind of mentioned it there. I know you struggled a lot with,
should I read this or should I not? And part of it was, you know, you've said yourself, like,
sometimes like reading that much, like you'll struggle with, it was not only that, it was the
time aspect, the commitment. What made you ultimately decide to read it? Because the
overwhelming feedback we got from the audience was they didn't want to hear someone else read this
book if it wasn't you. And people will, I think this is where kind of having your own podcast
probably hurt you as everyone knew your voice and knew what it sounded like. You weren't a
voiceless figure who was just a writer. So what made you ultimately decide, all right,
I'm going to go do this audio book. Well, I mean, first I should explain why I didn't want to do
it. And I think I had some pretty good reasons for not wanting to do it. First of all, I'm not a great
out loud reader. I think I do have mild dyslexia. I certainly do when it comes to spelling. So I
can't spell if my life depends on it. And when you hear me read even to my kids, like, you know,
Reese is eight so he can read. So if I'm reading to him, he's catching mistakes that I'm,
he's catching words that I'm flipping back and forth. So that was one reason there was just like,
this is going to be very hard for me to do. The second is I did the math pretty quickly,
meaning I had figured out how long it took me to read a page. I multiplied it by how many pages
that were in the book. And I knew that I was going to basically be in a recording studio for two weeks.
I also knew that meant that that was the one week a year that I kind of wind down is between
Christmas and New Year's. I was going to be in a recording studio all day, every day. And I just
knew how I felt, which was I'm exhausted. I'm exhausted. And I don't, I actually need a week
to recharge. I don't need two more extra weeks of work. The third thing was when Rick Rubin was in
town visiting over the summer, he was beginning the process of recording for his audio book.
And he had a sound engineer set up a studio in our basement. So he was beginning to do his read
that he and his family stayed with us for a couple of weeks. And one day he was like,
Hey, why don't you go in the studio with my engineer and just read a bit and see how it goes?
And I was like, all right, that's not a bad idea. So I did. And I read it and I sent it to you guys
and you guys finally acknowledged what I was saying, which was, yeah, that's pretty rough.
Like, dude, there's no intonation in your voice. Like you're, you sound like a robot reading that.
So now we've got confirmation on my worst fear, which is I'm a lousy reader coupled with all these
other things. And I, you know, so, so, so that, those were all the reasons I didn't want to do it.
And I think those were all very compelling. So on the flip side of that, I don't remember
who suggested it. If it was you or somebody suggested that I at least meet with this woman
named Stacy Snell, who I guess is it kind of a freelancer, but works for Penguin and she would
be the producer director of my audio book. And maybe Stacy had just said, let me, let me go
and spend an afternoon with Peter and do some coaching. So sure enough, one day, and this is
probably like November, she comes over here and we do some reading and for two hours we read,
but she coached me on reading and she gave me some really amazing tips that seems so self-evident,
but they made a difference. So for example, first is read slower, right? And I should have known
this because I consume virtually all of my books in audio first, and then certain ones I go back
and read in paper, but I listen at about 1.8 to 2x, depending on the author. And so in my mind,
that's the cadence of an audio book. But if you ever actually go and listen to an audio book on
1x, I mean, it sounds like this. So what she reminded me was, you know, it needs to sound
pretty slow at 1x speed. Everything she said is, and she could tell right away, she's like, you're
not present when you're reading. It's clear to me how bored you are of this book, and I can't blame
you for it. You've read every word a thousand times, but your boredom is showing in your reading.
She's like, a good reader reads this like it's the first time they've seen these words.
She's like, you have to get there. And I was like, wow. And she's like, oh, and by the way,
reading slow makes that easier. The slower you read, the easier it is for you to be present
with every word. So armed with Stacy's feedback, I decided I'm going to do this.
And so a couple of days before starting it, I had a session with one of my therapists, and obviously
one of the things you talk about in therapy is like, what do you worry about? What do we know?
What's going on in your life? And I said, well, you know, I'm really worried. And, you know,
a couple of days I start this reading process. And so Katie said, well, what's your why? Why are
you doing this? And let's write those down. So I had three reasons why I was writing this,
and I wrote those three reasons down on a piece of paper. And those were with me in the recording
studio. And the three reasons were very simply, one, the listeners of the podcast will expect this
and deserve it. In other words, you know, we feel really grateful. Obviously,
I don't need to just say this, but, you know, we have a very loyal group of listeners to this
podcast. And to your point, there is an expectation that the person whose voice they listen to is the
one that reads it. And I think it's a correct expectation. I think they deserve that. The
second is a pet peeve of mine when I'm listening to technical books that are not read by the author
is how many mistakes there are when things are read incorrectly. It bothers me to no end. I mean,
I remember listening to one book where the author had written the word causal multiple times. And
every time the word causal was misread as casual. Oh, it's like how that got missed. I don't know.
But, you know, I thought about how many technical words are in this book. And I was like, I'm going
to lose my mind if a person. And I basically said, I'm going to end up having to be in the
recording studio anyway, just to make sure everything is said correctly. And then the
third reason was just a very personal one, which was, you know, right now, none of my kids are old
enough to appreciate this book. None of them are going to read this book anytime soon. But one day
they will. And one day they might listen to it. And in fact, I thought further, and this is kind
of a weird thing to think about because we don't normally think this way. But like imagine Hemingway
had read some of his audio books and now like distant relatives of him could listen to it and
listen to him reading it. And I thought like long after I'm dead, my great grandkids could still
listen to this, but they'll hear me reading it. And I think that will be more valuable than hearing
someone else read it. So it was really more of like something for kids and grandkids to one day have.
But it's also, you know, there are a lot of stories in there about your early life and your
medical career and, you know, some, there's some fairly dramatic, you know, ER stories. And,
you know, your story is kind of like embedded throughout the book and especially in the last
chapter. So I think it would have, like you had to read it. You just didn't realize it.
Yeah, I think that's true.
But it is a daunting and kind of terrifying task at the same time. But I don't know. Are you
glad you did it?
Oh, I'm 100%. I'm 100% glad I did zero regret on that. And just glad that you
would have turned out glad with having Stacy there in my ear for the whole thing was incredible.
I couldn't imagine if I had to do it with somebody else.
Yeah, it's funny. There'll be a lot of times where you'll be like, you know, we'll be like, Peter,
you got to do this. And I'll be like, no, I suck at this. Like I can't do it. And it's like,
okay, yeah, yeah. Like just go ahead and do it. You're like, okay. And you send it. It's like,
yeah, this is totally fine. And I think that's what we all expected when we sent over the sample
from the studio in the basement. I remember listening to it.
You're like, he's right.
And I was like, this is bad. Like there is no sugar coating it. Like it was, I remember
talking to Lacey and I was like, I honestly think it's so bad because people hear him talk on the
podcast and clearly you can speak. But you sounded like you'd never read anything in your life. And
like, you were a caveman dropped in and you were just like, what is all this stuff around me?
Right.
So you've got these phonetic symbols and like, go.
Yeah. And it was, it was just a conversation of, yeah, we can't let them do this. This is going
to be embarrassing. But then Stacy came in and really cleaned it up. And I know I listened to
some of the audio and it, it does sound really good. So to see that progression, maybe down the
road, we'll release a snippet of the initial just so people can hear the difference of it.
Because it's blackmail material hits. It's strong.
Well, actually really, we got to make sure Stacy does it before, after, on her website or something
like working with me will get you from here to here. Before and after. That's funny.
And you kind of talked about it earlier where, you know, reading the book caused you to make some
edits. Some edits.
563 or was it 863?
I think that's the closest Bill and Diana came to wanting to kill me. I think if they could have,
if they could have killed me and nobody would have found out about it, they probably would have.
And been like, Oh, God, so tragic that something happened to Peter this week. Well, you know,
I'm sure he actually, we will, we'll publish this book with your name on it.
We'll release it as is. I think there, there is a little Easter egg in the audio version as well.
That's a little different too, which probably also led to some of Diana's stress. Do you kind
of want to talk about that piece of it?
Sure. So the, before, before we turned the book over to Penguin, so back when, you know, it was in
the, the old version that died, you know, it was a very similar structure to the way it is now,
just a much longer, less elegant version. But there was an ending to that chapter. So the end
of the book, the 17th and final chapter had an ending. And I loved it. Bill was sort of ambivalent.
When Diana saw it, she hated it. She was like, I don't get it. This sucks. And I was like,
what do you mean you don't get it? I even like sent her YouTube videos to help her understand it,
to get the reference. She's like, I don't get it. It's the dumbest thing I've ever seen. This is
awful. And at this point, Bill was like, I kind of see Diana's point. Like, I don't think it's good.
And I was like, and I was like, all right, fine. So they took it out. So we took it out. And
this is, you know, this is months ago, like it's long been forgotten.
So I'm in the studio finishing and I finished the whole book. And I said to Stacy,
do you want to see the alternative ending? And she's like, what do you mean? And I was like,
this book ended with a totally different thing. Where you see it ending now, there used to be a
whole page after this. And she's like, Oh, really? Let me see it. I was like, let me see if I can
even find it. So I'm like rummaging through my computer and I find it and I give it to her.
And I'm like, read it. And she reads it. And she's in tears. And I was like,
what do you think about ending? She goes, I think it's beautiful. And I was like, well,
what do you think of, do you want me to read that? And we can decide if maybe that goes in.
And she's like, yeah, I'd go. So I went back in the booth and I read it. And I go home that day
and I email Bill and Diana and I'm like, all right, guys. And by the way, you got to put this in
context. They are at the point of wanting to kill me for changing words at this point. Literally,
I'm like, can we get rid of the the here? And this word needs to be like this versus this. And
I'm saying I want to add another page and a half to this manuscript. It's going to screw up
everything. And I won't get into the details of those conversations. They were not pleasant.
But suffice it to say, the answer was, oh, hell no. And so I accepted the fact that it would never
make its way into the written version of the book. But I said, but would you at least entertain
this being in the audio version? And they were like, of course not. Like you can't have the audio
version and different from the written version. And if we kind of left it at that, I think, but then
I asked Stacy to send it once it was edited and I just forwarded it on to Bill.
So it sounds good the way you read it. So I was like, this sounds, this is good. This is moving.
Tried to find a place to kind of massage it in or put it in someplace, maybe not as the ending,
but someplace in the manuscript. And that kind of didn't work because I mean, without going into
detail, like that last chapter probably evolved the most of any chapter in the book. And we'd kind
of gotten to a place where it was working and that part had dropped out. So we kind of decided
as a compromise to leave it in the audio as the kind of like Stanley Kubrick directors cut.
But I think it's great. Yeah. But honestly, I feel like as far as print, like the last few paragraphs
of the book, and especially like the last line is something that like sticks with me. And I think
about that. I think about that every day, that line, and I won't say what it is, but every day
when I walk the dogs, I think about that. And I think when I'm thinking about like, what's,
what am I going to do today? Like, how am I thinking about this day and the week to come?
And everything, that line sings in my head. So glad it's there.
I think we capture the best of both worlds. I think it makes sense. I think it would have been,
even if we thought it could have been shoved in at the end, I think it would have been logistically
impossible because of how it changes the pages of the book and stuff like that. So I think it's
an elegant way to do it. And I know that also if people are anything like me, like a lot of times
you want an audio book and you want the paper book. You want to fold your pages, you want to
mark it over, you want to do that kind of stuff. So I think it worked out just fine.
Frankly, I was glad you were on some level that you were making like little line edits and stuff,
like, because it makes it better. There's always stuff you can find that, I did a lot of things
that probably didn't even notice, but- No, it got so much better. There is a huge sprint at the end
to just make this thing sound right. And you're getting these PDFs from the publisher, like,
okay, your book's done. Here's your PDF. Just proofread it and see if there are any
spelling mistakes. And of course, I think we both went to town on it.
Typically, I guess the industry standard is you would do three passes on the PDF final copy.
So once you are out of working in a Word doc, you're into a fully typeset PDF copy.
And it's expected that like the first round of passes on that, you might find some mistakes.
By the third round, there's none. We got up to six or seven passes on a PDF. I mean, these
people are going, they were incredibly patient with us.
The lovely people at Penguin Random House worked very hard to-
Absolutely. They were-
Accommodate all of our last minute changes.
And they also now understand why we say with you, the only thing you do in moderation is moderation.
That's right.
And also, it's just really funny to just think about the aspect of,
they probably thought of you like a child. Like, we left Peter unsupervised to record this book,
and he just totally went off script.
And speaking of things that kind of joke, like what could go wrong, did go wrong, voice,
everything else, you want to talk about the first day in the recording studio, what happened?
So we had two recording studios to choose from in Austin. And I don't know, I just was like,
Stacy's like, it's totally up to you. Which one do you want to do? And I was like, well,
this one seems a little closer to my house than that one. And given that I'm going to
be over there every day, let's minimize the commute. So we went to the closer one.
So first day, we go in there. And I sit down and we just jump right into it. And
right out of- I'm reading the book in chronological order, of course.
I just hear like a weird little hissing sound. And I call out to the engineer and I say, hey,
do you hear that? And he says, yeah, but that's not being picked up on the recording. They said,
okay. And I can get over it. Like it's annoying, but it's like I can work through it. So I keep
reading, get through the introduction, get through chapter one. I'm like, are you, it's getting
louder. Are you sure it's not being picked up on the mic? He goes, no, I can tell you it's not
being picked up on the mic. And I'm like, yeah, this can't be right because I can hear it with my
ears off the, off the speaker. Like, you know, you're wearing a headset in there and it's not
coming through the headset. It's what I'm hearing in the room. And I know how sensitive the mics
are in those studios. I mean, they're insanely, they're so sensitive that if you're moving your
feet on the floor, it's being picked up. So we keep having this back and forth where he keeps
insisting that this is not being picked up. And I, I just finally said like, I don't, I'm not going
to tell you, I know your world, but I know how recording works. And if I can hear this with my
ears off sound in the recording studio, it must be picked up. And then he kind of pivots and says,
well, we'll be able to strip it out in post. And I'm like, okay, so it is being picked up.
So finally, I'm one paragraph away from finishing the third chapter, which was all we were going to
get through that day. That's a big day to get through the intro and then three chapters,
but they were short chapters. But so it's a full day of reading. And I remember this,
I had literally one paragraph to go and we were done for the day and he goes, you know what?
I think we are picking it up. Like what? He goes, I think there's a, it's a grounding issue.
So to make our long story short, we ended up having to go to the other studio anyway,
because they, we couldn't record there. And they assured me that they would be able to fix that
in post and they could not. So when I finished the book, they were like, you gotta come back
and reread that first day again. But I think that also was a good thing in a weird way, because
I think I was a better reader by the end than I was at the beginning. And so in a way,
I got a day to practice where it didn't count. Yeah, it is. It's funny how it ended up. You
ended up getting a free practice run, which at the time, I don't know if we thought of it that
positively, like wasting day on something you were dreading doing, but I think the audio version
ended up really well. You know, one of the last questions that we got, which I think is a really
interesting question based on the whole conversation we had. And I think we can start with you,
Bill, because I'm curious what you think as it relates to this, which is looking back at
everything that ended up in the book, did you have a favorite chapter that you guys wrote? Is there
anything that stands out where like for whatever reason, you really look back fondly at that chapter?
So it's sort of like picking favorite child. But geez, so there are these four chapters,
kind of core chapters about the horseman diseases, right? Metabolic disorders, atherosclerosis,
heart disease, cancer, and Alzheimer's disease. And those were not in the original plan.
And kind of the way those all came together, it was a huge heavy lift to try and like
understand each one of these disease processes really. And it took a huge amount of research
and me spending time with Bob Kaplan, who was kind of our research guru for the book project,
and just kind of hammering these things out. Yeah, that was pretty intense, a pretty intense
experience. And I feel like a real sense of accomplishment about how those chapters all
came out. I feel really good about them. But as far as like the chapter that progressed the most
from like most improved, I think, is the final chapter. And just from where that started to where
that ended up, I think that has to be probably my favorite chapter.
It's interesting because you didn't like that chapter initially. I know that you and Diana both,
that was probably your least favorite. And Michael was like, in the early discussions we had,
Michael was like, is this- It should be a separate book.
Is this part of the- This book or is this part of a different book?
The second book you're going to write. And I didn't agree with that either, but
it had to change. And I'm always thinking about, like Nick said, where the reader is kind of from,
like you said. So that chapter ended up being one of my favorites, probably my favorite.
I think there were sections of various chapters that I really like. I think that
the insights that come out of the atherosclerosis chapter are so important and probably have the
potential to save more lives than anything else. I really think that I don't pull any punches in my
views on how we are mistreating this condition and why it does not need to be the leading cause
of death. No chance of that. And I do think that in a, and that's also one of those things where
earlier versions of it didn't get to the point quick enough. They had too much in it that didn't
matter enough. And it was really a very late, late edition was that the really clear pivot to the
causality stuff at the end that I think is a much more insightful way to talk about it. So I'm very
proud with how that turned out. I think for me, the exercise chapters, there are three chapters on
exercise, which speaks to the importance that that plays in this book. And that was probably the one
where even as recently as like July or August of last year, I was like, I don't see how we get this
to the finish line. Like I don't see how this gets done. And we were trying at that time to do too
much. And when we instead focused on what we could do in a book, because again, it's not a picture
book, right? This is not a how to exercise book where you're going to have like a picture of every
single step of like, here's how to deadlift, here's how to do this, here's how to do that. And we were
trying to do all of that in writing at one point. It had an incredible level of detail. Just wasn't
happening. Couldn't make sense. Like you can't explain these things in writing. And so I think
a big aha moment we had was, A, let's restructure this, which we did. B, let's simply make a page
of videos that explain some of these things so that we don't drown the reader in anatomic,
kinesthetic lingo that won't actually serve the purpose. And so when I look at how those three
chapters form together and coalesce around the centenarian decathlon in the marginal decade,
I'm really proud of that. And you mentioned Bob's name a few times, kind of both of you, but
I know this was beyond just the two of you. There was a lot of people involved in the research,
the writing, the science piece. So anyone else kind of, because one of the questions that we got was,
how many people do you think were involved in the writing of this book?
Well, Bob did the heaviest lifting in terms of the, because Bob was working on
the research full-time. So basically the way it would work is I would be writing and I would be
saying, Bob, I remember there was a study that sort of had this, like the end notes on this book are
probably 500. So there's just probably more than that. So I would say, Bob, can you go and find me
the citation of this study? I kind of vaguely remember reading it a year ago, blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. Or it would be, I want to write about this. Is the answer this or this,
Bob, can you go figure it out? So this was really important research that was being done.
But then the other thing that had to be done was all the fact checking. And one of the things that
I took as wise advice from other authors who had written scientific books is you can't just rely on
a publisher to fact check your book. They can fact check some things, but you have to have an
independent person to come in and do scientific fact checking. So we had one analyst named Vin
Miller who did a lot of that work because Bob was too close to it at the time, right? If Bob's the
guy pulling the citations, can't have Bob fact check it. So had to have a separate analyst that
was working on fact checking. And then once we got into a much, much later version,
then we had Bob go back and do specific certain fact checks on certain things,
which also meant, and God bless Bob, because this is long after Bob had left, he came back and did
a night weekend, like he was the guy that organized the end notes. And that was another thing that
just gave me chest pain. Like, I mean, the unbelievable thought of what it would take
to organize the end notes to this book and the version control problems that we had with multiple
different documents. I mean, it was so stressful. And by the way, it should go without saying,
people are going to find mistakes in this. It's impossible that we got it all right. It's
impossible that we got every end note perfectly. I guarantee you, we have a citation in there that
we got wrong. And that's why you have second and third editions to books. And so folks should let
us know when they see those things and we'll do that. But I think we did as good a job as one
could do in this regard and having a lot of people to shoulder some of those lifts.
I spent a lot of time kind of putting my head together and on Zooms and going back and forth
with Diana when you were off doing things and kind of trying to work out the kind of
literary side of the book and how to structure it and how to make these different chapters
kind of move better, basically, is a better way of putting it. So I worked very closely with Diana
and Bob, actually. Bob would give me the full research download on literally, I'd say like,
hey, Bob, I'm trying to understand how APOE works and boom, a G-Doc would appear the next day
with tons of sites and studies that just go down the rabbit hole with Bob about that.
So he was great with that. Bob has a endless number of G-Docs. I would love to know how he
stores all of them because you asked Bob a question, you are getting a G-Doc in response.
I spent weeks, we probably all spent weeks talking about the monkeys, the caloric restriction
monkey studies. I'm glad that they stayed in the book. I was really worried that the Bethesda,
Wisconsin monkeys were going to get chopped, but in the end, they found a great place for them.
It's a fantastic story to tell. There are a lot of folks in here that I put in my acknowledgments.
And in fact, it's pretty unusual, I think, that an author will read the acknowledgments in the
audio book, but there was no hesitation in my mind. When we finished the book and I said,
look, I'm going to not just read the epilogue, but the acknowledgments, they were like, oh,
that's unusual. A lot of authors don't, but it's a very sincere heartfelt thank you to a lot of
people who have played an enormous role in my broad education on this topic, which has been
going on for more than a decade, and also some of the real specifics. So broad education, the
podcast guests, again, the podcast started basically as a research tool for the book.
And then of course, one of the things I do mention in the acknowledgement section,
which is true and interesting, every single person that I ever sent a chapter out to for
technical feedback and review did so. There's not one person that I sent a chapter to, and every
chapter of this book, every technical chapter has been reviewed by a technical expert in that field.
At least one.
At least one, that's right. And oftentimes at least more than one. There is not one example
where I said, hey, you're so-and-so, can you read this cancer chapter? Can you read this
athro chapter? Can you read this? Where that person didn't come back with incredible feedback?
And I mean, the word is overused, but I'm humbled by that. And that means a lot to me. And I think
it makes this book a better book.
When you decided to read the acknowledgments, did they try and get you to read the footnotes as
well? Or did that not make the audio book?
You know, it's funny, and Bill, you probably don't even realize this, but I took a hit or
miss approach on footnotes. Some of them I read and some of them I actually didn't.
Oh, the ones at the bottom of the page?
The true footnotes at the bottom of the page, which obviously we took 98% of them out.
You were delighted, I'm sure. And of the remaining ones, some of them I just felt
they don't flow with the text. Like I'm trying to put myself in the mindset of the reader
or the listener rather. And if the footnote was so tangential that it would be difficult to get
back into the book, I didn't read it.
Yeah. There were some funny tangents that maybe didn't need to be read.
I think there's one about making all your dates read Richard Feynman.
I definitely didn't read that one. I don't even know if that one stayed in the book.
And Steven Rosenberg. You made them read the Transform 7 also.
That's right.
About immunotherapy.
Well, Peter, Bill, anything either of you want to end with as we end the podcast? And again,
the hope going into this wasn't to answer specific questions about the book. I'm sure we'll do a
podcast down the road, which is once people have had time to dive into it, answer specific questions.
Yeah, we should do a book AMA at some point. And obviously, I've been on a few podcasts
already for the book. And the coming months, I will be on many podcasts. We have a number
scheduled where we'll get into the subject matter. But yeah, I think this was a unique
opportunity to talk about something we'll probably otherwise never really talk about.
A little behind the scenes.
I would say it was an honor and a pleasure to work with you. And I learned a lot, obviously,
but as far as thinking and rethinking about these issues was an exciting adventure and a
little tough to get it on the page sometimes and get it just right. I'm proud. I hope you are too
proud of what we have come up with. I really am, Bill. And I think it's hard to imagine this
having worked out any other way. So I'm glad that all the way back in 2017, they said, Peter,
this will be a better book if you write it with someone. And that even back then, trusted me to
go and find who that person was. And I think this is the best book I could have ever been a part of.
So thank you, Bill.
you