Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode of the drive.
My guest this week is a gentleman by the name of Scott Harrison, who I suspect many of you
have not heard of, which is not uncommon for this podcast, but my hope is certainly that
by the end of this episode, you'll be glad you heard of him and heard him.
Scott's the founder and CEO of Charity Water, which we'll talk about in great detail.
Charity Water is a pretty unique charity, not just in that the work they're doing is
remarkable, but I think the efficiency with which they do it and the transparency with
which they do it and the sort of financial model that they've built is really interesting.
But truthfully, the real reason I had Scott on was not so much to talk about Charity Water.
And we do get to it probably at the end of the podcast, but it's more to actually talk
about his personal story.
And even though Scott, as you'll learn in this podcast, is religious, and I don't find
myself to be a religious person in any way, shape or form, I'm really moved by not just
his conviction, but this sort of incredible sense of purpose he's found in life.
And it's really his life's story and transformation that really moved me the very first time we
met, which was about four or five years ago.
And to this day, whenever I speak with Scott, I come away feeling on some level like kind
of a lousy person who's not good enough, which is probably okay, but more importantly,
just inspired.
And I'm convinced that you will come away also feeling inspired by Scott, who never once
is the kind of person that leaves you feeling like, why aren't you doing more?
But Scott has really dedicated his life to helping people in a way that I think many
of us can only dream of.
I would go so far as to say, honestly, that Scott is one of two people that I consider
the most remarkable people in the nonprofit space.
The other one being a woman by the name of Catherine Hoke, who some of you may have
heard of, she's been on Tim Ferriss' podcast and I'm sure to have her on here at some point
as well.
But between Cat Hoke and Scott Harrison, I find them to be two of the most inspiring
people who have really chosen to dedicate their lives to the public sector in this way.
Part of the stuff we talk about in this episode has been covered in his book.
So Scott is now a New York Times bestselling author.
That book is called Thirst.
I don't know that he'd want me to publicly disclose what the advance was, but it was
a very sizable advance and he gave every single penny of that to his charity and all of that
goes directly to the work that they're doing.
He's an amazing speaker and he's just kind of a magnetic personality.
So I would invite you to take a chance and listen to this, even if it sounds like at
the surface, this isn't what I'm really interested in.
But I think you will definitely get something out of this and you'll definitely get a sense
as I did of how we can get a glimpse of happiness and how Scott on one level, in the first chapter
of his adult life, seemed to be living what many of us might think, oh, that sounds pretty
cool and interesting.
And I can see how that would make you happy, but how he ultimately found something totally
different and now I think Scott's probably one of the happiest people I know.
So without any further delay, welcome to this episode with Scott Harrison.
Hey Scott.
Hey Scott, good to have you here man.
Nice to be here.
Thanks for slumming on the Upper East Side with me.
Took the train off.
It was pretty quick.
It's actually a nice day.
It's beautiful.
It falls my favorite time.
Where do you live?
You live in?
Tribeca.
Actually Battery Park City.
So we had kids and moved across the highway.
Got it.
So we met in kind of one of the funniest ways imaginable.
And that's been what, three or four years ago?
Yeah.
You gonna tell them?
Well no, no, it's just, I mean, you can tell, I'll tell the story from my end and you can
tell the story from your end, but we'll not name the name of the person who we met through,
but we met through one of my patients and we were all at this meeting called Dialogue,
which I've enjoyed and I've gone to probably four of them.
I didn't go this year.
This is my first year not going in a while.
And it was a weird day, but I had arranged for my family to come to meet at the airport
and then we were gonna fly together on his plane to New York.
And as we were leaving the hotel, he said, hey, I met this really cool guy.
He's gonna hop on the flight with us.
Do you mind?
To which I said, how can you ask me if I mind?
It's your plane.
Of course I don't mind.
But yeah, awesome.
And so we basically, you and I met in the, for the first time in the car ride on the
way to the airport because dialogue is big enough that it's easy to not meet somebody
there.
So we didn't actually sit in any sessions together.
So that was how we met.
It wasn't at your birthday?
It was.
It was just by coincidence that happened to be my birthday.
And the funniest part is we got somehow got talking about watches and pretty early in
the conversation you mentioned, look, I'm on a budget, man.
I run a nonprofit.
I can't, I can't be rolling with the high level watches.
And I think you said sort of what is your best, what's your favorite watch, you know,
on a certain price point.
And I said, oh, this is a no brainer, man.
It's a Seiko.
It's a Seiko cocktail.
Yep.
And I remember on my phone, I pulled up a picture and I showed it to you and you like,
oh, that's gorgeous.
And then, and then we, you know, we spent seven minutes talking about that and 23 minutes
talking about your story, which was really captivating.
But then if I remember correctly, your wife had then surprised you at the end of a flight
with that specific watch.
That's right.
This is the only time my wife has bought me a watch because she generally doesn't like
to support my watch habit, but she also knew how much I loved the Seiko cocktail.
So when we're on the plane, she whips out the watch, which I couldn't believe it.
Not only that she had done this, even ordinarily, I would have been very surprised, but how
could this have happened a few hours after we had just talked about it?
And then you gave the watch to me, which was, which was a wonderful surprise and nice.
And then I think that surprised your wife even more.
Well, I asked her, I said, you know, hey, I know this is going to sound strange, but,
and I love the watch.
So please don't assume that like I'm asking you this because I don't love the watch.
But I think giving this watch to Scott would be like it's almost, it's meant to be, it's
sort of, he's meant to have this watch because it's what we talked about.
And I told her the whole story and she was like, yeah, you're right.
You gotta, you gotta give him the watch.
Which I'm, I'm very grateful for.
I actually heard someone in California who's a family friend say once that on his birthday,
he would give gifts to everyone else.
He would give gifts to his children and then later his grandchildren.
So he would look at his birthday as the time that he could lavish extravagant gifts on
all the loved ones around him, which I always thought was so nice.
Well, and you have kids.
So I think you understand what all of us understand who have kids.
And I'm sure there are people who have come to appreciate this even before they have kids,
which I guess in some way I did as well.
But it is really much more enjoyable to give than to receive.
And it was probably two years before I went out and finally bought myself a cocktail.
And it was funny, I kind of forgot that I'd given it to you.
And then about a year ago, I remember somebody on Twitter said, Peter, please tell me best
watch to get under 500.
And I said, say, go cocktail, here you go.
And you just chimed in on Twitter and made a comment that nobody else would have known
what the context was.
But I was like, Oh my God, I totally forgot about that.
That's fun.
And birthdays have been significant for me and for the organization.
So that was just a fun, really fun thing.
So thanks for that.
Well, more importantly, let's talk about the real stuff that we talked about because we
had, you know, obviously that car ride.
And then we had like a five hour flight to New York when we got to really kind of talk
about your story, which I was just blown away by.
And at the time, my day job was running a nonprofit.
And unfortunately for me, that was probably the single, it's been the worst professional
experience of my life.
I really hated running a nonprofit.
I probably vented to you somewhat about how much I hated fundraising, which sort of became
the only thing I was doing.
But I was really blown away by not just your work, but the efficiency with which you did
it.
And once you're in the nonprofit space, you start to understand what metrics matter.
And look, I mean, a lot of nonprofits are doing great work, but some of them are doing
it with staggering efficiency.
And you know, I'm going to want to hear all about that.
But actually the part that really gripped me was your background.
So let's, if you don't mind, can we start at the beginning?
Sure.
Where'd you grow up?
I was born in Philadelphia and my dad was, he had been working for Arthur Anderson.
He was kind of on the big accounting career trajectory would hope to make partner one
day, had me and then started traveling.
He was traveling all the time and said, look, I'm actually going to jump off that track
and I'm going to take a smaller job.
But why not to be a transformer company, you know, selling power supply to the Navy
and to municipalities.
So we moved to get closer to his new job, which would have him not on the road and allowed
to just be a dad.
They wanted a bigger family, he and my mom.
And she was a writer.
So she was working for the Philadelphia Inquirer and the local newspaper.
And at four, we pick up from outside of a suburb outside Philly, moved to South Jersey
into this.
I remember it was a very gray drab four bedroom house, not their dream house by any stretch
of the imagination, but it was 22 minutes from his job, which he just had a 22 minute
commute.
I remember he just kept saying that.
And it was a good school.
It was on a cul-de-sac, so I could walk to school, elementary school.
And what we didn't know was that the gas company had installed a faulty heat exchanger in this
house and there was a carbon oxide gas leak.
So we move in in the dead of winter and it's an energy efficient house.
So the whole thing is just locked up tight.
And we all start breathing in these invisible fumes.
I get a little sick, headaches and just some kind of allergy spring up.
My dad gets a little sick, but we were only doing nights in the house and we were doing
it upstairs.
My mom, unfortunately, was doing all 24 hours in the house, unpacking boxes, fixing up the
house, fixing up the basement, actually.
On New Year's Day in 1980, she walks across the bedroom and she collapses unconscious.
And after a series of blood tests, they finally identify massive amounts of carboxyhemoglobin.
But this took a while.
It took a period of a couple months.
Yeah.
This was a real, I mean, in your book, which we're going to get to because obviously the
listeners, I think, would really enjoy your book.
This was something I didn't even know from meeting you.
This is something I knew only from reading the book.
But that was a really, really complicated diagnosis.
I mean, that was not obvious to the doctors what was going on with your mom.
And I almost, it's not even clear you're representing in as much detail just how sick
she became.
Yeah.
And what happened again from my non-medical perspective was my mom's immune system died.
So it was irreparably destroyed.
And she went from flying around the world with my dad.
Before they had me, they were flying to Paris and to Rome and vacationing in the Bahamas
and Bermuda.
They were completely healthy.
She was a tennis player, just this vibrant, amazing wife, and then later amazing mom.
From this moment, effectively anything chemical begins to make her sick, very sick.
Perfume, soap, car fumes.
The ink from books would make her sick.
The print, the smell from a new book.
And she goes from clinic to clinic and they wind up isolating her.
And they find that by isolating her from all toxins, she can be okay.
So the healthiest they can ever get her is drinking spring water, eating one organic
food on a rotation diet every six days.
So breakfast would be cashews, lunch would be lettuce, dinner would be a piece of cod
because she had a slew of food allergies that came along with this.
And bringing her back from the clinics with this diagnosis of multiple chemical sensitivity
or they called it environmental illness at the time.
And at one point, if I recall, she did a five day fast.
They put her on water only to try to sort of detox her.
And then try foods one by one and she reacted negatively to almost every food.
So I think she had maybe it was 20 foods at the end after testing over a hundred.
So what I remember as a kid was there was a miscarriage that happened around this time
and then family planning stopped.
So I was an only child growing up and I go very quickly into a caregiver role to help
dad take care of mom.
This started when you were four or five.
Four.
It happened very quickly.
We then prepared a special room for her that would be her safe room in the house.
And I remember it was a tile bathroom, a little bathtub.
And we put an army caught in there for her to sleep in.
And then we washed, we used to wash everything in baking soda.
Baking soda was just, it was everywhere in the house.
So we would wash our clothes 10 times in baking soda just to get any odor out.
We washed this army caught that was made out of cotton, you know, at least 10 times to
get all the smell out.
And then I remember my dad covered the door with aluminum foil because there might be
the slight smell from the varnish stain used years ago.
So this then became her room and she always wore these charcoal masks, which would also
help just filter out.
There were years where oxygen played a part and she'd be walking around with oxygen tanks.
Tell me how high her levels were.
So the diagnosis of carbon monoxide needs to be made through blood and you measure a
byproduct of it.
And once you cross, so most of us walking around should be at zero.
Yeah.
What was her level?
I actually wrote about it in the book.
I don't remember.
I remember it was way, it was shocking.
I feel like it was 20 or 25 times than the upper limit of what we would consider toxic.
Yes.
And way more than a smoker, you know, it was, it was in the upper room.
We never tested dad and I, it was interesting because we were also exposed and I remember
bouncing back.
So the food hour just kind of went away.
The headaches went away.
Oh, so you had food allergies as well.
I did too.
And I would, I would have headaches.
I would have nausea.
My dad eventually ripped out the heater.
So he found the leak and then, you know, threw the thing on the driveway.
It was a really sad story because my dad had actually suspected that maybe something was
wrong with the stove or the heater.
So he called the gas company out a couple of times.
They checked everything, checked the hose and said, no, everything's fine.
So it was a plumber friend of his that said, Hey, let's go down to the basement.
And they ripped out the thing and they found it themselves.
And this, you know, this really destroyed our, our lives.
And the gas company wasn't terribly accommodating.
If I recall.
No.
And, and I guess most people would have expected my parents to sue for negligence.
I think a couple of things happened.
One they had just become Christians.
They'd become people of faith right around this time.
I think I was two.
And they had a doctor friend, you know, from their church that said, Hey, I don't think
you should sue.
I don't think this would be good for your family to be in a long protracted, angry, bitter
battle.
You've got healthcare.
And it was an accident.
It actually was an accident.
It wasn't like the gas company was trying to kill my family.
This was an accident.
This was a faulty piece of metal that was installed.
So I think my parents took a settlement check for 1250 or $1,500 from the gas company and
said, you know, okay.
And I can relate to that.
I had a really bad back injury in medical school, which I've talked about in the past,
but a lot of things went wrong with my care, including a surgeon that operated on the wrong
side.
And I lived a different life for about a year, including three months where I couldn't even
feed myself.
And when it was all like, so now obviously I'm fine, right?
And I was fine within a relatively short period of time.
Within a year I was completely functional.
And within I would say three years, I was as good as before.
And whenever I tell the story, people are always like, Oh, you must have sued for a
lot of money.
And it's funny.
It never crossed my mind.
And I always kind of joke about it and say, well, I think it's because I grew up in Canada
and we're simply not litigious people in Canada.
I don't know.
But I also realized that in the moment, the only thing you want to do is get better.
And a lawsuit generally doesn't accelerate that.
Now I'm not for a moment saying there shouldn't be litigious action and lawsuits certainly
have their place.
But I think most people don't come to the conclusion that I think your family friend
came to, which is my brother's a lawyer.
So I see what lawsuits look like.
I understand from friends and family what that process is.
It generally results in more pain before there is a remedy.
Certainly stress.
Yes.
And I mean, we talk about it and it sounds touchy feely, but stress really matters.
And especially in the case of what your mom was going through, I suspect stress would
have been a far greater impediment to her recovery.
The other thing about your story, about your mom's story that blows my mind just as a doc
is people like your mom often fall through the cracks in medicine because they're viewed
as crazy.
So we have a bad habit in medicine of dismissing patients when we don't know what's wrong and
they don't fit into an obvious bucket.
So you say, well, look, she was totally healthy and now she's a wreck.
It's got to be in her mind.
She's got to be having a nervous breakdown.
There's got to be something going on.
And I see this a lot and I get approached a lot by people who are in that situation.
And it breaks my heart because I don't know how to fix it.
I mean, that's just, I don't, there's a real narrow lane that I play in, but deep down,
I know like I just have a hard time believing that there's that many people who are sort
of crazy.
And that in reality, I remember something one of my med school professors said, which
is we use this term in medicine, idiopathic.
Idiopathic means we don't know what the cause is.
So you have idiopathic fill in the blank idiopathic pain.
And he says, you know what it really means is probably idiotic, like, but referring to
the doctor, not the patient.
So I guess you were not old enough to recall, but in discussions with your mom since, I
mean, did you get a sense of how difficult it was for your mom and dad during the period
of time when the diagnosis was unclear and it was this huge mystery of what the heck
happened?
Well, I remember when I read about this in the book, people thought, damn, I'm going
to tell you, my dad was crazy at work.
So or the mom was crazy.
So they would say, oh, this is just in her head.
And you know, I remember the term psychosomatic thrown around so so much as a kid.
And I was never a suspect of that until I became a teenager.
And then I joined that camp briefly, just thinking, it's just not possible.
I mean, some of these things that she said made her sick just just seemed to defy logic
to me to a 13 or 14 year old boy.
You know, there's this I remember there's this scene that I write about where there
was a period of time where electromagnetic radiation was making her sick TVs and radio
waves.
And I thought she's just trying to rain on my parade and make sure I don't watch TV or
listen to the radio so that I'm reading all the time up in my room.
I got to try this with my kids.
Anytime they spend more than 30 minutes on the iPad, I start getting sick.
I got to get sick.
Start twitching.
So this this one night, you know, I'm very, very clever.
And the little teenage boy, you know, climbs up the stairs and I've got a radio in my hand
and all the lights are out and I'm padding very softly.
And there's an outlet right outside the door.
So her doors closed the tinfoil door.
And I turn the radio, I plug it in, but the volumes all the way down.
And I turn the speakers so that they're aiming right at the cot where she's sleeping on the
other side of the door.
And I'm like, I'm just gonna, I'm gonna nuke you all night with the radio waves.
You're gonna wake up fine.
And I'm gonna have a big aha.
I mean, I'm gonna drop the mic on this.
And I'm gonna listen to all the radio I freaking want from this point on.
Well, the opposite happened.
You know, the morning she woke up, she was terribly sick.
I don't remember the specific symptoms she had that day, but she was really scared because
what had gotten to her in her safe room.
I mean, this is the room that she would go to recover from exposure to things.
And actually don't remember feeling that much kind of shame or, you know, feeling that bad
as a kid, but it did cross that off the list.
You know, I believed her.
And that was a really important moment for me to say, wow, okay, she's, you know, specifically
with this, she's not crazy.
And that was one of the crazier ones.
I mean, you can understand how car fumes, you know, or a diesel truck going by is probably
not great for our bodies.
Well, mom would have a migraine within 30 seconds of that exposure or, or often would
even break out, you know, her body would just start reacting.
So it was weird.
It was a weird childhood.
I remember, you know, you just have these glimpses in these scenes that the books was
just this illustration of how far she'd really gone.
And mom being a writer, she was also an avid reader and she still wanted to have books
in her life.
So my dad's and my solution to this was we would, we'd bake them.
We would open up the oven and we would just start baking over, you know, the period of
a day or two on low, you know, maybe 200, 250.
And we'd be moving the pages just to try to alcacet to get that smell of new print out
through the heat.
We would also put them out in the sun.
So I just recently was home and I came across a family photo in an album of a hundred books
out on the grass, baking in the sun, just out, outgassing.
So that was a, there were these words, you know, outgassing, reacting.
These are words that getting pure that I would just hear, you know, countless times growing
up.
So I wanted mom to be like other moms, but I'd say in the first part of childhood, I
was really taking care of her.
I felt bad for her.
I would go sing her songs or I would go and sit with her.
I was always getting pure.
So if I came in from the outside world, I would have to wear special clothes that had
been washed in baking soda.
And there were clothes trees out in the garage where I'd take off the clothes that might
have, I don't know, the whiff of smoke on them.
My dad was always giving me the sniff test, like a bloodhound, you know, I'd walk in from
the outside and, you know, oh, I smell this or I smell that because I never wanted to
change my clothes.
I'd say I'm fine.
I wasn't around anything.
I went for a walk.
They would always smell something.
So then, you know, I would I would I was constantly getting pure so that I could be around her.
And it was it was it was weird.
I did a lot of the cooking for her.
I did the cleaning, did the washing up.
And then I think as that moved towards as it moved into teenage years, I just began
to really resent it and resent her.
Last thing, just going back a minute, you know, the what was really helpful for my parents
was finding other people like mom who had been sick.
And I don't remember.
She was the only one I remember that had been sick because of a gas leak.
But I do remember a couple people in our family, friends that had been completely normal.
And then one day, a pesticide company came in and did all the lawns in the neighborhood.
It was called chem lawn.
And then they just snapped and they were like, mom, the next day.
So there was something in their body that just couldn't take massive amounts of pesticides,
you know, throughout the entire neighborhood on their lawn and their front lawn in their
backyard.
And that made sense to me.
At least there was an event.
Pesticides are probably not good for any of us.
But your, you know, your body and my body, we can fight that off.
So I remember that really helped me, too, saying mom is not alone.
There is a community of environmentally sensitive patients.
And my dad was just this hero through the whole thing.
He doesn't leave her.
I mean, they slept in separate beds for almost 10 years because there was a period of time
where she needed to be in this special room.
And there was a period of time where he would make her sick, the candida.
I mean, it was just always, always something making her sick.
And he just stuck, stuck by her.
I mean, it was very loyal, tried to do the best he could with me and take me to baseball
when he could and soccer and gave me the most normal life that he could.
But it was far from normal.
You know, you obviously, there's many kids that go through variations of this.
But in many ways, you were sort of what we would call enmeshed, the enmeshment, meaning
you were forced into an adult role too soon.
And I guess it's not surprising to me that as a teenager, you'd start to kind of rebel
against that because you sort of you miss that period of life when you have absolutely
no responsibility and you had the responsibility.
I mean, it's hard for me to imagine what you're talking about based on a personal experience.
But I can try to extrapolate that, you know, look, you were forced into a caregiver role.
You were sharing care with your father of your mom.
And so do you remember when it started to sort of become frustrating to you?
And, you know, my guess is the combination of adolescence and puberty by themselves are
enough jarring disruptive change coupled with the, you know, the soil of all you've
experienced.
I think, you know, there was a hope as a child, maybe that this would end.
And when you hit adolescence and, you know, I realized this was never going to end.
There was no cure.
And you like, could you bring friends over after school and hang out or was that just
too disruptive to the house?
Only if they stayed outside.
So there were signs, keep out on all the doors, chemically safe, sensitive patient.
So no, they couldn't come in.
You know, there were periods of time later on in high school where if they did get pure
and mom was in a different part of the house, then we could open up the windows and air
out that room.
So there were some exceptions.
But the general rule was, you know, everything had all life had to happen outside of the
house.
You know, this is terrible for her too, to not be able to, you know, play video, not
video games, play board games or she'd be watching out a window as I played soccer in
the back, but she couldn't really meet my friends and see what they were like.
She couldn't invite them into the kitchen and bake brownies, all these things that she
really wanted to do.
So there was a lot of pain for her feeling like she wasn't able to show up as a mother
or as a wife.
How did your mom cope with that pain?
Emotionally pain?
Well, my parents, there's one answer.
She had this unwavering faith.
She would read the Bible.
She would try and stay positive.
She would thank God for her symptoms and believe that through these trials, she was
getting closer to, you know, to serving, you know, closer to kind of having this pure hearts.
So really, I mean, just a remarkable, extreme version of stoicism, really, if you think
about it.
I mean, I think, you know, the stoics, Marcus Aurelius and Seneca, of course, they don't
talk so much about religion, but there's still this belief that these challenges make us
better.
And so, you know, you can't sharpen the knife without a blunt object.
And for mom, I think that was in the picture.
It sounds like how she was describing it.
And in the picture of Jesus, he was suffering.
And you know, well, there's all these stories that she would find in the Bible of people
suffering and it being for a great purpose, you know, there being a reason for it all.
So I just remember she would walk around and she would say, like, praise God for the fabrics
offener that just made her sick.
You know, she was just trying to stay positive throughout all of this.
So you know, kicking up into the teenage years, too, I start to rebel against the role of
faith, the role of the church, the rules, the religiosity.
I didn't like going to church anymore.
You know, it's more fun as a kid when they're telling stories of Jonah and the whale and
you know, the flannel boards, but not as a teenager when you just realize you're not
allowed to swear, you're not allowed to sleep around, you can't drink, you can't smoke.
It was there are a lot of rules.
There's a lot of can't do's.
And I remember I have this vivid memory of coming home after school and mom, there was
a period of time where mom then lived out in the yard.
A friend built a lean to.
So she found that in times where the pollen wasn't too bad or the mold wasn't too bad,
there were seasons where she would feel better sitting outside than in her safe room.
And she would have this little igloo cooler next to her.
She would have a chair.
She would have her mask on and she would just protect herself from the wind.
So she would be on one of these four corners, depending on which way the wind was blowing.
And I would come home from school and she'd hear the car pull up into the driveway and
she'd yell my name and I would just pretend not to hear her and I'd walk in the house,
which, you know, that to me feels like the kind of the picture of this just got old.
This was tiring.
You know, I didn't want to go and find out what she wanted me to bring her.
And I can only imagine that on some level that produces some guilt and shame within you.
But at the same time, it's sort of a protective thing that you're doing because of all the sort of the pain and the trauma that you've been
you know, it's been inflicted on you since you're four years old.
And so I've always find like stories like this to be so tragic in a way.
And I mean, I think in many ways your story has a happy ending.
But for many people, these don't have happy endings because nobody's at fault here.
This isn't about like blame or fault, right?
People get sick, bad things happen.
And yet families can get ripped apart by these things in ways that aren't entirely obvious.
And I think what comes next in your story to me is makes much more sense after I read your book than just knowing a couple of snippets along the way.
Now, you're a pretty musical guy, right?
I played piano growing up.
You know, I remember my grandpa taught me at four, taught me on an organ and I always played.
So then in high school, you you transfer to a new school, if I recall.
Yeah, I got to talk about the first high school.
So this was also part of the rebellion.
So I'd gone to public elementary school and then they put me in a Christian kind of Baptist middle school, which I actually liked.
But then ninth grade freshman year of high school, they put me in the basement of a church school and there were nine people in my freshman class and they couldn't afford
enough teachers. So we would be taught by VHS video.
So they would wheel in the cart.
Remember those old gray metal carts and they had kind of the ribbed trays and they'd pop in science and we'd sit there for 45 minutes, which felt like it was 100 hours.
And it was just terrible.
And we had to wear these ugly uniforms and it was just everything was wrong for a 14 year old kid going to school in the basement of a church by video.
And I was surprised this was accredited.
How it's amazing to me.
They did their best.
And it's funny because I know a bunch of people that came out of that school that did all four years and actually became very successful.
I just at that moment, I wanted to explore the public high school and it couldn't be any more different.
There were 4000 people in high school.
I think my parents saw something in something simmering, maybe in my personality that really scared them.
Throwing me into this worldly high school where undoubtedly there would be drugs and sex and drinking and ungodly things going on.
And I remember just saying, look, I'm going to run away from home.
Or I'm not going back to the school.
And they said, you know, and I was smart enough to say, look, I'm not being challenged, academically challenged.
I was an avid reader growing up.
I remember getting a job when I was I think I was 14 writing or 14 or 15 writing for the local county newspaper.
So I was a pretty good writer.
I was an avid reader.
TV was just TV made bomb sick.
So we did have a tiny TV, but it was in a in a room that they made really uncomfortable.
And maybe I watched a couple of hours of TV a week growing up.
So reading was really my escape.
And I moved into the big high school and exactly what they had feared happens almost immediately.
Fallen with the wrong crowd.
I fallen with a crowd who's older and is not really interested in going to high school but was in a band.
So I then joined the band, which was an alternative rock band.
So it was kind of Counting Crows meets Pearl Jam meets Live.
And I was going to be the keyboard player.
What was the name of the band?
It's called Sunday River.
Just random.
It was like a ski resort in New Hampshire we'd heard of and nobody had even been to.
So I joined this band and I grow my hair.
I just start growing my hair out.
So it hits my shoulders and I become the bands and I self appoint as the band's manager.
And I am going to get us a record deal.
So you're the keyboard guy and the manager manager.
So I'm sending our demo tapes into New York City.
And for some strange reason, people listen to our tapes and say, hey, we'll book you.
So we start playing CBGBs the wetlands.
This is like what mid 80s late 80s.
This would be, let's see, 75, 93.
Okay.
93 to 95.
Yeah.
And we're driving my parents Ford Taurus station wagon.
You know, I'm throwing all the gear, the keyboards and the guitars.
We're driving into New York City.
We're driving into Philly.
We're playing not that interested in going to school.
So I'm a C minus student at best in this new high school.
And I'm not jumping into the drugs that the band was doing.
And I'm not jumping into all the vices yet, but they made it look good and they made it look cool.
So what prevented you from joining them?
I don't know.
I think I was still holding on to, you know, the virtue.
I was still trying to stay pure, I guess you could say.
So what was the, what was the best part for you in that moment prior to going,
you know, further into, you know, drugs or all these other things?
Was it just a sense of like community and tribe with these guys?
Yeah.
And playing music was fun.
I'm playing music in front of, you know, 300, 400 people driving into New York City to the legendary CBGBs where, you know, I don't know, all these great bands had been discovered and been found.
And then talking with A&R people at labels that were interested in being pursued by real managers.
This was a moment in time that felt like we were, we had a shot at getting a record deal and record deals back then they were the thing.
You know, there was Atlantic Records and BMG and Virgin, you know, it was a really exciting possibility.
How close were you to the other guys in the band?
Did they know about your story at home?
They did.
I wasn't that close.
They were in a way they were, they were other.
They were more worldly.
They hadn't been sheltered.
They, you know, had been sleeping around for years.
They'd been smoking and experimenting with drinking and drugs for years.
They were older, maybe two to four years older.
So I was the baby of the band, but it was, it was a sense of community.
It was, it was fun being together, playing music and driving to have these experiences.
It felt dangerous.
It felt edgy.
So I barely graduate high school.
I remember up until the very last day, neither my parents nor I knew whether I would actually have enough attendance credit to
get the high school diploma.
I mean, I was on the brink.
It was one day.
I thought shy of actually passing and I would have to repeat the 12th grade.
And I think I probably, oh, I probably got a doctor or something to lie about, you know, something.
I mean, I managed to pass, but certainly, you know, high school was not a proud achievement.
So when you were a senior, were you applying to college?
I wasn't because I was, I was delighted to announce to my parents that I would not be going to college.
I would not be pursuing further education because I would be getting a record deal.
Peter, that's what, that's what bands do, right?
All bands in New York city.
And we get, I would be getting a multimillion dollar record deal.
I announced to my parents.
So who would need a college education when you had a multimillion dollar record deal and you were touring not just the country, but the world.
And your parents had worked pretty hard to put money aside for you to go to college.
They had.
There was a little over a hundred thousand dollars sitting in an account since birth.
You know, he'd been putting in probably a couple hundred bucks a month or whatever he could.
My dad was very middle class.
They, they didn't spend money on things.
They'd run their cars 15, 20 years and you know, they buy a Toyota Camry and keep it for 20 years.
Would go to, you know, the diner when it was two for one special.
So he was a saver.
I need save for college.
So this was really an affront to them.
And I think what made it even more difficult was that when I was a child, I wanted to be a doctor.
So I was talking about Johns Hopkins medical school.
That was, if you'd asked me probably up until 13, 14, what I was going to do, it was doctor to help sick people like mom.
I was going to be in the med, you know, and I obviously didn't have the grades to do that in high school and took a different path.
So yeah, I moved to New York city by myself.
I'm the only band member that takes the leap, but I said, well, the band's manager, me needs to be in the heart of things.
I moved to an apartment in Greenwich village.
I was paying $650 a month.
It was on Christopher street and seven.
And it wasn't too big.
If I recall, it was, it was, it was hundreds of square feet.
It was tiny.
It was a sixth floor walk up and it just felt amazing.
I mean, I was living in the heart of the West village alone.
Yeah.
It's the dream.
It was the dream.
And I start working at Sam.
So you was at 96 95.
So this would be, were you here for the big snow storm in January of 96?
Do you remember that?
I was.
Yeah, this would have been 94.
So I was 19.
And you know, I, I start working at Sam Ash music cause I wanted some, some pocket money, um, alongside the, the very little money that our bands would, would make gigging.
And you know, I then realized that, so I actually met a manager for our band who says, well, I'm actually a real band manager and I'll take you guys on.
And we, we signed a contract.
And I remember him finding out that my dad had saved for college and he said, well, you're in New York city.
You're crazy to squander that money.
I mean, he's not going to give it to you for anything else.
So why don't you go to NYU part time?
You might as well get a degree and there's Tisch, you know, school of the arts.
I mean, it's, it's, you're in the city.
You might as well, you have the time and he'd been an NYU grad.
So I then call my parents and say, okay, you can start paying NYU.
So I've gotten those scholarship.
I mean, you know, I picked one of the most expensive schools in the country and I do wind up getting a degree again, you know, without any sort of colors.
I mean, see student really just putting in the minimum amount of work to make dad happy.
And what did you study?
Communications.
Cause it was easy.
I could write and communicate.
So the band breaks up.
Which by the way, does come back to serve you well.
There's a lot of, there's a lot of this.
It's so funny.
I mean, I've now gotten several awards from NYU.
They invite me into speak.
I just made a video for the like commencement ceremony.
So now I'm like celebrated by NYU many years later.
And every time they've interviewed me, probably six or seven interviews now, I'm like, okay, so here's what really happened.
Don't ask me this questions.
Cause I can't lie.
Okay.
I can talk about the city being a great campus.
I could talk about, you know, the diversity of New York and the community, but don't ask me what it was like for me.
Cause I would, I was not your good student.
So, okay.
So I'm living in the village.
I'm working at Sam Ash.
The band breaks up months later and there was a lot of drugs and we, we just didn't like each other that much.
I mean, it was, we didn't like each other outside of the time that we were on stage, but I've already made the leap to New York.
I've got this NYU opportunity and I'm making pretty good money selling high-end stereo gear.
I remember one night Stevie Wonder came in and I got to sell him $50,000 of gear and make a commission on that, you know, keyboards and modules and all this stuff.
So I was, I won some favor with my managers that I would get to do a lot of the big clients.
I then almost immediately start dabbling in nightlife.
So you've got all this stuff going on.
I'm at NYU part-time.
I'm working at Sam Ash and then the guy that booked out my band convinces me just by way of watching him that I was always on the wrong side of the equation because our band would turn up.
We'd bring a hundred people to the club paying customers and they might throw us a 20th of that or a 30th of that and say, hey, here's a couple hundred bucks.
Go split it up six ways.
You know, it wasn't even enough to pay for gas or, you know, the guitar strings, but I, I love the idea of the nightclub owner, you know, the person on the other side of the rope deciding who got in and who didn't.
So I, I try my hand at that and I joined this guy and say, you know, he starts throwing me a hundred bucks a week or 200 bucks a week and I'm just his sidekick.
And what's your actual job?
The job is to fill the venue with beautiful paying customers and then you get a cut.
And how do you go about figuring out who's beautiful and paying and get them into said club?
Is it literally going out to a lineup on the street and trying to identify in the line who should jump up?
That's a great problem to have.
Now you got to actually get the line.
You got to get the line.
So that a lot of that is just networking.
It's being out meeting people, getting their phone numbers, you know, later getting their email addresses.
But if you were a club promoter today, starting at zero, you'd have to be out seven nights this week and you'd be striking up conversations.
Hey, how are you?
I'm Pete.
What do you do?
You know, I'm in New York City and I'm living in a couple different places.
Oh, Hey, would you want to want to come to a party sometime?
I've got this amazing fashion party we're going to be doing for Prada during fashion week.
And you'd say, that sounds great.
I'd say, Oh, cool.
I'll, I'll put you on the list or I'll, I'll email.
And you might say, well, I want to actually put together a group of friends.
Great.
I'll sell you a table.
You know, it's going to cost a couple thousand dollars, but I'll give you prime seating in the club.
And I'll leave this amazing DJ flying in from Paris and you know, he'd throw his parties at hotel costs.
Like, you know, you may not have even heard of any of this stuff, but we make it sound so great.
It's a party that you have to be at.
So we're promoting.
We're constantly out there promoting.
And now I have Peter on the list and maybe you come and you bring a few friends.
So what did you do before email was around because this was phone pre-email.
All just dialing.
But then you don't have cell phones.
Like, how are you?
It was home phones.
It was office.
It was voicemail.
It was beepers.
We'd beep people.
They'd call us back.
Email, believe me, the minute that took off, we embrace though right away.
And then we started building, you know, one of the first email lists in clubs and open rates were 100%.
I mean, it was it was extraordinary.
Meaning everybody opened your emails.
Everybody would open an email, even a form email like that.
Or a short.
What would that open rate be?
5%.
1%.
You know, maybe, I don't know.
So imagine the next time, you know, Airbnb or you know, Google sends out an email or app.
Okay, Apple's a perfect example, right?
Apple sends an email new event coming new iPhones, maybe 5% to 8% would actually open it.
Yeah, you're you'll delete it or I'll see it later.
It just sits there.
So back then, you know, imagine Apple send something in every single person is like, oh my gosh, I got an email.
This is so cool.
So we start a list and you know, I just get good at this.
And I leave my partner I go start producing a live RMB open mic night at pretty legendary club called Nells on 14th Street that you know, is in Brett Easton Ellis books and you know, place that Mick Jagger used to always hang out.
So I'm I somehow, you know, this this skinny white kid from Philadelphia, New Jersey winds up helming this really impressive R&B show.
So Stevie Wonder would come and perform.
Chaka Khan would perform.
Prince used to come in and perform for free.
Prince?
Yeah, I used to have some fun Prince stories.
He's to always this was a kind of dark lounge, almost Victoria setting, Victorian era setting.
So they're the old mirrors and the little sconces on the wall, you know, with almost a candle lights.
And whenever Prince came in, I would have to go and unscrew the light bulbs.
He liked to sit in the very specific area, but he wanted it dark.
And you know, then his bouncer would just he would sit alone and then his bouncer would block off.
He would he would sit backwards in a chair and kind of just tell everybody they couldn't see him or couldn't doctor him.
And he would just sit there taking in the music and then sometimes he would actually jump up and perform.
That's so interesting.
So he really was there for the music.
You know, you get the impression a lot of celebrities like they like being there because they want to be the celebrity.
But he was the opposite.
Yeah. And I remember we would say at the time, I don't even know that I was that insightful as you just were.
We're like, why would the guy come to a club if he doesn't want to talk to anyone?
If he doesn't want to be seen and doesn't want to talk to anyone?
Well, of course, it was the music because we had these unbelievably talented keyboard players and drummers.
And a lot of them had gigged with Brian McKnight and Stevie Wonder.
So that's how the people were coming.
You know, if your drummer has a residency at Nels every Tuesday night, your drummer is like, hey, what are you doing on Tuesday?
And you'll come by and you recognize people and you just it's fun to jump up.
So I got to actually play piano for Stevie Wonder on stage a couple of times.
I remember I was playing overjoyed and Stevie wasn't even playing.
He was just standing up singing while I'm playing keyboards.
And it was a it was an amazing experience.
It was called Voices at Nels.
Move from there over into the more fashion model scene of clubs because there's more money to be made there.
We would call it models and bottles.
So this was the advent of bottle service when I guess a few of us promoters and club owners realized that instead of charging people $18 at the bar for a vodka soda, you could take the same $18 price point
and charge them $500 for a bottle of absolute vodka at their table and they wouldn't have to keep going up and getting refills.
And oh, by the way, the $500 bottle of absolute cost you what?
$16.
Yeah, sort of amazing to me when you look at like the high-end clubs like One Oak and things like that, like what you'll pay for a bottle there relative to the wholesale cost.
It's there can't be a bigger margin in any business in the history of civilization.
But it but the value if you actually figured out how many drinks you could get out of a bottle of Stoli, let's say, and then how much you'd have to pay at the bar.
It's it's commensurate because they're charging you 20 bucks for a vodka soda at the bar anyway.
So 30 drinks and you're at a $600 bottle.
Yeah, wouldn't you rather have it at the comfort of your table?
Yeah.
So yeah, the whole thing was just kind of crazy models and bottles.
So the way that the scene worked is we would have to figure out how to get beautiful girls inside the nightclub and then very wealthy guys would pay for the pleasure of sitting around beautiful girls.
So you'd have all your finance guys, you know, the Goldman guys with their Amex black cards and they'd come they'd we'd off them at the door, you know, we'd swipe the card for five or 10 G's and then try and they would buy tables and then we would populate the tables with cool people, you know, often models who would drink for free.
And we party for free.
And I mean, was there any interest in knowing or did it matter if these were professional girls or meaning professional girls, meaning women that were going to basically take, you know, money for sex.
No, no, it wasn't like that.
It actually wasn't like that.
And there was no official kind of process.
It wasn't like that.
No, we would because I feel like today that's sort of pretty normal.
I have a lot of friends who are single and they talk about this.
They're like where people get paid with the women get paid.
Yeah, we never did.
Yeah, the women are paid to be there and you know, it's just understood that like there's a way to plus up on what you're going to pay to go home with her.
Yeah, that's that was foreign to us.
I mean, this is many years ago.
No, we would make friends with the modeling bookers and the heads of the modeling agencies.
We would give them a great experience and then they would come out with the girls.
So a Booker from a modeling agency might take out 12 of his models.
We would make sure they had a great time.
You know, everything was free from the food to the booze.
But now you have 12 beautiful girls in a club.
So it's like their bait to get these guys in who are basically like the sharks, right?
For the they're they're chum for the guys who are sharks.
But a lot of these girls would love to date the Goldman guy living in the 12,000 square foot Soho loft, you know, who might be a gentleman.
Let's go with best case scenario.
Right, right, right.
So you've got the so everybody's potentially winning.
Because this is a matchmaking service basically where you're doing the first layer of screening based on wealth and beauty.
Exactly.
But that's all we did.
So then the rest would just happen.
And if and if you got a guy who was a jerk or was too handsy, you just wouldn't let him in anymore.
So we would be blacklisting the bad actors all the time.
And at the end you wind up with a group of really cool young rich guys who are fun.
The girls love being around them.
They're funny.
They're spending money.
They might be even good looking, you know, I mean, they're they're kind of the life of the party.
And the next thing you know, you know, you're in Saint Bart's with the same people or you're in Milan with the same people or you're in Paris like the party would travel around the world.
So the way we got paid as nightclub promoters, we would just said that the beauty of the business, at least for a while, is that your asset light.
So you just take a cut of the total business of the night.
So it might be 15%, let's say.
Let's say it's 20%.
So you walk into a nightclub and what were the best clubs back in?
So we're now talking kind of late 90s, right?
So I can only speak to my experience.
The first night I went out was at Club USA and there was this famous slide there.
The earliest clubs I worked at, there was the limelight.
I worked for Peter Gation.
There was the tunnel.
There was the Roxy.
There was Twylo.
Lotus was a big club for us.
I was there for many years.
Pangea, Halo.
I mean, you know, some of the names and people will say them and I'm like, oh my gosh, I actually worked there.
So I worked at 40 different venues over this almost 10 year period.
How many of those clubs are still around today?
None.
So what's the half-life of a pot New York club?
Maybe five years.
Now, some of the clubs exist because the liquor license is so valuable, but they'll just get re-skinned or repurposed.
So some of the same liquor licenses are there in the same building, but it's now just a new look, new feel, new name.
And there might have been six of those since I left.
Six change of brand or even ownership.
So that's kind of a blurry time to be quite honest.
Yeah.
So we've gone.
What we've skipped over is band in high school.
You're still not doing drugs.
You're not drinking.
You're not debauching.
By this point as a nightclub promoter, have we slipped into some of that?
For sure.
Smoking was first, then drinking, then lots of sex, then gambling, then Coke started with Coke, then marijuana, the next to see Special K, MDMA, you know, anything short of heroin that we could get our hands on as pure as we could.
Why don't you decide to draw the line of heroin?
We'd seen people OD and die.
You know, that was and I'd seen it firsthand.
My business partner snorted heroin once by mistake and almost died.
You know, emergency room.
He was out cold unconscious on a floor inside, you know, the kitchen of a nightclub.
So I just I'd seen really bad heroin trips.
Coke, you know, I'd never seen anyone die of Coke or die from, you know, ecstasy.
So I pick up all the all the dark habits of, you know, what you might imagine would come with the territory.
I mean, our lifestyle wasn't a picture of health.
We'd go to dinner at 10, you know, so the very late dinner at the trendy restaurant, we'd head over to the club around midnight, 1215.
And do the restaurants comp you guys as well?
Yeah, because we're bringing beautiful people.
So it made the restaurants look like a scene.
And you know, it was the beautiful and they would do this for a few tables.
I mean, it's the eye candy.
Sometimes we'd bring in guys who would who would just sponsor the whole dinner.
It depended on the model.
And the point is you never had to buy a dinner.
I wasn't paid for dinner.
During this period of time, how often were you going home to check on mom and dad for that matter?
Every couple months, every couple months and I would do a quick 48 hour trip and I same as always I'd turn up with my clothes.
I'd walk into the garage.
I would strip down naked.
I'd put on the clothes that they'd left out for me.
There was a period of years where it was medical coats or these gowns that they had gotten from, you know, a hospital that were sanitary and walking around like lab coats, you know, hospital scrubs in the house.
You know, my parents were your parents concerned.
They were.
I mean, I was living out their worst nightmare.
I was the prodigal son that had flipped them and church and you know, all shred of morality virtue, the bird and said going to New York City.
I'm going to make it rich and famous.
Okay.
The band didn't work.
I'm going to be the biggest nightclub promoter in New York City and I'm going to sleep with every hot girl that I can get my hands on.
I'm going to do every good drug.
Get my hands on and I'm going to live it up.
I'm going to party.
I mean, it was so opposite of the, if you think about the basement of the Christian school with nine people and the uniform, right?
This was living.
I'm on I'm out of my own.
I'm flying to Paris for fashion week and dating girls that are walking in the shows.
I'm staying at the nicest hotels, you know, drinking the best wine, going to Paris nightclubs that are, I mean, it was just, it felt amazing.
Were you happy?
I thought I was for a while because I was collecting the markers of happiness.
So, you know, I'll just take most promoters.
You know, one of the first things you need to do is you need to get the top model girlfriend to just have to figure out how to do that.
So, you know, collected that.
So kind of check bark.
Then, you know, I got the car, the BMW and you know, then I got the Rolex and then I got a nice loft and rented a grand piano and the great speaker
system. And so I was kind of, you know, as we would have a little more success, I would buy the things that I thought came with success.
And there was always an emptiness in that.
I think the more it just got really old, the banality of having to do the same thing over and over again.
And I guess what I mean by that is you would change clubs, but there were periods where we would hate emailing and then
getting on the phone because the email was one way to get people to turn up.
But if you called them in a much better shot, right, if I actually say, hey, Peter, you got to come tonight, it's going to be amazing.
We would still have to call hundreds of people to every week to invite them to the parties.
And I remember just hating.
So what was it?
So did you do it was basically seven nights a week?
You're trying to get people to go working three nights a week and then you're out networking the other, you know, three or four.
So you're almost you're out most nights a week, but I would only be doing three parties, maybe a Tuesday night, a Thursday night and then a weekend, a bridge and tunnel kind of Saturday night party, let's say.
And you got to this a moment ago before I interrupted you, but dinner's at 10.
So by the time I'm going to bed, you're having dinner.
Yep.
Then what?
Then the club at 12 15 till three 30 and then maybe home by four and then half the night, you're at after hours.
Well, hey, let's keep going.
Let's go back to somebody's loft with a bunch of coke to stay up because then you need that to you're tired because it's four in the morning and coke's not good for sleeping is my recollection.
Correct.
Not from personal use.
Actually, I've never used coke, but just from the pharmacology of it.
I reckon it probably isn't too good for sleep.
That's right.
So then but if you start doing cocaine or if you were doing it all night, you're amped up so high that at some point you will you have to come down.
So then you might take an ambient.
Yeah, again, so it's not exactly.
Not actually good for sleep, believe it or not, despite the fact that the FDA seems to think so.
Yeah, and you might be trying to go to sleep, you know, on a hard raging night that included after hours or a party at somebody's loft.
You're you're stumbling home and you really are stumbling home because you've been drinking all night and it might be vodka Red Bull.
If you're trying to stay up, it might be coke.
It might be you might be on ecstasy, which would have a, you know, maybe a three to five hour run, maybe even longer and, you know, it's 10 or 11 and you're walking home in broad daylight.
You've been up since, you know, dinner at 10 was your starting point and you're looking at all these healthy people just going about their business and see you're watching their runners at seven in the morning.
Feels disgusting.
Actually, it feels and you know, you're not a doctor or a surgeon on a midnight shift doing noble work.
You know, you've just been trashing your body and the bodies of all those around you.
So it really started to take its toll on me emotionally on me physically.
I write about this actually in the first chapter in the book.
I just go numb half my body.
I lose feeling in it inexplicably and I start seeing neurologists and getting in my eyes and tons of diagnostics and they can't find anything actually wrong with me.
It's sort of interesting to the irony of this after all your mother's gone through and you know, my business partner says, well, why don't you lay off the three packs of cigarettes?
I mean, I was I was such a fiend when it came to smoking.
I had smoked marble Reds to was the baseline.
But if it was a long night, I'd smoke 60 cigarettes in a day.
It's amazing.
I'm even here and I start trying to knock back all this stuff and and then now this leads into really the the epiphany and the change.
So the first thing that happens is I have a physical full-on numbness that is not diagnosed and I remember running my left hand under boiling hot water.
I remember exactly where I was in my loft and I couldn't feel it.
I was terrifying.
Yeah, I thought something was very very wrong with me.
This then leads to a internal to an internal conversation about my mortality and my belief system and the life that I'm living.
So I imagine that I have a brain tumor and you know, or some some horrible disease because why else would have my you know, have my body the parasthesia was it's never good.
You know, if you go online and start looking at you know, half or full body parasthesia like it's bad stuff.
So interesting, you know now with perspective perhaps this was more I don't know spiritual is the right word, but I think there was more going on than just the physicality of you know, maybe the drugs had caught up with me.
I don't know the smoking the drinking around this time couple months later.
I go to point to the Leicester for New Year's Eve and we would always spend about two weeks every New Year's fleeing New York City.
We hated New York around New Year's is just the whole just didn't like the tourist the Times Square the tourists this everything was wrong.
I mean anybody that was fun or interesting got the heck out of town.
They went to the Caribbean.
They went to you know, they would go anywhere warm.
So warm for us was typically in Brazil.
We go to a place called busios.
We'd go to Argentina.
This year we went to Uruguay to put to the Leicester.
We rented this amazing house and remember the house came with servants who would cook and follow after us picking up our towels and my girlfriend came down who I was sure was the most beautiful girl on the compound.
She was on the cover of fashion magazines in Europe at the time and it was 6 1 and Danish just beautiful and I just remember we said all right.
Let's go to the fireworks store.
Let's spend a thousand dollars on fireworks and then we blew them up next to the pool and let's buy all the magnums of Dom Perignon that we can and then there's just champagne flowing and then there was a party that wouldn't end and it started on New Year's Eve 2003 2002.
This is yeah, 2004 January 2004.
So it's the turn between 03 and 04.
We have a New Year's Eve party.
This is be the last day of 2003 and you know, there's a DJ that's come in and it's going to be on our compound.
So we rented the sound system and people from the town people from other houses that we knew we're going to party on our pool and you know, I remember just getting lit that night and taking actually went to sleep for a few hours woke up popped an ecstasy pill, you know, 9 or 10 in the morning and sometime in the afternoon.
I really wanted the party to stop.
I wanted all these people to leave.
It's not a good look when a party goes on for a day.
It's people look pretty ragged including myself and it just you know, I started having these realizations.
This is not how life was to be lived.
This actually wasn't how a beautiful compound like this was supposed to be enjoyed.
I mean we had wrecked the serenity of the place.
You know, the furniture was strewn all over, you know, glass bottles broken by the side of the pool.
I mean, this was just kind of gross and I just started doing some when everybody eventually did leave.
I started doing some soul-searching.
I realized that I you know, I certainly wasn't in love with my girlfriend and I don't think she was in love with me.
This was almost a relationship of convenience.
You know, I started reading a deep theological book called The Pursuit of God that my father had given me at Christmas
and you know, my parents for 10 years had been trying to get me back in church, get me back on the right track, preaching at me,
sending me different translations of the Bible.
I mean, this was all just falling on deaf ears, but there was something about this moment, the paresthesia,
that just really caused me to take stock of my life both spiritually and morally.
And just begin to kind of say, where am I?
And what have I done in a way?
And I realized that there would never be enough.
As I looked around, the interesting thing was almost everybody at the compound was richer.
They were older.
They had the plane.
They, you know, had the better car.
They had more money and they weren't that happy either, Peter.
I mean, this was, there was so much brokenness.
There was so much wreckage.
I mean, many of our top bottle buyers, the guys who would spend 10 or $15,000 paying for the booze,
you know, they'd run off on their wife.
Sometimes their kids didn't talk to them because they were dating models younger than their kids.
And there was a lot of brokenness.
So this week for me, I remember just having a change of heart saying, I'm not on the right path
and I want to find my way back to the spirituality, the virtue, kind of my heritage, you know, the moral foundation of the way that I grew up.
This isn't working anymore.
This sucks.
This feeling sucks.
I feel dirty.
I feel degenerate.
I feel like a hedonist and something needs to change.
Did you think of that in sort of a moral way or did you think of that more in just an absolute way?
I don't even know if that's the right way to describe it, but because, you know, I think you could objectively say all those things without applying a moral judgment too, right?
Yeah.
I mean, I think it was through a spiritual lens.
You know, I was trying to find my way back to God or what I believed that meant for me.
And that was virtue.
That was purity.
That was blessed are the peacemakers, you know, blessed are those who look after the poor and who give of themselves in the service of others.
You know, loving your neighbor.
I mean, I wasn't doing any of this stuff.
So that was that was the sacred text that I had been brought up with.
And I think I started to wish is really the way a lot of, you know, a lot of religion has lost that.
And a lot of religion has, you know, we don't want to go down that rabbit hole because we could spend another four hours on that.
But, you know, the virtues you mentioned are sort of the virtues that I think people would uniformly agree are wonderful with or without religion.
Right.
Yeah.
And, you know, we were talking about this.
I mean, I guess as a 28 year old adult at the end of myself, I came to see Jesus very differently, actually, as someone who was challenging the establishment, who was fighting against the religiosity and the oppression of the leaders of the church in quotes, I guess, at the time, and preaching a very different message of purity, of service to the poor, of absolute love.
I mean, I remember he called basically all the church leaders the worst names that you could ever call anybody at that time.
So I just I rediscover kind of my faith or softly.
Now, this is still so you get back to New York in January.
Still partying at the clubs.
Yeah. So, yeah. So that's what I was going to ask.
So you come back to New York, you're you're back to day job.
But I really have a heart change.
So I start trying to go to church again and I start trying to do less of it all.
So I quit Coke for a while, for example, and I'm trying to cut down to one pack a day.
And then there's times where I just OK, I'm going to quit smoking.
And I go into the nikoret and the patch.
And so there's a my heart has really changed.
The intention has changed.
I know that I'm going to have to break up with my girlfriend and have the heart.
Like there's who were you able to talk with about this?
This is a huge internal struggle.
No one.
I didn't have a best friend.
I was just about to say, you don't sound like you have real friends.
No.
You have a lot of acquaintances, but they're not they're not part of your soul right in the way that a great friend would be.
And I wasn't going to give my parents the satisfaction of letting them know that I might be turning back around.
Change of heart.
Or, you know, God forbid that I read dad's book on theology that he sent me.
I mean, that would just be I had too much ego at the time.
So this is a really solitary experience.
I'm going, you know, at 10 o'clock on a Sunday morning and sitting at the very back pew of a church on my own, not telling anyone that I went to church.
I'm wrestling with all these demons myself.
What's interesting is coming back from that trip, even your girlfriend doesn't realize what you're going through.
We had a really shallow relationship.
We didn't talk about things.
We didn't talk about hopes and dreams or or suffering.
So around this time, I remember it was interesting coming back a couple months later, the incidents of numbness, they just stop.
They stopped as quickly as they started.
And that was great.
I didn't have anything to directly correlate them to.
I mean, I had ratcheted back all the partying, but I was still drinking and, you know, still smoking just less of everything.
So, you know, I remember throughout this whole period of time, you know, I was clearly I mean, I was praying.
So I was like, God, I need to get out of nightlife.
This sucks. You know, it's not it's not for me anymore.
And, you know, I remember just hating the fact I remember feeling like I couldn't my day job kept me in the way of the life that I wanted to build for myself.
So it'd almost be like if you wanted to stop gambling, you probably need to stop working in a casino.
But you probably can't be a blackjack dealer if you're also a degenerate gambler.
Even though you could do your job, right?
And you're around gambling all day and maybe you don't go to the sports book that night.
But it's just like the environment was was still so unhealthy if you're struggling with that.
So that's how it felt for me.
And, you know, I remember there was just like this cry for help.
And the only person was to God, like, God, get me out of this.
Show me what I'm supposed to do.
Show me how I'm supposed to to live differently.
There's a scene I read about in length of the book, but something happened one night at a club and it involved a gun and involved a bouncer and a threat.
And I have this, you know, really clear opportunity to take a couple weeks off.
And I remember renting a cobalt blue Ford Mustang telling my business partner, look, I'm out of here for a couple weeks.
You handle the clubs.
And I remember riding north like that's where I was going.
He's like, where are you going?
I'm like north. I mean, maybe I wind up in Canada, you know, in Montreal or Toronto.
I grab on that trip.
I pack my, you know, iPod.
I bring a bottle of Dewar's and I bring a Bible.
And in some ways, you know, there's just I was kind of wrestling like with the faith and virtue piece, but I'm still drinking and smoking.
And I start just driving north.
I wind up in Vermont and New Hampshire.
I eventually wind up on Maine and I'm having this conversation with myself.
Again, there's just me.
And I'm saying, what would it look like never to go back?
What might the opposite of my life look like?
What's the clean break look like?
Like, what could I do?
And it almost like hit me.
The opposite of your life would be to walk away from all of these vices and go serve others instead of yourself.
Go serve the poor, you know, which is something that I'd never even, it never even conceived of before.
I hadn't given a single gift to a charity.
I wasn't a giver.
I wasn't throwing parties for charities.
Something compels me from an Internet cafe on Greenville, Greenville, Maine on Moosehead Lake.
It was a dial up Internet cafe.
I remember there were a bunch of gray Dell computers there.
And I start filling out applications to volunteer at all the humanitarian organizations I'd heard of.
And I just, you know, there are 10 page applications and I'm willing to consider going anywhere, doing anything.
To completely change my life.
So it's UNICEF.
It's the Peace Corps.
It's World Vision.
It's anybody I'd heard of.
And I go from there back to my parents to tell them that I'm going to do a year of humanitarian service.
And there's a kind of biblical concept that I've been brought up with of a tithe where, you know,
my parents had always given 10% of their money to the church and to charity growing up.
And for me, I saw this almost as a time tithe.
Like I'd spend 10 years living for myself.
What does it look like to give one back and completely give it to others?
So to donate 10% back.
So I go to my parents and I tell them this.
And then there's this place in one of my first club partners was a British guy that had a very popular band in the 80s.
And he took all the money that he made.
They were called Transvision Vamp.
And he bought this beautiful Maison Forestier, a house in the Pyrenees Mountains of France in a little village, maybe of 60 people.
And I had been there over the club years, maybe 15 times.
I'd taken girlfriends there.
It was just like my happy place.
And I knew where the key was.
You know, I wouldn't even need him to be there.
I knew how to open up the house and lock the house and deal with all the water and the electricity and all that stuff.
So I asked him around this time, hey, can I just go hang out in France while I'm waiting for the year?
And he said, of course, you know, you know where the key is, which was in this little rusty saucepan in and out building.
So I go to this town.
It's called Lapar del Puy Laurent.
It's near Jinkla.
And I'm alone again.
And the rejection letters start coming in.
So maybe this isn't a surprise, but no one will take me.
Actually, it is a surprise to me.
I mean, I can't imagine that.
Are there that many people that are lining up to offer a year of their life free of service?
I think the resume scared him, Peter.
I mean, what had I done for the last 10 years?
I'd gotten people drunk.
So basically they're worried that, one, this is not real.
And two, you're going to show up in two weeks leave and you're going to have taken a spot from somebody who could have stuck it out.
Sure.
Like who wants a party boy on their mission?
You know, I wasn't a serious person.
Serious people don't promote nightclubs for 10 years.
Do they?
Right?
I mean, if you're the person reviewing the application at HQ.
So nobody has a spot for me or anything good to do.
And, you know, never forget.
I actually didn't have, I didn't write about this in the book, but I'll never forget this one moment where there's no cell phone reception in this village.
And I was riding my bike maybe 10 miles down the mountain from where the, this little house was.
And I'm going through the main town and my Nokia phone rings, which kind of dates this.
And I pick it up.
The brick?
It was like the little one.
Yeah.
The junior brick.
Junior brick, little LCD screen on the top, little square.
Oh, I love that phone.
They were kind of contoured.
Yeah.
Indestructible.
I mean, the QWERTY.
Just great folks.
So I specifically remember this thing was in my pocket and I almost felt like I was going to be in a little bit of a situation.
I specifically remember this thing was in my pocket and I almost fell off my bike because I know he had called me and oh my gosh, my phone is ringing.
And it was one of the organizations called Mercy Ships.
And they said, hey, we've got your application here.
And I'd applied to be their photojournalist.
And this is kind of wonderful how this does come full circle because I dust off for this one.
I dust off my NYU degree and I'm like, I have a communications degree from New York University and let me come on your ship.
I will write stories about the amazing work that you're doing with a hospital ship and I'll take really good pictures.
So I put up pictures on my blog of like my girlfriends over the years and beautiful buildings and in Prague, like my Labrador Retriever.
And, you know, they're like decent photos.
You know, my travels around the world.
So they call me on the phone and I'm in this village and they say, well, we're a little worried you might not be a culture fit for us, but we've agreed to meet you.
And I said, where are you guys?
And they said, well, the ship is in Germany.
I'm like, well, I'm in France.
I'll see you tomorrow or the next day.
The ship was in Bremerhaven.
Quite a while.
It took me two days to get there on the train.
But I said, I mean, this is amazing.
So I take the train all the way up.
And I remember walking aboard this five hundred and twenty two foot hospital ship, this huge hulking white ocean liner that had been converted, gutted effectively and turned into a state of the art hospital.
And I have a meeting with what would be my future bosses and I convince them that I'm in this for all the wrong reasons.
I believe I'm talented.
I believe I can do this job.
I am not going to throw wild raves and corrupt the rest of the humanitarian staff.
Like I'm I'm in this.
I've had the life change.
I've always been pretty good at getting people to like me.
That's it. That's a skill in nightlife.
You know, if you're building a list, I was a good host.
I was I was always trying to make people feel comfortable inside the club.
And who do you want to meet, Peter?
Oh, no problem.
Come with me.
You know, hey, is everything OK?
Is your drink OK?
You know, I would know people's names.
I was so I was turning on all the charm.
Basically what I'm saying.
So I'm up in Bremerhaven on the ship saying, I will be your best photojournalist that you've ever had.
Oh, and by the way, guys, I also come with a built in list.
I've got fifteen thousand emails.
You know, I have a list of fifteen thousand people.
I have been getting drunk for ten years.
Fifteen thousand wealthy.
Some of them were influential.
I mean, Mick Jagger was on the list.
President of Chanel, right, or people in fashion and publishing and entertainment.
So they say, OK, they say, we'll take you.
And I said, when does the mission start?
Three weeks.
You report for duty.
So I go back.
I remember going to the decathlon in France and buying flashlights and, you know, whatever
I thought I would need for Africa because we were sailing into a country called Benin.
And then shortly we'd be going to Liberia, which was a country I'd never heard of.
Actually, I'd never heard of either of these countries, if I'm honest.
But I'd learned that Liberia had just finished a brutal civil war that had lasted fourteen
years and was led by the evil, evil dictator and warlord Charles Taylor, who had used children
for a decade and a half to slaughter an extraordinary amount of people.
So I report for duty actually on the island of Tenerife.
So the ship was going from Germany to pick up people in Tenerife, an island off the coast
of Africa, and then we would sail into West Africa.
So I joined the ship a couple of weeks later in Tenerife.
I get there first.
I know that the ship is sailing in the next morning and I'm going to walk up the gangway.
I'm going to surrender my passport and I'm going to officially join this mission.
I mean, I'm going to have a boss.
I'm going to effectively lose my independence because I've been self-employed for this
time, I guess outside of the music store ten years previous.
And, you know, I just was thinking about the ship and this idea of sailing, I guess it
was five days to Africa, sailing away to a new continent that I'd never been on and sailing
away into a new life.
And I realized that the best way to do that would be to go all in and just try and quit
everything in one go, to figure out how to quit gambling.
Well, I mean, I imagine you didn't have a choice.
You weren't going to be able to gamble, drink and smoke on it.
I could smoke and drink.
You know, I probably wasn't going to get illicit drugs.
Well, I mean, I could always gamble online, which I used to do.
I mean, I used to gamble on women's soccer games in Czechoslovakia that I couldn't even
see televised just because I needed the rush of winning or losing.
So I have this moment.
I was staying at the Sheraton in, I think it was Santa Cruz, the town of Tenerife,
and the night before, and I just sat in my hotel room alone and I drank seven or eight
beers, Amstel Lights, smoked well over two packs of Marlboro Reds.
And I'm like, this is it.
I'm just going to go out with a bang.
And I woke up the next day with a brutal hangover and I walked up the gangway of the ship.
And it's funny in doing some of the interviews for the book, people actually remember me
freaking of alcohol.
Like, did this guy just come from a bar at 7.30 a.m.?
And I actually didn't have the awareness of that.
It was just so funny, you know, I'm sure they were saying, did we make a mistake?
And that was it.
Like, there was something about, you know, the gangway was going to come up and I was
going to leave all of this stuff on land and sail away from it.
And it was a clean break.
So from that moment, this is now 14 years ago.
I've never had another cigarette.
I've never touched Coke or any of that stuff.
I've never gambled again.
I haven't looked in a pornographic image in 15 years.
Like, I walked so far away from my former life.
I drink a little bit.
I like craft IPAs and, you know, red wine.
What was the withdrawal like from the nicotine in particular?
So hard.
And I had failed attempts at smoking.
I mean, there was, there was, I think, a certain grace of being around medical professionals,
which probably made it feel like the new norm was not smoking.
The new norm was being healthy and helping people.
I used a bunch of the gum at the time and I think I used the patch.
But I just did it.
And there were, by the way, there were the engineers that would smoke.
Yeah, I was going to say, I'm guessing there were, you could have got a cigarette.
Sure, sure, sure.
There was still a ship subculture of the people that worked in the engine room and they'd
all be, you know, having a cigarette on the deck or there were authorized smoking places
for them.
But that was it for me.
And that allowed me to, it really felt like a do over.
It felt like 28 years, you know, I could close that book.
And I was starting on page one of a new blank book.
And I got to really create a completely new life and a new story for myself as a humanitarian,
of all things.
So what was that?
What was that you're like?
I mean, in terms of, did you develop relationships or friendships that where you could start
to share the stuff that had been previously just completely an internal monologue?
Yeah, it was an amazing place, Peter.
And someone asked me recently during an interview, they said, look, so many people, you know,
struggle with these addictions and they can't get out of it.
What do you think it was that allowed you to walk so cleanly?
I think the environment had a lot to do with it.
I went from an environment where all that was the norm to an environment of like Christian
doctors, you know, who were helping people get well, the best surgeons and nurses in
the world that had given up their vacation time to use their skills in the service of
others.
So that really helps.
And I love the new norm.
Like I embraced the new norm.
The new norm was healthy.
It was up early.
It was saving people's lives.
I mean, it was in the most profound and visually evident way possible.
So we specialized in max low facial surgery.
So these doctors would look for people with tumors, with cleft lips, with cleft palates.
We did a lot of cataracts and people who were completely blind and, you know, we could remove
the cataracts and put it in the lenses.
You had an OR on the actual ship.
42 beds.
Yep.
Wow.
There were three or four operating theaters.
I remember when we sailed into Liberia, it was the only, we had the only CT scan in four
neighboring countries.
The only working CT scanner.
What an amazing organization.
So you had these and even better, the quality of the medical staff was so extraordinary
because you'd have these doctors flying in from London or Berlin or New York or Los Angeles
who would do, I don't know, three weeks, often three months.
And they would just say, I can do this.
You know, I could go to the Maldives and stay at the Four Seasons, or I could fly to Liberia
and I could operate on 46 cleft patients and give 46 people their lives back.
So it was, and my job, the amazing thing is that I have the best job on a ship of 350
volunteers.
I would say my job is better than the chief medical officer or the surgeons because I
get to document all of the life-saving wonder that is happening.
It is my job to photograph every single person that goes through the operating theater and
document that transformation.
So the way that we would find patients was in some ways not unlike how some club promoters
would fill clubs.
We flier the country.
We made thousands of flyers.
The flyers had the pictures of the facial tumors, the cleft lips, a lot of the burn reconstructions
that we were doing and seeing after the war.
Stuff like flesh-eating disease, canker morris, no, no, these really horrible diseases, which
I later learned some of them were caused by water.
And it was like a casting call.
We'd say, if you look like one of the people in these pictures or if you know someone with
these afflictions, turn up on this day and our doctors will see you and we'll triage
you.
So the profound moment for me was my third, and this happens quickly.
So we sail in to port, I've been in, patient screening.
The triage day is three days later.
So everybody's prepping and I learned that the government has given us a football stadium,
the soccer arena in the center of the city.
And it was called Les Aldes Arts.
And I know also that we have 1500 surgery slots to fill.
So in a best case scenario, we are going to hand out 1500, hey, come on this day at this
time and we'll run 1500 people through our surgery hospital over four months.
And then we'll pick up and we'll sail to Liberia where we'll spend eight months in Liberia.
So actually we'll spend a year.
Third day there, I remembered very vividly.
It was five in the morning.
I couldn't sleep the night before.
I was so excited to see who's going to turn up.
I mean, is it possible that there's 1500 people in this country with these radical, crazy
afflictions and conditions?
And I grabbed my two Nikon cameras, my wide angle lens, my portrait lens, all my batteries.
And I put on hospital scrubs and I jump in this convoy of Land Rovers, maybe 20 Land
Rovers, all heading towards the stadium.
And as we turn the corner to actually see the stadium, I see the parking lot and there's
5,000 people waiting to get in.
In the early morning, 5,000 people have gathered in this mass.
And it just hits me, look, we're going to turn thousands of people away.
The need is so much greater than our response.
We don't have enough doctors.
We don't have enough money.
Are there local doctors there that could be trained?
They are.
And that's something that the organization has done, but there aren't the medical facilities
of the quant.
So I'll give you an example in Liberia.
Liberia has one doctor for every 50,000 of its citizens at the time.
I believe our number here is one for 300.
So for every 300 Americans, there's a doctor.
For every 50,000 Liberians, there were two surgeons that we'd heard of in a country of
a few million people, but nowhere to operate.
So the surgeon, you know, even if you were a surgeon, like you'd have to operate out
in the bush, there was no working medical facility or operating theater.
So we had the best hospital going, you know, on our ship.
So just, that was a really, really hard moment for me throughout that first triage day.
I felt like I wept 40% of the day because the stuff that I saw, I just wasn't prepared
for kids choking to death on four pound, benign, fleshy tumors.
People with their faces completely rotting from disease.
People who had been burned so badly by rebel soldiers often who had poured, you know, oil
over their bodies or the bodies of their children.
It was, I was in no way prepared to see it, like to smell rotting flesh and have to take
a photo of someone six inches from their face.
I mean, it felt like I was violating them, but these were the medical photos.
These were the befores that hopefully would have amazing after story.
So my first friend who I write about in the book was a little boy named Alfred and he
was joking to death on his face with an amelio blastoma, big fleshy pink tumor that had just
grown and grown and grown and grown over four years.
And his mom had actually taken him to witch doctors and they had cut him with knives and
with sharp stones.
They'd put pastes and concoctions on the tumor.
They had chanted to, you know, spirits and the tumor just keeps growing.
That's what tumors do.
How did you guys triage was the, if you only had 1500 slots for 5,000 people, was it based
on medical need?
Nurses were just rolling through the line.
I will say some people came with conditions that we couldn't treat.
Some people just came to see a doctor.
They heard the doctors were coming.
Some people came with broken feet.
Some people came with terrible cancer that had metastasized all throughout their body.
And we weren't able to help.
There was a, I remember there were some boys that came with Burkett's lymphoma.
We didn't have a good way to treat.
You can't operate.
You need medical treatment.
We weren't in the business of chemotherapy.
We were in the business of operating on the benign stuff.
So poor Alfred is just this terrified little boy and I just determined that he's going
to be my first friend and I'm going to see his story all the way through.
And he's going to be the first story that I share with the 15,000 people from my former
life of what we're really doing here.
So thankfully for me, he was, I think he was first in line that day and he gets a surgery
date three days later.
So we just get to work, triage two days and then the next day surgery starts and people
start turning up and the operating theaters are just scheduled out.
And then the recovery ward had 42 beds.
This is a proper hospital.
So I'm there as Alfred walks up on the ship, his father, Besson brings him and I'm documenting
his surgery.
So I'm in the operating theater all the time.
I just love, I love the blood.
I loved like just the visceral like change, seeing someone, seeing a surgeon open up someone's
face and then fix it and then put it back together.
I just, it was the most fascinating thing.
So I probably documented 50 surgeries in scrubs with my cameras right there.
They would allow me to get sterile and then just be there documenting it.
So Alfred's was my first and they just take this giant tumor and they cut it out and they
put in a titanium plate cause his jaw had been completely moved, blown out really by
the tumor.
And a couple of weeks later I got to take him home to his village and I'm falling behind
him with my camera and he's in his best clothes and I'm watching the village surround this
little boy that they thought was cursed, that they thought was written off for, for
dead and they're looking at him and they're touching his face and you know, he's, he's
like a celebrity in the village.
And that was my first kind of all the way through, oh wow, we're going to be able to
do that 1500 times.
We're gonna, we're gonna so transform people's lives.
When you write a book after two years, you see some of these little parallels, you know,
as radical as my life change was, you know, from the dirty degenerate, you know, drug
addict to, you know, now this like humanitarian photographer trying to tell stories of these
incredible doctors and patients.
You know, we were, I remember a woman soon after named Marguerite and she had gone blind
in her twenties so she, she could see her whole life and then exposure to the equatorial
sun with no UV.
She had these huge cataracts.
I mean, you could see them.
They were giant opaque white cataracts.
And so she'd gone completely blind.
She couldn't see her family, couldn't see her kids.
So I remember being in the operating theater as this, one of the surgeons, a guy named
Glenn Price makes a little slit from what I remember.
He like just sticks tweezers in and he pulls out the cataract and then he pops in the new
lens.
The thing took like 15 minutes, right?
I remember thinking I could totally do that.
Like you could train me to be a cataract surgeon right now.
I mean, it just seems so simple, you know, scalpel, make the slit, pop it out, pop it
in and then put a bandage on.
And there's probably some surgeons now that are like, if there's way more to it than that.
But it felt so simple as a, as a documentarian.
Did this sort of rekindle that thing that you had when you were 13 and you wanted to
go to Johns Hopkins and you wanted to become a doctor, did you now find yourself saying,
wait a minute, I'm definitely, I don't want to go back to being a club promoter.
I want to be a doctor.
Well, I almost got to be a doctor.
I was living vicariously through all the doctors all the time.
You know, in a way I felt like I was a part of all these patient stories and the doctors
would come and go.
And I was the constant.
This one woman made such an impression on me because I think it was actually, it might
have been two days later, we were going to remove the bandages and you know, there's
a little bit of healing that took place.
So I just, I saw the moment that I wanted to capture because I'd met her blind, I'd
interviewed her, I'd seen the surgery and documented that.
So I go down there when they start taking off the bandages and I'm just snapping stills
like click, click, click, click, click, click, click.
And she starts screaming.
Just the flash.
She tackles me, dancing, screaming, you know, glory, glory, like tackles her sister that
she can now see.
And it was just this euphoric moment.
I mean, there's, you know, going from being blind to being able to see.
It's hard to imagine.
I can't imagine what that would be like.
Like I can still, I can put myself in that tiny little room where it all happens.
And I think, Peter, I wanted to share these stories with people in the same way that,
you know, there was a period of time where I wanted to share a story that if you got
past my velvet rope and spent thousands of dollars on booze and you were seen with the
beautiful people or maybe you went home with the right beautiful people, then your life
had meaning.
This was real meaning.
I mean, this was life transformation.
This was real sacrifice and generosity by these doctors, by the donors that were paying for
these surgeries.
And I think I wanted to, I just wanted to share every story.
So I just start blasting my club list with Alfred's story, with Marguerite's story, with
the picture of the five or the 3000 people that we turned away when we closed the doors
of the stadium and the triage was finished.
And these people who are getting these emails, they don't know what's happened.
The last thing they remember is Scott was our hookup and then Scott kind of vanished
because I don't imagine you sent a retirement letter.
I actually did.
I sent a, I did send a retirement letter.
I went back and saw it recently.
It was, you know, it was a little high and mighty.
Like I'm leaving nightclubs behind to go explore a humanitarian journey.
You know, I mean, definitely some eye rolling now, looking back on an email, but I did announce
what I was doing and I said, you know, you are all going to come along for the ride.
I mean, I, I teased that you're going to come on the journey with me and what I see, you're
going to see.
So what they started seeing was giant fleshy tumors and some, you know, leprosy and just
some crazy stuff.
And you know, of course there's a few unsubscribes and people said, take me off this list.
I enjoyed the Prada party that you threw once, but I'm not down with the tumor party
or like don't need to see someone's face eaten by leprosy.
But the response that I got from most people was this is amazing.
I didn't know that this ship existed.
I didn't know that there were doctors who cared so much that they would, they would
even do this.
How do I get on the ship?
How do I give money?
How much did the surgery cost?
Oh, about $400.
How do I send in $400?
Well, here's how you do that.
So I remember this one woman writes me and she says, it's the middle of the day.
I'm sitting here at Chanel headquarters.
I'm in a brightly lit office and tears are streaming down my face.
I can't believe what I've just seen and what I've read.
I need to do something.
I need to be a part of this.
And so I have this immediate feedback loop that my stories are moving people.
The photos, the images are moving people.
I think what I learned there that it wasn't just the writing.
It was actually the images I saw.
I came across a quote this week that I love so much that I have never, I'd never heard
of before until this week, but it's from Carl Jung and it says transformation can only take
place in the presence of images.
And I think there was something so arresting or disrupting about these photos, you know,
just the extremity of a huge tumor.
And then the tumor is gone of cataracts, like saucers that you can see.
And then gone that really worked along with the stories that I was writing.
If I just said, Hey, Alfred's this 14 year old boy and he's been suffocating on his face
with a big pink fleshy tumor.
There's one way to do it.
But when you see it, when people saw it, it really, it moved them.
So I do this for a year and I'm just telling story after story.
My list actually starts to grow a little bit.
The other thing I forgot to mention is that I had to pay $500 every month to volunteer.
So this was, you talk about the, if the dream or the prayer was to create the opposite of
my life, I actually wound up in the poorest country in the world paying money to volunteer.
And this was how Mercy Ships helped support the organization.
They got all the crew to raise their own support for room and board and, you know, for food.
And that was a big income stream for them.
So I'm basically going broke on the ship.
Not only am I not earning an income, it costs me money to be there.
And you're learning back to a point we had earlier, you're learning about what a really
efficient nonprofit can do.
Sort of pieces.
Both on the positive and the negative side.
Sure.
I'm getting an inside look at a nonprofit and for sure the medical work was amazing
and transformative.
But I also got to look at a little bureaucracy.
How a big charity might work in some of the blockers.
And one of the amazing things for me was that my boss on the ship, he didn't know how to
handle me.
He didn't know how to handle this New York City crazy guns blazing 80 hour a week worker.
So he just gave me an incredible amount of rope.
I mean, I took over a photo office and I made that my own.
And I was really like this lone ranger.
He would initially assign me to take the photos and then someone else to write the
story.
I'm like, no, I'm doing it all myself.
I have to be a one stop shop.
And I think, gosh, that drove me.
I think he just knew that I needed some element of autonomy to feel like I could own the whole
experience and I worked around the clock.
I mean, there was nothing else.
There was no dating.
There was no, it was just all work.
When did the pangs start to go away?
I'm sure at some point initially when you got on that ship, you were still missing the
sex, the girlfriend, the booze, the drugs, the cigarettes.
I mean, was there a day when you sort of woke up and realized like, actually, I'm happier
now than I was back then.
It felt almost instant.
Wow.
Because I was so busy in a different direction.
Every single intention, every single task, every, you know, everything I was reading,
it was the whole community, everything changed.
You know, it's like I went from being on the Death Star to, I don't know, being around
the people of light.
Well, it's a very good point you brought up earlier.
I used to have a slightly different way of explaining that to patients.
When I was at Hopkins, we would see a lot of folks in the ER who were using IV drugs.
So heroin was a pretty rampant in Baltimore at the time.
It might still be actually.
Whenever we'd get a patient in there, usually it was to debride an abscess or something
like that, you sort of had to explain to them, look, you don't get an infinite number of
shots on goal here.
This is going to kill you really soon.
You're going to get endocarditis.
You're going to get an infection that's not going to be, it's going to kill you before
we get to it.
You can't just go back to where you came from.
To kick a heroin habit, you need a new life.
You need a new group of friends.
You need a new place to live.
It's a year later, do you come back to New York?
I do come back to New York.
That was probably the hardest part because then all the temptations are there.
The old girlfriend was still around and hadn't moved on yet.
The party was still there.
I would say, look, I felt during ... When I come back, I put on an exhibition of my
photos in order to raise money for Mercy Ships.
I get a calendar.
You're gainfully unemployed at this point.
You're in the crowd.
I'm crashing with my old club partner and kindness of strangers really at this point.
Because nightclub promoters, okay, I can only speak for myself.
I was not good at saving money.
I was fantastic at spending a little more than I made every single year.
I came back broke.
I'd been giving all my money to Mercy Ships, the people that I met along the way.
Many of these patients I'd wind up supporting afterwards.
I mean, Alfred, I'm actually still supporting 15 years later because I've helped him become
a plumber and it's been a joy to be able to do.
I was definitely broke.
I come back and I said, well, what can I do that would be useful?
I could bring people into the story in a space.
We got a gallery donated in Chelsea.
It was a milky white gallery, so it felt like a hospital.
I hung up these sheets and created different rooms, almost like operating theaters or the
ward.
Then I put 100, I think it was 108 images together, creating light boxes and TV installations
of patients morphing back and forth.
At the end of the gallery show, I asked people to donate the cost of one surgery, if they
could.
It was 380 bucks or whatever they could.
My goal was to raise as much money for Mercy Ships as possible and then go back and follow
the money.
I actually come back to New York on a mission, which is great.
The mission is continuing.
It's just the venue has changed.
The context has changed.
I remember my friends thought that I wasn't as much fun.
I'm not doing coke with them.
I'm not staying out late, but I still was in the clubs trying to raise money and trying
to get people to donate catering for the exhibition or donate printing.
I'm still working the network.
I guess I just felt like, look, there are going to be all these opportunities for me
to slip back into my former life, especially now.
There would be grace for that.
What if I didn't?
In some ways, the analogy of...
I personally love this parable, the prodigal son from the New Testament, where the son
basically flips everybody off, takes his inheritance, goes very, very far away and winds up gambling,
drinking, sleeping with prostitutes.
He winds up in a bad place at the end of himself.
He says, I want to come home.
He says, actually, that the servants in my father's house are living a better life than
I am now.
He comes home.
What I love about that is the father in the story sees his son across a distance and runs
out towards the son.
In that culture, a man would actually never run and reveal his ankles in that way.
It shows the passion.
He throws his arms around his son.
There's no admonishment.
Imagine the lecture that's been 10 years in the making.
Prostitutes, really?
Drugs?
Three packs of cigarettes?
There was no lecture.
He puts on a robe.
I love that detail in the story.
He gives his son one of the finest robes in the house, and then he throws him a party.
I love that.
He says, my son is home.
My son who was lost has been found.
Let's throw a party.
I love the idea of the change of clothes.
You got a sense of this kid who had just soiled his clothes far away, like with the pigs.
In some ways, I felt like I had changed my clothes.
I almost had on like, imagine if the robe was white.
I didn't want to get it dirty.
I could get it dirty.
I could stain it.
Then, I'd go to the dry cleaners.
Maybe I couldn't get it all the way clean.
I had gotten a new set of clothes, and why not keep them clean?
I just kept coming back to that idea that what if I did keep them clean?
How would the story continue to play out?
What if I didn't get back in a relationship and start sleeping with my old girlfriend?
What if I just stayed completely pure or clean?
I was actually able to do that.
How did you decide to start your own charity, which is really the cherry on this story,
which is it's one thing to realize that you can do amazing work for an organization that's
already up and running.
It's quite another thing to say, I'm actually going to take all that I've learned and create
an organization to affect change.
Sure.
The next part of the story goes, I learned something because my exhibition is effective,
and I raised about $100,000 for Mercy Ships.
Wow.
I tap into all my old relationships.
PR companies are donating.
Jeffrey Chowderal is donating the food.
I just went Prada and Gucci are donating handbags that we auctioned off.
We raise $100,000 through the gallery and through an event for the closing night.
All that money goes to Mercy Ships.
I then go back and follow the money.
What I realized was that a lot of my friends were really skeptical when it came to charities.
I could be this guide.
They had trusted me, certainly not before, but through all of the communications and
the photos and the stories, I was so prolific over that year.
You felt like you were living in my head.
If you were reading it and you were taking it in.
I wrote, oh, maybe 50,000 words.
I was just churning out content, like meet the patient of the day.
She's amazing.
I can tell you her story.
I'd be going into these villages and staying overnight and documenting video snippets of
the welcomeings.
I think a lot of people felt like they were really along the journey.
I raised the money.
I'm like, okay, wow, I can actually raise money for the cause, not just be a passive
documentarian.
It's a very strange thing.
Most photojournalists would only ... They would never get involved.
You're just telling the story.
I'm like, I'm going to get involved.
I'm going to take pictures and I'm going to use those photos to raise money to affect
change.
I realized that I have a gift for that.
Then I go back for another eight months to Liberia.
This is year number two.
Still volunteering.
We're now until like middle to late 05.
Yep, exactly.
I come across the water crisis.
Which you alluded to a little earlier.
Some of the diseases.
This time I got off the ship.
Back in Liberia, most of my time had been ... The first time had been spent in Monrovia
on the ward.
Now I said, I want to understand a little more of the context of this country.
I bought a motorcycle from a deckhand and that bought me some autonomy and some freedom.
Again, my boss was great.
He would let me stay in the bush.
Overnight I would have to sign permission slips.
I started exploring the country.
Going up to the Guinea border and the Sierra Leone border, the more time I spend in these
villages I see the water that people are drinking.
It just never occurred to me that people would drink out of swamps or brown, viscous,
muddy rivers.
I learned that 50% of the people living in Liberia didn't have clean water to drink.
Half the country was drinking contaminated, filthy water.
I started taking pictures of it.
Children drinking from swamps with algae and bugs.
You could actually see fish and worms in some of these swamps.
Little kids are just drinking straight from them.
My mentor on the ship was a guy named Dr. Gary Parker.
I just started sharing some of the images with him.
Look at the pictures that I'm taking out there.
You see what's going on out there?
The war zone.
It's a water war zone.
The doctors and the surgeons that I show these photos to all just start saying, you're like,
duh, kid.
Water makes people sick.
We know that so much of the disease that we're seeing is caused by unsafe water and lack
of sanitation and hygiene.
I get encouraged by the doctor that I most respected, this guy named Dr. Gary Parker,
who had a personal back, sorry, if I pause for one second just to tell his.
He was a California surgeon that had signed up for three months, just like many.
When I walked up the gangway of the ship for the first time, he'd been there 21 years.
He became a lifer.
He just never went back to his practice.
Another real piece, I now have a guide mentor that kind of like me, I'm going to tie the
one of the 10 years, but he never went back to his former life.
What might that look like for me?
He encourages me.
He says, well, you seem pretty passionate about this water thing.
If you really wanted to bring health to the world, if you really cared about impacting
the health of millions or the time of billion people, you would make sure everybody had
clean water. And that would be a great issue.
You want to play doctor to the world.
Don't help raise money for another 60 million dollar hospital ship that can do a few
thousand very effective surgeries.
Go get go make sure everybody in this country has clean water.
Maybe we wouldn't even need to pull into port here.
So I start thinking about this.
And at the time, I actually wanted to continue working for Mercy ships.
So I'm thinking about water and what I might do on my own that I finished the second
year and I try and work for them.
Like, hey, what if I did my exhibition model all around the world, Berlin and Prague and
in Paris and in London?
And, you know, let's raise huge awareness.
Let's make your organization and your doctors famous.
Let's raise millions of dollars.
And they basically said, no, thanks, which I don't blame them.
I mean, this was a very conservative organization based out of a dry town in Texas,
Lindale, Texas.
And some New York club promoter wants huge budgets to fly around the world, putting on
huge exhibitions of tumors and light boxes and the stuff, the ideas I had were just
crazy. So the door closes and they say, thanks, but no, thanks.
You know, you've really helped us.
It's amazing. I think I helped them get 20 or 30 media items.
You know, I got my photos published in the Wall Street Journal and the Independent in
London. So I thought I brought a lot of awareness and money to them.
But that door shut and I said, all right, well, I'm not going back to my former life.
Two years in. What if I just take everything I've learned and start the water thing?
Let me go work on water.
And what would it look like if I dedicated 20, 30, maybe the rest of my life to helping
people get clean drinking water?
What kind of impact could I make?
So I just started and that was I had my issue.
Like, let me try it.
People need clean water.
So I was living at that time on a walk-in closet floor on Spring and Mercer in Soho, New
York. My club partner had taken me in.
It was an unideal situation because he was doing heroin at the time with his friends.
But it was the only place I had to live and it was free.
And he says, well, you know, you can use my living room and my couch as your office.
And I did have, you know, a spare bedroom and then the closet floor when I got bounced from
the little bedroom in the back.
And I was on a mission here like from from day one.
I'm like, I'm going to be the clean water fighter.
I'm going to fight for clean water.
And therefore I'm going to be potentially the most effective doctor that the world has
ever seen. If I could get millions, tens of millions, maybe hundreds of millions of
people, the most basic need for health.
And I'd be working right alongside Mercy Ships and eliminating the need for, you know, a
lot of those conditions that we were treating.
So how did you get smart on this topic?
Like there's it's one thing to take sort of what I would call the first order observation,
which is these people are drinking a bunch of dirty water.
Dirty water is making them sick.
That's bad. But then there's like the second, third, fourth order insights that are
necessary, which is like, what's the root cause of this?
What are the non-linear implications of this?
How do you actually fix this problem in the most leveraged way, in the most scalable way?
Like, I mean, obviously today, you know the answer to all of those things, but that's an
overwhelming task for some guy sitting in a closet in Soho to figure out.
Thankfully, it didn't feel like that at the time.
I started flying around meeting with water organizations, started reading everything I
could on the global water crisis.
Then I started traveling around to Africa and to India.
I'm you don't have any money.
So I I file for a 501 C3 and I'm raising money then on the idea that our organization is.
So this is sort of like you're taking Angel's VC early dollars on your charity.
You got it. It wasn't even tax deductible.
And a lot of those early dollars were buying me a eight hundred and seventy two dollar coach
flight to Ethiopia, where it was very inexpensive to run around for two weeks.
And often I'd be hosted by the local partner who's covering room and board and food.
So I'm both trying to fundraise for my organization, which has a very clear mission.
We're going to bring clean drinking water to everybody on the planet.
OK, we're going to figure out how to do this as we go along.
But we are getting clean drinking water to everybody in need.
I have a huge observation at this time and I realize that this isn't going to be easy
because the lack of trust that I had sniffed out a little bit during that first exhibition
when my club friends were coming in and giving surgery money to Mercy ships, it was real.
Meaning the lack of trust amongst the donors.
Yeah, the donor.
The donor faith that you're actually doing what you say you're doing, or at least you're
doing it reasonably well.
People didn't trust charities.
I would hear stories of I don't know where my money goes.
Charities are big black holes that eat money.
You would hear stories of high overheads.
I don't know the impact.
You know, charity CEOs probably paying themselves millions of dollars.
I mean, everybody seemed to have a scandal that they could readily pull out of their
back pocket to say, this is why I don't trust, you know, the big philanthropy, the big
charities. And I actually found data behind that.
So USA Today had polled Americans and found 42 percent of people said they didn't trust
charities. And this is this is probably actually shocking to some people that are listening
because who is more generous or philanthropic than Americans?
We have this heritage, this cultural reputation of being some of those generous people on
Earth, if not the most generous.
Certainly my research when I was in the business of fundraising was that not only were
Americans the most generous, but New Yorkers were the most generous amongst all Americans.
People always ask me, why am I in New York now?
And I say in many ways, they could trace it back to my days of fundraising.
There's a Willie Sutton quote, right?
Why do you rob banks?
That's where the money is.
Why do you raise money in New York?
Because that's not just where the money is.
It's where the people are who are the most generous.
And I I remember being really surprised by that, but also felt like, you know, New Yorkers
really get a bad rap sometimes.
People sort of think of all these sort of wealthy people in New York or even, you know,
whatever. Just the average person in New York is sort of a hard person and, you know, sort
of fast living and blah, blah, blah.
But in many ways, I again, I don't want to take knocks at people, but I just would have
expected at the outset that other parts of the country would have been much more generous.
And I was constantly amazed at the generosity of New Yorkers.
Well, there you go. So I and that's where we started really from that closet floor and
from the couch of the drug den and so you know, not ideal conditions, I guess.
But so to combat that cynicism or that skepticism, I'd come across a guy called
Paul Tudor Jones, who was a hedge fund billionaire and he'd started the Robin Hood
actually co-founded Robin Hood.
Yep. Robin Hood Foundation. And, you know, in what I understood from his story, he also
realized that donors didn't trust charities. And he said, cool, tell you what, I'm rich
enough. I'll pay for all the overhead of the charity so that 100 percent of anything you
give to my charity goes directly to the programs, which was education in the inner city.
And to this day, the entire board of Robin Hood does just that.
So now it's him and his board. It's gotten too much probably for him. But, you know,
initially you can imagine the idea of that impulse. I'll fund it.
OK, now what's your excuse? What was your next excuse of why you wouldn't give to help the
poor here in New York City if you knew that all your money was going?
So I write him a letter. He doesn't write me back. And I guess why would he?
But I wondered, it just felt so clean, so extreme, so elegant. Two bank accounts.
What if I open up two bank accounts and I promised the public that all of the money
they would ever give to charity water? I wasn't very creative in the beginning.
The charity that helps people get water. Charity water.
What if all the money that they give goes directly to fund water projects that directly
help people get clean water? And in bank account number two, somehow I'm going to figure
out how to raise all the overhead separately. No idea at the beginning, but I love the model.
Two bank accounts audited separately and this this public promise that whether someone gave a
dollar or a hundred dollars or a thousand dollars or a million dollars, it would all reach the
100 percent programmatic. 100 percent.
So can I interject one thing on my high horse here? I applaud you for doing that, but I also
want a listener to understand something. Overhead is not a dirty term.
Absolutely not. And there's a great TED Talk.
Damn it. A lot of unshareable. That's right. And I believe everything you say.
Yeah. And after two things, one, his talk really impacted me, which is probably five, six years ago.
And then my own experience of realizing the same thing you did, that what my wife and I have decided
going forward, we support only 100 percent overhead.
So every dollar we give, we give directly to salary supportive people we believe in doing
charity. And we do that because we know it's much easier to raise money on the programmatic side.
It's much easier to say, give me a thousand bucks to go and build a well.
But my interest is, well, who's paying Scott salary?
Because I'd much rather pay Scott salary.
We do the same thing. You know, we maybe seven years ago, my wife and I just decided, hey, we're going to write on the
check, you know, 100 percent overhead.
Yes. Use this for the, you know, or even use it for what nobody else wants to pay for.
That's what we say. We'll write a note and say, you know, I mean, go fix the roof of the building, go pay the phone bill, go take
the extra trip home from the orphanage to go with your family around the holidays.
Right. Don't have the orphan.
Write me letters.
That's the easy thing. You're going to go get somebody else who doesn't trust to do that.
Yeah. So OK, so I'm totally with you.
And I know Dan Plata and really like what he's saying.
However, it's been an uphill battle.
He's been preaching that message for 10 years.
And the data hasn't showed that it's moving people.
So I was like, I'm going to fight a different battle.
I'm going to go and raise all the overhead separately.
I'm going to go find Peter and his wife, a different set of donor, a builder, an innovator, you know, who actually gets or could get excited about the salaries, the office.
You know, in many ways what it comes down to, in my opinion, which you've already figured out is you have to find people who believe in you versus the mission.
And those are two slightly different things.
They can often go hand in hand.
But in the end of the day, when I think about the sort of salary support that we provide to people, it's because like, yeah, I believe in that individual and I trust that individual.
And all I want is their life to be easier because indirectly, what you realize is their life is easier.
They're doing better work.
And what I think is elegant about the way you've done it is you've literally separated the financial stream.
And they get audited separately.
Yeah, that is different numbers.
That is so brilliant.
It's not fungible.
No, that is so brilliant.
And we took it a step farther than Robin Hood because I just I love like black and white before and after.
Like I just I don't do well with gray.
So I said, well, if we're going to be out there, that is the theme of your life, Scott.
You do not.
Despite the fact that you're sitting there in a gray sweatshirt right now, you do not do well in gray.
So you'll like this.
I say, well, I can't be up there talking about 100 percent unless we also pay back all the credit card fees.
So from day one and to this day, if you went online right now, you pulled out your American Express and you go to charity, what?
I don't know. You give 100 bucks.
And it's three percent of you got it.
So I get ninety seven.
But what did you give?
I have a hundred.
So what do you expect?
A hundred dollars to go to the field.
So in the other bank accounts and I can talk about how we do that later and all the trials and that.
But we actually pay back that three dollars and we send your hundred dollars.
You're intended hundred dollars to the field.
So that was pillar number one.
Pillar number two was then when you have two bank accounts, I just realized, OK, we've just created a non fungible, non black hole scenario.
So why can't we use technology to track these dollars as they go out and just show people where they landed?
So if we were going to build a well in Malawi, you know, we could say your money went here or to Bangladesh or to India or to Cambodia or to Bolivia.
And, you know, I looked into meeting the Google Earth founder when I was starting Charity Water.
I met him at a conference and they were building Google Earth and Google Maps.
And I just realized I was going to be able from day one to geolocate every water project using their free platform.
And all it was going to cost me was 50 dollar handheld GPS devices.
I think they were Garmin devices at the time.
You could go buy a Best Buy.
And we would be able to fund a water project that helped people get clean water, turn on a GPS device, take a picture of the GPS, take a picture of the project and then upload it and say, this is proof.
You'd be able to see a satellite image of your well.
So if 100 percent was the first pillar, proof then became the second pillar and proof would look very different in many different ways.
We would have hopefully myriad ways of being creative and connecting people to what their money did.
The third thing that I wanted to do differently was I wanted to I wanted the brand to feel unlike any other charity that I'd ever encountered.
I wanted to build an epic brand, a beautiful brand and an imaginative, inspiring brand.
And when I saw most charities, I saw marketing that I didn't want any part of.
I saw shame and guilt and almost toxic marketing.
And you may remember the commercials from the 80s and the 90s with Sally Struthers and the flies that land on the kids faces in slow motion as they look up and lock their sad eyes with the camera.
And then the 800 number slowly creeps across the screen and you give and you give out of the.
You give out of like shame often or guilt for feeling that you're in your comfortable living room and these kids in Africa flies crawling on their face.
Dude, that is so amazing that you brought that image up.
Like I remember the commercial you're talking about.
I would have I would have never pulled that out of my recesses of my brain.
Had you not mentioned that that's literally thirty five, forty years ago.
I just went and watched them recently to make sure that they were as bad as I remember.
And they're worse. So to me, the vestiges of shame and guilt and even the the language, by the way, this this is still pervasive today, the language giving back.
This is unhelpful. If I snatch the mic from in front of you, you know, you'd say, give it back as if I've taken it from you.
And the language implies we have, you know, we've pillaged and plundered to such extent.
We should probably throw a few scraps back to the poor.
Let's give a little back that we've taken.
And it implies giving out of debt or obligation, all unhealthy things without.
And I come across a quote by Nick Kristoff in The New York Times, and he said, toothpaste is being peddled with far more sophistication than all the world's lifesaving causes.
Charity brands suck. Doritos will spend hundreds of millions of dollars cleverly marketing stuff that kills us and our children.
But the most important lifesaving humanitarian efforts often have an anemic brands where they guilt and shame people into giving to them.
And by the way, this comes back in some way to the overhead problem.
And this is sort of one of the challenges in the nonprofit world that I think is really toxic, which is we have this belief that we shouldn't be able to pay people in a nonprofit.
Talent should be free. People should be willing to work for under market.
The reason Doritos can sell Doritos like you can't imagine, the reason they can push these things on you is not just because, well, they taste great.
It's because they can afford the best talent to figure out how to test all of these different things.
And I think a lot of nonprofits haven't really figured out that there is a bit of a war for talent and nonprofits are generally losing it in a big age demographic.
And my experience, nonprofits can do a really good job getting really young people fresh out of college who want some experience before going to grad school.
And they can do a pretty good job getting really talented sort of gray beards that are at the end of their careers and looking to quote unquote give back with respect to time.
But it's pretty tough to get an ultra talented 40 year old to go into a nonprofit when the alternative for many people, even those who are mission driven, is to go and serve a mission in a for profit setting versus a not for profit setting.
Absolutely. And that that is a real challenge even to this day.
You know, give you an example that we had posted a job for receptionist at Charity Water recently and 1300 people applied.
So that's great. Young. It's a really young talent pool. But you're right. The executive hires have been having much harder.
People like their charity people poor. And Dan has been fighting this for a long time.
You know, I joke all the time that even now, you know, I'm 43 years old, I've got a wife, I've got kids, I could drive a $60,000 Toyota and not a $20,000 Mercedes because of the perception.
Forget about the cost of the car. Right. People are totally happy with me in a, you know, what's the big the Toyota Highlander, right?
I got to like load that thing up. I could probably have a $70,000 Toyota SUV or a GMC, but not a $24,000 BMW.
Oh, he's reaching. That's why we were even talking about the watch. I mean, I'm not wearing a watch today. All this stuff matters.
You know, the perception becomes reality. So, okay, let me go back just to that bit. So the brand, so our brand would feel different.
It would be imagined if it inspired to be hope based. The last analogy I just want to make, I think Nike is such a great analogy.
If Nike were a bad old charity, their marketing might go like this. Hey, Peter, you're fat and you're lazy.
Turn off the TV, put away the junk food. Why don't you go for a run? Why don't you exercise? Now, instead of just doing it.
Oh, and buy our stuff. Yeah. Yeah. No. So Nike for years has been telling inspirational stories of people overcoming adversity, overcoming impossible odds.
Right. Nike believes that if you've lost your legs, you can complete a marathon and get over the finish line.
You know, you, you lost your arm. You can still be a shot putter. Right. I mean, they, they kind of for years have said,
we believe there's greatness within you. Right. And then you want to buy the shoes and then you want that symbol next to your heart that says, you know, just do it because the company believes that about you in their marketing.
So charities, you know, don't do that. So we wanted ours to be like, we believe you have a mind blowing capacity for compassion, for empathy.
We believe your capacity to be deeply generous and to extend your arm across an ocean and help people. You don't have to help. You don't have a debt or an obligation to help, but you can end the suffering because you choose to.
And you'll be blessed in the process. And, you know, you might even find yourself redeemed in the process of moving from selfishness and accumulation to helping others.
So there was, there was a lot of soft stuff. I mean, now I have language to it years later, but I just, I want to charity wanted to feel very different. I wanted to feel like Apple or Virgin and have a personality and have a brand.
And then the fourth pillar was, I was not going to send anybody that looked like some white guy from New York city to Africa to go drill a well or to India or to Southeast Asia.
I believed in my travels, just what I'd seen in Benin and Liberia and then Uganda and Kenya as I traveled around looking for water partners.
I just believe that for the work to be sustainable and culturally appropriate, it had to be led by the locals.
So our job would be to find the local organizations who could go and build these water projects. Our job would be to scale them, maybe buy them more drilling rigs or trucks or help them hire the hydrologist they need.
But they would be the ones getting the credit. I just, I love that idea that our role could be let's raise awareness for this important issue.
Let's build a movement of people who say we can and will bring clean drinking water to everybody on the planet. Let's raise money as efficiently as possible and as transparently as possible.
And then let's have all the work be done by the locals, leading their communities and their countries forward.
Yeah. And the irony of that is when you understand these problems, as you do, you realize that is the better solution. That's the sustainable solution.
Of course, on the flip side of that, it potentially deprives someone of the experience that you were so fortunate to have, which is your volunteers.
I assume you don't have that same body of volunteers.
People ask me all the time, can I go drill a well in Africa? Now, I didn't drill a well.
So I wasn't the doctor working in the rural area or the well drill. I was the documentarian. I was the storyteller.
So when I do take donors and I've taken about 350 people, including 50 kids over the last 12 years, they are there to learn.
They're there to listen and then come back and become advocates, not to drill a well.
I just don't need them in the ground. I don't need them standing on the drilling rig, pretending like they're doing something that the local does that anyway.
That's a liability, potentially.
Exactly. So yeah, we are not a good volunteer organization if you want to go and get your hands dirty.
So it's funny when I say this stuff, like give away 100% and just build a hyper transparent money flow,
prove to people what you do with their money and show impact, build an inspiring hopeful brand, and then work through locals.
It all sounds like common sense. I mean, you know, but this was so unique 12 years ago that we exploded.
I mean, people were throwing money at us. You know, I think we were $2 million in our first year from that couch.
I mean, it was just it was just working. And there was a flurry of activity. We were shooting public service announcements.
We were convincing luxury retailers like Saks Fifth Avenue to give us their windows for a week and get their employees involved and their vendors involved
and their customers involved. We were doing outdoor exhibitions showing putting dirty water from the East River and the Hudson River and ponds
in these big plexi tanks and getting people to sponsor these exhibitions and getting MTV set builders to donate it with their time.
And it was just it was startup. What could we do to get people to care about this issue, to know about it and then raise money?
You know, Scott, I know we both decided before we got on this this doing this interview that we sort of had to stop at a certain point in time,
which I know we've now gone past. There's so many more questions I want to ask you about Charity Water for the listener.
Let's wrap this thing up in the following way. If somebody wants to learn all of these details about Charity Water, besides going to Charity Water.org,
are there other talks that you've given that we can be linking to other places where they can learn?
Obviously, you've got a book that just came out. Yeah. Yeah. And there's so many amazing stories of the 100 percent model definitely came under trial.
And there were moments of almost insolvency. And the organizations now raise $330 million from over a million people around the world.
And there are so many stories of heroism and courage from the community and failure. And yeah, so there's I think that's that's one place to start.
There certainly are some talks online that we could we could link to. All right. So we're going to make sure we have lots of links.
You've given a TED talk as well. Not specifically a TED, but similar.
Oh, OK. I thought was it TEDx or no, wasn't it? I might do TEDx this year. Yeah. Well, you should be giving a TED talk. That's for sure.
So we'll link to that. So your book is called Thirsty. Thirst. Thirst. Yep. A little double entendre there, maybe. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
And all the proceeds, all my proceeds go to the organization. So I won't make a penny off it. And I was telling you, I just found out yesterday it's a New York Times best seller in the first week.
So that's cool. Fantastic. Congratulations. My wife was planning on that money to go towards our kids college funds.
But like, oh, this is this is not the right thing to keep. And I want this book to go out and really spread the story and hopefully inspire, inspire a lot of people, maybe to start their own causes, maybe to join us, maybe to give them the courage and the inspiration that no matter what they have done in their past, they're probably not as bad as me.
Where can people find you on social media? I'm just my name, Scott Harrison and Charity Water. Any books that you recommend when you talk about your journey, not just maybe what you went through, you know, 15 years ago, but even today, like what you give me three books that have been not necessarily transformative, but but have have moved the needle for you in some way in terms of how you've thought about either what you're doing today or how you got here.
There's an interesting book on the subject of poverty and approach called White Mans Burton guy named Bill Easterly at NYU that kind of talks about approaches to aid, you know, and good aid and bad aid. And that's, that's one of the beauties of doing clean water is nobody tells you to stop. I mean, no one is saying that taking a human being from a swamp or a dirty river, you know, to providing a sustainable source of clean water is, is harmful in any way. But that's, that was a really good read for me.
You know, on a personal level, when I got on the ship, I was reading this tiny little book written by a monk called practicing the presence of God, which was just this kind of idea of surrendering yourself to others and trying to live a pure and virtuous life. This guy lives a very simple life. He was cutting carrots in the kitchen and was just talking about really a life of virtue.
You know, with kids now, there's a book I really love the name escapes me right now. I just I'm on my second time around. I think it's letters to a God son by this guy, Stanley where of us and he talks about he writes a letter to his God son every single year teaching him a different virtue. So I'm trying to build character about teaching about kindness, teaching about generosity, teaching about integrity. And it's a really, it's really beautiful thing as a father, as I just think about
it's a book more for us as the parents.
Yeah, for sure. Yeah. But just thinking about how he conveys this and you know, knowing that the child will age into these letters. This is called letters to a God son.
Scott, you're one of the people that I think even I remember by the time we got to the airplane, you know, that on that drive back that day, which again, it was like a 30 minute drive of which we wasted seven minutes talking about watches.
I remember thinking, my God, this this is not a normal dude and dialogues a pretty impressive crowd of people. I mean, by definition, everybody had dialogues kind of cool, kind of interesting has done, you know, they're not just selecting the smartest or the richest or the most whatever.
They're trying to select people. They're trying to curate people who are really, really interesting. And so even after three days of being around those people, I remember thinking this guy stands out. You're a real inspiration. So thank you for what you're doing.
Thanks for having me. Time time flow. Oh, my gosh. We didn't even we didn't talk about probably half the stuff we wanted to.
I it's funny because I read most of your book before we spoke and it was like I remember thinking, yeah, we're never going to get through all this. So but look, I want people to read the book too. So we got to we got to leave some stuff out.
Thanks for coming by. Thanks for having me.
You can find all of this information and more at Peter at the MD dot com forward slash podcast. There you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at Peter at the MD dot com.
What's a nerd safari you ask? Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to the most interesting papers I've read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram and Facebook, all with the ID Peter at the MD. But usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing or other professional health care services, including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit Peter at the MD dot com forward slash about