Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hi everyone, welcome to this week's edition of the Peter Attia drive.
I'm Peter Attia.
This week, my guest is Professor David Sinclair.
He's a professor in the department of genetics at Harvard Medical School, and he is the co-director
of the Paul F. Glenn Center for the Biological Mechanisms of Aging.
David Hale's from Australia.
That'll take you about 10 seconds into our interview to figure out.
He did his PhD in molecular genetics at the University of New South Wales in Sydney.
And it was at that time that he met the man that would go on to become his mentor.
We talk a lot about him, and this is a guy, Lenny, who's actually come up on other podcasts,
so I won't get into him now.
But nevertheless, David met Lenny and decided he wanted to come to MIT to study with him,
which is what he did.
And David has gone on to become one of the pioneers in a particular field of aging that
focuses on a class of molecules known as sirtuins.
I'm sure many of you have heard of sirtuins, but you might not entirely be clear on what
sirtuins are.
I won't obviously make any attempt to do that here in the intro because we spend so much
time talking about that during this episode.
The other thing that David is really quite famous for is his role in the discovery of
a molecule or class of molecules that stimulates sirtuins.
And by the time you get through this episode, you will understand why that may be a desirable
thing to do.
And among these, the most famous is one called resveratrol.
Of course, resveratrol came to fame probably a little over a decade ago when it was noted
at least in one study, in one type of animal model, to promote a longevity phenotype.
And of course, what really made it interesting, at least for the lay press, was that resveratrol
is found in very low concentrations in the skin of grapes.
And therefore the logic went, hey, grapes make wine, wine contains resveratrol, wine
makes you live longer.
Hallelujah, the French paradox has been resolved.
Slight spoiler alert, that's not true, but we get into the whys that might be the case.
This episode, we only had, when I say only, meaning we had less than two hours, but like
has happened in other podcasts, including the one with Rhonda Patrick.
After we closed the podcast, because I wanted to be respectful of David's time, he had to
catch a flight to New York right after we spoke.
This interview took place in Boston.
We ended up talking for another 15 minutes.
And unfortunately, that 15 minutes was some of the most intense, detailed, nuanced discussions
of it.
And I left thinking, gosh, I wish we had more time to talk.
So I suspect David and I will speak again.
David has a book coming out next year, and I think that'll provide another great opportunity
to sit back down with him.
In this episode, we talk a lot about his postdoc at MIT.
He came out of a powerhouse lab that has produced other notable folks that, including folks
we've already interviewed, like Matt Kaberlin and folks we've talked about, like Brian Kennedy.
We talk about his contribution to the understanding of Sertuins, which was something that was
coming out of Lenny's lab.
And David really picked that up and ran with it.
What are these things?
What do they do?
What are the roles in aging, DNA repair, gene silencing?
We go over all this stuff in detail.
We talk a lot about NAD and its precursors, specifically something called NMN.
So if you are listening to this and you are in the camp of trying to understand how to
make heads or tails of NAD, NR, NMN, I think this episode will be helpful.
Tragically, it was not until 24 hours after we did this episode that I ran into George
Vlesic on an airplane who mentioned to me a paper by Josh Rabinowitz in Cell Metabolism
that came out about a month before we did this interview that we will link to that I
think makes a very compelling case for the futility of orally administered versions of
these precursors.
And that would have been a really interesting discussion to have with David because of his
expertise in this.
So at some point, I'll probably want to interview Josh and we'll go into that in really detail.
Because again, unless you've been up in the Himalayas hunting Yeti, you're probably aware
that these are kind of the hottest supplements out there.
We talk a lot about NAD levels.
What do these things mean?
Where does it go?
Where is it produced?
We again, as I alluded to above, talk about resveratrol and its potential in life extension.
We talk about the connection then between sirtuins and NAD.
We talk about his rationale for what he does.
So David is actually very open about kind of the stuff that he does personally, including
the fact that he takes resveratrol and metformin and NMN himself.
We also go into the differences between some of these molecules and again, a little bit
to his book.
There's a lot of stuff in here.
Again, sometimes it gets technical.
Sometimes it doesn't.
The show notes as always will provide a lot of help.
So if you have any questions about papers we reference, the likelihood that they're
in the show notes is actually quite high.
Also, if you haven't signed up for our weekly email list and you wouldn't mind getting an
email from me once a week, I suggest you head on over to the website, peterteamd.com and
sign up.
All I promise to you is to make it as non-lame as possible.
And finally, if you are enjoying these podcasts, please head on over to iTunes and write a
review there.
And again, I would hope that you like the podcast and leave a positive review, but I
guess in the spirit of getting as much feedback as possible, if you don't like it and you
have something to say that we can do to make it better, that's probably not an unreasonable
place to leave that kind of feedback.
So with all that said, please welcome to my interview with Professor David Sinclair.
Good afternoon, David.
Nice to be here, Peter.
Thank you for making time today.
I gathered only by the commotion in this very busy place we're in that there's a lot going
on here and making time to speak with somebody as inconsequential as I am is a big ask.
So I am incredibly grateful.
I'm pleased to be on.
We were introduced by a mutual friend who's no stranger to people listening to this because
I've had him on before, David Sabatini.
And maybe a month ago, maybe a little more than that, I said, David, you know, I really
want to know more about Sirtuans and who do you recommend that I speak with?
And he said, well, I think David Sinclair would be perfect.
So he reached out to you and you very graciously agreed to speak.
So again, I thank you for that.
And I'm really excited to talk about something that I know very little about, as you will
undoubtedly learn in the next hour or so.
Well, yeah, that's kind of David.
As you know, and probably the listeners know as well, he's a bit of a superstar.
It's kind of him.
I'll have to, you know, send him a note for that.
But no, honestly, it's really great to be on because I know you delve into the details
of the science more than anyone I've heard.
And I'm excited to be able to share that with listeners.
Well, yeah, that's the part that's got me excited.
So a lot of times I've listened to talks that you've given and I can tell your, I don't
want to use the word dumbing it down, but you're, you know, you're speaking to an audience
where you realize that if you go too far in the weeds, they're going to miss the point.
And so I found myself watching talks you've given on YouTube going, I wish he would elaborate
on that point and that point.
Hey, maybe then I don't understand it myself.
Let's see.
So I think just for a bit of background, I know you did your undergrad, your PhD in
Australia, and then somehow you wind up in Lenny's lab at MIT.
How did that happen?
I've been interested in aging since I was four, since I realized that everybody and
everything around me is going to die.
That's a pretty big shock for everybody.
Most people forget about it because you just can't function thinking about it every day.
I forgot about it until my teenage years.
And I realized that with the technology that was coming online, these are the days of early
PCR and gene sequencing.
We used to call it genetic engineering.
I thought maybe we're just the last generation who's going to live a normal lifespan, a regular
evolved lifespan.
And our children and our children, children forever are going to be able to benefit from
these new technologies.
And damn it, this is not right.
I've got grandparents, parents, friends, and about five billion people who could really
be benefited right now.
So at that point, I decided to seek out the best people in the world and see if I could
go work with them.
And I got a PhD in molecular biology, in yeast genetics, and that was a great PhD.
And a real turning point for me was this guy from MIT who I knew about because he was also
a yeast researcher.
He was a legend.
I'd read all these papers.
Lenny Gorenti came to Australia.
And here I am, this young 20-something year old, having dinner with Lenny Gorenti and
my PhD supervisor from Australia.
And Lenny starts telling this story halfway through dinner about this new project that
a guy called Nick Inor, Austrajakko, and Brian Kennedy had just started doing.
And it was to try and find genes that control aging in yeast cells.
And I said, OK, I know yeast.
And I've always wanted to figure this out.
Damn it, that's what I want to do.
Save me a spot, Lenny.
I'm going to come into your lab.
And he went, yeah, yeah, yeah, whatever, as he does to most people who want to join his
lab.
So I wrote to him pretty soon after, maybe six months, I was finishing up, can I come
to your lab?
And he wrote back like he does to everybody.
Sure, you can come.
But then a millisecond later, I was disappointed because he said, you have to bring your own
funding.
So that was no small task.
And that's a story in itself.
Just briefly, though, this is a lesson for anyone who's listening who thinks that getting
to somewhere like this is easy.
You have to be massively determined.
You have to have grit.
And I just wouldn't give up because there's nothing else I wanted to do in my life.
I certainly was looking at patent law even.
But that would I think I would have died if I had done that as a career.
I just don't have the attention span.
Anyway, I actually found funding.
It turns out I applied to the Helen Hay Whitney Foundation, which is a prestigious foundation
here.
And they wrote to me and said, you can't apply.
You're a foreigner.
And I said, well, this is the old days with early email.
I think it might even be post.
And they wrote back and they said, well, you're a foreigner.
We can't afford to fly you out to Boston, Cambridge for an interview.
And I said, well, I'll sell my car and I'll pay for the ticket.
As I understand it, I was the first foreigner who was allowed to interview and I flew here.
I stayed in Nicanor, Ostrichko's basement.
He was very kind.
And my interview was with a guy who everyone was telling me is a real tough guy, super
smart.
I'd never heard of him.
Of course, now everybody in science knows of Doug Melton.
He's king of, well, endocrinology and stem cells at Harvard.
And I was just this kid showing up for an interview and there was a line of people outside
his door waiting.
And I was fifth in line and I went in and Professor Melton said to me, David, tell me
what you want to do.
And I had literally five minutes to impress this guy, one of the smartest people I'll
ever meet.
I told your car flown 22 hours for a five minute interview.
Yeah, that was basically it.
And so I thought about it most of my adult life, what was aging about.
And a lot of people in those days, back in the late 80s, early 90s, were talking about
the evolution of aging genes, death genes.
And I studied evolutionary biology myself and that didn't make any sense.
You don't evolve death genes.
And I never subscribed to the group theory of selection.
So every person for themselves, selfish gene, love Dork and stuff.
And so my thought was the only genes that I could understand could evolve that have
relevance to aging are longevity genes.
And right about that time, there was the discovery of in C. elegans, the nematode worm of the
DAFT mutation from...
Yeah, I was about to say this must have corresponded with Cynthia's work, right, around the same
time.
It's just happening.
And Lenny at the same time had just discovered a mutation that they weren't sure what it
was doing, but it turns out it led to the Sirtuin story.
And so I said to Doug, I want to come to Lenny's lab and discover life genes, genes that give
life and longevity.
And I guess he liked the idea of what I was saying, certainly very passionate.
It probably didn't hurt that I brought a bottle of red wine as a present.
I just thought that's what you do when you come to people's place.
Later on, I learned that that's equivalent to bribing somebody, but I was just a young
kid.
But yeah, that's what happened.
No foreshadowing the resveratrol there.
Yeah, definitely.
It was an auspicious kind of a thing.
But being able to come to Lenny's lab, I would have worked in Lenny's lab for free.
I would have lived in the basement and done it.
That's just how much I wanted to do this.
So I came over.
It was late 1994, early 95, when things were just starting to take off, trying to understand
what these mutations were that Brian had found.
And was Matt Cabell in there as well?
Matt's also a close friend.
He was not there yet.
The lab has produced just a ridiculous amount of sort of prolific individuals in this anti-aging
space.
It was a golden age.
You could definitely feel that something special was going on in those days.
But I arrived.
I was the first postdoc to join to study aging specifically.
Was Brian a PhD student?
Yeah.
So Brian, I was this new guy on the block.
Brian teach me how to do yeast aging.
And he taught me.
But all the other postdocs, there are probably 18 to 20 postdocs there.
Big lab, all working on transcription regulation.
And that was the sexy thing.
And I was told by, I don't think I've told anybody publicly this, that the postdocs were
saying you're crazy to work on this aging project.
Lenny's lost his mind.
It's a house of cards.
It's going to fall down.
You can't study aging in yeast.
All of these things.
And within the first few weeks, I thought maybe I've made a mistake.
Maybe I was just fooled.
Maybe Lenny isn't that smart, as I thought.
But I stuck with it.
I do remember at one point on the phone, nearly crying to my mother saying, I think
I made a really big mistake.
And that stands out as a point where I could have easily just quit.
But I stuck with it.
And thank goodness I did.
Because Lenny was right.
And Lenny is really the smart visionary that saw that this was the right way to go.
So you sort of alluded to it earlier.
Lenny was sort of onto something, right?
There was basically a new pathway.
Now, if we go back in time to 1994, what did we know?
Well, we barely knew about Tor.
I mean, it was just being basically figured out that this thing that Michael Hall had
figured out a year earlier, Saul is figuring out, David is figuring out.
I mean, there's still this early triangulation of what's going on with rapamycin.
At the time, they didn't even, if I recall, I don't think we knew that there was mTORC1,
mTORC2.
And they were doing totally different things.
AMPK is pretty well understood.
Metformin's been around.
But I don't think people really had a sense at the time that it was anything other than
an anti-diabetic drug.
So talk me through this whole sirtuin thing.
That's a pretty broad question.
Let me narrow it down a little bit.
Talk me through what you were just about to allude to.
What was Lenny onto when you showed up?
Well, genetics is a fabulous tool because you don't have to go in with any hypothesis
that biology will tell you the answer.
And the gene that had just been cloned by Brian turned out to be what's called Ser4.
Now, Ser4 didn't turn out to be a mammalian conserved gene.
So Ser4 has not been as exciting.
But there was this partner of the Ser4 gene.
It was called Ser2.
And Ser2 and Ser3 and Ser4 formed this complex of proteins, stick together and control, of
all things, gene silencing.
That's what Ser stands for, silent information regulator, in this case number two.
And that was very unexpected.
In those days, if you think back, the cause of aging was thought to be DNA damage, mutations,
free radicals.
So we were all expecting to find genes that controlled DNA repair or antioxidants.
At that time, because I go back and I think, God, at that time I was still in college studying
math and engineering.
I didn't know.
I hadn't taken a biology course.
So I can't think about it through the context of my own education.
How well was it understood that there were introns and extrons and that much of the genome
wasn't even coding and stuff?
Was that well understood at that point in time?
It was.
In yeast, actually, they were ahead of anybody else in eukaryotes.
We knew that there were introns and not many introns in yeast anyway.
But we hadn't seen the full genome.
It was still bits and pieces.
Maybe five, 10% was known.
My PhD was sequencing three genes.
That's all it took.
Things were changing rapidly.
This new thing with PCR, you could move tubes into hot tubs and amplify genes.
It was all very exciting.
But what we didn't have any clue was that why a silencing gene that controlled, negatively
controlled genes, other genes, why that would have anything to do with aging.
It was totally bizarre.
It led to a string of cell papers.
One after another, every few months we were actually publishing something new and we had
a science paper.
That was the gold rush of this discovery because it really turned on the lights in this cave
of a whole new area of biology.
We're still trying to understand actually why those silencing proteins are relevant
to aging.
But what we do know for sure is that these same genes, these sirtuins in all life forms,
whether they're from plants all the way to us, do play a protective role in responding
to energy and nutrients just like the ampikinase neem topophage.
You alluded to sirtu.
Was that first found in yeast?
Yes, it was.
It was known already actually.
Lenny and we didn't discover sirtu was already known as a silencing protein that controlled
the mating type, in other words, the sex of a yeast cell.
If you don't have the silencing, what happens is that the yeast cells get confused because
they're now turning on genes for A and alpha, which means male and female.
A yeast cell that doesn't know if it's male or female will not mate and it's become sterile.
It turns out that's a hallmark of yeast aging is sterility.
The way you can tell whether a yeast cell is truly old is, is it sterile or is it just
sick?
That's how we used to tell.
But now we actually understand the cause of that sterility.
It's the actual movement of sirtu protein away from those genes that it should be at
to go deal with other problems in the cell.
I see.
It's not that sirtu becomes deactivated.
It just, for lack of a better description, shifts its attention elsewhere.
Right.
It's distracted by other things going on in the cell.
We had a cell paper in 1999 with Kevin Mills and Lenny where we discovered, and a couple
of other groups should also get credit for co-discovering this, is that the sirtuins
are also involved in DNA repair.
When you get a broken chromosome, it's the sirtu complex that goes along, helps unwrap
the DNA, we think, and put it back together and repair that.
While the sirtu complex is doing that, it cannot be also silencing.
There's not enough of it to go around.
You might ask, well, why would the cell do that?
Why don't you just make more sirtu?
What we think is that this is a very ancient system that coordinates controlling mating
and DNA repair.
You don't want to be mating and dividing if you've got a broken chromosome.
This is a way of coordinating those two events.
It's very ancient.
It's a very active system.
You need DNA checkpoint signaling, so it's not just random.
What we also have come to realize is that this, let's call it this distraction of the
sirtuins, it's conserved.
We find this happens in our own aging process as well.
There's really two roles.
There's gene silencing and DNA repair.
Sirtuins are HDACs.
Is that correct?
Are they all HDACs?
HDAC, histone deacetylases, this is the old name for protein deacetylases now.
What we've all come to realize is histones are just one of the things that sirtuins and
these other HDACs do.
They can target what are called nonhistone proteins.
They remove not just acetyl groups, but also other types of what are called generally
acyl groups.
That's a whole new world.
That means that sirtuins, the family, there are seven of them in mammals, five of them
in yeast, target other proteins, proteins that are in cytoplasm in the nucleus, even
in the mitochondria.
That's their role.
It's not so much only about controlling the chromatin and histone, but also about controlling
signaling and metabolism as well.
They can do that by targeting any protein theoretically in the cell.
Thinking back to DAF2, DAF16 as the parallels with FOXO and IGF, were there elegant experiments
in the yeast that could show you extreme conditions of lots of sirt, no sirt, and what that phenotype
is?
Oh yeah.
These were the first experiments.
I'll try to take you through them correctly in sequence.
What we showed with Brian, first of all, this is a 1996 cell paper, was that we were
looking for this movement.
There was this so-called age locus.
We didn't know what it was.
We didn't know where they were going.
We just knew that they left the silent mating type locus.
What we did was we stained it.
Brian had moved on actually to his post-doc.
Kevin Mills and I, a student at the time, our job was to find where are the sirt proteins
going.
We stained them and we could look at them on the microscope.
What we saw was they were going to this little place in the nucleus, which we eventually
figured out was the nucleolus, which is what makes the RNA, which makes the ribosomes.
It's a really important part.
The DNA that's within the nucleus is called the ribosomal DNA or the RNA.
That's where they were going, not just during normal aging, but also during an accelerated
form of aging.
There's a whole story that was lost in history actually that maybe I'll just quickly touch
on.
One of the first things I did when I got to Lenny's lab was to work on Werner's syndrome,
which is premature aging disease.
These are kids that die in their teens or 20s, aren't they?
No, that's a different Hutchinson-Gilford syndrome.
This one, Werner's, they lived till 40s.
They lived till their 40s, yeah.
The gene was just cloned by George Martin and his team out there.
The comolog in yeast is called SGS1.
I picked up the paper.
It was in Science, I recall.
I went into Lenny's office and I said, I've just been scooped, but there's a yeast homolog.
I'm going to work on that.
Is that okay?
He said, yeah, go for it.
We worked on SGS1 for a little bit.
What we found was that they were going through accelerated aging as well.
We had a science paper on that.
What was exciting about that was that they were also becoming sterile and the two complex
was moving as well, just like the normal aging.
We had this rapid aging model.
You might say, well, so what's the big deal?
You've got a rapid aging model.
That told us that there was some universal process that results in premature aging in
humans, probably in yeast, the same thing.
We could also study this much more easily than an old yeast cell.
Consider that to find a single old yeast cell, it's really hard, especially if you're just
studying replicative aging, which is the number of times they divide.
Each mother cell produces, on average, 10 to the power of 25 offspring.
That's, by my calculations, about 30 million offspring.
You have to pull out that one cell and study it by chemically.
Wait, you said 10 to the 25?
Yeah.
Sorry, 2 to the 25.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Yeah.
In any case, that's way more ... What we used to do is to sort out the old cells.
We'd label them with a chemical and pull them out with magnetic beads.
We couldn't get many of them, you'd just get a handful.
But with these SGS-1s proteins ...
You could get a bunch of them.
The mutants, we could get a lot more.
We'd made a lot of progress using that.
But every time we made a discovery with the SGS protein, our mutants, we went back to
the normal yeast cells and verified.
We were actually able to figure out with that mutant what the distracting problem was for
the CER complex.
That was actually DNA breaks and DNA recombination that was occurring at the most repetitive
regions, the most unstable region of the genome, which is the RDNA, which is in the
nicholleolus.
That was what was distracting those proteins.
Interesting.
When you knock out SIR2, is it easy to knock it out?
Yeah.
That was the next experiment.
Okay.
Then we wanted to know ... The prediction is if you knock out SIR2, you should get a
lot more of this instability at the RDNA.
Yes.
The question is, does it translate to accelerated aging or not necessarily accelerated aging,
but more cancer or some other phenotype, right?
Well, in yeast, it led to accelerated aging through the process I was telling you about,
genomic instability, DNA repair went down.
Also, that happens in animals, although it's a little more complex because it's embryonic
lethal in a lot of mice.
You can't easily do that experiment.
What you can do is the opposite.
You can turn on or over express the SIR2 gene in a yeast cell.
If we're right, you should get a few things that are going to happen.
You'll have more genomic stability at this, particularly at this RDNA locus in the nicholleolus,
and the yeast cells should live longer.
That experiment was done by an incoming graduate student, Matt Cabellon.
What a fantastic project to get when you walk in.
He did it, and the day that he got life plan extension with XTRISR2 was a very good one
for him and the lab.
What's the next step from there?
The most obvious thing is, how do you develop a compound that would do this without the
genetic mutation that empowered it?
Yeah, that was the issue because you can't easily genetically manipulate humans.
The question was, how do you turn on these genes?
We spent about three, four years working on caloric restriction in yeast and then in
mammals.
My lab and some others were leading the charge in showing that SIR2 ends, both in yeast and
mammals, were not only necessary but were sufficient when you over express them to mimic
calorie restriction.
Put another way, if you knock out SIR2, you don't get the benefits of calorie restriction.
You don't get the benefits of CR.
Right.
That's also now being shown by others to be true in mice as well.
That led to the idea that-
Is that true in all mice?
I couldn't say.
Even in yeast, you can get around the need for SIR2 and if you stress the yeast really
intensely with very little amount of calories.
But there are aspects of calorie restriction benefits such as a lifespan extension that
are ameliorated lessened by a SIR2 knockout but it's still complexified by the fact that
it's lethal in embryos and you have to knock it out in the adult to do a real experiment.
That's the same sort of issue that Cynthia had with the DAFs which was if you do too
early, the C. elegans doesn't make it into an intermediate stage.
You know what?
Somebody hasn't even done the proper experiment which is to take a mouse that you can knock
out SIR1 in an adult whole body and then calorie restrict.
Something that we probably should have done years ago.
But the technology is there to do that.
But what we did learn actually was both in yeast and in mammals was that it's not just
one of these genes that's important.
It's the whole family.
And that if you knock out, take yeast for example, if you knock out SIR2 in yeast, you
lose the ability to respond to some mild calorie restriction but if you really calorie restrict
them, they'll still live longer.
And there was a big debate actually between Brian, Matt, myself about that.
And where we settled on was that these other SIR2 related genes were also helping and they
work as a family.
And if you knock one out, the others can compensate.
Did yeast only have one?
Yeast of five.
And humans have a whole family.
Like eight or something.
Just seven.
Oh okay.
So only two more.
That's interesting.
Little known fact, most people ignore the other yeast SIR2 ones but they're just as interesting
and what we found is they also can extend lifespan as well.
So when you ... Actually it's funny, I was going to go back to something else you said
a second ago but what's the teleologic explanation for why caloric restriction and SIR2 ones would
move hand in hand?
Like for men, you talked earlier about your appreciation for evolutionary biology.
So an organism is in a nutrient deprived environment.
It still has to be able to do a bunch of things if it's going to be fit.
Do we believe that that's an environment where we need to see more stabilization of the genome
or repair or silencing or what do we think is the biggest insult during that period of
time?
Yeah, so the biggest insult to any life form is a broken chromosome.
That's lethal if you don't fix it.
Do we see that more likely happening during nutrient deprivation?
I would see that as ... I would have assumed, to be honest with you, I would have assumed
that was independent of nutrient exposure or at least if anything inversely correlated.
Well, if you don't have enough nucleotides to complete replication, you're going to break
a lot of times.
I see.
So they do go hand in hand but the bigger picture is that the SIR2 ones evolved, we believe,
what are we talking about, three and a half billion years ago in the first life forms,
probably life forms.
Maybe just after one of the first proteins to actually evolve, we think, would be a SIR2.
And its job is to sense biological stress in the environment, whether it's DNA damage
or it's a burst of cosmic rays, change in temperature or a lack of nutrients.
And their job is to allow that organism to hunker down and survive.
Stop mating, stop breeding.
We can do that in another day.
If we don't survive this, our offspring are going to die anyway.
So we think they control which genes to turn on and off in response to adversity and they
allow those organisms to survive.
But they're also talking to other pathways.
So they're going to talk to mTOR, they're going to talk to Cynthia's DAF pathway.
And collectively, these are the genes that we've settled on as the longevity pathways
but they didn't evolve for longevity, they evolved for survival during adversity.
How conserved are these across, let's use the big four models of eukaryotes from yeast,
worms, flies, larger mammals like mice and rodents.
Is this relatively well conserved the way the tor pathway is conserved or does it have
more bends in the road?
Well, they're surprisingly conserved that you can just manipulate one gene in each of
these organisms and get lifespan extension or one drug works in all of these organisms.
I would challenge anyone to use a chemotherapy to help a yeast cell.
So this is quite a magical discovery that the same pathways are that well conserved
and that ancient.
And that's actually one of the advantages we have.
Aging is actually not that difficult to be able to control and that's because our models
are very good.
If we can, I truly believe that if we can extend the lifespan of a yeast, a worm and
a mouse, humans are so close.
If you can do it across a billion years, you should be able to make that leap to a
few other hundred million years.
Exactly.
It's really just the regulatory agencies making sure that we don't do any harm and it's safe.
But the biology is all still there going way back three and a half billion years ago.
So it was 2006, 2007.
When did resveratrol emerge as an early search to an activator?
2003.
Okay.
And the story behind that was that we were looking for an activator, we're hoping for
an activator.
Were you in your own lab at this point?
Yeah.
You'd finish your postdoc, I'm guessing.
I managed to move to Harvard in 1999.
So that was the year when a lot of things happened.
While I was moving, we published the Stenia Repair Committee.
But just going back to the silly sort of social question, did you at some point think I want
to go back to Australia and set up a lab here?
Was it a difficult decision for you to stay in Boston as opposed to ... because you came
from Sydney, if I recall.
Right.
Well, the goal was to ...
Those are pretty different climates.
I've been to Sydney once, I spent two weeks there, I could stay there.
Yeah, I missed that.
But I also like adversity.
I thrive on adversity.
And so I've come to like living here.
The intention was to come here for two years.
I had a job to go back to.
But the first week of being here in Boston was like a city I could only dream about.
This is the Athens of ancient Greece, Rome of ancient Rome.
For biology, this is it.
And so I was in heaven.
I'd never experienced a city where you're on the train and people around you are reading
Science Magazine and Nature.
That's my dream.
So it was a very easy decision not to go back to Australia for reasons that if you really
want to change the world, you got to do it from here.
So now you're in the process of kick-starting your own lab, which comes with its own stresses.
Right?
You've got to secure funding and all those other things.
And then what's happening on the front of this stuff?
Yeah, so 1999, a few major things happened.
One was this DNA repair connection.
The second one was Lenny's lab published that NAD was a requirement for sirtuin activity.
And Shin Ami, who's at Wash U now, was the postdoc who made that somewhat serendipitous,
but brilliant discovery.
And then the third thing was the connection to calorie restriction was happening around
that time too.
Going back to the second thing, we talk about it now today, like it's in textbooks.
It's so obvious, right?
Sirtuins are NAD-dependent deacetylase.
Okay.
NAD is so ubiquitous in cells that if the quantity you could have in a cell varies on
a scale from one to 10, what is sufficient to produce this deacetylase activity?
Is it anywhere from two to 10 or does it have to be quite a high concentration?
It can be two to 10.
You can actually get very low levels in some disease conditions and the animal is still
alive.
And you're basically only saying that NAD is necessary for sirtuins to work.
Right.
Well, without NAD, we'd be dead in 30 seconds.
By other reasons as well.
Wouldn't we be dead just from not being able to do electron transports?
We would.
And there's more than 500 reactions that we need just to survive.
But what we didn't know in the 2000s, and it was actually quite a crazy thing to think
that NAD was regulating anything.
And that was actually what we first worked on in my lab was the control of sirtuins
with NAD levels.
The reason it's crazy is you read textbooks and NAD is the most ubiquitous important molecule
in the cell.
How could it possibly be varied during aging, let alone during the day when you eat something
or your circadian rhythm?
Now it's obvious.
We know NAD goes up and down.
It changes with age.
But in those days, people thought if you change the NAD levels, you'd probably die.
That's not true.
Down at the time that doesn't complex one of the mitochondria basically convert NAD
H to NAD?
So you would at least know that in the mitochondria, the concentration of NAD must go up and down,
or else you couldn't actually respire.
Well locally it goes up and down, but the steady state level is pretty constant.
And when you say going up and down, are you talking cytoplasmic, nuclear, plasma?
Where are we talking about?
We had a paper, I think it was 2007, where we had quite a surprising result, which told
us that it's not just the cytoplasm that it goes up and down.
It was also the mitochondria going up and down.
And we didn't know that.
We actually stumbled upon it.
We found that if we kept cells with high amounts of NAD, they would survive better, DNA damage,
other insults.
And we could deplete NAD in the cytoplasm, but the cells still lived.
We didn't understand that.
How did you do that, by the way?
How do you deplete NAD?
Actually, come to think of it, we could either overexpress NAD depleting enzymes, but actually
the way we found it was that when you damage cells with a DNA damaging agent, say chemotherapy
drug, the cells themselves deplete NAD naturally with this enzyme called PARP1, which is an
NAD-consuming enzyme.
And actually, that's very well known that if you hit a cell with a DNA damaging agent,
the reason that it dies is NAD depletion.
So we were measuring the NAD depletion in the context of...
And that's because the cell is trying to utilize that NAD to repair the damage you've just
caused?
Right.
Or you didn't know that at the time?
No, that was well known.
So PARP1 is a no-NDNA repair protein.
And if you block PARP, you also protect cells.
But what was interesting was that we could overexpress, give more copies of a gene that
made NAD, and this is called an MPT, which is the equivalent of the PNC1 gene in yeast,
which we found was important for lifespan in those organisms.
So we were overexpressing this MPT.
Cells had more NAD.
We hit them with the toxin.
They'd survive better than regular cells.
But the NAD was still being almost completely depleted from the side of...
Sorry, just because this is sort of the crux of it.
Did they survive because they were unable to deplete their NAD?
No, we saw that NAD just disappeared from the cell, but they survived.
But they still survived.
But there was a place we weren't looking at the time.
We tracked it down to the mitochondria.
So this begs the term the mitochondrial oasis hypothesis.
So myself and Anthony Solveil from Cornell coined this term.
So what we found was that as long as the mitochondria stayed active with their NAD, it didn't matter.
The cell could survive and recover from that stress.
And actually, it turns out that the levels in mitochondria, NAD levels are even more
important than cytoplasmic NAD levels for survival.
That makes sense.
And of course, that's a hard thing to measure, isn't it?
It was extremely hard.
That's where Anthony came in.
Anthony is a chemist and a biochemist at heart.
And it was extremely hard to isolate these mitochondria, preserve the NAD.
And then we had to use new technologies to be able to do that.
How was that done?
We were using mass spectrometry for the first time to measure NAD.
And what Anthony did brilliantly was to make labeled versions of NAD in its precursors.
And he could spike those in and use those as references to measure NAD levels in these
compartments.
And NAD, if I recall from just biochemistry, you don't get to move that in and out of plasma
into cells.
It's made de novo in the cell.
You have what you have.
You can make more.
You can bring in precursors, but you don't get to shuttle NAD between cells, correct?
As far as we know, right.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's sort of like an ATP problem.
It's really hard to quantify ATP in a cell.
By the way, does NADP do any of this as well?
Well, it's important, no doubt.
It's part of this whole problem that we're working on.
But if you add NADP or even NADH, which is only different by 100, those don't work to
activate sirtuins.
Only NAD plus will do that.
And I mean, not to get too nerdy on this, but it's obviously more than just the charge,
but the charge must play a role if NADH can't work, right?
Yeah.
So it's probably a combination of the charge and some other...
Good size, yeah.
Size, yeah.
Okay.
So now you've made these three discoveries, the second of which we just went into in a
little bit more detail.
How does the story unfold now?
You've got your spanking new lab.
Well, you worked for a little while on the SGS1 furnace protein and telomeres.
Put out a paper on that.
And we didn't work on sirtuins for about a year because Lenny said, I don't want you
working on sirtuins when I left the lab, which was a bit of a shock.
Why?
He didn't want the competition, I suppose.
I thought a year was enough to give him a head start, but we quickly started working
back on that.
Is that a common request of people when postdocs leave their labs?
No, of course not.
But what am I going to do?
I mean, the guy trained me.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I go in my career.
But in those days, it was very competitive.
So the Lenny of today is not the Lenny of previous years, and he's a wonderful friend
and mentor to me.
But that's how it was in those days.
It was very cutthroat.
I see.
But if it were up to you, you would have continued to work on sirtuins.
Right.
Now we're basically back to 2001, 2002.
The moratorium is up.
You're now back to working on it.
And nobody at this point in time has yet figured out a way to exogenously manipulate sirtuins
more than the stuff that we've already talked about, which is nutrients, stress, and things
like that.
Yeah, we were trying to feed yeast, NAD, and we gave them nicotinamide, which is a precursor
to NAD, vitamin B3.
And actually, Kevin Bitterman, who's now a very successful venture capitalist, my first
friend, he put nicotinamide on yeast, and we could measure the sirtu activity by the
color.
And if sirtu was more active, they'd turn red.
And he walked into my office, one of his first experiments when we worked on sirtuins, and
he said, David, something's weird.
We didn't get activation.
We got inhibition.
So the yeast had gone red.
And I said, Kevin, it doesn't matter what happens.
As for some expected, that's even better.
So that led to a paper that said that vitamin B3 high doses is inhibitory of sirtuins.
And now the labs around the world use nicotinamide as an inhibitor for sirtuins.
And I wouldn't recommend taking really high doses of nicotinamide.
Why is that?
There's a few answers.
By chemical answer is that there's an evolved pocket in the sirtuin structure that measures
nicotinamide levels, and it's a feedback loop.
So nicotinamide, to get nerdy, is the product of the reaction.
It takes NAD, cleaves it.
Oh, I got it.
So it's just a negative feedback loop.
It's negative feedback loop.
So we're going to study in the context of tuberculosis.
And what we found was that when we calorically restricted yeast cells, this was one of the
most highly upregulated genes in the whole yeast cell, which was very unusual.
People had discovered this before in their own lab, but they were wondering, what the
heck is this?
NAD synthesis pathway got to do with calorie restriction, got to do with stress, but we
knew exactly what was happening.
This is a stress response that was turning on NAD production and activating sirtuins.
So we had our first Nature paper, actually, on that 2002, I think, 2003.
And we found that PNC1 could mimic caloric restriction and raise NAD availability.
And if we knocked out the PNC1 gene, yeast cells didn't live longer when we calorie restricted
them.
And what's really interesting about that, I think, is that PNC1 doesn't just get turned
on by caloric restriction.
It's turned on by heat, low amino acids, salt, high salt.
And so this is a gene that senses the environment and turns on the sirtuins.
Exactly what I was explaining earlier about those early life forms on the planet, sense
their environment and through NAD and other ways they can turn on these pathways for defense.
So where did you go from PNC1 to Resveratrol?
Well, we teamed up with a company at the time.
They were called Biomol.
And they were making reagents for H-DAC assays, this kind of thing.
And Conrad Howitz was a scientist there.
And he had invented, wasn't even available yet, an assay for sirtuin activity in vitro.
I forget why he reached out to me, but he said, hey, well, maybe I wrote to him.
But whatever happened, he sent me some kits to test.
And they worked.
And it looked great.
And what was the gold standard prior to these kits?
Oh, gosh.
A mergers for tuin activity required western blotting, which is detecting the cell groups.
It was horribly hard.
Still is.
And this was a very quick way to look for molecules.
And what Conrad did was to take that assay and look through his collection of molecules
at Biomol.
They had libraries of these things.
And two of the first molecules that were discovered by him to change the activity of SIRT1, human
SIRT1, were a couple of plant molecules.
Now he found plenty of inhibitors.
Inhibiting wasn't the hard part.
Exactly.
But he called me up and he said, David, this is something's weird.
We've got these molecules that seem to activate the enzyme.
And I said, that's great.
That's what we need.
And he goes, well, I don't know if it's real, but let's work on this.
So we worked on it together for about six months trying to prove this wrong.
Because in the history of pharmaceuticals, there's only been a handful of molecules ever
that have been true allosteric activators, as these apparently were.
But we thought it could be fake.
It could be messing with the assay.
It could be an antioxidant activity.
But what really clinched it for me at first was we put these molecules onto cells.
And they lived longer, but only when the SIRT2 gene was present.
And the chance of that happening and us being wrong about this idea were pretty low.
So that was a good sign.
But the other thing that's not well known in history is that those first two molecules
that Conrad Howitz discovered, they were not resveratrol.
They were actually, I think, pisetanal and quercetin.
Quercetin's found in fruits and onions, I think.
But there was a brilliant CEO, Rob Zipkin.
And Rob was a chemist.
And Conrad showed him these structures that were quite similar, these two molecules.
They look like two rings connected by a bridge.
And Rob said, hey, you know what these two molecules look like?
Resveratrol.
And so Conrad and I are like, oh, what's resveratrol?
Anyway, I certainly was.
I didn't know much about resveratrol.
But I Googled it and comes up with, I'll suspect an ingredient for red wine.
And I could just see the next 10 years of media, which actually happened.
But it was an interesting time because we were, it was the first molecule that I can
recall was clearly lifespan extending in an organism that you had a defined genetic pathway
that wasn't just found off the shelf.
We really knew the pathway and we figured out.
And it's still, as far as I know, the only drug program that has come out of the aging
field where it was by design that we find these molecules.
So full credit to Dave and to others who have their molecules that have come out of drug
development.
So when they first started to make resveratrol for the purpose of these experiments, they
weren't extracting it out of naturally occurring sources.
It was just being synthesized straight away, even though it was acknowledged that, hey,
this thing also exists in nature.
Well, no, I think that probably was an extract, but I'm not being very articulate.
But the point I want to make is we did it in a different order.
So Rapamycin and Metformin were already on the shelf doing other things discovered by
others for doing things.
And then you can trace them back to the pathway and you get lifespan extension.
We didn't do it that way.
We said, here's the pathway.
This was the direct target.
We went genetics first and then found a molecule and then tested on the organism, which is,
you can do it both ways, but this was more rational science.
But anyway, that's the reason.
But we also had this very interesting result that we found a yeast mutant that, and actually
a sort of mammalian mutant, that was blocked that couldn't respond to resveratrol.
So we already knew that there was an amino acid that was required for this activation
by resveratrol in the test tube, which told me this isn't just some random thing.
This is a highly conserved mechanism because we could also show this amino acid was found
in other organisms as well.
And which amino acid was that?
In SIRT1, it's called E230 and the mutation made a lysine.
So it went from a negative charge to a positive charge at that location.
We didn't know why it blocked it.
Now we do.
But that was one of the early things that we had in our knowledge base to be able to
go forward.
Now, when you put resveratrol in cell culture like you had with the previous two compounds,
you mentioned with the previous compounds, if they lacked SIRT2 and they did not get
the longevity phenotype.
Did you see the same thing with resveratrol?
We did in yeast and then in worms and then in flies.
And so the fly work, a couple of Brown University scientists, Mark Tater and Stephen Helphand,
did the fly work.
We did the worm work predominantly.
And that went into another science paper, I think 2005, 2004.
And what was exciting about those days was that here we had things as distant as a yeast
cell and a fly separated probably by 500 million years or more.
And we had a SIRT2 dependent drug lifespan extension, molecule lifespan extension, which
to me said that we're on to something interesting here.
Yep.
Remind me, what was the phenotype of the non-SIRT bearing organism?
Oh, now you're stretching my memory.
In flies, I don't recall there being a strong phenotype.
If you're asking where they really short lived.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's what I'm basically trying to get at is when you demonstrate the first proof of
concept, which is this drug won't work on you if you don't have SIRT.
In other words, I think where I'm really going with this is are there other plausible explanations
for how these compounds could have extended life outside of SIRT2?
Yeah, yeah, sure.
There's plenty of possibilities.
I mean, it could have just been that the SIRT2 ones were making them so sick that they
weren't.
But one of the reasons that we thought that it was real was that we tried to rule out
every other possibility.
We fed flies antioxidants, even if you got life-saving extension wasn't through the SIRT2
ones.
You can only make hypotheses and test them as best you can with the tools you have in
those days.
That's what we did.
But now we can actually go back and replace the SIRT2 mutant with this point mutation
that only knocks out changes one amino acid, which is real.
That's real microsurgery.
And when we do that and we go back now, we can still see a requirement for SIRT2 for
these effects.
So it was the mouse paper in 0506 that was the one that kind of brought this to everybody's
attention, even outside of the aging community, correct?
Right.
Well, so the resveratrol story in yeast was one thing.
But when the mouse paper came out in Nature in 2006, it went global and it caught the
attention of probably most people on the planet, certainly those who drank wine paid attention.
The wine industry sales, I'm told, went up 30 percent and have stayed up.
But yeah, that was 2006.
Very interesting time.
What's not well known in history is that we didn't know if this was going to work.
Was it real Hail Mary pass of experiment?
Going back to that experiment, those were not wild type mice.
Those were overfed mice, correct?
They were metabolically ill?
We had both experiments running in parallel.
But we got the results earlier for the fat mice.
And that was what?
So you had the control mice and you had the treatment mice, the control mice.
Both mice were fed the same, which was a sort of high fat, high sugar, metabolically disruptive
diet, presumably the usual.
Yeah, the so-called Western diet, correct?
Yeah.
So what was the outcome of that experiment?
How much longer did the resveratrol treated animals live, approximately?
I think it was 20 percent, something like that, 25 percent.
And that was initiated at what age?
A year.
So those are pretty mature mice.
They're middle-aged mice almost, right?
They're what, 30, 40 years old equivalent?
Exactly.
What dose, do you remember?
I'm going to guess, I think it was 200 milligrams per kilogram.
Per day.
But we also had a group on feeding every other day as well.
And those turned out to be pretty interesting as well.
That's a pretty high dose relative to, did the ITPs that came out that following used
doses that high?
So we've done it now in two different doses.
We've done 210 times less.
And it actually, it works in both.
And what we find actually is that the higher dose is acting on other pathways, including
the AMP kinase metformin-related pathway.
Activating it, so it's synergistic with metformin?
We don't know that, but part of the debate about resveratrol is that if you give cells
in culture or mice too much resveratrol, then it kicks in other pathways.
And in this case, it was activating AMP kinase as well.
We published that in our first paper in 2006 in the supplemental that most people haven't
read.
But we knew it was activating AMP kinase at that high dose.
And what that means is that when you're activating multiple pathways, it's very hard to dissect
that.
We these days, both in cell culture and in mice, were very careful to use the minimum
dose to get an effect, not overdose, because it just makes things much more complicated.
So you mentioned that you had a parallel experiment that was done in presumably mice that were
not overfed.
What did that experiment show?
So the fat mice, they were healthier.
That goes without saying, I think.
Most people know that.
In the thin mice, they also were healthier.
They had better cardiovascular system, less cancer, a whole variety of things that were
it didn't reach statistical significance when they ate resveratrol every day.
But if we gave it to them in their diet every other day, we saw a lifespan extension that
tells me a couple of things.
One is that it could be that being fed every other day kicks in some other pathways that
are helpful.
We don't know that for sure.
We'd be kicking in pathways that aren't helpful, wouldn't it?
If I understood you correctly, didn't you say that the mice, the non- so the lean, we're
going back to the lean experiment, if you fed the treatment animals resveratrol every
day, they did not have a statistically significant survival advantage.
If you fed them resveratrol every other day, they did.
Is that what you said?
Yeah.
So if you only give them food with resveratrol every second day, we had mice that were living
far longer than just the diet alone.
Were they being fed non- resveratrol food on the alternate days?
No, they were.
So they were calorically restricted.
Right.
Okay.
So there's now two variants.
So they could have been the caloric restriction that was extending their lives.
No, because the resveratrol added on to that as well.
So there was another control of just being fed every other day.
Exactly.
Right.
And that came out in a cell metabolism paper in 2008.
So from that experiment, one might conclude that resveratrol enhanced caloric restriction,
the response to CR.
It did.
Yeah.
So if you had a control group, a CR group fed every other day, and then a CR plus resveratrol
group, you would see a dose response.
And we did that.
And one of the things that might have been happening is that now resveratrol is not a
very potent molecule.
You've got things that are a thousand times more potent now.
But the other problem with resveratrol is that it's not very soluble.
And the blood levels, both in mice and in humans, doesn't get up very high unless you
eat some fat.
So that Western diet, we had much better absorption than this low dose lean diet.
And so it may have just been getting the drug on board, quote unquote, the drug, or it may
just be that resveratrol isn't potent enough, or that we're wrong about this.
But the reason I don't think we're wrong about the sirtuins is when you overexpress
the gene in the brain, for example, it will extend lifespan.
And other sirtuins do that as well.
Just going back to that, that's a very interesting idea about the fat solubility.
Was the experiment ever done where you took mice and you fed them with and without the
resveratrol?
Because presumably, it's not the solubility of the fat that they're eating.
It's the bile acids that enable the emulsification of the molecule and the, you know, whatever,
the jejunal absorption.
So that would be a quick way to show even without a hard outcome, if you were just getting
more into the cells, right, if the resveratrol had greater absorption with and without a
fatty food that's resulted in bile acids secretion.
Yeah, well, we didn't measure bile acids, but we could definitely see by measuring blood
levels that resveratrol was getting on board when we gave some fat in the food.
And that's true in humans.
That's why if I take resveratrol, I do it with something that's fatty.
So some oil, a yogurt, it works really well.
Got it.
Okay, well, that's elegant.
Okay, so then three studies come out thereafter.
Two of them were ITPs through NIA.
One was not.
You were on two of those papers, I believe.
And one of them, actually two of them were sort of looking at multiple molecules in testing,
correct?
And I think one of them, I thought it was odd because it looked at rapamycin, which
made sense, and then simvastatin, and then resveratrol.
I never understood the simvastatin part.
I wouldn't expect that a short-term treatment with simvastatin would have much of an outcome.
What did those studies find, the ITPs?
They just showed what we already published, which is that if you give resveratrol in regular
food, it doesn't extend lifespan.
And why couldn't that have been overcome?
That seems like they should have, given that you'd already, because you published years
in 06, these were like 08 and 11 or 11, 12, something like these were several years later.
Sure.
Yeah, those scientists didn't consult me at all.
They just put in the food and went for it.
I see.
So in parallel to this now, something really interesting happens, which is all of a sudden
a pharma company takes notice of something, which is resveratrol.
Was there an IND that gets filed on that, or was this a pure grass application, meaning
an FDA sort of generally regarded a safe pathway?
How was resveratrol taken into a clinical trial?
With humans, that is.
What was going on in the commercial side was screening of more molecules.
So there was a whole bunch of synthetic molecules that we can talk about.
Resveratrol itself was considered a proof of concept molecule largely.
If it ended up in the clinic, I mean, as a drug, it would have been great.
But what we're trying to do-
And your intuition was, it might be, it might not be.
Well, we knew it was a terrible molecule.
Because of the solubility alone.
Yeah, right.
But was it millimolar?
What kind of concentrations were needed once it was in the plasma to reach it?
Is it a micromolar or a millimolar?
It's a micromolar, which is, it really, that's not a drug you'd want to go ahead with.
But it allowed us to get into humans and see what would happen.
Do we see the same kinds of things?
Or could we deliver it on the skin or on the eye?
So that was our goal.
And there was some very good formulation chemists who were trying to, and succeeded in working
out ways to make resveratrol absorbable in the body.
And there were some clinical trials that were initiated under an IND.
There was one that was looking at blood sugar levels.
And that one, I think, is published now.
And what kind of doses were they using in the phase one?
Do you remember?
It was massive levels because the scientists that were running the studies, they were worried
that there wasn't enough about bioavailability.
So they were giving, I think, 10 grams a day, which is-
Was there any toxicity at 10 grams?
Unclear, unclear.
That there was some, in regular people, there was nothing.
There was a couple of patients in a cancer study that had renal failure, which happens
anyway in these late stage patients.
But that was enough to say, this is not worth it.
Because this is a blockbuster drug anyway.
It's a probe at best, at least according to the company that was running the trials.
So they exercised an abundance of caution and stopped that trial in the cancer patients.
That's odd.
Why was it being done in cancer patients?
Part of it was that trying to remember, but the person who was running the trials had
a lot of experience in it.
But I recall that there was some animal data, or at least some in vitro data, that was very
well could help there.
I see.
So I didn't actually realize that at all.
So you're saying it was in a phase one that they had this questionable outcome and thought,
well, maybe it's not worth pursuing this, and we'll move on to the second and third
generation variants of these?
Well, right.
So the company was bought by a large pharmaceutical company.
And a large pharmaceutical company looks at resveratrol and they say, this is not a drug.
This is not something that we want to continue with.
And so that was certainly part of the decision I'm imagining.
But what they really were excited about were the new chemical entities.
There were hundreds of them made, or very potent drug-like molecules that they wanted
to take further.
And they did take those into humans as well.
And I should mention that those molecules have been in mice.
And Rafael de Cabo deserves a lot of credit for doing that.
And so he's taken the same molecule that went into humans, put them into mice, these same
one-year-old mice, and found that those do live longer, even on a regular diet.
So that's why I think maybe it's just resveratrol wasn't as potent as we needed it.
And these other molecules succeeded.
Now, you mentioned, and I want to come back to this at the end, because it's interesting
you're one of the few people in this space who speaks openly about, look, in the presence
of incomplete information, I still take compound XY.
You alluded to a moment where you still take resveratrol.
Without having any certainty, is it your hypothesis that you might not be taking enough, but it's
unlikely that there's any harm?
And you said you take how much about a gram?
Well, so my calculation is this.
First of all, I like experimenting.
I'm not afraid of death, that's for sure.
But I want to be the first person to know if there's a problem.
I'm also keenly aware that what's going to happen to all of us if we don't do anything
is not pretty either.
And so what have I got to lose?
It's cheap.
I've got buckets of it in my basement.
There's been never any sign of toxicity.
It's been in humans for a long time now.
So there's no downside here.
But the bigger risk it would seem is, what if you're not taking enough?
Sure, but one gram, I think, if it's not working at a gram, then it's not working.
I don't think it's worth going higher.
What's important is that we've made advances since then.
We're talking about discoveries from a decade ago.
We've got much better things now.
So I still take my reserve role because I've seen enough data in humans as well
that it can protect the heart.
Is it going to make me live 10 years longer?
Probably not, not even five.
But will it potentially delay cardiovascular disease?
Absolutely.
You mentioned in a talk that you, I think you mentioned this in the talk,
but you take metformin as well.
Yeah, quite recently, probably at least half my colleagues that I talked to.
Yeah.
Now, you're only taking a pretty low dose, if I recall, from at least what you said in
that talk.
Is that because of the additive effects potentially of resveratrol also activating AMPK?
Yeah, you're exactly right.
If you're starting to take combinations of molecules like I do, you want to ramp it up.
We're going into unknown territory.
So I'm...
Especially if there's overlap in these pathways, right?
As you've alluded to.
There absolutely is overlap.
Anyone who says there isn't, is myopic or lying?
These are pathways that are additive.
So it could be that taking two grams of metformin plus, I'm taking two other molecules, would
be overdosing it.
And I don't want to do that.
So what I do is I start on a reasonable low dose based on all the data that I've read.
And then I make sure that I'm okay.
I feel okay.
My blood tests are okay.
And then I talk to the experts, they're all my friends, and I say, what do you think about
going up to?
One gram, one half gram.
So actually, recently I have gone up to one and a half grams, given advice from people
who shall remain nameless.
Yes, we'll keep everybody nameless.
So let's fast forward to some of these other molecules because this story is just so interesting.
And feel free to go back and patch pieces of history if it makes things to where we
are today.
But today we are in a place where there's a company, there are two companies out there
that are selling NR, precursor to NAD.
They're packaging it with, is it Terrestilbene?
Tell me what that molecule does specifically and why it would make sense to include that
with NR.
Yeah, so Terrestilbene is essentially just resveratrol with some methyl groups on it.
It's a more novel, sexier version of resveratrol.
But that's the...
But is it any more active, in your opinion?
So Lenny has told me that it is, but I don't know enough to be able to give a sensible
answer.
Okay.
So you now have a cert activator with an NAD precursor that are both basically over
the counter, right?
That's right.
So tell me about the excitement in that space.
I don't want to get too much into the politics of the companies because they're at the time
of this recording, they are in World War III.
So let's just talk about the science and not all the other stuff.
Yeah, well, if you take the 40,000 foot view of this...
So Lenny is in his 60s now and I'm in my 40s, very late 40s.
And you got to do a calculation, how many years do you have left to not only see what
happens but potentially even be vindicated.
And I'm sure that's part of what Lenny's thinking.
What would Lenny be vindicated for?
For finding that the sort of two ones are important for health, longevity, in humans.
Oh, I see.
Meaning that following this discovery, some of the air left the balloon and now there's
a resurgence of, hey, no, it really did matter.
Is that what you mean by being vindicated?
Well, I think there's a race to see whose pathway is more important.
Got it.
And the sort of two ones and M. Tor and Amy Kynace and some others are in this race.
I think it's a silly argument because they're all important and they talk to each other.
Yes.
But ego is involved and people want a legacy and Lenny's legacy, as I understand it, can't
speak for him directly, but is that he wants to have made a major contribution to human
health.
And this is a way of showing that within a timeframe that's reasonable, who wants to
wait another decade?
If I was him, I wouldn't want to.
And so I think that that was a good way of being able to quickly test the hypothesis
in an area that, going through the supplement route.
I, on the other hand, I think because I'd had the good experience with pharmaceuticals
and I also had more time to wait, I took that route.
And so the two of us are heading in parallel.
No, we're very good friends.
We talk all the time about this, but it's an interesting, from an historical perspective,
that we've got these two guys who are taking very different routes to what we hope has
achieved the same thing, which is to help people in the end.
And Elysium, obviously they've talked very publicly about their goal is to sort of provide
a supplement, but at a much higher quality, obviously in the United States.
I can't speak to this in the, in other countries, but the regulatory environment here is quite
unique in that basically the supplements are quite unregulated.
So you're sort of at the mercy of the person who's making the supplement.
And obviously having a number of Nobel laureates involved with a company like Elysium and a
commitment, a public commitment to use the highest quality stuff, at least a person can
buy this and say, look, I'm not getting crushed bird feathers, which I'm pretty much guaranteed
to be getting with half the stuff I buy online.
Look, I bring this up because I think half my patients are either taking Elysium's basis
or ... I can't remember the name of the other company, Chromadex, is that the other ... Yeah.
Half my patients are probably taking NR.
They always ask me, what do you think?
To which I say, I have no earthly clue.
I'm pretty sure it's safe.
So it passes the first test, which is I don't think it's hurting you.
One of the issues I've always struggled with is if it worked half as well as it works in
the mice, it shouldn't be subtle.
You showed in one of your talks an exercise, a contrast between two mice running on a treadmill,
and that was actually one of the milder successes.
That was like a 50% improvement in exercise tolerance.
I've seen other studies that talk about an 80% improvement in exercise tolerance.
If people were experiencing a 20% improvement in exercise tolerance, I believe we'd know
about it.
Do you feel that that's happening and we're missing it, or do you feel it's just not going
to be possible to elucidate that without a clinical trial, even though it's a supplement?
I get a lot of emails every day.
You might be the single most emailed person on this topic, I'm guessing, right?
Oh, yeah.
Wait till your book comes out.
Probably a thousand of them this week, actually, and I'm not exaggerating.
To any of you who've written to me, I'm sorry.
I just can't answer them all.
I will try.
One of the main questions is-
Well, hopefully by having this discussion, let's go as deep as you want into it so that
you can say, go listen to that discussion and you'll get all your nuanced points across.
Yeah, or go buy my book.
Even better.
That's coming out next year in 2019.
Do you have a title for it yet, by the way?
It's a tentative title.
Okay.
So at the time of this recording, people listening, we don't yet know the title, but David's book
will probably be out in the late summer, early fall of 2019.
That's right.
Okay.
Yeah, so I have some insights into this NAD world as it's developed.
It's extremely hot.
They're selling tons of the material, which is great.
That helps people.
Now I get a lot of emails from people who claim and they show me data that they used
to do races when they were 40 and then they now they're 60.
They can't win races.
They can't cycle, but they've gone on this or that in our product or even at a man and
now they're winning races again.
So these are stories I hear constantly every few days, but I can't judge those.
Because these are people I don't know.
There's no placebo.
But I think that some of this, if it were true, that's what we would expect.
If these molecules could help people, you would hear these anecdotes, which I hear.
But I can't declare that I know anything more than you, Peter, about this because they're
all anecdotes.
So that's why we're doing a human clinical trial.
Now you mentioned N-M-N a moment ago.
Can you tell us listening to this, the difference between NR, nicotinic riboside, which is a
one-step precursor to NAD and NMN?
Well, it's very simple.
So NR is converted by the body into NMN and then NMN is immediately converted to NAD.
So those are the steps.
So I misspoke.
I actually thought it was NR that was one step away from NAD and NMN went to NR, but
it's the other way around.
Correct.
Okay.
Both of these can be, we know definitively both of these can be brought into cells to
be used as cellular building blocks for NAD.
Is there any dispute about the ability to get from high plasma levels into the cell?
Yeah.
There's a debate.
It's not earth shattering.
It's very academic.
But yeah, we're debating in the field about which molecule gets transported and which
one doesn't.
And NR definitely gets transported.
The question is, does any NMN get in transported?
And I believe you've written, and I think I read in one of your review articles, perhaps,
but it could have been somebody else's, that NMN might be slightly more stable than NR.
Well, we find that in a lab that if we put them in solution on the bench or leave them
on the shelf, that NMN is more stable than NR.
That's why I keep my molecules and lab's molecules in the freezer just to give them
some extra shelf life.
And did you imply by what you said a moment ago that there is no dispute that NR at least
gets, if you have a high plasma level of NR, it is brought into the cell?
Is that diffusion mediated?
Is that transported?
There's a transporter for NR.
There's evidence that there's an NR transporter.
But either way, they both raise NAD levels quite effectively in the body, in humans as
well.
And I'm sorry, I know I asked this already, but when you say they raise NAD levels, you
mean mitochondrial NAD levels or cytoplasmic NAD levels?
Oh, gee.
Most of these studies have been done on whole cells from blood or tissue.
So they're just like PBMCs or something like that?
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
The problem with that is that it's a very dynamic system.
This isn't a regular drug that just hangs around and you can measure it.
This is actively utilized by the body.
So even if it disappears into some pathway, it's still probably being recycled.
So we have to be very careful not to jump to conclusions.
If you don't see it in the blood, maybe it was taken up by the muscle or the brain.
So these are the studies that are ongoing now.
And if you see it in the PBMC, it doesn't mean it made it into the hepatocyte.
Right.
This is all just in an animal you can do that.
We're starting to do those experiments in humans right now using NMR to be able to
measure NAD levels in living tissue.
And when you say NMR, do you mean like MRS or like?
Yes.
Okay.
I do.
So phosphorus, MRS.
Yeah.
And you can measure ATP, NAD.
Right, right.
So those are really powerful and you can actually now do it with seven Tesla magnets with people
in the machine while they're exercising.
So that's where we're headed with this in our next clinical trial, hopefully.
In your intuition, David, if you could cherry pick the hierarchy with where you'd want to
see the upregulation of NAD most, which cells would you preferentially be directing it into?
Well, it depends on the...
If we want to treat a disease, obviously we've got to target that particular tissue.
So if we're treating a mitochondrial disorder of the muscle, obviously the muscle, for longevity,
I would want it to definitely get into all tissues if possible.
I think it would help if it could get into the hypothalamus where there's some central
regulation.
But what the field has discovered is that all these tissues, not all, but many of these
major tissues are secreting proteins that can induce longevity.
So I wouldn't want to prioritize unless we're talking about a particular disease like liver
disease or muscle wasting.
One of the things David Sabatini and I talk a lot about, I'm actually going to see David
for dinner tonight and I'm sure this will come up, is if you could wave a magic wand
and make rapamycin, for example, tissue specific, let alone complex specific.
But you get into this.
And the same thing with metformin.
It probably does have some tissue specificity, probably working more in the liver than it
is working in other cells.
It seems unlikely that a molecule would have uniform and ubiquitous take-up of all cells,
right?
Of course, yeah.
So with NAD, we don't know.
We're basically still in the infancy of knowing where the NR or NMN would be preferentially
taken up.
The MRS studies would help us understand that.
So that's going to help.
And the reason I qualified that statement was that we're still getting approval for
these studies, but that's the plan.
But also there are labs that I'm aware of who I think shall remain nameless as well
for to protect their own confidentiality, but they are working on tracer studies to
be able to give NR and NMN and see where it goes in the body and be able to measure each
tissue.
That we'll know probably within the next six months to a year.
So you mentioned that what Elysium or Chromadex are doing is using ... They're just basically
in a different regulatory paradigm, which is they're using molecules that are generally
regarded as safe.
They're outside of these IND pathways.
You're interested in the same sort of targets, but you're going to go down ... I don't want
to say more rigorous, but it is more rigorous.
Let's call this my spade.
You're going down a much more rigorous pathway.
It's more expensive, that's for sure.
Yeah.
I mean, literally two logs more expensive, if not three logs more expensive.
I want to be sensitive to any confidentiality because that's the nature of the work that
you're doing now.
But what can you tell us about the molecules you're working on directly and indirectly
in that space?
Sure.
In the NAD space, there's a couple of companies.
One is ... I can go of old is called Metro Biotech, which is here in Massachusetts.
And they work on ... They've been working for five years on making NAD precursor molecules
that are better than these two that are available publicly.
And there are ways to improve them.
Better bioavailability, better stability, better efficacy.
And those are moving into the clinic as well.
And then there's another company called Jumpstart Fertility, which is both here in Massachusetts
and down in Australia.
And we're finding really great effects of these molecules on female infertility or low
fertility.
And that's something we're going to be publishing shortly.
And is there a type of infertility that this seems most amenable to?
Because going back to your evolutionary argument, under periods of stress, we see fertility
as one of the first things to go for obvious reasons.
But infertility comes in so many flavors, right?
There could be an inability to release an egg.
There can be aneuploidy.
Even when the eggs are secreted, there can be uterine hostility.
There's so many things that can result in infertility.
What does this particular thing target?
Well, so what we find in the biochemical pathway we've figured out, and we published a little
bit on this, is that there's a protein called BabR1, which is a kinase that regulates spindle
quality.
And one of the problems with old eggs is that they don't have nice spindles and they rip
their chromosomes apart when they...
Hence the aneuploidy.
Exactly.
So down syndrome, et cetera, abortion, aborted fetuses.
But what we found is that this BabR1 is regulated by the SRT2 protein, which requires NAD.
And what we think is going on after chemotherapy or during aging is that the levels of NAD
in the ovary and in the egg are low and it's getting this aneuploidy.
And that explains why when we give NAD to...
Or any precursors to eggs in vivo, the eggs come out healthier, more numerous, and are
much better at allowing for fertilization and healthy offspring.
I don't know much about fertility as this next question will illustrate, but presumably
you can still see aneuploidy on the male side.
So is there a male fertility opportunity here as well?
I realize it's not as probably as common a problem, but presumably you still have to
have a perfect split of the chromosome in the sperm.
Yeah.
Possibly.
It's an area that we're looking into.
I don't have anything solid enough to be able to say if it works or not, but in theory, yeah.
And you just went back to something earlier.
Is NMN available over the counter?
It is.
More recently I can see it on the internet.
Okay.
But one of the things that I want to bring up is you can find my name all over these
products.
Not basis.
They're reputable, but there are others that use my name all over the place.
Meaning without your permission.
Correct.
And Harvard's permission.
And so I've sent more cease and desist letters than you can imagine, and they keep popping
up.
So that's an important point.
So if a listener after this talk is saying, hey, David Sinclair sounds like a smart, reputable
guy.
If his name's on something, I should take it.
What can your name be associated with right now that is with your permission?
Nothing.
Okay.
So basically anything that's out there that's over the counter that has your name on it
is not endorsed by you.
Correct.
Okay.
Thank you for clarifying that.
Great.
Yeah, it is.
But I try to stay above the fray.
It's nice when you can stand on Harvard's shoulders and let their lawyers send those
cease and desist letters.
It would be nice if that were true when I spend a portion of my salary every year on
this.
Really?
That's a shame.
I'm sorry to hear that.
So fertility is a super interesting angle.
I would have never thought about that.
That strikes me as highly testable as well, which one of the challenges of longevity research,
as you know better than I do, is if you want to make claims in humans, you better buckle
up because it's going to be ... I mean, it's almost untestable.
So when you look at what other companies are doing, like Restore Bio going down the mTOR
pathway, they're not going after longevity, right?
They're going after very, very specific indications that are testable in shorter periods of time
in a respiratory failure, things like that.
What are the other disease states that you think would be most exciting if you don't
already have plans to go down that from your pharmacologic standpoint?
Well, we've been targeting diseases that are rare and have a high unmet need.
So I can't divulge all of those because that's company stuff.
But the fertility part, that's very clear.
I'm able to tell you that those trials will begin next year in IVF clinics.
And that will be the first time a doctor looks at those eggs from a woman.
She'll probably know that it's working or not.
So that's very clear.
So it's a company ... So we're sitting right now in a headquarters that is the name of
... What's it called?
Is it Life Bioscience?
Yes.
And that's a parent company or sort of ... Tell me how that fits into a number of the scientific
entities that you're involved in.
So Life Bioscience is a family of companies that uses shared resources and knowledge.
There are eight of us right now that work on different aspects of aging, not just NAD
biology, but the usual suspects.
All the major hallmarks of aging that we could list off.
Each one of these companies has world leaders and drug development programs in that so that
we think we can, quote unquote, conquer aging from different aspects.
But together we're stronger as one unified company, Life Biosciences.
Earlier you spoke about sort of eight or nine central tenets of aging.
We've covered some of them, and I'm guessing that your book is going to go into this in
greater detail.
But can you rehash what you ... Or at least as many of those as you're going to recall
on the spot, not to put you on the spot.
That's a long list.
Yeah, sure.
There's epigenetic changes, cells of cell communication and inflammation.
Let me count this.
Analytics, so senescent cells build up.
There's protein misfolding.
There's telomere loss and genomic instability.
There's metabolic changes.
So MP kinase and metformin would address that.
And then there's responses to what we call amino acids and other nutrient inputs.
And those collectively go awry during aging.
But what causes all of those to happen?
That's something that we've been working on for quite a while.
And you think those are more coupled than they are uncoupled, those pathways?
Or do you think that ... I mean, there are clearly situations in which external stressors
can perturb more than one of those.
But senescence seems somewhat uncoupled from nutrient sensing, doesn't it?
It may.
And I'm not asking that rhetorically.
I just don't know.
Well, no.
The answer is we think that we've found an explanation for all of these things to happen.
A unifying theory?
Right.
So I've kept it close to my vest for a number of years.
But it actually goes all the way back to the Sirtuin story in yeast.
And hopefully the listeners who've stuck with this podcast are still with us because this
is the punchline.
I promise you they are with us.
So the punchline is that ... So this is all off the top of my head here.
We haven't published this yet, but I'm going to tell you my thoughts and your listeners.
So the genome is digital information.
It's very easy to preserve.
It's the reason we went from analog to digital in the 2000s.
DNA is four letters.
It's digital.
It's easy to replicate.
It's easy to store.
You can boil it.
It's very robust.
What we've actually come to discover is that the genome is fairly intact in old people
and old animals.
We've sequenced the genomes of lots of old mice.
And all the genes are still largely intact.
So what's going wrong?
Well, the other part of information that you inherit from your parents is the epigenetic
information.
And I use that term loosely, but basically it means what's the pattern of gene expression,
which genes are turned on and off at which time.
And that is analog information.
That has to be analog because instead of just being a single code, it has to operate
in three dimensions, actually four if you count time.
And so that's an analog system.
And it's constantly adapting to what we eat, what we drink, if we run, when we sleep.
And you have to turn genes on and off all the time.
But that pattern of gene expression that's set down when we're young, because it's analog,
analog information doesn't last very long.
Anyone who's had a record player or magnetic tape knows that these things don't last.
And that's the problem, I think, with aging, is that we don't lose the digital information.
So the compact disk of our lives is still intact when rolled.
But it's as if we've got a scratched CD and the cells don't read the right genes at the
right time anymore.
And they lose their identity.
In fact, if we, there's an analogy, which is called Waddington's landscape, where in
the 1950s, Waddington grew a picture.
It's a beautiful picture of some hills.
It's a mountainscape.
And cells actually roll down the mountainscape and land in different valleys down below.
And that's to, before he had access to the genome, that was his way of saying, this is
how cells know what they are.
They land in these valleys and they stay there.
But what I think is happening during aging is due to the vibration of noise over time,
we lose that pattern of gene expression.
We lose that information, genetic information.
And those cells or those marbles in Waddington's landscape, they jump over into different
valleys and lose their identity.
So your neurons are not functional like neurons anymore.
Your liver cells are more like neurons.
And we see that in our lab.
We're just writing up a couple of papers right now for this.
And we're able to actually manipulate the epigenome in cells and in mice and have a
look what happens to those animals.
And the prediction is that you get all the hallmarks of aging.
The challenge with this entire space is you think back to the time in the 1950s when he
created that analogy.
And in some ways, it's amazing that it could still be relevant 75, 80 years later, whatever
it is.
On the other hand, it humbles you to realize how much more has been learned about that
process in that time.
And sometimes I think about it because you and I are interested in the same problem that
I'm worried I just don't know anything.
I'm worried that in 10 years I'll look back at my hypotheses and my, or not even my hypothesis,
just my understanding of the current state of the art today and think, you know what,
that was directionally right, but it was so oversimplified.
And oh my goodness, like, you know, so it's sort of like we're back in this problem of
time.
Like we're going to run out of time.
And I mean, how confident are you that in, because you and I are almost the same age,
how confident are you that in our lifetime we will see step function changes in human
longevity?
And to put this in context, there really hasn't been a step function change in human longevity
probably since the introduction of sanitation.
I mean, everything has been quite incremental, maybe antibiotics, vaccinations, antibiotics
have probably been the last step function change.
Will we see one in our lifetime?
How confident are you?
I'm getting more and more confident.
Honestly, when I started in this field, I thought we'd probably not see the type of
technologies that I'm seeing now.
It's making my head spin, not just in the technologies, but also the investment and
the number of people working on this now.
This was the back order of biology when we started.
And there's been some new results, which I'll just hint upon because we haven't published
and it's very early, but I've seen, it sounds like a scene out of Blade Runner, but I've
seen things you wouldn't believe.
It's maybe not that dramatic, but let me go back to the compact disk analogy.
You've got the scratched CD.
How do you find the polish?
What is that?
Let's go back to the yeast analogy.
What causes those scratches?
Why do you get loss of gene regulation?
Anyone who was paying attention earlier on in this conversation will remember that these
DNA breaks in the chromosome, broken chromosomes, distract the CER complex and they move away
and you get the expression of genes that have no right being on.
Because the CER-2-1s have lost, they're distracted from the deactivation function and they're
dealing with the repair function.
Exactly.
So using that, what we've got a lot of evidence for now is that something very similar, if
not essentially identical in principle, happens in mammals as we age.
What that means is that insults to the genome, and one of the major insults is a double strand
break, but there are probably others, cause these proteins, CER-2-1s and other factors,
I'm not saying only CER-2-1s, but factors that control gene expression, silencing and
other things, have a dual role, we know, in DNA repair and other things, such as responding
to stresses, heat, whatever.
But this is the cell's way of coordinating gene expression changes, hunkering down during
times of adversity and going off to repair the system, which in this case we study DNA
breaks.
And that's a beautiful system when you're young.
It works great.
You get exposed to cosmic rays, you go out in the sun, you've got lots of DNA breaks,
eventually these proteins will go, repair those breaks, and then go back to where they
came from to settle down the response, to turn off the inflammation, to turn off the
DNA repair when it's not needed.
But the problem we think is it's antagonistic pleiotropy.
Okay, so Peter Medawar and the other brilliant scientists in the 50s speculated, I think
correctly is that things that are really good for you when you're young come back to bite
you in the ass when you're older.
And I think that's what's happening here is that this response to these stresses like
a break end up not just distracting these proteins, but end up disrupting the actual
structure of our chromatin.
And these proteins don't always go back to where they came from 100%.
Do that for 70 or 80 years.
And it's not surprising that the genes that were once perfectly programmed and turned
on at the right time, lose their ability to do that.
And we've got remnants of that program when we're 70 and 80.
What's exciting is that information is still there to be accessed.
The question is, how do you get the cells to remember to access at the right time?
What's that polish?
And I think we're pretty close to finding that.
If you had unlimited resources, and not just financial resources, but metaphysical resources,
like any experiment would be ethical.
You could do something that today no IRB would approve.
Is there an experiment that you would wish to see done that could accelerate our knowledge
in this space log fold?
That would mean staying within ethical boundaries.
For example, to do a human experiment in longevity would be ethical, but impractical
because of the duration of time.
But if I gave you a time machine and an infinite amount of resources, tell me what the most
elegant experiment you can think of that would, again, just leapfrog our knowledge.
So the experiment that needs to be done, whether it's with metformin or other drugs in development,
including these raphologs and the NAD precursors, is to take a group of 5,000 people.
That would be sufficient.
And just give them the medicine and wait three, four years.
And you'd know from that number of people that you're changing the hazard ratio, the
mortality rate.
You'd have to start with people probably in their 70s.
I think that was the calculation that I did.
But you don't need to wait a whole lifetime to know that these things work.
So this is basically Nier's argument.
Yeah, exactly.
Nier's not doing mortality as much as he's doing health span.
But it's exactly right.
You do enough people.
I mean, it's going to cost tens of millions of dollars.
But think of the trillions of dollars that would be saved if we can prove this.
But if I'm going to play devil's advocate for a moment, what if by doing that experiment,
we are missing the opportunity, the window of opportunity for these drugs to act?
In other words, we know that caloric restriction is less and less effective the longer you
wait in the organism, at least within mice.
And that's what made rapamycin so interesting is it blew everybody away that you could start
this drug on mice that were 600 days old and they still had 9%, 14% increase in lifespan.
If you had more time, do you think we could get a more clear answer starting earlier?
Acknowledging that you'd have to wait longer if you wanted to use a hard outcome.
Do you worry that we would risk doing this in people in their eighth decade that it might
not work, but that just tells us that it doesn't work late, not that it doesn't work
period?
I don't worry about that.
We could, with enough capital and money invested, we could do multiple different experiments.
We could do people in their 50s, 60s, 70s, and 80s.
So dream with me.
The other thing that makes me optimistic is it's not just rapamycin that works late in
life.
We've got results in my lab now that we'll be publishing that if we start even later
than 600 days in a mouse, which is what, closer to a 75-80?
We can still extend lifespan.
Using what?
I know you won't name the company.
No, I can tell you.
We're using the NMN.
So there are multiple ways to act late in life.
When you use NMN in the lab, are you also using a PT analog or a resveratrol analog?
Are you able to just use NMN and see?
Just the natural molecule will work.
We're now gearing up to do the drug subjects.
This is not in high-fat, over-fed animals.
This is in wild-type animals.
We just put it in there drinking water.
Oh, because NMN is more soluble.
Exactly.
Interesting.
Yeah, but we've got better molecules that we're now testing.
We think that we can beat, or again, try to beat, rapamycin and maybe a combination together.
Do you think there's overlap in those pathways?
Yeah, yeah.
We're both thinking the same thing.
We want to do the combination.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And I want to take the combination one day.
Well, we now actually have some early data.
I don't want to scoot myself, but we're able to now genetically modify adult mice with
AAV, the virus, the endosociative virus.
And we can now genetically change a mouse.
So we've just put in all seven sort of genes into mice, in old mice.
You've put the seven human sort genes into mice.
Seven mouse genes into the mouse.
But that sort of experiment would have taken a decade to do just a few years ago, but now
that we can deliver genes, we can do very good experiments.
Not only that, we can also do multiplexed.
We can do combinations of genes and combinations of molecules.
So even experiment.
Yeah, you're stacking the matrix now.
Well, yeah.
I mean, we should be doing this.
It's just a matter of resources.
But I think we're now at a point in the aging community where these combinations need to
be tested.
It's the question that's on everybody's mind.
What happens if you put them in combination?
Are they better or worse together?
And so what we've done is we've put all seven sort of genes into a mouse and fed them some
man-to-man to give them the fuel and the genetic requirement.
And interestingly, there are additive effects when you do both of those things.
And this is how we're able to see these dramatic effects in these old mice.
So is your optimism towards the NAD precursor space and these two inactivating space equivalent?
And do you see them as necessarily parallel paths?
They have different uses.
The NAD is where I'm mostly focused on now.
And is that because of the observed age-related decline in NAD?
In part, but it's also because in theory, all of the seven Sirtuins should be good.
And their lack of NAD could be the main problem that's going on in older people.
And so the idea is that instead of just activating one Sirtuin, which is what resveratrol did,
we think, you can potentially activate all seven of them and replenish what's been lost
over time.
And I think seven is probably better than one.
You mentioned at the outset of this discussion that you were four years old when you became
aware of mortality.
Was there something that occurred that made you aware of mortality at such a young age?
I had an unusual grandmother who was brutally honest with me.
She would never lie.
And any question I asked, I was quite...
And you were probably very precocious and curious.
I suppose I was.
But yeah, she would never lie.
So my question that most kids have is, are you always going to be around?
She didn't even...
She didn't call her grandma.
She wanted to use her first name, which is Vera.
So Vera, you're always going to be around.
Of course not.
I'm going to die.
Yeah, but what about mom and dad?
Yeah, they're going to die.
What about my cat?
It's going to die.
And then of course you're thinking, if they're all going to die, what's going to happen to
me?
But it turns out all kids go through this.
It's been studied extensively that between the ages of four and seven, kids understand
that there's death.
And at first they're in denial.
They're saying, well, maybe those adults will die, but my teachers and my parents, they're
not going to die.
But then by age seven, it's undeniable.
All kids know that everything around them that's living at one day will die, including
themselves.
But what's very interesting that happens at age seven is it's buried deep in the subconscious.
You very rarely think about it until you have to, because I don't think as a species we
could get by for all running around, oh my God, we're going to die one day.
So seven-year-olds onward till about 50, you try not to think about it.
That's pretty common.
You start looking at yourself in the mirror at 50.
You notice your teeth are wearing out.
You feel a little bit of age.
You see some wrinkles.
You think, oh, yeah, crap.
This is really happening.
And you think more and more about it.
I'm unusual because I work on this every day.
So I'm always thinking about it.
But I think on average, when I talk to people, especially in their 20s and 30s, it's not
something that is on their radar because it's going to be something that happens in a
distant future that they're not even looking at.
Do you have kids?
I have three.
How old are they?
They are 15, 13 and 11.
How do you explain what you do to them?
I was just as brutal to them as my grandmother was to me.
Yeah.
And actually I saw my oldest daughter go through this, actually all my kids, but it
was more dramatic to see it for the first time myself.
And I gave a TED Talk about this.
When I told her that I was going to die, she burst out crying and for a week couldn't
sleep.
It was traumatic.
And, you know, maybe I'm a cruel parent, but I also try not to BS my kids either.
But what I saw with her was what even I think most kids do, including myself was, you
just can't think about it.
It drives you not, you won't sleep.
So she forgot about it and we've never talked about it ever again.
And if I talk about death, she says, shut up.
Don't want to hear about it.
And she probably won't think about it in a big way until I'm old or her grandparents
are dying.
David, this has been a really interesting discussion.
I want to be sensitive to your time.
I think the listeners of this podcast will be upset to know that we're only going for
about, you know, an hour and 40 minutes instead of the usual three or four hours.
But where can people find you on social media and how do you like to interact with
people that have questions besides adding to the list of the thousands of emails you
get a day?
Yeah, emails.
I can't reply to everyone, but on social media, I'm now on social media.
I find that's a good way to communicate with people.
And so I have a Twitter handle, which is David Asyncler.
And I'm also on LinkedIn, but we're putting together a social media page so we can have
a discussion.
It's now there's so many people interested in this.
Yeah.
And the information that's locked in my head seems to be on demand.
So that's how I want to reach people.
This book is coming out, which has me regurgitating and vomiting on the page, everything
from what we've learned in my life with my kids all the way through to understanding why we
age in this universal hypothesis that we're putting, I'm putting forward.
And then the consequences of what happens when we do this.
Now, it's not a question of if anymore.
It's a when it's going to happen.
What happens to planet earth?
What happens to humanity?
What happens to your family as this starts to come out?
And some good, some bad, what do you have to get ready for economically, socially?
And it's all going to be in there.
Well, I really look forward to reading it.
You know, I'm in the midst of writing a book as well.
And I'm guessing you struggled with the same thing I'm struggling with, which is not just
the writing of it, but more importantly, you almost don't want to hand the thing in
because you know that the day you hand it in, there's something new that you're going to
want. You're going to know something more.
And so as we were talking about it before we started the podcast, like you submit these
books a full year before they hit the press.
And then, of course, it basically is a static document until, you know, sure, you could
have an online updated to information.
But did you struggle with that?
Especially, I think, you know, people like us, I think, have a little bit of a humility
around the half life of facts.
And that's that sounds like a very sort of pompous thing for us to say.
But I just think we have the luxury of knowing that basically whatever we know today is, you
know, quite likely to not be entirely true tomorrow.
How did you cope with that?
This is now just a very personal question for me as I'm struggling with this phenomenon.
Well, yeah, you're a perceptive guy, Peter.
So I'm also one of those guys that I'm at the podium about to give a talk to a thousand
people. I'm still changing my PowerPoint slides.
I'm just obsessed with perfection.
And that's one of my downfalls.
Same thing with the book.
I've been writing it for 10 years and it's needed updating, of course, even to the point
that last night I was editing it.
I've already turned it into my editor three weeks ago.
You're a nightmare to the editor.
And she's received probably seven updates already.
And I'm going to stop.
I promised. But every time I wake up, there's something more really interesting to add that I
want to put in there.
And, you know, a year from now, I think it's going to be an even better book than it is now.
But I'm really happy with everything I've gotten down on the page.
Because when I talk to people, people write to me every day, unable to answer questions that I
think are burning in a lot of people's minds.
Well, David, this has been great.
I find it sometimes hard to talk to people you don't know until the day of the podcast, which is
the case here. But I found there's a common language that we that we speak or maybe a common
passion, not a common language.
This is a topic that's new to me.
But anyway, this has been really exciting and I can't thank you enough for your time.
Well, I appreciate the opportunity and I really enjoyed it too.
Thanks.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com.
What's a nerd safari, you ask?
Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week email where
I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read and all things
related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but
usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing or other professional health care services,
including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnosis or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have
and should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my
disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.