Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode of The Drive. This week I had two guests.
This was a first. I've never interviewed two people simultaneously, which is not to say
it's rocket science. I think a monkey can figure it out. And I'm at least as good as
a monkey, so I was able to figure it out. But it did stress me out a little bit because
I was trying to figure out how do you keep two people engaged. But it seems like we did
a pretty good job and I think you'll enjoy this episode.
My guests were two guys who I just referred to as the Brothers Bell, but they're obviously
known more commonly by their actual names, Mark Bell and Chris Bell. Some of you may
recognize these guys, especially if you're interested in powerlifting or if you've ever
paid attention to some really interesting documentaries, in particular, Bigger Stronger
Faster, which was sort of the breakout performance for Chris Bell. That is, I believe, a documentary
that if you look at all of its downloads on Netflix would certainly put it in kind of
the top 10 docs of the last decade. I could be wrong on that, but I feel like I remember
reading that somewhere. Prescription Thugs was also a follow-up documentary. And there
are a number of others, including one that is in the works at the time of this recording
that we'll link to as well. His brother, Mark Bell, his younger brother, is an absolute
legend in the world of powerlifting and he owns a number of records, all of which are
staggering and we'll get into those during the episode. This was also a bit of a first
for me in that it was the first time I interviewed people I didn't know personally. So obviously
I'd communicated with Mark and Chris through email a bunch leading up to this, but I didn't
have a rapport with them in the way that I've had with every person I've interviewed to
date, which actually is a little harder. You have to pay a bit more attention when you're
doing your homework. So I hope that doesn't come across as being strained. I don't think
it did. I think we were definitely getting along well and having fun. The other thing
that may or may not come across here is we were exhausted. We did this interview up at
a place that Mark Bell was renting for the month up in Malibu. And so I went up there
and they interviewed me for their documentary slash podcast. And it took about three hours
and 15 minutes. We took about 45 minutes off to play patty cakes and grab ass and eat.
And then I proceeded to interview them for about two hours. So I think by the end of
that two hours, we were all collectively exhausted. So that may or may not come across. Anyway,
all those caveats aside, this was a super interesting podcast because what I really
wanted to talk about was not just their stories and their lives, which I think are very interesting
and touch on so many of these themes that I've become quite interested in. If you've
seen either Bigger Stronger Faster or Prescription Thugs, you'll know that their older brother
Mike died. And they talk about that quite openly in this podcast. And it's actually
quite, it's quite touching and it's actually quite emotional. Chris gets kind of emotional
at one point during this and it's sort of palpable in the room as we're talking about
it. They talk a lot about their parents, their upbringing. I obviously am completely
fascinated as to what kind of upbringing could produce such remarkable human specimens and
they are remarkable human specimens. Let's make no mistake about that. I also get into
some of the details about like their training and very fascinating to understand like how
relatively low volume their training was and yet how it produced such remarkable achievements.
So I guess I would say the following. If you've never heard of these guys and you're
not that interested in powerlifting or strength training, I still think you will find this
interesting though there may be some parts you want to fast forward through once we get
into the technical details of some of their lifts. If you have any interest in strength
training, you're going to want to get to know a lot about these guys. And one of the things
I actually learned in the interview, I hadn't even done enough homework before the interview
to know this is the YouTube channel that Mark Bell has, which I've since looked at and it's
an incredible resource for someone who is trying to learn how to do the major lifts
correctly. So without further ado, here is my interview with Mark and Chris Bell.
Mark, Chris, thank you so much for making time to talk to me about this kind of stuff
today. Thank you. You know, this is kind of unusual for me. It's two firsts. It's the
first time I've interviewed two people simultaneously and also interviewed people that I don't know
much prior to this, but I kind of feel like I know you guys for you. Please do. You can
only interview one person at a time. Oh, you've learned this during the documentary.
It's just the way it is. So if we both talked at the exact same time, then this would not
work. Could be trouble. We will try to keep that in mind, but I do feel like a kind of
know you guys, which is weird. That's I'm sure something that you guys have experienced
before when someone's watched one of your films or seen a documentary that you've been
in or a part of, and it's sort of like they meet you and they sort of think they know
something about you, right? It's like, well, I know what this guy's all about because he
said XYZ. And so I'll try to free myself up from that. I get a lot of hugs because of
it. People like, I feel like I know you. Can I give you a hug? Yeah. It just depends on
who it is, whether or not I like that or not. When people do that, what are they thanking
you for? Because I'm sure people do thank you a lot. It's a really bizarre thing. I
never thought anybody would thank me for like making a movie, but I guess it's had
a profound effect on their life. So they say, thank you for making that with my film, Prescription
Thugs, for example. A lot of people will see that and realize, oh, you know, I have an
opioid problem. I have a drug problem and they'll go do something about it. So I think
with Bigger, Stronger, Faster is like more getting off your ass and going to do something
with your life and wanting to be somebody. You know, that's something that I think is
really important to a lot of people trying to prove that you're not just another bum
from the neighborhood.
And the thing about Bigger, Stronger, Faster that I found so appealing and surprising,
and I think that's, I would guess, at least part of the reason why 10 years later it's
still endured, is the vulnerability of it. You didn't hide your own issues, your family's
struggles. I'm sure I'm not the first person to say this, but your parents come across
as like the two most lovable people on the planet. Like I actually didn't have the urge
to hug you, but if I walked in here and saw your mom, I would absolutely have to give her
a big hug. You know what I mean?
Yeah, absolutely.
Was that designed or did you, that just happened by accident that you realized, hey, I'm just
going to show my family.
It was really weird. When we did the movie, we had a lot of great people helping out.
My philosophy is like, go find the best people and do it. So like, if you're going to make
a documentary, I was like, who's, who's a good documentary filmmaker? Oh, Michael Moore,
he's won an Oscar for Bowling for Columbine. I thought Bowling for Columbine was one of
the best, whether you agree with the politics of it or not, that's not the point. The point
is it's one of the best written documentaries I've ever seen. And I actually won an Academy
Award for the writing of it and it really inspired me. And I just said, I want to make
a movie about steroids, so I want to adopt the same style. So I watched Bowling for Columbine.
I literally wrote out every scene from Bowling for Columbine and then tried to define what
that would be if it was about steroids, like what that particular scene would be. And in
doing that developed like this style. And then I actually brought people in that worked
on that movie. So the editor of Bowling for Columbine was an editor and a help on our
movie as well. And that's sort of how I got into making the movie about steroids. That's
how I approached it was getting the best people and putting them in the right spot. So I had
learned a lot like in the course of making the movie as well. Well, he directed the cameras
at us once he started to get into some of the basics of the film. I think for a long
time you were kicking around the idea of he knew that there's something magical about
Gold's Jim Venice. And he knew something was magical about a lot of the things that we're
doing the environment we're in. But it wasn't until he got into some of the actual ideas
of what the film ended up becoming to where he started running through these different
scenarios with his producers. And he's like, yeah, you know, my brother's you know, my
brother Mark does this my brother Mike, you know, he was doing that. And you know, I did
this and they were like, wait, hold on a second. Your brothers are taking steroids right now.
And he's like, yeah. And he's like, they're like, that's we need to we need to get that
on film. Yeah. And the point I was getting to is those people that worked on these other
great movies were the ones that defined that to me. So when I was on the phone with my
producer Alex Bono, I was like, Hey, you know, you know, my brother's Mark's on steroids
and Mike's on steroids and I'm in the middle and I'm just trying to figure it out. And
as soon as I said that, he was like, that's the movie right there. That's exactly what
the movie is. It's like you're the middle brother and you're conflicted whether or not
you should take these drugs or not, regardless of whether you've tried them in the past,
you tried them once you felt a little guilty. Let's just tell that story. And what I found
is in making films, just being honest and telling the actual real story that's going
on is the best place to be. Right now we're embarking on a documentary about nutrition
and I keep going back to like, keep trying to manufacture what the movie should be in
my head. And I'm like, going back to it should just be what is going on right now. What exactly
is going on right now? I'm conflicted about my diet. I don't know how I should eat. I'm
trying to find answers and that's really what it should be. The most honest representation
of that and not a representation of like, here's what I think about the ketogenic diet
and here's why you have to do it. And so by taking this approach, I think it's allowed
us to be pretty open minded about the whole thing. There's something about that movie
also that I've watched it obviously probably half a dozen times, if not more. And each
time I see it, I'm struck by this feature, which is the empathy with which you approach
people. Even when I think the viewer can tell, like you don't necessarily agree. So
I'm blanking on the boy's name, but the high school kid who'd killed himself. That's right.
When you spoke with his father, that's a very touching scene because if you're watching
that purely through the lens of what the research and the data would say, it's pretty clear
that steroids probably had nothing to do with that tragedy. And that boy might've ended
up in that situation with or without steroids. But at the same time, I think if I were doing
that interview, I worry that I would have come across as condescending or like a no
at all. But I was very touched by the fact that that wasn't at all the case.
Yeah, you didn't press the issue at all. The guy just said it. The guy said steroids had
nothing to do with my son's death. And that was that. And I thought it was spectacular
as well when you're watching it, like that interviewer right there, even though it's
my brother, he had an opportunity to kind of jump on that guy. Like, wait a second,
how could you say that? But it never goes any further than that. And it shouldn't need
to ask the beauty because you were able to sort of look, there are people where you can
cross examine them, but you don't cross examine the father who's lost his son. Like there's
there's absolutely no role for that. And so there's a certain level of civility that I
think there were other questions where I'm like, there's I think other ways to approach
it, right, rather than go, I'm going to jump down his throat, say, well, why don't I just
pose a question to him that is comparative, saying like, Hey, look, your son died from
steroids. That's what you're saying. That's what you're telling me. He died from steroids.
But also like, you know, my brother died in a sober living facility and drugs were involved.
And so like, I'm trying to compare and in his case, I was like, well, hey, look, you
know, you're gonna have a steroid awareness night in this baseball stadium, where fathers
are going with their four year old kid, and they go and they drink six beers, and then
they drive the kid home. And it's like, you know, what's the difference there? Isn't that
ironic? And so I was just trying to like figure out ways to not be mean spirited to
the guy, but yet like, sort of come across where it's like, just make some points to
him. And hopefully, like, it'll sink in with them. I don't know if it ever did or not.
I don't know if it does or not. But that's sort of my approach is to like, not really
go in there with a mindset of like, I'm going to destroy this person. Because think about
it all realistically, we are all human beings. We're all in this big soup together, we're
all here, we're all on this planet together, and we all have to function together. So like,
to pick a side and stand there just doesn't seem to make any sense. And what makes more
sense is like, when this movie is over, that guy is still a human being, he still has a
family, he still has things going on, right. And so I'm not trying to destroy that guy,
I just want to try to figure out what his point is and move past it. And, and so I think
that that's, you know, my philosophy is to try to try to keep the peace so that after
the film, we can still continue to have a relevant and smart, intelligent conversation
about the subject matter.
So I remember seeing the movie for the first time, probably in 2009. And I really I'm not
saying this, just because you're sitting here, but I really do credit that documentary with
being the thin end of the wedge that got me to begin to revisit a set of beliefs that
I had just taken for granted. So one of the challenges of medicine is, it's not necessarily
a discipline that's full of critical thought. And part of that is just the nature of you,
there's too much stuff you got to learn, you know, so you can't approach it through
the lens of intellectual curiosity all the way. It's just these are a set of facts, cholesterol
causes heart disease. Well, maybe it turns out to be the light, but proteins and inflammation
and a few other things. But look, the zero-thorter answer is, and of course, one of those hugely
dogmatic things is anabolic steroids, that's got to be like one of the most dangerous things
on the planet. And so all through my medical training, I've never really given this any
thought. And I just sort of assumed that stuff's got to be bad. And I even remember as a kid,
when Lyle Alzado died, I remember the cover of Sports Illustrated, I distinctly remember
the day he died. I had just come home from a run. It must've been the hottest day of
the summer. And I remember like, you know, reading the newspaper about it and it was
like, it was pretty clear, like Lyle Alzado died because he took steroids. And I was in
high school at the time and it was like, steroids are bad. Your movie comes along and I collect
quotes, right? So I've got, I have a file of just my favorite quotes. I'm going to read
you one of my favorite quotes, which I think applies to so many things we do. This was
John F. Kennedy said this, I believe at a Yale commencement in 1961, for the greatest
enemy of truth is very often not the lie, deliberate, contrived and dishonest, but the
myth persistent, persuasive and unrealistic. Too often we hold fast to the cliches of our
forebears. We subject all facts to a prefabricated set of interpretations. We enjoy the comfort
of opinion without the discomfort of thought.
That was before we got a man on the moon, huh?
Oh yeah. That was when the man on the moon was an idea. So when I think about bigger,
stronger, faster, through the lens of that, I realize that my understanding of steroids
was primarily the comfort I had of opinion. It was an opinion that had been passed down
and passed down and passed down, but I actually hadn't really submitted myself to the discomfort
of thought. And I don't think your movie is meant to necessarily make the case that, hey,
steroids are good, steroids are bad. I mean, that's also part of the beauty of the movie
is the way it ends with you, Mark, is actually a very powerful ending. Super powerful. Like
the last scene of that movie is one of the most powerful things ever because it deliberately
doesn't try to say, here's the answer. But what it did, at least for me, was it said,
dude, I don't actually know Jack about this topic. So before I form an opinion, I might
be wise to start thinking about it.
One of the interesting things about filmmaking is we come across these things by accident.
We were editing the movie and my editor left the computer on one day and went back to the
computer and there's my dad and my mom and they're like, yeah. And they're like, they're
cheering after Mark one thing and we're looking at it like, that's an awesome shot to end
the movie on. Like it's like the family and we're like, look at Mark, he's on steroids.
Like he's awesome. You know, and, and that kind of feeling, you know, and see him hit
a few more dingers, that part with the Simpsons. And so when you're making a movie, there's
a lot of happy accidents. Like people go, you're a brilliant for, you went out and got
these day laborers and you brought them in your house and you guys made supplements in
your kitchen. Those guys worked outside my office. They were there every day and every
day I joked like, I'm going to just get these guys to make my supplements for me. And I
just joke around like, is this a joke? Then when it came around at the time where we have
to shoot a scene, I'm like, why don't I hire those guys? They're, they're so cool every
day. I'd like to put some money in their pocket. So I paid them a hundred bucks to come make
supplements with me for that. No idea what was going on. And I'm sure they probably still
don't know that they're even in a movie, but they were, and they were, they were an awesome
part of it. It just shows you, it just shows you how wide open this, this industry is and
like how things aren't what they seem. You know, you think like, oh, a supplement must
be made in some factory with everything's all through the FDA. And it's like, no, it's
not the world's just not like that. You know? So prescription thugs sort of carries on in
the theme of the same type of investigation, but also it's very, very personal. Yeah. It's
a little darker. You know, I remember the first time I saw it, I was confused at the
very beginning because I was like, but wait, their brother died. Why is, did they film
this earlier than I thought? And then I realized, of course, no, that was B roll. Basically
that was, that was film you had before you started making prescription. Yeah. Yeah. And
so, um, right off the bat in the beginning, I was like, I want to make this movie. And
I just remember had his phone call with my dad and my dad's like, my dad was crying and
he doesn't cry that often. Mark will tell you, right? And you don't hear him cry. He
was kind of like, I'm crying twice choked up pretty much. And he said, this is the legacy.
This is it, Chris. This is like, this is what your brother meant in bigger, stronger, faster.
When he said, I know there's something out there that for the world to hear, but I don't
know what it is. He's like, this is the message, the message that you don't need drugs and
ball, right? And what was really fascinating about that is my dad comes back around full
circle again, the point where, um, I was in trouble and I wasn't doing too well. My dad
called me and said, only time he's ever yelled at me and he said, I don't know what's wrong
with you, but you're a drug addict or an alcoholic or something. There's something going on with
you and I can't figure it out, but you're not right. And I just cried for an hour afterwards,
you know, just like, Oh shit. I let my dad down. Like that's the worst feeling I get
choked up now talking about. I was like, the worst feeling you could possibly have is like
you let your father down. And so for me, he was very instrumental in just being there
for me and being like for him to show his anger just once, I think is what saved my
life. Do you remember that time Mark, when he was going through some stuff? Yeah, of
course. Yeah, it was hard. You know, we are, we already lost one and, uh, you know, I,
I guess one thing that's important to share with everybody is that it's never over. People
ask a lot of questions about success or getting jacked or bench press in more way. Uh, you
could take steroids and you can do all these different programs and you can do all these
different diets, but it's never over. You never, there's never a spot you get to and
you're like, fuck yeah, this is perfect. This is where I wanted to be. I'm going to hang
out right here. Every once in a while you catch glimpses of your own set of greatness,
right? And it feels good, but with his battle, it took so much support and it's still, it's
still, it's still a lot of support. There's still a lot of, he's come such a long way,
but there's still a lot of healing that has to continue to happen for his life to be as
prosperous as it possibly can be. And for him to reach, he has a lot of big goals, but
he's not even halfway to some of these big goals because he's still in the healing process
and he's heading towards all those things now, which is amazing to see after where he
came from. But it was almost like his life kind of restarted that 40 years old or so.
And his girlfriend at the time called me and it was a weird number. I don't even really
answer my phone that often, but I was just like, this is a weird hour night. It wasn't
too late, but most people don't really call me past like seven, eight o'clock. It was
like nine, 10 o'clock. And you know, I hear this voice on the other side, just real frantic
and really upset. And I was like, didn't understand who it was. And then started talking about
Chris and I was like, Oh, it's Lauren. Okay. That's why the phone number's from the East
coast and stuff like that. So, so then I said, okay, well, where, you know, where is he?
What's going on? Can you calm down? I can tell me more. And I guess he was inside their
apartment. She was outside the apartment and she just didn't know how she was going to
find him. Like what condition he would be in. And I said, well, as bad as it could possibly
be, I was like, you're the only like family he has there. I was like, I need you to go
and check it out, you know, because if he's really sick or if something happened, we need
to figure out a way to try to handle it. And so I said, make sure you just take his key,
remove his keys from the house. That way he doesn't go anywhere. And I said, and call
me back and let me know that he's still alive. You know, so she called me back. She was still
kind of hysterical. She's like, he's still alive, but he's passed out. I took his keys
and I talked to my wife, Andy, who just somehow always knows the right thing to do or the
right thing to say. And I talked to her about it. She goes, we're going to book him a flight.
We're going to get him up here and we need to book Lauren a flight too, because if we
don't book both of them, he's not going to come. He probably won't be able to get to
the airport in the morning and he'll probably just figure out a way to miss the flight and
we're going to get him here and we're going to safe proof everything around us and we're
going to figure out a way to help him. And that's what we did. We flew him to Sacramento.
I had a long time family friend that was an alcoholic herself and she explained to
me, you know, some of the things that we're going to go through through that process.
She gave me the place to send them for, what is that? Where are you going? Detox. Detox.
There we go. For like three or four days, you know, they take your phone and they give
you certain pills and it's very strict regimen and thing. No contact with anybody. And you
know, that set everything in motion. But what I always try to share with people, it's
a very long process. Even though that was only three days, it then led into him going
into rehab for another 60 or 70 days. And then it was just constant communication, trying
to figure out what he wants, what he needs. I think the coolest thing that came from it
all was sitting down with him and we had kind of this intervention thing, which really fucking
pissed me off because he didn't remember any of it, but he did say some things in there
that were, that really helped a lot. It helped me a lot and it helped everybody understand
a lot better of what was going on. And he said, I feel alone. And when he said that
I was like, I understand he's in LA and he doesn't, you know, he kind of has a girlfriend,
but he doesn't have us. We're not there. He flies up here for Thanksgiving, but he doesn't
have family. All he has is a bunch of fake ass motherfuckers around him that are in Los
Angeles. That's what Los Angeles is made of. Sorry, LA, but LA is like that. People
come and go in your life in a flash. I mean, they do in regular life, no matter where you
live, but you see that a lot in Los Angeles. You just meet a lot of people that are striving
to be actors, actresses, and you find out that most of these people are full of shit
a lot of times. Every single day you meet the person that's going to change your life or
they have the deal for you, you know, every day. But anyway, you know, we were able to
just surround him. My parents obviously played a huge role in all that and we were able to,
you know, have them here still today, what, five years later, four years later, four years
later. Yeah, it's weird because even thinking back to those times, like that's just not
the same person. You know, it's just a completely different person. I was, I guess I was in
that body, but I wasn't registered in that body. You know, like now I feel like just
a completely different human being altogether than I was a couple of years ago. You know,
I think that you have to go through some of these things to get, like if you want to,
for me, there are certain things that I wanted in life and there were certain things I had
to go through to get it, you know, and I never wanted to be a drug addict or an alcoholic,
but I thank God for it because I think that it's helped me to really help other people,
you know, and that's sort of the bigger goal is like, well, how can I use all this to help
you? You know, how can I use it to help other people? Like all, all I'm doing, I was inspired
when I was a young kid to lift weights and do, you know, do these things. And so when
I got older and I realized that it was all bullshit, I made bigger, stronger, faster.
You know, I just wanted to help people understand what we want. We have the coolest people in
the world asking us questions all the time. Joe Rogan's texting him asking about the carnivore
diet. Donald Trump Jr. is asking me how to improve his squat. I mean, there's some crazy
weird shit. I don't know if he's the coolest person in the world, but there's some crazy
weird shit going on though. Yeah. You know, that, you know, who were kind of unlikely heroes,
I guess, in some weird way. It's really crazy. The kind of people, even, even being able
to talk to you, it's like you're somebody I've listened to every podcast. We've been
chasing him down for some time. I've read everything. You know, like I read all the
blogs. I'm like, I, I just consume this stuff like crazy. So even though like be able to
talk to you is to me amazing. And I think that that's something that if we can spread
that message to other people that, you know, look, get involved in something, be proactive
about it, be excited, get other people on your team and go for it in life. And it doesn't
matter what you do, but to me, that's what makes our life fun is like now I have all
this opportunity to do all these, you know, fun things like Mark and I are going to go
see Joe Rogan perform tomorrow night. Tell me that's amazing to be able to get invited
to do something like that from somebody like Joe. And he's like, Hey, you guys want to
come? Of course we want to go. You know, and that to me is what it's all about. And what
it's all about is like, I just told you about when we did prescription thugs. Well, my partner
on prescription thugs who's sitting right across the room is Greg Young, GB Young and
Greg on prescription thugs saved my life. He was the person who was able to communicate
with the other producers that Chris is in trouble. We have a man down, but he's not
going to die and he wants to save the movie. So he could have easily went to the other
producers who was actually Peter Billingsley, who was the little kid in Christmas story.
Ralphie, he was our producer, but he went to Ralphie and he said, Hey, Chris is going
to be okay, but he's in a rehab and we got a man down and this is serious business and
we got to take care of it. And so because he did that, obviously has this loyalty to
us when it came around to make this film that we're making about nutrition, we brought Greg
on Greg when he started was about 330 pounds and now he weighs about 280. So he's already
lost about 50 pounds just doing like a keto diet and, and he comes and trains with us.
And so to me, that's what it's really all about is like getting in there and helping
somebody else change your life because I know Greg well, and I know what he's going to do
is he's going to turn around. He's already told the next three people that are going
to tell the next three people until the next three people. And all it is, is we're getting
people on the side of being healthy. That's all we're trying to do as mental health has
improved big time. He's more determined. He's in the gym now. He's never been in the gym
before, which that takes a lot of courage to even work up the steps just to even get
your butt in a gym. And before he said he didn't even want to get up off the couch.
And you know, the thing with, with it is like, we're not really selling anything. We're just
trying to, trying to help people with their lifestyle. Mark sells products, obviously,
and that, that allows us to be able to do these things, which I think is a really cool
thing. Yeah. Our, our X for everything is 10 minute walks, go lift some weights, stop
being so fat, stop eating such gross foods. You know, like that's, that's our prescription
for everything. Yeah. But again, I think what's interesting is it doesn't come across at least
to me. And maybe that's cause I've gotten to know you guys a little bit since you first
reached out to me, but it really doesn't come across as the way a lot of people in the fitness
space come across, which is again, I'm not going to name names, although I've got a long
list of people that I think are complete and total douche bags in the space.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Occasionally my Twitter account will release my criticisms of some
such individuals, but you know, there's this sense of, look, you just got to work harder,
you know, without acknowledging, Hey man, if you're down in the dumps, if you're 330
pounds and you're eating poorly and you're sitting on the couch, like it's not just a
matter of willpower. Like you have to make some other changes to at least get the inertia
to make these changes. And I, again, I just think it comes down to this, I suspect it
comes down to something you can only learn having suffered.
You know, what's amazing to me is like, uh, through doing this, like Greg's a guy that
I work with, you become closer to the people too. And so you also, you're drawing your
friends in more right here, rather than, than like pushing your friends out and excluding
them from things like you're sort of including them now and everything. And it's easier to
be friends with somebody that has the same dietary habits as you, it's easier to be friends
with somebody that does the same things as you has the same habits. And like, if I want
to be successful, I'm not going to let their bad habits sway me in a bad way. I'd rather
let my good habits sway them.
And building on that, I think it's also, I think people sort of don't realize that once
you start to let down sort of barriers and you can sort of communicate this vulnerability
about your own struggle in this case, it's amazing what that does for other people, because
I think many, many of us kind of go around thinking we're the only ones struggling with
problem X or problem Y. Uh, you know, I've talked about David Foster Wallace a number
of times. He's sort of someone I obviously never had the luxury of meeting, but I love
his work. And he's talked about this so eloquently, right? Which is every single one of us is
only experiencing the world from our own vantage point. We only know what's in our head. We
only know what we see. And it's so easy to think you are alone, which goes back to what
you said earlier, which is Chris is, he's break, he's, he's falling apart because he
feels alone.
Perspective is such a huge thing. And a lot of times it's easy to be judgmental, but I
think about my own life. And I think I had to what I can would consider perfect parents.
Both my parents were there for everything. My dad was like our baseball coach. And I
can't remember my dad ever telling me, no, that he couldn't hang out with me or throw
a football around with me or whatever. I can't remember a time where my mom didn't cook dinner.
Like, you know, they were just, just around. There was no shortage of, we can't complain,
no shortage of like resources, basketballs, weights, money, no shortage of hugs, no shortage
of love, no shortage of encouragement. So when somebody asked me certain questions about
whether it's my lifting or whatever, my lifting, you know, I, I started out in a way different
spot than maybe somebody else. Maybe somebody else grew up with abusive parents. Maybe they
didn't even find fitness until they were 40. Whereas I found it at 12 because we had it
in our basement because I was privileged enough to have parents that were always heading in
the right direction, always trying to do right by the family. And we're really trying
to, you know, build, build towards something. Whereas there's other people that maybe their
dad wasn't around, maybe their mom wasn't around, maybe their alcoholics, maybe they're
being abused or who, who know the list of things is unbelievable. But your starting point is,
is a big factor in where you start to end up.
And Mark talks about that a lot. And I think that that's the, you know, he said, he says
not everybody starts at the same spot. And so we can't really compare ourselves to other
people. Mark and I right now are training with Michael Hearn. Michael Hearn is a freak
ever since he was 14 years old. He looked like a professional bodybuilder, right? So
he's not just having the worst transformation in the history of the world. Cause at 14 or
actually actually more like 16 or 17, he looks the same as he does now at 48. Yeah. So he's
always been jacked. So exactly. And so, you know, for us, we're like, man, we, if we were
to compare ourselves to him, we'd just feel like crap every day. If I compare myself to
Mark, I'm going to feel like crap every day. Cause he's bigger than me and stronger than
me and leaner than me right now. He's, he's getting ready to do a bodybuilding show. But
you know, in my head, my goal is to try to beat him. You know, like we're, we're still
brothers. So in my, in my head, I'm starting way back from him and I'm not comparing myself
to him, but I still in, in some weird way go like, man, I hope I surpass him somehow.
I hope I can sneak in. I'm hoping he, you know, after his bodybuilding show, he has
been too many days of cheating, you know, and I can still beat him in something. But
I used to always beat him in powerlifting. I used to tell him emphatically, you will
never be as strong as me. I would, I would tell him, you'll, you won't even get in within
a hundred pounds of my bench press. And for a while that was like so true. And then now
I'm not even close to him. So it's like, it's funny how those things happen and can reverse
never say never. Yeah. Never say never. Right.
To me, the journey's kind of everything. My brother, he has a more eloquent way of saying
it and I'll sort of bastardize it, but the gist of it is you don't judge a man by where
he stands. You judge him by how far he's traveled to get there. And yeah, I always thought of
that. I mean, I, he said this even when we were young and I remember, I think I just
always grew up with such a chip on my shoulder that whenever I sort of felt myself being
compared to someone who was better than me or I would assume was more privileged than
me, I would not necessarily verbalize it, but internally I would think, well, screw
them. I've traveled way, I might not be where they are, but I've traveled way further to
get here. And you know, I have always been in negative energy. It doesn't help your situation.
Totally. Totally. Right. And I'm still kind of, you know, completely fascinated by whatever
it is that motivated the three of you as brothers to be, you know, trying to be anything other
than ordinary. And again, I don't think anybody just wakes up and says, I'm programmed to
be ordinary, but you know, you guys have accomplished kind of remarkable things. I mean, I want
to come back and talk about the physical stuff because it is, I'd like to be able to put some
of that in perspective for people who don't really fully understand what some of these
lifts mean. And so we'll certainly come to that. But it's interesting because it's not the
story I would have expected, right? What I would have expected is something in childhood
wounded you guys, you know, and it's like your entire adult life has been a way to cope with
some pain and that's been channeled into mostly positive things. But then sometimes it's gone
off the rails. Like that's the narrative I would construct if I didn't have any background.
I really honestly, when I when I said January 23rd, 1984, it was a day that changed my life
forever. I meant it. I really meant it. When Hulk Hogan beat the Iron Sheik, we were we
were fanatics. We were nuts, man. We were like, well, that's so loved it so much. And
we wanted to be part of that without all we could see as ourselves inside of a wrestling
ring. We had the ability to dream because our dad provided and mom provided that for
us. That's all we had to worry about as kids was to dream big. That's it. That was the
only thing when I remember like the smell. I remember I remember everything about like
getting our first Nintendo, you know what I mean? I remember all these different things.
I remember watching that match. You know, I don't know how old I was. Yeah. Seven. I
don't know. There's such a difference. I really remember those. Those are really strong memories
for us. And I don't know. There's there's just such a difference from when we got involved
in watching wrestling to before it. Like I don't I don't remember anything before it.
I just remember the I actually don't even remember to tell you the truth. Not even January
23rd. It was before that January 23rd was the big day where Hulk Hogan pinned the cheek.
But before that, this was WrestleMania one. Correct. That was before that. Even this is
1984. WrestleMania one or 87. No. 85 85. WrestleMania one was WrestleMania one with Hulk Hogan and
Mr. T. It was the year after. Yeah, it was after he had to develop for you or whatever.
Yeah. Before that, Mark and I were watching wrestling and Mark used to have to hold the
clothes hanger. We had a metal clothes hanger that was attached to the antenna of my job that
we could get, you know, so that the TV coming. I can't really watch it. I could kind of be like,
he had to like hold it. But he was only like five seriously was like five or six. And Mike was two
years older than you. Yeah. Year and a half older than me. You're four years older than Mark. Yeah.
So he was like a little kid. He's like five. Maybe I'm 10. Right. And Mad Dog's like 12. And we're
watching wrestling and we're watching this body slam challenge every time Big John Studd would
come out and they hold up the bag full of money and they'd be like, we're going to $25,000 body
slam challenge. The smallest bag for some reason. Yeah. Tiny little bag and dollars in there too.
Not even hundreds. And we're like excited. Like who's going to try it this week? And we know the
guy's never going to get them and body slam them. Who's going to get them this week? And it's like
Chief J Strongbow. So we're kind of bummed out like, ah, Chief J Strongbow. He's not going to do
shit, you know? So Chief J Strongbow like walks out and he's standing there and he just starts
shaking his head like, no, he's like, got his hands crossed. He's like, no. And he turns around
and Andre the Giant walks out behind him and we're like, oh my God, it's Andre. And we were so excited
with the Andre was going to come down and slam them and take the money. But it was even better
because Andre came down and tried to slam them. And then the manager smashed him in the back and
Andre took the money and threw it out to the whole crowd. To us, like those moments were like bigger
than life. They were the hugest things that happened. It was like so much to where we would,
my dad would always, you know, say, Hey, if you guys want to do something special, I'll do one,
one thing a year. And it was always like, let's go to Madison Square Garden and watch wrestling.
Let's go to WrestleMania. You know, it was always something to do with wrestling. So for us, it was
a huge influence on our lives. We're just like what we saw in the movies and on TV. And we lived in.
I do think seeing our dad being a suit and tie every day was not anything that we wanted for
ourselves either. And he worked for IBM and he poured so much into that job. He would do anything
for that company. And he worked there for nearly 20 years. I think right around the time he got to
a point where he would get some privileged things upon retiring, like around 19 years or so,
is when they let him go. And it was like, wait, what? Like all this, this work that you put all
this time into, you're just out the door. And he realized it himself like that was a huge lesson
for us. Well, he hadn't he said he, you know, later he told us he had no ownership of anything.
He's like, I didn't own the fucking stapler. I didn't own the paper that they had. I didn't own.
He's like, all I owned was myself. So and after that, he I think he had like a knee surgery and
some things. So he went through his own process, but went through probably a lot of personal
development, which maybe he didn't even really realize that he needed to go through because he
was stuck in corporate America. He was like frozen. His brain was frozen in time where it
was corporate America and family, corporate American family, go back and forth between
those two things. It didn't leave time for anything else. But when he lost his job,
I think he paused for a minute, took a breath and said, I'm actually really smart.
I'm going to be an accountant. He was already doing some of that. I'm going to go into real
estate. He picked back up. I think within three years, he was not only making the money, he was
making an IBM, but he was doing it. And then some, our grandfather was an entrepreneur. Our
grandfather could tinker and fix anything. He had a used car lot. And I think a lot of our creativity
in their own backyard. Yeah. Yeah. And his own, yeah. So his own yard. He built his own home,
you know? So when I, when, when I look at my grandpa and I look at my dad, like I feel like
he and I are giant steps backwards compared to what those two are able to accomplish.
Well, there's something you said that I find really quite, quite powerful, which is despite
the fact that your dad was working for the man, busting his ass, he'd give anything for IBM. He
still gave you guys everything. Yeah. You know, you said, absolutely. You never were without a
hug. You never, there was never a moment when you wanted to play with your dad and he wasn't there.
And so my guess is that would make it a lot more palatable when you get shit on by the man.
Because can you imagine the guilt that would rest upon you if you're doing all this stuff in service
of your family, right? You're working this hard to provide for your family, obviously.
But in the process, you're, you got to make these hard sacrifices to not spend time with your family.
And then in the end, you get the shafts. That's where my mom came in. She had the strength to
pull them aside one day and say, you're not here enough. And he was like, what? He was like, I'm
trying to be. She's like, yeah, you keep getting these promotions. You keep making more money,
but you're not here. And he was like, Oh my God, I didn't, like he almost, he got lost in it. He
didn't know. And so my mom pulled him back in and, and that, that really helped.
Were your parents athletic when they were growing up?
No, our mom was. My mom was slightly, but she, she came from a family, a big family,
and she was the babysitter. You know, she had a lot of responsibility as a young woman.
Like literally raised.
She raised seven other kids, basically, you know, my grandmother at the time,
my grandmother was going through alcoholism as well. And same with our grandfather. So
our grandfather was the chief of police on my mom's side in the family. And he was dealing with
alcoholism. And he dealt with that up until he died. My grandmother got sober and she'd been
sober for what, like 30 something years, I think when she passed away, which was like last year,
maybe our grandparents lived down the street from each other and we would go.
We didn't realize the dynamics of that until we got older, that my dad and mom met on the bus.
And my dad like winked at my mom or something when they were like 13, but they were literally like
just a few flavors, few football fields away from each other. But when I go to my
mom's side of the family, the house was real dark and you didn't want to hang out there as a kid.
It smelled like alcohol. It smelled like cigarettes and just had unease, just sitting,
just like fogging through the whole household. You just knew you didn't want to be there.
You didn't know why, but you knew you didn't want to be there. No one was mean really, but just,
it was like, kind of like just to be the fighter where everything was like the house is just
depressing. But then we'd go to my dad's side of the family and everything was like bright and
everything's wide open. And somebody's dressed up as Santa Claus on Christmas. Somebody's swinging
around and acts randomly for some reason, some unsupervised kid. And then someone's got a tennis
ball and someone's got a wiffle ball bat. Our grandfather would pull stunts. So he would pull
stunts. Like he'd blow out his birthday candles and the cake would fall through the table. He would
he would just do crazy. And he'd film it. He'd blow the filmmaker. He was a filmmaker. He would
blow him everything. He'd blow his candles and then the cake would go flying across the room and
smash into the wall. And as kids were like, oh my God, he would do things like he'd put like a
little pulley and a string underneath. And he said, when I blow out the candles, I'm gonna make the
cake fly across the room. The kids are gonna go nuts. And it was always my grandfather, every single
year, every single year, and they still do it in our family, you pull the rope because he will
always put the trap for Santa Claus. So the day after Christmas, you pull the rope and you always
get Santa Claus's boot and it's full of candy. And that's what the kids do every single year. And
they still do it in our family because my grandfather started those traditions. So we always
when you're like 14, you're like this stupid. Yeah. You're out there like, I gotta still pull the rope.
Yeah. Come on, grandpa. But that's, I think those things that are like are ingrained in us, we had a
great life growing up. We had a fun life growing up. We used to go fishing with our grandfather
and things like that. We just grew up close. When did you realize just from the standpoint of
strength, you guys weren't normal? I was in 11th grade and I had, so my knees were really bad.
And when I was in 10th grade, yeah. And my knees were really, they just always hurt. And I didn't,
I had no idea why. And so I went to the doctor and the doctor's like, Oh, you got these bone
spurs in your, in your knees. We got to remove them. So he did this like arthroscopic knee surgery.
And I was, I had to be off my feet for, you know, a couple of weeks or whatever. And I, and I did
that, but I was always in pain. I didn't really know why it's because I had arthritis, but I had
no idea when I was younger and nobody diagnosed me with it at all. So I was playing football at the
time. And I went to see this chiropractor who was also our strength coach and he taught me how to
squat. And so it just started out where Mad Dog was going to the gym all the time. He was playing
football and he was really good and he could squat like 400 pounds or something. I just remember.
He was 16. Yeah. He was strong. He was pretty strong. And I was like, and that dog is pretty
strong. And then by the time he's like 18, you know, he was even a little bit stronger. And my
chiropractor, this guy who was trying to help me fix my knees said, well, you know, to fix your
knees, you need to squat. And I said, Oh no, I've been reading the bodybuilding magazines. That's
the last thing you want to do. It's bad for your knees and it hurts your knees. He's like, no,
it doesn't. I've been a power lifter forever. Just trust me to squat. And I was barely into even like
working out. So I started with a broomstick and I just prided myself and going back to that doctor
every day, every time, not every day, but like once a week saying like, Hey, now I did a hundred
pounds. Now I did 110 pounds. And you're how old here? Like 12, 16, 16 at this point. Yeah. And this
guy's squat at 700 pounds at around weighing around 16 years old, turning 17 about shit. I started
squatting a broomstick and within six months I'm squatting 315 for like eight reps. People are like,
what is going on with this guy? You know, people in my school were going like, this is weird.
And when you say that you are at this point, are you doing like top of the thighs are breaking
parallel? Like these are power lifting squats pretty much. They were power lifting squats.
There was nobody really just training at the time. But then pretty soon I was up over 500 pounds,
like in high school, squatting over 500 pounds and squatting over 500 pounds for working out,
doing reps. We responded really well to, to not doing a whole lot. So we'd go in the gym
and we'd do one heavy lift and we would leave. And our coach, we had like a guy that was trying
to coach us and he was like, Bell brothers just squat and leave. He's like, you don't even do any
assistance work. We're like, yeah, that's all we need. And he ended up squatting 675 that way at
around 18 or 19 years old. So I don't, so we were like, no, we think it's working. Yeah. I mean,
I think I, you know, I think the fact that, um, less training stimulus helped and we were like
really into Mike Menser. We were just talking about him before and Mike Menser was our uncle's
favorite bodybuilder. And he was all about like doing less and getting away with like
just going in and working really hard for a short amount of time. And we took, you know,
took those lessons, but we realized that we were strong early on, but for Mark, what was insane
was there was this day. It's like, this is sort of the day lifting started like the day lifting
began like for the whole world, going to like a Rocky montage after. If this was the movie of Mark's
life, there's this day where my cousin Steven came over to visit. Steven's like, ah, I can't,
I know I can't bench as much as you, but I know I can probably, I can even his age. Yeah. Steven's
my age. He's like, I'll kill Mark. And I'm like, I don't think you will. And he's like, no, I'll
kill Mark and bench. I can bench like two old family. Yeah. I'll kill Smelly and Ben. And so,
they get on the bench. They start going. It's like 135, 145, 155. We just keep going up and up. And
I'm like, I'm thinking Mark is really getting strong. Like whatever we've been doing, it's
been working. We get up to around two. Oh, doesn't have any idea how strong I am because he's only
had me do sets of like a six to 10 reps usually. And as we were going up in weight, we just kept
adding fives and tens and five and 10, five and 10. I got him on this bench off with my cousin.
My cousin fails at like, I don't know what he failed at, but then like 205 or something.
And Mark did like 240 or 250 pounds. At what age? He was probably like 13, 13, maybe 12 or 13,
like young, like, like what the hell is going on here? I definitely didn't look like I could do that.
My mom, actually on the same day, my mom benched 135 and she'd never lifted in her life.
She just picked it up off the. And it was weird too. Because she just was like,
like this and she started laughing all and like sinking into her boobs and everything.
Yeah. Boom. And she just like smashed it out. And we're like, Oh my God.
Yeah. You guys remind me of a family I grew up with, which is just, and it's actually,
sad thing is it's an equally tragic story. So not that anyone listening to this will ever,
I don't know if they'll ever hear this, but their name was the Stuparix. So there was Rob, Matt,
Russ, and there was one other Stuparix and they were from another planet in terms of strength.
So, you know, even though boxing was my thing, like I found a great place to lift weights,
which was this Dungy little gym at the university of Toronto that was mostly just grown men power
lifting. And then there was me and my best friend from high school who were like, you know,
they hated the fact that we were there, but by the end they grew to respect those because
they basically got us into power lift. And it's so funny. Everything you say reminds me exactly of
the Stuparix, which were, they literally only benched or squatted or deadlift, nothing else.
And their strength was redonkulous. I remember, I think it was Rob at a weight of 185. He had hurt
his shoulder so bad that he could only narrow grip bench and he's narrow gripping 385 for 10.
Like here. It's like, cause my shoulder hurts. So I gotta go narrow.
So I gotta go narrow, you know, transmit more of this to my tries. Yeah. And, um,
these guys were freaks of nature. And I don't know if any of this shit was true, but the rumor
was that they were, you know, they came from Viking stock and their mom could apparently
bury any one of their friends in an arm wrestle. If they brought a friend home, that's great. Like
you want to arm wrestle their mom, you're going through the table. Yeah. It's like, it's funny
cause we were like that, but we weren't even the strongest kids in our high school or we weren't
even the strongest kids in our area. Come on in Poughkeepsie. I think it's like in the water or
something. I mean, there was, there were people, we were the strongest. We were by far, we'd kill
people in strength, but, um, we had dudes that were huge in high school that were just like monsters.
That w we went to a pretty big high school. I mean, when I went to school, I was, but you, you were,
you were just smaller. Yeah. Well, a lot of people did steroids on Poughkeepsie. So when I grew up in
Poughkeepsie, I had a belt that said Royd sucked on it. It said Royd suck and it would make
everybody in the gym mad because everybody was on the juice and I was stronger than all of them.
And they would get so pissed because they'd see me coming in, squat,
and they'd see the belt, right? Sucks. And I, Oh, you're, you know, you're on shit. Well,
everybody would always say that I was on stuff and I just never was, you know, I just,
it just didn't happen. So to me all growing up, it was funny that we, I ended up making bigger,
stronger, faster. Cause I have that, I had that written in big block letters across the back of
my belt, Royd suck. And I ended up making this movie about steroids and talking about how they,
maybe they're not that bad. So how old were you, Chris, when you peaked and what, give me, just
give me, well, first of all, let's take a step back. Thanks a lot. Can one of you guys explain?
You're done. It's all downhill. One of you guys want to take the liberty of explaining to the
listeners what powerlifting is, what Olympic lifting is, why those are sports in and of
themselves. Let Mark do that. He's the expert. All right, Mark, tell us what they are. So, uh,
Olympic lifting is what you might see on TV when the Olympics come around. Powerlifting is not an
Olympic sport. Olympic weightlifting is a clean and jerk and the snatch. Those are the exercises
that you do basically involves taking the weight from the floor and figuring out some way to get
it over your head. There's different rules in both of them, but that's the gist of it.
You get three attempts on both of those lifts and the accumulation of both of those lifts is
called your total. So in powerlifting, you do a squat in this order, bench press, and then a
deadlift and you get three attempts at each one of those and accumulation of those that's goes into
what is called a total. Powerlifting is really difficult because it's hard to have leverage on
all three of those movements. Olympic lifting is, is very difficult, but it requires a whole
different skill set. Mobility becomes a big factor. Speed becomes a big factor. You're trying
to like basically move your body around the barbell, whereas powerlifting is not even like a good move
in the bar. Yeah. Power, it's just not even a good term for it because it's, it's not really a
definition of power, but right. Power has a speed component to it. Yeah, right. Yeah. And you are
doing it as fast as you can, but it's so heavy. It doesn't look fast. Yeah. Yeah. But yeah, in
powerlifting, you know, for the squat, we're required to try to get our hip crease below where
the knee is, which is always in controversy because the human body can't process looking
in two places at once. So that rule should have been changed a long time ago, but it never has been.
So that's a squat. When it comes to the bench press, you need to pause the weight on your chest
for a moment. The referee will say press, he pressed the weight back up to full lockout
and the deadlift is pretty simple. You just pick the damn thing up from the ground and
until you're able to stand up with it fully erect, as they say. And then they just give you a down
signal and that's powerlifting. And you alluded to something earlier, which your numbers are
actually quite interesting. So, so I was not a particularly good powerlifter. I just did it as
sort of ancillary training for let's talk numbers. Yeah. So I weighed, I weighed 158, 160. My bench
was my weakest. I think my best was 270 or 275. It's respectable. Let's just say 275. Okay. So my
squat was about 495. I think pound for pound, that was my best lift. And my deadlift was about 505.
This is an honest man here. He didn't even give himself the five pound bump on the squat.
So you would agree though, that I was more of a squat deadlift guy than a bench guy. I was a pretty
weak bench guy actually. I was the weakest guy in the gym. You can only be good at one. And we
were really good at bench press. That was our main thing. Yeah. Sometimes you get it too. And sometimes
like somebody might be somewhere in the middle of the road on all three, and then they're able to
raise up all three over years and years. But your PRs Mark are remarkable. I don't have them here,
but if I recall, you actually benched more than you deadlifted at a PR. So give me your PRs.
First of all, there's kind of two parts to my lifting career or maybe even three parts,
but I guess to make it more simple, I used powerlifting gear, which is a supportive gear
that gives you assistance that allows you to lift more weight. It started out being protective and
then the companies made things more and more extreme. And so therefore you're able to actually
lift more weight. I did a 1,080 squat, 854 pound bench press and a 766 pound deadlift.
And that's all in equipped powerlifting. When it comes to raw lifting in the gym,
I've squatted 700 pounds raw before I benched 578 in competition. And I think my best deadlift
might be like 715, I believe somewhere in that range. So right now that's an interesting
distinction. To be clear, raw means no knee wrap. Yeah. So the raw powerlifting that I did was no
knee wraps, no squat. So belt only. Belt only. Yeah. Belt wrist wraps. That would be it. Sometimes
people still consider knee wraps being raw just because you're not wearing like a squat suit or
bench shirt. But yeah, those were the numbers. At that time I was so locked into what I was doing.
I did every and anything that I could to be stronger. You know, I've made the statement before
and it might sound arrogant, but I just said, you know, if you met me at that time, I would
bend the most savage powerlifter you would ever met because not because of my strength. I wasn't
the strongest guy in the world. Although I posted numbers that rivaled some of the strongest guys in
the world for that time, I was as strong as I could be. I don't think I could have squeezed
any more out of that. I pushed it as hard as I could. I got as big and as heavy as I could.
I tried eating healthy to get big. I've tried eating disgustingly gross to get big. I've tried
to do all kinds of different things and I think I pushed that envelope pretty good. I think maybe
the one thing that could have been a little bit better is I could have slept a little bit better
looking back at it, but I was just so big it was hard to sleep. I think he's right on that. I mean,
I know we know a lot of people in powerlifting and he just put everything into it. You know,
there was times where just like even the amount of food he would eat and stuff and I would say like,
aren't you worried about this or that? He's like, I'm just worried about winning. You know, like
he wasn't worried about any like everything was so laser focused in on these big lifts and these
big weights and the amount of energy and the amount of seriousness like it was. And it was
so dead serious in the gym all the time because like kind of was life or death when you're
squatting a thousand pounds. There'd be like a lot of fights and arguments and in the old super
training because it was highly competitive and people would, you know, like somebody would mess
up like just getting the rack, somebody would go to rack it and they wouldn't put the monolith down.
So he's spotty the wrong way or whatever. They yell at each other and just getting all fight and it
was just so aggressive and crazy. A lot of intensity. It's sort of where you had to go
to get there in the sport of powerlifting. So what were your PRs assisted? So I did like 675 squat.
I never did raw powerlifting, never came into the fray like as far as I was there, but I was
actually there. It's interesting. I was there before the equipment was really good, but not when it
went raw. So really like a single ply squat suit. I did like 675 squat. I did a 472 bench in
competition, but in bigger, stronger, faster in just a bench competition. I did 501 in a bench
shirt. I think the best I ever did in gym was like 585. That's where the shirt, the best I ever did,
I think raw in the gym is 500. But you know, now I blew out my shoulder and those things don't work
like that anymore. To give some people perspective, you know, everything in my gym is specialized.
The plates are specialized. The barbells are specialized. At the time when we, when I was
lifting those big weights, we had a bar, which is called the Iron Wolf bar. And this, this thing is
so, has so much crazy knurling on it. It's like a cheese grater that it kind of ruined the inside
shape of our squat rack. Because when you try to move the weight around or roll it at all,
it would sheer metal off of there. And if you went to duck underneath it to do a squat,
it would tomahawk you. It would, it would just fricking cut the top of your, your hair right off.
I could just boom, like a, like a razor. So everything in there is specialized. And that
bar was designed that way. So it stays sturdy on your back and it was extra thick so that there
was no whip when you're trying to squat. Because when you have that much weight on your back,
if the weights are flopping around, it's going to be really hard to try to stabilize it. And you're
going to end up probably falling on the ground. And also we had, you know, we use kilo plates,
which are super, super thin, or we had to always buy, you know, thinner 45 pound plates. And to
give people an idea of what some of this stuff looked like, I mean, it'd be very common to walk
into super training gym on a Tuesday or on a Thursday night. Tuesday was a big squat night.
Thursday was a big bench night. And you would see six, seven, eight, nine, 45s on each side of the
bar. One time just to do it, just cause I wanted to try it, I could have easily used our kilo
plates and stuff. But I was doing some math and I was like, holy crap, I can bench press 20 45 pound
plates. I'm like, I'm going to fucking try that tomorrow. And so it was 10 45 pound plates on
each side. If you can envision that. And now that's a special bar too, cause it has an extra sleep.
That's 900 pounds plus the bar 9 45. Yeah, it's like, yeah, right. Yeah. And, uh, you know,
I did it off of boards and stuff in context for people. Like for me, I understand these numbers
because I just know like even just like, I remember this, like I was never even able to get
two 25 for 10. I could never quite get there, which I always thought was like, until you can do two
25 for 10, you're not actually benching. And I remember like I could only get to about eight.
And so I was just such a pathetic bench presser, but I also know like how heavy that is. So the
numbers you guys are talking about, like, I don't even understand what eight 57 bench press means.
Like how do we, I'm just trying to think like you could bench press the back of a car. You could lay
under a car and at least get the car out of its suspension. Right. You know, I don't know an easy
way to, uh, try to explain something that's a little bit complicated to people that might not
understand it. All I know is that typically when you go into a commercial gym, somebody might be
moving around a plate, two plates, maybe three plates and the strongest guy at some of these
commercial gyms sometimes are pretty strong, but usually you're going to see somebody use
four or five, you know, four plates on each side. It was very common that week in and week out at my
gym and still is very common where there's groups of people, you know, one after another, I guess
where you can make a comparison is a friend of mine was a collegiate wrestler and he
ended up being an alternate on the Olympic team. And when he went to train at the Olympic training
center, he said, he remembered there was some guys there after he was there for a while. There's
some guys there that would brag and they're like, Oh, I'm an all American from this place or that
place. Or, um, you know, all state from this college or whatever, whatever, whatever their
thing was, whatever the championship was. And he was just like, we all are, you know, what's
special about you that you're not a special snowflake, you know? And so inside the walls of the
gym, as we were building up and making ourselves a lot stronger, that's what we'd see day in and
day out. It was just commonplace to see somebody squat 700 pounds, 800 pounds, deadlift, 800 pounds,
things like that. I think that was sort of, I took it for granted as a kid that from my first
exposure lifting weights, which was starting at 13 till 19, I only knew that one gym. Yeah. So I
only knew exactly what you're describing, which is we were the weakest, you know, me and my friend
were like the little babies there, but you'd see these guys who were simply from another planet and
everything was only counted in plates. Right. It was like, is it six places at seven places,
eight plates. And of course, you know, this was such a crappy gym that the bars were all bent.
Like, you know, you had to know how to position yourself under the bar to squat because the bar
was so permanently deformed. Dangerous. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's just crazy. And now as you said,
I go into like crunch, which is where I lift weights when I'm in New York. And it's like,
you don't see anybody really going above two or three plates typically. And look,
they're still strong dudes, but what you're describing is a different world. Looking back
on it, I wish I knew more when I was doing it. Looking back on it, we tried to learn as much as
we can as we were doing it, but along the way, I've gotten injured and being hurt is worse. Like to me,
now it sucks because I'm hurt. I can't fix it. So I got hurt from, I tore my tricep just from
pushing things too hard, pushing too much too hard. Two or three years ago, maybe or what?
It was like five years ago and it just never healed, right? And it never,
when I went to the doctor to see if I needed to get it reattached, it's like, ah,
it's torn, but it'll probably heal pretty good and blah, blah, blah. And like, you know, so I just
didn't get it reattached. And also it was right before I went to rehab. So I wasn't in a good
state of mind to go get it reattached and whatever. And it just never came back. And so I wish I knew
more in, you know, now, but what's, what's nice about now coming back around is a lot of the
things that are injured. I've been, I've been able to rehab and been able to, you know, fix as well.
So I still print lifting pretty heavy, but I just wish we had that knowledge back then of like,
you know, not getting hurt. So knowing what you know, and you guys have heard me talk about the
importance of weight training. I, it's probably the only thing that for me is never compromised.
My life sort of revolves around weight training. So I have to get in the gym three days a week
and my hotels when I'm on the road are planned around where those lifts are going to be and when
and blah, blah, blah. And yet doesn't mean that every week I can squat and deadlift and do all
the things that matter, but almost without exception. So this stuff's important. But the
other thing I'm sort of fond of saying is, look, rule number one is don't get hurt.
So if someone's listening to this and either like, you know, these numbers don't mean anything or
whatever, but they still get the gist of it, which is, hey, I probably ought to be lifting weights.
And let's say they're thinking, hey, I want to be able to squat and deadlift and bench. I want
from each of you guys a really, you know, sort of the most important thing that you know, after all
of your years of both watching coaching and experiencing that you would pass on to somebody.
So let's start with you. Yeah. The hard part is rule number one is to challenge yourself.
Rule number two is to not hurt yourself. So that's where things get to be a little difficult. As we
get older, a lot of times that shifts, right? But in the beginning, you need to get hurt.
Sounds foolish to mention that, but we've all been hurt in the gym and we've all learned
a lot from it. And I'm not saying that you should haphazardly jump in there and not warm up and stuff,
but the truth is we could sit here and promote warm up and stretching and stuff and no one's
still going to do it. Well, but hang on, but let's talk about it. You guys are big on warming up the
glute mede. You've got, you sell a thing that one of the things I'm hoping you either have here or
I'll have to buy it on the website, but I like your little hip circle. So I mean, that was one
of the most important insights of my life was you can't squat or deadlift until your glute mede,
your TFL are working. It's foolish to start a workout without warming up. You've got to move
around. If you're going to do any sort of upper body stuff, you've got to get the elbow joint warm.
You've got to get the shoulders warm. And there doesn't have to be any science to it. There's not
to be anything in particular to it. If you're going to squat, you throw on something like hip
circle, you walk forward, you walk backwards, you walk side to side, and maybe you do some
sort of bending exercise where you're picking up barbell or plate, you know, and just bending from
the hips basically. But you have to warm up for your workouts, but if you're not challenging
yourself, then you're missing out on a big piece of the puzzle because you're never going to get
the results that you're looking for. People always think that when they look at other people
on social media, when they look at Jeff Bezos, the guy that owns Amazon, if they look at Elon
Musk or they look at The Rock, people are like, man, that's so cool. Like, that would be awesome
to be them. Like, must be easy. Like, must be easier because they're them, because they have
that money, because they have that freedom. It is 10, 20, 30, 100, a thousand times harder to be them.
It gets to be harder and harder to be yourself as you continue to grow in fitness. And so,
that's the reason why you have to challenge yourself each and every day. You have to figure
out a way, how can I be better than I was yesterday? It doesn't always mean that you have
to do more weight, but you have to challenge yourself in something. There has to be progress.
Without progress, I don't believe you can even have happiness. And so, the progress is going to
be very, very motivating to you as well. And it's going to be something that will help keep you on
track. Before I go to you, Chris, I want to follow up more on that. Talk to me about some of the
ways that you would monitor progress when you're already at the level of the world's best,
which you were. The days are long gone where there's a PR every day in the gym. You PR once
a year, that's a good year. So, what are you doing to motivate yourself day in and day out
when you're still benching every week and still squatting and still deadlifting? Like, how are
you finding out? What are these incremental goals? As you chase one thing, something else starts to
fall apart. And there'll be tipping point. You want to be really strong? Well, maybe you run into
an injury just because. Like, sometimes we're sitting there and trying to think about it. We're
like, well, I don't know. Maybe your hips are tighter. Maybe it's like, how about it's just,
you try to lift up 700 pounds and you've been doing it for the last three or four weeks. And
that's just that. Like, that's just the way the body is going to be. So, there's always something
to work on. There's always something to improve. You always have that kind of white belt mentality
where you're like, I don't know everything. I don't pretend to know everything. There's still
so much to learn and expand upon. And when you look around, you're like, are there other people
that are better than me in this lift? Are there other people that are stronger than me? Of course,
there is. Are there other people who've gone further than me? Of course, there is. So, that means I
have a lot to work on. There's always a PR to chase. There's always something to chase. It might not be
on that lift. It just might look like something different. One of the magical things that I've
learned in the gym, and it's one of my favorite things is just, and I share this with everybody,
do you know a way to get a PR every single time you step foot into a gym? Low standards start low.
Well, that's my life right there. Yeah, low standards. No, to try something you've never
done before. You know, what's your max set of seven with incline dumbbell press? No clue, right?
What's your max set of three sets of seven with one minute rest on incline dumbbell press? You have
no idea. Or machine, or like you can get excited and you kind of make it anything. And you start
to kind of make it into a little bit of a game. And that's where it gets to be really fun. Oh,
yeah, last time I tried this, I did, I think I only did 95 pounds. I'm going to try 100 pounds.
I'm trying 105 pounds. And at first, a lot of those things will go up and up and up and up.
And after a while they will dissipate, but you can always think of, well, maybe I'm going to
try sets of 25 today just because I've never done it before. So what about you, Chris, all the hard
knocks you've learned, what's the advice for the person listening to this who like wants to get
stronger and doesn't want to be intimidated when they walk in the weight room? Yeah, the number one
thing for me that really changed my life altogether is my diet. You know, like what I put in my mouth
affected what I did in the gym. And I didn't never saw that correlation when I was younger,
because I just ate like crazy and was a power lifter. But I can really see now that every
competition that I won once I moved to California. So I explained to you before we were even on the
podcast, I was telling you, when I moved to California in 1993, I met up with a group of
power lifters. One of them was Michael Hearn, another one was my friend, Ron Fedko, who is a
maniac. And he was a so Ron Fedko was a power lifter. He was getting his degree in applied
mathematics at UCLA, getting his PhD. And now he's the head of the computer science department
at Stanford. This guy would bench he bench press 526 with no bench shirt. He squatted 804,
something like that. And deadlifted like he's close to eight, something like that at 198.
And when he met me, he said to me, you're too fat, you need to lose weight. Like, like one of
the first things he said to me when I was like, hey, you know, I want to really weird stuff too.
And you're like, I said, I want to read. He told us about like the mitochondria and stuff. Oh,
yeah, way back. He's like, my red blood cells are way off. I should be able to press that for more
reps. Really? What? Yeah, he's always like he bends to 25 for 64 reps. Yeah, he was a maniac.
So anyway, he told me one of the first things he said was like, you're, you know, you're just too
fat to be a good power lifter. Like he just had no. He was rough on the edges. Yeah, he was rough
around the edges. But he's like, you know, but if you lost weight, you'd be pretty good. I'm like,
well, I have no idea how to like really lose weight. I've been, I've been trying to lose weight.
That's why I'm in the gym. But the entire time from the day I stepped in the gym, my goal was
to lose weight. And I'd never been able to until I figured out this keto diet, you know,
where you, so you, you talk about how you were chubby as a kid, Chris, Mark, were you chubby
as a kid? I was fat too. I got fat around, I got fat around 13 and continued to build because we
didn't know anything about eating everything we ate was snack wells and granola bars. You know,
wait, is that bad? Yeah. Oh, okay. Pretty cool. I was a little bit more in the middle, I guess,
but like, you know, by around 16 years old, I was like 240 pounds, but I was like, kind of,
it was kind of big, kind of big and fat. And then, you know, I started to learn more because he was
picking up stuff, relaying information to me. And then I started to kind of slim down and getting
better shape. But when I met Ron in 93 and I, the very first thing he said was like, Hey,
go get a piece of paper and write down everything I said. So I ran and did it. I got the paper. I was
all excited. I'm 23 years old, getting information from this great power lifter. And he just says,
red meat and water. And I write it down. I'm going, okay. And what else? That's it. That's your diet,
red meat and water. I don't even want to see you chewing a stick of gum. And I was kind of scared
of Ron. So of course I didn't even chew a stick of gum. And I went for like two or three weeks on
no carbs, just literally ground beef. This is before grass fed beef was even a thing. I don't
even, I don't even think you'd be able to find it if you had to. It was those big fat tubes.
Going around back then. Yeah. Those big fat tubes of, uh, you know, the beef, the five pounders.
Disgusting. And I would just cook bones and shit there. And I did that for a couple of weeks
and, um, lost like over 20 pounds, won the powerlifting competition that I went into
and then continued to do that down to like 198 weight class. And the next meet after that,
I'd started around two 40 and got all the way down under 198. How much strength did you lose?
And when you got strong 40 pounds, you actually got strong way stronger. Yeah,
way stronger. And the thing is so, cause I lost weight. I was able to grab the bar. Now
I was able to squat better, right? I was able to get down to the bar. And so it was hard doing
like losing the weight and getting there. But once I got there, I was, I stayed relatively strong.
But my biggest problem was that for some reason, uh, there wasn't any research on a keto diet back
then. There wasn't any research at all on a, uh, there was research, but I didn't know how to get
to it. You know, especially the internet wasn't even around 1993, right? So barely around. What I
did was I, um, I stopped doing it because I was, I was afraid that the diet, I didn't know anything
about it. I thought we needed carbohydrates. I thought we needed. So for me, the biggest lesson
I learned was that I should have never got off the original, you know, keto slash carnivore
diet that worked really well for me. I'd gotten off of it for like 10 or 15 years until getting
back on it more recently in the past two years. But I feel like those years in between were lost.
I feel like I ruined them. I feel like because I wasn't optimizing my training along with my diet
that I kind of wasted those years, you know, if someone said to you, Hey, I want to learn how to
squat, but I can't come to you and your gym. What do you point them to me? And I typically point
people to videos that you do. Yeah. Like who, who are you liking on YouTube? Do you, do you have
instructional stuff on there? He's got a lot. Yeah. I have over 3000 videos on YouTube. So we,
you know, we have a whole media team and we, we pump out a lot of, a lot of information. The most
exciting thing is that he's got videos from Ed Cohen on there, Ed Cohen's best squatter ever,
you know, and, um, videos from Stan Efroning, the strongest raw power lifter ever, you know,
one thing that Mark Rippetoe did really well is and people will bash him because they don't like,
there's a lot of people that don't like the way that he squats, but really what he's trying to do
is he's trying to show you a universal way to squat and people are like, and a very safe way
to squat. Yeah. Yeah. Biomock. Yeah, it is very safe. A lot of people will say, Oh, he's leaning
over way too much. Well, most people can't squat in an upright position. They just don't have the
ankle mobility, the hamstring mobility. He's just trying to, he's trying to too, in a five minute
segment, tell everyone how to squat. And that's, I think people lose, lose sight of that. Give people
the benefit of the doubt. CrossFit is a great place for people to start, you know? So that's
interesting because, because there's some people that argue the opposite, right? Which is CrossFit
tries to take relatively untrained people and get them to do Olympic lifting. And even when you look
at Olympic lifters, they don't do that much Olympic lifting. I'll say this, there has never in the
history of the world has there been a better fitness program than what CrossFit puts out.
Nobody spends more time and more money on what they put together. I know because I've been on the,
on the back end of it, I've seen, I've seen what they do. I've seen what they do with their website.
I've seen what they do with all the different things. I'm not even a CrossFit nut. I don't
even care about CrossFit really, to be honest with you. One thing I don't like that they do is the
gymnastics element with adults is kind of a weird thing just because it's so hard to learn as you're
older, but so what? It's a deeper and stronger challenge, right? But when you start to learn
that they spend millions and millions of dollars, obviously they make millions and millions of
dollars, but when they spend millions and millions of dollars setting up a fitness contest that has
over 200,000 participants and it narrows it down to the number one man and number one female in the
world, I think that that's fucking awesome. And that's one of the coolest human studies that's
going on. They also teach a lot about nutrition. When you go on the back end of their website,
if you try to take one of those coaching courses, you will get absolutely slaughtered. I don't care
how much you know about fitness. You'll get destroyed in that. It is so hard to try to figure
out how to like referee some of these things or how to even answer some of these questions that
are on there. They have done an amazing job and I know that they're reaching out to a lot of leading
researchers when it comes to the nutrition aspect. I know they used to have Rob Wolf and they kind
of have moved around a little bit. I'm not sure if you ever spoke with them, but I know some others
that have and they do a good job of investigating and poking around and finding the right thing.
I'm not saying it's the answer for everybody, but if you are somebody that just has no clue on where
to start, I'd recommend try a CrossFit box because they're everywhere. They're all over the place.
Also understand that your first experience may not be great, just like if you went to a therapist
or you went to a healthcare professional, like they might suck, right? So what? Go and try another
spot. Go and try somewhere else. You should typically find that they're very encouraging.
The environment is very encouraging. They want you to exercise. They want you to get better.
Their business model isn't that of a huge chain gym where they're like, we just want you to sign
up for 20 bucks and never see you again. So I think CrossFit offers a lot. It teaches people how to
squat, teaches people how to deadlift. I do wish that they paid a little bit more attention to
people trying to gain muscle, a little bit more like a little bit more bodybuilding stuff, but
they keep evolving and they keep moving with the times. Let's actually talk a little bit about
that because you're in the process of doing exactly what you just described. You're training
for a bodybuilding competition. That's probably by the time this podcast come out, the bodybuilding
competition will have already taken place because it's in a few weeks. But you know, I was saying
before we started this, I think you and I, Chris, we were just playing patty cakes in the kitchen
and I was like, yeah, I was like, there are a few things I know less about than bodybuilding. Now,
which isn't to say that growing up, I wasn't obsessed with it, right? Like I fricking had
every copy of every magazine. I had pictures of Lee Haney all over my wall. Obviously I know every
single line of pumping iron, including all the outtakes. So you know enough. No, no. I mean,
I know that, but the point is I don't know anything about how to like make a person bigger. Like if
someone came to me and said, Peter, I want to get jacked. What should I do? My answer would be,
I have no clue. Like I don't know. I think it involves what you eat and how you lift,
but that's about all I know. So to me, this is like a super interesting art. So what have you
guys learned about this? And I want to specifically hear what you're doing. First things first, I
would say a lot of bodybuilders, a lot of people that are into bodybuilding get their start because
they start lifting for football or baseball or boxing or whatever, whatever else they're doing.
They start like lifting weights for to get prepared for something else. And then they
get bit by the bodybuilding bug. So I think powerlifting is a great place to start for most people.
And I think it's where most people do start is sort of like, start, I started benching for football
and then I started squatting. And then, you know, next thing you know, I was into bodybuilding. So I
think like a great way to just dive in and get started is through some sort of lifting program
that might aid something else that you're trying to do. That way you're also killing two birds with
one stone, you're getting better at what you're trying to do. And then, you know, who knows, this
might be something that you enjoy and want to pursue. And then powerlifting to me is, I don't
think I'd ever let my kids box. I just, I feel fortunate that I got out of it alive, minus the
IQ points I don't have. But I would love it if each of my kids at least spend some time powerlifting,
because whatever you go to do later in life, you will have correctly learned the mechanics of the
most important movements in the human body, which primarily come down in your area, San Diego,
is his name Jeff Martin? Oh yeah, crossfit kids. Okay. He started that like dissolve the name of
yeah. Now it's called X brand X something. But anyway, so yeah, his thing is awesome. He's got
all these kids involved in powerlifting, right? So I went Mark, that's awesome. Mark's company
slingshot, they sent me down to San Diego with a camera and said, go film this powerlifting meet
for kids. And it was all kids from like, I think ages like seven or eight, up to like 15. And out
of everything we've done on that channel, and everything we did with Mark's YouTube channel,
that was the most fun I've ever had. Just hanging out with kids that were like, you know, between
the ages of eight and 15, and having them say, Mark Bell changed my life. He wasn't able to make it.
He had like something else going on that day at the gym. But to go there and be able to interview
those kids and I would say, Oh, Mark's brother, they would get so excited that I was Mark's brother.
Like, no way, you know, Mark, my kids, my brother, like, no way you grew up with them. And to me,
it's like the joy of seeing these kids get involved in powerlifting was just exciting.
You know, I did a seminar there. And it was incredible to see the way these kids can move.
I was like, Oh my God, I was like really apprehensive about doing the seminar. It was like,
what is that going to look like? I go to all these CrossFit boxes. And I get asked to come in and
teach a seminar on how to squat bench and deadlift and takes me hours and hours on end,
because it's very, very difficult to teach people how to squat, meaning to teach adults how to
squat who haven't who are tight in the hips. Yeah, tight in the hips. Maybe they don't have
a lot of experience lifting or they just have bad experience lifting and they haven't learned
enough yet. Getting with these kids was crazy, though. I was so shocked. Their form on everything
was impeccable. I was like, Holy shit, because he runs a tight ship down there. He has the kids.
The first thing that you see when you walk in is, first of all, it says parents, please wait outside
for your child. They don't allow the parents to hang out in there. If you want to come in and check
the place out for a minute to make sure there's not a bunch of creepers around you, obviously you can.
But they want you to drop your kid off there. And the second thing that you see
is there's a room where kids go and they do their homework. And so it sends a message like, you know,
you're you're stopping here first, you're going to do your homework first, we're going to check in
with you, make sure you got all your stuff done. Then we're going to go lift weights.
I have a feeling his kids are going to end up at this gym. Well, it's interesting.
In Ramona. So when I remember when I saw my boy who I have a one year old and a four year old,
and then I who are both boys, and then I got a 10 year old girl, or almost 10 year old, and the
boy who's four, because he still isn't in school, meaning he's only in like, you know, whatever,
like goof off school. He doesn't actually he never sits in a chair. So any time I watch him
squat to pick something up, I go, Oh, stop there. I got to get a picture. Yeah, because it's like
form is great. The form is it's ridiculous. Your heels are down. Knees are open. Oh, my God.
Actually, that's like he looks like a little power. He looks like a little Hercules. Yeah.
And then conversely, my daughter who used to be able to do that now, you know, she's whatever,
just finished fourth grade. Her squats worse than mine. Like her form is horrible when I say,
Olivia, get down and squat for me. That's something I look at all the time. And I say,
how do we how do we maintain that in our children? Like how I wish I could have maintained that. And
I think that that's something that somebody needs to figure out. Well, I mean, I think the answer is
we're born with it is the first. Yeah, sure. We are all born knowing how to hip hinge. Exactly.
And I would argue that sitting is the thing that cripples us. It's a big part. And so how do you
maintain it? Well, you can't eliminate sitting, but you can minimize it, right? So if every kid
had a standing desk in school, for example, that's a step in the right direction, because
most of that sitting comes at school. And then secondly, it's like how you teach people the types
of exercises to do. There's people working on the standing desk thing. Our friend Kelly Starett is
leading that charge. Kelly and Juliette Starett leading the charge to have kids have stand up desks
and they're doing programs where they're raising money to make that happen. Do you know Kelly
Starett, mobility, what he's a crossfit guy. And they've had great success. They find that kids do
better in school when they stand too. So they've been another big element of, you know, having
children progress with some of those things rather than go backwards would be to simply have the
physical education, you know, have a little bit more emphasis than it does. It used to a real
physical education and now you can't really do it anymore. Kids can't do pull ups or pushups or run
a mile. And everyone should remember the president should be able to do some version of that. I'm not
saying everyone should be like super proficient at it, but you know, when you start in kindergarten,
you learn your ABCs, you start to learn some math and as you keep progressing, your English progresses,
your math progresses, you learn more stuff about history. It starts out with like George Washington
and you progress to learn more about American history and so on. But when it comes to the physical
education, not much really changes. It's like, it just is like playing and then it goes into like a
little bit more stuff and then it just completely fizzles out. And now it's a lot of times not even
in school anymore. We used to have that presidential physical fitness thing, right? And it actually was
like a program that made sense, but then they just completely like discontinued that kind of stuff. And
I think that like getting kids to be active, they're at school all day and then like gym class is like
nobody wants to get dressed for gym class and nobody does anything. A lot of times kids take the kids
out for a walk or something, you know, I mean, I don't know what's a ball around with a kid. I
would kick a ball around with a kid that I mean, if they're five, six, seven, they're not going to
turn that down. I do this stuff with my daughter when she comes in the gym with me in the morning
because in San Diego, I just work out at home. And one of the things I've got her doing, which is a
competition, is what's her, how long can she dead hang in a chin up? And she's, you know, I forget
what her record is now, but it's like, you know, the first time she did it, she could only hold 17
seconds or something like that. And now she's like over two minutes dead hanging. Really? Yeah.
She's a savage. That's pretty good. And you know, she's light as a feather. Yeah, but that's still
pretty cool. Right. So so now I can't hang for two minutes. I die after 30 seconds. Well, the fact that
she's getting an idea of what that's doing too. Well, and the funny thing that I love about doing
it is explaining to her the mental fitness. So that time she failed at 17 seconds, she just went
from hanging to failing. And I was like, Olivia, I didn't even see you shaking. I didn't see you
suffering. What the hell is going on here? Like, yeah, yeah. Like, I don't think you understand the
purpose of this exercise. You are trying to test the limit of what you're capable of by definition
that is going to hurt. And the other thing, oh, this is funny. Maybe I was wrong. That actually is
interesting. A kid doesn't register. Super healthy though, too, because sometimes in competition,
a kid may be more discouraged to swim next to the other kid next to them because they're like, I
don't, I just think if I try harder, I'm not going to get any further ahead. That kid's still going
to whoop my ass in this. It's just her versus her, which is cool. Yeah. And then I even once
she started to get the bug in her and she wanted to do it every day, she would go in and do it.
And I was like, look, Olivia, you got to take a couple of days off. Like if you really want to
hit this, you need to rest and recover a little bit and we'll start planking and doing all those
other things. So, you know, I hope Olivia, you need your electrolytes and we need to get you on some
PCA. How many egg yolks have you had today? Olivia, if you really want to do this, we're
going to push it. You're going to be the Olympic hanging champion. So what your first experience
with bodybuilding was when now this is it. This is your first one years old. So I'm dying to know,
like, can I not look like a pathetic guy? Like what would I need to do if I wanted to be half
as jacked as you bodybuilding is amazing. You can make changes really, really rapidly, make changes
really, really fast. For me, I'm very fortunate. I'm around a lot of people that have a lot of
great information and so I have the ability to have some accelerated success with the amount
of people that are surrounding me in this effort. But the diet is interesting. The cardio is
interesting. We're in a country that's so fat that there's like studies that show that cardiovascular
training is bad for you. That shows like it increases your estrogen and your cortisol so
much you can't release fat. I mean, just some of these things are it's really crazy to think that
people are trying to even study something like that. When you look at bodybuilding,
bodybuilders for years have done these certain things very specific ways and it works time and
time and time again. It just continues to work every single time. Bodybuilders are, you know,
partially responsible or probably largely responsible for ketogenic diet, even sticking
around the first place because they will always introduce some form of low carbohydrate living.
That's how I learned about it many years ago. But the discipline to do all the things
that you don't want to do when you normally don't want to do them is really, really powerful.
Stopping yourself from eating extra. Jay Cutler came into our gym recently. He's four time Mr.
Olympia and he said on a podcast that he... Can you explain to people what the difference is
between Mr. Olympia and any other bodybuilding contest? Yeah, the Mr. Olympia contest is the
Super Bowl. Yeah, that's what Arnold Schwarzenegger was seven times. That's what he was famous for
during the eight's and those guys. So, you know, this isn't just some schmuck. This is a...
This is the world's best bodybuilder for four years. Yeah. He said he ate seven times a day.
And I just sat there and went, wow, that's a lot of dedication to eat seven times a day. That means,
you know, all your meals are prepped and everything. And he said he ate the same food
at the same time every single day. He did his cardio at the same time. He did his weightlifting
at the same time. He would go tanning at the same time. He would get a hot tub, get a massage and so
on and go to sleep. All, you know, all these things were regimented out. So that way he never skipped
a beat and that way he could be precise and that way he could be the best. As he was talking about
all these things, I kept kind of dwelling on that seven meal thing because I've tinkered with some
intermittent fasting and I've teetered with some different things, but I was fixated on that. I'm
like, as I got into this bodybuilding stuff, I started asking some other guys. I'm like,
well, can you do this? And can you do that? They're like, no. I'm like, well, I can have like,
I'm supposed to have like 150 carbs a day, 65 grams of fat, 350 grams of protein. I'm like,
can I just have like a hundred grams of protein in one shot and have like a big steak meal? They're
like, no. And I'm like trying to figure out all these loopholes. They're like, there's no loopholes.
This is the way it's got to be. It's 50 grams of protein at every meal for seven meals. That's
350 grams of protein. That's what you're supposed to do. And so I finally got it through my fat
head that that's what I'm supposed to do. But these things are lined up in a very specific manner.
Now, when I went and started to try to look and poke around and figure out how many times a day
the average person eats, it was 15 times a day. Because there's so much snacking.
There's so much snacking. And I just never, I never even thought about it, but I'm like,
I'm on a diet all the time. I'm always trying to lose weight. And boy, do I sabotage the fuck out
of myself because I do that all the time. I'll grab, you know, and it's stuff that's, you know,
within this reasonable, healthy menu. Sure, sure. It's a handful of almonds or whatever it is.
Cheese stick. And you think you're so hungry and you think you need it to recover and you think you
need it to be jacked, but you just don't. You can actually handle eating a lot less than you're
currently eating is one thing to know. And you can actually handle a lot more training.
Now I'm not trying to suggest that you just get in this crazy mode of overtraining and develop,
you know, body dysmorphia and all these things. But I do think you could probably push yourself
a lot further than you know, currently. And when you, if you go from not implementing bodybuilding
stuff to implementing bodybuilding stuff, it makes a huge difference. I know you've been on
Joe Rogan's podcast. We've been fortunate enough to be on this podcast as well. He's the perfect
example. You take somebody like that already has a good structure or yourself. And you mentioned
kettlebell training and mentioned some different things. You were speaking with Daniel Rago and
telling him some of the things that you've been doing. I know and Daniel knows because we train
with Michael Hearn that if you implemented some bodybuilding stuff or not even some bodybuilding
stuff, if you if you just embraced bodybuilding period, you'd be able to look so much different
four weeks from right now. So give me an example, like a practical example. Probably up your protein
too. That's usually one. I don't know what it is now. So I can't really say that. But right now,
I'm in ketosis. So my protein is pretty low. It's probably about 100 grams a day.
Yeah, you probably want more like one point seven. So the science that I've heard, you know,
one point seven grams per kilogram of body weight will elicit muscle growth, right? So we need at
least that much. For me, it's 135 grams. So I think it's just like finding that number, sticking to
that number and like marks that incorporating some bodybuilding stuff. For me, the changes with extra
protein happened immediately. And like he'll tell you, it just changed. It was like one day,
I was skinny fat. Next day, I was muscular. And it was kind of kind of like that. But you
had is this rule of 50 grams per meal times the seven meals. I mean, presumably that's because
amino acids have a relatively short residence and you've got to kind of keep the exposure to those
things high for a longer period of time, right? And I at least get the hypertrophy, right? And
that's specifically for me. That's for my body weight. That's for the energy expenditure. That's
for my age with a general understanding of what I can do in the gym. I mean, maybe taking a step
back because I don't know. I weigh 230 pounds. But you're getting close to competition. So
you want to show up at the competition weighing what? You personally? I'm just going to kind of
end up where I end up, but I would imagine it would be another 10. There'd probably be another
eight to 10 pounds of actual weight loss before now and then. And they'll probably be another
five to 10 pounds of water weight that's dropped. I don't really know what they have in store for me.
But I guess estimate your body fat percent will be on the day of. Oh, I don't have any idea. But
I think I'll probably weigh about 215 pounds or 210 pounds. I think actually really the lower,
the lower that I weigh, I feel like the bigger that I'll probably look without getting, you know,
getting out of hand with that. Then I'll start. And at the peak of your building phase before you
begin this taper, how much did you weigh? I didn't have one because I was just kind of. You just came
straight out of powerlifting and. Yeah, I just kind of got shoved into it because I was, I was
dropping some weight, but I was probably about 240, 245. So that's, that's what I'm talking about.
It's the difference has only been, it's only been about 10 pounds, but it's crazy because like even
just on my YouTube channel, we posted a video a few days ago, but it's from about three,
about two, three weeks ago when I started all this. And it's me working on some posing.
I just flat out look fat, you know, compared to now, obviously not fat, but it's just fat,
flat out look fat. Yeah. Mark is like you said, he's got, he's in a position where he can talk
to some of the best people in the world about training diet and nutrition. And what he was
doing was a podcast with a Hani Rambad, who is the nutritionist for Phil Heath. Who's a.
Phil wean will win last year. Yeah. So he's now won seven consecutive.
And how many did Ronnie Coleman win? Eight. Eight. That's the most. Have you seen
Ronnie Coleman's documentary? I know that it exists. I should mention that because it was a
really great story. I thought Lee won seven. Oh, did Lee win eight? You're right. 84 to 91.
And then Yates won like six or both those guys won eight. Yeah. So Mark's working with
honey Rambad, who's helping him do his diet and stuff, which I think is amazing to be able to
have access to like the top people in the world. And he was working the other day with Charles
Glass doing posing and Charles is known as the godfather of bodybuilding. He's at gold's gym
every day. He trained Dexter Jackson for the 2008, you know, Mr. Olympia contest as well as like a
ton of other amazing person to, you know, he's been helping us both a lot. You hear different
things about the guy, but he just he trains at four o'clock in the morning. He wakes up at about
two thirty. He eats at three. He makes sure he gets his ass to the gym when he gets when he gets
to the gym. He's not full of like motivational talk or anything like that. But a lot of times
one of his first questions will be, would you eat this morning? And if somebody says they didn't
eat anything, he's just kind of he doesn't even really say anything. He just kind of like walks
off. But he's just it's almost like, oh, I guess you're not all in, you know, I guess you're not.
I guess you're not as into this as I thought, because this is this is the method that we're
going to use. So the nutrition is clearly important. And I mean, if there's one thing that's
clear and everything you're saying, it's just how empirically wise this this sport is, right?
I can't even eat at a restaurant because I can't afford to have any oil or can't I mean,
there cannot be I can't have a day where I have 120 grams of fat. It's I'm supposed to have,
you know, 65 grams of fat in a day. And if for some reason something was off and I had
70 or 80, it wouldn't be the end of the world. But I'm supposed to wait by percentage of macro,
what percentage of your calories are protein fat carbohydrate right now? I don't really know that.
Daniel would have to run the math over there. But Daniel, can you run those numbers for us, man?
350 and protein 65 grams of fat and 150 grams of carbohydrates. Sometimes the carbohydrates are up
a little bit from there, but the fats are 65. And you said the carbs 135. 150. Awesome math going
on. But you know, it's like I said, it's very specific and carbohydrates. Just to try to clear
everything up for people that are listening, because I know you're a keto proponent, and we
love the ketogenic diet. Ketogenic diet has always worked really well for me because it's allowed me
to keep control over the amount of food that I eat. It's one of the few things that has burned
off my hunger. It's one of the few things that have burned off my cravings. It's the only thing
that has ever done that before. Where in the bodybuilding cycle,
2600 calories, what's the percentage is the macros. We're getting some information from
Daniel Arago off screen here. For those that are interested. Oh, yeah, yeah. What's a Peter want
to know the macros for the fats probably. So it's 2600 calories is what you're saying.
Not a whole lot of calories. But you know, one thing on that is I don't feel deprived at all.
I feel like I'm eating because I'm eating every two and a half, three hours. And everyone keeps
talking about how brutal it is, how hard it is. And I know that it'll get worse because you do
start to calorie restrict. And they, you know, everyone says like the last two weeks kind of
feel like a zombie. But I've been feeling really good. And as I mentioned earlier, the progress is
the motivation is every day I see something new or different on me. And I'm like, Wow, I just didn't
even have any idea I could do any of this. I've tore both my biceps. I tore my pec three times.
I tore my hamstring. I've torn a bunch of stuff. And I never tried to consider to really bodybuild
because I was like, man, if I died down, I'd look weird because I've torn all that shit off my body.
People kept asking them for years, when are you gonna do a show you should get, you know,
you're getting lean. I kind of thought I was done. I was done powerlifting. I didn't have a
lot of direction and wasn't sure what I was going to do next. And so this challenge came,
uh, it came at a perfect time. And I don't, the challenge came from a podcast with honey, right?
Yeah. That's right. He was like, he was on his podcast and he said, well, why don't you do a show?
You look great. Well, he said, he said, he said it even more than that. He was like, I signed you
up for one. Yeah, you're doing it. So where does the ketogenic diet make sense for the bodybuilder?
What phase of, you know, is it when they're trying to get leaner? Yeah. I see. So for,
for, for some of the like pro bodybuilder guys, the ketogenic diet probably doesn't play into
anything they really want to mess around with, unless they've been destructive for a while
with their behavior. Like if they, if they have eaten, if they've gone way off the rails
and eaten, but a pro doesn't do that professional bodybuilder, somebody who's being serious, who's
trying to win money at these shows, they would not be somebody that would be doing that. So they
wouldn't even need to utilize a ketogenic diet where ketogenic diet would play into where it
would really help even somebody like myself, former fat kid is it'll help me to kind of continue to
tighten up. And it will also give me some mental freedom. I think one of the worst things you can
ever do, whether it's business or any aspect of your life lifting is get stuck in one thing.
Cause you thought of times you're, you're focused in on that one thing and you can't see anything
else. And so if you were always just doing a bodybuilding diet and if you were always utilizing
cardio for 45 minutes every day, all these things would become less effective. So where the ketogenic
diet can come in, you could utilize the ketogenic diet to become technically, uh, works out pretty
good on paper, but I don't know how it works in theory would be, you could become more sensitive
to carbohydrates by dumping in a ketogenic diet at certain points and changing up the style of
exercise that you do for awhile. Bodybuilding competitions, obviously Olympia is not a drug
regulated competition, correct? So you can't compete at that level without lots of drugs.
What about at the level outside of Olympia? So like this competition you're doing, is it a,
is it considered a drug free competition? I don't even know much about, I've never even been to a
bodybuilding show. So this, this is all very new to me. I, I've only caught the tail end of a
bodybuilding show at the Arnold classic where, you know, I went to go see Brian Shaw and some of
the bodybuilding stuff was finishing up and it was, it was impressive. I mean, it was, it was
pretty crazy to see those guys. Cause those are some of the best, uh, that's effectively the
Olympic level. That's Olympia level bodybuilding. You got Dexter Jackson up there. It was 51 or 52
years old. I mean, there's some real savages there, but, uh, yeah, I don't even know. Like I, I know
the posing I've been working on that, but I don't know like the categories and I barely know.
So for this competition, are you using anabolic steroids or diuretics or any of the other sort
of aids that one would use as in bigger, stronger, faster? You know, I talked about utilizing them
from the time I was 25 and I've been using them. I, you know, I've been, I say in the movie, uh,
I'm going to probably be on and off them the rest of my life. And that's what I believe it's
direction I chose when you choose a certain thing and you like the result of it. Like,
I don't feel like there's any reason to go back. And for me, for now as well, you know,
I get it prescribed, which is a kind of added bonus to making sure that it's like, I guess more on
the up and up, but to me, it doesn't really make any difference whether you grab it from some dude
at the gym or whether you get it from a doctor. I actually think that the, I think that, uh, you
know, there's, they're not going to be all that regulated anyway, no matter, no matter how you
slice it, but, but what are the, again, I don't know anything about how body builders use steroids.
What are the, what are the, you know, body mass is the main thing. So people get confused about
what they actually do. People get confused about what steroids do. I think people think that,
that steroids automatically make you strong and they don't necessarily automatically make you
strong. What they do in most cases is they allow people to gain more weight. Now there's some cases
where people don't gain a whole lot of weight and they do gain strength, but if you don't continue
to gain weight at some point, that strength will only level up so much. So when you introduce
steroids, steroids don't multiply on top of themselves. They only work to a certain level.
So you're, you're on level one with your lifting and you progress and your genetics and everything
allow you to get to level four. You take steroids and maybe over a period of time, you get to like
level six, but you're still not going to be able to get to level eight, nine or 10 where these guys
like Jay Cutler and some of these mammoth people are because of their genetics, because of their
environment as children, because of X, Y, and Z, you're probably just never going to be able to
level up to their potential. But which is an important distinction because I think a lot of
people, your starting point as well, a lot of people look at, you know, let's just make
Phil Heath because he's the best in the world today and you're going to think it's all drugs.
It's all drugs, but I don't think people understand like I could inject a human being
with every anabolic steroid period. Like let's get the world's supply of anabolic steroids and
inject it into me. Yeah. I couldn't look one 10th of what that guy looks like. Right. And the best
coaching and the best whatever people like to make things easy and simplify it and they can't come
close to Phil Heath. They can't even come close even with a ton of drugs. So they just want to say,
oh, it's just steroids. It's not, it's not like, oh, this guy works harder. This guy's better.
And I do think that steroids cloud the sport. I do, I do think that if there was a way to get
steroids out of the sport, that it could be more popular across the mainstream. However,
well, it's part of the reason why it has become more popular because they do have like men's
physique and they got some of these different categories. Now where you're seeing, you're
seeing more men and women. It's gotten more main, more mainstream with some of that stuff.
The body types don't look as crazy, right? Yeah. Now there's a, um, a category called
classic physique. And it's like, it's interesting because like in the very first year of classic
physique, my friend, Danny Hester, he won Mr. Olympia classic physique. He's about 190 pounds.
He looks awesome. He's always, he always looks awesome. He's about my height, 190 Jack shred.
It looks amazing. And then the next year, the guy that wins, it's like 240. You know what I mean?
You're like, this is not classic physique anymore. Like, yeah, like what happened to the
little guys that were in great shape, you know? And the guy that won looked, he looked amazing,
but it's, and it's a different look than the bigger bodybuilders, but it's not like,
it's not yet a natural thing. It's not like one guy is natural. One guy's on. It's like,
they're just on different levels, right? Yeah. So classic doesn't mean drug-free. It means
you're trying to produce a phenotype that is, you're trying to look like Arnold Schwarzenegger
is like, what's funny is like now they have a category. Arnold Schwarzenegger was Mr. Olympia
seven times. He was considered in the Guinness book of world record, the greatest male physique,
which is just a title he gave him. He couldn't win a California bodybuilder. That's what I'm saying.
He can't win anymore. Like so, so they, if you look like Arnold, you'd win classic physique now,
which is kind of crazy. So who's your favorite seventies, eighties bodybuilder?
Frank Zane, Mike Mencer, Mike Mencer. Yeah. And Arnold. Arnold's a really big, uh,
influence fan of Dorian Yates too. You know, we blood and guts. A lot of that was my,
he was, he was later, right. Um, nineties. Oh yeah. And Mencer and Yates actually have quite a bit in
common. They trained, they trained together too. And, um, I trained with Mike Mencer when I first
came out here, when I moved out here in 93, like you see people at the gym and your meat head. Uh,
first thing I did was I'm training with Mike Mencer. Yeah. I don't care. He blew out my knee
because he had me do these crazy squats in the squat machine and it messed up my knee for like
six months, but it's, I still had got to train with him that which was cool. But at the time I
got to train with him, I showed up at the gym and he was outside smoking a cigarette and he's all
fat. And it was just like, Oh, this is Mike Mencer now. This is what he is, you know? And it's like,
you know, a lot of times in life, especially me, I've met all my heroes and pretty much everybody's
let me down. So it's just the way life is. I guess. Have you ever met a hero that where they exceeded
your expectation? Um, I don't know. Let me see. Have we? Yeah, we have many times. I'm sure,
I'm sure we have. Yeah. Ed Cohn, Stone Cold Steve Austin's one of my favorite people in the entire
world. He's amazing. He's so intelligent. Joe Rogan's. He's so well researched. Like he just,
he's just awesome to be around. Like there's, there's people like that. I think where we,
Jay Cutler was like, the rock, the rock is an amazing dude. Like when you meet the rock,
you're like, well, it's all probably just an act, but the rock will look you in the eye,
shake your hand and say, how's your mom doing? Like, and he means it, you know, and you could,
you could feel that he means it. And, uh, and that's important, especially when you're that
big of a celebrity and stuff like that, you know, one of the things I struggle with, and I was
actually talking about this a little bit when I was on Joe Rogan's show, I've been pretty vocal
and open about my view that once I really spent like five years learning everything there was to
learn about anabolic steroids, I came to the conclusion that, well, I can't speak to what
happens in bodybuilding because I think that takes it to a different level, but certainly within the
level of how they're used in cycling or, you know, more physiologic levels of use, I can't see any
evidence of harm. Now, EPO is different. You can certainly take too much EPO and cause problems,
but once you start talking about testosterone, stenazolol, oxandrelone, these drugs that are
typically used in sports, again, I was having a very hard case. I'll give you, I'll show you
right here, my tricep. It's torn. I was bench pressing 455 after it, my triceps hurt a little
bit. They were sore. And then I popped my tricep. I've never been hurt lifting in my entire life.
At the time I was on a ton of juice. So you're, you're arguing with me that you just didn't have
the tendon strength necessarily. And I attribute that to steroid use for sure. 100%. So to say
that there's no ill effects of them or no side effects or no, I guess I'm thinking more of the
cardio metabolic liver, kidney, cardio. No, but can you injure yourself? You know, Joey Diaz, one
of my favorite people in the world. He's hilarious. He says, he's like, you see these guys in the gym
and they're like 50 years old and they used to take steroids and now they just like, like a bag of
shit. You know, it's like, I kind of agree with that statement too, that there are a lot of people
that have taken steroids and abused them and gotten really crappy skin and crappy, like just,
you know, things that, uh, that don't look good, not aesthetic and probably not healthy. I'm sure
that they've driven a lot of people's blood in a bad direction, which could, which could lead to
other things possibly. Right. But, but not definitely. So I think that's where we're
looking at like the detrimental effects of steroids would be among, it's like among the users that are
losers. If that makes sense. It's like, it's among the users that, that aren't paying attention to
everything else. Yeah. And I guess under medical supervision though, when you're again doing these
things within physiologic doses, which is pretty different than what the average person is doing.
We're talking like something that a doctor would prescribe. Yeah. Well, you know, for example,
you take somebody whose testosterone is like two standard deviations below the mean and you
revert them back to the mean or median level of testosterone. If we're going in that respect,
I would have to go back and say that you're a hundred percent right. I haven't seen anything
like even a muscle tear on a normal dose, but I was, I was using pretty good doses. I was just
trying to, well, at the time I was using trend balloon and I was using testosterone together.
And then I was taking some other oral stuff. It was like right after I got out of rehab,
like I gotta get jacked, you know, and like, and it's funny cause they tell you in AA that if you're
on steroids, it affects you from the neck up and you're not allowed to take them. So people got on
my case about and how much testosterone just 200 milligrams a week. I've always stuck to the
200 milligrams. I never really went above that because I never wanted to get like puffy, you
know, which is interesting cause I don't think I've, if I've ever replaced a person's testosterone,
which I've done many times exogenously for patients who are low, I've never had a patient
that high and 200 is not high from a performance standpoint. I've seen guys show up. What is it?
Usually a hundred. I mean, yeah, if I'm going to start a patient again, I'm, I have, it's much more
complicated. I need to know their sex and we're binding globulin, their estrogen, their free
testosterone is really what we're trying to fix. But very unusual that I would ever start a patient
anything more than 50 milligrams twice a week. It's interesting cause everybody I know is on the
same, goes the same doctor has the same dose. So it's, it's just the, well, and again, it's a very
different, it's a very different thing. I'm where I try to optimize for me. My interest in replacing
testosterone is resolving insulin resistance, preserving muscle mass. Like it's a, it's a bunch
of other things. It's interesting that you say that and it actually gives me a lot more confidence
in going to somebody talking to somebody like you. It's like, I just know almost everybody that's on
testosterone. They all take 200 milligrams. Like I don't think I've, I think I've once had a patient
take a hundred twice a week. So I think it would, I think when you're saying it is like, oh wow,
you actually, you actually don't give everybody the same dose. You know, first of all, I don't even
like, I mean, most, most patients that I need to replace testosterone in, which is still a
minority of patients, I'm not using testosterone, right? My first goal is can you get them to
endogenously make testosterone? So, you know, the way I, I have a, and what are you utilizing to do
that? Yeah. So I start with the final thing I care about is free testosterone. So a free testosterone
is low and I define low as somewhere between one and two standard deviations below the mean of our
reference range in the lab and symptomatic. So you have to have these two things in my opinion.
So if, if the number's low, but I see no evidence of symptom, meaning they're not having a difficult
time maintaining muscle mass. They don't have too much adipose tissue. They're not insulin resistant.
Labitos fine. All of these things. Then I don't believe in fixing the number, but let's assume
you have someone who's symptomatic and who's low. So free testosterone is low. The next question is,
is free testosterone low because testosterone is low or because sex and we're binding globulin is
high because free testosterone, which is what matters is proportional to testosterone and
inversely proportional to sex and we're binding globulin. So once you answer that question,
if sex and we're binding globulin is too high, you have to investigate why. And there are really
only four reasons for it. Insulin, thyroid hormone, estrogen, and genetics. So you, you do your
investigation. You figure out what's going on. If testosterone is too low, the next question is,
is it too low because you're siphoning too much of your testosterone into either dihydrotestosterone,
DHT or estradiol? Yes or no. If yes, you can block both of those, right? You have five alpha
reductase inhibitors. You have aromatase inhibitors. If it's low, not because you're siphoning too much
away, then the question is, are you not producing enough? And if you aren't producing enough, are
you not producing enough because you don't have enough DHEA, which is a substrate, or do you not
have the pituitary signal? Is your FSH and LH too low? So there are actually nine steps in
understanding someone's testosterone and free testosterone level. And we can actually impact
every single one of those steps pharmacologically if we're trying to put this in service. So,
so yeah, it's a, it's a much different approach when you're doing it for medical management.
This kind of blows my mind too, because I'm going like, wow, there's now, so this is like, you know,
you learn something new every day. It's like, I'm just used to people taking 200 milligrams of
testosterone. Now you just turn me on to nine different ways that I can increase things. You
know, it's like, right. You can give a person, you can give them something that stimulates LH or FSH
production. So there's a pre-hormone that's a synthetic hormone that mimics, well, it mimics
basically an estrogen molecule at the hypothalamus that then tells the pituitary to make more FSH
and LH. That in many ways is a... And now you're putting this into practice clinically and you're
seeing awesome results with it. Yeah. And this is funny, this is one of those things that we learned
sort of from people who were doing this, but it's now actually become, I mean, I would hesitate to
say mainstream because I don't think people are fully mainstream in understanding this, but now
you're seeing this stuff published in medical literature that says, hey, there are really
reasonable safe ways to increase a person's testosterone without even giving them testosterone.
Well, you can also start with... I'd be more interested in that.
Even without supplementation, right? There could be certain foods, right? There could be certain
foods to avoid. Maybe somebody doesn't have a sound diet. I mean, a sound diet has to throw you out.
To me, the first step in evaluating a male for hypogonadism, which is just the technical term
for low testosterone, especially if the... So this is a not uncommon finding. The guy has low
free testosterone, but his estradiol is not too high. His sex and
testosterone is low. So that tells you where the problem is. The problem is in the brain.
And the number one diagnosis for that is sleep deprivation. So when I finished residency,
I didn't measure free testosterone. I only knew my total testosterone, but it was 220. That was
on a scale where two standard deviations below the mean was 350. Two standard deviations above
the mean was 1200. And I'm 220. Yeah, after my hip replacement, I was 49. That's when I got on it.
Yeah, 49. I mean, most women have a higher testosterone. My doctor just said,
I don't know how you get out of bed. I don't know. I just do. So in my case,
my testosterone went from 220 to about 650 by just sleeping. Once I went from not sleeping
four hours a night, boom, that improves. A lot of Americans are not sleeping because they're obese,
because they're heavy. So if they could figure out a way to get momentum, get the diet straightened
out, get to sleep a little bit better, they could start heading the right direction too.
Yeah. And the other thing is cortisol. So if you have hypercortycelemia, that is going to negatively
impact testosterone production directly and indirectly. What is hypercortisol?
High levels of cortisol. That's all it is? Yeah. Yeah. In medicine, we have to come up with
fancy ways to say things because it makes us feel smarter. So if you have too much cortisol,
one, you have a shunt, right? You have something called a pregnealone shunt or steel, where you
start to steal precursors of testosterone to make more cortisol. So that's depleting you of substrate
to make this. But I think perhaps the more sinister issue is these high levels of cortisol
impair you from entering what's called delta wave sleep, which is where you make the FSH and LH to
make the testosterone. You only make this stuff when you're sleeping. What about, you know, there's
a lot of doctors that are like are prescribing stuff to people and they'll prescribe some of
these cholesterol, you know, medications. Statins. These statins. Yeah. They're probably damaging,
right? I mean, some of these things are probably damaging towards just a natural male testosterone
and even with the females and stuff. Aren't these things kind of plaguing us a little bit too?
In theory, you could make an argument that says if you take a statin, which is inhibiting cholesterol
synthesis, and given that you need cholesterol to make sex hormones, that should be depleting them.
But we don't actually see that in the data. So even though it's a no, you don't actually see that now
that doesn't mean that at extreme levels, it won't show up. I think I've been saying that for years.
Well, like it blocks your cholesterol and that's what makes your hormones. It turns out that's
probably overly simplistic. The body is more complicated and more rigorous than we give it
credit for. So the body will prioritize its use of cholesterol for two things above all else,
which is forming cellular membranes because cholesterol is what gives a cell its fluidity,
membrane fluidity, and then hormone production. So particularly glucocorticoids and sex hormones.
So does that mean that you couldn't statinize a person into the next millennium end up suppressing?
No, it doesn't. You probably could. But I think at the levels that most people are taking them,
the evidence would not actually suggest that we're inhibiting endogenous testosterone production.
I think with what I do, I was made the movie Prescription Thugs and then all of a sudden,
I'm like, statins are bad. Stay away. And then I listen to you talking. You had a really
intelligent conversation with Dr. Kraus. Ron Kraus.
Ron Kraus. And the guys are all talking about statins the whole time. Like,
wait a second. These guys don't know that they're bad. And I'm like, well, these are the guys that
actually know what they're talking about. They treat people every day. And so it kind of opened
my mind back up to statins. So I think a lot of times when we're doing research or we're trying
to find out the truth or whatever, I was like, oh, statins are all bad. And I just think all one
way. And I'm trying to not think that way about things. Like where I'm thinking nothing's all bad,
nothing's all good. And that's kind of the way to bring this thing full circle as we probably wrap
up so we can let you guys get back to your day. At the outset, I said you kind of in many ways
opened my eyes to revisiting something that I just assumed was dogma. Steroids are bad. If you have
one milligram of testosterone, cypionate injected into a human being, you will kill them. That was
my view. And then I come away from bigger, stronger, faster. And I'm like, maybe I got to
rethink this. Now it's not to say I have any understanding or expertise of how steroids are
used in bodybuilding or things like that, where I suspect they can still be harmful if abused,
but certainly within medical, physiologic levels. Yeah, where is it relative to your life and to
your patients? I now, I honestly believe that anabolic steroids when used at physiologic levels
are safer than Tylenol. Yeah, absolutely. You know, are far less toxic and frankly,
you know, far less likely to lead it to morbidity. And so similarly, maybe you'll leave this
discussion thinking, okay, maybe it's not statins are all bad. Maybe the idea is they got to have
a time and a place. The overall overarching thing I've learned from making this movie about nutrition
that Mark and I are working on right now is that nothing is all good and nothing is all bad. And
Mark has been really illustrating that to me as we go through, he goes, see, carbs are all bad,
right? See, they're all bad. And it's like, well, no, now I can see how you can use them as a tool,
right? And then statins are all bad. No, no, now we can see how we can use them as a tool and we
can keep people alive longer. And certain people, you might need this tool only for a couple of
weeks to get you to this point and then you can get off of it or whatever. Like it's, it's allowed
me to think more openly about everything that we put in our bodies and everything that we do to
try to be better. Yeah. That when we were inhaling some food before this and you shared your salmon
with me, which was fantastic by the way, especially with that Himalayan sea salt, that was damn good.
I can't take credit all the way to the Himalayas for that. Yeah. The wife, he cooked that up too.
So that was wonderful. But that was a great example of, I mean, again, I know you're in the
midst of a bodybuilding competition prep, but it was beautiful to just see how regiment it's like,
I'm going to have this many grams of salmon. I'm going to have this many Japanese sweet potatoes.
And it's like, you know what? In this moment, these molecules are the tool I need. And I think
that's the takeaway to me is a statin, a carbohydrate, a whatever, it's a tool. And, and the key to me,
if you want to be a great carpenter in life, which I think is should be our, all of us should want to
be the best carpenters in life is have the most tools, know how to use each tool and know when to
use each tool. And when I have patients say to me, doctor, I am morally against fill in the blank.
I am morally against statins. I am morally against supplements. I am morally against XYZ. I say,
okay, I'll never force you or try to talk you into doing anything. But that's sort of like a
contractor coming to my house to rebuild it. And me saying, I just don't want you using the Phillips
screwdriver or the saw. You can do anything else, but don't use those too. That's strike. Can he still
build the house? Of course. But I've just taken away two tools and a lot harder in the hands of
a good carpenter that, that, you know, that seems like a bad idea. So you guys have opened my mind
up to a set of tools known as steroids. And you opened our minds up. Well, very well. Open your
mind. Guys where, so, so tell me when, when's the doc going to come out? So we don't know. I mean,
one question I should just say, a lot of people ask us, when's it going to come out? And they also
ask us like exactly what it's going to be about or what we're trying to say. And I can tell you,
I don't know either answer at all. I have no idea. So every film that I do is a journey. I never know
when it's going to end. It makes a lot of people that work with me mad. And I just say, well, like,
that's just how I do it. Like if you go, okay, we're going to make this movie. We're going to film
for six months and we're going to edit for three months and then we're done. And you, you can do
that. That's like a way to, to do it. But I feel that for example, Mark and I started this movie.
He had no idea he was going to do a bodybuilding show. So, but that's got to be in the movie. That's
awesome. That's like a really cool thing that's actually happening. So what if I just decided like
in the beginning of the movie, when we first started filming, I decided I only want to film
this, then we wouldn't have this whole bodybuilding thing, which could end up being what adds a layer
to it that makes it connect all the dots for people. Totally makes it more nuanced. Or whatever,
right? So we don't really know. But I would say that in general, we're planning on it just coming
out next year, because we're not worried about it for this year. And we're just planning on making
the best thing that we can. And so we like to encourage everybody, like people send me a lot
of information and people give me a lot of tips and I'm open to all of it. I listen, I listen and
read all my comments and everything because I'm open to whatever's going to make the best film.
I'm not trying to set out to make one specific thing. So between when this comes out and when
this film comes out, what is the best way for people to reach you, Chris? They can just find me
on Instagram at big strong fast. That's kind of the one thing that I check all the time. So okay.
And what about you, Mark? Twitter, too. You can't get a hold of me, because I've got too much shit
to do. But one thing I want to encourage everybody to do is really simple, because nobody ever knows
where to start. And we don't get a lot of answers, because people that are smart don't give you
definitive answers, because that's just the way it goes. Just try to start walking. You know,
almost all of us are lucky enough to have the ability to put one foot in front of the other.
Try to go for a 10 minute walk every day. Talk to your son, your daughter, your mom, your dad,
if they live close by, or if you can get a second with them. Do it after lunch, do it after dinner.
Preferably, it'd be great if you can do it more than once a day. But it's just a great place to
start. A great way to clear your mind. There's a lot of shit going on nowadays. If you have
an hour and a half, or whatever it might be, to be on Instagram all day, you certainly can carve
out 10 minutes for yourself every day to go on a walk. Really, really simple, easy thing to do.
And because people aren't going to be able to reach out to you directly, they want to be able
to take advantage of the amazing stuff you've already done. What's your YouTube channel?
Yeah, it's the YouTube channel is Super Training 06. You can also check out my Instagram, which is
at Mark's Melly Bell. And you can also check out my website, which has all my products,
Slingshot, the hip circle, some of the stuff you've seen, which is markbellslingshot.com.
One thing that we haven't talked about, but it'll leave it up to people to go watch it,
is my new film, A Leaf of Faith, which is about Kratum.
That's right. We didn't even get to that.
Well, we didn't really get to it, but I'll explain it really quick. Kratum is a plant that comes from
Southeast Asia that a lot of people are using to get off of opioids. And they're also using it just
to feel better. Like for me, every day I use it as a pre-workout. It just makes me feel great before
I get in the gym. I've gotten a lot stronger because of it. I've gotten in better shape because
I can focus better. So A Leaf of Faith is available on iTunes. It's available on Google Play,
YouTube, and Amazon right now. It's not on Netflix yet?
It's on Netflix on August 27th. And then when it comes out August 27th, I think that's going to be
sort of the real launching point for it because with all my movies, I put them on iTunes and they
go around. When it gets to Netflix, that's when people start talking about it. So I'm excited.
Yeah. It's a good segue into he and I have created a product together because we believe in Kratum
so much. It's helped us so much. It's helped us manage pain. It's helped us to continue on our
diets even. Sometimes in life, you just need something else to do. You need your mind to be
a little bit distracted from your day-to-day grind. And it's a great product. It gives you some euphoria.
It's helped me with creativity and business and stuff like that. And the product is going to be
called Mind Bullet and you'll be able to get it at mindbullet.com. All right. So we're going to link
in the show notes to where people can find you, Chris, on social where they can see all the stuff
you've put out. I'm actually really excited to hear. I didn't even realize I'm embarrassed to say
that you had this YouTube channel with all of these videos because I'm always looking for ways
if I can't plug one of my patients into a trainer that I trust to teach them the correct mechanics,
I actually don't want them to just learn to squat on their own. I kind of want them to be able to
see how it's done. So this will be a great reference as somebody that's contributed content
to Mark's YouTube page. I could say that he puts in more effort and time than a lot of people that
I see that are putting out videos. They put out almost, is it a video a day? They crank at like a
breakneck speed to like, it's like a movie studio over there. So he's just constantly cranking stuff
out. And it always features like all these people from the fitness industry that people love to see.
And he's always got great information. So I commend him as a filmmaker. I'm giving my brother
props for having a great YouTube channel. We spend probably over a quarter million dollars a year
just on our YouTube channel just to get information out there. Obviously, it promotes the brand,
promotes the product, but it's I really love trying to get that information out there to arm people,
give people, you know, give people information that they need. Anybody listening to this podcast
that ever wants to come check out Super Training Gym, Super Training Gym is free. I can't always
guarantee that I'm there. But if you want to look up that Instagram, it's at Super Training Gym as
well. Hit up whoever answers questions on there. And they will let you know if and when I'm around
and when you can come in. But the gym is free. In and of itself, that is just an unbelievable
service. Guys, I want to thank you both not just for your generosity and time today, but obviously
more importantly for all the work you guys have been doing over the past decade plus to share what
you've learned with not just me. I'm personally grateful for that. But obviously by extension,
many more people. So we're very grateful as well. We're huge fans right back at you. And I love your
podcast. So I'm excited to be on it and be part of it. Well, you guys are part of the inaugural set.
And if the podcast ends up sucking, you guys will know that you were you managed to be in that
exclusive. We're in good company. Sucking, sucking podcast. All right. Thank you. Thanks, Peter.
You can find all of this information and more at Peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode. You can also find my
blog and the nerd safari at Peteratiamd.com. What's a nerd safari you ask? Just click on the link at
the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively
non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting
papers I've read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeteratiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the
obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this
podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have
and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit Peteratiamd.com forward slash about.