Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode of the drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
My guest this week is my friend, Apollo Ono. For those of you who might not recognize Apollo,
which I would guess is not many of you, Apollo Anton Ono is an eight time medalist in the
Winter Olympics across three games, 2002, 2006, 2010 in short track speed skating, which
is one of the most intense, crazy sports to watch. We're going to have lots of videos
of it in the show notes. And if that weren't enough, he also went on to win Dancing with
the Stars, which sadly we don't get into in this episode, though I wish we did because
we were talking about it over dinner. And it's simply another manifestation of the type
of drive and determination that he brought to his sport. He brought to that show as well.
He has a really unique upbringing and he was raised by a single dad and his father, who
was an immigrant, played just an unbelievable role in his life through the good times and
the bad, which I know might sound like a bit of a cliche, but the level and the detail
at which we go into it in this podcast, I think is quite inspiring. There's no question
that at least in my mind that had Apollo been raised by somebody other than his father,
it's very hard to imagine he would have achieved the success that he has achieved. His father's
role in his life has just been unbelievable. And I think that's a common theme we see in
the people who are the greatest. One of the things that I didn't really fully appreciate
prior to this podcast was how this entire nation of South Korea basically grew to hate
him in ways that are almost impossible to describe following a very controversial race
in 2002. We go into that in great detail, so I'm not going to go into the whys and the
whats now, but the story is incredible, both how he got to that point of being so despised
by an entire nation and also how he basically went into the belly of the lion to confront
this head on and ultimately the finish to that story is as remarkable as how he got
there. Apollo has been known even inside the circles of Olympic athletes as having kind
of a surreal approach to training and we're going to link to some videos, including one
that is my absolute favorite with some of his training routines, but his discipline,
his work ethic are legendary once that switch was clicked. He spent the early part of his
career basically riding on talent and then just realized, nope, I'm going to go all in
on this. I never want to finish a single race and have a single regret. His determination
character responds to adversity. I mean, they're certainly inspirational to me. And frankly,
I think this is of all the podcasts I've ever recorded. If I was going to say to my
kids, I want you to listen to one. This is the one I want them to hear at least of all
the podcasts I've done so far because this to me is really about grit and I feel very
strongly that that's arguably one of the, if not the most important, one of the most
important things we want to be able to instill in our children is a sense of grit. So hopefully
this will serve to give my kids a lesson on that and potentially for yours as well. The
parallels between Apollo's life and Rocky Balboa are just amazing to me and I can't
resist making those comparisons a few times and not withstanding the fact that his name
is also Apollo and of course Apollo Creed though, spelt with two L's is the fictional
character that is one of the most important antagonists of Rocky Balboa. That that's not
lost on me, but if I were to sum up one Rocky-ism that sort of explains Apollo's life, it's
the one where Rocky Balboa in the sixth installment of that movie series is explaining to his son
that it ain't about how hard you hit. It's about how hard you can get hit and keep moving
forward and obviously I love that as a, as a metaphor for life, but I think it's illustrated
here. Apollo is just a great storyteller and he's, he's a beautiful speaker and I think
that's reflected in the fact that this interview goes on for almost four hours. It would have
easily gone on for six or seven had we not already made commitments to do other things
that evening. So I hope you find this interview half as interesting as I did. I think the
show notes will have some really great stuff in them and there's going to be links to some
really cool videos that we allude to, including not just races, but some of the other stuff
that goes above and beyond that. Lastly, just a couple things on some housekeeping. Every
Sunday I send out a weekly email that has been getting great feedback from the people
who subscribed to it. So if you don't subscribe to that, please do. If you end up thinking
it sucks, you can always unsubscribe from it. Secondly, we've got a team of both Bob
Kaplan and Travis Denson who do an incredible job putting together show notes. Again, the
feedback we get is there is no podcast out there that puts together show notes the way
we do. It's basically a full time job for one person, a part time job for another person.
And I believe that that shows in the volume of stuff that we're putting out there. So
if you're enjoying the podcast, at least take a look at the show notes because you'll
probably find something else that you might have missed or that becomes more clear. Lastly,
if you are enjoying this, please head over to Apple podcast reviews, give us a review
if it's favorable. Great. If it's not, please at least be constructive in your criticism
so that we can figure out how to make this show even better. Without further delay, here
is my guest today, Apollo. Hey Apollo, thanks for coming down, man.
Thanks for having me.
It's kind of funny that we're doing this now as opposed to what we were supposed to
do.
The original plan though, as I mentioned, is very memorable and I'll never forget it.
The fact that we have a nice dinner, we're chatting, we're getting the rhythm. Okay,
and then just follow me. We're going to shoot this place. It's right on the water. We're
in Malibu. It's perfect. It's very quiet. Guys, we have a problem. I don't have keys.
I locked myself out. Yeah. The only saving grace is it could have been a lot worse if
I'd killed myself or broken a bone, hopping that fence to crawl around the back of the
house to try to get in. That would have been-
No, you seem pretty athletic. I was like, oh, he's okay. If you were struggling over
the first fence, I was like, okay, maybe I should get my hand, but he's got it. He's
pretty good.
You held the light for me. It was awesome.
Thank you. Now on lighting and grip, Apollo.
I'm the main act here. I do the fence hopping. I do the wall scaling, but yeah, I need to-
Get rid of that Arnold guy. His lighting skills are just below average, bottom of the
rung.
By the way, all guests who come to my house, you have to drink Topo Chico. Is that your
first Topo Chico?
It was my first. It was nice. I love the glass bottle. I love the fact that you love it and
you're so passionate. When you give it to me, it's like you're giving me keys to the
house for the weekend. It's like, tell me how it is after you're finished.
Well, I like the fact that only halfway through the first bottle, you asked for a second,
so you've got that other one.
It's nice. Yeah. It's a strangely addictive quality.
Yeah. When I first got into it, it was out of control. I was like, why am I drinking
six of these a day? It's became an expensive habit because they're hard to find. Well,
man, there is so much I want to talk about and I think we'll hopefully be able to get
to much of it, though probably not all of it just by the nature of the depth we'll probably
go into on some stuff. But let's, for lack of a better plan or strategy, let's just go
back to the beginning. So you grew up in the Pacific Northwest.
I grew up in the Pacific Northwest. I was a very high energy kid, one who was mischievous
because I think just had tons of energy. My father was working most of the time to provide
so that we didn't struggle too much more than we already did, which I didn't know at the
time.
And your dad grew up in Japan, came to the US. Do you remember how old he was?
He said he's about 17 and a half years old when he came from Japan to ... I think he
landed actually in Oregon originally and he just started his life. He didn't speak a word
of English. He didn't really know anything about the American culture other than what
was kind of fed to him when he was in Japan. The only focal point he said that he had was
that he just needed to get outside of the protocol-like lifestyle that was existing
within the Japanese culture. I think that to him meant going to the place that was a
complete 180 and that was the United States.
So he left on his own at 17 and a half.
He left on his own against my grandmother and grandfather's wishes, which they wanted
him to go to school, study, eventually work for a university and just kind of follow the
same path that most, I think, Japanese follow. This is what you're supposed to do. This is
what you will do and this is what your life is going to be on a day-to-day basis.
Something inside my dad just said, I don't want that. I don't want that type of future.
He came and he risked a lot. He didn't have any money. I think he had a camera in which
he sold upon his arrival and that's what he used to begin his life. I can't even imagine
how difficult that must have been coming to the US, not speaking a word of English in
a time where Japanese were not exactly the most accepted people in our country. Then
trying and he used to tell me, he was like, I was a bartender. I was like, how could you
possibly be a bartender if you don't speak English? My dad's just really short too. I
can only imagine what that looked like. Also, the grief that he probably got from all the
people who were ordering drinks that he would probably mess up. He said that he slammed
his head against the door many, many times to try to figure it out and he did.
Yeah, it's not exactly a forgiving crowd, right? Six drinks in, when someone gets their
drinks screwed up, they're less likely to be empathetic to the guy struggling.
Yeah, I'm sure it was really challenging. Then my dad, weirdly, he said that he was studying,
I think he was studying accounting and then someone asked, oh, he was walking by one of
the classes, was hosting a hair cutting competition. That's when my dad said, oh, that looks interesting.
I could use some extra money. Let me try that. He ended the competition, essentially, got
in third place or something randomly and then began his career to pursue being a hairstylist,
which is really, really, if you knew my dad, it makes sense now, but even when I hear the
story, it's just that nothing adds up. He begins his life and he actually was and started
a pretty interesting career as a hairstylist and more than a barber, I guess you could
say and was starting to travel the world, had some success and he said that everything
was changed, obviously, when I was born and upon my arrival, both my father and my mom,
I think they were obviously going through some conflicted times and so they divorced.
My father took full custody of me and he didn't know how to raise a child. His only...
How old was your dad? Do you remember when you were born?
I don't know because my dad told me he's been 35 since I was born, which is funny.
That's a great anti-aging strategy.
Yeah. He looks great too. He looks not his age at all. Again, my dad, his only context
for raising a son was the fact that people would come into a salon and that was his basis
for conversation. As your barber or your hairstylist, that's your personal psychologist if you've
been seeing this person for 10 plus years. As he's going through this process of raising
me, he's basically getting all these women who come into a salon free parental guidance
advice on a daily basis and I think he started taking it.
That is unusual when a couple splits that the father would take sole control. Do you
know much about that in terms of, has your dad talked to you about... I know you've told
me before that you don't really have contact with your mom. In fact, you've never had contact
with your mom since she left, right?
Essentially, what my dad says is he is, I was the better suited to take care of you.
I also felt even though I knew nothing about raising you, I would do and I had the ability
to do what it takes to raise you properly. At least that's what I thought. At least provide
some form of security blanket for my one and only child. That's exactly what he did. It
is interesting. I never met my mom even when I have a conversation with my girlfriend.
She's like, haven't you ever wanted to just meet her? It's really strange when I say it,
but I never think about it. I grew up in a single parent household. Everyone in my neighborhood
pretty much was single parent household in some capacity or they were raised by their
grandmother and grandfather. I didn't grow up in a bad neighborhood by any means, but
that just was very normal where I grew up. To me, I never thought about it. I never understood
what that was like having two parents, but I didn't know. My dad did an excellent job
obviously raising me, but there was never an inclination or a want to actually meet
her. I think as I get older, there is more questions of I'd like to know from her perspective
what happened. I think we all have those interesting thoughts and moments where we want to just
divulge and just say like, man, I'd like to know my other half. My mom was adopted, which
I found out much later. Her background in ethnicity is also somewhat mysterious, which
is why my fascination with trying to understand my own genealogy and background in historical
context. Have you been able to dig into that through? Because the problem was if you're
using stuff like Ancestry, you have to have enough information to put in the system.
Yeah, exactly. This was maybe in 2006 or something, I think it was maybe 2005. NBC was doing a show
called Who Do You Think You Are? It might've been 2003, I don't remember, but I remember
during that time, essentially what they would do is they would ask for permission. They would then
find out every single thing there is to know about one side of your family. You say, okay,
I want to know about my father or my mom. I was really interested in my Japanese heritage. I had
asked them to start really diving deep on my father's side. Then they had traveled to Japan,
they started talking to people in Japan. For people who don't know, Japan is such a small but
highly protective society, especially when it comes to personal records. They essentially got
zero information. For whatever reason, they were like, we know that you have probably some
samurai blood from this Yasunaga clan in your grandmother's side of the family, but that's
really all we can get out of this thing. I was disappointed. To go back, my relationship with
my mom, there was none. For all you know, you could have half siblings, of course. Your mom was
presumably quite young when your parents split. She could have very easily remarried.
She still keeps in contact. I think it's been many years, but she was at least until my very
first Olympic Games in contact with my father. Essentially, she said and called him after she
had heard that I had won my first Olympic gold medal. I'm very proud of him. I've been following
him. She lives in the Pacific Northwest region. She obviously saw my face on newspapers and on
television leading up to the Olympic Games. I think she felt very proud, but she did mention
one thing to my dad. She's like, I feel this point in the life and both of our lives, I don't want
to disrupt his path. Maybe when he's ready, he'll seek me out or something of that nature.
That's always been in the back of my head. I also have this weird protective side of me because I
have so much love and respect for my father in everything that he did. I don't want him to feel
like he was less than if I go out and reach for my mom. No, it doesn't make sense.
You would? No, I don't think so, but that was inside me for a long time. When you're raising
a household, I think you're skewed in multiple ways and they create little small micro traumas
psychologically that maybe you don't recognize when you're younger or you're missing some elements,
which makes you more dependent. Maybe you're more alpha, maybe you're less. I don't know what that
is, but for sure, it definitely, I was not the most equilibrium based athlete in the world.
I think a lot of athletes are like that. I think there's always something that happens early stage
and for me, it was always like my father would always teach me that you can always be better,
you can always be better, you can always be better. There's always another level to go to.
Perfection is seemingly unattainable, but that's your goal and you don't stop until you get there.
That was so drilled into me psychologically from a young age. It wasn't like super tiger dad,
although thinking back, he did push me extensively. I didn't get that feeling when I was a kid,
but it definitely taught me a lot about my ultimate goal is to probably make him happy and
have respect for what I'm doing and also I want to achieve that perfection. I never did. I have had
races where I would call it the perfect race, but now when I look back, I'm like, ah, it was far from
it. I think that psychology started from my father and watching him in his work ethic. I was always
athletic as a kid growing up in Seattle and I was a swimmer and I did track and field and I
wanted to play football. He said, no, I wanted to box. He said, no, I saw this crazy sport of
short track speed skating and I was actually, at the time I was swimming a lot and my father
wanted me to go to Stanford or Michigan full ride. That was his goal, right? We were getting these
weird conversational actual snail mail letters. I remember back then basically telling my father,
if your son continues on this path of excellence in swimming, we would love to have a conversation
about having him become accepted into this school. This was from Stanford. I forgot what year it was.
What was your stroke?
It was breaststroke and backstroke or my two. So I was 50 and a hundred meter breaststroke.
Do you remember what your best hundred? Yeah, I don't remember.
I don't remember, but I do remember my 50 meter backstroke. I broke like some 20 year state record
at one time. I remember because the guy who record who I broke at the time, he was still like,
he was like semi coaching and my coach at the time, Bill Christiansen brought me up there and he's
like, oh, you know, this is the kid who broke your 20 year record. And the guy's like, wow,
you know, I have no idea what even would be.
What's interesting is, you know, usually backstrokers don't make good breaststrokers and vice versa
because backstroke and freestyle are long axis strokes. Breaststroke and fly are short axis
strokes. In your case though, I can see there's an interesting thing, which is your legs are so
freakishly strong and those are the two leg driven sports. So those are both what we would
call rear wheel drive sports versus front wheel drive strokes. So it's interesting to think that
you would be perfectly suited to do that, which means you would have been probably a really good
IMR as well. Yeah, I was, I was decent. My hundred meter. I am. I don't remember any of my times. Look,
we're talking like when I was 12, 13 years old, right? So a lot can happen between that and
college, but yeah, still, I mean that there was something there. I want to go back to something
you said a moment ago, right? Which was at a very young age, your dad sort of instilled in you this,
I don't want to put words in your mouth. I don't think you said it as the need to be perfect,
but a quest for perfection. You know, I talk about this a lot with my daughter, which is this idea
of mastery, which is this process of trying to master something that you'll never actually master
because that's technically not feasible is the beauty. Like that's the thing. And you know,
books that have been written about, it's usually written about athletes, but I think it can apply
to musicians or any number of other fields. They talk about the common bond that seems inherent to
many of these people who have achieved greatness like you have is this love of practice. Did you
sense that early on? Did you enjoy the practice or were you more task or goal oriented as far as
the outcome? Early in my career, I would say that I wasn't, I didn't enjoy the process as much. It was
based on sheer talent. And this is, I'm talking from the age of 14 until I was probably about 17.
And you started skating at what 13? I started skating. I actually started really,
really skating at 12. I started really training at the age of 14. So you started swimming what,
like as a five, six year old, but eight swam locally and you know, local competitions and state
competitions. And then when I saw the sport, short track speed skating in 1992 and they get in 1994,
that's when I said, wow, this is an amazing sport. I used to inline and quad skate like on the side
at the nearby local skating rink. I feel like I could do that. That seems pretty easy. It also
looks ridiculous, right? These guys are wearing these, when you're like 11, 12 years old and you
see these guys skate, it looks fake. And then when my father drove me north to Vancouver, BC,
I saw it live because the Canadians, they obviously loved winter sports. I was like,
this is the most incredible sport I've ever seen in my life. It doesn't make sense how these human
beings can be leaning over these impossible angles on a blade that's one millimeter thick.
And they're wearing outfits that resemble Superman without the Cape. Like literally that's what they're
doing. And they just have helmets on. I was like, this is perfect. Like I have to do this sport,
right? Superman without the Cape. Now that I think about it, there's, you know, we'll come back.
There's like flying around the ice cream.
I was going to say like, why don't they just have the capes on? It would be so much cooler.
Yeah, that'd be cool actually.
Yeah. Well, I want to come back to the evolution, but let's pause for a moment and have you explain
the difference between short track, long track, in line, all of these different types of skating.
Sure. So inline skating is predominantly done outdoors and they skate and they have competitions
all around the world. Now they have velodrome like competitions, but it's in. So if you've ever seen
a velodrome track for track cycling inside of that as a warmup area, that's where inline speed
skating competitions are being held in places like Bogota, Columbia, which is by the way,
Columbia is huge in the inline skating. I don't know why or how, but it's been huge there. And so
I big growing up in the Pacific Northwest and having rain be a very big part of our culture.
I did indoor skating. So think of your imaginary like roller rink and you have four pylons, right?
One for each corner. And you basically skate around and you're on like a roller blade,
but it's got how many wheels per the blade? I started out in quad skates. So two in the front,
two in the back. And then it's just basically just speed skating. So like if you've ever been
in a roller rink growing up as an American and it says, okay, it's time for speed skating. And
everyone goes out there and they play a song and we just get around really fast and he finished.
That's literally how I learned. And then someone in the local roller rink was like, hey, you should
try out for art club. And I was like, okay, that looks, that seems fun. And my dad at that point
was like, anything I can do to create more fatigue in this child, I'm in. I just want to
get him exhausted. Because your dad is working nonstop. He's working all day long. He comes home,
he's exhausted. And I'm like this kid who's just completely berserk out of control. Like I just,
I never get tired. I could just run and run, run, run, run, run, just unsatiable appetite for
everything. Were you getting into trouble at all? Absolutely. Absolutely. It was very mischievous and
environment has a lot to do with that. But for whatever reason, I was, I excelled pretty early
in some gifted programs when I was a child. And my dad was very much a proponent of pushing
education and cramming it down my throat and being like, look, take this test until you pass it,
basically. How did your dad have the time to even oversee how you were doing in school and overseeing
looking over your shoulder while you're trying to get your homework done? How did, do you reflect
back on what that even meant? I don't think he really could. I think he did what he could. I mean,
most of my childhood was spent, my father was not there during the day. So I would go to school on
my own. I would come back on my own and then until he came home and I can come back from school at 3
PM or something like that until seven, 8 PM, sometimes nine, 10 PM, he's not there. And I'm
alone in the house. I had to cook for myself. And you're eight, nine years old. Yeah, very, very
young. So at a very early age, I was very independent on just relying on myself to kind of succeed.
I didn't think anything of it at the time, like I was this latchkey kid, right? I had no idea.
My dad hates that word saying, I'm like, dad, that's pretty much what it was. There's no way,
I can remember many, many nights, it's like dark outside. And I'm like, where's my dad? This is
weird. But that was the reality. And thinking back, my dad, he put aside every single want he had in
his life, everything. And it was all about me. And for that, I feel obviously eternally grateful,
but also I learned so much from such a selfless man, I get it, like I'm his son, I'm the only son,
I'm everything he has, everything he wants to do, he wants to see me succeed. I didn't recognize it
when I was that young, I do now. So every waking moment was like, how do I create more experiences
for this child? How do I take my son to, we don't have a lot of money. So how do I take him to nature
and experience things that are free? How do we go out and we can draw, we can create something in
the sand, I can go and appreciate the ocean if that takes us to drive. I mean, we used to drive
to all competitions, like we would drive from Seattle to Prince George, Canada, that's a far
drive in the middle of winter to go skate one day competition against Canadian kids who I don't know,
I'm the only American there. And my dad is like basically driving for two days straight with no
sleep, just so I can have that experience. When you're that young, you don't recognize
how much of a sacrifice that is. Incredible, right? And then I think about now, I can't even do that
now. I feel vibrant and peaking at this 36 year age, right? So I just have a tremendous amount
of respect for my dad in terms of his dedication and sacrifice, just because he's just one of the
best and he didn't know what was good, what was bad, he just tried to do everything. So going back
to the skating, so that's what inline is. And then talk about the different disciplines of skating on
ice. Yeah, so you've got there's short track speed skating and then there's long track speed
skating. Long track is the one that's been around forever. Like that's when we go back and see the
Olympics 50 years ago. Correct. That was long track. Correct. So long track speed skating is
what most people think of as predominantly being on an outdoor ice surface. That's a 400 meter oval.
So imagine that you just had a track and field track and you basically just, it froze over during
the winter and you poured ice and that's your, and you had used a Zamboni, that's your track. Long
track speed skating has the 500 meters. It has the 1000 meters, the 1500 meter, the 5,000 and the
10,000. It's sort of parallels running in distances. Yes. But you also in long track speed skating,
it's all about time. So you've got your own lane, no one interferes with you. You can have some
moments where your pair, which you're skating with is, he's in front of you. You can basically
get a little bit of draft on the back end of a straightaway, but for the most part, it's you
against the clock and there's no hiding, right? You can't, like, as soon as you stop skating,
you kind of immediately sort of slow down with the exception of like some gliding, but the most part,
like time trialing, just like being on a bike, there's no hiding, there's no cheating. And when
I first started, I actually started out how I started out doing long track as a proponent,
because that's what everyone does in Calgary and other parts of Butte, Montana, I would skate.
So that's long track speed skating. The skate itself used to be a fixed boot and a fixed blade
meaning there's, imagine a shoe and then on your heel and then again on your, under the ball of
your foot are these two cups that basically just, they just lock into the bottom of the shoe. And
then on the bottom, that is the skate. And how long is the blade? The blade's about 17 to 18
inches long. It's again, it's only about a millimeter thick, a little bit thinner than a short
track blade. The actual bend and rocker of the skate is different, but it's a relatively flat
blade, correct? It's very flat. I used to play hockey growing up, but I was a goalie and goalies
have a much longer flatter skate than the skaters. The skaters have a very rounded blade. And so
when you're a goalie, you have all of this equipment on, so you're relatively slow.
But in a straightaway, a goalie, even with all his equipment, can generally skate pretty fast,
even relative to the regular skater, just because you have more blade on the ice. So I'm assuming,
I don't know how many inches it is, but it's obviously much shorter than what you're describing.
So when you have what, 17, 18 inches of surface on that ice, that's a ton of contact, right?
A ton of contact, but it's only in between the two cups at any moment and even shorter actually
of the time of which your blade is touching the ice. We can get into those details
in differently, but that's long track speed skating. They then evolve to a clap skate,
which means that the rear heel of the blade was hit.
Detaches, yes.
And it detaches so that when you push, the blade actually still stays on the ice as a full pull.
As the heel comes off.
So you get like a five to 15% additional advantage every single time you push. And I
was, I watched that phenomenon come on.
How much of an impact did that have on times?
It changed everything. It changed who was good. It changed who wasn't good. It changed which
countries were really strong for a period of time because people couldn't understand how to skate in
a clap skate mechanism because the technique is so much different. And it really became a lot to do
with the type of equipment that you had and your ability as an athlete to transfer your power
through the clap skate mechanism. You could be the world's greatest on a fixed skate mechanism,
go to the clap skate and not even make the top 20. So it was a really difficult learning curve
for a lot of athletes. And a lot of people started just to just basically give up and they just,
they just dropped out.
What year did that transition take place?
This was 1995 when we really started to see it. 95, 96 and 97 was when that was the peak years
of the clap skate really changing.
What drove that technological change? Was there some whispering that, oh, this is politically
motivated to change the power structure within the sport? Because which countries
prior to the 90s were the most dominant in long track?
Well, I would say with the exception of the Americans, right? It's always been the Europeans
were always the best. A couple of Japanese, but for the most part, it was always the Europeans,
meaning the Netherlands, some of the Germans, and some of the Russians.
Though Eric Haydn in 1980, has anyone ever matched that feat?
No one has ever matched that feat. I don't think anyone ever will match that feat.
And that feat again was he won five golds.
He won the 500, the 1000. He went all the distances in one Olympic games, which is,
it would be like Usain Bolt.
No, no, it's, yeah, there's no way to explain that. I mean, the closest thing to that that I
would say in recent times is Katie Ledecky winning the 200, the 400, the 800 in the Olympics.
If there were a 1500, which there is in the worlds, but not in the Olympics, don't get me
started on that. She would have won that as well. But you're right. I mean, it's sort of like
prefontaine at one point holding the American record in everything from, I think, the 1500 to the 10K.
Then of course, to win the gold in all of those is.
And Eric was a specimen. He was a very special genetic human being and is. Aside from that,
his work ethic was astronomically high and he was a complete, this guy was a savage when it
came to training. He would bury and still does, by the way, bury most people on a bike and he
doesn't train anymore. He's just, his ability to tolerate pain and threshold and lactic acid
is like when I was like, when you watch a racehorse and that racehorse is obviously in pain,
but doesn't slow down. It's very similar. And when I was growing up, Eric Haydn was the king.
And to be honest with you, he's to me, he's still the king. And I tell him he's still the king
because what he did was so ridiculously difficult. And my sport of short track speed skating,
by the way, is very different than long track.
Yeah, I want to come to that. But before we leave Eric, I mean, one, I know we've talked a little
bit about some of his training. I want to hear more about that later on. But my one connection
to him is of course, he went to med school at Stanford, which is where I went. And when I was
in med school, I used to ride my bike a lot. And there's this very famous hill near Stanford
called Old Lahonda, which is sort of the benchmark hill for cyclists. And anyone listening to this
who rides a bicycle in the Bay Area knows Old Lahonda and not only knows it, knows their time
up it, because that is the metric. That is the equalizer. It's about three and a half,
3.6 miles. It's got a number of switchbacks. It's relatively steep. I feel like it's almost 7%
grade on average. And I believe the benchmark time is about 20 minutes. So if you're below 20
minutes, you're allowed to call yourself a cyclist. If it takes more than 20 minutes, you know, you
ride a bike. So it took me a while to break 20 minutes. My roommate in medical school, his name
is Matt McCormick. He was about 17 minutes, 20 seconds, which was exceptional. He was certainly
the fastest of any of the people that I knew on a bike. Eric Haydn apparently was about 14 and
a half minutes up Old Lahonda, which was and remains to my knowledge, the record up that hill.
And I used to, I had a model that I built that would calculate how many watts you needed to
average to go up that hill. And I forgot, I don't think I've ever plugged Eric's time into it, but
it wouldn't surprise me if that were a 600 watt effort given his body weight.
He's a big guy. Eric Haydn was a very big and heavy, obviously quad dominant athlete.
So, I mean, I should go back and do that. But I think for someone Eric's weight to have gone up
that in 14 and a half minutes, it's hard for me to imagine he could have done that at less than 600
watts, which anybody who's ever stepped foot on any sort of ergometer knows that like anybody can
hold 600 Watts for 10 seconds. Most people can't do it for a minute. Very few people can hold 600
Watts for a minute to hold it for 14 and a half minutes. That's so much power. And then of course,
he became a professional cyclist. Right. And I think he rode in a couple of tours.
Yeah. Yeah. I think he rode for 7-11 and he's an orthopedic surgeon now and I've never met him
or know him at all, but it's hard for people who don't follow that sport, myself included,
to really reflect on what it would mean to be the best in the world at such a broad
range of distances because those are physiologically completely different events.
I mean, the 500 and the 10,000 have nothing in common really. They're completely different
energy systems. They're different technique, different energy systems, different training.
I didn't even realize that. So of course that makes sense. Different technique, right? It's
the difference between someone running 200 meters versus someone running 5K.
There's different equipment involved. I mean, there's so many things that are so...
And in the 80s, I think sport science was, especially in speed skating, was never a huge
part of what we did like track and field and like cycling, which are in my opinion,
at the absolute pinnacle of pushing that red line, right, of utilizing science and what we
understand of the sport. Speed skating is a very unconventional, it's a uncomfortable position to
be in. It's not natural to speed skate being in that position, especially as a long track
speed skater. So to train for that is, and still is, really, really excruciating and there is no
balance, right? We only turn left. So there's lots of imbalances aside from physical being.
But Eric was a huge part of that motivation to train like an animal, as was Lance and a lot of
the other guys who I looked up to as being superhuman, not only for their accomplishments,
but the way that they mentally attacked pain and training, because that's where you win your actual
wars in the training part. When you get to the competition, you can't do anything. So if you
didn't show up ready, you can't hide that, you know? In my sport...
You can only lose it by showing up in the wrong headspace, but the right headspace won't win it
if you haven't done the work.
Yeah, your likelihood of doing very well is dramatically much higher if you prepare. And I
think that goes with pretty much anything. So I was really interested in that psychology of what
makes up someone like that. So with Eric Haydn and many other athletes who trained in the
same tutelage of his original coaches, and I believe her name was Diana Holum, she was based in
Milwaukee, in the Madison region of the Midwest. And her training methods were very unconventional,
and they were obscene, and they probably would be deemed very, you know, almost punishment.
They're on par with waterboarding today. It's like, you know, not allowed to do that training.
Yeah, like, hey, Eric, here's what we're going to do since you're... And by the way,
we had 100 athletes to start, only 12 remain. That's our team. Now we start training together.
So you can imagine...
Because the other 88 got broken.
Yeah, broken very early, or they just didn't have the ability to recover
based on pure genetics at this time. And that's how we trained back then. And watching and hearing
these stories about Eric going up the Lake Placid ski hill with a large rope tied around him,
and that is tied to a tractor trailer truck tire, right? And he's just doing hill sprints up
and down for like three hours. And he just did crazy stuff like Rocky style training. And that
mentality, like, I mean, for me as an athlete, sports science is amazing, and I wish I concentrated
more on it. But that psychology was what I was actually really, really, really interested in.
That's what I loved. I loved to do stuff that people thought was completely obscene and crazy.
And, you know, like, for me, like, I would say 80% of my career, all my races were won ever before
I got to the start line. The other competitors were racing for a second. And they just knew
that I was like just completely off my rocker. I was not in the same headspace as them. I was
different. I didn't talk to anybody. I was... And I wanted to create that kind of bubble, right? And
I got that from these kind of legends who I looked up to. There's a video that will definitely make
sure we link to this. I have a feeling this podcast will have more links to videos than most of ours,
but there's a video that I remember seeing. It was like probably six, seven minutes long.
And it had some snippets or highlights of some of your training. And I actually was discussing it
with Lance Armstrong once we were having dinner. And I was like, dude, you got to see this video
of what Apollo was doing. And you were doing, I think, single leg lateral jumps up two steps at a
time. Yeah. Yeah. Most likely. I mean, Jesus Christ. I feel like I've done some crazy things in my day.
I just don't think I have the explosiveness single leg. That's the thing. Most people don't appreciate
how much of a reduction you have in power when you go from two to one leg. Right. It's not half the
power. You're losing way more than half when you take that second leg away and then adding to it
that you're doing it laterally. Yeah. Like it's... And I remember in the video, it says, yeah,
this is basically a 48 minute set. Yeah. That was probably following like an ice session. Yes.
Like a two and a half hour ice session. That's where you would do those. I mean, how often does
someone get injured doing that? Because the thing that struck me is like, look, you can be the best
stud in the world. You can have the toughest head in the world, but at some level, your ankle's
going to catch on that stair and you're going to fall over a ladder. Like you're always just
one millimeter away from breaking your ankle. You're looking at me like, no, that would never
happen. Yeah. Never thought about that. Never saw it. Never thought about it. Definitely the risk
is there. But then again, in short track speed skating, I mean, we skate together every day,
sometimes twice a day for four to six hours a day and we're inches from each other. And that blade
is literally this close to my face. Now, if this blade gets this close to my face, it's going to
slice my face off. Just for reference, that's like, that's 12 inches from your face is where
you're putting that blade. I mean, every day, every crossover, every lap. Is that why you have such a
smooth shave? The sport was very dangerous. And I used to do really dumb stuff. Like we would have,
at one point in the ISC, the international skating union implemented a rule that had to have,
you had to have a neck guard to protect your neck and all major arteries on the body needed to be
covered with a cut-proof material like Kevlar. And so everyone was wearing these cut-proof material
inside of the skin suit. So it was basically sewn into the skin suit, the racing suit.
And I hated the feeling of the Kevlar because it didn't stretch. I used to cut mine out.
So I would rate, it's completely legal, right? But I used to cut mine out and I used to race,
we call it racing naked, right? So you'd race naked. So if I fall with another skater,
the likelihood of me getting cut is like 80%. And you're done. Like that's one time you're done. But
when you're young and you're dumb, I did many, many dumb things like that. But now they actually
check before you get on the ice. They see if you've altered the skin suit.
So what year was Short Track a demonstration sport? Was it 92?
88 in Calgary.
88. Okay. And so what was the impetus for creating this new sport?
You know, I'm not sure because the sport actually has been around for a long time. And people used
to do Short Track speed skating outdoor in New York City, I think in the sixties.
I see. So it was just one of those things where the sport had been around forever and it was like,
now we're just going to bring it to the Olympic level.
Yeah. And it was, you go from long track speed skating, which is all about time. It's imagine
like you're watching a track and field race, but no one can ever go outside their lane. You know,
we see that in a hundred meters, but imagine like a mile. You can't move. These is the lane you're
given and there's only two people on the track at a time. And everyone does basically just does
time trials. So that was like not that interesting to me. And also I just liked the fact of racing
was so much more, it was just more intimate, right? And it was psychologically a huge part of what I
wanted to race against other athletes and outsmart or out strategize them. And I like that moment of
risk. And so short track speed skating is very different than long track speed skating. So you
go from a 400 meter oval outdoor to, and long track is also indoor, but to a Olympic size hockey
rank. And the track is 111 meters around at the inside, at the tightest perimeter, right? That's
the actual track size. And you've got instead of just two people on the track at a time going for
against the clock, you've got five to six, sometimes seven to eight skaters on the start
line at once, all racing and jocking for position and drafting each other and passing on the inside
and outside and grabbing each other, bumping, making mistakes and, you know, leaning over
these angles because it's such a tightly held oval inside. Our skates are set up differently.
We don't have a clap skate. It's a fixed skate. We tried using clap skates in 1997 and 1998,
but it just, it was the sport is too dynamic and there's too much weight transfer from the,
from the ball of the foot to the heel of the foot where, you know, sometimes I would lean
so far forward on the ball of my foot. When I'm coming out of a corner, my heel would lift off
using a clap skate. And so it was just very, very dangerous. You couldn't, you couldn't use that now.
I mean, short track speed skating is one that the blades are so offset. So imagine this is my,
my skate. Instead of having the blade right in the middle, the blade is actually way over here
on the, on the left side on both the left skate. Because you're always going left. Because you're
always going left and you're leaning over so much at these angles that you need to have that
additional offset to make sure that you can still have enough pressure on that leg and also be able
to maneuver properly. So while I never even realized that in watching that, that your blades were not
symmetric on the bottom of the boot. So they're not even straight. They're actually even sometimes
tilted depending on the, what you like as a skater and your technical. You, as a skater, have some
say in that degree of tilt. You have all the say. So your control over your equipment is the one
thing that is a huge part of short track speed skating that if you don't short track speed skate,
which I'm assuming no one on this listening to the podcast does, it's such a huge part of the sport.
It would be the difference between me feeling like I could never lose and me feeling like I'm not
going to make it into the quarterfinal. Like if my equipment feels that far off, it just feels,
you just feel like you lost all your power. Maybe I can use another example. So imagine you're a
boxer and you've got boxing gloves that weigh, you know, two pounds each. And then imagine the
next time you put the boxing gloves on, then I'll 10 pounds each. That's, that's what it feels like,
how much different it feels like as an athlete when your equipment isn't, is not dialed in or,
and then small things like the ice temperature, the grip of the ice, meaning like your perfect
body weight and the amount of power that you typically generate in the corner. And they wet
the ice, don't they? To give you guys more grip. Yeah. Because the angles you're at are ridiculous.
We pour actually hot water in the corners of both sides of the track. And we actually,
we're actually skating on top of the water. We're actually not digging in the ice. If you slow it
down. So what's giving you the grip? If you're not digging into the ice, you technically are,
but most of the time you're on top of the water. So the grip is a combination of both the,
the way that our blades are set up. There's such a hardcore bend in the blade that when you lean
over on that 1.1 millimeter piece of metal, the blade will flex to a certain degree. And some of
that bend comes out and what's remaining is still a curve that allows you to hook yourself around
that corner. Oh, I see. Wow. So if you laid that blade in its maximally flexed position on a flat
surface from end to end, could you put like a dime underneath it? Does it have that much bend
or curvature in it? Not a dime, but you can see it. So like if I had my blade here, I should have
brought my skate and I didn't put any pressure on the blade and I just laid it down. The only
ends of the blade will be touching the middle part in between the two cups, which I mentioned,
which was the ball and the heel, that whole area doesn't touch the ice until I put a lot of pressure
and then the ends no longer touch in the middle touches. So it's a, we bend our own skates,
we rocker our own skates. It's very, you know, it's very technical. We use a radius machine,
which measures one, 1000th of a hair in between these two areas, which is about, I think it's
about like four and a half inches across the blade and we mark it. And so you're born in what?
80, 82. So when you're 10 years old, this is a demonstration sport in the Olympics. So by the
time you're 13, it's about ready to become a full fledged Olympic sport. And it's sort of,
it's in the crosshairs now for you, which is it's a sport that you're passionate about. Your dad's
like, fine, let's let him do this because it's better than him getting a concussion every day.
When you started, I'm just guessing you were quite naturally talented to begin with because
you alluded to it earlier that you didn't really start training until you were 14. So there was
this year when you were just getting by on talent. Yeah, actually further than that. So,
you know, from 12 till 14, my father took me around to small local speed skating competitions
and I was winning most of them, even the ones internationally, which I say internationally,
meaning just going to Canada. And I wasn't getting any competition in the States. I was getting all
of my challenge from racing against other athletes inside Canada. And I had beaten pretty
much anyone west of Toronto. And now it was a time where the only remaining place for me to
compete in Canada was Montreal, because that's where the real skaters came out of. So it's the,
it's, it was Montreal, not Vancouver that had the epicenter of skating. Yes. And like Fredericton and
a few other places, Quebec and Quebec city was a big producer of great Canadian short tracks,
speed skaters. Something about Quebec, growing up, I was really serious in martial arts and
boxing and yeah, like the national championships were always in Quebec or Ottawa, like some place
close to Quebec. And the nationals was the only time you would face these guys. And they were like
a different breed, man. They're different breed. They were really, really tough dudes. Yeah,
they're tough guys. Yeah. And I had a lot of respect for them. The Canadians to me were always
very, very strong in the sport and they still are today. You know, short track speed skating is not
like cycling where you've, you've got all of these different athletes from all these different
countries all over the world. At the time there was only a few really, really strong countries
in short track speed skating. The U S was not one of them by the way. So after, so in 92 in the
demonstration year, that's sort of the moment when it, I guess, presumably after 92 people say, well,
okay, we're going to take this sport seriously. Now the countries are deciding how much do we
want to invest in this and cross of our athletic programs. Correct. Did the United States at that
moment, did they do well enough in the demonstration games to decide, let's put some resources into
this? We did okay. We weren't definitely weren't dominant and we weren't on the podium. I mean,
on the women's side, Kathy Turner had won a gold in 92 and again in 94 other than that, there was
no real funding mechanism. We were there, but you know, at the time people were training in
the U P they were training in Marquette, Michigan. Now, were you thinking,
because now by the time you get into the sport, it's 94, which means there was another Olympic
year. Cause that was the year 94 was the year summer and winter offset. If I recall, right.
That was the whole Nancy Kerrigan, Tanya Harding year. Wasn't it? That makes me feel old. Cause I
remember that like it was yesterday. Were you thinking I want to go to the Olympics or were you
just thinking, no, I just want to keep, you know, sort of beating whoever I'm skating against and
I'm going to still be a swimmer. I knew that I didn't want to swim. I see. Okay. Yeah. It was
around that, around that time period. You're kissing Stanford and Michigan. Goodbye. I knew
at that time that those were not in my path. Looking back, I very interesting and I don't,
I'm pretty sure I would have not gotten a full ride to Stanford if I had pursued and maybe I
would have, but I, you know, obviously I didn't. So, you know, at the age of 14, I was winning
quite a bit of competitions locally in domestically in the United States. And I was essentially being
scouted by a few of these junior development program coaches who at the time, the junior
development program was in Lake Placid, New York, the same place where the 1980 games were, where
Haydn won his amazing five medals and the miracle on ice from the U S beat the Soviets in the summit
final. They went on and won the gold, but that's where I was going to have to move to. And these
coaches, Patrick, one at a time came to my father and said, we, we actually have a lot of interest
in bringing your son early. You have to be 15 years old to be admitted into this program. I was
only 14. And was this a summer only program or was this an academy where you'd actually go to school?
It's a real academy. Like you, you actually literally move there. You go to school there
and you train to be hopefully the next stage would then go to the national team and train to go be a
part of the Olympic program. Okay. I didn't know what any of this stuff meant. Right. So they
approached your dad. They approached my father. They approached me. I wouldn't even know that.
I was like, okay, that sounds not fun. You know, on the other side of the country,
like I want to stay in Seattle. We've got very few sunshine days a year.
It's the summertime. Like I don't want to go there. This was 1997, the summer of 1996.
And they essentially said, you know, we, we want Apollo to come and what do you think? And
my father was like, absolutely. I got to get this kid focused on something. You know, I kind of
alluded before that I was pretty mischievous as a kid. I had difficulty concentrating and staying
on task to one specific thing. And are you one of those kids that today would automatically get
this label of for sure. I'm sure I would have been loaded up on all day long, all kinds of stuff.
Right. So which my dad was always, he wouldn't care if I even got that diagnostic. He would
never allow that for some reason. My dad's been like 20 years ahead of the game in terms of
nutrition. I don't know where he learns this stuff, but anyway, different topic.
He's got good lineage, right? I mean, if you, you know, just, just follow the Okinawa and you're
pretty much going to be okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. The centaurians, my father then approached me and
I remember this very clearly. He's like, look, you've got this incredible opportunity to train
in Lake Placid, New York. You potentially could go on to be a part of the Olympic team,
which would mean that you would make the 1998 Olympic team in Nagano, Japan and compete.
Your grandfather is still alive. I'm from Japan. This is your heritage. You had, this is, this is
an incredible opportunity. Wait, was that a real possibility that it was because you would have
only been 16, right? I would have only been 15. 15 in that, for those Olympic games. Correct.
I mean, for a men's sport to go to the Olympics at 15 is almost unheard of. It's not unheard of
for women, but for men, that's really, that's amazing that they thought that that was a chance,
right? Yeah. So that was, that was the end goal. Like Michael Phelps went to his first Olympics
at 15. Right. What most people don't realize is he was fifth in the 200 fly, was the only event he
went for, which was still unbelievable. It's hard to believe that a 15 year old boy could have
gone to the Olympics and placed fifth in the world at arguably the second most grueling race in
swimming, if not the most grueling race in swimming. He went on to break his first world record before
his 16th birthday, if my memory serves me correctly, making him the youngest male athlete to ever have
a world record in a time sport. Yeah. Michael's not human. I'm the Michael for years. He's not
human. Doesn't matter what he says. And he trains like a monster, but he also is just not, he is put
on earth to be in that water. I think he told me one time because I'm more comfortable in the water
than I am in my bed. It's more comfortable for me to be, I guess there's like a sense of weightlessness,
right? Yeah. But that's amazing. Well, actually you and Michael have something in common, which is
you are both the most decorated Olympians in the United States in the summer and winter games.
Michael, of course, also being the most decorated Olympian ever, but I don't think any US Olympian
is more decorated in the winter games than you, are they? It's arguable and subjective, right? I
had an amazing career and I was very blessed to be and won that many medals, but I also had the
opportunity to win a lot of medals too, right? So like I grew up in the Olympic training center with
these wrestlers. They only have a chance to win one medal. Right. Yeah. No, certain sports are
amenable to any more medals. That title has been kind of tasked over and over again. And I smile
when I hear it because it's amazing, right? But I still look at Eric Hyde and Bonnie Blair and
they're very good friends of mine and I still consider them to be like, you know, really on
top of the podium. So, okay. So it's summer of 96. You're basically being brought in 18 months before
what could be your first Olympics. Correct. So it is, it is the summer of 96 opportunity to move,
to be part of the junior development program. My father says, you got to do this. I met a
mischievous age. I didn't recognize my own talent. He says, yes, I say no. He says red. I say black,
like I'm always the complete opposite of what my father is saying. And so, you know, he essentially
packs my bags, tries to explain to me the incredible importance of what I'm about to embark upon.
And then drives me to SeaTac airport, drops me off, waves goodbye. And then I wave goodbye. I had
a plan in my head already what I was going to do next. And I walked right to the payphone,
which we use payphones back then in 96. Put a quarter in it. Yep, exactly. And I called my
friend and I said, I'm supposed to go to New York today, but I'm not. Come pick me up from the
airport. And then for the next, like I would say eight days, I was bouncing around from like,
no, like almost like 11 days actually, bouncing around from house to house. All while my father
believes that I'm still in Lake Placid, but I'm so angry. I'd never called him and he hadn't got
a call from the, what did the coaches do when you didn't show up? So the coaches called him
eventually. I think this is probably like on day six or something like that. And they're like,
Hey, Mr. Oh, no, very curious. The offer is still wide open. We just never heard from you.
Do you have plans on still attending? And my dad's like, Oh my God, you lost my son. And,
you know, all these things. And he figures out somehow which house I was at picks me up. He's,
he's very angry, obviously, because essentially I was running away as a kid. And, you know, my dad,
it's got this sense of wisdom and he's noticing these like small little habits that I had been
doing as a child that he really, really tried to train out of me. And he thought that by placing
me in this kind of single discipline sport of going in circles would do a lot psychologically
from a beneficial perspective. I didn't know anything about that time. All I knew is I didn't
want to go there. Why do you think you didn't want to go? I mean, you had been successful. Yeah.
Do you think on some level you were afraid of going and finding out you might not be as good as
you thought you could be? I don't even think it was. I didn't even think I got that deep. I think
it was just, I just didn't, I literally didn't want to go. I wanted to hang out with my friends
in the Seattle area. And it was that, it was that simple and also stupid that I was going to be
throwing away potentially. Cause I could have very easily just said, no, I'm not going to do this
thing and done it again. Right. And just never went to New York. And then we would never be sitting
here talking about this. So credit again, my father who the second time he comes and takes me
to the airport, gets on the plane. And with the second time, meaning it's still the summer 96.
It's just like a couple of weeks later. Two weeks later. So first of all, I mean,
that's pretty interesting that the coaches there didn't say, well, forget this kid. Like he just
failed the test, right? Like the test was, do you have the mental fortitude to even show up on day
one? The coaches were like, we have to have this kid. He's this kid is, he is going to make us
speeds getting like amazing. Those are not my words. These are things that they're trying to
tell my dad, which he tried to kind of tell me to me, but you know, when you're 14 and you don't
agree with anything your father says, it doesn't make any sense. And so again, this time he
accompanies you there. Oh, he makes sure. So he flies to Albion, New York. We take the drive to
Lake Placid. He gets out of the car. He shakes Patrick. Well, in his hands, it's good luck. And
he walked turned around and goes home, you know, and Patrick went and was like, Oh shit. Like I get
this, this Calvin and Hobbes character in my life. I don't need this kind of heat. And, uh,
but Patrick actually turned out to be an incredible coach and mentor and guy.
That first night.
It was just so awkward and weird. I mean, you're, I mean, I'm a 14 year old kid. I'm living now in
a dormitory. I've got roommates from parts of the country. I don't, I've never heard of or
recognize. And they're all short track skaters or it's short, long skiers.
There's both, there's both in the, in the junior Olympic program, in the Lake Placid Olympic
training center, you've got lose, you've got Bob sled, you've got cross country,
you've got the ski jumping guys, you've got long and short track speed skating.
And you've got all the biathletes and you've got everyone there from the winter regions because
Lake Placid is very cold in the winter. And so I, I'm a complete fish out of water. I look different.
I talk different. I wear different types of clothes. I listen to different types of music.
I can't relate to anybody. And I feel, I hated it there the first seven days. I remember this
very viscerally. I really, really every day would call my dad and be like, I hate it. This,
this place is not for me. And my dad's like, just, you gotta give it 30 days. You have to be there
for a month. Just give it time. Give it time. And prior to going, had you done much in the way of
off ice training, like, you know, you and I have talked and we're going to talk later today about
some of your legendary workouts in the weight room. Had you discovered that yet? Or were you
mostly an on ice guy and not doing a lot of dry land? I mean, my dad would take me when I was an
quad, an inline skater. My dad would wake me up really, really early in the morning before he
went to work and he would make me go to the park and skate. So the tiger dad or whatever you want
to call it. That was very much, and I hated it by the way, it was horrible. I hated it so much.
I told my dad, I want to quit one time. Cause he was like, Oh, you want to quit? Okay. Tell me
that you really, really want to quit. Okay. And for him, it was never about me actually becoming
the best. I don't think that actually was ever part of his goal and life plan. His plan was to
instill these mental strengths within me that never allowed me to quit what I was doing,
to develop the capacity to understand what it was like to truly leave no stones and turn during the
preparation. It's a very Japanese in his, in his way, right? Like, okay, you want to do this one
thing, then everything you do is dedicated towards being incredible. And you know, the thing about
this, the Japanese sushi masters, right? They have seven years before they're ever allowed to touch
the fish. They're just making rice every day. Dude, I would blow my brains out month two. Like,
I could not deal with that. Right? You're telling me I'm an amazing sushi. Like what happens if
you're just really, really good and you're talented. Nope. There's, you can't break the rules. It's
going to take you seven years of touching this rice and making it perfect before you allowed to
touch the fish. So like that kind of mentality of like this ever going method of trying to become
perfect. And my dad left Japan, so he didn't want to do that, but I think he couldn't help himself.
That's just a part of, well, I mean, my guess is he realized that maybe at its most extreme
end, it wasn't what was right for him. But I suspect he realized that there were elements
of that that were beautiful, that were important and that he was succeeding as a result of,
I suspect he wanted you to have some elements of that discipline. And that, again, passion might
be overly simplistic, but the ability to stay on that thread and master something, which is
interesting, right? Because look, like all parents, he wanted the best for you. He, at this point,
you know, you're 14. Even maybe he couldn't have imagined you'd go on to be what you did, but it
was like, look, this kid's going to go to college and whatever he's learning here, this grit will
translate over to that next phase of his life. And maybe he didn't really know when had a master
plan. I think he did. And I think he'll tell you that he did, but it wasn't exactly graphed out.
This is the recipe for having success and being a successful father, which I consider my father to
be, but it was tough, right? I mean, you imagine I'm really, really, really young and I'm being
forced at waking up at like six or five in the morning to go skate outside in a year.
Well, that's right. If I'm doing the math right, you're 14. You're a year younger than the normal
entry to this program, right? Yeah. Yeah. That started. And when we, when I arrived in Lake
Placid and I was going through the process of understanding, like if I even liked the sport,
like I'm probably like a week number two or three, I started recognizing, wow, this is,
I feel a lot of freedom here. I don't, my dad's not here. The only kind of authority figure I
have is my coach who is really, really easy, but also I respect because he's figured out a way to
talk to me in a way that speaks to me. Is he kind of your first real coach? He's my first
real coach. So all of the previous year and a half or two years, you were. It's my dad.
Who obviously, you know, despite his greatness, doesn't really know much about speed skating.
He knows nothing about speed skating. So you're sort of like, you're just going out to the track
and just, you don't have a strategy. You're just trying to win. Yeah. I mean, every time I would
skate back then, it was cheerily based on talent. Nothing more. I didn't train. In other words,
off the line, you're going for broke every time you're not trying to be tactical and outsmart
somebody necessarily. Yeah, basically. And arguably I was just better than most of those kids. They
didn't, in my eyes, they didn't know how to speed skate very well. So now you got this coach and
presumably he's looking at you being like, we got to break some habits here. Yeah. So we do the body
composition test first and I'm like, obviously the highest. My nickname was Chunky as a kid.
And, you know, I was eating everything in sight. We had cafeteria. Just let's put this in perspective.
There is no way you were a Chunky kid. I was Chunky. What was your, what was your body fat on
that first test? I don't remember the body fat, but it was the highest and there was some chubby
kids in my, in our program. There were some chubby kids. I mean, look, I'm 14 years old though. I
don't know how, how lean there, I was going to be coming out of there looking like, you know,
shredded, but I was the highest by far. Did you always kind of have that physique of just having
enormous? Yeah. Enormous quads, enormous, enormous, but I was just a thicker kid and partially
because I just was eating everything and I was going to puberty and everything was tasty and I
would just eat it. I had no understanding at any capacity of nutrition and that what it meant.
Which is so funny knowing you now, right? Like you're, you're so dialed on everything.
Yeah. Try to be much more specific in terms of how you live your life. And
anyway, but back then it also didn't really matter thinking back. So I, you know, I get these tests
back and I'm deeply embarrassed to be, you know, the most chubby kid out there. And I, I remember
the coach telling me one time, like, what do you want to do? Like, what are your goals for this
year? Like goals? What does that even, what do you mean? My goals for this year. I couldn't even
think about the next six months, let alone the world team trials in eight months from now. Like,
I had no idea what that meant. And then so I started to understand that I actually liked
speed skating. I liked being out there on the ice. I liked the feeling. I remember one time I,
because I was so embarrassed by that first test. Oh, by the way, going back to just one sort of
technical issue about the sport, Short Track has how many distances? It's the 500, the thousand.
500,000 and 1500 meters. 1500. And then we have a relay. And across those three distances,
had you exhibited proficiency equally or were you more geared towards one or the other?
At that age, I was stronger in the 1500 meters. Okay. I was more, I would say we would call it
an endurance athlete. So two and a half minutes on the ice at a time separated by 20 minute breaks.
And then you race basically every 20 minutes. Jesus, that is Phelpsian. Yeah. It's like that's
there were races, I think in the Olympics where Michael would have what, 17 minutes between a
heat and a final or something, which it just seems impossible to imagine. Yeah. Your recovery has to
be very, very high. And that's why most athletes in Short Track speed skating, even to this day,
they train for all the distances. They train for the 500, which is the pure sprint 40 seconds.
They train for the 1500 meters, which is two and a half minutes. And they even train for the,
3000 meters, which is only held at the world championships, which is like, you know,
four and a half minutes. So going back to my story, I was so embarrassed by this body
composition test that I sat down with Patrick Wentans and I asked him, is it possible that I
can become too good too early? And he's looking at me. I remember looking at me like, what the
hell is this kid talking about? No, that's why you're here. Right. And he's like, no. And I was
like, what happens if you burn out? He's like, he only burn out if you don't like the sport anymore,
if we train you too hard, like, and it's not going to be the latter. So as long as you continuously
like this, you're going to be, you're going to do great. You just, you got to focus. And that began
my kind of understanding of if I really concentrate on this and I really care about the outcome,
I was able to achieve really, really interesting results. And I went to the junior trials,
which means you make the junior world team and I was supposed to make that team and I didn't,
I got third. So it's like swimming where the top two make it. Correct. Okay. And I remember going
back home and being so pissed that I didn't make that team that I just started actually really
attacking the weight room. Was that kind of your first big loss? Was that the first time you
were surprised at an outcome? It was the first time that in short track speed skating that I was
supposed to make a team, but I didn't. And I just remember that feeling was just, it was so like,
itchy. It's like an itch that you can't scratch and it's there every day, every second of the hour.
Do you remember that race? What happened? You race at multiple different distances,
but it just, it was a combination of I wasn't good enough and I wasn't racing properly. I
shouldn't have made that team. So you sort of reached your limit of natural talent.
At that age. Yep. And that was the time where if I wanted to make significant changes, I'd have to
really concentrate both technically and also on the physiology of training to be a short track
athlete. And I started attacking the weight room and that was the only way that I knew how to
exert like this, you know, I'm this, I'm going through puberty as a kid. I've got all this
testosterone. I'm genetically gifted for the sport. I just have to put it to work. And so
that was the one major difference is I just remember just basically putting more plates
on the squat rack at the age of 14. And it was very easy. And I noticed like, I remember like
a week would go by and my like strength would increase by like 30%. Like it was like just
compounding boom, boom. Every single week I was just getting stronger and stronger, stronger.
And when I arrived in the world team trials in 96 to make the 1997 world team, I ended up actually
winning the competition, which in for, you know, the viewers who don't understand that's like a,
I was 14 years old racing against guys who were grown men. Yeah. So this is a junior world.
No, this is everybody. The team to go to the world's represent the US. This is, and again,
for most people who don't follow Olympic sports outside of Olympic years, you know, you sort of
have an Olympics three out of four years because you've got the Olympics or worlds. You actually
compete every single year. Yeah, exactly. So you, you, we've got world cups, we've got world
championships and that's what we're doing. You know, every single, we're not working at like
home Depot and just like having fun. So you made the team for, this is 97 to go to the world. So
this is the team. This is now means you're an odds on favorite to go to the Olympics in 98.
Absolutely. I mean, I dominated those trials. What did you do at the worlds that year?
I think I got 19th in the world, I think. And I remember that I had never skated against the
Chinese or the Korean. I only skated against Canadians and Americans at the time.
So you hadn't even skated against Europeans. I skated against no one other than those two
countries. And you know, when you talk about Canadians, I probably skated against really
only like 10 guys from Canada who were semi-competitive with me. So when I went to the
world championships, the first thing I noticed was the track pattern in which these athletes
were skating were so vastly different. And that's when this light bulb came on my head.
And I was like, Oh my God, the US is so far behind. We are skating the wrong way.
Everyone is basically when they exit the corner, they're hugging the, you know, the blocks. And
they're basically creating the smallest distance possible to protect their inside lane and position.
And I was way out by the boards. So you're taking a faster turn, but going a greater distance,
right? You're basically creating more pressure on your legs, but you're being more protected.
So it's also, I just noticed the strategy was so much more important in international competitions.
And I felt like we were skating two different races and you know, I performed, you know,
pretty poorly because it's my first world championships, but that's when I saw like,
this is the big leagues. These are the guys who are really training to win medals. These are the
Koreans, these are the Chinese, these are the Canadians. This is the real national teams.
This is all they care about. This is all they do on a day to day basis. And it was a huge difference
between racing domestically at the world trials level in the US versus international.
Once you actually go. And that's when I was like, wow, I have to, if I want to remain
competitive, like I felt so, I felt so far away at that time. Were you discouraged? I mean,
it sounds like a silly question to be 19th, but did you actually expect to go there and win
or did you expect to do better than 19? No, I didn't have any expectations to be honest with you.
I didn't know what to expect. What I did understand was, you know, again, this is 97. So this is
pre-Olympic year, which means we were having the world championships in Nagano, Japan,
because they usually want to have a test event to make sure the venue works properly. So you can
imagine all of the Japanese that are there, right? My father's there, my grandparents are there.
I mean, it's a full arena with 20,000 people in that arena. I'm 14 years old. I've never skated
in front of more than like a thousand people in my life, let alone this many people. And I just
remember the roar was so deafening. And I just was like, man, this is, this is, this feeling is
so addictive. And looking at like all the other athletes in their like colorful skin suits and
the Koreans and they skated so differently than we did, the Chinese had their own style of skating,
the Canadians, the Italians. And I was like, man, this is like, this is crazy. Like this is,
I can't believe that I'm here. And I finished that competition. I very much realized and
recognized that the Koreans, in my view, were significantly better than everyone else.
Technically, the way they raced, the way that they carried themselves on and off the ice was
very, very unique at the time. And, you know, I came home from those world championships with
an incredible experience. I mean, mentally and psychologically. And then unfortunately,
instead of spending, this is now 97 this summer. So I'm going into
a lot of trials for the Olympics are going to be in February of 98.
So I come home in March of 97. So you've got basically eight months till the trials.
So I've got three and a half to four months until I go back into the national team program. Now,
before I was in the junior team program training in Lake Placid, we now I would be relocated to
Colorado Springs, the official Olympic training center of the United States. And this is where
all of the guys who I just beaten, you know, a month before this is where everyone's going to
be housed and trained 80% of the guys, some guys had their own personal coaches and Saratoga Springs
and other areas, but most of the team was training in one location. And, you know, if you have 12
people there, only five are selected to the team. One is an alternate for skate, the relay,
the top two from each distance skate individually, the games with an opportunity to win a medal.
None of this makes any sense to me still. Okay. Even though I had just won and even though I had
done very, very well, I come back from that competition and I go back to Seattle and instead
of training, my food choices were like basically Taco Bell pizza and zero, zero athletic activity.
I'm talking to it. Why? I don't think that I truly understood the importance of the off ice
training mechanism and off season training. I thought this was the break that you're supposed
to take. And my dad's like, I'm pretty sure you're supposed to be working out. I was like,
Oh, whatever. I just, you know, tell him I did. And I just, I didn't. And I, I fell back in the
same negative habit of hanging out with the same kind of crowd and individuals who that's what my
dad wanted me to get away from. And now what I was doing, I'm getting older, I'm more crafty,
you know, I've got experiences under my belt and I'm just doing it on my own. And finally,
when I get back to Colorado Springs, you know, I, and you head back at the end of the summer,
the beginning of the summer now, this is the end of the summer, the summer of 98. So you're like
four months from trial more like maybe like five and a half months from trials. And so now I'm in
a position where I've gained like all this, I think I gained like 20 pounds or something crazy
from when they saw me the last time you can imagine, right? I'm still going through puberty.
I'm still kind of maturing zero training, eating complete garbage food. And my physique totally
changed. Like I just show up with like spacey. There's two spare tires around my, but my body,
you know, and they're like, and I remember hearing when we're doing body composition,
we all take our shirts off and do the, do this test. I remember some of the other athletes going,
holy shit, like what the hell is that kid been doing? Because everyone's been busting their
ass in the off season because they all recognize the importance. And I, I just remember being
called a Springs and it was a different environment. I didn't, I didn't have Patrick
wetlands. My head coach had a different coach at the time because Patrick stayed with the junior
team. No, Patrick was the assistant coach now to the national team. He had zero power or say in
any of the training, just the way that structure was working at the time. And I wasn't mentally
committed to the sport at that time. And that's not a good thing, right? So here I am now training
with the national team, huge importance. Everyone's trying hard. Everyone's committing everything
they're doing. And I just going through the motions during that year. I just, do you have
a sense with the benefit of hindsight as to what, what else might've been going on in your head at
that time? Cause you've now tasted success, right? And not only have you tasted success,
you've tasted success on the back of huge effort, right? You had already discovered the weight room.
You had discovered your capacity for work, which like Phelps and like Haydn and like
all these other great athletes, it's really the capacity for training that seems to differentiate
them. You figured out you had that, you figured out your super power and then you decided, yeah,
I'm not going to do it. It's like this self-sabotage. I think that early in my career,
and I actually, I struggled with this later on in my career too, as an athlete where it's going so
well. It's almost too perfect. It's too easy. Let me throw, let me throw a little monkey wrench in
here and really let, let's see if I don't train and if I can really make the team again, because
let's see if I'm really that good. Yeah, yeah. I see what you're saying. So psychologically,
I had a pattern. I think of doing that. What's the minimum effective dose of training I can get to
still, you know? Yeah. Let me basically like screw off and like almost throw this opportunity totally
away and see if I can still come back and get it and remind me, cause I'll come back to that. And
the way that I raced for many, many years also is exactly like that. Let me wait until the very,
very last lap to make a move. I don't know. That's a very dangerous, like you're talking about,
it has to be perfect. You can't, yeah, the margin's gone. Yeah. So you're playing with fire at that
point. Right. And I remember one time skating a race, great Canadian speed skater, Mark Ganyal,
he watched me do this. I got waited till the last half lap that I passed all four skaters on the
outside and he's like, Oh, you're playing with fire, man. You're going to get burned one day.
You know, I remember that like in my head because I did and it, and it did burn me. So anyway, so
I mean, just to go back to your question. Yeah, that's, that's what happened. I mean, I,
I've been blessed enough. I was blessed to have a really unique gift to athletics and specifically
in short track speed skating. And I was really squandering. It was so easy. It was too easy.
I couldn't recognize that you've got this talent. You really also have to really, really dedicate
yourself and don't throw away this incredible opportunity because there's a thousand guys in
line who have half the talent, but would do 10 times more work just to be a fraction of what
you could possibly become. I didn't recognize it. It was just so stupid. And I'm, I kicked myself
now thinking about that, but that's what happened. So the whole year that year in Colorado Springs,
I went, they're just going through the motions, very defiant against my coach. Didn't really
want to be there. So when you entered the trials in December of 98, did you think you were going
to make the team? No, I, I wrote it off. I was like, I don't even want to make the team.
So you completely self-sabotaged at this point. I am so far departed. I'm the same. I have the
same mentality as I did before I went to Lake Placid. And so when I go to these trials and we
do a time trial in the beginning, let's say there's, let's say there's a hundred people show up for
the trials. You do a nine lap time trial and from those results, only 16 are now racing. And that's,
that's the bracket. 16 people now is making up your preliminary quarter heat semi final. I finished
a year. Don't say 17th. I finished 16th in the trials. So you made it. No, no, I didn't make the
team. I made the cut from the bracket, but I got last. So basically I should have got 17. That means
we wouldn't have to skate the whole competition. Right. Right. Right. I ended up skating the whole
competition. So you now earn the right to complete the right. I earn the right to try to compete.
And we still have video tapes of this, like every race I'm just crossing the line with like my head
facing the ice and looking down and just completely defeated as you know, a 15 year old. And so my
father, this to me is a really important part of my life. My father sees this and he had been
spending all his time in Seattle, right? So my father sees this. He then takes me from Boston
with the time. So it takes me back to Seattle after the meet you've lost. You didn't make the
team. I mean, everyone was just, I hear the quiet conversations. Oh my God, this kid is just, you
know, he's another student who stood away. He has so much talent. My dad's embarrassed, right? He's
like, Oh my God, like this, you know, what the hell happened? Like you were number one, less than a
year ago, you were supposed to go and be a medalist. My dad already bought tickets for the
Olympic games. Like he'd already set aside time to spend there. So now we're in, we're in a spot
where my dad is like, look, you have to make a decision. Do you want to continue in this path of
Olympic, you know, pursuit or do you want to do something else? And I was like, I don't, I don't
know what I want to do. He goes, that's exactly what I'm talking about. You don't know what you
want to do. So he takes me to this place where we used to go to and have vacations, which is three
and a half hours Southwest of Seattle area called Mo Clips beach, which is sounds nice, but it's
like rains like, you know, 300 days a year. And it's like very dark and it's beautiful now, but
he drops me off and he says, you're going to stay here until you figure out what you want to do with
your life. What do you mean stay there? You're going to stay here in this cabin. We rented a cabin
and you're going to stay here until you're ready to do the real answer with what you're going to do.
And I don't care what the answer is, but you have to come to a real decision and commit yourself.
And that's what you're going to do. And he leaves.
This is like the best parenting story in the history of parenting.
The bad kid, right? The only tough love is the only way to do this.
And he drops me off and he says, this is what you got to do. And I have food and I didn't have,
I mean, there's no video games.
Yeah, exactly. You don't have a cell phone and iPad.
There's no Instagram. There's no, there's nothing. It's just me and nature. And I have like workout
gear. I have a stationary bike. Like I have my old bike and I set up a little spinner in the back
and that's it. And like a pen and pad to write, to make notes and journal.
And every day I'm in here 15, 15. And you know, again, if you go back, like I, I grew up kind of
taking care of myself, so it's not a big deal to me, but I mean, thinking back, I'm like, Oh my God,
that's a pretty serious. What do you think? Have you ever talked to your dad about what was going
through his mind on the three and a half hour drive back to Seattle when he dropped you off?
He was terrified and scared and, and, and afraid he's making the wrong decision. Is he a bad parent?
Is this too much? Am I going to be able to handle it? And I think my dad is like, this is,
nothing else is working. No one can get to this kid. He's got all the green lights in his life
and he's throwing them away. Like this is it. This is the last straw. This is the last effort
with the guy didn't have, you know, jocko willing down the street to like basically say, you know,
like to really drill home the importance of what it needs to be done. I can call jocko right now.
And I would love it. I would have invited him over for dinner tonight. I never even thought of it.
So just thinking back, I was so fractured mentally. Did that first night in that cabin hurt more than
that first night your dad yanked you back to Lake Placid? No, those would be two tough nights, right?
It was different because this time when I left the Olympic trials in 98, I actually knew that I
could have made the team. And here's the sick part. I think that if I trained just for one month
before, I probably would have been top three and I would have made the team had I just put like a
fraction of effort and I didn't want to do it. I know for sure. I wanted to taste such devastating
defeat when I'm supposed to win something. I think I was addicted to that self-sabotage of,
okay, I'm at the real bottom now. What do I got to do? And so I spent nine days in this cabin
alone writing down, making a journal. I still have the notes actually. I'm writing down my thoughts
and praying and trying to just determine like why am I here? What am I supposed to do? Give me a
sign. I was like mindlessly going out on these runs 45 minutes, an hour, half an hour. And
it's raining every single day, by the way, because this is December and it's cold. And like there's
no, by the way, there's no one there. This is like the place where they send people who are part of
the witness protection programs. Like there's literally, there's like a, there's a native
American reservation, 15 miles up the road. And other than that, there's like, there's literally
no one else staying at these cabins. So it's you and like someone from the Gambino crime family
and witness protection as a 15 year old. It's not fun. I mean, now I would like love to spend time
there alone. And so I was going to say, give me the address I need to go. It's incredible. I mean,
it's a place where I go when I need to make really, really what I consider to be important decisions
where I want to make a shift. You still go. I haven't been in a couple of years, but I'm,
I'm planning on taking actually my girlfriend pretty soon. It's a beautiful place is there's
nature is, I think really, it's always been a very important part of my life. I think my dad did
that when I was ready to go where the exact cabin was. I know the exact cabin. I know the exact
place. They rebuilt it. Right. So it's, it's much nice. Someone bought the, it was called the iron
Springs resort at the time. And back then it was iron and Springs generally don't go side by side.
It wasn't nice. And definitely they should have left off the word resort for sure. At the time,
if like iron Springs jail, you know, penitentiary, every road is basically like a one-way road and
you're surrounded by the beautiful trees. But again, I'm just running every day and mindless.
I'm just trying to figure it out. 15 years old. I'm at the fork in the road. What do I want to do?
Do you want to please my dad? Does my dad want me to speed skate? Does he want me to do this? And
then finally I was like, you know what? Like, I think I want to speed skate. I think I want to
actually truly dedicate myself to do this. And also I was pretty bitter that I didn't make the
team, which doesn't make any sense. Right. Cause I didn't, I threw it away. Yeah. But I was also like,
I hated the feeling of that, of like the opportunity was there and I didn't take it.
Were you still in touch with your friends that you had grown up with that obviously for the
year and a half prior, you'd been somewhat detached from because you're now living this
separate life training. But what did your friends think of this opportunity? I mean,
did a lot of them, they didn't know, they didn't understand what you were going through. No,
I didn't really talk about it. They didn't really understand. And that was very much in my own head.
And it was, it was when I made the decision to continue one more time and really, really give
short track speeds, getting a try is that changed my whole life. I mean, what do you think happened
in that nine days that made you, cause you had to leave there, go back home, watch the Olympics six
weeks later, basically watch three other skaters in your flag and your colors and thought, you know,
I really could have been one of those guys and then decide, I mean, not that you would have known it
at the time, but this would go on to occupy your life for the next 12 years. Right. Yeah. So I,
I remember calling my father and saying, I made a decision. I want to come back to Seattle. And he
didn't ask me what the decision was, by the way, he just came and picked me up and drove me back.
And during that three and a half hour drive, I explained him what I want to do. And he's,
I think I can feel that he's like, okay, let's see. And so I go back to Lake Placid, the train
under a different coach. You wait till the Olympics are over. I don't know. This is,
this is still during the Olympics. I go, I go the right away because after the Olympics,
there's a world team trials, which the format's messed up. But so after the Olympics is a world
team trials. Now I have the opportunity of, of making the world team, which at this time,
after the Olympics, no one's training, no one cares about the world team. And I remember just
kind of training really hard and studying and I get, I get sixth at those world team trials.
So I was a double alternate, which means I would skate no distances at all, but I would basically
just carry the bags for everybody. And if two guys got hurt, then I had a chance at getting in.
So I went to those world championships and I was, I just had a different view. My, something had
switched in my mind and I started taking notes and I made promises to myself, like real legitimate
promises that I could never get out of it. When I get home, I'm not calling anybody. No one's even
going to know that I'm back home in Seattle and my off season or the time spent after this,
the next four and a half months is going to be completely dedicated towards just,
just being a monster. And so set up the stationary bike in the basement, had a small seven inch or
nine inch Sony Trenton TV, VCR, and I just watched skating tapes every single day, trained twice a
day alone until I arrived back in Colorado Springs as a part of the national team program. And I was
significantly more fit and stronger than anyone else and developed such a strong aerobic base that
I was bearing everyone on my team. Even though I was still ranked number six, I was by far number
one. And so the next big test for you would have been the 99 worlds. Yep. Which was where that year?
Sophia Bulgaria. The real test was actually that year, 98. I won my first world cup medal. I ended
up winning a gold in the thousand meters against the reigning thousand meter Olympic champion,
Kim Dong-sung and Fabio Carta, who was like many times you should have been, you should have been
world champion. And I won. I came out of nowhere. That became my real first taste of, of winning
on the world circuit. And again, this is post-Olympic year. So it's not that important. Like
people don't really care. No one in the US is even watching this stuff. It really cared to me.
It also was a time where I got in, I started to work with a sports psychologist and that was the
big, big difference in terms of performance. What did he or she teach you or what was the most
important insight that you got early on from that experience? So this, this guy named David Creswell,
who was pretty young at the time, I think he was actually still studying and he was going to. How
did you meet him? He was brought in as an intern to basically look over a lot of the younger athletes.
And he also was doing a sports psychology kind of residency program at the Olympic training center.
And so he was so pro about all these different things. And he started asking me,
we would play badminton like for fun. I would make mistakes like over and over again. And he would
notice that I was kind of getting down on myself and he would ask me these like little questions.
Oh, what happened there with that shot? And I, this guy was so young. I was like, I can't respect
this guy. And I just, I didn't recognize the time that he was basically trying to figure out
how I ticked, like what made me angry and the inconsistencies that would happen on the court
were a direct representation of actually what was happening in sport. And so that was my first
real foray into understanding. And so we did everything from like, you know, meditation
exercises to breathing exercises, to writing down positive self, you know, the basics, right?
Positive self-talk, manifesting what you want. And then he began my real true process of
visualization. And then I ended up winning the 99 junior world at that time in Montreal,
which was a huge win. The time was still eligible to compete at junior world. I was still eligible
16. And it was hugely beneficial. The mental component of the sport was always to me,
the most fascinating and the most underutilized in every aspect. And to my detriment later on
in my career too, because we did, I did things that completely are very destructive when we look
at the thing about it in terms of sport science and the training that we did. And, but to me,
I didn't care. Like I wanted the edge of being able to say, I'm going to wear this 45 pound weight
vest. I'm going to go up this man to incline five times back to back and do skating jumps
every 25 steps on one leg and then switch to the left and then do them alternate boom, boom, boom,
and just do that back to back until basically I throw up. Now there's no physiological benefit
you're getting after like the first set, right? But the psychological advantage that you created
just this mental hardness that no one else would do. And I loved it. The harder it snowed outside,
the less people that are outside. I want to be out there with the weight vest doing some dumb
training. That to me was the epitome of what was a driving force later on in my career. And I
craved it time and time again. You mentioned it earlier, and I know you've talked about in the
past that you always looked at boxers as role models, even though you didn't end up boxing.
And it's funny because that's very much a boxer's mentality, right? I mean, I think with every
sport, so much of it is going on between the ears, especially a sport when it's against another
individual, which is not the takeaway from the team sport, but when you lose in tennis, there's
no subtlety about who won and who lost, right? But this idea of how the training feeds the beast,
growing up, I felt it's so funny. I mean, on a much smaller level, I remember I used to run at
4.30 every morning. So all of high school, I would run at 4.30 and it had to be somewhere between 5
and 13 miles was the distance. And growing up in Toronto, it was so cold in the winter that
like the colder it was and the darker it was, the happier I felt. Because I remember thinking like
the guy I'm going to fight is not up at this moment. There is no way he is in a warm bed.
And that just that fact absent any physiologic benefit became the thing that you needed to hang
on to. And again, I don't know how many skaters thought that way, but you clearly were training
like a fighter. And living in the Colorado Springs Olympic Training Center, we were all
rooming with different short trek athletes. And then there was one time in which instead of
rooming with a short trek athlete, they had asked me if I wanted to room with a wrestler. And every
one at the time was like, no, the wrestlers are dirty. These guys always get staph infections.
They're like just nasty. Then they're crazy. And I was like, sure, I don't mind. Like I'll
run with the wrestler. And that was my first entrance into the mind of a fighter. And I loved
it because I'm like, look, I wear spandex for a living and skating circles. It's not the most
manly thing known to me on this planet, but I wanted it to be more than it's not as primal.
I mean, you could argue wrestling or practicing are about as primal as any sport gets. Right.
You're fighting against another human being, basically. In my own right, I was fighting in
my own ways. Right. And there's many correlations there. But I love the psychology of those wrestlers
that I would see. And I would go in the sauna post weight training workout. And I would,
I was the only non wrestler in the sauna every time they were in there ever. And I just remember
like talking to these guys and hearing them talk to each other and watching them cut weight and be
like, these guys are not human. They are doing everything against what I was told from a sport
science perspective. And they still are winning like that mental toughness and fortitude.
That's what I craved was that old school Rocky mentality and that hardness that is created that
I loved. And I thought that was the only way that I could beat the Koreans. That was the only
because I didn't skate as beautiful as they did. And even to this day, I still love it. Right. I
still like that mentality. And it was a huge part of my career was was developing that mental
fortitude and that strength and that consistency of being so obsessive and replace my self sabotage
stuff with the self sabotage came in the form of like, let's just do some workout that makes no
sense. Yeah. You went to the pendulum swung so far. You stopped self sabotaging and incompetence
and in effort and you started to overdo it. And again, I even just some of the videos I've
watched, I'm like, Oh my God, like I watch it now as an old guy who's only thinking about how to
avoid injury. And I'm like, Oh my God, like all the ways you could have just destroyed your body
with those things. Yeah. We used to do some really just ridiculous, ridiculous training, but
you know, again, you're young, your body's resilient, you're gifted, you're doing what you
love. You're in an arena where that's the only thing that matters. Nothing else exists outside
of this realm of short track speeds, getting it's the most important thing in the world. Nothing
else is here. It was beautiful and I loved it. And so 2002 is the big test. Now you've had four
years to get on the horse. You've won some meets, some important meets, but for most Olympic
athletes, the world only considers the Olympics. They don't care about winning the worlds, even
though the competition is just as stiff at the worlds. So going into the trials in late Oh one,
were you nervous? What was your confidence level going into make the 2002 team? I wasn't nervous
at all. I was ready and I skated incredibly fast there. I did a time trial. It was like 123.8
was my time trial time. Wait, wait, that's your 1500. That was my thousand meter time.
And at the time no one was skating under 125 in the world. So when the world heard that I had
skated this lap time, they knew that I was ready. And you know, the Koreans, the first time they had
to worry about an American skater who was in their race. It was the first time a Canadian had
to worry about me was kind of through 1998, 99. So it's interesting. The time trial is kind of a
nice normalizing metric because it strips out the technique, the strategy, the where this person is.
So just because you have the fastest time trial doesn't at all mean you could win. You may still
get, you may have a dumb race. You may not be able to maneuver and sort of physically get in and
around other skaters, but it's certainly a beautiful metric. It's a bromberg. Yeah. Yeah.
It's sort of like in cycling. It's your FTP, your functional threshold power. And it shows like,
oh, this guy is in incredible shape. By the way, what is your lactate at the end of a thousand
meter time trial? How high would your lactate get? I don't even remember. My lactate was low.
You're like Lance Armstrong in that regard where Lance is lactate after the typical set that they
would do, which would be a one kilometer uphill sprint. And they would do lactate checks at the
end of these. I mean, his lactate levels were just half of everybody else's. Yeah. I was very,
I was low. So a lot of the sprinters had super high lactate levels. Like they were like in the
twenties or something crazy. And I was like always like nine or something weird. I forget
the actual numbers, but we would do six by 1000 meters with what rest. I want to say the rest
was two minutes. So it's two minute rest or on an interval that gave you about two minute rest from
however you go to nine laps again fast. Jesus. Yeah. We hated doing lactate testing, but that was,
oh, so they would prick you each time. Each time. Yeah. So that generates your lactate
performance curve. Yep. Yeah. Yeah. Yep. And mine was pretty steady. Like I would maintain like my
lap time and also my speed was around the same, even in the set four or five, six. Wow. In speed
skating, a lot of it's got to do with technique. So yeah. Although it's so funny. Like I don't
know what they're doing these days in sports science cause I don't really pay much attention,
but I wonder if they're doing muscle biopsies on people and looking at lactate clearance and stuff
like that. No, no, no. No one's offering up a little vastus lateralis biopsy. I, and maybe
they are in cycling, but I can tell you from just listening to your podcast, 99.999% of all
athletes in the US who are Olympic level have no idea what they're doing when it comes to nutrition,
when it comes to training, they're just doing what kind of they're told. And I say that with
all due respect, right? But that's just all that much more impressive that they can do so much.
It's changing slowly. But since I retired in 2010 and being so obsessed with like looking back on
my career and wanting how different I would have done it now versus then and just understanding how
the human body works and all the different efficiencies or deficiencies or over-training
and recovery. And there was so much, I think specifically for short track speed skating,
because we were so predominantly dominated by the Korean culture and skating. They never used
sports science. They did everything by eye. Very old school, right? They were just technically the
most proficient to the most beautiful. Biomechanics were, and if you did study their training and you
did study the way that they skated, it all made sense. But they, again, they didn't, you didn't
have a sport science team there measuring lactate. When I went to my first Olympic games in 2002,
like the rumor to the Korean team was that I had like some unknown military NASA grade technology
that I was using because I couldn't figure it out. Right? Cause I didn't skate that nice.
Was O2 Salt Lake City? Salt Lake City. Okay. Yeah. Post 9-11, it was incredible experience.
It was incredible being 19 years old. Your first medal, was it a gold or a silver? My first medal
was a silver. Was it the thousand? It was a thousand meters. Oh my God. Which is, that's the
funniest race of them all. I didn't know that was your first medal race. That was my first Olympic
final. Can we talk about like how funny the race isn't funny, but the video we're going to link to
is exceptional. Right? It's perfect. It's actually perfect. I'm so happy that I can laugh about it now.
I feel like so honored that I could have shown you that video because you hadn't seen that video
until I showed it to you. No, but it's so perfect and so many levels. You know, it's like watching
your face, watch it for the first time. I can't believe I couldn't have had that on film. Like
there was just genuine, like joy. Like you couldn't stop laughing at that, which is, I'm
sure that would have not been that funny at the time. So let's tell people about that race, right?
So you're pretty favored going into this race. It's you. There's a Chinese skater. Yeah. To give
you context, I was in the cover of Sports Illustrated and I think that the article was
about, this was February of the games. It's pretty amazing to put a speed skater on the cover of
Sports Illustrated. It was ridiculous. And you know, I was sponsored by Nike and I was going to
these games and they said, like, Apollo has the chance to win four medals, four goals going into
these games. And everyone in short track speed games, like that's not going to happen. No one's
that dominant. Our sports do volatile and variable. It's just impossible. Yeah. Which is true, right?
I mean, this is a much harder, not to take anything away from long track, but in long track,
you only have to worry about yourself. Right. It's you against a clock. As you said, in short track,
anything can go wrong. Yeah. Almost without exception, it seems to go wrong. It always
goes wrong. Yeah. Whatever plan you had never goes exactly. My favorite Mike Tyson line, right?
And I don't know if Tyson actually said it, but it's like everybody has a plan until they get
punched in the face. It's exactly what happens to everyone's technique is beautiful until you start
to get tired. Yeah. Or until some guy jumps right in front of you and like grabs you or pushes you
or you get bumped or someone time trials it from the start. Now your whole plan from the beginning
is completely out the door because you're not prepared for that. So here we are a thousand
meters. I'm in the final. I've got one of the best Canadian skaters, Matt, you took out. I've
got a Chinese legend, Lee Jia Jun. I've got this young kid on hand, Sue, who's 16 years old. He
looks like Harry Potter with glasses. Literally that's our nickname for him as Harry Potter who
skates. So technically beautiful that I'll get back to that later before talking about it. And
then we've got Steven Bradbury, the Australian, the Australian. And by the way, let's tell us after.
So the race begins. I have my strategy. Bradbury had called you before, right?
Didn't Bradbury have some connection to the company two days before the semi-final? And he says,
Hey man, Hey mate, that's a time. Steven Bradbury was working for the skate manufacturer that made
my skates in, I think they were in, in Brisbane. He says like, Hey, I know you're probably going to
get on the podium. Would you mind giving a shout out for the boot company, RBC revolutionary boot
company? I'm like, Oh, Steven, no problem buddy. You know the problem. Hey, it's good to see you.
And he was like, Oh, so he's like the typical Australian is I loved him.
I never thought this guy would make it past the preliminary round. I didn't know, actually,
I didn't even think about it. I didn't know he was skating the Olympics. Like that's how much non,
like he wasn't even there in my mind. He was just another person who happened to be on the ice.
Like he could have been replacing the blocks on the ice, right? He wasn't even a competitor.
Yeah. You're thinking, wait, why are you wearing spandex just to replace the blocks? Like you,
you could do that in much looser fitting clothing. Yeah. I mean, I say that like jokingly and then
the day of the races, he, like this miraculous thing happens where two people get disqualified
and fall down. He makes it into semi-final and then he makes it into the final. Like he doesn't
make it. He makes it because people fall down and get disqualified. And now he is like sitting here
in this, in this final with like any, by the way, the Canadian, the Chinese, the Korean and me,
anyone I want to be can win gold, anyone I'm just going to win gold. I feel very, very confident in
my ability to win gold. And I had a very specific strategy two and a half laps ago. I start my,
my outside pass. I blast off one lap to go. I noticed that the Chinese skater is starting to
set up a pass or at least put himself in position to pass me. I didn't want that to have happened.
So I started skating very defensively and protecting my outside and inside position,
thus slowing us down. We fight the Chinese skater falls down about a half lap to go.
I swing a little bit wide. The Korean skater tries to go on the inside of me. He falls down
into me. I fall down and we all take out the last guy who's Matt, you took hot. Who's in third place.
The Canadian, the Canadian, the Chinese goes down. The Korean takes me. And then we all take
out the Canadian. So everyone falls down the same corner, which to this day has never happened.
The last corner, the last corner, I can see the finish line. I'm in first place by the way. So
I feel like I'm going to win. And I remember thinking in my head, I'm going to win. I remember
thinking that. And then literally, as soon as I snap my fingers, it was like the karmic reaction.
You're spinning out of, like you're down and spinning. I'm spinning. I hit the wall. I don't
know what happens. I later find out that like my right skate through my back, hitting the boards,
my right skate comes inward and actually stabs my left leg. And that's where I have a small cut
on that left leg. I get up, I throw my skates across the line. And what I didn't know at the
time that Steven Bradbury, who was like over a half a lap behind when we all fell down,
only takes about eight seconds to get around the track, comes around and he finishes first. And I
end up finishing second. And the video, which I mean, we're going to link to the video of the race,
because I remember the first thing I thought when I saw that was I was actually impressed
that you had the presence of mind to get up and get across the line because it looked, and I'm not
a skater, so I can't speak to it, but just as an observer, it looked so disorienting when you went
down. It was that I was like, geez, I wouldn't even think to do anything other than just stand up.
Like I wouldn't, and it's not like it wouldn't take me two seconds to realize to get across the
line, but you didn't have two seconds. It had to be like a brainstem activity. There could be no
cerebral involvement. It had to be pure brainstem of I'm down, I'm spinning, I'm cut, get across the
line. And you did what none of the other skaters were able to do. Like you were the first one in
that whole melee to get across the line, but of course Steven got across first, giving you the
silver medal. Yeah. And I ended up winning the silver and it was a really good shout out for
the boot company because first and second guy both were wearing the same boot. That's right.
That's right. And Steven, I remember he just kind of goes across the line and raises one on barely.
He's standing straight upright across the line. I believe it. It's the least
blank impressive finish. And Bradbury cannot believe what just happened. And no Australian
was watching the winter Olympics, by the way. So all of a sudden they got to probably send someone
there from their media team. They're like, Oh my God, you got to get off the surfing track and get
over on the, on the, right. Right. Right. So he, Steven wins. I ended up actually winning silver,
very disoriented, had no idea what just happened and got a cut in the process. And it was the most
important race of my entire Olympic career because at the time, look, I very much wanted to win.
Not only that, it was so important for me. I felt like I should have won. I think that's natural
for me to say that, right? I really felt like I should have won and I felt like Steven should
not have won. I didn't know actually that he won at that time. I couldn't believe what just happened
and I was trying to figure out in my head and process. Meaning after you've crossed the line,
it's still not entirely clear that he's won. Even though you've seen him also skate across the line,
sort of bolt upright, but you haven't figured this out. Yeah. I mean, I knew, I knew that someone
crossed the line and it was probably Steven, but more importantly, I was figuring out like,
what just happened. Right. Is there a rule that says like you can't come from 200 feet behind when
everyone, yeah. Yeah. Like what's going on? It was more like, I was more thinking like that last
half lap, like what happened? And then I noticed it like I got this itchy feeling on my left leg.
So you don't even realize you've cut yourself. I had no idea at the point at that point until
I went into the locker room and took my skin suit off and they had a chance of like, Oh my gosh,
like that was a crazy, crazy race. And I remember coming out and someone asked me, well, Paul,
what does it feel like to lose the gold? That was the first question. It was the first question.
Michael was like, I didn't, I didn't lose the gold. I won. I won the silver, you know, and
that, that answer wasn't entirely me. There was a guy, Brent Hamilow, who was our sports physician
at the time came in the locker room. Cause he had to look at my cup before we went back out there to
go receive our medals. And he was like, Hey man, I know you wanted to win, but that was incredible.
Like you have to be so proud of yourself for having that ability to cross the line. It was
so instinctive, right? I would be an idiot to claim that I had that plan and it was all my
grandmaster idea to do that, but it wasn't. I just, I felt like I had to finish the race.
Dude, it's another boxing analogy, right? And we can't get away from the fact that your name is
Apollo. Okay. And in the second Rocky, when Rocky and Apollo fight, they both go down. This is a very
rare occurrence in boxing that both fighters go down. And if they both can't get up, it's a draw.
But if one of them can get up and the other guy can't, he's the winner. And obviously everybody
knows how that goes. Rocky amazingly managed to get up while Apollo couldn't. So this time, Apollo
actually got up first. Yep. Got up first, but I finished second. And cause my first Olympic games,
I felt like I had been through a lot psychologically, even though- Did you have to race
again that night? Two days later. Okay. Oh, this is something I should tell you. Before I went out
there, I had to get stitched up quickly. Guess who my surgeon was? Eric Heiden. Come on. Yes.
Eric Heiden. So Eric Heiden stitches me up and I was looking at him. He's like, Hey man, that was
amazing. That was so incredible. And all I want to tell was like, Eric, I'm just trying to be like
you. I'm just trying to win every distance. Because I still, even though it was pretty
impossible, that's what I wanted to do. I wanted to win all, I wanted to sweep just like Eric Heiden
did. And I feel like I had the ability to, if everything went in my direction and this was the
first blemish, but it was pretty cool to be able to be stitched up by kind of like your idol and
then have that conversation and then have him say like, Hey, look, your Olympics aren't over yet.
Like you're just getting started. So get back into the game, remain your focus and forget about this
race as much as you can and prepare for the next one. When I went out there, happy as hell, 19 year
old kid from Seattle could have thrown it all away. And here I was competing in my first Olympic
games post 9 11 hearing thousands of Americans screaming USA, chanting my name. I would never
replace that with anything ever in my life. It was so, it was just, it was awesome. I mean,
every, and I felt so proud to be able to win a medal for the US and win a medal for my family
and for my team and for my country. It was, it was awesome.
Mad Fientist How long after the race, did you get to talk to your dad?
Immediately because NBC grabbed him and they wanted him right down by the ice and right away.
Mad Fientist What was his reaction?
He was just proud.
Mad Fientist Was he worried about your leg? I mean,
what else was going on in his mind?
He was worried about my leg. He was right by the ring side and he's, my father's looking in.
I see my dad right away. He's just, he's just very proud, you know, and that to me,
it felt very, very good. And I remember standing on the podium, even though not hearing my
own national anthem being played, just feeling amazing and actually thinking back,
if there was any person in that race who I would want to win the gold versus me,
it would probably would have been Stephen Bradbury. And just because that guy, and people don't know
this, he had been through hell, like a skate blade had gone through that guy's leg at one point.
Like he had almost died many times on the ice, like pools and pools of blood. He had come back
from devastating injuries, broke his back, like weird, crazy stuff. And through it all,
he stuck with the sport and he was the last man standing. He wasn't the best speed skater.
He wasn't the most technically gifted physically. He was a monster, but he wasn't supposed to win
that race. But because he didn't give up, he ended up winning that race when everyone else
was better than him. Everyone else was there and it was, it was pretty remarkable.
So Matt target, who's a swimmer, an Australian swimmer he's been to, I think three Olympics.
He's a good friend of mine. And I actually sent him the video that we're going to also link to
because that's the one that we were talking about earlier, which is the, there's an Australian guy
who does a commentary and voiceover dubs the video. And it's really funny. His point being is like,
if you just stay out of people's way, you can still win. Right? Right. And he met, I think he said to
me that in Australia, there's still an expression around his name. Like you can pull a bribery,
right? Yeah. You win the lottery. Oh, you just pulled a Bradbury. Oh my God. You just jumped
up at a plane, your parachute didn't open. And then somehow someone else grabbed you,
didn't Bradbury like just freak golden horseshoe luck. By the way, Stephen Bradbury retired that
night. Every women gold. He knew him. Yeah. He's like, this is the pinnacle. This is the pinnacle.
I am now on and I am, I have an Australian stamp with my face on it. This doesn't get better than
this for me, Australia's first winter Olympic gold medal. So you had to go on and continue
through these games. So how did the rest of those games go? My next race was the 1500 meters in
which I was battling against my rival at the time, which was two guys, Mark Ganyal from Canada,
and also Kim Dong-sung from South Korea, who was the reigning Olympic champion in that distance.
And Kim Dong-sung had this very specific strategy, which he had been testing on me
throughout the entire year. And that was he was going to lead the race with about seven laps to go
and just do a negative split. So every lap get a little bit faster, a little bit faster,
escaped very defensively. And I, my strategy was known all over the world that I always waited
until the last two laps. Because your explosiveness, you just basically based on your lactate tolerance
and your explosiveness, you're going to out muscle somebody. I had another gear that other people
didn't have. And I think that the training that we did at that time directly just, you know,
is a massive attribute to exploding when there was a lap or two laps to go, as long as I could have
that reserve. But you needed the lane. You had to be able to technically, you had to have the ice
to do that, right? There's got to be space. And so in short track speed skating, if I'm passing
a skater in front of me and we have some sort of a conflict or collision, I get disqualified. At the
time, that's what the rules were. So you had to pass the other skater who was in front of you
completely cleanly with no contact. That puts a huge onus on the guy passing because he's got to
take a huge distance. Well, they changed the rules after this, after this Olympics, but at the time,
that's what the rules were. And so it was very important to pass completely cleanly with no
contact and any capacity. And I remember everyone knew that my inside passing lane was the best in
the world. How many kilometers an hour are you guys going about 40? We're going like around 35
plus miles an hour. Yeah. So you're going about 50 kilometers an hour. Yeah. There is at that speed,
aerodynamics is everything. Like there's an enormous draft advantage if you can slingshot
around someone. And I could skate behind someone all day long and break world records because I
was so comfortable. Anyway, it could, but I wasn't very good at leading for whatever reason. My
technical ability would change and my track pattern would change. Which is so interesting,
given that you still broke, you still have that time trial world record, like going under 125,
because there's no one blocking the wind for you there. Right. But later on in my career,
that became less and less of a big attribute of mine. So I was less and less a good time
trialer, more and more of a good racer, so to speak, about a lap and a half to go in the
1500 meters. I'm in, I'm actually in fifth place. I pass three skaters on the inside to pass into
second place. Now there's a lap remaining. It's me and Kim Dong song. I know that there's only one,
I'm actually doing this prior lap too late. I probably should have done this earlier, but I
didn't wait a little bit too long looking back. And I tried one, one last pass on him on the inside.
I recognize right away that he had known that I was going to be passing on the inside. So he
protected that inside lane position. And he really, really came over to protect that position as much
as possible. And I wanted to make sure there was no contact in the capacity. So I put my arms up to
show the referee who was in the corner. Look, there's no contact. I'm not pushing him. There's
nothing going on. And I slipped back in a second, finished the race. He ends up getting disqualified,
even though he finishes the race and wins. He had been parading around his South Korean flag and
celebrating in victory. My coaches knew that there was going to be a call being made. And why
was he disqualified? So he, at the time there was something called cross tracking. So even though
you're not, you're supposed to, if you come out of the corner and you're supposed to maintain your,
maintain your lane effectively, your lane, right? So if you, if you come out of the corner and
there's technically an inside lane, you can't immediately cut it off. Right. It's like blocking.
And so he was disqualified. I was a word of the gold and thus began this crazy relationship with
the country of South Korea that I would have never been able to do to explain. And so.
So you get a silver when you should have had a gold, you get a gold that you feel,
is this really a silver? Yeah, it wasn't a clean win. Right? That's very clear,
but I was awarded it. And at the end of the day, a win is a win. And so I celebrated as such.
So this time you get to hear your national anthem for the first time.
I hear my national anthem for the first time. It's incredible. It's everything you can think it.
We sit there. I remember watching that on TV. I remember where I was watching that on TV.
And it's like, I don't know you it's, but it's still emotional for us to watch this, right?
And to sort of, I think we put ourselves in the shoes of like these kids, right? And we think like,
wow, I can't imagine the sacrifice they just went through. The difference between winning and losing
seems to be almost random, stochastic, if you will. Right. But you did it. Wow. I can't believe
that you're standing there. And I mean, I think that's why we just love the Olympics, even sports
that we don't necessarily pay attention to outside of the Olympics, right? I think that the fascination
is like, we know these athletes aren't doing it for money because there is no money in the Olympic
space, you know, with the exception of like the 0.001%. And you know how much they dedicate. You
know that four and eight and 12 years of their life is dedicated towards this one moment. And
there's a sense of purity associated with that, that they really truly do it because they love
the sport. They want to go to the Olympic games and they want to be the best against the world's
best. And I think we can appreciate that. Now you won two more medals in 02, didn't you? No, I won.
I just won those two medals. You did. Okay. So you didn't win on the relay that year? No. One of the
guys fell in the relay. I feel like we would have won gold actually, heading out fallen. Which has
got to be tough. I mean, you always feel bad. I don't, I follow swimming much more closely,
obviously in any other sport, but it's always just the saddest thing for me when I see a guy
on the swim, you know, on the four by whatever this thing is. And when that one person has a
bad leg, you just, you feel worse for them than you feel for the other swimmers who swam their
best. Cause like, it's just hard. And I always sort of think it's beautiful when people console
the one guy who has the bad race or the one girl who has the bad race. Yeah. In short track speed
skating, it's such a variable. We grow up with that mentality. We call that short track. That's
your equivalent of shit happens, right? It's that short track. That's short track. Like, look,
man, like you plan everything. You are the best. You've been undefeated for years. You get the
Olympic game. Boom. You fall down. Shit. That's short track. Like that's the sport that you signed
up for. And if you can't subscribe to that mentality, you chose the wrong sport. But short
track to me is very much like life, very much like life, right? You can do everything right.
And for whatever reason, something out of your control gets thrown in your way and you have to
take it as such and learn from it obviously and come back stronger and better. But for the
most part, I think that's what it is. But you became one of the really few athletes that rose
above the sport, at least from a commercial standpoint. I mean, there are obviously a handful
of Olympic athletes that we can all name that end up on the, were you on the cover of a Wheaties box?
I was on the cover of a Wheaties box. That's like about as American as it gets. It might not be
necessarily the most lucrative commercial opportunity, but it is certainly the most
distinguished, right? I mean, to be on the Wheaties box is sort of. It's always a dream. Yeah. So I'm
not going to ask you to sort of explain why you think you rose to that level. How much of it do
you think had to do with just what you did on the ice versus something about you that sort of
captivated people's interests that goes beyond just the performance? Like, you know, obviously
you're a good looking guy, you're articulate. Your story is incredibly interesting as evidenced by the
fact that we could sit here and talk about this for like six days. And you also seem very comfortable
in that role too. Like it wasn't, you get the sense some athletes are really uncomfortable
with that. They're appreciative of it. And it's this great opportunity to sort of remunerate
some of their success. But you seem like totally natural in that role, right?
I think, yeah, I mean, I, look, I was extremely blessed to be able to be one of the few athletes
that both NBC chose and wanted to feature as a star athlete. And my story for whatever reason,
and I think, look, immigrant father comes to the U S doesn't have anything, tries to raise this
kid. This kid is bad, finds his life through sport, turns it around, understands the power
that he has throughout the sport. And then against all odds, I was able to deliver in some capacity
and I didn't deliver a gold net first race. It was a silver. Well, it was a scrappy silver. I mean,
I think that's in some ways, I think people much prefer, like if you had gone out, you know, I
don't know what the expression is in speed skating, but if you'd gone wire to wire, right? If you'd
time trialed that event and won by five lengths or, you know, by five, you know, body lengths or
whatever, it's like, okay, wow, he's dominant, but to fall, cut your leg, you know, barely know which
way is up and down and manage to really take the group of four that you're racing against and be
the first one across the line. That's a, that's a heartfelt silver that I think most people
probably find more appealing and actually probably creates a better substrate for the
way we like to use sport as metaphor for life. I think that's exactly, I couldn't have articulated
it better. I mean, I think that we, you know, Americans, look, we love dominance. We love to
win, but we also like to see a story that, that somewhat mirrors what we can relate to. And it
wasn't perfect in any way. But I think at the end I was, I also didn't want to cross the line. And
even though I was upset, I didn't win gold. I didn't want to show that. I didn't want to be like,
hey, I should have won gold. That guy, that Australian guy shouldn't have been in the final.
He's not a good skater. That I didn't want to have or be near that type of a mentality. Instead,
I had an opportunity, I think, to be really, really appreciative and have gratitude for the chance to
even be there. Number one, even though I was supposed to win the race, but take it from that
perspective and then just like I won my first Olympic medal, you know, like that that's the,
this is how the race played out. Not to plan, not exactly how I would have written it, but this is
how it went. And I've been through a lot personally to get to that point. And I really,
really wanted people to see that I was proud to win that silver. I was proud to win a bronze.
I was proud to be there and compete. That was really important for me to people to recognize
and see that I didn't take it lightly. I didn't take it for granted. Like I'd done in the past
and it was something that I was humbled by. And I mean, I got to the start line in that race and
people were chanting my name like in the arena. I mean, I'm 19 years old. That, that is not normal
of any stretch of the imagination. I got to imagine that's different even from the world's
like that's a totally different experience. Right. It feels so different as an hour camera
in my face every second, every inch that I move around and there's immense pressure. I hear people
in the audience who I don't know, Apollo, bring home the gold, you know, like, and I can feel like
the actual genuine authenticity that exists within saying bring home that like people really,
really wanted me to win. Well, yeah. And you've alluded to it already, but this was only what,
four months after 9 11, this was still a very unified country in a way that I don't know that
we've experienced since. I'm walking in the opening ceremonies in Salt Lake city from
our staging area to inside of the time, it was called the Delta center. That's where the,
the opening ceremonies were. And I remember seeing on all of the rooftops and in the trees,
all of the American servicemen snipers, they're sitting there and I remember looking up and
seeing them and then they, they, because they know it's us, right? Cause they've got their,
their binautros on the goggles and they wave. And I'm like, this is much bigger than me.
My representation of what I do, my silly sport of short track, speed skating,
my insignificance of going in circles in this world. And I'm 19, so I can't really understand
it to that degree, but the feeling is there that what I do here is far more important than the
results that I give. Obviously I want to win. I want to bring home the color gold because that
is what we signify with being successful. But at the end of the day, I wanted the representation
of who I was on the ice at that period of time to reflect, I think what we would be proud of.
And that would make my father proud. And I knew if I had that happened that I could be proud that
our country would be proud aside from all the other conflict and things that we disagree with.
That was a really important part, right? Of, of what I was doing. And it's a tremendous amount
of pressure too that you don't recognize. No one can prepare you for the Olympic games.
I used to do visualization and hear and have previous tapes recorded and then like try to
visualize and close my eyes and visualize a race that I wanted to have happen while the crowd is
in my ears. But when I went out there for my first race, I couldn't, nothing could have prepared me
for that. My heart rate jumped from like whatever being like 50 to like 160, like literally within
seconds. And I was like, Oh my God, like I'm, I'm starting this nine lap race now at threshold
versus this is not supposed to work. You know, like I'm not prepared for those six by 1000s are
paying off now. Yeah. That's also a very addictive feeling. So what's the letdown like after the two
weeks after the games are over? Yeah. Well, depends on how you do. So you've done well. You've
obviously got a great commercial career ahead of you, but you still have four years until you're
going to be back on that stage again. You'll go to the worlds again. You'll do world cup, but you're
not going to feel that electricity for four more years, right? Correct. And nothing replaces the
Olympic games. There's no competition on the planet. So post games, you, I go on the media whirlwind
tour for basically six to eight months. I do every single interview and conversation and
sponsorships and commercial advertising stuff, because that's the only way you as an Olympic
athlete can generate any source of revenue. You're not really paid to win gold medals. You're not
paid to be a part of the team. You're there. And so what percentage of Olympians, United States
Olympians can secure enough sponsorship that that can become a sole source of income to sustain
them through another Olympic run. I E they do not need to go out and get another job. Maybe
less than a percent. Wow. For sure. Less than a percent, because even if you win a gold, it
doesn't necessarily guarantee you to have a good generating of income. If for whatever reason you
weren't featured or NBC didn't see you or sponsorships aren't interested, you just, you're a guy with
a gold medal. And I know a few who won gold, who have the most normal jobs that we normally would
see like, wow, that guy won gold. And why is he working here doing this like day to day activity,
like this manual labor? But that's just the reality of what happened. So I was blessed. I didn't have
to do that. I got great sponsor opportunities and I took the sport of short track speed skating,
which was relatively completely unknown to most Americans. And the first time they ever saw it
was that thousand meters in which I fell down and people were like, Oh my God, this is the craziest
sport I've ever seen in my life. And it was like, it's like roller derby. Yeah. That's what people
say. NASCAR on ice, we call it. Right. And it's crazy. It's fun. It's fast, it's explosive. There's
strategy. It's unpredictable. There's crashes. It's aggressive. The only thing, you know,
if they just allowed you to punch each other, it would be like the next American like checkbox.
They should be able to carry knives too. You should at least be able to like, you know,
clothesline somebody, right? Yeah. That would be, we get some different looking
athletes on the ice. That's for sure. There's so many other things I want to talk about. And I
realize like we're getting looks out there because they want us to go out for dinner. So let's
talk about oh six and 10. So, you know, one of the things you've told me before that I was
blown away by was the difference in your body weight between 2002, 2006 and 2010.
Most athletes who go from being 19 to 23 to 27 are putting on more muscle are getting bigger and
bigger. Right. You're maintaining muscle and getting leaner and leaner and leaner. Remind me
again the difference between your fighting weight in those three Olympics. Sure. So in 2002,
the training focus was power, ballistic, strength, and speed. Those are the important factors in that
time period. Do you remember how many watts you could generate for a minute on a bike on an erg?
I don't remember. I have to ask Dr. Randy Wilbur, who's I think he's still at the Olympic training
center in Colorado Springs, head of sports. You got to get all that data and send it to me. I
want so badly to see your LPCs and your wattages and stuff like that. I bet it was just sick.
It was good. I don't know if it was like astronomically high. Like I've hear these
other stories of other athletes who were short track speed skaters to be just freak in every
genetic response, but my ability was to recover really quickly. That was the one component. I
remember doing a test in, I remember doing all these different sports science tests. I remember
these doctors basically saying like, you need to live at altitude. Your body responds extremely
well the higher you go. For whatever reason, your body just produces a ridiculous amount of red blood
cells. You come down and you love it. So in your ability to recover high or low is different.
Yeah. The first time I trained at altitude, I got to go and swim in Colorado. I was like,
like I'm not swimming. I'm not doing the same stroke. Nothing feels the same up here. I
couldn't believe it. Yeah. I think Colorado is like 6,400 feet. I think you're at the elevation.
Back then we lived high and we slept high. Right. Because I think today isn't the conventional
wisdom. You want to live high, train low. Doesn't that produce the best outcome? Correct. That's
correct. So you're better off actually having a tent and training at sea level. Yeah. Then there's
some arguments against the entire tent related. What type of stress that places on the human body
and is it natural form of stress? Did you get the proper response? There's some arguments back and
forth that Dr. Renny Wilbur was like, no, I think the actual natural environment far exceeds. I'm
sure it does. Something that he tried to explain to me, obviously I didn't understand. So in 2002,
you're weighing what? So 2002, I weighed approximately 164 to 167. So call it 165. That
was my fighting weight and I could like press around 1400, 1450, 1500 pounds. I'm just giving
you just context. So a small car. My back squat was never really that high. I think a lot of it
had to do with just the way that I hinged. I was very good hunched over in that position. I could
generate a lot of power when my back was rounded. Which you don't want to be squatting in that
position. Yeah. It's complete opposite. But you were still probably what squatting? I think you
said you were probably in the mid 300s for 12 reps. Yeah. About 350, 365, 275. Which is still
pretty, that's probably a max of 500 at a body weight of 160 is no slouch. Yeah. I mean,
my vertical was really high. Almost like 36. Jesus. Do you know what your single leg vertical was?
No, I don't remember that. Again, this is all stuff that I wish that we had. Because we trained
so hard. I'm convinced by the way, the single leg vertical is probably the best predictor of speed.
Yeah, I think so. And your ability to generate force into the ground. I like to see the difference
between doing a single jump and doing a series of two or three. And seeing that reaction time
and generating a power over all these cool tools and ideas that I wish we had implemented. We
probably had the ability. We just didn't implement them properly back then. So in the 06, what did
you weigh? 06, I weighed about 155 pounds, but I could still lay press the same amount of weight.
So I was significantly leaner in 06, significantly leaner. So long gone is the chubby boy. Yeah,
gone. We have new coaches. I now have a Chinese coach going to those games.
These were in Italy this year, wasn't it? Yes, Torino, Italy. And I performed very well in those
games. I ended up winning a gold in the 500 meters. I won wire to wire, controlled the race,
did very well. Wasn't the best skater out there for sure. But strategically, it was my day. Did
you also get a relay medal that year? Yes, we did. We got a bronze. And then what did you weigh in
2010? And in 2010, my goal was to be under 150. And I hadn't been under 150 since I was 14 years
old. When I was 14, I was 135, 137. And then I ballooned back up, obviously. So my goal was
to be under 150. I ended up competing between 142 and 146. Jesus. So I would say on average,
it's about 143, 145 pounds. How much strength did you give up to get there? It was weird because
I could leg press the same amount of weight. I could leg press nearly 2000 pounds at that
weight, like 1900, something like that. The difference was my pure ballistic power
was drastically different. I stopped doing all Olympic lifts. So were you doing a lot of
plyometrics? A lot of weighted plyometrics. But again, I cut most of that weight that year,
like that Olympic season. So you can imagine like the first half of the year was spent just
cutting this weight. So essentially living in a catabolic environment all the time to eat excess
muscle mass from your upper body, traps, arms, you know, I mean, I had no, I see that picture.
My arms were so skinny back then. It was very similar to what you'd see in someone who's climbing
in a toilet. I remember Lance saying that during the tour years, he wouldn't do one pushup or swim
one lap in the spring and going into it because it's like you had to be able to waste as much
muscle as possible from the upper body. You want complete atrophy from the hips up. And there's
a crazy stories that we hear that like these cyclists would like basically put themselves in
a sling in the summers during their training. Right. Cause it lose also. And the reason why
and people are like, why would you want that body to say those people that ask that question
have never ridden a bike up a hill. That's how long it's every bound counts. Yeah, it is. I mean,
cycling in many ways is such a beautiful sport because there are a few sports that can be reduced
to such formulaic outcomes. And when you can take functional threshold power divided by mass in
kilos and get a number in Watts per kilo that essentially predicts who's going to win the race
up a hill. That's pretty amazing. And speed skating, it's harder because one, I don't know
what the metric is of power, but two absolute power to translate to a bike is much easier.
Like you're transmitting from the leg to the pedal, to the crank, to the wheel, but in skating,
there's more to it, right? It's not entirely clear what the relationship is between the 2000
pounds that you can leg press versus how many of those pounds in Watts are hitting the ice, right?
There probably is not a correlation. Or it's probably loose correlation, but everyone's
different because if you can't put the power. If you don't have the technique, it's irrelevant.
Yeah. So like a bike, the technique is pretty simple. It's a push and pull at the basic level,
right? But in speed skating, there's seven parts to one push. Literally, there's seven parts to
one push that you have to drill in your head to make it automatic and normal. And you're never
on just one plane of balance on that piece of blade. You're in the heel, now you're in the middle,
now you're back towards the heel, and then you finish the ball or towards the toe. And it's
different depending on the speed, what you're doing, the track pattern. There's so many elements
that are always changing. For example, the Koreans, they don't lift weights, right? That became my
obsession. This started in 2002. Yeah, because you went to Korea, didn't you? I went to Korea
before 2010. In 2007, because I was so obsessed and fascinated with how they continuously kept
producing incredible athletes that I was competitive against. And they just skated so
beautiful. Now you were at this point, pretty much a god to them and they were gods to you.
Did they welcome you with open arms? They did actually. They invited me, and partially because
I think they just wanted to study me. They just wanted to see like what made me tick,
how strong is my ability to train? Can I handle their type of training atmosphere and environment?
And I was fascinated to go into the belly of the beast. I wanted to go into that lion's den
and understand what makes them tick. And my dad was completely against it, but I was like,
this is something I have to do. And eventually he was like, this is something you have to do.
Why was your dad against it?
So after the 2002 Olympic games, there was after that race where I was awarded the gold and the
Koreans came up to qualify. There was 16,000 emails sent in the form of death threats to the United
States Olympic committee because of that race to me. It was pretty crazy. So it was, again,
it was a time where my relationship with Korea changed overnight. We ended up not going to
Korea for two years for competitions because we were unsure of the environment.
When you say we, you mean you and your dad or the US team?
No, me and the US team. We none of us went. I mean, my face was on a toilet paper inside
the country. Like I was the second most hated person aside from Osama bin Laden inside that
country. Literally.
Unbelievable.
It was unbelievable. We can talk about this other thing. Like for two hours,
I have a thousand stories in relation to that. And like when I actually decided to go against
everyone's wishes, I was like, I can't just keep running from this problem. I gotta go.
The number one, they haven't heard me tell my story. Like they hate me for reasons that are
unexplainable. And also they're not really that fair because they don't know me. I'm not a
referee. I didn't make the judging call. I am an athlete. I am a, I'm a sportsman. I compete like
anyone else does under the same rules and capacities. And I walk away regardless of outcome.
Right. And it was a changing time. So the Koreans were always number one. I was the only threat at
the time to them and their legacy. And it was a huge, huge part of my fascination with actually
saying, you know what? I gotta go there. Even though they're going to study me, I have to go
and understand it's like someone going to train with Usain Bolt in Jamaica for like three months
and seeing what is he doing? Is he doing some exercise? What are they eating? Where is their
sleeping habits? What is their recovery? How did they get massage? Right? What kind of all these
elements. And you already knew that they weren't doing the type of off ice work that you
were. What surprised you the most about what they did on ice? The two things that I recognize right
away was their efficiency in training. There was no talking when you're on the ice. There was all
business. When you shut up at the ice rink at four in the morning, four 30 in the morning, there was
already probably 30 skaters there who are eight to 12 years old who had been practicing technical
drills before you even got there. So their commitment to perfection in terms of technique
is drilled in at a very young age. So their efficiency ratio, they don't have to be as strong
as me in the weight room because they're so much more efficient. That's what it came down to.
This by the way, has another beautiful parallel to swimming, right? I mean, unlike cycling,
in swimming, the relationship between the power you can actually generate and how you can transmit
it to the water is elusive. And I don't know if the guy who wins the race is necessarily the
strongest on land. It really doesn't matter. It's so much more about avoiding drag and efficiently
putting your muscle into the go. So in that sense, it's much more like skating where
there are certain swimmers who have some of the most unimpressive physiques. I mean,
Phelps has such an impressive physique to begin with. It's sort of the best of both worlds, but
there are some really ridiculously scrawny looking pathetic swimmers who like biscuit chest dudes
that can't like literally can't do anything. But when they get in the water, they sure as hell can
do something. Sure. It's very much the same way with speed skating. And I saw that. And the first
thing I recognized was their ability to copy each other was unlike anything I'd ever seen. When you
go watch a US short track speed skating practice, everyone skates entirely different. You can pick
out who's who. When you watch a Korean speed skating practice, they all look the same. You
can see a couple of the guys that stand out, but for the most part, and it's beautiful to watch,
they're very quiet. They don't make a lot of noise when they go around the corner,
they're extremely efficient. And I remember the first day that I showed up, we broke like five
world records in that practice. And to the girls who are leading, by the way, in the 3000 meter,
we did five times 3000 meters, five times 27 laps, to the girls I never ended up seeing for the next
couple of years. They never made the team. And they were the ones who were leading this from start
till finish breaking the world records. So they just have a mass talent pool of skaters that they
can just pick and choose from. And just like the old school Eric Haydn era of survival of the
fittest, we're going to pick out the pure genetic monsters who not only technically are the most
efficient, but also can handle the greatest amount of volume and load and training. They're going to
rise to the top. And usually the South Korean skaters only last one or two Olympics at the
absolute most before they're just gone. And they just like literally overnight, they just-
They get replaced by the next cog in the mission.
It became and make the team. So my whole goal for showing up in Vancouver was in 2002,
I was dominant. 2006, I had won a gold, probably could not have replicated that. And in 2007,
I was losing my dominance in the sport significantly and people were skating so fast.
Was that mostly just apparent to you? Because usually the athletes the first to figure that out.
Or was it also visible to those around you? I think people started to notice that I was
no longer this undefeatable, unrecognizable, unknown mystery athlete from the US. Everyone
knew my strategy. Everyone knew my natural gate and rhythm of skating. And it was like do or die.
I wasn't dominant and I wasn't winning. I was winning, but I wasn't winning with the same
fashion I was where people were like, Oh my God, that guy just smashed the pack.
So was there a period then between 07 and 10 when you were even wondering if you would come back?
It was not wondering if I was going to come back. Cause I'd already committed. It was more,
how do I actually get to the games and have a chance at meddling? That was the conversation.
Like how can I win against this next generation of South Korean athletes that I've never faced
before who are so fast and so good. How old are they? You're, you're now 25, right? 26.
Yeah, they're 18, 19, 20. That was usually the range.
Which is interesting because if you really think about it for a male speed based sport,
you should still be able to peak in your mid twenties.
Yeah. For whatever reason, it was always a young man sport, short track speed skating.
I think a lot of it's got to do with flexibility and the way in which you move. And maybe there's
no correlation in the capacity, but that's just what it was in 2002. A lot of the heavier guys
had to retire before 2006. They couldn't meet the cut. The sport had changed from 2006, 2010,
a whole next generation of guys were tired because again, they couldn't meet the cut.
The way that we trained the focal points, what was important during training,
the elements that made you a fast speed skater are all changed. And we had a big coaching
turnover. So we went from a Chinese coach. I had a originally had a Canadian coach, American
coach to then a Chinese coach to then two Korean coaches who threw everything out the window when
it came to sport science and said, we are going to take you Apollo and change the way that you
technically skate. And physiologically, my goal was to show up as a different type of an athlete
that they would never prepare for. So I want to change my natural gating rhythm.
I can't help but bring the Rocky metaphor back. This is when Rocky comes back to fight club
because he gets killed by club or fighting Rocky style. And then Apollo comes back to train him.
I'm grinning as I say this because I realize it sounds so stupid, but it's really the example.
It's like you can't come back and fight club or the same way. You got to lose like 15 pounds and
you actually have to box instead of slug. Correct. If I want to be competitive, if I took the same
strategy of success from 2006 and 2010, I won't make the semi-final. That's apparent. And so that
meant I had to make drastic changes by 07. You had three years to change everything.
After I had gone to Korea and skated and recognized and knew what I was really up against and saw this
next generation of South Korean athletes who were training there, that would be the ones that I would
compete against and also recognize also when I stepped on the ice in 2010 and look in the
coaches box and see that I would have skated against 80% of the coaches because they all
retired and became coaches of those national teams who are then coaching their athletes to beat me.
They know me better than anybody. They'd seen me for 15 years at that point, right?
Technically. So the goal was to show up as someone who they couldn't prepare for. Different strategy,
different mentality, different training. And that meant drastic decisions and changes. And so I
hired a strength and conditioning coach who lived with me at my house in Salt Lake City, Utah,
to watch and monitor every single thing that I ate, every single extra training regimen that we did.
And I was a guy that I was never like, you never had to push me to train more. It was like, okay,
we need to figure out how to rest. Yeah. Like let's, let's figure out how to do some things a
little bit better, better here. And so it became a huge emphasis on recovery, a massive emphasis on
nutrition, which is recovery and just making sure that everything that I was doing was correlating
with my end result, which was being, let's be this light, let's maintain this strength. And I know if
I can at least do those two things, I've got the unique technical ability to at least get myself
to the podium. And it was a struggle because I love to eat. I love food. I'm always hungry. And
at 153, there's not a lot of weight to lose. Like, like, like my skin was very thin around my legs.
Like I had, it was all muscle. So I had to go catabolic. I had to lose excess muscle mass that
wasn't being specifically derived from the sport and perhaps was being generated from the weight
training that we were doing, whether it was deadlifts, whether it was poles, whether, I mean,
there was no more. I mean, in 2019, 1999, we were still doing bench press, right? It's a part of our
weight training program. That's got, that makes no sense in general. So even those cleans, really,
I mean, you could argue there was obviously an explosive benefit to the cleans, but two and a
half to three pounds there, probably an upper body mass, right? That you just don't necessarily need.
Now the benefit from those is incredible. And looking back, I probably should have incorporated
some specific type of Olympic or deadlift like activity. But I was so hyper focused and obsessed
with losing weight. I remember writing down on these little post-it notes and putting them all
throughout my house, the weight, and then like, Jesus, and then like zero regrets, like make sure
you get to the Olympic games with zero regrets, regardless of your outcome there, you have to
arrive, leaving absolutely no stones unturned in your preparation. You wrote a book by this title
years later. Yeah. And that was just because that was my mentality. And I was doing like dumb
workouts. I had two training sessions with the Olympic team, and then we would do an additional
one or two on top of that every day of the week, with the exception of Saturday and Sunday,
which was pure recovery. Saturday morning, we would skate Saturday afternoon, it was recovery,
Sunday, well, there was recovery. But the rest of the time I was doing these crazy sprints and
intervals on a treadmill that my, my strength and conditioning coach could monitor and watch my gate.
We would try and change the way that I naturally ran. So we increased the, the cadence and I wanted
to be a higher cadence athlete who had very high cadence versus the previous Apollo, which is all
power, slow, and it was very hard. It's nearly impossible to change, but that was the goal point.
Which is interesting to come back to a cycling analogy here, right? Which is today we see
cyclists riding at a much higher cadence and a lower torque to generate comparable power,
shifting the load to the cardiovascular system from the muscular system.
Yep. And all comes down to efficiency, right? Generate the least amount of lactic acid,
and increase the amount of speed and repetitions that you're crossing over in the corner without
the more static you are on one leg, the more strength and lactic acid you essentially are
producing. So if you can decrease the amount of time you are on each leg, the less likelihood
you are to get tired as long as you're naturally able to do that. So I mean, it was a real struggle.
Like I cracked on that treadmill, I cracked in the weight room all of the time. And I questioned
my path on that process. Cause you can imagine, right? I'm a guy here who I have a recipe for
success. I know what works. And now you're going to abandon it. Not only do I abandon it, I go the
complete opposite direction and I change everything and everything that I know about what made me me
in hopes that I would do this gamble and show up to the Olympic games and be the best I've ever been
and complete unpredictable to the other athletes. And it remarkably worked out, but there was a lot
of questioning in my head. And I remember many, many nights I'd lay in bed starving,
so incredibly hungry. Cause I just, I for sure wasn't getting enough calories in my body.
Absolutely. And just like wondering like, is this the right path towards success? Is this going to
work? Cause the last thing I want to do is get to the games and be like, shit, that was a bad
decision. Right. And that's painful for so many reasons, not the least of which being you have
just spent four years before you got that feedback, right? It's one thing to say, you know,
I'm going to try this new way of washing my car today and see if it produces streaks or no streaks
and then you do it and it produces streaks and you're like, well, okay, that was 30 minutes. I
wasted, but like, this is four years to figure out that the new washing technique streaks the car.
Yeah. And for the first four and a half months, like I, I just wasn't skating very well. I was
tired. I was fatigued all the time. Other athletes on my team were better and skating
faster than I was. I was doing workouts that I probably shouldn't have been doing at that
latent stage. And the chatter is basically he's sticking around for one too many Olympics.
And he's like, lost his mind. Like he's like, what is he doing? Like, look how much weight he's
losing on like a monthly basis. But again, goes back to that psychological advantage of
this is what it took. And this is the place that I was in. And to me, having that edge of going to
a place where no one else went to, and also it's very personal, right? Going to a place where you
never knew was possible. It's incredibly powerful. It's you have a sense of inner strength when you
get to those Olympic games and I hadn't raced a single race, but I was smiling before that even
happened. Like I felt so like weightless, not only because I'd lost 20 pounds from over my career,
but because I just, I really felt prepared. Could I have done it differently? Absolutely.
Could I have gone back and implemented sports science and other elements that we now know
would have dramatically increased my performance ratio? Yes. But the process of going through that
and hardening my mentality and going through those dark times where you're questioning yourself,
being in a sauna alone every day, sweating and meditating and visualizing to be your absolute
greatest potential. Thinking about not an almond more or an almond less that goes into your body,
like on a daily basis, like that obsession is fatiguing, but also really beautiful thinking
back and I miss it immensely, but it was a huge burden and weightlessness and victory,
personal victory that took a whole team to get me to that point when I arrived in Vancouver and
I had an incredible Olympic games. Didn't actually end up winning a gold in those games,
but still feeling like I won and having the most consistent Olympics I ever had in my life.
And that transition from 07, 08, 09 as you're completely changing your style,
completely changing your body, changing the way you train, adjusting to a sport that is still
basically in probably a profound evolution more so than a sport that's been around for
hundreds of years or at least been an Olympic sport for a hundred years. It's still in that
growth curve of figuring out the balance between technical versus strength versus power. What was
it like to go back to Korea in, is it was in 07 you went back? To live in Korea was in 07.
And I know we sort of talked about this before, but you had kind of an interesting homecoming
back to Korea post-02, right? Which was in 04. We kind of glossed over that a little bit, but
for two years you didn't go back, right? Yeah. So after the 2002 Olympic games,
when I had won that gold medal in the 1500 meters and the South Korean was disqualified,
thus began this like really interesting relationship with the country of South Korea.
I think I had mentioned that I was the second most hated person in South Korea. First was Osama
bin Laden. We received 15,000, 16,000 death threats via email, which crashed the United States
Olympic committee servers during the Olympic games. So instantaneously, we knew that that country was
very unhappy with what had just happened. And it was a subjective call, not made by me,
but made by a referee who was the corner judge who decided this thing that there was a cross-tracking
penalty. And I was awarded, could have went either way if you replayed the race again
with different judges. So fast forward to the 2002 world cup soccer world cup,
and it was Korea versus United States, a Korean athlete scores the first goal,
rips off his jersey underneath the jersey painted on his back is my last name, OHNO. Oh, no. And
they essentially do a replay of that race on the soccer field and pretend and they throw the arms
up and everything. Basically showcasing that they think that that was a misstep in the judging call
and I should not have been on word of the gold. So they were really infatuated with that result.
It was also a time in which I think anti-American sentiment within the country was at its probably
peak. And a lot of people were kind of pointing fingers about things that were happening
inside the country that involved Americans and could have been penalized, should have been
penalized for their actions in the country and they weren't and they were let off. And so they
thought that this was not okay. And outside these decisions in courtroom areas that these things
were happening, people were chanting my name as if I had anything to do with any of those incidents
in any capacity. So again, it was a really sensitive time and it escalated even further
because these death threats continued on throughout the year. So much so that my face was on toilet
paper inside Korea where they were selling this and you can imagine that's a crazy thing to have
happened. I had a lot of friends who were in service who were in the country and they were like,
dude, you are not liked in this country. Do not come here. It's not okay. They don't even watch
speed skating. They don't know the sport. They don't know you. They just know they're supposed
to hate you. And so this spread, this nationalism inside South Korea was always strong and they're
very patriotic people and very passionate. And they just, they got behind this thing that I was not
the good guy. And we compete every single year in these world cups, right? So from 2002 to 2004,
we had probably three world cups that were supposed to be in Seoul. All three we opted out
not to go. Now those are important world cups. Those give you the world ranking in order to
get best seated for your world championship. So it had to be pretty devastating for us to not go.
And we just didn't know what the threat was going to be. We didn't know if it was going to be real.
We weren't, we weren't certain of all it takes is one crazy person to make a, you know, an action
and something could happen. And my father definitely didn't want me to go. I'm the only son.
He felt that the threat was real and he just wasn't worth it. It's only sport, right? Why would you
put yourself in danger and at risk? And to me, I just, I felt I was really hurt. I think emotionally
because I grew up around the Korean culture. Like I was obsessed with the Korean skaters. I had
Korean coaches, you know, I looked up to them and Korean friends growing up in federally Washington
and Seattle, Washington, and I ate the food. I understood it. And so I just felt like it was
very unwarranted because they never heard my side of the story and they didn't know me as a person,
but instead I was judged by a preconceived notion or speculation that wasn't accurate. And so
getting that across a huge language barrier is impossible. So my only thought was well,
in 2004, I have to go there. And so finally made the decision as a team to go to Seoul to compete
and upon arrival, you know, we were told that the risk is still there. There's going to be body
guards, but I had no idea what to expect. I'd never been in this position before. And upon arrival
in Incheon international airport, there was an empty baggage claim, meaning they cleared out the
baggage claim, the area that we arrived at. And it was like a hundred to 200, maybe 300 plus
security guards and police who were standing shoulder to shoulder to block out the Korean
media in which there was like hundreds of people there and fans trying to take pictures and get
interviews because it was a, you know, it's like my first time coming back. So I'm like the second
most hated person in the world. Now I'm back to compete on their home soil in their view to see
who the best, the best is. So like, this is their rematch, right? It's not the Olympics, but this is
their rematch. This is their opportunity to prove for once in a while for all that it was a complete
fluke that I won during those games. And it was the bad call. And the skater that you defeated in
oh two, was he still skating? He retired. So this wasn't even really about you and him anymore.
This is about you in a country. It was about me in a country about me versus South Korea,
which is really insane for many different levels. But looking back, it made me a lot
stronger mentally and it made me train like a complete monster. Every waking moment I was
driven a lot by my pure fear that the guys on the other side of the world were better,
more prepared, younger, talented, genetically gifted bodies suited for the sport of short
track speed skating. And how can I beat them? The only way I knew was just to be tougher,
right? Mentally be able to withstand pain thresholds that they would even dare step
into that. This is my mentality is the only way that I could make up for my lack of,
you know, whatever God given talent and abilities that I did or didn't have. And so
when I arrived in South Korea, and I don't tell the story often because it's never came up,
but the week prior, we were actually in China for another World Cup. And usually whenever we
go to China for the World Cups, they're held in like Harbin, Changchun, like these north
eastern regions of the country that are very cold. Back then, they just were not nice to visit.
Skyscrapers are being built everywhere. Like it's just not a pleasant place to be in during that
kind of infrastructure booming period. And you usually always got sick at some point,
like the Chinese food was just not clean or what we just didn't have the bacteria to fight. And so,
you know, me being a guy who would like eat street food sometimes when I go over there,
that was no longer an option. And all of my team got sick during that first week. And so we
traveled the next week to South Korea. And typically when you go to a World Cup, you arrive
on a Monday, compete on a Friday. So you spend Monday through Thursday adjusting to the climate,
getting used to the ice conditions, understanding the environment, and essentially just preparing
yourself for the competition. And so I was the only guy in my team who didn't get sick in China.
But upon that plane ride from China to South Korea, my stomach was starting to feel a little funky.
Talk about bad timing, right? I'm going to the heart of the lion's den to be at my best.
This race in this competition is a World Cup. It means nothing overall that year. It's 2004.
People don't care. No one's paying attention. It's so intrinsically important for me to perform well
at that competition. Nothing else matters that year because of all of these things that are
encompassing. And so I arrive on Monday. On Tuesday, I have like really bad food poisoning from China.
And it goes into Wednesday. It goes into Thursday. And at this point, I'm like down 10 pounds.
And what's normal for the type of training you would do on the Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday? I mean,
this is like kind of like a dual meet in swimming, right? Where it's like, you're not shaved. You're
not tapered. You're just sort of going through the motions. It's like, it's basically a meet that's
a practice. Would you guys be treating these meets that way? More than a practice, but for sure,
not as important as a world championships and definitely not showing all your cards.
You would ideally train pretty hard the Wednesday, Thursday. Yeah. So we arrive on Monday. We'll go
for a run with the team, do some skating drills and exercises. Tuesday, we have a harder high
intensity. We'll do like five times seven laps intervals, right? With like four to six minutes
rest in between pretty high intensity, 80 to 90% threshold. And then in the afternoon, we'll do
some form of a plyometric jump training. And all this is by the way, like fractions of what we
would normally do in terms of training. So this to us is a complete rest. Right. But you're not even
able to do this based on the food poisoning, or you are sort of still going through the motions
of these practices. I'm kind of going through the motions and by Thursday, it's pretty apparent
that I'm full blown, like extremely dehydrated and starting to question whether I should even
compete in the competition. Right. Which is like an impossible choice to face because no one's going
to buy the story that you didn't compete because you lost 10 pounds due to food poisoning. Yeah.
The story is going to be, oh, you wimped out. You know that you didn't win effectively. Yeah.
You're host. And then you show up and compete 10 pounds dehydrated. There's no win. It's lose,
and my father was actually there too in South Korea because he got really scared of my wellbeing.
And, you know, I was just assigned two bodyguards to follow me around the whole competition and the
entire time. And I remember walking in on Friday, the first day of competition and getting on the
ice and hearing all of the Korean fans literally booing and just being like, you know, I don't
know what they're saying in Korean, but I'm sure something like, like, you know, you're losing.
It's probably not nice.
It's not nice. You know, definitely take me out of the game. And, you know, I performed okay,
actually, the first day. I did not bad. And there's something about, and I'd love to really
understand the science behind this because I've had this repetition time and time again. Whenever
I got sick in my sport, I always performed pretty well for whatever reason, even through time trials.
Do you think it just has to do with the forced rest that comes before it?
Maybe forced rest. Maybe the white blood cell count is a component. I mean, who knows what's
really there? Maybe the immune system is working overtime. I don't know, but I mean, I'm exhausted.
I physically feel terrible, but for some reason, my output is still very, very, very high.
This time was different because I'm pretty lean already. You drop all that water. I was drinking
water. It was coming right out 10 minutes later. Like literally, it was just severe, nasty food
poisoning that lasted about three and a half days. And so, you know, I get through the first day,
I get through Saturday, the 500 meters, I was pretty much useless in the sprints for whatever
reason. I just had no strength in between races on Sunday, which is a thousand meters and the
3000 meters. I'm like lying on the floor, you know, like just trying to rest. And I ended up actually
somehow just doing very well at that competition. I ended up winning the thousand meter, winning the
3000 meter. So at men, this is Saturday, Sunday, this is Sunday. So on Sunday is the big day,
which means you skate the thousand meter and the 3000 meter super final and then the relay
on the same day. That's how the world cup schedule usually works. It doesn't work that way in the
Olympics, but it's very, very different. And so I skated very well and I ended up winning the
competition on the home soil. So what, how do the fans react to this? Well, you know, when I first
got on on Friday, they were all booing. And by the time I left, I would say 80% of them actually
were clapping and they were cheering. And someone had leaked to the media that I was really sick
during that time. And I think that had a component of that of people, people understood that I
actually was performing at subpar optimal levels and I still was able to somehow pull it off. And
it was really mentally excruciating because I very much wanted to win, but not because I wanted
to beat them, but because I just, I wanted to prove to me, it was, it was like, look, I'm legitimate.
Like I am a competitive athlete who on any given Sunday can win, may not win every 10 times,
but I'll win at least one of those 10 times. Right. And I wanted to showcase that and just
kind of searching and, you know, reaching for respect because I didn't get that when I first
arrived, like it was like basically, you know, the thought process was you did not deserve to win
and you cheated to win and I didn't feel like I did. And so the only way to re to retract those
statements from those people who were making them was to try to go there and win wholeheartedly
openly. And I did in that manner. And so that was, that was the first change in our relationship
in terms of being the most hated to having respect for me as an athlete and as a sportsman
to actually like going to the airport and then people having like fan club signs. And this
happened within the same trip. This happened the same, meaning you described your arrival,
but by the time you departed, the same Korean fans were cheering for you. The same Korean fans
were cheering for me in the airport with signs. And I remember the head of KSU at the time,
Mr. Chang came up to me. He's like, I don't know what you did or how you did it, but you are
leaving here in a much better place than you did when you arrived, which is awesome, you know,
because that was the actual goal. My goal was not to defeat really them, but to just show them
that I'm. Just to earn their respect. Yep. That's, that's what it came down to. And it did it in a
convincing fashion. So it was, it was awesome. So between 04 and 07, you've obviously gone back
to the Olympics. You've demonstrated that this isn't some fluke. You've earned their respect.
And now in 07 you're going to actually train with them as you try to come back and make the Olympic
team in 2010. Yep. So again, I kind of go back into the, the belly of the beast. I go back to
the place where no other. And they're embracing you now. But they're also at the time, the South
Korean short track team was very, very fenced off from the rest of the world in terms of their
training methods. That was their secret sauce. We don't understand why they're so good. How do they
get that technique? How do they, they don't lift weights we hear, but they're so good. We watch
them during training and it looks like they're over-training. What did their bodies look like?
I mean, designed for short track. If you could be God and you could make a perfect short track
skater, tell me what their body looks like. So you take your pelvis, tilt it forward. So the complete
opposite of what you do in a squat, do the complete opposite. Tilt your pelvis forward.
Okay. And so your lower back is now rounded, have a shorter torso, longer legs, thinner and frame
naturally, and basically zero upper body weight, because then you can strengthen your lower body
very easily. That sounds like a cyclist. That's the tilt you put into a cyclist's thoracolumbar
spine. No upper body, all lower body. That's how you design it. And very, and strength, the weight
ratio, that's strange. That's the perfect speed skater. And there's a few that exist. I actually
wasn't one of them. My proportions are actually, my legs are a little bit too short. My torso is a
little bit too long. And you're pretty muscular all around. Like you don't have that emaciated
upper body. No, I didn't naturally, but the South Korean athletes, men and women had this naturally.
And so when I watched them skate, I recognized right away, I was like, these guys aren't thinking
about their technique when they're going through the corner. It's natural. Like they're just
skating. It's like walking. You don't think about left, right, left, right. You just walk. When you
go for a jog, the same thing, you're not thinking about which foot is in front of the other. That's
what it's like when you don't understand speed skating is you're thinking, let me tilt my left
hip in. Let me put my right shoulder down. Maybe make sure that my shoulders and my hips are level
with the ice, no matter what angle I'm skating at. Make sure my nose, knees and toes are in
in line at all times in all periods. Like I'm thinking about these things every corner because
it's not natural. Really? Even, I mean, I remember you once telling me the funniest thing about how
you would drive to the rink in that position. Yeah, I was obsessed. I mean, of course we can't
do it on the podcast because we don't, we don't have the visual, but like the image of you tilting
yourself over the steering wheel, driving that way to mimic the corner. It never became
autonomic. You never got to the point where you could make that turn and perfectly line up without
a single thought. I trained myself to do it automatically, but I don't think it was a natural
feeling for me. It took years and hours and hours of obsessive driving with like all the weight on
my right hip with my left hip. You know, like imagine driving and you put all the weight on
your right leg and your left leg is not even touching the ground. Okay. And your left hip is
actually raised a little bit and your left hand is on the steering wheel and your right shoulder
is down. Like that's an uncomfortable position to be in every single day to and from the ice rink.
And I did it because I want, I just wanted to feel natural. I wanted to skate as natural as I saw
the other skaters skating. I love this kind of stuff. I mean, that's what I sort of enjoy about
having a discussion like this is I think so many people, if they're sort of watching you on TV or
they're watching Phelps or they're watching Lance Armstrong or they're watching, you know,
pick whatever great athlete. I think people just assume like it just came so easy to them. And,
but I don't think they realize that the best of the best have this ability to force themselves to
do this type of work, which is not to say that there isn't a natural talent. I think the best
of the best combined natural talent with sort of, you know, whatever, but you know, you don't even
have the same sort of physical dimension advantage that some of your peers would have,
but it's this complete obsession. It's this like, who would even think I'm going to use the extra
hour a day I'm driving to train speed skating. Yeah. It's all I cared about. It's all I thought
was important. It's all that mattered in my life. And when you prioritize that as being the sole
significant piece of your life from waking moment till you close your eyes and hopefully when you're
sleeping, you're thinking about it too, it changes your perspective on how you live your life and
what actually you do on a daily basis to impact you. I mean, I want to come back to finish your
career, but I can't help, but at the moment, ask a question that I'm afraid I'll forget to ask if we
go back to the Olympics, which is now that you're not a professional athlete, do you still have that
level of focus or is that something that is very difficult to maintain for a prolonged period of
time? In other words, do you now relish the fact that you didn't have to think about what we had
for dinner? Like you could eat as much as you wanted and you can now sit here comfortably and
you're going to drive home tonight and you're not going to have to contort yourself into some crazy
position. I mean, what's the new guidance system you've applied to the missile that is your life?
It definitely have the same, I think, quirks that I did from sport that are transferring over to my
life. I now recognize them. When I was training as an athlete, I didn't recognize them. I didn't
know what they were. I just thought that that's what I did. This is the things that me driving
in that way to the ice rink was normal. That's not normal. That's not even normal for an athlete.
It's really not by borderline unhealthy psychologically to be that obsessed at that
level all the time. There wasn't one day I went to the ice rink. I didn't wake up and didn't want
to be there because it was in a choice. There was no, do I want to go to a not? That was even
a conversation. Now, concentrating the different projects that I have and delving into areas where
I don't have the experience, I don't have the time spent and education, it really helps because I
completely immerse and I spent hours and hours and hours on certain elements. Is it in the same
intensity? Probably not. It's difficult to relate that in the same way, but for sure the traits and
attributes that I developed as a short track athlete for absolutely sure they are beneficial
attributes to apply towards specific parts of life. Also, just the fact of feeling like
when you look at life, no matter how bad shit gets, you can always come back. No matter how
sick, no matter how tired I am, I was able to compete. I was able to train now in doing business
or relationships, taking the same kind of mentality of saying like I've done things
physiologically I never thought was possible. I broke through barriers mentally that I think
were really powerful. How do you apply those with an open mind and with a way that's a different
perspective on life? I'm much softer as a person now than I was back then. I was so rigid in every
element you can imagine and tight actually with my time, with the way that I viewed, I think the
world, with the way I viewed my teammates. It made me probably unpleasant to be around on the ice
most of the time because I wasn't there to make friends. Did you have significant relationships
with a girlfriend or something during that period of your life? Kind of off and on, but none that
really were, no, nothing that I would really say like this was huge. Not like what you enjoy today.
No, totally different, but my view is different. My life really kind of began after I retired from
the sport. I learned so much through it, but I really recognized that my life began when I
decided to not come back to the sport. It was really beautiful to be able to do that.
Why is it that many athletes can't articulate what you just said on two levels? The first being,
I'm amazed at the number of athletes that I meet who once they're done with their sport,
they can't seem to apply that greatness to the next chapter. In other words, they've clearly
worked hard. They've clearly learned to do something well even when no one's looking because
that's basically what most of practice is, but they really struggle to make that leap. Then
secondly, for many athletes sadly, once the lights are gone, once nobody knows your name,
there seems to be this depression that sets in and maybe depression might be
too far on the pendulum, but there's this sense of their purpose is over. They don't think about
what that next chapter looks like. Did you struggle with any of those things at all? I
remember just seeing you now on the other side of that where it looks like everything's worked out.
I mean, was there ever a challenge where you thought, oh my God, I don't ever get to
carry a flag. I don't ever get to put a medal on my neck. I don't ever get to be on TV for
being the best athlete or something. I mean, was that a transition?
It was an incredibly difficult transition and one that I don't talk about that much,
but I don't care who you are. I heard a podcast, I'm going to say like a couple of years ago,
which I really resonated with it. It was talking about seals coming home from war
and feeling so out of place in normal society that they can't wait to go back. Not that they
love war. They hate war. They don't like what it is, but-
They probably love the purpose.
They have a purpose.
The camaraderie and the purpose, right?
They feel like this is what they're supposed to do. There's a sense of belonging and a sense
of purpose, like you said. In the Olympic space, you have one single focus for a long time,
four, eight, 12 years. Nothing in your life matters more than that sport and everything
you do is generated to be important in that sport. If you win, you're celebrated, which makes it even
more dangerous because now there's a level of expectation that you are going to carry this flag
further. Like you said, there's a ton of attributes you create as an athlete that are incredible life
lessons that you learn through sport. They're amazing. The problem is when you retire from
an athlete, you've now dedicated most of your adult life towards this one specific task that
has absolutely zero relevancy to life. I went in circles in spandex for most of my adult life.
Well, most of my younger adult life, right? And now I retired. I didn't intern. I wasn't working
at Goldman Sachs as a finance guy. I don't have experience working as a job. And now I'm thrust in
the spotlight to go and basically act and interact in normal society. If you didn't make money, you
didn't win medals, then what do you do? Like you basically you sacrifice like the first 12 years of
your life that you normally from the age of 18 to 28, those are so incredibly important to gain
expertise and experience and social skills and personal development and try anything that you
want and fail at them and still okay and get back up. You didn't have that opportunity. You're now
starting out as an 18 year old, but you're now 28 years old. And so that's the challenge is from a
competitive perspective, when you've got a corporate entity looking at hiring or perhaps you want to
get a new job like, hey, that's great. You got you're an Olympic athlete. I know you probably work
hard. I know that you probably spent a lot of time doing this, this and this, but you've got zero work
experience. You didn't finish college. You don't have any idea what it takes to be here. Like,
maybe I'll take a risk on you. Maybe I won't. It's a difficult position to be in. But on top of all
of that stuff, you have to look at the actual psychological issues that exist. And that's where
really, really gets dark. I'm not excluded from that. I was so fearful in 2008 that when I retired
in 2010, I wouldn't find my place. I wouldn't find my running start. I didn't want to go from 2010
retire 2014 or 2013 say I'm coming out of retirement. I want to go for another games.
I never wanted that to be me. I said, as soon as I retired, I really, really want to walk away
because I'm doing something else. And I want to win at something else. It's completely unrelated
to speed skating. It's unrelated to the Olympic space. So it's almost like a chip on your shoulder.
Not everyone is like that, but that was my perspective. And, you know, a lot of athletes,
when they retire, like literally like at the snap of a finger, when they come home from the Olympic
games, there's no coach, there's no training program, there's no cafeteria, there's no,
there's no more structure and schedule that has been kind of given to you in a way that's pretty
easy to follow. You just, you wake up, you go to the ice rink, you train, you come home, you eat,
you focus on skating tapes, sharpen your skates, go back to the ice rink, train again,
etc. It's very mundane, specific, but pretty easy to follow. It's simple. I say not easy, it's simple.
That's a great point, right? There's a big differentiation between simple and easy.
There's nothing easy about it, but there's a beauty to being able to focus on one thing
at the exclusion of pretty much everything else.
Yeah. And now you wake up and man, what do I do? Like how important is money? How important is
having a family? How important are relationships? How important is personal self-development? How
important is my nutrition? Do I even understand nutrition? Everyone, my nutrition is giving the
food to eat. Do I go for runs? Do I work out? Like, so I see a lot of athletes.
Is there much effort around preparing athletes for that transition in retirement?
There used to be, I don't know what it's like now. I think there's probably more of an emphasis
now, but they always look, people always tell you, look, your Olympic career will end at some point
and you have to be prepared for the transition. We used to do these things called USOC summits
in which two years before the Olympics, you would go to a winter destination. For example,
we would go to Park City and then all the Olympic hopefuls and existing Olympic athletes in the past,
two or three generations would come. Eric Hyde would be there. Bonnie Blair would be there.
Dan Jansen would be there. Michelle Kwan. These people would be there and you basically would
talk about what it takes to train for the next two years and then what to do before,
during and after the Olympics. The issue is no one really takes it seriously because you have
this invincibility complex that, you know what? I'm not going to get hurt. Sure. Like I'm just,
I'm just going to keep skating until I die. And I was naive enough. Remember, I made some bad
decisions as an athlete. You know, I told you pretty early, I was asked at the age of 17 at one
of these summits, two years before the games, I had said like, I'm like, what do you want to be
remembered for? And I wrote down, like I want to be the most decorated winter Olympic athlete of
all time. The greatest speed skater to have ever lived in short track speed skating. And they put
that in a Steiner ice arena in Utah. I forgot about this, but the things that I learned there
were so important, but people could tell me all the time. And someone asked me like, what do you
want to do in retire? I was like, what do you mean when I retire? Like I was built for this sport.
I'm supposed to be here to motivate other human beings throughout my actions on the ice.
It's very naive to say. And I, for some reason, I just thought that it was okay to live that life.
It was like, I didn't have a parachute. I lived that way in speed skating. On one side,
it's beautiful because there is no plan B. And when there's no plan B, you really commit to plan
A. You better make sure that plan A is going to be executed. That's the burning of the ships,
right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You burn the ship so you can't leave the island. But again,
there's still something here. There's a difference between people who seem to get more out of the
sport. It's almost like they're actively versus passively participating in the process. You can
very passively participate, I suspect, where you follow the lessons and you go through the motions
of doing everything you need to do for the sport versus I think a more active way of doing that.
And I say active in an emotional way, not a physical way. Obviously, both examples are
physically active, but to be emotionally active through that process, I suspect you are, whether
consciously or subconsciously assimilating the knowledge, the skill, the failure, the discipline
into what could be the next chapter. So let's go back and finish. How does the story end?
It's oh eight, it's oh nine. So oh nine is really the last major competition before the Olympics,
right? It's the world. It's the world championships. They're being held in Beijing and I'm competing.
And there's one other US short trek athlete who was my junior. He started speed skating because
he watched me in 2002. Now we're competing on the same team. He's from the same area I grew up in.
I used to be his idol. And I always used to look at this kid and be like, this gets a lot better
than he actually realizes. Once he realizes how good he is, he's potentially going to be world
champion or Olympic gold medalist. And in and throughout this process at the world championships,
I just performed sub optimally. I wasn't a major contender. I wasn't a top tier guy to win. I
wasn't on top of the podium. I think I got like fifth at the world in the world in oh nine. Yep.
I got to go back and check, but it was the first time I watched from the, you know, after the
competition, we have a banquet. All the athletes are there. Everyone's getting awarded. You go in
the podium, getting your checks. And it was the first time in a long time that I wasn't,
didn't have the spotlight. I wasn't the guy that people were talking, man, that race, all that
pass. Oh my God. So powerful. Like it was not about me. And I was like, Oh man, this is,
this is weird. Is this what it's supposed to be like? Do I just start to dissipate and just
kind of wither away? And I used to be good and I'm still respected, but just don't have what it
takes anymore to be competitive. And I'm kind of losing that edge. And I can't keep up with the
evolution of what's happening in short track because the body types are changing and the
training is changing. The athletes are changing. And so I left there really, really, really worried
and upset. And also hearing that chatter again about, I don't think that Paula was going to be
actually on the podium in 2010, which is a big, different conversation. You know, I've been at
that level for 10 years now at the top, top, top of my game in the year 2000, 2001 season. I won
every single race that season and both the Korean athlete who I, you know, had that tussle with and
that Mark Ganyal character from Quebec, both camped me during that race. And it was like, you are the
greatest athlete to compete in short track speed. Like two champions that I look up to and analyze
said that to me to now being at a point where no one was talking to me, not even on the podium,
not even on the podium, but not only that people aren't even taking my lap times during practice
anymore. Wow. So like this is psychologically damaging because from a confidence perspective,
you race differently. And I started to recognize that other athletes aren't respecting me on the
ice the same way they used to. I used to be able to actually have an off day, but if I just kind of
attempted to pass it, someone, they just let me in because there was so much respect for what I had
done in the sport before that no longer existed. People skated as if I was just like a random skater.
Yeah. So there's huge psychological advantage you brought to the start line was gone.
Was gone. And so it really made me dive deep and say, okay, like, look, this is my last chance at
really trying to show up differently. And I think that, you know, my Korean coaches that
have been telling me, they're like, look, the Korean coaches themselves, they know you so well.
They studied you from 2002 until today. You're the only thing that mattered to them. So they
watched every single race you've ever skated time and time again, and they have pawns in their
skating rings to basically mimic your skating, just like a boxing, like your sparring partner.
So they have guys who try to mimic the way that you skate in that style so they can practice
against you every single day. I didn't have, we didn't have that. We didn't think about it like
that. They were, they were different level. And so I went back to my house in, in Utah and I said,
man, I'm going to go back to kind of where I developed my strength. And I said, I'm going to
go spend a summer in Colorado Springs alone. I drove there. Was there some part that thought,
maybe I should just retire because it's one thing to go through what you went through. It would be
entirely another thing to fail on the Olympic stage. Yeah. I didn't want to give up. That's
for sure. I still believed. This is interesting. I mean, let's explore that for a moment because
I gotta be honest with you, man. I don't know that I would have had the intestinal fortitude to
continue. If I, if I really felt like I'm on the decline and every day I'm getting a little less
good and everybody around me is getting a little bit better, I don't know. Maybe that's why I'm not
Olympic champion. Like, I mean, that's, that's kind of a remarkable inner confidence. And did you
explicitly or implicitly tie that back to some of these other difficult things you'd been through,
including getting thrown out in the woods when you were in the summer of 98 and things like that?
I did, but you know, again, you're like, did you talk about this with your dad? I mean, who would,
I did, I did extensively. He was my confidant and there was three people in my life who were my
confidant. It was my dad, one of my best friends, Ian Baranski, who was basically living in my house
in Utah as like a training partner. And then John Schaefer, the guy who I brought in to live and
train me during that period of time. Those are the three people who I really, really had conversations
with. John is the most optimistic, positive person on the planet. Like there's nothing he believes
that can't be accomplished through strength and focus. And so his thought was, Oh, it doesn't
matter. You're going to come back and you're going to crush everybody. You're going to smash
everybody. You're going to skate lap times that don't exist. You know, my dad's more realist.
Ian is a very, very, very strong, different view. He's much more of a realist. And you know, he saw
what was the view between the three of them. My dad didn't really have an opinion, right? He's
more just like, look, I support what you either do to make sure you, you really go through the
drawing board and develop a plan. And I was a different person then. So my dad was, I think
he was happy to see me, but he also recognized that it was not going to be easy. John with the
time was like, well, you know, I think this is still possible. You can still win every single
distance in the world and you won't lose in a big year. You know, that's his attitude, which I
needed to have that around because I'm not naturally that type of a person. And then Ian was-
Meaning you naturally don't have that much confidence.
I have confidence, but it's different. Like I definitely, it's not like I walk in and say,
I can't lose. There was times, right? When my equipment was on point, like earlier in my career,
I was like, I could fall down. I guess I win this race. Like no one's going to beat me. I'm just that
much better than everybody else. But at this point, you know, I was battling some small injuries and
some equipment issues and nothing was quite right. So I never felt like I was a hundred percent,
like maybe 80% of the time. So the one person I felt like really knew me was my friend,
Ian Barranci. Now to give you kind of some backstory, like as a short track on book athlete,
you never show your cards, even to your teammates, because eventually you raised against them in the
Olympic trials. So you kind of show that you always hold something back. And so I was really,
really good at that. So people didn't really know like what was going on internally.
They just thought that I was like the stoic never show pain, incredibly focused, super hungry,
quiet, kind of crazy guy who just comes to rank with an insatiable appetite for pain and training
every day, like with like a complete robot. Like that's, that's who Apollo is. And that's what I
wanted the people to believe. Right. The reality was and who I would, I needed somebody to kind
of confide in was Ian, my close friend. And you know, Ian was my first roommate when I was traveling
on all these years, like when I was 12 and 13 years old. So he knew me from when I started till
to this point. And he basically was like, look, you are not the same athlete you used to be.
Like you're actually, even though you have the same recipe for success, you're just not the same.
You're older man. Like your body's stiffer. You don't skate the same. You don't look the same.
Your equipment's a little bit different. The other athletes are changing. The sport is changing.
And you know, he's just keeping it real, right? Someone has to. And so I kind of went back and
I'm like, man, like how do I, in my view, like all these years spent training still only matters
on this one day in the Olympics. Like none of this stuff matters. My previous wins in my own head,
my previous wins don't matter. I keep my medals inside my sock drawer in my house. I never bring
them out. I don't want to think about that. I want, I want to think about I'm the underdog every day.
So I said, I got to make some huge, huge changes. And so I, a week after the world championships,
I'm back in Salt Lake city. And normally you take like a decompression period and you really, really
think about things. And I was going to stay there for about a month and then potentially go
somewhere else to train. I just packed my bags like one day and I just left and I drove all the
way to Colorado Springs, checked myself into the Colorado Springs Olympic training center
and began training. So the Olympic team moved from Colorado Springs to Salt Lake city in 2007
to train. So the speed skaters were no longer in Colorado Springs, the train center. So when I
arrived back there in 2009, I was the only guy there. Everyone else was off training in, in,
in Utah or wherever else. And I brought my bike and I basically set up a little training plan. I
just trained solo for this is like February, March of 09. Yeah, this is like February, March, April,
May. I think I first saw the team again, like the end of May. And I did, I spent that entire time
and like essentially complete solitude, just training by myself. And I just, you know, I,
you know, I just like anything else. Like you analyze the situation. What are the goals? What
are you trying to do? What type of training you need? And mine wasn't based solely on sports
science because I didn't seek that route. I probably should have, but I didn't seek that
route. I just like, okay, got to improve cadence, got to lower the body weight, maintain strength,
but really have to just get an incredible aerobic base shape like you've never been before. And
that's going to carry you throughout the rest of the year so that you won't have issues with burnout
or, you know, with any over-training. And do you develop that aerobic base on the bike or on the
track more? Well, we don't skate in the summer that much. We don't skate till the end of May. So
that period off. So it's on a bike. It's on a bike. It's on inline skates. It's running.
It's with treadmill. It's with Stairmaster, but it's really spent a lot of time for me. I use the
Manitou incline in Colorado Springs, which is like the scar on the roads, one mile of cog railroad
steps that go up. And that was my, that was my sanctuary. Like I lived on that thing so many
times a week. I used to go up it with weight vests and jumps and you know, you can't beat that thing.
It's just one of those elements where you just get a little bit faster at it and you get easier
to compensate, but you hurt just the same no matter how fast or slow you go. And so it's the
fastest time you could make it up that mine was like 1736 or 1738, which is fast. And obviously
lots of athletes do this, right? It's not just the skaters. Yeah. A lot of athletes, I would say
the average time is probably 22, 24 between there. And that 17 and a half minutes was not with the
40 pound weight vest. I assume. No, no, no, it was clean. I needed to go back to that space again
of like, this is where I started. How much of that training do you think was for your brain versus
your body? 90%, 95%. I was probably doing everything wrong to be completely honest with you.
There's no reason why I should be going for a three hour bike ride. My races last no more than
two and a half minutes. And of those two and a half minutes, I'm probably only really skating
for a minute and a half, three and a half hour bike rides going up and down. Like the canyons,
they're important. Maybe you go a couple of those rides, but you don't need that. I should be doing
specified interval training according to the time that's under duration. And you can extend that,
but I shouldn't be spinning my wheels for hours at a time. But what did I gain? A mental perspective
and a honed focus and a resiliency and the feeling that I was reinventing myself was really important
to me psychologically. So I would walk on the ice differently. I would walk into the ice rink
differently. I would project a different type of energy upon my opponents and other skaters. And my
conference level would be higher. So that's what I went after. And it wasn't until I came back to
Salt Lake City and invited John Schaeffer back into my home until he said, look, no more of these two
hour runs. Like what are you doing? This is like so 1960, like you're wasting your time and you're
actually training the sprint out of your body, which is your biggest strength. And then I kind
of explained to him my goals. And we began that journey towards shedding all that weight and it
was excruciating. And so how the story ends is arrive in Vancouver, BC, 2010. And going into
the Olympic trials, had you gotten back in enough shape that most people felt like you'd make the
team? Yeah, everyone knew I'd make the team. It wouldn't be as dominant as I normally would be,
but for sure I'd make the team. So that's a big improvement over where you were at the worlds
earlier in the year. Yeah, I think so. I think it definitely came a long way. And technically,
I'd improved a lot and people had seen some big changes in my body. And going into Vancouver,
you've already figured out like this is your last Olympics. Internally, I didn't tell anybody,
but internally, I've always wondered what it felt like for multiple Olympians. Like, you know,
when Phelps rolled into Rio, how bittersweet it is in a way, because they, I don't know, like,
do they appreciate it more then or the first time? Because you'd think, well, the first taste of this
is the greatest, but perhaps in some way, like I'll give you another example. It's totally unrelated.
Like I have three kids, right? And you've met them all. And I remember when the first one's
born, I'm thinking this is the greatest thing in the world. And now our third one, you kind of know,
it's your last one. In some ways, I think I'm actually enjoying it even more. Like changing
the diaper is like, you know what, there's going to be a day when I don't get to do this anymore.
And so did you have that sort of feeling when you walked into the opening ceremony? One, you're
being probably looked at now as a leader of the team, right? You're certainly one of the
leaders of the team, just from a maturity standpoint and experience standpoint.
And you also know inside, like, Hey, I don't get to put this uniform on and walk into this opening
ceremony again. This is really the last hurrah for this chapter of my life. It's an absolute
greater sense of appreciation for what you're doing. And also that you know that this is, this is it.
And I'm older, more mature, I can appreciate the process that I've been through. I've got scars.
I've got wins and losses. Mentally, you've gone through a lot, you spend a lot of time alone. So
you've battled your own internal insecurities and demons and self doubts. And now you're at a place
where you feel like you've you've experienced a lot. So to me, the last games was the best,
for sure. When the first Olympics was incredible, never take it away. But I was so young,
difficult to absorb that type of information at that rate of speed, which you've never had
access to before. 2006, different environment, different games, been through it one time,
understand it. I know how to do this. I know how to handle the pressure. I know what the sounds are
like, go through the process. The last one, you go walk into the arena, you hear the sounds and it
sounds awesome. Just you have a greater sense of appreciation. And also, you're just really focused
on just trying to be your absolute best. So it's not like you're there to experience the moment,
because you just don't have time to write your you're there for a specific task and a goal. And
unfortunately, that detracts away from your time to be present and experience the Olympic games for
what we see them as it's amazing production of the world coming together to compete. We go there
and it's just like I'm ice rink Olympic Village, ice rink Olympic Village, ice rink Olympic Village,
rest, recovery, massage, sharpen skates, game time. That's a recipe right there.
Yeah. In many ways, you do as a spectator even feel bad for the favorites because it's a totally
different experience in swimming, for example, like usually the meat kicks off with the 400 IM.
And so if you're a favorite to win the 400 IM, I'm not even sure if you're showing up to the
opening ceremonies. You're not. You're absolutely not. Yeah. I mean, it's like, whereas if you're
not a favorite, if you're like not even going to make it out of the first heat, you're going to go
to the opening ceremonies because that is part of like, that is the experience, right?
You're probably going to open ceremonies. You're probably going to have a drink.
Yeah. So it's important to keep in mind, like the sacrifice that has to be made if you really want
to win using that very specific example. It's a moment in time, right? So as much as you want to
have fun and go talk to their athletes and mingle with the different cultures and community,
you've trained your entire life for these two weeks and you are not going to allow one slip up
to detract away from that in these two weeks. And it's funny because when you're four years
away from a game, it's like when it's 2006, oh man, I'm four years away. This is going to take forever.
You know, like this is, I know I hear when it says it's going to be here before I know it.
And then two weeks from those games, you're like, man, I wish I had another year of training.
You're not saying that in 2006, you know, you're wishing like the games were in a year or two.
And so it's a different perspective, but I arrived and I hit my goal set in terms of my weight and my
cadence. And the first check mark for me was when I got on the ice in Vancouver and the Chinese
coaches are there, the Canadian coaches are there, the Russian coaches are there. All the coaches from
the different teams are there and they're videotaping our practice as they are. Everyone else's
practice. Cause the first look at seeing what shape you're in, did he change anything since the last
world cup? Is your body weight different? Are your equipment different? What are you doing differently?
And the first thing that we heard via the chatter that was going on was like,
we don't even recognize Apollo. This guy we trained to beat. He didn't show up. We got a new
guy, a new guy, new guy with a new cadence, a new rhythm, a new style of training, a new style of,
of racing, a new tech. Everything was different. And that's exactly what we wanted to do. And
I had an incredible team to help support that. Not only my strength coach, John Taver, but the rest
of the Olympic team and my teammates too, we're a huge part of that, right? Cause we trained every
single day together and it's a really, really powerful feeling to be able to show up. And
like to me, that was the win. Actually it was before I ever raced. I was like, man, like I went
through this. I took a huge gamble and I wasn't sure if it was going to work. I think it did.
I feel like it did. Everyone else is saying like it did. My coaches are beyond happy and they can't
believe what we just accomplished. And I haven't raced the race yet. That's a very powerful feeling
to go into your first race with. And then from there, it's like, look, I've done the work.
There's nothing more I could have done. I wouldn't change anything. And it's time to just
focus on strategy and compete. And then I ended up winning another three metal at those games
and retiring with eight medals. Were you sad or happy at the closing ceremonies? Was that?
It was both. I was both sad and happy. I couldn't believe that my, my life had turned into this
direction. I couldn't believe that I'd spent this much time dedicated towards a sport. I couldn't
believe the amount of press and interest that we were getting from a crazy sport, like short track
speed skating and just feeling grateful. And then also kind of promising myself to like, Hey, like
any opportunity that comes your way, you are going to say yes, no matter what for the next year.
And then thus began when I walked off the plane from Vancouver, I like wasn't in one place for
more than two or three days, just bouncing around from speaking engagement to appearance to meeting
to sponsor blade of stuff. And it was incredible. Who are your sponsors by the end of the 2010
Olympics? Who were your main sponsors? I had Alaska airlines. We had Omega subway was still
subway was yes that year. Coca-Cola was a sponsor. There's a few others, but those are the major
sponsors. And when did you announce your retirement? I announced our retirement 2012 publicly,
but I knew, I knew in 2009, this was my last games. It was just one of those things where I,
I was happy and I was, I really wanted to complete the game. Like I always talk about that,
right? But like, I never wanted to come back. I never wanted to finish my career feeling like
I was missing something. Like I want, like I had an itch. I wanted, I didn't want to be
going down the line, working on some new app and be like, man, I think I'm going to come
up out of retirement. And I had that feeling watching Phelps in 2012 during the London
Olympics. You had that feeling for him or yourself? Myself to wonder like, man,
I'm still in great shape. I still feel really healthy. I know a lot more about myself,
nutrition, technique, training than I ever did. I'm pretty sure I can make this team and I'm pretty
sure I can be competitive in the Sochi Olympics in two years. And then so instead of that, I had
that conversation with myself internally while doing commentary in NBC Olympic games, while
interviewing Phelps at his first press conference and talking to him about the pressures of being
so successful. How does he maintain, you know, like his sense of in 2012 was a very difficult
Olympics for Michael. I mean, I don't know him of course, but I just, I know enough about swimming
to be able to watch and read between the lines, but he went through, he's going through a lot.
There's only two events he entered in the Olympics where he didn't win a medal. The first was that
fifth place finish in the 200 fly as a 15 year old boy in 2000 in Sydney. But what a lot of people
forget is he finished fourth in the 400 IM, his signature event in London. And that's a race that
if I recall, I mean, at the time, Lochte was probably the best 400 IM in the world, but Michael
had done really well in the trials and basically touched out another swimmer that most people
thought was going to get that spot, but then kind of faded at the back of the 400 IM. Didn't look
like himself. No, didn't at all. And I've always thought it was sort of inside baseball minutia.
If I were to say like as a swim fan, what were the greatest Phelps performances of all time?
I'll tell you what is number one, his anchoring the four by 100 relay right after his abysmal
performance. And I use abysmal in quotes, but for Phelps, his abysmal performance in the 400 IM.
And I remember watching that race thinking, Oh my God, this could shatter his confidence for the
rest of the meet. And then he shows up in the next race, the four by 100 free relay and crushes
the anchor, crushes the lead off leg. There's a backstory to what happened in the anchor of that.
And they didn't end up winning the gold, but that was one of his most remarkable performances.
But overall, that Olympics was sort of sad for me to watch Phelps because I felt like,
God, like he's not the same swimmer he was. He got touched in the 200 fly and all these other
things. So what was that like for you both talking to him about it, but also just now thinking,
wait a minute, should I be doing this again? You're going through this process of what you didn't
want to do. I didn't want to do that. And I was having that conversation and then, you know,
I had some friends who like, they always thought that I retired too early. They were like,
man, you, you still got another four years. Cause you were what, 29 at this point.
That's 28. Yeah. I was young by the way, looking at Michael and seeing him by the way, in that race,
directed anger and rage is very powerful. And Michael swims very well when he's angry,
very well. And he needs to have. So you saw that between the 400 IM and the four by one.
Cause I was very similar. I needed to have, like if I was winning too often,
like I needed to throw in a little self-sabotage, little monkey wrench in there to lose a race and
then get that feeling of losing. And like, Oh, I do. I forgot what that tasted like.
I think Michael won so easy for so long. You know, like it's difficult to push yourself when
no one else is. It's only you out there and you can win if you're 70%. Right? So, and he's so
incredibly talented. It's that that's what I saw and maybe that's wrong. That's my view.
And so when I was watching that and I said, you know, I'm not going to make a decision here.
So I came back home. I went to that same place, Mo clips in iron Springs resort. And I said,
I'm going to really think about this and make a real decision on whether I want to do. And I said,
you know what? I'm not going to go back. I'm going to continue on this path of trying to
become an entrepreneur and trying to learn and explore and grow as a human. And that's what I'm
going to commit to. And I'm not going to listen to this short sighted wants of wanting to relive
in those Olympic moments again, because I think a lot of that's what it comes from is like, you
know, two years out from the games, although I'm there, I'm on the other side of the lens for the
first time ever. And it's a different feeling. And I want to be the guy on the start line in
that fourth and fifth lane getting ready to go. I want to be one of the favorites to win this race.
And I want that pressure. I want that moment of, okay, the curtains open. It's do or die. Like you
either perform or you don't. The paper is never going to lie at the end of the day. And you don't
get that anymore. You do if you have a different perspective in terms of business and opportunities,
but as an athlete, it feels different. It doesn't matter how, which way you chop it up. So I'm glad
I made the right decision. I decided not to go back to the sport and I was going to pursue
different opportunities and different, different things in my life. And that was the decision I
made. And I'm still happy about doing that. God, it's such an amazing journey because, you know,
I've known quite a bit about you before we spoke today, but I didn't realize, I think all of the
internal struggle, I think it's just so easy to kind of look at athletes and look at the ones who
have done so well and assume that it was always clear in their mind that they were going to win
and they just executed. And you don't realize the best athletes are still humans, which means they
still come with all the doubts that the rest of us have and the, the self loathing and the shame or
the, in some ways, perhaps even perverse incentives. You know, I can't help but hear your story and
wonder how much of this was sort of you needing to prove yourself to someone to something from the
moment we talked about, you know, your mom not being there. I've always wondered is like,
is there something about you wanting to demonstrate to her like, Hey, I'm worth it. Like I was, you
know, I was an amazing kid. And that may be too obvious a statement, right? Maybe that, maybe that
never even factored into any of this stuff subconsciously, but you were a very driven
kid from the beginning. I described these are like missiles without guidance systems.
Those are still good things to have. Like it's great to be a missile that just needs a guidance
system. When you think now, I mean, where do you want to be in 10 years? Obviously it's going to be
mostly business related. I think it, you know, we were talking about it over dinner. Like it's not
like you necessarily want to go back to coaching skating or something, which is unfortunate.
Cause I think in many ways you could bring so much to that sport if unfortunate for the sport,
not for you, that you could bring so much knowledge, as you've said, like your knowledge
of nutrition and training and specificity today is so much beyond what you had at the time. But
let's just pause it for a moment that you're not going to become the head coach of the US
speed skating team. Where do you want to be in 10 years? 10 years. I want to be, I think first and
foremost healthy. I want to have increased my personal relationships with my close family and
friends made new ones along the way, increased the amount of experiences that we've shared together.
Business. I think that I'll always have an urge to be involved in different projects and different
ideas and whether they succeed or fail. I want to win, but I don't think it's necessarily, that's
the, the real importance is that I go through those processes and hopefully I learn and apply
those lessons at the next business opportunity or the next venture or path that I'm doing.
And I think at least my father told me at one point, he's like, you know, Apollo in your mid
thirties into your early forties, you will become significantly more self-reflective and inquisitive.
Of many questions. My father's a very curious person as am I. And so like these questions come
up in my life that I never asked when I was an athlete, like what is really important? What do I
really care about? We were talking about like watches and these, these things that have like
limitless acquisition opportunity. Where does some of these things really play a role in my life in
the longterm and what do I really need that really makes me happy? And you know, I feel really blessed
to have had both incredible wins in my life, both on the field of play and off the field of play.
And also I'm really blessed and have gratitude for the incredible stupid mistakes that I've made
and losses that I've created both on and off the field of play, either through business and
relationships and the way that I acted or whatever. I am human. Like anyone else, I've developed
superhuman like attributes associated with this sport as with anyone would who dedicated a lifetime
of achievement towards something. Maybe they wouldn't be Olympic champion, maybe, but they
would be very, very good at that thing. And I think that I've just, I've realized that the things that
make me really happy, this pretty small list. And I feel really, really grateful and happy to have
recognized that at the age of 36. And I want to continue that and I want to continue to explore.
I want to continue to learn and hopefully I can give back and teach the next generation of kids
and people, whether they want to be an athlete or not. I believe that everyone should be playing
sports in some capacity regardless of your output or your skillset. I think there's amazing life
lessons that are learned about how to win, how to lose. And just like I went through about
committing and dedicating and sacrificing and going through the physical pains that you have
to go through. I think there's really, really powerful things. Even if you just suck and you're
the last guy picked, it doesn't really matter. There's things that you learn through that process.
I think they're difficult to teach if you don't have the physical component that's associated.
And so I think about that often as I, you know, every year that goes by, I'm eight years retired
now from the sport of short track speed skating. I have no desire to go back. I love going to every
Olympic games and commentating. I feel at my element, it's a homecoming and reunion for me
to see all my old friends and associates. And I keep tabs in the race. And sometimes I watch
speed skating tapes until four 30 in the morning and realize like, dude, this doesn't matter anymore.
Like put it away. And then also just trying to find out and understand more about myself. And
I think that's really interesting. And so I've gained a lot from just spending time and learning
from people who I don't consider to be, if you asked me younger, when I was younger, experts in
their field, but now I've had a much more open mind. I've learned a lot from you. I've learned
a lot from a lot of the people that you are friends with a lot of these different podcasts
and the advent of technology and access to information is so incredible. You know,
when I went on my first Olympic games, we didn't have Instagram. Like people were barely using
their phones in the same degree that we were doing today. So like your access to the internet
was just to Google a couple of ideas, but that's really the bare minimum. If you're creating
content, you are one of the very few. Right. And so I just, I think it's really interesting.
And I've been traveling around the world. Yeah. Your travel schedule is worse than mine. And I
tend to lament my travel schedule, but yours is, I mean, you're really never in the same place
for more than two or three weeks, right? Yeah. This is probably the longest I've been in one place
in the US and actually in years. So I'm actually really enjoying it. I've been spending a lot of
my time, but 80% of my time in Asia and my routine is pretty aggressive. I've always had a fascination
with Asia in general, both the food, the culture, the people, the diversity, the growth, the
opportunities that exist there. But you still don't speak Japanese fluently. I know. I still
don't speak Japanese fluently. I speak more Korean than I do Japanese. And I think this is a
byproduct of me being honest. I just have to introduce you to Tim Ferriss because he will be
able to teach you Japanese in a shorter period of time than I'm convinced anybody could teach you.
That's right. That's right. That's his amazing ability to deconstruct world-class people.
Japanese was the first language he learned outside of English because he went and spent a year in
Japan when he was in high school. And I remember one night over dinner, he just explained to me
how he learned the language. Because if someone says to me, look, I went to live in France for a
year and I learned French, I'm like, okay, well, I get that. That strikes me as achievable. I get
to spend a year in Mexico and I learned Spanish. I get that. I can relate to that. But you take a
white kid out of Long Island and send him to Japan for a year. And he comes back speaking,
obviously with an accent, but very fluent Japanese. That's incredible. And he can really
articulate that process. So I don't know. We might have to make that happen.
Sure would make your dad pretty happy, right? It would make him very happy. My dad still counts
in his head in Japanese. So as much as he wants to be full on American as he is American, but he
still can't shake that. Man, I know they're waiting for us inside. So I guess we should
continue this discussion off the mic, but I want to thank you so much for everything for coming
down. And also just for being so generous with your insights as well. I know I'm guessing that
a lot of what we talked about today, you've talked about a thousand times before and it's sort of
like, God, do I have to tell that story all over again? But I think we've also talked about a bunch
of things that certainly I've never heard before. And maybe that means that for others, there's
also more of a collection of stuff here. Last question I have for you though is thinking about
your racing career. You talked a lot at the outside about your father instilling this
belief in you that there should always be this pursuit of perfection, even if you never get there.
Is there a race when you look back at your career that was the narrowest gap between what you
perceive to be the perfect race and your actual outcome? Not necessarily the place you stood on
the podium, but just in terms of your execution. Yeah, there's one race that I publicly talk about
as being the quasi perfect race. And it was the 500 meters in Torino, Italy. I was not favored to
win that race. I hadn't won that race all year long. I hadn't won a gold yet in those Olympics.
It was clear that the South Korean team was just better at those games. And I was in the final and
I had incredible athletes to skate against. And I knew my only option was to basically,
we call it jamming the pack where you slow down so that people can't get their momentum to pass you.
So if you can imagine driving a Honda on a freeway and a Ferrari is behind you, imagine the Honda,
wherever the Ferrari goes, the Honda is in that lane. So it doesn't matter how fast the Ferrari
is, he can't pass because he's blocked by that car. That was the strategy that I use in that race.
I wasn't the fastest, I wasn't the best, I wasn't the most likely to win. And I was able to pull off
a wire to wire win. So that was publicly, that was one of the races that I think that was the
most perfect for me because everything was on the line. I wanted to win. Everyone had given up on
my team. They thought that I wasn't going to win that race. My sports psychologist at the time
basically said, Apollo, this is your second Olympic game. It's amazing what you've gone through
crazy that you came back and you won another couple of medals. You should be really proud of yourself.
And I took that as like, are you giving up on me, man? There's only one more race left. And so
it was personally very, very powerful and visceral. And then I've had a couple of other races where
just execution wise, it was so perfect. Just the pass being in that flow state,
everything felt very automatic and easy. It slowed down the minute and a half long race felt like
five minutes. I felt like I produced zero lactic acid in my body. And it felt like I just was
simply significantly faster than everybody else. I felt like Neo from the matrix. And I don't say
that with any exaggeration, it just felt so incredibly easy to maneuver and dance on my
skates and pass that I was like the puppet master. And those are the feelings that I think we,
all of us are addicted to, whether you're a writer, whether you're a doctor, whether you are a singer,
you have that one glimpse of being in a true state of flow. And it's so difficult to replicate. And
you spend years, years searching for that one time and you do everything possible. You go back
and eat truck. What did I eat that day? Well, I had three grapes in the morning. Well, you know,
what's going to happen for the next two years. I got three grapes and they're all green for the
rest of my life. Right. You just try to replicate because you don't know what changed. And I'm not
sure we can, we can really identify what that is. But those moments are the ones that I crave. And
I get into those moments no longer in sports. Sometimes I get it to where I'm in the gym,
when I'm alone, that's my sanctuary. But in conversation, like our conversation,
three and a half hours went by earlier and I had no idea because I was so transported into that
moment. And to me, that feels perfect because you're present, you're here, the quality of time
is being spent. And you know, hopefully people at home didn't fall asleep listening to my crazy
speed skating stars. I'm sure they didn't. I'm going to get you into race car driving because
that is another example of where this flow thing happens. So your lap time on the track is like,
you'll, you'll focus on that. I mean, in many ways to me, driving a race car is basically
just a bunch of time trials. And I know it sounds like a cliche, but my absolute fastest laps in any
car on any lap never feel that fast. Yes. That is the most amazing feeling. Usually when I set a lap
record, which is just meaning my lap record, like I'm never going to be the guy that sets the actual
lap record, but my lap records are always after the fact, I just noticed it. I'm like, wait, holy,
you took like five tenths off your fastest time ever. And that felt effortless. That really is a
beautiful feeling, isn't it? It's an amazing. And you're right. It is so addictive. And I think
that's part of why competitive sports have been displaced by, you know, things that I do,
not necessarily competitively, but just came about to live with myself, like, you know,
archery and race car driving and these things, because you're waiting for that day when it's
like, oh my God, you did 12 out of 12 shots all bullseye. How did that happen? That's why people
run. It's why people do Ironman and some people do triathlon. That's why people do everything.
And I'm convinced that you have to care enough about the outcome for you to get in that state.
There has to be some form of consequence, maybe not physical, maybe not danger, but psychologically
to impact you to almost force yourself into that realm. That's why I think athletes always
time and time getting in that flow state more than anyone else, as with the military and people
in the service, because they're in real true flow state because they will die if they're not.
But I think that there's a lot to be said there. And I think that we as human beings take that for
granted. I think athletes a lot of times take that for granted and trying to achieve that flow state
of maintaining that mental consistency. And that's what I was seeking for all those years.
That's why I read all those books about sports, psychology and the brain and human behavior and
trying to understand myself and others. And it's a beautiful thing. Yeah.
So where can people find you on social media?
Social, I'm at Apollo Ono on Twitter. My Instagram is there for pictures, but I'm not as active as
I'd like to be. And it's something that I would like to restart.
And what's your handle on Instagram? Is it the same?
It's the same at Apollo Ono.
Any books that you recommend that you've, I know you've written a couple, any of those that you
think people ought to follow up on based on what we've talked about today, because I know you have
one called No Regrets, which basically describes kind of this ethos going into the 2010 games.
Yeah. I mean, my book of, it was called Zero Regrets. I wrote that right after Olympic games.
I had an amazing experience. Zero Regrets.
Yes. Zero Regrets.
I said no regrets.
But it's kind of like a snippet into my life. And also you got to remember I was in that mind frame
of really just post-Olympic games without all these other experiences involved to be able to
really think back objectively and think and remember and really understand what was happening
at the time. But that was one of the books that I had written with a ghost writer. When I say I
had written, I didn't actually write the book. I wish I was a great writer and had that talent.
My writing skills are subpar, but I really enjoy reading and I really enjoy learning.
And so I've, I mean, look, I've invested, I've spent time into businesses and deals and things
that are so far away from sports that would really blow people's minds. And it's because I just
fascinated, right? I'm a curious learner and it's been amazing opening the next chapter of the life
and seeing where life takes me.
Well, it's amazing to know that your athletic career spanned, what, 12 years basically?
Your professional career, your career as a father, whatever else you go on to do is going to span
multiples of that. So in many ways, the best is yet to come, right?
I believe so.
I hope that's true for all of us.
I think so.
All right, man. Thanks again. It's been awesome.
Thank you. Thanks, Peter.
All right.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my
blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com. What's a nerd safari you ask? Just click on the
link at the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my
subjectively non-lame once a week email, where I'll update you on what I've been up to,
the most interesting papers I've read, and all things related to longevity,
science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions
and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes
only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient
relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the
user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare
professionals for any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of
interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise,
please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.