Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hello everyone, welcome to this week's episode of the Peter Attia drive.
My guest this week is professor Tom Seifried, who many of you will know, but I suspect an
equal number of you will not know.
Tom has come to us through many channels, meaning the requests to speak with Tom have
come on many levels.
There's been a lot of requests through social media, through the site.
And of course, based on our discussions with Dom Dagestino, Tom has been front of mind
for quite a while.
This is my first time meeting Tom, but I feel sort of like I know him because I've read
so much of his work and Bob Kaplan, who of course you all know, as my trusty right hand
guy who lives in Boston actually takes a course from Tom and he's taken a course in
the past and continues to just wander around Tom's office and just hang out with him overall.
So in some ways this felt kind of familiar though.
It was my first time meeting Tom.
Tom's background is that he's got a PhD in genetics and biochemistry from the University
of Illinois.
He got that in the mid seventies and a bunch of other distinctions that I'm not going to
go into because we're going to link to all that stuff.
He did his postdoc in the Department of Neurology at Yale and it was there that he first became
interested in ketones because of their application in the amelioration of recalcitrant seizures.
As we get into in the episode, that led to his interest in cancer, which is now his focus.
Tom has published over 150 peer reviewed publications.
He's the author of numerous books, textbooks, etc., including kind of a treatise on this.
So his magnum opus is effectively a book called Cancer as a Metabolic Disease.
I probably got my first copy of this a few years ago and in many ways that's what sort
of felt quite familiar in speaking with him.
He's currently a professor at Boston College and his research today focuses on the mechanisms
by which metabolic therapies can manage chronic diseases such as epilepsy, neurodegenerative
lipid storage diseases and above all cancer.
In this episode, we talk about Tom's background, as I sort of alluded to, his work in epilepsy
and how that led him to the interest in caloric restriction and ketosis.
We revisit the man, the legend, Otto Warburg and talk about the Warburg effect and Warburg's
point of view on these things.
And I do push him a little bit on this because I want to point out that it's not entirely
clear amongst people what the Warburg effect really implies and how ubiquitous it is.
And I have to be honest with you, I don't necessarily share Tom's views on a number
of these things.
So I wanted to do my best to sort of represent as many other views as possible, but at the
same time, I hope the discussion is helpful.
We get into a bunch of the semantics.
I knew this was a very technical topic and I know that not everybody has the luxury of
listening to this while they're reviewing the show notes.
So we do go over the differences between respiration or oxidative phosphorylation and
fermentation.
It's very important to understand this.
So one thing to keep in mind with this podcast and frankly, any of the more technical episodes
we do, if you're struggling with a concept, hit pause.
I don't think it's worth sort of going through these, not understanding them.
I think it's cool to listen to this, hit pause, go back, hit Wikipedia, ping us with a question
on social media or whatever, if there's a concept that's dumping you.
But this is obviously going to be one of the more important concepts.
If you can't understand the difference between respiration, oxidative phosphorylation as it
were and fermentation, then a lot of this won't make sense.
We also get into this idea of substrate level phosphorylation, a very important concept
and the fermentation of glucose.
We also talk a lot about glutamine.
This is something that I haven't spent a lot of time talking about in the past.
I think I do touch on it a little bit with Dom DeGostino, but we get into it in much
greater fashion.
We, of course, get into ultimately the fundamental question that I think people who are interested
in metabolic therapies for questions have to be able to answer, which is, is cancer
primarily a metabolic disease, meaning a disease whose origin arrives in the mitochondria or
in the metabolic machinery of the cell, or is it primarily a genetic disease where sometimes
you will and sometimes you won't sustain mitochondrial damage?
You'll see this in the interview.
It's not entirely clear to me that I buy the argument that cancer is entirely a metabolic
disease, though, as some of you will know, I am very bullish on the use of metabolic
therapies in cancer, but I'm also very bullish on the use of immunotherapy in cancer and
when appropriate chemotherapy in cancer.
My view is that cancer is about as hard a disease as there is ever going to be to target,
and therefore we ought to turn our attention to as many legs of the stool as possible and
not just one.
I think the discussion gets a little bit heated at one point when I take issue with something
Tom said about suggesting that biopsies could exacerbate cancer.
I really don't want anybody to come out of this believing that having a biopsy is going
to increase their risk of metastatic cancer.
I think that anyone's entitled to a hypothesis, but to my knowledge, there are absolutely
no evidence to support that claim.
We talk a lot about a particular type of cancer called glioblastome multiforme, GBM,
also known as a grade four astrocytoma.
This is, of course, a cancer that if you haven't heard of it, you've certainly heard of its
effect.
John McCain, who recently passed away, suffered from this.
I lost a friend to this when I was younger, and I think that if you know somebody who
has died of brain cancer, the chances are there's a pretty good chance this is the cancer
they had.
This is one of those cancers that gives cancer a bad name.
In all fairness, I don't think there's ever been a true documented survivor of this cancer.
It also may provide one of the more interesting model systems to study metabolic therapies
for cancer.
I guess the most important thing we close with is I sort of pushed Tom a little bit
on what experiment he would want to see or do to advance the thinking in this field.
In many ways, Tom's a little bit of a guy that's on the sidelines of sort of mainstream
cancer.
These views, these metabolic views unfortunately, unfortunately in my view, don't get the attention
they deserve.
Other people that I'm going to be talking with in the future, such as Sid Mukerjee and
Lou Cantley, are going to be some ... I think some of the people who are now starting to
see through their own research some of the potential applications for these things.
I think that in many ways the problems that Tom has been working on for the last 30 or
30 years are very slowly beginning to gain acceptance.
I don't like to use the word mainstream, but I think you know what I mean, in the more
mainstream circles of oncology.
This interview does get technical at times, and so as is the case with virtually all of
our interviews, please pay attention to the show notes if you're having difficulty, if
for no other reason than the fact that a heck of a lot of work goes into preparing them
on the part of our analytical team.
If you like this podcast, I would ask of you very kindly to go and leave a review at
iTunes.
I suppose if you don't like this podcast, you can also do that.
Lastly, if you are interested in receiving a weekly email, which comes out every Sunday
morning from me, that usually talks about something I've done that week, something I've
learned that week, something that is hopefully of interest to you, by all means sign up for
that at PeterAttiaMD.com.
I think that's pretty much all I want to say as we go into this.
With that said, please give it up for my guest today, Dr. Tom Seifried.
Hey Tom, how are you?
Well thank you very much.
Well thank you so much for making time.
I know you've got a long lineup of students outside your office here who are kind of pissed
at me for sitting here taking up time when you could be answering their questions.
They'll recover.
A lot of people have been sort of reaching out to me on social media and saying, you
know, you've got to have Tom on, you've got to have Tom on.
The podcast with Dom was excellent, but there's so much more we want to understand about cancer.
Certainly cancer is something near and dear to my heart.
I did my fellowship in oncology.
But at the same time, I think I understand cancer far less than I understand things that
I didn't formally train in.
I think I have a better understanding, for example, of heart disease than I do of cancer.
So I'm really excited to explore a lot of topics today and acknowledge that we probably
won't even scratch the surface of all that you think about.
But all that said, how did you get interested in this?
We started it when I was at Yale University, Department of Neurology, where we had been
working on epilepsy and lipid storage diseases and ganglicides, basically, the complex lipid
molecules.
And one of the individuals that I was working with at that time, Robert Yu, he was my mentor
at the time, he had done some research on ganglicide changes in tumors.
And we had been looking at that.
And I said, you know, there was some interesting molecules in those tumor cells.
So I also knew Dennis Spencer, who was the chief of neurosurgery at the time at Yale.
And he said, why don't you come up to the operating room with me and I'll get you a
nice piece of glioblastoma from a patient.
You know, I'm a basic scientist.
I'm not a clinician.
I don't know what's going on.
So I said, sure, you come into the operating room.
And it was kind of an experience that I'll never forget, having someone take a tumor
out of someone's head.
And they were asking me all kinds of questions like, you know, do you think we should put
pellets of radiation in the cavity and, you know, all this kind of stuff?
I didn't know.
I said, I'm here to look at the ganglicide pattern in the tumor.
I don't know how to treat the cancer or anything like this.
But any event, we had then started making our own brain tumors in the mouse based on
the work of Harry Zimmerman, who started the first school of neuropathology in the
United States at Yale University in the back of the 1930s.
And he was still alive at the time.
He lived to be 98 years old or something.
So I was interested in doing comparative studies of glycolipids in human and mouse brain tumors
to see whether or not we can come to some common changes.
And that's how we got started, pretty much looking at comparative biochemical profiles
between human tumors and mouse tumors.
And there was some similarities, but there were many differences as well.
But we didn't get into the kind of therapeutic evaluation of these tumors until we also had
a huge program in epilepsy, mapping genes for epilepsy.
We did a lot of things at Yale.
Everybody was working on the glycolipids of the tumors, glycolipids of developing brain,
lipid storage diseases and epilepsy.
I wrote a grant internally at Yale, which was rejected, asking about ketogenic diets.
And what year was this?
This was back in the late 70s, early 80s maybe, 1980.
And they said, oh, nobody's interested in ketogenic diets.
It's kind of passe.
This was before the work at Hopkins or?
Yeah, Hopkins, John Freeman was a friend of mine too, who was the godfather of ketogenic
diets.
He was the one that saved Jim Abrams' son, Charlie.
And Jim was a movie director.
And his friend Meryl Streep made the movie First Do No Harm, which was based in part on
Jim's experience with his son.
But I wasn't connected at that time to Abrams or any of that stuff.
That was even before the Charlie Foundation.
I just had this inkling that maybe ketogenic diet would be interesting to test against
some of the epilepsy models that I was working with.
Does that mean you suspected that something to do with glucose metabolism?
No, nothing.
I just thought it was an interesting approach, a non-drug approach for seizures.
And anyway, the grant was summarily rejected.
So I said, well, nobody's interested in this.
So I left Yale and I came up to Boston College here to start a program.
And then we were here from then it was 10 years, 15 years later, we developed some of
the best animal models for epilepsy.
And we were looking at brains of biochemistry and epileptic seizures and the genes that
caused epilepsy.
And then one of my PhD students, Mariana Tran, says, oh, they're having a big meeting out
in Washington on ketogenic diets for epilepsy.
And maybe our model would be appropriate for this.
I said, nah, this is, you know, I says after my experience at Yale, I said, nobody's interested
in this crap anyway.
You're still traumatized by the grant.
So I said, they're not in it.
You know, I got a summarily rejected.
So this is nobody interested in ketogenic diets.
So anyway, she said, oh, so I said I had a few extra bucks in the grant.
So I said, OK, go on out there.
In fact, she wrote a little blurb and they funded her to go out there.
So she comes back and starts telling me about, wow, you can't believe what I saw out there.
All these guys are interested in this ketogenic diet.
And this guy, Jim Abrams, and he wants to start this foundation called the Charlie Foundation.
It was like to study epilepsy and ketogenic diets and stuff.
So I said, all right, what the hell?
So we started to put them on the mice.
And it was funny because we didn't know what we were doing.
But then at the same time, it was two things came together at the same time.
We were studying ganglicides for lipid storage diseases.
And there was a drug company over in England that gave us this new drug that was supposed
to stop ganglicide synthesis and therefore reduce the storage in the brain.
Of course, at that time at Boston College, animal didn't charge me for animals, which
they do now, which is a tragedy because you can really do a lot of work.
The damn mice cost so much money and there were so fewer restrictions.
I mean, we followed all of the animal care protocols, but we had access to a large number.
So we could do experiments that you couldn't do anywhere else.
So when we got the drug from the company, we were feeding the drug to the mice and we
looked at the ganglify.
Yeah, it's really down.
But so was the body weight.
And then when we put the control group in, we found out that the tumors shrunk and the
ganglicides were reduced from this drug.
But then the body weight was also reduced.
And the controls were also...
They're both animals being fed ad lib?
Ad libitum.
One had the drug, one didn't.
Okay.
So the drug somehow either reduced intake or increased expenditure?
We don't know, but the body weights were reduced by about 15% or 20%.
And the tumors were significantly reduced by about 60%.
So I told the company that...
I just threw them on...
This was a pilot study.
I told the company that your drug seems to really shrink brain tumors.
And they go, why?
This is a much bigger market than, say, Tay-Sachs disease, right?
So that's when they gave me $200,000 to investigate the mechanism by which their drug was stopping
brain cancer.
Because I showed them the data and they were all excited.
So we then began to investigate this.
And Perna Mukherjee, Dr. Mukherjee, who worked, started with me.
I said, hey, Perna.
Which I hired her specifically to start looking at this.
And then when we realized that, what's working?
She said, a lot of times these drugs work through calorie restriction.
So I said, well, why don't we put a control group?
We all decided, let's put a control group for body weights.
And then we just...
One was the guys with the drug and losing weight.
The other guys would just take the food away from them.
So the body weights would be absolutely identical.
So they were parafet.
It wasn't parafet.
One group was eating ad libitum and they were losing body weight.
And the other group...
Oh, I see.
Okay, I got it.
We had to restrict the calories to match the body weight.
So they're parawated.
Yes, parawated.
Yes, and then we evaluated this and the tumors were exactly the same size.
So it had nothing to do with the drug.
Even though the drug was working on the targeted molecule, it wasn't the targeted molecule
that was responsible for this.
So that's when we also decided with the epilepsy overlapping, does the ketogenic diet work
through calorie restriction?
Because many of these children that get ketogenic diets, they have very restricted calories.
And you have to give very small...
You can't let kids eat massive amounts of fat because invariably, John Freeman told
me the diet doesn't work if they just...
Like one out of two or 300 kids just loves to eat all this fat and the seizures don't
go away.
So we...
In other words, the thinking at the time was there is some amount of caloric restriction
that is necessary within the context of the ketosis to also affect the epileptic seizures.
Yes, absolutely.
But you have to be very careful because many of these children are on the growth spurt.
So you have to be careful on how much restriction you give.
And the other thing, of course, it's self-restricted.
There's several physiological systems in our body that when you eat a lot of fat, you just
don't eat a lot of calories.
It's a turn off.
It works through the vagus nerve.
The hormone choliscis thekinin is kind of an appetite suppressor.
It affects the vagus nerve, which then stops the appetite.
You don't eat as much.
So I have so many stories.
So I was sitting on a bus one day...
You're on the right podcast, Tom, because we don't have time restrictions.
Yeah, but listen.
So they made this thing called the vagal nerve stimulator.
And it was made by a company, I can't remember the name of it, made a fortune.
They would implant the stimulator into the persons who has epilepsy.
And it would send out things to stimulate the vagus nerve.
And I was sitting on the bus with this guy from Norway.
And he says, I said, you're putting this in the patient?
Yeah, we're putting this in the patient.
How does it work?
Yeah, it seems to work really good.
I said, how much is it?
And he says, well, the operation is like $4,000.
But the device, it was like $15,000 or $16,000.
But they were putting them in all these epileptic patients and they're working.
I said, how does it work?
He said, I don't know, but it works.
So I said, I didn't know.
I'm sitting on the bus.
I don't know.
And they went to MGM Studios down in Florida.
They closed the whole place down in the middle of the week in December so that they could
attract all the epileptologists to use their device to put into these patients.
It's one of these kinds of things.
So anyway, comes back when we were working on ketogenic diets and calorie restriction.
We realized that humans have this internal system to stop calories.
And if you don't stop the calories, invariably, you don't get the management of the seizures.
So we in our parallel studies in epilepsy with mice and cancer and all this other stuff,
we started to learn what's working in the patients.
How do we translate what's working in the patients into the mice?
The mice can be another source of information that we can feed back.
And we published this big paper on calorie restriction and that the ketogenic diet was
working largely through calorie restriction.
And maintaining low blood sugar levels was the key to maintaining control of seizures.
Now if you had a...
I don't know if you did this experiment, but if you took animals on an equally low caloric
diet that was not ketogenic, so let's just say a very high carbohydrate, low fat diet,
where presumably glucose levels would be higher even though they would still be calorically
restricted, would you get the same anti-seizure benefit?
Same results, exactly.
So because what was happening is that when the body is restricted of calories, you then
make ketones.
So the level of ketosis was also seen in the calor...
It would be like a human doing water-only fasting.
So how calorically restricted did they need to be if they were not on a ketogenic diet?
40%, 30 to 5 to 40% restriction.
And then we did some studies in another group.
We found out that 35 to 40% restriction of calories in the mouse equates to a water-only
therapeutic fasting in humans.
And that's because the...
Yeah, their metabolism is...
Right, seven or eight times higher than that of a man.
So humans can achieve much higher ketosis than a mouse can.
And the mouse...
So one week, a one-day water-only fast in a mouse is like a seven-day water-only fast
in a human.
And the blood sugars go down, the ketones go up.
IRBs don't allow you to fast mice that long anymore, do they?
Oh yeah.
As long as they're healthy.
Calorie restriction is generally a healthy thing.
You don't want to over-restrict because then you put into a nutritional imbalance and you
don't want to go to the level of what we call starvation.
This is another...
Calorie restriction is healthy up to the point where you start breaking down muscle.
If you start breaking down muscle, then you enter into a new physiological state called
starvation.
And that's very pathological.
You don't ever want to go to that digression.
So some people, they get so carried away with water-only fasting, they can enter into starvation
mode.
I know this for a fact because I used to spend a lot of time with George Cahill, who used
to run the Joslin Diabetes Centers down here in Boston.
And he and I would talk for hours and hours with Bud Veach at the NIH about how long people
can go with this transition over from therapeutic fasting into starvation.
And also the body builds just like anything.
Your body gets accustomed.
You can go a long time without eating if you're in shape, if you've done this.
But it depends on what your body weight is, how old you are.
It depends on a lot of different things, how long you can go without eating.
The bottom line is that we were trying to develop a therapy and figure out the mechanisms
by which ketogenic diets were therapeutic.
Going back to the Cahill stuff for a moment before we come back to that, did you have
a sense or did George have a sense of when those patients are in a negative nitrogen
balance?
I assume it matters as to what their starting weight is and muscle mass and things like
that.
But were there general rules about once you cross over that point where you're basically
pulling nitrogen out of the muscle?
Right.
And he got those data actually from the 10 guys that starved to death and mace prison
in Northern Ireland.
Bobby Sands and that group actually.
He was there monitoring their blood work while they were dying of starvation.
These were prisoners that they were fasting as a protest, correct?
Yes.
They made a movie out of it, Every Mother's Son, about that there was 10 Irishmen that
were-
How long did they live on average?
I think he had the data.
He was never able to publish it.
The British government was on top of him about that.
But he was able to collect the data and shared some of that stuff.
It was very interesting.
It's a horrible thing.
It's like one of the worst ways to die is starvation.
So what happens to your diaphragm is the last muscle that will be digested.
And there's a momentum that starts.
Now you have to realize that these guys that did this-
So they don't die of just acidosis.
It's actually the diaphragm.
You drown in your own body fluids, basically.
Jesus, brutal.
So because what happens is once your diaphragm can't work, your lungs fill up with fluids
and you drown in your own fluids.
And the diaphragm presumably stops working because of either the loss of muscle or the
electrolyte imbalance.
Yeah, both, a combination of both.
And then there's a moment, you can't stop it.
Once the momentum starts-
It's like these horrible hiccups, right?
Yeah.
Once the momentum starts, it seems like they try to do an intervention on a couple of the
guys and they weren't able to reverse it.
So it was pretty horrific.
Now those guys were all young Irishmen in their 20s and 30s.
I don't know what the oldest guy was, but they lived from, I don't know, 68 to 85, 90
days without any food, just water.
But then he subsequently fasted these very obese people-
For 40 days.
Longer, for six months, eight months.
Oh, wow.
He has the data.
One guy, a postman, lost his job, weighed 450 pounds or something, couldn't deliver
the mail.
So they put him on the water only fasting for six months, I think, six or eight months.
Guy lost 250 pounds.
This is different from the guy who, there was a single case report of a patient who
weighed a little over 400 pounds and did a 382 day fast.
Yeah.
But I didn't realize that was Cahill that was over-
I don't know if that was Cahill.
There was another, there's a couple of them.
And he was overseeing, he showed us the data on this one guy, the postman.
And the issue, of course, is I don't know if he took many supplements because your body
fat holds a lot of vitamins, fat soluble vitamins.
The minerals come from your bones, the liver controls an awful lot of B vitamins and things
like this.
I think there were supplements over the course, but they weren't, you don't need a lot of
supplements.
Your body holds all of it.
We evolved as a species to starve.
Our existence today is dependent on our ability to go long periods of time without eating.
We don't receive that anymore.
But-
Yeah.
And it seems that our ability to access minerals and vitamins is highly dependent on our nutritional
state.
In other words, your need for those things tends to go up in a fed state.
At least according to some research I've seen.
Yeah.
You're right.
And our ancestors were hardened people.
Their bodies were already acclimated to a starvation mode.
So they were very efficient in maintaining mineral and nutrient balances.
I think in our society today, and this is purely speculation, I think a lot of the foods
are depleted in the kinds of nutrients that we would need.
Therefore, some people are almost like in a starvation mode, but they're eating food
that has no nutritional value.
And consequently, you store a lot of fat.
Because the body doesn't usually get rid of sugar.
As I said, sugar is stored.
It's not, you know, pea out sugar unless you have type 1 diabetes or something.
The body has all these filtration systems to keep carbs, which is then transferred to
fat and stored as fat.
That's our energy to keep us alive when there's no food.
But all these ideas and things were developing when we were doing the epilepsy studies.
And it became clear that calorie restriction was a key form, key mechanism by which the
ketogenic diet was working.
And we have since then seen in numerous children with epilepsy that breakthrough seizures
will occur when blood sugar spikes.
Define spike in that very specific case.
How high does it need to be in milligrams per deciliter?
Yeah, it doesn't really...
For managing epilepsy, there's many cases where it just has to go a little bit above
the baseline.
So kids will have a very low 70, 68, 65 milligrams per deciliter.
They'll grab a cupcake at a party or whatever and spikes up to 120 or whatever.
And then you'll get a breakthrough seizure.
And do you believe that it is the absolute value of 120 in that case?
Or do you believe it's the D by DT, meaning the rate of change of the glucose?
We can't know that.
It hasn't been done effectively.
All we know is from the clinicians and the nurses that have told me all this information.
And of course, when your child has a breakthrough seizure, nobody likes to see a kid seizing.
I mean, it's very...
It's traumatic.
It's not a pleasant thing.
So once they realize that the kids have to maintain this very stable, the parents are
very, very restrictive of these kids.
Because they don't want to see their child seize.
So they're very restrictive.
So when we do the same thing for cancer, the problem with cancer is you don't see a breakthrough
seizure.
You don't see a group of tumor cells starting to grow faster.
You don't see the immediate effects, but they're there, but you just can't see them.
With epilepsy, you have a very visible, clear indication that something went wrong.
And invariably, there's a spike in glucose.
Now, what's very interesting is in these kids, they could be maintained for months without
a single seizure.
And then one drink of grape juice or whatever the hell, boom, breakthrough seizure within
sometimes minutes from the time you took the...
So it's a very...
They can flip back, but then they can also get back on track again.
They don't have a large number of seizures.
They can just...
They can get back on track.
It is a very sensitive system in our brains.
Then as John told me, John Freeman, he says, we don't understand that if a kid is maintained
seizure free or minimal seizures for long periods of time on ketogenic diets, and then
we remove the diet, they seem to be managed.
In other words, they don't return to their multiple seizures that they would have had
every day.
So he doesn't know if it was because the diet did something fundamental or they outgrew
the seizure or whatever.
Again, these are areas in epilepsy that are under active investigation by a lot of...
But it's interesting.
It's almost like a reset.
One of the things that impressed me about reading the case studies of these very, very
long fasts is that in the reports that are published several years later, many of the
subjects maintain their new weight reduced state, which is a bit counterintuitive based
on what we know today about traditional dieting approaches where everybody will return back
to baseline.
And so it begs the question, right?
When you starve this person for six months, do they completely change the way they eat
on the other side because of a behavioral shift or is it a physiologic shift?
Meaning their metabolism has been kind of quote unquote fixed.
Yeah.
Well, I think it's probably a combination of both.
I mean, again, these are very complicated physiological processes.
They call it the thrifty gene.
That was a term.
It's not one gene.
It's like the thrifty physiology.
If you do yo-yo dieting, you can be screwed up for a long period of time.
Those things all have loose ends.
There's nothing that we have found that's absolutely consistent in all patients all
the time when it comes to those kinds of things.
And that's why they're always interesting to talk about because someone always has some
new idea about something that they've seen.
Kind of fits in a little bit with what everybody else is.
I don't really dwell, engage in those kinds of things as far as our research is concerned.
We know about them.
We talk about them, but we don't other than the calorie restriction that we introduce
into the mice.
And then when we found out that the calorie restriction and the ketogenic diets were working,
so people say, well, why don't you just do calorie restriction because cancer, back to
cancer, we don't like to restrict the term restriction.
Even the term, you already got a disease now you have to be restricted.
So ketogenic diets are a little, takes the sting out of a therapeutic fast and they can
also replicate some of the same physiological changes.
The key is to lower the blood sugar and elevate the ketones.
And that's what ketogenic diets do for managing epilepsy.
And they do the same thing for cancer.
The issue, of course, is we don't know the mechanism by which lowering glucose and elevating
ketones is responsible for the management of the seizure.
This is under an active investigation by a lot of labs.
The actual mechanism, is it the elevation of the ketones?
Is it the reduction of the glucose?
Or is it some combination of the two?
But for cancer, it becomes very clear.
The mechanism of action is very clear for how this kills cancer cells.
It's based on Otto Warburg's theory.
So when we started to do this and realized that calorie restriction was shrinking these
tumors down massively, based on the drug that I told you about, because it was working through
calorie restriction.
Then I said, how is calorie restriction stopping tumors?
And then we realized that it was lowering blood sugar.
So we started measuring blood sugar in these calorie restricted mice and measuring ketones.
And we were seeing that we were getting these major shifts.
And then we said, then it became clear, who is the guy who did this or thought about it
was Warburg.
Now he wasn't doing ketogenic diets.
Had he done and known about that, I think he would have been able to crack this cancer
thing far, far earlier than it.
He didn't do ketogenic.
He didn't know anything about that.
So let's back up for a moment for people.
I think most people listening probably know what the Warburg effect is and who Warburg
was.
But maybe just give us a moment of setting the stage for what his observation was that
now bears his name.
Well, his interest was in biochemistry.
He was a classical chemist, biochemist in his time.
And he began to look at the metabolism of tumors.
So he made an observation, which was solidified that cancer cells continue to do an ancient
fermentation metabolism, even in the presence of oxygen.
So this, the Pasteur effect from Louis Pasteur with the yeast was that yeast will ferment.
They evolved, that organism evolved to be able to ferment, get energy in the absence
of oxygen.
But when as soon as oxygen came into the presence, they stopped fermenting and they immediately
started respiring.
They have a system that can do that.
So the Pasteur effect was basically the termination of fermentation in the presence of oxygen.
That was the Pasteur effect and it was repeated in all these yeast strains and this kind of
thing.
And that was a fundamental biochemical advancement, so to say.
But Warburg recognized, he knew Pasteur's work very, very well.
And then he said, geez, these cancer cells, man, they continue to throw out lactic acid,
even in the presence of 100% oxygen.
So he grew cancer cells in 100% oxygen and they were still making lactic acid.
So clearly the Pasteur effect wasn't working.
I'll just interject for a moment to explain something to the listener and we'll probably
have a picture of this.
But of course, you take glucose to pyruvate in the cytoplasm.
And that's a, you know, that yields a couple of units of ATP.
And then you have sort of a choice of what you're going to do with that pyruvate.
If your demand for ATP is incredibly quick, usually exceeding the capacity of oxygen to
get into the cell, you'll make lactate.
And that's also relatively inefficient, meaning you don't get that much more ATP.
I think you get another two molecules of ATP per unit of pyruvate, but at least you have
the advantage of saying, I'm not limited by oxygen.
Alternatively, if oxygen is plentiful and more importantly, if the demand for ATP is
not excessive, you can shuttle that pyruvate into acetyl-CoA and the mitochondria and you
can generate over 30 units of ATP.
And so what you're saying is there is an observation which said, hey, if I put this
cell in the presence of lots of oxygen, it really shouldn't make much lactate.
Right.
And that's what he finds when you take normal tissue like kidney slices or muscle slices
or liver, you grow them in 100% oxygen and they produce minimal, barely detectable lactate.
There's always some going to be produced in every tissue, but basically it's very minimal,
but the cancer cell continues to dump out massive amounts of lactic acid, even in the
presence of 100% oxygen.
So this was a phenomenon.
And he saw this over and over again.
It didn't make any difference whether it was a human tumor, a mouse tumor, rat tumor.
They were all doing this same kind of thing.
So what he concluded from this was that their respiratory system was defective because like
you just said, if pyruvate...
Now that's the Emden-Meierhoff pathway going from glucose to pyruvate.
Pyruvate is the end of that.
So then the opportunity is that the pyruvate would enter into the mitochondria under oxygenated
conditions and be fully oxidized to water and CO2.
And oxygen is the acceptor of the electrons to form the water.
And the carbons are coming from the foods that we metabolized.
But the cancer cell was dumping out large amounts of this lactic acid.
So why would a cancer cell dump out lactic acid?
And it became clear to Warburg through a variety of experiments that the respiratory system
was defective in these cells.
Let's just clarify that.
Many people, when they hear that, will assume...
We think respiratory system, we think of lungs.
What you really mean is the mitochondrial machinery that undergoes what we call cellular
respiration.
The lungs are bringing in the oxygen...
The oxygen and getting rid of the CO2 that enables...
That enables all the cells, the majority of our cells in the body, to perform this
very efficient form of energy production, which then frees up the cells to do their
sophisticated behaviors.
Liver cells do what they do, kidney cells, brain cells.
They all do what they do because they have this very efficient energetic system that's
working called respiration.
The lungs are just the facilitators of the body to get the good air in and the bad air
out.
So basically, the cancer cell was continuing to produce massive amounts of lactic acid,
despite the fact that there was all this...
So he was then looking at the mitochondria, noticing that there were some defects in these
kinds of things.
But he wasn't at the level of electron microscopy or this.
He just made the...
What year?
This is in the 1920s?
Nineteen-fifties.
Mostly late 20s, 30s, 40s, all the way up to the 50s.
I think he stopped his research maybe in the early 60s.
Now he won a Nobel Prize, didn't he?
Was it for the description of this phenomenon?
No.
It was for the discovery of cytochrome c oxidase, which is actually one of the key enzymes in
the electron transport chain.
Cells generate energy through respiration.
So he was nominated other times.
And there's still some controversy about how many times he had been nominated for the work
on cancer, but never to achieve another Nobel Prize.
But he was considered one of the dominant biochemists in the 20th century.
And he had very strong ideas and very excellent quantitative measurements for this.
A lot of his work was reproduced by dozens and dozens of scientists.
So that was the fundamental observation.
But he then extended this to the theory that why are the cells producing all this lactic
acid?
Because the organelle that is supposed to be involved is defective.
This led to a lot of controversy.
What do you mean, defect?
How defective?
What do you mean?
Much later, Pete Peterson from Johns Hopkins had done a magnificent job in collating all
this information.
And he found that in every kind of a cancer cell, no matter what kind of it is, there
was some defect in the number structure or function of the mitochondria.
And it could vary.
So some cancer cells have very few mitochondria, but they look normal.
Very few of them.
Other tumor cells clearly have a lot of mitochondria, but they look abnormal.
So whatever it was, it was something to do with an impairment of the respiratory system
within the cell.
And if the cell can't generate energy through normal respiration, then it has to ferment.
There's no other way they can get the energy.
So it became the Warburg effect, which everybody talks about, is one of the biggest problems
in this whole thing.
Because Warburg in his paper clearly said that aerobic glycolysis, or what they call
the Warburg effect, is a secondary problem that's subjected to many, many variances in
the environment.
But everybody focuses on this.
He said the real issue is the damage to the respiration.
And everybody says, no, respiration is normal in cancer cells.
And why would they say it's normal?
Because they started doing cells in culture rather than looking at the tissues themselves.
And once you start doing culture work, you're taking cells from a tissue and separating
them and growing them as if they were microorganisms in a culture dish.
Well, this changes everything.
They're no longer connected to each other.
They're growing in some artificial fluid.
And they're doing things that they sometimes do and sometimes not do in the real world.
So you make a lot of assumptions about things based on a system that itself is artifactual.
So let me ask a couple of technical questions.
Obviously measuring the amount of lactate or hydrogen ion that's produced is a way to
give us an indication of how much anaerobic metabolism is taking place.
If you're not in cell culture, how do you quantify the amount of aerobic respiration?
You look at the amount of oxygen consumed and the amount of lactic acid produced.
So if you're doing aerobic respiration, you're consuming a lot of oxygen and producing very
little lactate.
And then you can quantitate the amount of ATP being produced per milliliter of oxygen
that you consume.
And according to this, this can vary from anywhere from seven ATP units to nine, depending
on the system.
But it's, you know, Warburg used the number seven based on his data at that time.
So you could calculate the total amount of ATP being produced in the cell based on its
oxygen consumption and its lactic acid production.
And Warburg, did he ever do this in situ?
Yes.
He did it in slices and then he did it in cell culture as well.
So he created some of his own problems as well, switching from one to the other.
The concern that we have now is that many cells in culture look like they're consuming
a lot of oxygen.
And they're making lactic acid, but they're consuming a lot of oxygen.
So like you said-
So suggesting that they're doing both, which is still a bit odd.
Yeah, right.
Well, that was Sidney Winehouse's argument.
His argument was the cancer cell needs so much energy that respiration by itself can't
be sufficient.
So they have to ferment and respire at the same time.
And that made everybody feel that, yeah, Warburg was wrong.
They do have good respiration, but they just need so much more energy.
They need to ferment at the same time.
But the work from Pete Peterson showed that they have defective respiration.
So I mean, they have defective mitochondria, structure, number, and function, besides many
other studies have shown.
So you know that they can't be doing oxidative phosphorylation or respiration because they're
very organelle that is needed for that is deficient in some way.
And that could be many different ways.
As I said, there's no one, all cancer cells, all cancer cells have a defect in respiration.
How that defect came about can vary from one type of cancer to another.
So one has to recognize that.
So not every cancer cell will have the exact same defect in respiration in the mitochondria.
Some will have very few mitochondria.
So they just don't have quantitatively enough organelles to do respiration.
But what seems to be there seems to be functional, partially functional.
Other cells, as I said, are loaded with mitochondria.
But when you look at them, they're morphologically abnormal.
So structure dictates function.
In biology, we know that structure dictates function.
So if the structure of the organelle is abnormal, you know that the function of that organelle
is not going to be normal.
And is the idea that those mutations were acquired?
Oh, I wouldn't call them mutations.
They would call them defects.
Now, you can have a mutation.
In other words, the genome is unaffected in some of those cases?
Yes, we've done that.
We sequenced the entire genome of five different independently derived cancers from mouse,
all derived from different origins.
And we didn't find a single genetic abnormality, what we call pathogenic, where the mutation
would actually have an effect on a function.
And we didn't find a single one.
So that's all.
So let's take, maybe take a step back and for the listener again, we'll go over some
of the basics of genetics.
Because I think that for many people, there's an understanding that, I mean, by definition,
a cancer has a mutation that renders it incapable of listening to normal cell signaling.
Do you have a sense broadly of what amount of human cancers arise from germline mutations
rather than somatic mutations?
It's obviously very small, but I don't know what the number is.
Well, they say it's about five to 6%.
Oh, it's that high.
Okay.
And you hear about them, the BRCA1, BRCA2, Lefram, NEP53.
Lynch syndrome, et cetera.
But when we looked into those so-called inherited risks, we call them inherited risk factors.
None of them have ever been 100% penetrant, which means that every person having that
gene must express...
They're not purely deterministic.
Yeah.
They're not deterministic.
And as Warburg said, there are many secondary causes of cancer, but there's only one primary
cause.
The primary cause is the damage to the respiratory system.
So if the inherited mutation damages the respiratory system of the cell, the probability of cancer
is a real possibility.
So, because everybody who has Lefram, any tumors or BRCA1 tumors or whatever, they all
are all fermenters.
So the fermentation metabolism is there in every cancer.
But there are some people that have the exact same mutation that the other person has, but
they never develop a tumor because for whatever reason, in that person, that mutation did
not damage the respiration.
That could be an environmental suppressive effect or another gene in the genome that
prevents the inherited mutation from damaging the respiration.
We don't know that.
So we only know that you don't get cancer if your mitochondria remain healthy.
That's what we know.
So that's an important...
Because that goes back to the prevention issue.
How do you prevent cancer?
You prevent cancer by keeping your mitochondria healthy.
How do you do that?
Well, you avoid...
If you can avoid those risk factors, mostly from the environment, like viral infections,
intermittent hypoxia, radiation exposure, carcinogenic exposure, all these different
things, every one of those things can damage respiration in a population of cells, then
leading to cancer.
Because we know of no cancer that has normal respiration.
But when you grow them in culture, people say, yeah, they have normal respiration.
They're taken in oxygen, so therefore, a warburg is wrong.
But when you look at the structure in the vivo, and you look at the tissues, and you
look at the actual architecture of the tissue, invariably, you find damage to the respiration,
damage to the structure and function of mitochondria.
So what the field has done is put more credibility into the results from cell culture work than
into the actual tissues that people see and look under the microscope and look at.
Because the warburg effect was largely forgotten for many years after his initial observation,
right?
Yeah.
A lot of what he did was forgotten.
And Pete Peterson was one of the few guys that kept the fire burning.
Because a lot of the...
Because as I said, when Watson and Crick discovered the DNA as the origin of the genetic material,
but it wasn't only them.
There was a whole group of other people that were doing it.
They just weren't acknowledged as much.
Yeah.
And then the field ran off into that.
And they also knew that there were chromosomal abnormalities in some cancers.
So it made it clear that, hey, you know, these genomic defects in the tumor cells are
likely the real origin of the disease.
So the whole field, more or less, shifted away from the traditional biochemical analysis
to the more molecular biology analysis.
And therefore, you find more and more mutations, more and more genetic defects, and all these
kinds of things, leading people to believe that these were the causes of the disease.
And a lot of really nice experiments were done where they would introduce mutant viruses,
virus particles into cells, and they would integrate into the nuclear genome.
And then you'd see the cancer cells lose, become transformed into a neoplastic kind
of a cell, giving the appearance that this was a cause effect.
They didn't realize that those same viruses went into the mitochondria and blew out the
respiration.
So that wasn't even considered as possible.
If the viruses are doing that, presumably they're integrating into the genome?
Yeah.
Well, they would do it both ways.
They can do it a lot of different ways.
So sometimes the viruses actually infect directly into the mitochondria.
They produce proteins in the mitochondria that screw up the electron transport chain.
Other times, the virus is integrated into the nuclear genome, producing a protein product
that then disrupts the mitochondria.
Either way, the mitochondria disrupt it, whether if it's a direct effect of the virus replicating
inside the organelle, or it's an effect of a product produced by the virus that then
goes and disrupts the organelle.
And this is what we're finding for the majority of these situations.
So even the inherited mutations that we look at, they disrupt mitochondrial function.
And if they disrupt mitochondrial function, you are at risk for developing a neoplasm
in that particular population of cells.
There are some cancers that don't follow that, correct?
I mean, aren't there some cancers that have normal mitochondria?
We haven't found any, because the evidence for that is that they're all fermenting.
We haven't found the cancer that doesn't ferment.
So if the cancer is fermenting, it's obviously not respiring.
If it's respiration would be normal, it shouldn't be fermenting.
As a matter of fact, Dean Burke did this kind of a study way back in the 50s.
He went and looked at various kinds of hepatomas, because there was an article that was published
to say that there was this very low, slow-growing hepatoma that did not ferment, which was
directly related to your question.
But Burke, who was at the head of the NCI at the time, studied these things in massive
detail and was able to show that the slowest-growing tumor did have a significant elevation of
lactic acid production over a normal cell.
But you had to look at it really carefully and do the experiments over extended periods
of time.
So even the slowest of the slowest-growing tumors, guys that would be maybe considered
benign, were still making lactic acid.
Another interesting thing was the crown gall tumors in plants.
This is another interesting ... Plants have cancer, but they don't metastasize.
They just grow these tumors.
People back in the 30s were testing Warburg's theory in these plants, and they all had damaged
respiration and they were fermenting just like the mouse tumors.
When you say respiration, you mean photosynthetic respiration?
No.
No, plants have both.
Plants can get energy from chloroplasts to build carbohydrates, but they also have mitochondria.
Oh, I didn't realize that.
So their carbon fixation obviously comes from photosynthesis.
But when they make their equivalent of starch, they had an effect on-
Yes.
So they will burn their own fuels to generate respiratory energy.
But they also have dysmorphic cell growth, and they've called these crown gall tumors.
You see them sometimes on the side of trees and things.
So people back in the day analyzed the biochemistry of these things, and they also found that
they were following Warburg's metabolic profile.
But they didn't metastasize.
The reason they don't metastasize is they don't have an immune system.
It turns out that from our work and the work of others, the metastatic cell is actually
part of our immune system.
So macrophages and leukocytes, these are the cells that have the genetic capabilities of
moving around the body, entering into tissues.
This is what they do.
Plants don't have that.
Plants don't have that kind of an immune system.
So they don't metastasize.
They grow in place.
But humans and other animals, of course, that have these cells of the immune system, therefore
they can get metastatic cancer.
So before we get to that, because I do have a number of questions about that topic, another
argument that's been proposed for the Warburg effect is the need for cellular building blocks.
The other thing that the tumor is doing above and beyond its non-tumorous cell mate is growing.
And although not necessarily faster than a regular cell, it certainly grows in a less
regulated way, and therefore it's going to proliferate.
So van der Heiden and I think Lou Cantley and Craig Thompson wrote that paper in 2009
that is, I'm sure you're familiar with, there's a science paper, I believe, and they proposed
this other explanation, which was, look, it's not just an energetic thing.
In fact, I don't recall if they said it's not just or it's not even about the energetics,
but the point here was this is where you get building blocks to make cells grow.
Do you think it's possible that both of these are correct?
Yeah.
In the process of upregulating the Enden-Meierhof pathway, you are going to get the carbons for
building blocks.
At the same time, you're going to get some energy.
Now through the Piruve-Kaines system.
However, this is very interesting.
But they deviate from the path from Warburg's theory in saying that respiration is normal.
They think there's nothing wrong with the mitochondria.
They've said that many times.
Craig Thompson has said this.
You have to ignore a massive amount of evidence to make those kinds of statements.
You just have to ignore everything that Pete Peterson has done, which is a life's work
showing that the mitochondria have no idea, but he doesn't mention that.
They don't discuss Pete Peterson's massive amount of evidence.
But you're right.
In order for a cell to grow, you need a lot of building blocks and you need carbon.
Where's the carbon coming from this?
And it's coming from both the pentose pathway and the glycolytic pathway, and it's also
coming from glutamine.
So these cancer cells are sucking down glutamine.
So you're getting the amide nitrogen to form the nucleotides.
You're getting the glutamate that then goes into anaplerosis in the TCA cycle.
So between glucose and glutamine, you aren't getting all of the building blocks that you
need for rapid cell division.
But where's the energy coming from?
Okay, without energy, nothing grows.
Nothing can live without ATP.
So where is the energy coming from?
And this is our thing.
So we, myself, and Christos, Chernopoulos, and Hungary, I proposed this a long time ago
on a purely theoretical basis, having been convinced that Warburg was right, that the
respiration of all cancer cells is damaged to some extent.
So if that's the case, the Warburg effect was only the glucose part of the puzzle.
It wasn't the glutamine part of the puzzle.
So now with our new information, we know that most of the ATP in the cancer is coming from
substrate-level phosphorylation in the mitochondria, which is disconnected from oxidative phosphorylation.
So what we have now is the missing link in Warburg's basic theory.
So explain what SLP is.
Substrate-level phosphorylation is the production of ATP when you move a phosphate group from
an organic substrate onto an ADP molecule.
So it's an ancient way of generating energy.
In other words, it's an organic molecule that's an electron acceptor rather than oxygen.
Right.
So instead of going through the electron transport chain where you use NAD, NADH, NADP, NADPH
as electron transporters.
Well, electron donors.
Electron donors.
You can do a very quick trick where you take an ADP and restore it, meaning it has two
phosphates, you restore it to an ATP by using an organic molecule to donate a phosphate.
Well, for substrate-level phosphorylation.
Yes, yes.
So succinyl CoA has a phosphate group on a serine inside the protein itself, and that
phosphate group is then donated to ADP.
Use GDP, make GTP, both.
Depends on the situation.
But in cancer cells, it's ATP.
So you're moving phosphate groups from an organic substrate onto the ADP as the acceptor.
And you can generate massive amounts of energy from that process, which can replace the level
of lost energy from oxidative phosphorylation.
And does that occur inside the mitochondria, inside the inner matrix?
Yes.
Yeah, it's in the matrix.
So you're going to be blowing out a lot of...
You're going to make a lot of ATP.
It's going to just replace.
In the normal cell, you're making most of the ATP from oxidative phosphorylation.
But in the cancer cell, you're making most of it from substrate-level phosphorylation,
inside the same organelle.
Why don't our cells do this under demand?
So if we jumped up and down and did 25 burpees right now, we would very quickly exceed our
oxidative capacity for respiration, and we'd start making a bunch of lactate.
Why aren't we also undergoing SLP?
Well, we do, in the heart muscles.
They do.
They've done various cardiac restrictions and things like that.
And a lot of this has been worked out in the heart.
So it does happen.
We do do substrate-level phosphorylation.
But it only can be done for short periods of time.
It can't be done extensively.
You can't replace oxidative phosphorylation under normal conditions with substrate-level
phosphorylation.
When you hold your breath, you're going to be able to survive for a certain period of
time.
Lactic acid builds up.
I mean, this was shown by Hosh Kotska when he did some incredibly interesting experiments
trying to hold various aquatic animals underwater and looking at the metabolic changes that
occurred.
So seals, porpoises, turtles, these kinds of things.
He strapped them to a board, held them underwater, and then he would measure all these metabolites
in the bloodstream.
Now, these were animals that actually could live underwater.
If they did it to us, we'd all be dead, right?
We couldn't live that long, but five minutes at the most.
But these animals could live 10, 15, 20 minutes being held underwater, and they weren't breathing.
Of course, now they were stressed out because they were strapped to a board.
The bottom line is he started measuring all these metabolites in the bloodstream.
Lactic acid goes right through the massive amount.
I'd expect that, right?
And succinic acid is another...
So succinic acid is part of the...in the electron...in the TCA cycle, is a powerful stimulatory towards
oxidative phosphorylation.
And it was being dumped out into the circulation.
So it wasn't being oxidized.
So he claimed that it was amino acid fermentation that was doing this.
So the body was grabbing amino acids and metabolizing them and generating energy through
substrate level phosphorylation.
Well it turns out the cancer cell is doing this in a massive amount because they don't
have the oxfos.
So you look at cancer cells and they're dumping out succinic acid.
And succinic acid stabilizes HIF1 alpha, so you can continue to up the transcription factors
for driving fermentation.
So this whole thing is just a massive shift from oxfos to substrate level phosphorylation.
Does creatine phosphate fit into that SLP pathway or is that totally separate?
No, I'm not sure about that.
It could be a source of the phosphate groups, but I haven't looked into that.
Dominick may know a lot more about that than I do.
So when you go back to sort of...there's an undercurrent here to what we're talking about,
which is the view that you hold is the minority view today.
It sounds like...
Just...it's only...it's just a matter of time, okay?
Why do you think that is?
What do you think is the...
I know people want to come up with conspiracy theories and that's sort of one of the things
about social media that I find frustrating is people always want a conspiracy theory
to be the explanation.
Like, oh, the drug companies don't want this to be true or something.
I find those things hard to believe.
Do you think there's a better explanation for why these hypotheses are not being investigated
with the rigor that maybe they should be?
Well, you have to look at the discipline of the individuals that are working on the project.
Okay.
Most of the people doing cancer research are molecular biologists, which they are.
You have that perspective on the nature of the problem.
So you don't look at respiration directly.
You look at gene expression profiles that may be directly or indirectly related to that,
and then you make claims about what's going on.
So most of the people are of a discipline that says that genes are changed and not looking
at the actual consumption of oxygen and like, production of lactic acid, not looking at
what Warburg actually looked at.
Then you have a very different explanation for what's happening.
So a lot of people today look at, use the seahorse instrument to measure oxygen consumption.
And when you put cancer cells and tumor cells, normal cells into a dish, they're all taking
up oxygen similarly, and therefore Warburg must be wrong.
Warburg also said that tumor cells and normal cells, some will take up oxygen at the same
rate, except the tumor cell is uncoupled and the normal cell is not uncoupled, which means
that the oxygen uptake in the tumor cell is not linked directly to ATP production.
People ignore that.
So they just don't ... And some of the most beautiful experiments ...
How would one measure that?
ATP is very tricky to measure, ATP production.
No, ATP can be measured.
The problem is that what's the origin of it?
Well, that's what I mean.
Isolating ... So let's say you have a tumor cell and a non-tumor cell, and they're both
taking up lots of oxygen as measured by calorimetry, and one's producing a bunch of lactate.
But how can you tell if the cancer cell is taking up oxygen and not making ATP?
Well, if it's taking up oxygen ... Well, if it doesn't make ATP, it's dead.
All right, so-
Sorry.
If it's not making ATP commensurate with its oxygen consumption.
Well, sometimes you look at that and you'd say, well, look at the oxygen consumption.
The ATP production is commensurate with oxygen uptake.
Yes.
Okay.
That would be coupled, wouldn't it?
As long as it's not producing lactic acid or succinic acid.
Okay.
So I'm a bit confused.
Why couldn't it do both?
Couldn't a cell undergo anaerobic metabolism, make ATP, that is accounted for by the amount
of lactate that's produced, but similarly take up oxygen and in a coupled fashion make
ATP there?
That's an important point because a lot of people stumble on that.
The problem with that is that when you're looking at the ATP production coming out of
the mitochondria, it's not always easy to know whether it's from a coupled, generated
by a coupled mechanism where the oxygen is in fact linked to the ATP through F0 ATPase,
or whether it's coming from mitochondrial substrate level phosphorylation.
Oh, got it.
It's not easy to do the mass balance of this many moles of oxygen were produced or consumed
and this many moles of ATP were produced.
You can't do that math.
Well, Warburg did that, but he was looking at it.
But he didn't know about SLP, right?
Well, lactic acid production, the production of ATP at the pyruvate kinase is substrate
level phosphorylation, but it's cytoplasmic.
Yes, yes, it's not mitochondrial.
He did not know.
He couldn't have known because the very systems that were, they didn't come out until the
50s, 60s, that we knew that there was another form of ATP production inside the mitochondria.
What people have failed to realize is that they consider, every biochemical textbook says
we only get 2% oxygen coming out of the mitochondria through a substrate level phosphorylation,
just like we get from the cytoplasm.
But for cancer cells, people say, oh, we can get a lot more ATP from the cytoplasm, but
not thinking you can upregulate the same phenomenon inside the mitochondria.
As a matter of fact, we think that substrate level phosphorylation in the mitochondria
is far greater than the amount of ATP produced in the cytoplasm.
And that's because others, Cantley and others, a number of people have found that the PKM2
isoform of pyruvate kinase doesn't make much ATP.
It makes a buttload of lactic acid, but it's not linked to the ATP production.
So therefore, they have to say respiration is normal because the cell is making so much
ATP.
But if Otto Warburg is correct and all of the structural biochemistry is correct, the
cell can't be making ATP from oxfos.
It can't be because the structure of the organelle is defective.
So where the hell is all that damn ATP coming from inside that organelle?
And then when you look at the data that we have, and glutamine is being consumed in massive
amounts, so it's got to be coming from substrate level phosphorylation.
What is the fundamental structural defect in the mitochondria?
Which is interesting.
I'd never thought until this discussion about the possibility that you could have a completely
normal mitochondrial genome and just have structural defects.
And then of course, obviously you can have genetic abnormalities that lead to protein
productions that create structural problems.
But in the case of the former, perfectly normal genome-
Mitochondrial DNA genome.
Mitochondrial.
That's right, mitochondrial.
But you now have a defective.
What is the actual physical defect?
In the structure?
The number structure?
It can happen in many different ways.
For example, if a carcinogen enters into the mitochondria, they cause a lot of oxidative
stress.
And what we found in our massive studies- and this is how we got onto the mitochondria,
knowing that Otto Warburg was in fact correct.
I mean, at first I didn't know what the hell was going on like everybody else.
But when we found no mutations in the mitochondrial DNA, and we knew these cells were fermenting
because they were making a lot of lactic acid.
Then we started looking at the lipids inside the mitochondrial lipidome.
We call it the lipidome.
And we have found that cardiolipin, the signature lipid in the inner membrane, is defective
in all the tumor cells that we've ever looked at.
So that tells us right there that there's a problem in the function.
And then we link that to abnormalities in oxfos.
So clearly, lipids are abnormal.
That would affect the function of the proteins of the electron transport chain.
Therefore you're not going to generate the amount of ATP through oxidative phosphorylation
because the very lipid and protein structures are abnormal.
And you can't produce the amount of ATC.
So that supports what Warburg knew that there were many problems in the mitochondrial function
that would then force the cell into fermentation.
So what did they ferment?
They ferment lactic acid and succinic acid.
What are the fuels for that?
It's glucose and glutamine.
So glucose and glutamine are ultimately the fuels that drive the cancer.
And they drive it through a process of substrate level phosphorylation occurring in the cytoplasm
where they can build a lot of metabolites for growth and also through the pathway called
glutaminolysis.
Now, one can't render glucose zero, meaning there's no dietary or pharmacologic intervention
that could reduce glucose levels to zero.
Are there any that could do that with glutamine?
Or is it similar?
Let me address the glucose issue.
We can't get to zero, but we can get damn close to it.
So we have people, published papers, people who have gone powerful therapeutic fasting
only and then given large injections of insulin.
Sure.
And they've got to below one millimolar.
Yeah, 0.5.
But sustainably, it's very difficult to be below about three millimolar, right?
Right.
But here's the situation.
The problem is when you do that, you go on to calorie restriction, restricted ketogenic
cells, you already are lowering the blood sugar to a significant degree.
And what we found is that glucose transporters actually get upregulated in the normal cells
when you start doing this.
So the normal cells become glucose hungry and they become direct competitors now with
the tumor cell that absolutely needs the glucose because the normal cells can burn the ketones
and stay alive.
The tumor cells can't burn the ketones because they're mitochondria defective.
So you need a good mitochondrial system to burn ketones for energy.
So what we do by calorie restriction and restricted ketogenic diets is we make the
normal cells glucose hungry and we transition them over to ketones, keep them alive, but
they're still glucose hungry.
And they are now competing directly with the tumor cells that absolutely have to have the
glucose.
It's interesting because clinically we don't see that, right?
So clinically when we put most people on a ketogenic diet or a calorie restricted diet,
in the short run, they actually become physiologically quite insulin resistant.
Interesting when you challenge them with glucose, they have a paradoxical rise in glucose
and insulin that's overcome by refeeding them with carbohydrates for three or four days
prior to the glucose challenge.
And the offered explanation is that during a period of starvation and or carbohydrate
restriction, the muscles, which are obviously the dominant sink for glucose, basically become
resistant to insulin, not in a pathologic way, but rather in a way to allow the brain
to have access for the remaining glucose.
Well if you do it in acute systems like that, rather than the chronic changes that we talk
about, you can get those kinds of an effect.
Generally calorie restriction makes the body super insulin sensitive.
Yeah, it's interesting.
This is something I've struggled with because I was on a ketogenic diet for three years
and at the end of that period of time, I went up to Stanford and did an insulin suppression
test, which is along with the euglycemic clamp, really the gold standard for measuring
insulin sensitivity with Gerald Reven, the late Gerald Reven.
And Jerry was just interested in my physiology.
It was like, wow, you're kind of a weird guy.
You're on this bizarre ketogenic diet, hadn't studied it.
He did at the time have a publication of about 400 non-diabetic subjects who he had put through
the insulin suppression test.
The way this test works for the listener is you take an individual, you hook them up
to two intravenous lines, one that puts glucose in, one that puts insulin in, and over a six
hour period of time, you follow a protocol of injecting glucose and insulin.
And after about six hours, the glucose level reaches a steady state level referred to as
the SSP or steady state plasma glucose level.
And the higher that is, the more insulin resistant you are said to be.
The worse you are at glucose disposal, the lower that is, the more efficient you are
able to dispose of glucose.
And that number, the SSPG, correlates to the one over the M value, which is the Y axis
intercept on the euglycemic clamp.
So anyway, so I went to Stanford one day.
Why would you inject glucose and insulin?
If you were on a ketogenic diet, and you were to take glucose, your insulin levels would
already go up to the maximum physiology.
So you're actually giving too much insulin in a situation like that.
Well, so this was part of the issue, right?
We didn't know what to do because the protocol is all developed around people not on a ketogenic
diet.
These are all people eating a standard diet.
But what you're alluding to is what we discovered very quickly.
So again, this is supposed to be a six hour test.
And when you looked at, and I looked at the data before we did this to get a sense of
what the parameters were, of the 400 non-diabetics that they had done this on, the most insulin
sensitive person ended up having an SSPG of about 79 milligrams per deciliter, meaning
the lowest that anyone's glucose got following this protocol was 79 milligrams per deciliter,
which is perfectly reasonable.
And the highest was, I don't recall this, but we could look up the paper, but I think
it was somewhere in the vicinity of 200, 300 milligrams per deciliter.
So that's a person who is functionally a diabetic.
And even though they're quote unquote normal, their A1C was less than 6.5, they're very
soon to be a diabetic.
And of course, when you do this on people with type two diabetes, they're all very,
very high.
So we're doing this test where they're sampling glucose levels every 30 minutes.
And within an hour, meaning after just the first, second, third sample, it was clear
my glucose was going down very quickly.
So they said, okay, we're going to back off on the insulin to your point at 90 minutes.
And I have to go back and look because I have all the data.
I could be wrong.
Maybe it was a little longer than that.
I think it was about 90 minutes.
They basically turned the insulin off.
Now at this point, my ketone started to go down.
I think between the 90 minute and the two hour mark, it got really bad, really quick.
And my ketones at this point had gone from, I don't remember, somewhere between two and
a half, maybe three millimolar down to less than one millimolar.
And they said, you know, we're going to stop the test now because your glucose is in the
40s.
I believe I was at about 48.
Yeah, no ketones.
You're going to go unconscious.
You got to be careful.
Yeah.
So in the end, I almost did go unconscious.
And the last thing I sort of remember was the profound perspiration that came over me,
which is very different from the perspiration you experienced on a day like today in Boston
where it's hot and you're sweaty.
It's not that type of a perspiration at all.
It felt like I was in a shower and I began shaking and probably was about to have a seizure.
And then they went to...
So the last blood glucose I think they got on me was about 31 milligrams per deciliter.
And when they were injecting the dextrose, the D50, I was conscious enough to realize
the IV had infiltrated.
So all I felt was the most ridiculous burning sensation in my anti-cubital fossa because
I realized the dextrose was not getting into my vein.
Why you put yourself in a situation?
Yeah, no, I'm an idiot.
I mean, the worst part of that story is I would never do any of that stuff.
When I came back to life, I had a huge, huge infiltrated IV in my right, in my left anti-cub.
I took a picture of it and I sent it to my wife who I didn't even tell that I had flown
up to San Francisco that day.
I think I was just like, I travel so much that I could be gone for a day she wouldn't
even know it.
And I was like, hey, check this out.
And she's like, where are you?
And I was like, oh, I'm up at Stanford today doing such and such.
She's like, what?
You just about died?
And like, you got to...
If you're going to die, I mean, you're an idiot.
But you've got to tell me in advance where you're going to be when you die.
Yeah, well, I mean, our goal is not to try to kill ourselves, it's to kill the tumor
cells and make the rest of us...
Okay, so my long-winded story there was to illustrate a point.
I turn out to be an exception to that rule.
And I did this with oral glucose tolerance tests as well.
And I never had that physiologic insulin resistance.
In other words, I seem to be one of the people for whom what you're saying seems to be correct
chronically, which is whenever I'm on a ketogenic diet, my glucose disposal is remarkable.
But now putting on my...
Your insulin...
Your very high insulin sensitive.
My muscles become very insulin sensitive, but without the refeeding of carb.
What I noticed though is clinically, I see so many patients for whom that is not the
case.
If I do an OGTT, an oral glucose tolerance test on a patient in a ketogenic diet, I feel
like, and again, I think other physicians listening to this will have to weigh in with
their opinions, I feel like 70% of them fail the OGTTs and look like they have diabetes
or are very soon to.
However, if on the repeat OGTT, you just say, look, for the three days prior to the test,
you're gonna eat two potatoes a day, they pass with flying colors.
In other words, they show that they are indeed very insulin sensitive, but they need to be
primed a little bit.
So my point though is, if that's the case, if the 70% of patients or whatever the number
is, they wouldn't actually benefit from this effect, right?
Because they'd be walking around and not...
The muscles would be selectively not consuming that glucose.
Unless you can get the blood sugar down.
As I said, we're experimenting now, because don't forget, our goal is to starve the tumor
cells.
I mean, we're singularly focused on this.
The issue here is how you starve the fermentable fuels without causing...
Without starving the normal cell.
Or harming at all.
It sounds to me like you were brutalized in that experiment.
That's not what we want.
That's a not to be done at home.
That's not what our goal is here.
Our goal is to emerge from the therapy healthier than when you started.
So the question becomes, how low can you get blood sugar without compromising the health
status of the individual?
And again, if you're in ketosis, you can push your blood sugars down really low.
But you'd want to do this without insulin, because insulin itself is pro-tumorgenic.
Only if the blood sugars are high enough.
Once you get those blood sugars down and you take away all the glucose from the body or
the majority of it, it kills the tumor cells.
We have the data to support that.
Insulin per se is killing the tumor cell.
If you...
Insulin not, no, no.
Or the reduction of glucose.
The reduction of glucose.
So you're saying basically...
Because you can't eat insulin.
Insulin is such an ATP.
Exogenous.
But you're saying insulin does not function as a growth signal outside of its anabolic
activity in taking up glucose?
Well, if you have high insulin, like growth factor, of course, is linked to the insulin,
of course, that facilitates the uptake of glucose.
If you don't have glucose, what does it make any difference?
What else is going on?
Because without ATP, you can't get energy anyway.
So the goal is to deplete the sources of fuel to the cells.
So insulin, you can't eat insulin.
Now insulin drives the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex, which facilitates...
That's why they say, oh, you can get this and that.
That's only if you have a lot of glucose around.
Insulin becomes pro-tumorgenic.
But if you have very little glucose and you give more insulin, remove the...
It doesn't stimulate tumor growth.
We have direct evidence to support that.
So in fact, the Germans used to do that.
They used to put people into insulin comas.
The problem is you don't want anybody going to an insulin coma.
If they were in ketosis, you could give a shitload of insulin and you're not going to
die.
There's evidence in the literature to support that.
So you got to keep the door shut on that insulin, on the glucose, as tight as you can
without harming the rest of the body.
So we use insulin and then we do hyperbaric chambers, but that comes only after you shut
the door on the insulin, the glutamine.
So if you...
So how do you shut the door on glutamine?
The glutamine door, you have to use drugs.
And the best drug we've found so far is Don 6-Diazodiline, norlucine.
It's an old drug was made years ago.
They used to use it on cancer patients, but they never targeted glucose at the same time.
So the tumor cells were sucking down the glucose.
As a matter of fact, you can even make the more glucose sensitive if you take away the
glucose.
So there's no dietary strategy that could effectively reduce glutamine?
No.
Glutamine is a non-essential amino acid.
We make it from...
We can make glutamine from glucose.
I mean, so it's why it's called non-essential.
However, in physiology terms, it is essential.
It plays a massive role in the gut, in the immune system, in the urea cycle.
I mean, it's such an important amino acid.
It's ubiquitous.
It's the most abundant amino acid in our body.
Yeah, that's a funny distinction.
I'm glad you pointed that out for this is a total aside, but I'm sure that there are
people listening to this who get confused by the term essential and non-essential because
it's eight of them are essential and 12 are non-essential or something to that effect.
But what you're pointing out is an important distinction.
They're non-essential because we don't have to get them exogenously.
They're still essential for our survival once produced endogenously.
Yes, absolutely.
In glutamine, if you look, it's the most abundant amino acid in our serum.
It's everywhere.
And our immune system...
Yeah, so the point being, there's nothing you're going to eat or not eat that's going
to change that.
No, and people ask me that all the time.
It's got to be drug.
You got to do it drug.
And you have to use drugs, but it has to be done strategically.
And you have to have people that are knowledgeable about this.
You can't just have some guy just jack you up with a drug that blocks glutamine because
your immune systems will be compromised.
And our immune system is needed for the health of our gut, the health of killing bacteria.
And if you use, if you paralyze them too much, then you're going to get infections.
You're going to have all kinds of other issues.
So that's why we developed the press pulse concept.
So you press the glucose hard with diets and drugs, and then you pulse the glutamine.
So what we think is going to happen is we will target the glutamine with a drug that
will selectively kill tumor cells, paralyze the immune system, but then immediately give
large amounts of glutamine back.
And the issue, of course, is that you're going to restore your gut and you're going to restore
your immune system because they're only paralyzed.
They're not killed.
And when you say immune system, are you referring to the cellular or humoral system?
The cellular, mostly.
Because you've implicated, we're going to come back to it, but you've kind of implicated
the humoral system with the macrophage in terms of mutagenesis.
Well, we're talking about the cellular immune system.
Yeah, you're talking about the T cells.
And B cells and macrophages and natural killer cells, leukocytes, all these kinds of things.
They're all glutamine dependent.
They're all heavily glutamine dependent.
Okay.
So if you have a patient that's burned the skin, now you open up the bacteria, you have
to give large amounts of glutamine because the immune system is needed to kill the bacteria.
You have to restore the gut function.
A lot of the cells in the gut are glutamine dependent.
So that's why you give large amounts of glutamine to cancer patients that have been subjected.
But the problem is, of course, is the tumor cells are using the same fuel.
So you have to know.
And as I said, if you kill too many of the tumor cells too quickly, you've got to have
a cell system to remove the corpses.
You've got to have some...
And that's what the macrophages do and some of these other immune cells.
They'll come in and remove the corpses, the dead cells.
Otherwise, you get infections.
You die from the indirect effects of these things.
So you have to know how to strategically target glutamine without compromising the normal
physiological systems that we have.
So before we get into the therapeutic stuff, which I understand is probably what everybody
wants to hear about.
I still want to get back to kind of understanding some of this stuff a little bit better.
So experimentally, I'm still struggling with this sort of chasm in belief systems between
what sounds like the majority of people who take the view that says, look, the respiratory
system of the cancer cell is relatively normal.
If you're seeing an increase in fermentation, it's an artifact of a higher throughput of
substrate to generate more building blocks.
This strikes me as a very testable hypothesis.
We shouldn't be debating this.
There should be a set of experiments that could resolve that, correct?
Yeah.
And I think that diagram there on the board is the illustration of the strategy to test
that hypothesis, basically, which is where are they getting their energy from?
The bottom line is where are they getting their energy from?
If you stop their energy...
The board picture, by the way, we're looking at everything.
We're looking at the...
We'll put a picture of this, of course, up there, but it's basically the TCA along with
everything outside of the TCA as well.
It's effectively looking like...
It's even metabolic pathways that I can't name at this moment.
Yeah.
Because you have to try to integrate, like you said, you have to try to integrate all
of the knowledge that we have on the biochemical systems into a strategy to manage the disease.
And I break it down into more simplistic things.
In other words, energy.
Without energy, nothing grows.
And the evidence that I'm convinced about that I've read massive amounts of literature
and looked carefully at everything, the structure and function of the mitochondria in tumor
cells is compromised.
All right.
That's a fact.
That's, in my mind, that is a solid fact.
And to deny that, one would have to ignore the evidence that I've looked at.
You have to look at a mitochondria and say, no, that mitochondria that has no cristae
and is very few in number, there's nothing wrong with it.
Okay.
Let's call it white, black and black, white.
But let's go one step further because there's an objective way to assess structure, but
shouldn't we just ask the functional question?
Well, as I said-
Experimentally, I mean.
Yeah, of course.
And we do that.
So we know structure dictates function.
That's a common in biology.
Then if that structure looks abnormal at the electron microscopy level, at the various
levels, why don't we look now at the activity of the proteins in the electron transport
chain?
And just as this may be a naive question, but there can be large ranges of structure
that could still produce optimal function.
And you would think that for something as important as respiration, which to your point
might be the single most important function of a cell as evidenced by the fact that toxins
like cyanide are uniformly fatal within seconds.
You'd think that the structural leeway within a mitochondria would be so high that you could,
let's just say you could quantify structure as a scale from one to 10.
Obviously, a 10 out of 10 structure is perfectly functional.
You'd want to believe that that thing would function good enough down to like a two out
of 10.
And only if you were staggeringly compromised does everything go to hell.
So in other words, just to push back for a moment, one could argue, hey, yeah, of course
there's structural changes, but they're not functionally relevant because they're within
a parameter space.
Yeah.
No, that's an important point.
And I think the normal flexibility of ourselves-
Yeah, that's the better word.
It's the flexibility.
The normal flexibility is able to accommodate those kinds of changes over the short period
of time.
Mitochondria is such an incredibly vibrant system.
It's a living organelle inside of our cells, right?
It's a separate organism actually.
Separate DNA.
Yeah.
And they've turned over all of their DNA to the nucleus except for 13 critical genes.
And those 13 critical genes control the life of the cell.
Why should I do this activity when I can get a dumb ass nucleus to do it for me?
But I'm still going to hold the keys to the kingdom.
There's still 13 genes that if anything goes wrong with them, you're dead.
And this is the whole thing.
Why cancer cells don't die through the apoptotic mechanism?
Because the very organelle that controls the kill switch is dead.
The switch doesn't work.
So the cell bypasses the normal control of life apoptosis in the cell because the very
organelle that dictates that is now defective.
So consequently, this cell now is reverting back to the way it existed before oxygen came
into the atmosphere on the planet.
They were all fermenters.
They grew with unbridled proliferation until the fermentable fuel in the environment disappeared
and they all died.
So it was very clear what was going on before oxygen came onto the into the atmosphere.
Cells would proliferate unbridled.
It's in San Gorgi, Albert San Gorgi.
It was alpha period in the existence of the planet.
So everything was working on substrate level phosphorylation.
It was no oxidative phosphorylation.
They're all doing that.
What we have in our system today is these same capabilities, but we don't use them,
but only for very short periods of time under various physiological stress situations.
They don't become permanent.
In the cancer cell, they have become adapted because as Warburg said, you can't get a cancer
cell from a cell that cannot ferment.
So neurons in the brain can't ferment for very long.
You never rarely if ever get a tumor out of a neuron except neuroblastoma, which is
outside the brain.
So heart cardiac myocytes rarely form cancers.
Even muscle cells rarely form because you lose sheets and stuff.
So cells that need a lot of oxidative phosphorylation rarely can form a tumor.
Only tumors can form in those cells that can upregulate fermentation pathways.
If you can't do that, you're going to die.
But wait, wouldn't skeletal muscle be one of the highest candidates to be able to upregulate
fermentation given their ATP demand?
Yes, but they have a syncytium of mitochondria inside the muscles and they've adapted.
This is their part of the normal physiology.
They can ferment for periods of time under extreme stressful conditions.
They can't permanently do that.
They die.
The muscles will die on you.
The cells will die if you try to force them into a long-term fermentation metabolism.
But they have the capacity to upregate fermentation for short periods of time like many cells do.
But brain can't do that.
You're going to have a heart attack.
This is an interesting point you bring up.
Let's go back to a myocyte within my quadricep versus a epithelial cell in my colon.
To your point, the probability I will get a cancer that comes from the myocyte in my
quadricep is virtually zero.
No, and say virtually zero.
Outside of a sarcoma.
Sarcoma is, well, what's the origin of the sarcoma?
What kind of cell?
Depends.
It can be a myolio sarcoma.
But just humor me for a moment.
Probability-wise, the myocyte in my quadricep or my pecs or something forming cancer is
so much lower than the epithelial cell in my colon, right?
Yeah, or an epithelial cell in your kidney or your bladder or one of these kinds of things.
I just pick colon because it's such a high cancer probability.
Right, sure.
Breast is another one.
Yeah, right.
So what is it?
Explain to me again the difference in there because I would say the muscle cell is far
more adaptable at making lactate when it needs to because I demand of it much more
than I demand of my colonic epithelial cell.
But then say what you were saying again about the toxicity of lactate to that cell versus
the epithelial cell in my colon.
Well, the epithelial cell in your colon, if it becomes, and again, it's a longer process.
It's not something, you don't go from a normal cell to a cancer cell overnight in a colon.
There are some situations where cancer can happen much quicker than people would normally
think.
It's like it's a protracted process.
So the cell has to have the capacity to shift from an oxidative process to a fermentation
process.
You have to have the machinery in the cell to be a fermenter because without that capacity,
you can never become a tumor cell because the cancer is two-fold process.
One is the gradual chronic interruption in respiratory function coupled with a gradual
compensatory shift to the alternative form of energy, which is substrate level phosphorylation.
So if the cell is incapable of making that shift, it will never become a cancer cell.
It can't because in order to be a cancer cell, you have to be able to replace oxfos with
fermentation.
And if you can't do that, you're not going to become a cancer cell.
And that's why brain neurons rarely become tumor cells because they can't do that.
Brain cells die.
So if you interrupt oxidative phosphorylation in the neurons of our brain, we call that
neurodegeneration.
So we don't generally get tumors.
We get tumors from the glial cells and the microglia and these kinds of things.
Yeah, this is an important ... I mean, I know what you're saying, but I know the listener
will be confused by this because they're going to say, but gosh, my aunt had brain cancer.
It's very important that we distinguish between the glial cells and the neurons.
Right.
And the microglia, there's another form of which we think are the only ones here.
But when we hear about astrocytomas, which would be the most common brain tumors, they're
not actually ... The cancer is not existing in the neuron.
That's correct.
They're not neuro.
So these are the kinds ... Or cardiomyocytes.
Yes.
You generally ... Because you're going to ... They die.
These ... Because you're packed with mitochondria and you start ... They start fermenting.
They die.
They can't deal with that.
Again, see, that's the part, Tom, that just confuses me.
It's so counterintuitive.
I would think that if there's going to be a cell in my body that I want to be able to
buffer lactate and specifically buffer the hydrogen ion that comes with it, that's actually
what's killing the cell.
I would want my cardiomyocyte to be the single most robust cell in the body because it has
to be the last guy standing.
Yeah.
Well, this is the whole thing.
When you get a heart attack, you die from brain damage.
You don't die from ... Your liver and kidneys are fine.
That's why you can donate your liver and kidneys when you have a heart attack because those
cells are not dying because they have the ... Yeah, the brain is most susceptible to the hypoxia.
But the point is, even at the level of the highest stress, I would want my cardiomyocytes
to be able to access all fuels, glucose, fatty acid, ketone, you name it.
They do that with degenerative heart disease, but they don't form cancer.
They have a capacity.
This is where we found a lot of substrate level phosphorylation in the mitochondria,
the TCA cycle, was discovered in stressed hearts because they were saying, well, the
heart should be dead, right?
I mean, why is it still functioning here?
Where's the ATP coming from?
They found that most of the energy in the heart is coming from mitochondrial substrate
level for shorter periods of time.
I'm not saying you can't do this as a permanent shift, but the concepts were developed from
the work in the heart, but you would expect, yeah.
Well, same with my brain.
I mean, if your brain damage, you can't function either.
So, the two organs, heart and brain, are remarkably dependent on oxidative phosphorylation for
function, and disruptions of oxidative phosphorylation are usually catastrophic for those cells.
I mean, of course, after time.
I think I understand your argument.
I was thinking about it in reverse.
You're saying because the brain and the cardiac myocyte have evolved to be so efficient under
oxidative conditions, it's not so much that lactate is harmful to them.
It's that once you start to disrupt, if the hypothesis is correct, that it's the disruption
in the mitochondria and its capacity to carry out oxfos that's harmful, you die long before
you bother getting cancer.
Those cells get undergo apoptosis or just die.
I understand your point.
Yes, that's the point.
That's the point.
So, the key is that how long does it take to transition a cell from an oxidative phosphorylated
state in a cell that can become a tumor like a colon, as you mentioned?
So, the real problem that these other cells have where cancer is so ubiquitous, whether
it be breast or colon, according to this hypothesis, would be their metabolic flexibility.
It's their capacity to easily wax and wane between ... I shouldn't say it.
It's not their flexibility.
It's their lack of dependency on oxidative phosphorylation.
Well, they depend ... I mean, obviously, like you said with cyanide, I mean, it shuts down.
Everything's dead real quick.
But that happens so quickly that they don't have the ebb and flow.
It's their capacity to upregulate fermentation over time because it doesn't happen overnight.
It's a very gradual thing.
And heart cardiomyocytes and neurons of the brain can't do that, that these other cells
are capable of doing.
As I said, what happens is, again, you had that mitochondrial stress response.
And this is where your oncogenes come in now because the oncogenes are transcription factors
that upregulate fermentation pathways.
So basically, when you damage the respiratory system of a cell, HIF1 alpha becomes stabilized.
And now you can upregulate glucose transporters into the cell.
Is it glutamine?
They're all that overlap each other.
Clicacid dehydrogenase, all these enzymes that are geared for maintaining a fermentation
metabolism.
The transcription factors that make those pathways upregulated are the oncogenes, basically.
So the oncogenes have to facilitate ... If you're not going to get the same level of
energy out of your oxfos, you've got to compensate to get ... Because as I tell everybody, the
singular most largest consumer of energy in any cell is the pumps, these pumps that are
on the surface of the cells that maintain the ionic gradients that allow what we call
life.
Because once you reach equilibrium, you're dead.
So most of the energy in any cell, cancer cell, heart cell, and it's the proton mode
of gradient across the membrane that determines whether or not that cell is going to be alive
or not.
So you need ATP for that.
If the ATP dissipates, you can just swell and die.
You don't have to go apoptosis or whatever.
So you have to then determine, where's my ATP coming from?
How am I going to keep those pumps going?
So an fermentation becomes a replacement.
Therefore, I'm going to need a lot of extra fermentable fuels to make up the loss of the
energy that I'm getting out of oxfos.
So oncogenes have to turn on because they are the transcription factors that upregulate
the transporters for glucose and glutamine.
So you're bringing in two alternative fuels to make up the difference, and therefore the
genetic behavior of the cell begins to change.
And then because the cell is now using damaged respiration, you throw out a lot of reactive
oxygen species from the damaged respiratory system, and they cause their mutagenic and
carcinogenic.
So the nuclear genome gradually collects all these different mutations and defects coming
from the ROS of the mitochondria.
But at the same time, the cell is not dying from this ROS because it's being protected
by the fermentation pathways of glucose and glutamine.
How much of that lactate is leaving the cell and going back to the liver to undergo the
Corey cycle?
Yes, a lot of it.
A lot of it does.
Has anyone ever looked at patients who have a very, very high tumor burden and seen if
they appreciably have higher serum lactate levels?
Yes.
Blood cancers have been done.
In fact, there have been some patients who have had various leukemias where they died
of lactic acidosis from so much lactic acid being produced from the tumor cells.
There's a couple of papers reported on that.
Lactic acidosis from massive leukemias.
So the leukemia, the same thing, it's a blood cell.
They're mitochondria defective.
So they're thrown out a lot of lactic acid.
Although that's a confusing one because I could come up with another explanation which
is in very, very severe leukemias, you could also create multiple end organ ischemia just
due to the defective nature of the white blood cells could actually cause capillary damage.
That lactic acidosis could actually be from other organs.
That's true.
The tumor that I read seemed to focus on the lactic acidosis from the cancer cells
themselves.
But it doesn't rule out what you just said.
Yeah.
And I don't know how you'd quantify the distinction.
No, it's another one of these things.
But the question is, but you're right.
You can't make like a solid tumor seeing a lot of lactic acid in the bloodstream.
The Corey cycle clears it out pretty quick.
So you're going to be taking that lactic acid and making glucose again from it, which then
goes back to the...
Do tumor cells up regulate the machinery?
I believe MCT2 is the lactate transporter.
Do they up regulate that specifically?
Yeah.
I mean, it's up regulated and so is lactic acid, LDHA, lactic acid dehydrogenase A, which
converts pyruvate to lactic acid.
Oh, yeah.
Rather than B. See, most cancer cells do not have elevated levels.
This is why some people say, oh, cancer cells can burn lactic acid.
Oh, where are they burning it?
Oh, well, because they're taking it back in.
The cancer cells are burned.
No, it's bullshit.
If it can't put pyruvate into the mitochondria, it's pumping lactic acid, how is it possible
we take lactic acid, make it back to pyruvate and put it in there?
If it does that, and it's going to go up to...
You're going to store it as glycogen, glycol.
It's not going to be respired.
But do you know if anybody's looked at that and seen if MCT2...
I think it's MCT2.
Yeah, they're up regulated.
They're up regulated.
There's no question.
Because otherwise, the hydrogen ion would poison the cell.
Yeah.
So you have the whole thing is up regulated, monocarboxylic acid transporters.
They dump out and they also take in ketones.
Don't forget that same transporter brings in ketones.
So when you go into ketogenic diets, the MCTs are up regulated as well.
So you're bringing in more ketone bodies now to replace those...
There's an irony for you, right?
The thing that you use to bring in ketones is giving you the exit for lactate, which
protects the cell from the harm of the acidosis that comes with the hydrogen ion.
In the micro environment of the tumor, it's a real mess.
So some of the lactic acid is persisting.
The hydrogen ions are persisting until they can ooze out into the local bloodstream and
get back to the liver that way.
But otherwise, it's going to be a real acidic mess, which then contributes further to the
fermentation behavior of the cells, which then they're resistant.
So they're fermenting, right?
So they don't need blood vessels.
So this is the whole why the anti-angiogenic field has failed.
They said, well, we'll target the blood vessels and therefore the cells will die because they
can't get the oxygen and whatever.
But the cancer cell doesn't need that.
I mean, it doesn't need the blood vessels.
It can ferment.
Did you know Judah Falkman, by the way?
You guys were basically neighbors.
Yeah.
I know he came down here, he gave a talk.
You know, some of his...
He targeted some unusual kinds of cancers with his anti-angiogenic.
But Napoleon Ferraro, I believe, was the guy who started taking that all off.
And he even came to a meeting and said, none of this stuff is working.
Well, because the...
And this is why Avastin, as I wrote, you know, avoid it like the plague.
It's a stupid drug.
It was taken off the market for breast cancer because it was harming more people than it
was helping.
But they still use it for brain cancer.
And I think it makes...
Do they still use it for colon cancer as well?
I don't know of colon cancer, but certainly for brain cancer.
So what are you doing?
You're targeting the blood vessels and then forcing these cells to spread throughout your
whole brain.
So just for the listener, right, Avastin is an anti-angiogenic drug.
This was a Genentech blockbuster, right?
Bevacizum is the name of the drug.
And they still use it.
I think it's despicable to consider anybody using it.
I mean, don't they know the biology of the problem?
They would never do that.
And it's already been a bust in all the brain cancer studies that I've seen.
In fact, my friends have told me that work on this.
But it makes the...
Well, it's generally been priced out of use.
Certainly outside of the US, I don't think any third party payers would cover it.
And it's a very expensive drug.
It's about $100,000 a year drug.
And all it does is contribute to the invasive behavior of its tumor cells.
And all of these other things.
You're basically driving this idea, which I haven't wrapped my head around yet, is you're
actually enhancing the promotion of the hypoxic factors that are giving cancer some of its
selective benefit.
Yeah.
And it's forced...
And don't forget the cells that are invading, which are coming from disrupted microglia
in the brain, macrophages, they'll invade.
They already have the capacity to do this.
They live without blood vessels.
So you're facilitating the invasive behavior.
This has been seen on histological preparations, like brains that have been looked at after
Avastin.
They find tumor cells spread through everywhere in the brain, rather than clustered in one
area.
It's like they've just gone everywhere.
But when you look at the image, the radiographic images, it looks good because you don't see
the necrotic area that you would normally say, oh, it looks like it's like...
The image looks a little bit better.
You need to tell the patient, it looks like it's working.
But the overall survival is no different.
Sometimes it's even less.
It's a false image of what's going on.
You can't see the big central area.
It looks like it's very vague and diffuse.
And you look at the panel, yeah, it looks like this thing is working.
It gives the guy false hope.
Because the end result is look at the overall survival statistics and they're abysmal.
So I want to go back to something you said a moment ago.
You said macrophage, which reminded me of a point you brought up earlier, which I guess
I'm just not really familiar with, which was the idea that the macrophage themselves may
be responsible for actual metastatic behavior.
Yeah.
Can you say a bit more about that?
Well, this is a concept that goes all the way back to Akil from 1906 in Germany, where
he was able to show that in colon, I believe it was colon or melanoma, I can't remember
the tissue, he was actually observing fusion behavior between the neoplastic cells and
the cells of our immune system.
And then claimed that he thinks after this fusion event that these cells become much
more aggressive and much more dispersive than before these fusion events.
This was then solidified by the work of John Pollock at Yale University, where he did some
beautiful experiments showing that malignant melanoma is actually a macrophage disease.
The resulting of fusion hybridization.
This was then further established by Melissa Wong, her group at the Portland Medical Center
there, the Health Science Center in Portland, Oregon.
Beautiful work showing how in the colon, how macrophages were fusing with neoplastic
stem cells, forming these hybrid cells.
So the question, and we know that all these metastatic cancers are highly fermentative.
We know that's a fact, they're all highly fermentative.
And they're all very, very invasive and they spread, they migrate through the blood brain,
they migrate everywhere, they just invade.
And these are all behaviors of macrophages.
When you say fusion, so you have a neoplastic cell that is above the basement membrane and
you have a macrophage.
And tell me what the fusion actually is.
Are they fusing genetic material or are they just fusing cytoplasmic material?
What's actually happening?
Well, it's a combination of both actually.
So macrophages, cells of our immune system are extremely fusogenic.
They do this wound healing.
Like you'll see multinucleated giant cells in a lot of parts of our bodies during wound
healing and this kind of thing.
And cancer cells, you also find a lot of these multinucleated kinds of cells.
So our body recognizes wounding as an acute problem and the immune system will come into
that local area to facilitate wound healing.
And when the wound persists, sometimes these cells will fuse with each other and fuse with
other cells in the microenvironment to facilitate wound healing.
The problem is, is if you have an epithelial cell, like a breast cell or a colon cell,
that is coming and becoming neoplastic, becoming dysmorphic in its growth regulatory and it's
fermenting.
But it doesn't have the capacity to grow anywhere outside of that local area.
It doesn't have the capacity.
So our immune cells come into this lesion, if you will, that's persisting.
The immune cell throws out growth factors and cytokines to facilitate the wound, to
facilitate wound healing.
The problem is those factors are also facilitating the growth of the neoplastic cell.
So the neoplastic cell is dysregulated, but the very cell that's coming in to try to correct
the wound is now provoking the cell to grow even more.
But what is the wound that the macrophage is coming in to see?
Because the neoplastic cell has not yet violated the membrane beneath it.
No, but it creates a, it throws out lactic acid and creates a kind of a hypoxic micro
area.
Okay.
And it's a hypoxic because the lactic acid is a signal of hypoxia.
It's a signal of some sort of damage.
You're not supposed to have pockets of build up lactic acid in parts of your body.
So it sends out, and normally if this does happen, if we have a contusion or a cut, cells
of our, the monocytes mass migrate out of the bloodstream, go into the wound, clear
up the debris, kill the bacteria, and then move out of that section, go back to local
lymph nodes and sit there in the event that they need it again.
Or they pass, they form pass, they're all massive numbers of white dead blood cells.
So these cells are part and parcel of the correction of the wound.
The problem is in that if you have a colon lesion or a breast lesion from an occluded
milk duct or whatever, or a lesion in the colon, you have population of cells that will
start to proliferate, creating a damage to the local micro environment, signaling a system
that's immune.
There's something going on here.
Right.
So when the monocyte gets out and differentiates become the macrophage, goes to this now poorly
differentiated cell, why doesn't it just kill that cell non-specifically?
Because this is just a macrophage.
And how does that-
Well, macrophages aren't designed to kill cells.
They're designed to kill bacteria that may be in the micro environment.
Don't forget they're a wound healing cell.
But going back to the bruise example, right?
So you get a contusion in your thigh.
The macrophage does play a role in clearing that cellular debris.
Yes.
So why doesn't it just effectively do the same thing with the cancer cell?
Or with the soon to be cancer cell?
Yeah, because the cell is not recognized as being...
It looks like it's a part of the local normal epithelial cells.
Okay?
It's not looking as if this is a foreign invader.
This cell has all of the...
It looks like a regular epithelial cell that's proliferating.
Because don't forget we replace ourselves by proliferation.
But the lactate secretion, which is what got it there in the first place, wouldn't that
tell the macrophage, hey, something's still wrong here?
Yes.
This cell is hardwired to do what it's supposed to do.
It's not like thinking, oh, let me problem solve.
It's not a problem solving cell.
It's hardwired to respond to a particular environmental issue.
I see.
So you're saying the lactate is the fire alarm that got it there, but then when it gets there,
it doesn't see the fire?
No.
Well, it tries to put out the fire, but the problem is molecules that are used to put
out the fire are actually stimulating the growth of the cell that shouldn't be grown.
So it's out of context.
Okay.
So how does this facilitate metastases rather than just local advancement?
Right.
So at what point in this protracted process does this now spring to become a metastatic
lesion over a controlled proliferative abnormality that's not yet breaking through the basement
membrane or doing this, right?
So we don't know.
Sometimes this can happen very fast.
Sometimes it takes a long period of time.
Because we have these certain cancer cells called cancer of unknown primary.
They're highly metastatic.
No one knows where the hell they came from.
All right.
We don't know what's, but they're very highly invasive.
Then we have other cells that, well, he had a lesion there a long time for several years.
This thing never healed.
It was always oozing.
It was, and eventually explodes into a metastatic lesion.
We don't know at what point it varies from one person to the next when, now what happens
is when the macrophage, we know biology, there are fusogenic cells.
There's massive amounts of biology to show that macrophages are very fusogenic cells.
They can fuse with themselves or with other fibroplasts.
They can fuse with a variety of different cells.
Usually that's part of the wound healing process to facilitate wound healing.
But if you fuse with a stem cell that has already defective respiratory systems, you
would then dilute the cytoplasm of the cell that you fused it with.
It fuses again and again.
It's a process that takes place.
You eventually dilute the normal mitochondria in the macrophage and you replace it with
the abnormal mitochondria from the cells that you're fusing with, then leading to a
cell with dysregulated growth properties.
How many mutations would it take to do that?
We don't know because there are some metastatic cells that don't have any mutations, if you
can believe it.
Deep sequencing, they haven't found any mutations in some of these cells.
But they're fermenting and they're spreading.
They're growth dysregulated.
But wait, how are they growth dysregulated without a mutation?
You have cells that are carcinogenic, that are tumor-ogenic, that have no mutations.
Baker pointed this out.
It's like people can't believe this.
On the other hand, we have skin cells loaded with so-called driver mutations that never
form a tumor.
So this linkage between the number of mutations and the type of cancer is just ... There's
so many flaws in this.
So there are cancer cells that have been looked at that have highly invasive metastatic
and they can't find the mutations in there.
That's not common, but it happens.
So it's a violation to the whole concept.
In glioblastoma, there are some tumors that have been found that have none of the driver
mutations, none of the abnormalities that you would have expected that are found in
others.
So there's a break linkage between mutations.
You don't need new mutations to cause a metastatic lesion.
That doesn't mean that a metastatic lesion has no mutations.
But maybe I'm asking a different question.
Okay, so two women have breast cancer.
And for all intents and purposes, they have very similar patterns of mutations in their
breast cancer.
And let's just make it easy and say that they're hormonally similar.
They're ERPR-positive, HER2-new negative breast cancers.
Both women present as stage T2N1.
So they've got whatever, a five centimeter tumor if that's still a T2, I don't even remember.
And they've got two lymph nodes or one lymph node.
They both have a resection.
Ten years later, one of them is still disease free.
The other one has died from brain metastases, which were presumably seated before the primary
tumor was resected 10 years earlier.
It's not a sloppy surgery where they didn't get part of the cancer.
What I'm hearing you say is, yeah, one of them could undergo metastases while the other
one did not, even though their primary tumors looked very similar.
Is that correct inference?
Yes, yeah, I think that's correct.
And what we find now with a number of papers is the needle biopsies that are used to diagnose
the tumors can create a wounded, even a more aggressive wounded situation in the micro-environment
of the tumor, leading to the phenomenon of inflammatory oncotaxis, which facilitates
the fusion.
And in other words, by looking at the tumor with a needle biopsy to make the diagnosis,
you put that patient potentially at risk for causing a metastatic lesion.
And then when you look at the profile, you say, well, this doesn't look too bad.
No, not here.
But wait, let's say we do that.
We're going to immediately resect that tumor anyway.
So how is that, how quickly does this process take place?
The wound is between the outside world and the tumor, not between the tumor and the inside
world necessarily, especially if that tumor is going to come out within a few weeks, right?
Yeah.
We know from a number of studies that needle biopsies can facilitate in some patients the
invasion of cells into the local and spread.
We know this.
And reported in the literature for breast, for colon, for liver, for brain.
The very act of stabbing this growth can...
Well, but yeah, no, I think what's...
So then you can get the cells out in a relative...
Yeah, but I think what's known is that you can seed tumors along the tract of where you
do that.
Yes.
Yes, that I understand.
But maybe I misunderstood.
You're saying that a woman who has a needle biopsy of her breast, who then goes on to
get a lumpectomy, has that increased her risk of brain metastases?
Well, it wouldn't be brain metastases right away.
That brain metastasis, the secondary metastatic behavior, has taken a while.
It's not just the brain.
But how does the needle biopsy increase the risk of that?
Needle biopsy creates a more inflamed condition.
That's why you call it an inflammatory oncotaxis.
And this was one of the reasons why they get rid of the morselation procedure, because
this is what was happening.
So these women were dying from metastatic cancer, from morselation.
It's kind of a machine that used to be made by Johnson & Johnson for moving uterine polyps.
Well, you're taking a polyp and you're grinding it up and creating inflammatory oncotaxis.
Now, there might have been one polyp out of a thousand that would have this...
Right, but that's very different from the...
I'm asking a very specific question, because here's my fear.
What I don't want is anybody listening to this who's got a breast lesion, who thinks
now they can't have it biopsied.
I think that's a very different case than the example of...
Well, the evidence is clear in some cases, not all cases.
Not everybody who goes under a needle biopsy is going to have metastatic cancer.
No, but that's not the question.
I mean, what I'm asking is, is a woman, if you take a thousand women, you take...
It's a thought experiment.
You take a million women with an identical breast cancer and you take half a million
of them and you just do the resection.
And the other half a million, you do a needle biopsy to confirm the diagnosis, then you
do a resection.
Are you saying in the half a million women that had a resection following a biopsy, their
probability of metastatic cancer later on is greater?
I think so, but I can't be sure because that experiment hasn't been done.
I'm basing it on what has already been known about needle biopsies facilitating the spread
of the tumor.
But again, I'm just being critical of this because I feel very strongly about not causing
panic in people.
Well, I don't know...
I mean, these data are about needle track seating.
Yeah.
Well, needle track...
For example, like as you said, you have a liver biopsy, you can get cancer cells through
the tract even after...
But that's very different from saying...
Because that can be dealt with, but this is a very different...
Yeah, well, I think this is from what I'm looking at.
Now, I look at the brain predominantly, right?
How many...
We have what we call secondary glioblastoma.
And that is very...
It's not uncommon that when you go in and remove a low grade tumor, that within a shorter
period of time, it turns into a glioblastoma.
This is the same phenomenon.
You're just doing it on a little bit larger scale rather than just through a needle biopsy.
So you go in and you take out a low grade tumor and all of a sudden within a year or
something you've got glioblastoma, sometimes even less.
And you're saying, what the hell happened here?
So this is just a larger...
But what's the control for that observation?
Well...
Meaning like another explanation would be the person who has the stage one astrocytoma
is more at risk for the stage two, three or four astrocytoma.
From the operation itself, from the provocation of the micro environment.
But without...
We'd have to have a group of those patients who don't undergo surgery.
That's right.
And you would have to...
But who's doing...
Nobody's doing these experiments.
But here's the situation.
What our philosophy is that if we shrink the tumor, whether it's a breast tumor, colon
tumor or whatever, if we take away the fermentable fuels and shrink that tumor down, then it
becomes a candidate for complete debulking, not diagnosing.
When you take a needle biopsy of a breast and you look at...
Why are they doing that?
They're doing it for basically two reasons, to try to diagnose what level of cancer you
have and then to give you a gene readout.
Like these genes are going to play some role in whether or not you're going to get a treatment.
Right?
Well, yeah.
So those are two.
But for example, in the case of doing a biopsy before a breast resection, there's value in
knowing if a woman might benefit from neoadjuvant therapy, for example, based on the receptor
profile.
Yeah, but...
In other words, it might not just be the gene, right?
Knowing that she's ER...
That's true.
Knowing that she's triple positive versus triple negative might change what you do.
I guess it could.
But the bottom line is that why don't you assume that you have a problem?
Why don't you just put that patient on metabolic therapy and shrink that tumor down and then
do a non-invasive check?
Did the borders change at all from the metabolic?
And then just to bulk it completely.
The probability of cure is going to be better, in my mind, than if you do a needle biopsy
without doing the bulking.
And just to say, let's look at this.
How long after the needle biopsy do you put that patient at risk for possibly seeding a
cell that gets into a lymph node that then can spread out and later that you get brain
metastasis, liver metastasis, or whatever else can happen from these cancers?
So the question is, why put anybody at risk?
If we know we have evidence from the literature to say that is a possibility, why would we
want to put anyone at risk for that?
Unless the information you get from the needle biopsy is going to be a curative procedure.
And a lot of times it's not.
Okay?
It's just for diagnosis procedures.
And now today we're using all these gene screens, $7,200 to tell somebody what kind
of gene profile.
And that may no longer be relevant after you've taken a needle biopsy from the very tissue
you're doing.
Yeah, and I think that makes sense.
I guess I'm a bit confused by the idea.
I guess I just don't see the-
These are controversial issues.
And I'm looking at it from the point of the biological processes that are taking place
from these procedures.
And knowing that I've seen literature on lung, I've seen liver cancer certainly for
brain.
But here's ... So, I mean, there are so many potential arguments, right?
So you look at one of the most metastatic cancers of all time is pancreatic cancer,
right?
It's almost uniformly fatal.
And yet up until recently, very infrequently biopsied.
It's a very difficult biopsy.
Right, right, right.
You have to do it with an ERCP.
No, that's true.
In other words, you can still have incredibly aggressive metabolic cancers which are not
biopsied often.
And then conversely, you look at a GBM.
You look at the cancer we're sitting here talking about, the brain, a very aggressive
brain, the one that John McCain just passed away from.
Well, that's ... I mean, that's only locally metastatic.
It never leaves the CNS, does it?
Oh, yeah, it does.
Where does it go?
It goes to bone.
It goes to liver.
It goes to ... Nobody looks at the-
What percentage of patients die from ... Or-
Not many, but when they look, they find.
This was one of the big things.
This is how we discovered the macrophage origin of the cancer.
We started looking and saying, how many people do autopsies of organs on people who die from
glioblastoma?
And what did you find?
There's 100 articles in the literature with metastatic GBM to various organs for people
dying.
People say, well, it doesn't happen that often.
You know why they die the GBM before they start recognizing they have metastatic liver
cancer?
But when you look at livers and kidneys and these other organs from patients who have
died from GBM, those studies that have looked have found cancer.
So clearly, these cells are coming out of the brain and they're getting into the other
organs.
The problem is the patients aren't living long enough to have a problem.
Who's worrying about the guy's liver when his brain is starting to swell up from all
the treatments they're giving him?
I mean, 12 months, most people are dead.
But there's over 100 articles in the scientific literature showing outside, I call extracranial
metastasis of glioblastoma.
So it's not that it's ... And people ignore it.
It's like knowing that the mitochondria damaged in cancer cells.
People ignore it.
Well, I guess that would be a more forgivable thing to ignore because I'm not convinced
it necessarily changes the story.
The mitochondrial one is a much more interesting question, right?
I mean, that to me, of all the things we've talked about today, Tom, that's the one that
kind of has me scratching my head the most and wondering, in 2018, how are we even having
that this should be something that's not debated?
This should be sort of like ... This would be like debating whether DNA is necessary
to make RNA.
That discussion was settled in the 50s and anyone who disputes that now is sort of disputing
the shape of the earth.
So I guess to me, given the stakes here, I would love to figure out why people aren't
answering this question.
Well, let's look at the situation from even a greater distance.
In the United States, we have over 1,600 people a day dying from cancer.
This is horrific, right?
There's over a half a million people a year, 1,600 people a day dying from cancer.
Obviously, there's something seriously wrong.
There's something massively wrong with what we're doing with this disease.
We're talking about needle biopsies.
We're talking about this.
We're talking about that.
The issue is we had 1,600 people a day dying.
Why are all these people dying from cancer?
So it's either we have a fundamental misunderstanding of what the nature of the disease is, we're
mistreating it, we're treating it as something other than what it actually is.
So the debate that you mentioned now is that the results of the dead people are the consequences
of the fundamental misunderstanding of the process of the biology of the disease.
What I'm arguing is that now understanding the biology of the disease, we have the potential
to drop the death rate by more than 50% in 10 years.
There's no question about it.
If you stop doing half of the stuff that we're doing to these cancer patients, looking at
the biology and the nature of the disease, how to best go about this strategically, I
think we can drop the death rate by 50%.
We're doing stupid things, right?
Needle biopsy tumor cells for genetic profiling that has no relevance to the nature of the
disease.
That's just one.
But just to go back to that, because I'm sorry, I just really want to make sure people aren't
going to stop refusing their biopsies.
Have we seen an increase in the rate of metastases in the era of needle biopsying for genetic
sequencing?
I mean, we could go back and look at the death rate from cancer 50 years ago before anybody
was doing this, and it was the same.
Yeah.
Well, I think that we've probably ... I just want to say that every year we have more and
more dead people.
The increase is faster than the general population, okay?
So we had 3.8% increase in death.
I don't know.
Is that actually true?
Is the age-adjusted, population-adjusted mortality of cancer today higher than it was 50 years
ago?
I think it's about 3% or 4% lower, isn't it?
Well, I just did the last five years, okay, from 2013 to 2017.
But to test this hypothesis, we'd want to take an even longer time period and go more
extreme as far as like ...
Well, I mean, every year, there's no year that we have fewer ... They're always coming.
The dead people are piling up.
So when I look at the numbers and I say, okay, what was the percent of population increase
in the United States over the last five years?
And according to the demographics, it's 2.9%.
Okay.
Of the same period, how many cancer deaths ...
Right, but again, I don't know my epidemiology well enough to make this case, but I'm going
to try anyway.
Isn't the growth in population more a function of the input of people, meaning birth rate,
rather than the people who are getting cancer, which are the older folks?
Well, we have younger people too, right?
Right, but the majority of cancers and older folks.
Yeah, the majority of cancer or older folks, for sure.
So I'm not sure that that population argument would answer that question.
Well, maybe.
There's always a guy you can find ... I think all you have to look at is the numbers of
people that are dying from the disease.
I mean, that's a fact.
No, it's a fact, and it's a tragic fact.
I guess a 50% reduction in the mortality of this disease in 10 years is a very bold statement
given that we've seen about a 3% reduction in cancer mortality in 50 years.
Yeah.
Which I think you're arguing is unacceptable and understandable.
Well, I'm looking at it from the tragedy.
In China, it's 8,100 people a day dying from cancer.
I mean, that's the number over there.
Maybe that's the bigger population, but the problem ... It's now surpassed heart disease
in their country.
Clearly, it's not whatever we're doing.
And yes, 50%, if you did what we think you need to do and to manage this disease, looking
at it from the biology of the disease, I think I would not be shocked if we had a 50% reduction
in 10 years.
So normally, I ask people what their dream experiment would be, but I want to ask you
two.
I want to ask you this question twice.
The first one, the first time I'll ask you this question will be the easier one, because
it'll be the clinical trial.
So what would be the dream clinical trial to test the hypothesis that says we can reduce
the mortality of cancer by 50%?
What would you want to put head to head to definitively ask that question?
What we do right now is if we do metabolic therapy at all, we do it at all.
It's either standard of care versus standard of care plus metabolic therapy.
We're missing the critical control group, metabolic therapy without standard of care.
What are we doing to these people?
So tell me what the experiment would be.
Let's use breast cancer as an example.
Okay, breast cancer.
So you have your standard, whatever you're doing today.
You got a lot of people dying of breast cancer, metastatic breast cancer.
So we're going to now take metabolic therapy and we're going to combine it with standard
of care, which is what the group in Turkey is.
And how would you integrate that?
Let's talk about how you would do it, not necessarily how it's being done.
How would you, for the purpose of the experiment, integrate standard of care.
Okay, so we would use the chemo and we would have people on metabolic therapy, which would
be lower.
And you would do those in parallel?
You would have some patients that would be treated only with the standard of care, which
would be our control.
And then we would have people treated with the standard of care plus reducing blood sugar
elevating ketones and targeting the energy metabolism, which we can do.
And would that include things like metformin or DCA or other things like that?
It could include.
Hyperbaric oxygen.
Yes, yes.
And that's what we're doing in Turkey.
So it's basically standard of, however, in Turkey we're doing the lowest dose of chemo
that we can use to still be in compliance with the law.
And if you get rid of, now the control-
And now your metabolic therapy alone group.
Metabolic therapy alone group.
What would that group do?
That group would be the press pulse concept.
So we down regulate the glucose first, shrink the tumor up, make the micro environment less
inflamed, less angry.
Specifically tell me what would be in that.
So these patients would be on ketogenic diets?
First we would lower their blood sugar gradually, depending on the status of the individual.
So you'd go into lowering their blood sugar, elevating their ketones, putting them to therapeutic
ketosis essentially.
So a lot of these people also have multiple other series of metabolic abnormalities.
They have type 2 diabetes.
They've got triglyceridemia.
They have all kinds of other things besides having cancer.
So basically by bringing them into a state of therapeutic ketosis-
And how do you define that?
Is that defined by the amount of glucose and ketones?
By the glucose ketone index that we published.
We published the paper on this.
And what's the ratio that-
It's ratio about close to 1.0 or below, if we can get it.
This is where the millimolar of ketone and the millimolar of glucose are about the same.
And that people hit that somewhere between three and four, I'm guessing?
Days after?
Three to four millimolars tends to be the place where they're about the same?
It could be.
It depends on the individual because some people have higher glucose, higher ketones, and yet
they still have the same ratio.
So some people have very low glucose and not that high of a ketone, but it gives them the
same ratio.
So the issue is get your ratio-
The only time I've been able to be at one to one is when I'm not eating anything.
Yeah.
Well, it's variable from one person to the next.
And then the other thing too, we have to be very careful about, is a lot of cancer patients
very hard to get into one.
You're a young, healthy guy.
Guys that are young and healthy can get well below one.
Women are better than men.
We've done some studies.
So basically, but cancer patients are freaked out because they have anxiety, and anxiety
elevates corticosteroids, and you have a tougher time bringing your- So we also institute with
the press, besides ketone supplementation, as Dom DiAgostino has been telling, and the
ketogenic diet.
And then we have stress management, which includes music therapy, yoga therapy.
There's a variety of ways to reduce emotional stress.
And that's a very important part of the management.
You have to let the patient know that their disease is not terminal, that their lowering
of the stress is going to make the medicine and the work.
So once we get the patient into metabolic ketosis, now we have options.
Now we can start using insulin therapy to bring the blood sugars down lower.
We can put them into hyperbaric oxygen, which creates oxidative stress predominantly in
the tumor cell and not in the normal cells.
The normal cells are burning ketones that reduces oxidative stress.
When you say insulin therapies, do you mean actual insulin?
Yeah.
We're testing that now.
The Germans used to do that years ago, but we don't think we have to put people into
metabolic comas to do this.
We think we can do it without it.
We're testing it now.
So I'm working on it now.
As we speak, we have these experiments going next door.
So the question is, you don't want to use insulin therapy unless you're in therapeutic
ketosis.
You don't want to go into a hyperbaric chamber unless you're in therapeutic ketosis.
And then we would pulse with drugs that target glutamine.
And together, you're removing the antioxidant capacity of the tumor, making it vulnerable
to hyperbaric oxygen.
How much can these drugs lower local levels of glutamine?
Enough to slaughter the tumor cells.
But I don't know enough about this.
Is that a 50% reduction that's necessary to do that?
Because you're getting about a 50% reduction in glucose based on the therapy you've described.
We want to lower the glucose even further because you can do that.
And with ketones correction with targeting glutamine, it's got to be pulsed because
you can't chronically reduce glutamine to the availability to the physiology.
But acutely, how much do you lower it?
We can lower it quite effectively.
We can shut it.
And well, don't forget, the cancer cell is absolutely dependent on this fuel.
The normal cells get, they can burn the ketones also.
So they're not going to be energy deprived completely.
Whereas the tumor cell will be deprived energy completely.
Are there some cancer cells that preferentially utilize ketones?
No cancer cell can use ketones.
You have to have a good mitochondria.
A cancer cell that would have some oxidative capacity, a small amount of oxidative capacity
could burn some ketones.
But most of the most aggressive cancer cells can't burn ketones because they're mitochondria
defective.
That you need a good mitochondria.
That's why it's a selective, it selects for enhancing the vitality of the normal cell
while putting the cancer cell at a competitive disadvantage.
So the ketones are not to kill cancer cells.
They provide the normal cells with a fuel as an alternative to glucose.
That the tumor cells can't use the ketones.
And if there are many experiments like this, if you take cancer cells and grow them in
a dish without glucose and glutamine, just ketones, they die.
But normal cells don't.
The normal cells can survive on the ketones without the glucose and glutamine.
So it's very clear that the tumor cells can't use it.
And as I said, you have to have a good mitochondria to do this.
So we're selectively marginalizing these tumor cells because of their metabolic in capabilities.
But it has to be done strategically over time.
And where does the hyperbaric oxygen fit in?
Is that part of the pulse obviously?
Yeah, that's a pulse therapy.
And how much hyperbaric?
We want to try to replace radiation therapy with hyperbaric oxygen because the mechanisms
of cell death will be very simple.
So how many atmospheres?
We do it at two and a half atmospheres.
For how long?
Well, we were doing it for 90 minutes every day, something like this.
So it's designed to put oxidative stress, killing the tumor cells by oxidative stress,
the same way a radiation therapy would work.
Radiation a lot of times doesn't work because the cells are in a hypoxic environment.
So why are they in such a hypoxic environment?
Because they're fermenting.
They're blowing out all this fermentable fuels into the waste products.
Got to clean that all up.
That micro environment has to be brought back to a normal state.
And therapeutic ketosis, we published several papers showing that it's a powerful anti-inflammatory
therapy.
It makes the micro environment less inflamed.
It's pro-apatotic.
It's anti-angiogenic.
So you're killing all these bad blood vessels and replacing them with normal blood vessels
that the normal cells will be able to use.
So it's reconfiguring the micro environment while putting stress and killing tumor cells.
Now the tumor becomes more and more vulnerable.
And now it becomes more and more damaged by drugs that are going to chip away at the
surviving cells.
It's not something we're going to go in like a bull in a china shop.
It's going to be a gradual degrading of the tumor.
And where does the surgery take place here?
Is the surgery taking place before all of this happens?
No.
The surgery would take place at some midpoint.
The midpoint would be where the surgeon now looks at the tumor and says, I can take care
of this.
It's not going to be a diffuse mass.
It's not going to be an angry inflamed thing where you have to cut out half the guy's
colon in order to get what you think is the part of the cancer that's in.
Now this thing will be now much more shriveled.
We've seen it.
It's much less angry.
It's a micro.
It's more demarcated.
You can see it on this in the histological slides.
You can see what the hell happened to this tumor.
How come it's smaller?
How come it's more the margins are more sharply defined because you took away the inflammation
that was being driven by the fermentation fuels.
So you shrink in this tumor down.
Now the surgeon comes in and can potentially cure these people that would be maybe not
curable in the past.
So this is why I'm saying we can reduce the death rate by 50% if you view the tumor as
a metabolic problem rather than a genetic problem.
The gene mutations are all downstream epiphanoma.
They're red herrings.
Even Vogelstein, who still claims that this is a bird Vogelstein from China, he still
claims it's a genetic disease, but we're never going to cure the disease by targeting the
genes.
We're going to treat these patients, all this kind of stuff.
But we can do that with metabolic therapy.
We can actually eliminate the cancer based on metabolic therapy.
It's a process.
Who's trained to do this?
No one.
I mean, we need physicians to be trained to do this.
They've been used to train to give high doses of radiation without killing the patient or
poisoning these poor people with drugs that are very toxic and keeping them alive so you
don't die from the treatments.
This is absurd.
Why are you using radiation and chemo in the first place?
We have to stop proliferation.
Okay.
If they can't generate energy, they're going to stop proliferating.
They're going to die.
What is the experiment, the clinical trial that you're involved in in Turkey that you've
alluded to?
Yeah.
What we do, my colleagues in Turkey do, is they use chemo, but they use the lowest possible
dose.
Is it for breast cancer?
All cancers.
In fact, the results are the same.
All cancers are the same disease.
They're all fermenters.
Once you knew that they're all dependent on these two fuels, then all you have to do is
target the two fuels to put them at risk for elimination.
The question is, how can you target the fuels without harming the rest of the body?
And that's the press pulse concept.
So we know we can press things constantly without harming the body, but we have the
pulse, the glutamine issue, because we don't want to deprive our normal immune system and
gut systems of the very fuel needed to provide normal physiology in those tissues.
So this is why we have to pulse the glutamine issue.
How many glutamine drugs are there?
Well, there's some coming all the time, but the one that works the best for us is Don.
Are there any that are in clinical trials in the United States?
Yeah, there's a couple.
There's a name.
There's a few names of them.
They target various aspects of the glutaminolysis pathway.
The problem is we have a drug that's called a dirty drug.
It hits multiple pathways of glutamine metabolism, and it seems to work better than all the other
drugs, at least from our perspective so far.
Which drug is that?
This is Don, the sixth norilucine.
It was used in clinical trials years ago, but it was partially effective.
But they weren't targeting.
They weren't doing the full metabolic approach.
If you don't do all the parts of the problem, the horse is going to get out.
It's still not going to be effective.
And today, no one anywhere on the planet is doing the kind of a therapy that we think
need to do to make this all work.
Now, there's bits and pieces of it.
And then what are the drugs that are in current clinical trials that are targeting glutamine?
Well, there's a BEPTS, I believe, an acronym for another very complicated structure.
And then they're making Don analogs that are supposedly less toxic.
What we find is with the ketogenic diet, Don becomes far less toxic.
So you can actually use far lower doses.
So I was talking to somebody the other day, is it better to wait for a pharmaceutical
company to build a new drug to target cancer, or is it better to develop a way in which
a previously very effective drug could be less toxic?
And both of them, the end result is the same.
You're going to get something that's going to work far better than what was previously
available.
So how many clinics in the country, in the world, are treating cancer as a metabolic
disease using a strategy that will take away the two prime fermentable fuels for the disorder?
And the answer is no one.
No one's doing this.
But this trial in Turkey is doing this?
Well, they're not targeting the glutamine.
So they're doing these other processes.
So it's the glucose, the ketones, the hyperbaric oxygen, but not pulsing with glutamine, not
the anti-glutamine.
Not doing the glutamine.
Nobody's doing the glutamine.
We tried doing that in our Egyptian patient that we published recently.
We used chloroquine and we used EGCG, which is a green tea extract.
But they're not as powerful in the clinic.
Now that poor guy, he just passed away.
We were devastated by this.
We published the paper.
He lived 30 months, which is far longer than most people with a glioblastoma.
He was doing really well on metabolic therapy.
We pushed off the standard of care for three months.
So we did surgery after three weeks of therapeutic ketosis, debulked the tumor, most of it, because
you never get all GBM.
And then we didn't do...we were forced into the radiation therapy after three months,
even though the guy was doing remarkably well.
So this is a...so we said, why are we irradiated?
We have to, because it's part of the standard.
Even in...this was in Alexandria, Egypt.
And then a year later, he starts developing...or what?
Six or eight months later, he starts developing a headache.
His head starts to swell.
And they did the compression, the bulking, and they found, looked at the tissue.
There weren't any tumor cells.
He was dying from radiation necrosis that he took from the radiation.
So this is why I'm very much against it.
I think we're not going to make any major advance in brain cancer until we stop irradiating
people with the brain, because you're creating a bigger problem.
And this is leading to the demise of all these poor patients.
The survival after radiation is almost zero.
So and that's in my mind, it's becoming...it's doing in part to the radiation that we're
given to these people.
So whether they're dying from the tumor or radiation necrosis, they're going to be dying.
They shouldn't be doing that in the first place.
So the standards of care have to be dramatically changed in order to improve overall survival.
So when I say we can drop death rates by 50 percent in 10 years, we're not only dropping
death rates, we're massively increasing overall survival and quality of life at the same time.
So I have a lot of anecdotal information with people who have been treated with metabolic
therapy, part of it.
They're living far longer.
The quality of life is much better.
And when they die, they die in a very peaceful way.
And this, some of my clinician friends have been telling me this, these guys that are
on these metabolic therapies, the quality of life is really good up until about two
weeks before they die.
Whereas the people doing standard of care never live as long, and the quality of life
is horrific.
They're living there, they're in capacity.
So do you think that metabolic therapies offer the potential for cure or just another therapeutic
option?
Because if you want to reduce the death rate by 50 percent, there's no lead time bias slash
therapeutic extension that's going to do that.
That is a paradigm shift in cure, not treatment.
I think it's both.
I think you're going to be able to extend dramatically overall survival.
You're going to improve dramatically quality of life.
And how do we know if we're cured?
The issue is that if you die from a heart disease at 85 and you had cancer when you
were 50, a so-called a terminal disease.
No, I mean, I think we could pick something simpler than that, right?
If you are 10 years disease free, to a first order approximation, you're cancer free, right?
If you had colon cancer 10 years ago and 10 years later you die of a heart attack, I think
it's safe to say you died of heart disease.
Even if on an autopsy they find dormant cancer cells.
Well, here's a situation.
If you take standard of care and you live 10 years or like you said, and you drop dead
of a heart attack, was that heart attack the result of the cancer or the treatment?
You also have to put into perspective what effect does the treatments have on your overall
long-term survival as well, right?
So Dana Farber down here just opened up a branch of medicine called cancer survivor
medicine.
It appears that many people treated with standards of care are suffering horrifically from all
these other kinds of diseases they never had, but for the fact that they were treated with
all this toxic stuff.
So we would eliminate that.
Why would you, if you're in therapeutic ketosis and you're unlikely...
But I'm still like, what's the proof of concept that the metabolic therapy can lead to a cure?
So is your hypothesis that this gentleman in Alexandria, if he hadn't undergone radiation
for the GBM, your belief is he could have actually had a cure?
I don't know because we can't know, like you said, we'd have to wait 10 years to know that.
So if we were to institute an aggressive metabolic program for managing cancer...
But it seems GBM would be the place to do it, right?
Because it's, you know, it unfortunately is such a uniformly fatal cancer.
And it's fatal because of the treatment that they're giving these, this combination of
what they're doing to the patient as well as the tumor.
The problem clinically, right, is that the mass effect doesn't give you a lot of flexibility
to delay surgery.
So between corticosteroids and radiation, when a patient...
So most patients present with GBM, not as incidental findings, they have symptoms from
the mass effect.
So we have to be sympathetic to the clinicians in the conventional pathway who are saying,
I got Bob here, he's complaining, he's got, you know, hemiparalysis and he's got a GBM.
The idea that we're going to wait a month to put him on a ketogenic diet when I need
to either cut that thing out now or radiate him or put him on corticosteroids.
So in other words, this is going to be a very difficult thing to study.
Well, it's a judgment call on the part of the neurosurgeon, okay?
So he looks at the data, do we have a watchful waiting period?
This is...
I've spoken to many neurosurgeons, a lot of my friends.
I said, what's the stat?
What do we do here?
He said, occasionally, if you have brain herniation possibility, the patient will be dead in a
week, we don't do debulking.
That patient has to be debulked.
All right.
But you don't have to give them steroids.
You can just do debulking.
Steroids will shrink the edema.
Yeah.
Of the three, what would be the most evil in your mind?
Meaning metabolically evil, the radiation, the corticosteroid or the surgery?
Oh, clearly the steroids and the radiation.
So then it would seem to me that every GBM patient should go and have the resection.
And then undergo metabolic therapy, even though they're not technically going to be free of
disease.
Yeah.
I think this is the strategy.
How long the watchful waiting period is will give the neurosurgeon an opportunity to do
a greater debulking.
And there's a hundred articles in the literature showing that you live longer on debulking,
the more you can debulk the tumor.
So if we can shrink the tumor down, like we did to the...
On our Egyptian patients, we waited three weeks.
We put them under incredible therapeutic fasting, water only, 900 ketogenic diet.
They did a very awake, good...
900.
900 calories, kilocalories.
Yeah, but not water only, you said.
Water for the first three days, water only.
I see.
And then we transitioned him.
He did an awake cradiotomy.
He was done very well.
Then we pushed off the radiation therapy for three months.
And then they did...
And we didn't want to do that because the tumor was looking really good.
He had a correction of the midline shift.
He was in good shape.
So I think he suffered from the radiation.
I think he didn't survive because of the radiation treatment.
Do you think that GBM would be the best histology to study this in?
Oh, yeah, because it's the...
As you said, the survival is...
You're gonna see a signal if one's there.
Yeah.
And then I've spoken to a lot of my friends who think that, okay, we have to debulk immediately,
then we're gonna go on metabolic therapy.
We can push it off for two weeks and then do metabolic therapy.
The thing we have to do is we have to eliminate radiation.
I think radiation is the biggest part of the problem.
I think if you're doing metabolic therapy, you should eliminate radiation right away.
I have no doubt about this.
It's absolutely, in my mind, a problem.
And this is one of the reasons why there's so few people surviving.
It's because you are radiating this.
If you didn't irradiate, you could survive a lot longer.
I think with metabolic therapy, you can double, triple the amount of survival.
How do we know this?
Because those patients that I know who rejected radiation and chemo, took surgery after two
years or a year, are doing well.
They're out four years.
So clearly...
With which histologies?
GBM.
There are GBM patients alive at four years?
Yes.
Pablo Kelly.
In fact, I'm gonna be there next week.
He's gonna be sitting in the audience.
Is this published?
No, it's not published, but the guy has all the documentation.
It's just that it's not yet published.
Why?
Because I haven't sat down and wrote it up yet.
What would be more important than writing that up?
Writing another paper up that I thought the guy was gonna live just as long, but he gets
a radio...
No, no, no, no, no, no.
Look, that guy was one guy alive three years.
If you have a cohort of patients that have been alive for four years with GBM, I don't
know what would be more important than writing that up.
Do I?
I don't know of anything more important either.
But you don't forget it.
We should stop this podcast now, so you can start writing that up.
Well, I'll talk to it.
In fact, he's gonna be giving a lecture after my lecture.
Because that's really where you wanna be able to generate interest on a clinical trial.
So how many people?
He's a young guy, 25 years old.
He says, I don't want radiation.
I don't want chemo.
I don't want any of that stuff.
I don't want surgery, he says.
Oh, you're gonna be dead in three to six months.
That's what they told him.
It's all in the news.
It was in the newspapers.
I gave him the stuff on the metabolic therapy.
I didn't know he was gonna live that long.
I thought he was just gonna live a few extra months.
He comes back and he says, I'm still alive.
And there's a big newspaper article in the British newspapers about this guy who rejects
all.
So after two years, he decides, let me...
He had an inoperable glioblastoma that now became operable after metabolic therapy.
So they debulked it.
And now, after another year, he doesn't have any tumor left.
And he never had radiation.
He never had chemo.
He had surgery, very delayed.
And they did a histological analysis after the debulking, said, yes, you did have a GBM.
Because what a lot of people say, if you live that long, you never had a GBM.
You didn't have GBM.
That's bullshit.
It's just not...
I mean, you're creating a situation that leads to the demise of those very people that you
are trying to help.
And when you irradiate the brain, you free up massive amounts of glutamine by breaking
the glutamine-glutamate cycle.
So those tumor cells are sucking down massive amounts of glutamine.
And then you give the steroids to reduce the edema, which then elevates the blood sugar.
So I was gonna give you two experiments, two dream experiments.
So the second one would be going back to sort of the more fundamental premise of this,
which is, if resources were no constraint, how could one unambiguously make the case
slash test the hypothesis that despite structural abnormalities in the mitochondria, the production
of lactate and the fermentation is not purely for respiratory compensation?
In other words, we talked about this idea that says you can have a structural deficit
but still be functionally good enough.
How could that hypothesis be tested?
Because that seems to be one of the central arguments here.
Well, I mean, there's several ways we look at this.
If a cell can live with ketones without glucose and glutamine, you'd obviously have some mitochondrial
function that would keep them alive because they wouldn't be able to ferment.
But let's like, we're in a resource unconstrained world.
So what are the dream experiments that would test that in humans?
You have to...
I mean, in vivo, because a lot of these mechanisms would be tested in vitro because you can't
do those kinds of experiments.
But the metabolic therapy that we have designed, Dom the Agostino, myself, Joe Maroon, who's
the team surgeon for the Pittsburgh Steelers, neurosurgeon, George Yu, who is a prostate
oncologist, prostate cancer oncologist, we all sat down and we built this press pulse
therapy.
So if you deprive the tumor cells of their fermentable fuels and you kill and you essentially
eliminate, I can't detect any more cancer in your body, that's based on the biology
of what the problem is.
So the dream experiments are to ferret that out mechanistically in vitro.
So to prove that this is the case, and we're doing that right now when we target these
things, these cells die.
So you can put them in a normal cells wouldn't die.
So clearly what's going on here?
I mean, it was shown in many papers.
In fact, they're back in the thirties and forties, beautiful papers showing that the
respiratory system of tumor cells is massively compromised.
Okay, if that's the case, then they're surviving on fermentation.
There's no other known biological system in the world that can provide alternative ATP.
But yet most people don't agree with that statement.
So that's what I'm asking is what experiment could take the debate out of that very important
question?
If they don't believe it, if I look at the data and you look at the data and we both
come to the same conclusion and this other guy looks at the same data and he says, I
don't believe it.
Then it tells me the data are not convincing enough if everybody's acting in good faith.
Well then do you have to ask about what's good faith?
If I have...
Or what's better data.
Okay, look, here's the way I look at it.
If science is a human activity, okay, there are people who say things that are not true
and everybody believes it.
Right?
So I look at something and but I don't know.
I'll refrain from making all political jokes right now.
Yeah, right.
Right.
I understand.
But I understand completely.
But the issue here of course is that you have...
It's one thing to say, okay, we had a review on a paper that we know there's a massive
biology on the role of cardiolipin in controlling the electron transport chain.
I mean there's dozens and dozens of papers on this.
A molecular biologist, I don't believe it.
Well, what don't you believe?
What part of this massive amount of scientific evidence that you don't believe?
I'm unfamiliar with cardiolipin, therefore it can't be right.
Well, that's not the reason to discount the right.
And when you write the paper up, why would you not cite Pete Peterson's massive compendium
of evidence saying mitochondria are abnormal and you say mitochondria is normal?
Well, how does that jive with the massive amounts of evidence that say that's not...
What I try to do in all my writings, I never try to ignore an alternative fact to what
I'm saying.
I try to say there is a fact that I'm not yet completely clear about, but I'm not going
to ignore it.
You'll find in the scientific literature today in the top journals that they're ignoring
massive evidence that don't support their position.
And that's one of the problems.
And like we were saying that this problem in cancer, all these top journals, cell science,
nature, up to 50% of the article can't be reproduced in other people's labs.
This is a crisis in the field.
What's going on here?
So you're ignoring massive evidence that doesn't fit your particular mindset.
So you'll just discount it.
I don't think it's any different than the geocentric, heliocentric model of the solar
system.
The Catholic Church refused to believe that the earth was not the center of the solar
system despite all the evidence that said it was.
They just refused to believe it.
We have the exact same thing in the cancer field.
You have massive evidence showing that the mitochondria are structurally and functionally
dysfunctional.
I don't want to believe it.
What can you do about that?
What can you do about that when you have the evidence to show that and you choose to ignore
it?
It's slightly different than the heliocentric, geocentric system that we had.
The difference today is that we have 1,600 people.
Yeah, I mean it's slightly different, right?
But I don't want to get into details.
It's a fact.
You have fact.
Yeah.
And don't forget that you-
Well, but I think the Catholic Church was basically relying on a religious framework
as their counter argument.
Of course.
And so their belief system was formed by something different.
I think in the scientific-
Yeah, but when Galileo said, please look through the telescope to document the Copernicus
was right.
They didn't want to look in the telescope.
So because it would disrupt their worldview.
If you've just put the list-
No, I mean I think that's a fair statement.
I guess, again, I come back to this through the lens of I'd love to know what the experiments
are that could ... Because I view it as a stalemate.
If you're looking at a body of literature and they're looking at a different body of
literature and every time everybody looks at everybody else's body of literature, they
say, well, there's an alternative explanation for this.
We're making no progress.
The answer to me is collaborate, generate new experiments where-
That's why I think knowing the biology of the disease as well as I think I do, and we
never can know completely everything because every human being is a different entity or
dealing with a different entity.
If we can increase overall survival and improve quality of life massively advanced to what
we're doing today because of we use the strategy based on what we understand to be the biological
problem and the results support that, then I think that's the advance.
Glioblastoma would be a wonderful-
Speaking of that, realistically, when do you think that case report of these four years
surviving cohorts will be published?
I'm going to try it when I talk to him over there.
I'd like to speak to the very physicians that actually took the data from him, from Pablo.
How many patients are in that cohort?
Just him.
Oh, there's just one guy who survived four years.
Well, one guy because he rejected-
No, I understand.
I misunderstood.
I thought there were several patients.
Well, there's Andrew Scarborough who initiated a first couple of raids and said, no more
of this.
He took no radiation, no chemo.
He's still going.
He had a stage three astrocytoma, which is also quite lethal.
Then there's Alison Gannett.
She's on the news.
She has a website saying that she survived GBM without this.
I have other anecdotal reports based on what people have told me.
One poor guy, he had no money, no insurance, so they didn't want to rate it because they
wouldn't be able to rate any revenue from this guy.
He just did ketogenic diets way back before even I was talking about it.
He's still alive 16 years.
What was the...
Did they eventually do surgery on him?
They did surgery, but they didn't do anything else.
What does that say?
Again, these are anecdotal, but with Pablo, we have data.
We have clear data from him.
It's not like we don't have data from him.
We have a lot of these things people would say, well, you can't do this.
You can't do what I'm asking you to do because it violates the standard of care.
The standard of care should never have been written in granite.
It should be flexible.
If you have something else that comes along that might be better, you'd think there would
be an enthusiasm.
No, we have not seen that.
We try to get this through the University of Pittsburgh to try to do this.
The advisory board, right?
The IRB.
The IRB refused.
They would only might consider metabolic therapy after standard of care fail.
What's standard of care fails all the time?
Why don't you try metabolic therapy as an alternative to standard of...
No, we can't do that.
Why?
Well, because we can't do that.
Because we can't do that.
That means there's inflexibility.
We're up against firewalls after firewalls after firewalls to try to change the way we
continue.
We're doing all the gene screening, mounting to nothing because cancer is not a genetic
disease.
We have all these firewalls that are preventing us from moving forward the way I think we
need to be moving forward.
For a GBM patient, what do they have to lose?
There was a paper that just came out the other day in from out of British Columbia, Canada,
carefully looking at survival for GBM.
They said it's woefully similar to the 1926 Bailey and Cushing paper for Christ's sake.
What's going on here?
You mean in 100, almost 100 years?
John McCain's size is 12 months.
That's no different than if he had the cancer, than if he had the tumor in 1926.
That tells us we have a serious, serious problem.
And I'm offering an alternative that might be able to change that.
What is wrong with that?
Why would I be attacked for something like this?
Right?
So you tell me, I have to know what's going on here.
So I go up and I say, you can't irradiate the brain.
Oh, you've got to do it.
Here's my parting shot of advice, Tom, which is it's worth nothing, but your passion is
palpable.
I lost a friend to GBM.
So the very first person in my life that I ever knew that died of cancer, died of a
GBM.
And I was with him almost until the day he died.
And it was the saddest thing to see the last year of his, he lived 18 months and a year
of it he couldn't see.
So you know, talk about what is it like to be a 19 year old kid who can't see anything?
And I look at, it's actually one of the saddest stories.
I don't even want to tell it.
It's so upsetting.
Anyway, I get it.
I think my advice would be the following.
Whatever you've been doing, the phone rings, what the hell, perfect time.
Whatever you've been doing is not getting through.
You got to do something different.
So there's a quote by someone who's escaping me.
It's like the definition of insanity is doing the same thing over and over again expecting
a different outcome.
You got to do something different.
I don't know what it is.
If I had that advice, I'd offer it.
But I'm just saying, you've got to try a new approach to get that clinical trial done.
Yeah.
Well, don't forget, I'm a professor in an academic non-medical school environment.
So we designed the preclinical studies that allow the clinicians to then adapt it to
their patient population.
So this is what ... We're one of the only groups in the world that are actually doing
bench to bedside real research because I have tentacles for all these different clinical
things.
I get it.
All I'm saying is the current ... You're abutting a resistance and you've got to go around it.
You've got to ... You've got to go around it.
And it might be that you get enough of these case reports published that it becomes very
difficult to ignore and people would say, look, here's a concession.
We're going to do surgery immediately and then follow with metabolic therapy.
Because I think we're going to have a very hard time saying no surgery, no clinical steroid,
no radiation.
I think that's metaphysically not going to work.
No, no, no.
I didn't say that.
I said, no, no.
I know.
And if you're going to accept immediate surgery but delaying or postponing radiation and or
corticosteroid therapy until they are necessary either due to medical progression and or symptom
control, you have a chance.
And so of course the question then is you've got to find advocates on the other side of
this ledger, meaning ... But the ledger meaning in terms of the thinking about this disease.
Yeah.
Well, I agree with you.
And so what would you suggest?
What's the roundabout approach?
You're in the field.
I mean, you're ...
No, no.
A great discussion over that scotch that you promised me before we started this podcast.
It's easy.
No, no, no.
We're trying to do this, right?
Yeah, yeah, no, no.
I mean ...
And we need guys like yourself and others to get the word out that there are alternatives
and that who's going to be the bold one.
And I know I'm speaking to now people who want to set up these special clinics, special
kind of treatment clinics where we can bring everything under the same roof so you don't
have to run over this place and that place.
We take the patience.
This will happen.
It will happen because people want to live.
Yeah, look, I mean, that was going to be my ... If forced to give one idea now, because
I don't think I know the answer, but if I were going to give you one suggestion, it
would be do this from a position of pull, not push.
So right now you are pushing this idea.
What you really want to do is take a page out of the Charlie Foundation where they're
basically saying, look, in the end, the results were so dramatic that the parents of the children,
a third of whom now no longer suffer from epilepsy, another third of whom have at least
a 50% reduction in epilepsy, they basically become the voice of reason.
And I think that's a part of the reason today, not the only reason.
I think the data are so good, but I think they're a part of the reason why today the
only place in sort of the traditional medical view where a ketogenic diet is viewed as a
legitimate first line therapy for recalcitrant disease is in epilepsy.
Now, I think there will be a day when that expands.
So what I would hope is that there's a network of people, family members probably, who have
lost people to GBM, who would become the ones that would be your mouthpiece, right?
Would become the ones that would say, you know what?
I'm tired of the fact that my loved one died in nine months, seemingly in vain.
And there's this body of evidence, which look, admittedly at this point is small and is uncertain,
but nothing in science is certain, but they're offering an alternative.
I want to know that that could be tested.
Yeah.
And the thing that kills me on these private foundations and things, their advisory boards
are made up of physicians that subscribe to the gene theory of cancer.
So when the patients and their advocates hear about this-
Here's my second piece of advice.
I know I said I wasn't going to give you any advice.
My second piece of advice is you're fighting an uphill battle.
You don't need to.
It could be a genetic disease and a metabolic disease simultaneously.
I would argue that cancer is, when you think about the three diseases, the three disease
processes that are going to kill all of us sitting here right now in this room, it's
going to be atherosclerotic disease, neurodegenerative disease, or cancer.
Statistically speaking, that's how we're going to die.
Of those three, I don't think there's any that are more evolved and complicated than
cancer.
I think cancer is by far the hardest of those.
And therefore-
Well, now, there's where I would disagree strongly.
Well, but that's too long a discussion.
The point is, whether you agree with me or not, let's argue the following, or let me
state the following and or posit the following.
It's a very evolved condition, and therefore you could have genetic pressures, metabolic
pressures, immune pressures that all predispose to it.
So I don't think it has to be an either or.
I think metabolic therapies could be valuable whether or not the genetic ideas of cancer
are right or wrong.
So to me, it strikes me as an unnecessary fight.
Instead, the answer should be, look, we should have medical oncologists, radiation oncologists,
surgical oncologists, immuno-oncologists, and metabolic oncologists.
Period.
Now, you might argue those radiation oncologists are causing more harm than good.
That's beyond my pay grade.
You might be right.
But you're basically arguing for a fifth branch of oncology, which is the medical oncologist,
above the three that we conventionally have.
I think the immuno-oncologist is coming into his or her own right now.
I don't think it's worth arguing about whether it's a genetic disease or metabolic disease.
It's just a goddamn hard disease, and we need every therapy imaginable, and sometimes that
will be doing things that are completely new as you've proposed.
So anyway, on that note, I want to thank you very much for your generosity of time and just
your passion for this and how tirelessly you've worked on this.
This is only our first time meeting today, Tom, but I've been familiar with your work
for probably eight years now, which is a small fraction of the amount of time you've put
into this.
Dom is a very close friend, and so through Dom and through Bob, I've learned a lot more
about your work.
I know that a lot of people listening to this are going to be rooting for you to do this.
Is there anything that someone who's listening to this, who's got a loved one, who's either
died of GBM or has GBM, that they can do to increase the chances that either others
can get the types of therapies you're talking about in clinical trials or that their loved
ones themselves can?
What else can they do?
Well, I mean, in my position as a researcher who does the preclinical studies, I mean,
we get support from Travis from Foundation, the Metabolic Therapy Foundation, and that's
what keeps our program going, and that's what tells us what we think should work really
well or what might not work to help these people get the outcome that they want, which
is high quality of life and living a lot longer.
My big thing is that, is we can identify those, and where do you do that?
You need funds for that.
The federal government is mostly like what gene is involved.
So this is where it comes back to the same problem again.
You don't get funding for things that actually can really work versus studying the disease.
Let's look at the meta ... Let's study the disease more.
We don't need that.
We know we have a path.
We have a clear-
So is there an easy path for patients who want to make financial contributions to the
lab?
Is it through a foundation that is the easiest way?
Yeah, well, there's two ways to do it.
You could either do it through the foundation because we have a continual grant set up through
single cost, single cure foundation.
Okay.
So we'll link to that to make sure that people know what that is.
And also at Boston College, if you want to fund the work directly through the university,
it has to be through a very specific statement.
Okay.
Otherwise, the university will-
Absorb it.
Absorb some of the other funds.
So basically, that's the way ... Now, what we do then is our data are immediately given
to the clinical people who then put it on their patients and then feed me back and say,
this is working well, or we don't think this is doing as well as we should.
Why don't you tweak it in this direction?
So I work with the physicians directly and I give them the preclinical information.
They feed me back and see how it's working.
Sometimes it works a hell of a lot better in the human than the mouse.
So let's be sure that we have from you any and all means that people who are passionate
about this, interested in this, either personally or through indirect experience can support
this work.
And more importantly, I think, create maybe a bit of a groundswell that puts a little
bit of pressure on the IRBs to say, look, this is ... GBM is as high stakes as it gets.
It's the type of cancer that gives cancer a bad name.
And maybe this is one area where we have to increase our appetite for risk in clinical
trials.
I agree with that.
And I think that this is a disease that we think we can make major advances in and why
not give it a shot?
Because it's not going to hurt anybody.
It's not going to accelerate their demise.
It's only going to-
I would disagree with that only in terms of a talking point to say it could.
We don't know.
But that's the point of risk, right?
When the outcome is so asymmetrically bad, which is uniform death in an accelerated fashion,
we have to be willing to take the risk of potentially doing worse than that.
I don't think that's the case.
I've never seen it.
Understood.
But I think the way we talk about this, when we talk about this as though there's no risk,
I think that reduces our credibility with people who say, well, how can you say that?
Any open cranial surgery produces risk.
Yeah, that's the point.
And that's going to be a part of all what we're doing.
Well, the point is, Bob's heard me rail on this many a time.
This is sort of idiotic idea of a Hippocratic oath, which is technically he didn't even
say it and it's such a dumb thing anyway.
First do no harm.
I mean, you couldn't do any good if you weren't at least willing to do some harm.
No one goes into it wanting to do harm.
But anyway, this has been really exciting and I really appreciate your time and your
insights and above all else the work you've done.
So thank you, Tom.
Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com.
What's a nerd safari you ask?
Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week
email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social you can find me on Twitter, Instagram and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the
practice of medicine, nursing or other professional healthcare services, including the giving
of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own
risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical
advice, diagnoses or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they
have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously.
For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash about.