Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hi, everybody.
Welcome to today's episode of The Drive.
My guest today is my good friend Navdeep, or Nav as we like to call him, Chandel.
Nav is a professor of medicine and cell and molecular biology at Northwestern in Chicago,
which is where I actually met him to do this interview.
Some of you may recall that name because Nav is one of the cast of characters that I went
to Easter Island with in the fall of 2016, the other being David Sabatini and Tim Ferriss.
And we actually spoke about this stuff at length on a podcast that Tim recorded while
we were on Easter Island.
Nav's real area of expertise is in the mitochondria and in metabolism.
And in fact, he wrote a book called Navigating Metabolism, no pun intended, in 2015, which
I highly recommend for anybody, especially people who A, want to understand this stuff
and B, don't want to have to buy 17 textbooks and get into every unearthly detail.
In fact, this book was written more for a general audience than a very specific audience.
And I have a copy of it and love it.
In this episode, we talk about a bunch of stuff, but we talk about what got Nav interested
in the mitochondria.
We get into Ross or reactive oxygen species, something that I think many of you will have
heard of.
And then we talk about some really nuanced stuff like this stuff about mitochondria being
actual signaling organelles and Ross maybe being beneficial for that signaling.
In other words, we get into this idea that reactive oxygen species may not be all bad.
It might not be a black white thing, which anyone who listened to this podcast realized
we love to explore things that aren't just binary.
We talk about antioxidants and whether they're harmful or not harmful.
And I suspect that a lot of people will have a point of view on that.
And we get into mitochondrial DNA, which in and of itself is super interesting because
some of you may already know this.
And if you don't, that's fine.
You'll learn it on this episode.
But the mitochondria have their own DNA distinct from the cell.
And that DNA is of bacterial origin.
It's also transmitted to us maternally.
So there's a whole bunch of weird stuff going on genetically with the mitochondria that
makes it super interesting.
We get into a little bit of a discussion around cortisol.
Nav is super interested in the role of cortisol in health.
And then we talk, of course, about metformin.
And I suspect that for some people listening to this, that's the only thing they're going
to care about because these days everybody's asking me about metformin, which means it's
front and center on a lot of people's minds with respect to longevity.
Now we don't even go as deep as we could on metformin.
I'm saving that for another guest that's in the queue who I'm not going to even say too
much about that, but there's a lot more coming on metformin.
This however, will be a great primer for that because you'll certainly understand how metformin
works and how it may play a role in longevity.
We talk about the role of the mitochondria in cancer.
And again, we take a different view here from what you will have heard from other guests
potentially.
We talk about NAD and NAD precursors.
And that again is another thing that people I think are pretty excited about.
At the end, somehow Nav jiu-jitsu's me and turns the tables on me and asks me the, so
what should I eat question, which anybody who knows me knows.
I can't stand being asked that question, but because it's Nav, I humored him a little
bit.
Before we jump into that, please keep in mind we have an email list every Sunday morning
I send out an email and that email has a whole bunch of stuff in it.
It's usually pretty short though, but it's basically something I've read that's interesting
that pertains to longevity, science, lipidology, performance, or just something that really
interests me beyond those things.
Keep in mind we put, I would say an ungodly amount of effort into preparing show notes.
And when I say we, I'm using that term very liberally.
I actually do none of that, but I have a team that does that and that is spearheaded by
Travis and Bob.
So the people who do spend time on those show notes always come back to us with feedback
like this is freaking awesome.
Please keep doing this.
And our intention is to keep doing that.
So give us a reason to keep doing that by going and checking them out, especially when
it comes to understanding some of the technical stuff that we talk about here and getting
some of the references.
And lastly, if you are digging this podcast, please head over to Apple podcast reviews
and leave us a review, especially if it's positive, but if it's negative, at least have
the courtesy to give us some constructive feedback so we can improve upon whatever it
is you don't like.
So without anything further to add, please welcome Nav Chandale.
Hey Nav, good to see you again, man.
Great to see you Peter.
The last time I saw you, me, you and David Sabatini were hanging out near the airport
in San Diego playing patty cakes.
You guys were drinking some really lame stuff.
Oh, Rosé's.
Rosé.
I like sparkling stuff.
So what got you interested in mitochondria?
So when I was in college, I was a math major.
I loved math, right?
I probably did math because as an immigrant, you moved from the Himalayas to Miami, got
a funny accent.
Math.
He's a universal language, right?
So I became a math geek, but everybody's got to make a living.
And so I worked in a laboratory, which was in a hospital and it was a transplant laboratory.
And the biggest thing in transplant is how do you preserve organs?
I mean, you have an MD, I don't have an MD.
I think that's a fair statement.
And there's this Wisconsin solution that was used to...
We used it liberally.
And so I wanted to make a better version of it as a 19 year old.
And if you've got to do that, then you've got to think about metabolism.
The first set of experiments we did, and I went to a FASIP meeting and it's called three
phosphoglycerate protects against anoxia injury of hepatocytes.
Anoxia is low oxygen, the absence of oxygen.
And then that got me interested in metabolism.
If you're a mathematician and you start working metabolism and eventually like mitochondria,
it's electrons, it's enzyme kinetics, right?
There's math.
And in fact, my PhD is on enzyme kinetics.
And so I'm doing a PhD on an enzyme that's very critical for respiration.
So like the enzyme that uses oxygen in every cell is what I did my PhD on and how that
enzyme works under different oxygen levels.
Again, lots of math.
And then Michaelis-Menten, but much more sophisticated enzyme kinetics.
And then after that, the thing that was probably the most influential discovery in the mitochondria
field for me, and I still think this is one of the three greatest discoveries in the mitochondria
field, of course, it'll be contentious because lots of people might take issue with it.
So the first one is Hans Krebs in the TCA cycle in 37.
There's the 60 paper by Peter Mitchell, how you make ATP.
So those are the two big things, right?
C, bioenergetics and biosynthesis, because the Krebs cycle eventually makes carbon molecules,
which are the backbone for lipids, nucleotides, amino acids.
The third big experiment came out in 1996.
So Xiaodong Wang, when he was at Emory, found that the protein that I used every single
day to do enzyme kinetics.
So I worked on cytochrome C oxidase.
That's an enzyme.
Everybody tells you cytochrome C oxidase means that it uses cytochrome C as a substrate.
Let's take a step back for someone who's going to be listening to this who doesn't know everything
about it.
Before we get to Wang's experiment, tell us who Hans Krebs, what he did, what the TCA
is.
A lot of people will think, I kind of remember this from high school biology, but give me
a quick refresher course.
So I'll prime you a little bit for it.
A cell brings glucose in just to make it easy.
It turns glucose through a number of steps, enzymatic steps, into two smaller three carbon
units called pyruvate.
Assuming the demand for ATP is not extraordinary and there's sufficient cellular oxygen, what
would be the most efficient way to get energy out of that?
Pyruvate has two choices.
It can either become lactate, and usually that happens when there's not enough oxygen.
All right.
The other thing I always like to say to people, and or when the demand for ATP is exceptional.
But the other place where it really goes is pyruvate goes into what's called the TCA cycle.
And it's really a cycle.
So where glycolysis is a series of linear steps, A, B, C, D, E, then you get to pyruvate,
and pyruvate actually goes in a circular fashion.
And this occurs in a part of the cell called the cytoplasm.
The glycolysis part does, but the TCA happens in the mitochondria.
Which we're going to get to.
So pyruvate to lactate is all in the cytoplasm, but pyruvate then gets imported through a
pyruvate mitochondrial pyruvate carrier.
And that's important because it could be a target therapeutically in certain diseases.
I think most of us appreciate, and this is what you're getting to while you're focusing
on pyruvate, pyruvate has two choices.
Go to lactate or the mitochondria.
So clearly, the pyruvate to lactate is cytoplasm.
It going into the mitochondria and eventually becoming acetyl-CoA, that's an important reaction.
So where pyruvate goes and how it gets in and out is quite important.
And discovery of that transporter gives you a way to maybe target that.
So now pyruvate's in the mitochondria.
It's in the mitochondria.
And then it's a three carbon, and it becomes acetyl-CoA.
Acetyl-CoA is very important, and we can get into it later.
Because acetyl-CoA can acetylate.
To acetylate, the eight means you put it on, basically.
Ace is an enzyme.
It's the end of an enzyme.
Take it off.
And then it goes to the TCA cycle.
Which stands for?
So some people call it the Krebs cycle because Hans Krebs discoveries, I'm going to try carboxylic
acid cycle.
Some people call it the citric acid cycle.
So we'll use those interchangeably.
And so the TCA cycle, as it's going in the mitochondria, it generates NADH and FADH.
These are these reducing equivalents which then feed electrons to the electron transport
chain.
And the electron transport chain can pump protons, which is basically like a battery,
to generate ATP, which is the currency that makes cellular functions work.
So the way I like to explain this to people, because I think it's such, it's just so damn
elegant.
You look at a piece of food, and all you see is this potential energy.
You see, and of course, within all the bonds that exist in food, which is where we get
our energy from, you have carbon-carbon bonds, carbon-hydrogen bonds, carbon-nitrogen bonds,
carbon-oxygen, nitrogen-oxygen.
I mean, there's only a finite number of covalent bonds that exist.
But the two most energy dense, I think, are carbon-carbon and carbon-hydrogen, correct?
Isn't that where the majority of the chemical energy is liberated?
Those electrons have to eventually be accepted by something, right?
And oxygen is the final acceptor of all of those.
So in some sense, the whole purpose of eating is to take a potential energy that is in a
chemical form, turn it into an electrical potential energy inside the mitochondria,
and then eventually pull a little jiu-jitsu and turn that back into a chemical electrical
energy via the conversion of ADP to ATP.
I mean, to me, that's the simplest way to explain this.
It's just like a battery, right?
Yeah.
It's kind of amazing that we exist.
Well, that's why they call it a power plant.
What is the, you know, in the public domain, what do people call mitochondria?
The power plant of the cell.
Power house, power plant, right?
And for exactly the elegant explanation you just gave.
So we're already talking about the dogma, right?
Which is, it's all about ATP.
So if you asked in 1996, what is the major function of mitochondria?
Make ATP.
That's it.
And for good reason, because let's call us bade to spade.
As we know, if you interrupt that cycle for even moments, it's uniformly fatal.
Most people are familiar with a toxin called cyanide.
Cyanide is fatal at incredibly low concentration.
There are only a handful of toxins that are more potent, more lethal at lower concentrations.
And they all tend to, you know, like the trytotoxin, I think, blocks a sodium channel transporter.
It might be even more lethal.
But why cyanide is so lethal is it disrupts that process you just described.
Indeed.
But it's not clear which organ fails right away.
So we'll get into that in a second.
The genetic experiments don't totally confirm that idea.
Interesting.
I'd like to hear more about this.
Let's get into that in a little bit.
So in 1996, if you ask that question, it's all about ATP.
And so there is this protein, cytochrome C, that's part of this energy generating system,
which is ATP.
And Xiaodong Wang and colleagues found that if that protein gets released from mitochondria
into the cytoplasm, which had never been detected before, it can rapidly kill a cell.
So now the decision for life and death is based on the localization of cytochrome C
between the mitochondria and into the cytoplasm.
So if it's in the mitochondria, it helps you generate ATP.
If it's out, it kills you.
And I assume it only escapes when the mitochondria is under the most intense duress and destruction.
So when a cell is under some sort of toxin stress, could be low oxygen, complete absence
of oxygen, could be a growth factor, which is telling the cell to live, is not present,
death by neglect.
Let's call it that.
When the cell is being neglected, either by nutrition, starvation, complete depletion
of nutrients or complete depletion of growth factors that keep them happy, the positive
signals then cytochrome C gets released.
But it's a very profound discovery because this is a protein that we were all convinced
had only one role.
We call it the day job now, make ATV.
It's got a moonlighting job that sometimes it leaves the mitochondria and doesn't make
ATP and bam, it starts a cascade, which is called apoptosis cell death.
I was just about to say, is this part of a programmed cell death as apoptosis?
This is programmed cell death.
So here I am in 1996, I'm 26 years old, very happy doing enzyme kinetics, bioenergetics,
and I see this finding and all of a sudden I stopped caring about ATP because in part,
a lot of that how it works was more or less discovered.
I didn't have the insight, because obviously why would I be still working on it?
I still thought there was more to be discovered, but the reality was I was probably just cleaning
up little side things in that field at best.
That's not hopefully to disparage the bioenergetics field, but there's still some important questions
there, more at a structural level and there's some beautiful work there.
But what I was doing was-
The kinetics had been worked out now.
Some of it had been and not, but this was great because this connected the mitochondria,
just not for energy and what the mitochondria does almost in a cell, like in an autonomous
way.
But this says it starts to control cell biology and function, like the decision of life and
death.
So obviously, the first thing we think about is it can't be selected just for death, right?
It must be doing something interesting.
So let's think about what else it might release.
And one of the first things that we thought about, which is something that people had
noticed for almost 40, 50 years before, they release superoxide and hydrogen peroxide,
reactive oxygen species, oxidants, free radicals.
And most people in the mid-90s assumed that mitochondria only released this so-called
cleaning molecule, a toxic molecule, when the mitochondria is damaged, maybe in neurodegeneration,
maybe in aging, we'll get into this, maybe when a heart failure, when there's low oxygen
ischemia.
So in other words, is there almost as a way that the mitochondria, when it's not working
well, it just spills out.
Because mitochondria has all these electrons and they have to, they're not working, those
electrons just spill into superoxide and eventually to hydrogen peroxide.
And what we thought about is, well, maybe nature could have used that as a signaling
molecule.
In other words, to dictate cellular function.
And so there were some papers just right as we were working that came out and it showed,
in fact, H2O2 could be a signaling molecule, but they didn't think it was necessarily mitochondria.
So there's a neat little story that there's another system in the cytoplasm that can generate
H2O2 and they thought that's all about signaling.
Signaling basically means it's making decisions in the cell to die, to live, to proliferate,
to grow, if you're an immune cell, to make cytokines, to do inflammation.
But the mitochondria only did it when it's not working and it's spilling all these electrons
into hydrogen peroxide and it's causing damage.
And we actually showed that, in fact, under physiological conditions, you can make hydrogen
peroxide, which has a beneficial effect.
And so from that point on, the first paper was published in 98, now almost 20 years,
there's my group and lots of other people continue to show that mitochondrial generation
of this cleaning molecule can actually cause cellular functions to happen.
For example, we've shown our T cells, which are part of the adaptive immune system, right?
They fight off pathogens, right?
Or innate immune cells as well, just immunity in general, right?
They fight off viral infections, bacterial infections, that H2O2 is used by those immune
cells to properly function.
And what's the profound implication?
Which is what you're going to get into is antioxidants.
Are they beneficial?
Are they harmful?
So already to the audience, it should be obvious, if I'm saying that something you think is
a cleaning molecule only, then antioxidants are great.
You're getting rid of this toxic molecule, cleaning molecule.
You're getting rid of this bad stuff.
But if it's also there for good purposes, like immune function.
Paradoxically could be bad to have an antioxidant in your system at a time when you need enhanced,
especially adaptive immunity.
And so one of the clinical trials that came out was in the ICU sepsis, that's the big
disease, which is basically on a simplistic level, tons of inflammation.
And those trials failed.
They made them worse, antioxidant trials.
In cancer, again, in lung cancer, vitamin E trial, it didn't have a curative effect.
Yeah.
Do you think it's overly simplistic to say that there ought to be a balance in the body
between pro-oxidative and anti-oxidative stress?
And it's never the case that one is absolutely good or absolutely bad.
It depends on the state of the organism.
So under perhaps a normal state, a more anti-oxidative, i.e., let's reduce the ROS is the right thing
to do.
And that's to your point, when the immune system is required to take the front step,
cancer and sepsis being two enormous examples, that having too much antioxidant property
can actually be harmful.
And that's a moment when you actually want to be able to inhibit that process.
So one of the interesting antioxidant trials, now again, caveat in this experiment I'm going
to tell you is an exercise experiment.
So we all agree that if you do vigorous exercise, it has benefits.
And you can take a biopsy and look at all the genes that exercise turns on.
And these are genes we think are beneficial to the host, to the rest of the body.
If you give high doses of antioxidants, so that's the caveat, it's high doses, probably
not the doses that most people use, it actually turns off that beneficial response.
So in other words, to your point, I think what you're making is that when the system
is stressed and the mitochondria integrates that stress, how does it pass that information
back to the cell?
We think that perhaps it releases hydrogen peroxide.
So clearly exercise is a good example, right?
That's a stress to the system, to your muscle.
And how does that muscle then turn on all these genes and blah, blah, blah?
We think it does it perhaps by releasing hydrogen peroxide.
Prior to this insight, Nav, is it the case that people knew the mitochondria was signaling,
but assumed there was a different molecule that was used to transmit the message, or
the people didn't actually think the mitochondria were playing any role in signaling and we're
still back in the ATP only paradigm?
They did think about signaling only in the context of pathology.
So in other words, so there are these childhood diseases like Lee's syndrome where there's
a mitochondrial mutation in a particular protein and there's a devastating disease,
the kids don't live that long.
And it's clearly that's a mitochondrial mutation and a protein that gets mutated, doesn't function
properly in the mitochondria and you get a childhood disease.
So how does that work?
So people say, well, probably ATP or maybe too much ROS.
So in that context, there was some idea of signaling, right?
But this is saying under physiological conditions.
This is not pathology, it's physiologic.
When you get a pathogen, in other words, when you get a virus or bacteria, that happens.
You get a cold, your immune system has to be activated.
That's not pathology, that's a good normal response.
So under all those conditions, the mitochondria is playing a signaling role.
And so I've coined this term, so there's the mitochondria as powerhouses.
So my talks never talk about that.
The title of every talk I give all around the world is the same.
Not very original anymore, mitochondria as signaling organelles.
And H2O2 is one way, cytochrome C is another way, right?
That's probably maybe the most original because that's for cell DAT.
By the way, 22 years later, do we still think that that work out of Emory is what has been
added to that body of knowledge about the role of in apoptosis and program cell DAT?
They know the whole pathway.
But it is still coming from the single enzyme?
Yeah, yeah.
Wow.
There are these proteins called BACs and BAC that make these pores in the mitochondria
and it releases this 13 kilodalton protein.
It just releases that protein right out and then it binds to a whole bunch of other proteins,
apath1 and caspase-9 and starts this proteolytic pathway which eventually causes cell DAT.
So they've worked out all the biochemistry.
But the main point remains?
Conceptually, yes.
Wow.
You don't get that all the time in biology that 22 years later the punchline is still
the same.
The punchline is the same.
I mean, there's a lot of details that I have to say, but conceptually, yeah.
Are there other ways, by the way, that cells can undergo apoptosis?
Oh, yeah.
Now there's a whole industry.
Every day there's a new version of it.
And in fact, we can talk about one new one which I'm very excited about.
So clearly, we can show that H2O2 in many contexts will signal for positive responses,
immune functions as we just talked about, the exercise response.
But clearly, there must be cases where H2O2 or other reactive oxygen species cause cell
DAT.
How does that work?
And there is a new form of cell DAT that was just discovered by Brent Stockwell and Scott
Dixon at Columbia in 2011 or so, 2011.
And it's called ferroptosis.
And it's basically taking H2O2.
If there's free iron, you can make a hydroxyl radical, an OH.
And that will then make a lipid hydroperoxide.
So if you have polyunsaturated fatty acids, it will basically make it into a lipid hydroperoxide
which can be very toxic.
So the bottom line is there are times where hydrogen peroxide with iron and lipids, the
three can come together and make something called a lipid hydroperoxide which will cause
cell DAT in ferroptosis.
The good thing is your body is full of an enzyme called GPX4 that gets rid of it all
the time.
Now, if you don't have that enzyme, you're in big trouble.
So there are places where clearly H2O2 is positive and it can become very lethal by
making another form of reactive oxygen species.
But again, nature has selected, I can't count all of them, but at least 30 enzymes which
are constantly mopping up these reactive oxygen species, keeping them quite low so you don't
get to those toxic levels.
So when we go back to apoptosis, which I didn't think we were going to even talk about this,
but it's so great to be able to bring it up because I think for many people that they're
still probably thinking, what are we talking about apoptosis?
So if a cell undergoes a genetic mutation, nuclear genetic, we'll come back to mitochondrial
genes later, but if a cell undergoes a genetic mutation in the nucleus that's unrecoverable,
it will on a good day kill itself.
It will commit suicide.
I mean, that would be one of the things that would drive apoptosis.
You're getting to tumor suppression mechanisms.
Yes, exactly.
That's where I'm going.
Do we know if this mechanism you just described of apoptosis plays a role in the type of cancer
apoptosis that we want to see?
And if so, the implication is the nuclear genome must be communicating with the mitochondria.
Yes.
So there is a drug that targets that Abbott made, a good friend of mine, Steve Fesek,
was involved in it, who's now at Vanderbilt.
And so in the 90s, they figured out the structure of a particular protein that controls cytochrome
C release.
And so they've made a drug against that protein, and specifically in cancer, to make the cancer
cells sensitive to chemotherapy, basically.
Right?
So what do cancer cells love to do?
They upregulate anti-epoptotic proteins, right?
So what does that mean?
It means they turn on a whole program, which is basically an anti-death program.
Right.
Protects them from everything you just described.
Yeah.
This release of cytochrome C and all of that stuff.
And so one idea is why don't we target those anti-epoptotic proteins, these anti-death
proteins?
And it's because if we can target them and prevent them from functioning, then when we
give them chemotherapy, now the cells will die a lot quicker.
The problem with chemotherapy is all these anti-death proteins are there.
So a normal cell, like, you know, so doxyarubin is a good case.
A normal cell being a heart gets toxicity at the same time you're trying to kill the
cancer cell.
So it's not selective.
It's not selective, right?
And so people have been targeting these anti-epoptotic proteins in cancer as a mechanism to make
chemotherapy more effective.
Yeah.
So this mechanism we were talking from 1996, anything we would get into this, but it's
been a long time.
This is my previous life.
I haven't thought about this in a long time.
But yeah, it still applies and it's very important for cancer.
So while we're still going on history, I just alluded to something a moment ago that I think
is an important point for the listener to understand, which is, you know, everybody
knows or I guess most people who were thinking about biology would understand that the part
of the cell that contains your DNA is called the nucleus.
And we've got lots of genes in there, about 20,000 genes.
But the mitochondria has genes too.
Not that many.
What is like 35 or something?
37.
And there's the key point there is there's 13 genes that are essential for the respiratory
chain to work.
And the respiratory chain is where all that oxygen is being consumed.
That's the one that makes that energy, that electrochemical energy we talked about that
ultimately gets converted to ATP.
So the key subunits of the respiratory chain, which generates that battery that we've been
talking about, it holds on to those 13 genes that are critical for it.
So for example, complex one, and it's one of those respiratory chains, there's these
five complexes.
Well, one of the complexes has 45 subunits, but a few of them, which means 45 proteins
make this huge complex.
But a few of them are in the mitochondrial genome.
Complex three, very important, my favorite complex.
Everybody's got to have a favorite complex.
And so my favorite complex.
I see a t-shirt here.
Yeah.
My favorite complex is complex three, and it has one gene that's still in the mitochondria.
By the way, are you saying that just to be contrarian because complex one is actually
the coolest?
Because like, how can complex one not be your favorite mitochondrial complex?
I'll tell you in a second.
It's just because you're cool and you're too cool for school because you study this.
The rest of us who are in the peanut gallery, we default into complex one being the coolest.
So you're saying I'm a mitochondrial hipster, right?
I think you are.
You're leading the charge, Janice.
No, but complex three is very interesting because it has 11 subunits.
Only one subunit is in the mitochondrial, encoded by the mitochondrial genome.
So at one point, the mitochondria, so going back in evolution, we think there was an alpha
proteobacteria and an archaea, probably a metagen.
These two prokaryotes got together and had a symbiotic love affair.
And just to explain to you, so we are eukaryotes.
And what does that mean again?
We've got a nucleus, we've got a bunch of organelles.
And what's a prokaryote?
It doesn't have those organelles.
So bacteria.
So you got a bacteria and you got an archaea and they got together.
So we think the archaea is kind of where the nucleus came from and the alpha proteobacteria
is the modern day mitochondria.
And one of the best evidences is I remember an experiment that I did as a graduate student
was I took a bacteria that somebody had discovered in the 70s, a beautiful paper in nature, and
this bacteria, if you gave it like succinate, like a mitochondrial substrate, it'll grow
on it and it would respire very similar to modern day mitochondria.
Modern day mitochondria.
Wow.
A nice, elegant proof of concept that the mitochondria are basically bacteria.
They came from bacteria.
Yeah, they came from bacteria.
Yeah.
And you know, those who doubt evolution, I always tell them that every organism I know
burns glucose very similarly.
It is hard to make that.
Yeah, if you're not, I don't want to go down this path because we'll simply alienate a
million people.
But it is interesting to think like it strikes me as it's very hard to come up with an alternative
explanation for why you would have this effectively foreign DNA inside every cell.
And I just, I'm so intrigued by this mitochondrial DNA thing because again, it's such a tiny
number of genes on a relative scale, but yet they're so critical.
And to my knowledge, I don't think there's any other organelle that carries its own genes
with it.
Is there?
No, it doesn't.
And what's interesting is that it only encodes for like a 1% of, you know, there's, I don't
know, 1,000 proteins in the mitochondria.
But it's absolutely critical.
Absolutely.
You knock those 37 genes out.
You knock out any one of those genes out.
You're done.
And so why did the mitochondria hold on to those?
Right?
So it basically gave up, you know, if it has a thousand proteins, it said, you know what,
the nuclear genome, you take 990, right?
I'm going to hold on.
And they're all the critical catalytic subunits in all of this.
And then there was, they're really essential for the function and I'm going to hold on
to them.
It's almost like it doesn't trust its symbiotic partner.
Right.
It's like a love affair, right?
Yeah, I love you.
But I'm going to hold on to a few things.
Yeah.
And it's very interesting because I believe I could be wrong, but I, you could make the
case and correct me if I'm wrong, that that we pay a price for that lack of trust.
In many ways, don't you think the nucleus would be a better steward of those genes?
Doesn't the nucleus have more ways to protect the genome than the mitochondria?
And therefore, don't we run a greater risk of disease when the mitochondria with its
beautiful stewardship over its precious 37 genes gets under stress?
Yeah, this is a very important point you're making.
Basically we have a lot of DNA repair enzymes, right?
They're all in the nucleus.
There's these proteins called histones that cover the double strand DNA.
So you know, and there's many mechanisms to protect our genome.
And the mitochondrial DNA is just like this round little circle.
It's so vulnerable.
It's totally vulnerable and is especially vulnerable because the sight of those free
radicals we've been talking about is right there.
Exactly.
That's the worst part.
You put these very exposed, fragile, not protected genes in the presence of a potential toxin.
Right.
I mean, I wish I had more time to think about it.
I wish I was quicker on my feet because I think I could think of an elegant analogy
of how counterintuitive that is, right?
Leaving the keys to the kingdom in the hands of the guy next to the, you know, I can't
even think of it.
I'm not smart enough, but like, it doesn't make sense.
It's like a hen house next to where the fox is like.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's a better idea.
So what's the advantage of it?
One thing I should stress is that potential molecule that could be damaging in superoxide,
hydrogen peroxide, hydroxyl radicals, the mitochondria where the mitochondrial DNA
resides in the mitochondrial matrix, there's tons and tons of antioxidants there.
So even though that the DNA itself can be protected, it's protected from a variety of
these toxins because there's so many proteins that clean them up, essentially.
The highest level of antioxidant activity sitting in the mitochondrial matrix, and I
think that's because to protect that almost naked DNA.
So one other little-
If that makes sense.
Yeah, no, it really makes sense.
Thank you.
Because this has been on my mind a lot lately because I saw a paper recently, I may have
even sent it to you about another hypothesis around inflammation, the effect that inflammation
can have on the mitochondria and the mitochondria starts to shed its DNA, which actually kicks
off an immune response as it exits the cell.
And that's what got me thinking about this.
I was like, wait a minute.
That's a really good point.
That must happen an awful lot.
And actually, what did they peg it to?
They pegged it to hypercorticillemia, which we're going to come back to because you're
kind of a cortisol guy too when it's all said and done.
You're a cortisol file if such a word exists.
No, in the hormone world, I call people like you insulin prophets.
And many of your other former guests, I'm the cortisol prophet, right?
I think that's the missing link for a lot of stuff.
Not any real data, but it's just my own intuition.
Well, these data that I saw actually suggested that the hypercorticillemia, not just cortisol,
but other glucocorticoids and including other hormones from the adrenal glands could really
become toxic to the mitochondria at high enough doses.
And it was basically jettisoning broken strands of mitochondrial DNA that basically kicked
off immune responses.
And sort of you had these inflammatory responses that resulted from an immune response to mitochondrial
DNA being damaged by cortisol.
So bringing it back to kind of dinner table trivia, the other thing about mitochondrial
DNA that's interesting is it comes from one parent.
So tell us what that's all about and why that's the case and what the...
Well, we don't...
Yeah, I mean, again, two big questions in the field.
One is why we still keep those genes.
We just went over, it's kind of like it doesn't trust.
And then the other one is why does it come from the mom?
And there's an implication there, which is you have far less dilution by generation.
You do, but why did nature select that?
I'm asking you.
I don't.
I don't have a good explanation.
Even teleologically, you don't have a good explanation?
I really don't.
We think more about the function of mitochondria.
I mean, there's a whole group of people who think about the bottleneck of mitochondrial
DNA being passed on.
But I actually, I don't have a good explanation to it.
It's a fascinating...
I think lots of people have very interesting ideas around it.
But to be honest with you, why we continue to have those genes and why does it come
from the mom?
I think these are still outstanding questions in the field.
Something that my lab doesn't work on.
And as you know, Peter, I don't comment on things that I don't work on just because you
can speculate, but you want to have good data.
But I do want to talk about one aspect of mitochondrial DNA.
And this is in my wheelhouse, which has nothing to do with those two questions, which is a
third role, but going back to signaling.
So if you think that H2O2...
So what does mitochondria dump into the cytoplasm ATP for energy?
We think H2O2 for signaling to do immune responses, exercise, etc.
What else could it release?
Well, one of the things that could release is mitochondrial DNA, which would then kick
off an immune response.
The only thing about that hypothesis that I struggle with is how do you release mitochondrial
DNA in a physiological way without not releasing cytochrome C?
So you're saying maybe all the damage that's...
Well, okay, I'll give you an answer.
I'm making this up now.
But maybe you are also releasing cytochrome C. The cytochrome C results in the apoptotic
death of this cell, but the DNA gets into the plasma, which is where the immune system
begins to recognize it.
So you could still have apoptosis at the cellular level, but globally, so locally apoptosis,
globally you have the immune response.
So it depends on that cell dying.
Yes, which makes sense.
That's okay.
You're saying, I don't see a way that that could happen with an intact cell just willy
nilly passing off its mitochondrial DNA.
That makes sense.
Yeah, and people have sort of proposed that it could do that, and maybe it can.
And I'm open to the idea, but someone's got to show me how you selectively release some
mitochondrial DNA without releasing everything else.
Where H2O2 and ATP get released in a much more benign fashion without cytochrome C.
Now, ATP has an active transporter.
It has an active transporter.
H2O2 goes by diffusion?
We think so.
Probably maybe VDAC channels, voltage-dependent anion channels could maybe release the super
oxide, which then gets converted quickly to H2O2 right outside the mitochondria.
So again, the mechanisms of, it's kind of like water, right?
Before the aquaporins, we just thought water just went back to diffusion.
Now there's active transport.
Actually, Pioneer was at your institute at Hopkins, right?
Got the Nobel Prize for the aquaporins.
I didn't know that.
And so when we think about signaling, the simple idea is what gets released?
ATP, what gets released without cytochrome C getting released?
That's the key, right?
Because cytochrome C gets released.
It doesn't matter.
Everything is the cells on its way to die.
So what gets released?
So we know hydrogen peroxide, ATP, and metabolites.
Metabolites are always being released.
So citrate.
Well CO2.
CO2, yeah.
Or obvious reason.
But citrate, right?
So citrate is very interesting molecule.
Citrate gets exported from the TCA cycle into the cytoplasm where it can get broken
down back into acetyl CoA, which can then be a primer for making new lipids, new fatty
acids, right?
But also that acetyl CoA can cause acetylation reactions like on histones to control gene
expression in the so-called chromatin modifications.
Meaning it goes back to the nucleus.
Yeah.
So citrate could be a signaling molecule, right?
Well, if it's doing what you just described, it would be.
It would be, right?
And so there's a bunch of...
So in my wheelhouse, the ones that I like to think about, H2O2 and TCA cycle metabolites
that get released, and they do.
They're in constant flux between the cytoplasm and the TCA cycle, and they can control gene
expression through chromatin modifications, through histone modifications.
So because we're going to come back to this through a totally different lens, I want
to also have you and or me explain somewhat to the listener what this idea means of histone
deacetylation.
And basically, because those terms I think are largely foreign to even reasonably informed
folks, but I think the reasonably informed folk will understand what epi genome means,
what a modification of a gene means, and how genes are potentially silenced or upregulated.
Is that happening often in the mitochondrial DNA as well, or are they pretty much just
on their own?
They don't have...
So what transcription factors tell those genes when to turn on?
Again, they're all a nuclear encoded and they have to be...
Oh my God, this is so staggeringly inefficient.
There has to be a reason for this that hasn't...
Why?
I mean, I know you're fascinated by mitochondrial DNA, and I don't have good answers for this.
That's why we didn't want to talk about this.
Which is, why does it continue to have those genes?
I'm hoping there's a college student out there or a graduate student out there who's thinking,
I want to understand what could be the reason for this.
Because if you can find in my somewhat simplistic way of thinking about problems, I think when
you look at something in nature and you don't have a clue why it's occurring, if you could
get a clue why it's occurring, you will unlock a whole bunch of other knowledge as well.
That might not be true, but that's like kind of a working hypothesis.
In this case, think of like you're one of the world's experts on this topic, and yet
you're acknowledging there are so many fundamental obvious questions.
Like a high school biology student could ask the questions I'm asking on this topic.
These are not like super nuanced questions, and yet the field doesn't know the answer.
That's really interesting.
To be fair, there are people who think a lot about this and they have opinions on it, but
what I'm just simply saying is what is well established is that mitochondria generate
ATP and they generate metabolites for growth.
All of this stuff, including my signaling hypothesis, it's still a work in progress.
Like everything we've talked about, just full disclosure to the audience, it's a work in
progress.
So if you're a high school student, come on and join the party.
There's a lot to be discovered here.
Well that's the beauty, right?
It's not like we're ever going to run out of questions that need to be answered.
I think the difficulty in the field historically has been the bias about ATP and thinking about
energy and solving that problem.
The great biochemists did that.
They figured out how we make ATP, fundamental to life.
They figured out how we make the metabolizing TCA cycle, but now it's getting much more
challenging because those same processes can control gene expression.
Well, how does that work?
I have some reasonable hypotheses we're testing, but I'm very careful as you know to not give
a strong opinion on a work in progress.
So let's shift gears a little bit to talk about some other broad mitochondrial questions
because I do think that people today, and maybe it's just the bias I experience because
of what I'm looking for, so this might not be the case, but it seems that the interest
in mitochondria has exploded.
I think people are realizing there's a lot going on here.
It's more than we realize.
Mitochondrial function is now a term people use all the time, but they're not just talking.
I don't think they're just talking about oxidative phosphorylation.
I think they're talking about broader things.
And when we talk about aging, we talk about some things changing in the mitochondria as
we age.
When you think of hallmarks of aging, we can debate the merits of some of them, but something's
different in the mitochondria of an 80-year-old versus an 8-year-old.
What are some of those changes?
Well, so this is going to get contentious now because the data suggests that you have
a decrease in mitochondrial DNA.
Some of that mitochondrial DNA has deletions that the capacity to do maximal ATP generation
goes down, oxidative phosphorylation.
The key there is maximal.
So one of the perplexing things, and this is really perplexing for me, a much more...
So I don't think much about mitochondrial DNA, and that's why I didn't have good answers
for that, but this is the one that really is...
And this is fundamental to the aging.
When you're born, let's say, you have 100% capacity.
And then as you age, that capacity, if you're giving 100% mitochondria, you get an A+,
100%, how far do you go as you age?
Just to actually make sure I understand what you're talking about, are you saying amount
of ATP generated per mole of oxygen as a metric?
As a metric.
We could use ATP generation as a simple one.
Its ability to...
For every mole of oxygen, you generate X mole of ATP, and whatever your maximum is, it declines.
And you can burn it through fat, glucose, carbohydrates, protein.
It's working at its maximal efficiency.
Everything's fine.
And that efficiency now declines with age.
The question is, is it ever rate limiting?
So you and I, I mean, again, these are loose terms, at any given point, are using maybe
10% to 20% of our maximal activity.
Hey, speak for yourself, dude.
I mean, I do wind sprints every day, man.
Okay, so when you do that, you might go up to 40% or 50%.
I didn't realize that.
You don't hit that.
And so when we knock out a protein in the mitochondria, and we knock out it completely
from 100% to 0% pathology happens, we go from 100% to 50%, we never see any pathology.
Even under stress?
Even under stress, if anything, they behave better.
So yeah, this is very interesting, right?
And so then when I look at the data on aging sometimes, you know, in some tissues, it goes
down by 50% of maximal, maybe 70%, 80%.
But is that ever rate limiting?
Well, if what you said is true, then it would not be rate limiting within a certain band.
So I am on this full disclosure again.
I am in way out of space on this idea.
I don't think mitochondrial function, and if you don't have a disease, let's be clear,
normal aging, we're talking about, right?
You don't have cardiovascular disease, you know, you're just sort of pretty healthy.
And I don't think a healthy heart, you know, is rate limited for mitochondrial function.
The implication there is that most people think, again, this is like dogma, like with
antioxidants, right?
They're good for you.
So that mitochondria are declining, let's give supplements that boost mitochondrial
function.
Is that a fair statement?
Heck yeah.
I think there's no evidence to support that.
What is the most popular of said supplements?
Would that MITOQ be a popular supplement?
No, that's an anti-mitochondral targeted antioxidant.
So we can talk about MITOQ in a second, actually.
We should maybe talk about MITOQ.
Well, let's go back to it, but let's go back to your question.
What is, well, no one actually has, you know, people have been trying to have these, what's
called mitochondrial biogenesis activator, something that will make more mitochondria.
And I'm not quite sure what supplement people use that they think is the best one.
But I would argue the opposite, which is that they're not rate limiting.
And if anything, maybe you can decrease mitochondrial function in certain tissues a little bit to
activate stress responses, which will then fight off if you do get a disease.
And this is going to go into metformin.
I was just, how do you read my mind?
I didn't even start mouthing the word yet.
Why did you know I was going to bring up metformin?
Because we think metformin is a weak mitochondrial complex one inhibitor.
Yes.
Another, which is part of the respiratory chain.
That's why complex one is my favorite complex.
That's why you're a complex one is your favorite.
But I'm a poser.
I'm a mitochondrial poser.
So okay.
Because what I was going to actually ask you was on the heels of that, when you give metformin,
you inhibit complex one, you are now reducing mitochondrial function.
That mitochondrial function.
And if what you're saying is correct, you would need a lot of metformin to generate
actual ETC toxicity.
Do we ever see that?
No.
I mean, you do if you go to certain doses, obviously.
Not physiologically, we can't, do we?
The anti-diabetic dosing that is given to people, I mean, there's some toxicity can
happen due to certain patient populations.
But it's a very safe drug, right?
It's used by almost what, 300 million people now.
It's estimated to be used by half a billion people as the diabetes epidemic explodes in
China and India.
So no one quite understands how metformin works.
We think it's a, you know, it has three effects.
Clearly, it lowers glucose production in the liver.
It has some anti-inflammatory effects and it has some anti-cancer effects.
Well, let's talk more specifically about it.
We were joking around when we were at Easter Island that our next trip actually needs
to be to France.
To see the goats.
To see the lilac from where, wasn't that in France where that metformin came from?
So two sentences on how metformin was discovered?
They noticed these goats that were eating were pretty healthy.
I love these stories.
But you know-
Yesterday, I was talking to Ted Schafer about goats as well.
So I love that the two Northwestern guys, the only two podcasts that will ever have goats.
The votes are going to be these ones.
So what's interesting about metformin, I think, is it got approved as an anti-diabetic drug.
People went back and looked at people who were taking different diabetes and epidemiologically
found that there was a lower rates of like prostate cancer.
So you're probably talking to Ted Schafer about this, right?
So and they're lower in breast cancer.
So then people started investigating as an anti-cancer drug.
Then some people started noticing, wow, it has anti-inflammatory effects.
I've talked to a friend, David Sabatini, that isn't it interesting that rapamycin, anti-inflammatory
somewhat, anti-cancer promotes metabolic health.
So how does that all work?
Well, he'll argue it's all mTOR.
I said, well, I would argue how can metformin do three very disparate effects?
Anti-diabetic, anti-cancer, anti-inflammatory, just like rapamycin would, it must be hitting
a node that's very important for the cell.
So metformin doesn't hit mTOR.
Does though.
AMPK does.
AMPK, but that's due to first hitting mitochondrial complex one and then activating AMPK, which
can repress mTOR.
But the analogy that I'm using basically is mTOR we know is the master of the universe.
So is mitochondria, right?
So if you inhibit mitochondria, not to the point where you cause toxicity, just enough,
you can activate a variety of pathways, which can promote, have anti-cancer, anti-diabetic
and anti-inflammatory effects.
Now metformin is somewhat tissue specific.
It seems to have a preference for the hepatocyte.
So it gets into the kidney and the liver.
I think we've talked about this before about mTOR, right?
So mTOR and rapamycin, right?
Why wouldn't you use rapamycin?
Well, it might get in everywhere.
I think David's arguing, you've argued, wouldn't it be great if you can get metformin to go
to the liver?
But not to the skeletal muscle.
So metformin already has a little bit of that property.
It only gets selectively into, it doesn't get into the heart that well, right?
So it doesn't infect your heart function, not directly.
It affects your liver, your kidney.
It actually accumulates quite a bit in the gut.
And some people get diarrhea with metformin.
And so some people think metformin is affecting your microbiome.
And there's a huge literature now thinking that some of how it's having its effects.
So I think the liver, so I think there's three places that are important.
The liver, and that can account for some of shutting down the glucose production and having
the so-called anti-diabetic effect.
The colon, and affecting your microbiome.
And I think the immune cells, I think that's the big one we're missing.
So that's the one that I'm very fascinated.
In other words, metformin getting into your macrophages or your, probably maybe not your
T cells, but at least some of your immune cells that might be causing high levels of
inflammation.
And if you look at the three drugs that people like to use, aspirin, metformin, and statins,
globally use combined maybe what, a billion people?
Probably more.
The Venn diagram where they all overlap is inflammation.
So let's talk a little bit about the anti-inflammatory properties of metformin because the first
thing is the one I guess we would understand the most, which is, you've alluded to this,
but I just, I want to orient the listener a little bit.
The mitochondria, you said, have these five complexes.
Each of them have multiple subunits.
And what happens is these are basically the chains between the inner mitochondrial membrane
and the inner part of the mitochondria, where these reducing agents like NAD, NADH, NADP,
and NADPH are transferring the electrons and building up that gradient.
So by the time you get to the end of this thing, you've got so much potential energy
in all of those electrons and you run that transfer of phosphates from ADP to ATP and
everybody wins the game.
So this is essential, this electron transport chain, like messing with that, probably not
a good idea.
Metformin comes along and it blocks complex one.
Now it doesn't block it completely, it blocks it partially.
Now complex one, the chemical reaction that's occurring on the inner part of the mitochondria
is the transfer of NADH to NAD.
Now we're going to come back to NAD, but for totally unrelated reasons.
When you do that, what is that telling the cell?
By inhibiting that, the cells read out is what?
Physiologically.
Three things.
First, that battery that you're talking about that generates to make ATP, less charged.
So then what happens?
ATP goes down, ADP goes up, there's a kinase called AMPK.
Kinase, AMPK is the AMPK, hence AMPK.
It gets activated and in part that.
That enzyme is activated is a signal that says I'm not fed enough.
And one of the major things it does is it promotes autophagy.
My favorite word.
Your favorite word, right?
It's one of the dominant things it does.
That's why when AMPK gets activated, we get another little benefit, a la Rapamycin's effect
on mTOR, which is it says, hey man, I'm telling you from an ox-foss standpoint, energy is
low, shut things down.
Nutrients are scarce.
Right, and this is happening in the liver.
So for example, glucose production that happens in the liver starts to shut down in part,
or lipogenesis, making new lipids in the liver.
And that's why for fatty liver, it might have some benefits.
So that's one.
Something is, which you alluded to NAD to NADH.
Sorry, NADH2.
NAD to NAD.
Right?
Making NAD.
So that ratio also gets transmitted back to the cell.
And what's that signal?
How does the low NAD to NADH get transmitted?
So the biggest one is lactate to pyruvate.
Right?
It's a lactate to pyruvate.
It is a source of, so there's many ways you can feed pyruvate.
So we talked about glucose to pyruvate.
So glucose to pyruvate uses NAD to NADH, and usually pyruvate to lactate will go...
Go ahead and explain what I'm doing.
So I have to tell you, and I think we're both, because we're not on camera, one of the difficulties
of really getting into the nitty gritty of metabolism is it's so much easier to write
it in diagrams.
Right?
I mean, when you write it in the diagram in simplistic ways, it's just like...
It's easier.
It's just easier, right?
I mean, it's just...
So Nav's laughing at me because I'm closing my eyes, drawing it.
And as I'm saying it, you know, NADH, no, it's the NADH.
I mean, I'm getting confused.
I promise you, this will be one of those episodes where the show notes will be handy because
we'll have all the diagrams.
Well, they can actually, you know, what they can really do, right?
There's a book I've heard.
Yeah, there's a book.
You want to give a plug?
This is a good moment.
I'm happy to give a plug.
So for all you metabolite lovers out there, Nav wrote a book called Navigating Metabolism,
wah, wah, wah.
And I actually picked up a copy as soon as we got back from Easter Island.
In fact, I probably ordered it from the airport in Santiago.
And it's a fantastic resource.
And we will absolutely be sure to link to that.
I would say it is, and I'm not just saying this because you're sitting here, but if you
are a person who's interested in this area, but you're not going to devote your life to
it, it's a fantastic...
It's the one book you need to get.
Obviously, if you're someone who's doing a postdoc in Nav's lab, it's something you need
to read, but it's not going to be sufficient to get you to the next level of understanding.
But for the knuckle draggers amongst us, you can get pretty far on understanding this stuff
through Nav's book.
And it's actually a pretty quick read.
It's not like reading Stryer's Biochemistry where...
That's a very good book, by the way.
Stryer was my professor.
As was the Leninger book.
So anyway, yeah, a little digression, which is to acknowledge this is hard.
Apologies for it.
But I think this topic is so important, and I just know I get asked about this stuff
all the time.
I'm, on a personal level, professional level, so interested in this topic that you just
have to pay the price.
You have to be willing to get into the details.
And the reason is we're going to talk about other things.
If I had a dollar for every time I've been asked, should I be taking NR, NMN, and should
I be going to a clinic where they do IV, NAD, and all these things?
If you want to be able to think through those things and read the papers that are asking
those questions, you have to understand how this stuff works.
There's no shortcut.
So unfortunately, we have to continue doing this the way we're doing it, and that might
mean that I have to close my eyes and pretend I'm drawing Complex 1.
So I guess we should just talk about NAD then, NAD and NADH ratio.
I sort of interrupted you, though.
No, no, no.
Let's go back to metformin.
Yeah, the NADH.
Right.
So what metformin doesn't allow is it starts to weakly inhibit Complex 1, so your NADH
to NAD is going to be slowed down.
And how that gets transmitted to the rest of the cell is not fully understood, so I
have many ideas around this.
And we can talk about one of them later because it has to do with neurodegeneration potentially.
But the big thing is that NADH to NAD ratio is very important.
And one of the important things is that when lactate, which can come from the muscle, the
liver takes it up and the lactate becomes pyruvate, and that can then eventually become
glucose, that's gluconeogenesis, it needs NAD.
But if you have metformin, you don't have as much NAD, so lactate to pyruvate slows
down and therefore you don't make as much glucose.
And that's another reason why metformin has its anti-diabetic properties.
That just gave me an interesting idea.
We have a friend in common, Josh Rabinowitz at Princeton, who's a classmate of mine in
medical school, a colleague of yours.
Brilliant metabolism scientist.
Off the charts, incredible guy.
He had a paper that came out, I've talked about it on the podcast very briefly.
I actually want to interview Josh and I just have to drag my ass down to Princeton or he
has to drag his up to New York City.
But this paper in Cell Metabolism, which we'll be sure to link to, took orally administered
NR or NMN, both precursors to NAD, and it showed that the liver could take those up
in significant quantities, combine them with tryptophan and make lots of intrahepatic NAD,
but none of it made it into the cell.
So the NAD wasn't making it into the cell and the NR and the NMN were not being taken
up by cells other than hepatocytes.
But what you just said made me think of something.
If the liver in the presence of NR and NMN is making a lot of NAD, that means it's making
lots of substrate to enzymatically force gluconeogenesis.
Or is that never rate limited and this becomes irrelevant?
The latter, what you just said.
I said, so we're never too low on NAD?
No, no, we are.
We are the maximal amounts.
And so there's two things about NAD.
One is just the quantity of NAD, which then is utilized by sirtuins, PARP, a variety of
other reactions that are important biologically, especially the sirtuins, which are NAD dependent.
But that's just simply NAD.
What I'm talking about is the ratio of NAD to NADH.
And so these supplements, I don't think, they don't drastically change that redox ratio
of NAD to NADH.
It's just the absolute amount of NAD, which is then utilized by sirtuins and PARP.
And there's something to be said about this because people talk about how NAD ratios decline
in the mitochondria as we age.
Does that-
Is that rate limiting?
Yeah, exactly.
Does it matter if it affects the enzymatic chain at complex one?
Comes back to, is a 50% decline in NAD rate limiting for complex one activity?
Because that would mirror what metformin is doing.
Metformin is lowering the ratio of NAD to NADH, which would seem to parallel what we're told
happens when we age.
That's a bit counterintuitive.
Exactly.
Bingo.
So this is my argument.
Most of the people say you got to boost your mitochondria because NAD is declining, the
respiratory chain is declining, mitochondria rate limiting.
But how does that jive with this metformin inhibiting complex one theory then?
If you think that mitochondria and NAD and everything around mitochondria is declining,
you want to boost them.
If you think they're declining and maybe it's adaptive, that's why it is declining, which
is my favorite theory.
Wow.
That's a little out there, man.
That's way out there.
That this is, there's a reason.
And if you can then give something like, and it's never rate limiting really, at least
for normal physiology, not maybe for stress.
And then if you can give something like metformin, you can now stress out that mitochondria at
times and turn on some adaptive responses.
So that's a different theory, right?
So the best evidence for it really is we have to really nail down whether all of these effects
of metformin happen by complex one inhibition.
There's wide disagreement in the literature.
Just to be clear, all these roles of metformin for cancer, for diabetes, for inflammation,
does it require complex one inhibition?
So how would you test that?
Well, it's hard to have a complex one knockout.
Exactly.
Because that's incompatible with life.
So that would be the obvious answer that doesn't work.
Well, so I would argue for any drug, the best experiment is to make a mutant of that particular
complex that doesn't bind metformin.
Bingo.
Yeah.
So I'm not a good structural biologist, but we did something really clever.
We noticed that the yeast has a protein, single protein, which will catalyze NADH to NAD.
What complex one does in part?
Yes, exactly.
It doesn't proton pump, which means it doesn't contribute to ATP generation.
We have engineered cells and mice to get rid of complex one and put back this yeast.
Complex one, which is refractory to metformin, but ask this question.
But the phenotype of that cell is what?
What is its electron transport chain doing if it's basically losing anything at complex
one?
Basically complex two through five still can't work.
No, no, no.
So what this protein, this yeast complex one homolog, the single protein.
Well, it does everything except the electron transport.
No, it does the electron transport.
Sorry, it doesn't do the proton pump.
Okay, got it.
So you basically reduced your battery charge a little bit, but you haven't interrupted
the electron transport.
Oh, that's elegant.
Thank you.
That's very elegant.
It's clever.
Yeah.
This is about the geekiest moment right now.
This is like, this is, yeah.
It's one of those aha things.
It's clever, right?
Very clever.
Very clever, right?
So the first experiment we did is we did the cancer experiment.
So people had noticed, at least in laboratory settings, if you give metformin, you can reduce
tumor burden in mice, the classic sort of experiments.
So what we did is we took those cancer cells and put back the yeast version.
But I want to say something here before you say, you tell us what happened, which is in
fairness.
And we did a lit review of this in 2014.
So it's very dated.
I know what's going to happen.
A bunch of people are going to say, Peter, can you please link to it?
It's an internal document.
I may link to it.
I got to go back and look and see how ridiculous it is, but it's now four years old.
But it was not clear at the time of this review if the anti-cancer benefits, which seemed
real, were either due to the inhibition of complex one or due to some other mechanism
by which AMPK was activated.
And to my knowledge, that is still not clear.
Oh, it's clear.
You're going to sell me it's clear.
For cancer.
Okay, keep going.
So I'll tell you the experiment in cancers and then I'll tell you for diabetes, does
main effect anti-diabetes, I think that's still up in the air.
For inflammation, I think there's some strong evidence for complex one as well.
So the simple experiment we did was we said, let's put back in cancer cells, human cancer
cells, we put it in a mouse and it grows rapidly, right?
And you can do it in colon cancer, breast cancer, lung cancer cells, typical cancer
biology experiments.
And we put the yeast complex one in.
And okay, so when the yeast complex one is not there, metformin decreases tumor burden.
If the yeast complex one is there, it does metformin can bind to it.
So the mitochondria still continues to work and voila, the tumors don't go down.
So what you demonstrated through that experiment, assuming we're not being fooled by some other
artifact, which is always possible, is that when you prevent metformin from this one particular
issue, which is binding to complex one and inhibiting that, its anti-cancer properties
cease to exist.
Did you assess the effect in that setting on AMPK?
How much was AMPK activity upregulated?
Yeah, so we don't think the anti-cancer effects are due to AMPK.
Fair, but do you have an answer to the question?
Do you know what happened?
Yeah, so we-
Because they should go down a little bit, but not off.
Yeah, so we didn't think about that.
We looked at other properties like NAD, NADH ratios, which we think is the more important-
And how much did the NAD-
Oh yeah, no.
You could shut it down.
Yeah, yeah.
With metformin, you could decrease it.
When the yeast complex, you can recover that ratio, the NAD to NADH ratio.
And all the metabolomics that go with it.
So when you inhibit complex one by metformin, the TCA cycle slows down and you can capture
that by mass spec classic, what's called metabolomics, which is basically looking at metabolite
profiling.
And what's cool about that is there's a very good scientist, give him a shout out, Jason
Locasal at Duke University, again, kind of a younger version of Joshua Benelitz.
And what Jason- and hooked up with the University of Chicago Ovarian Cancer, a very famous Ovarian
Cancer doctor, Ernest Lengel and his fellow Iris Romero at that point.
And they were giving metformin to patients and then they gave these biopsies to Jason.
And Jason could detect TCA cycle.
He could see if met- he could ask two questions.
Did the metformin get actually into the tumor?
Yes.
And the second one was, if our mechanism of complex one that we showed is correct, then
the TCA cycle metabolites should be altered and they were in those human cancers.
This is cell metabolism paper you can, people can look in.
What year was that?
That was so we published our metformin paper in 2014.
I think Jason's paper was in 2016.
I think we did the simple elegant experiment which shows the necessity of complex one inhibition.
But I think Jason did the- as close as you can, if that mechanism is correct, then the
humans he did the best- the next best thing you could do, which is show that TCA cycle
metabolites.
So clinically, it begs a question.
Is that working because hepatic glucose output is going down and insulin is going down and
presumably IGF is going down.
If insulin is going down, IGF-BP3 should go up, insulin should go down, even if there's
no change in the amino acids.
Those things should all, if you had a little like on off switch, more glucose or less.
Less is better.
More insulin or less.
More IGF, more or less.
Less.
For cancer.
All of those things would move in the right direction if hepatic glucose output went down.
So do we believe that that is the vehicle through which that transduction is becoming
clinically relevant?
Or do we believe that somehow inhibiting complex one in a cancer cell is deleterious to a cancer
cell?
I think both mechanisms are working in concert.
And so clearly metformin, as you pointed out, lowers glucose, insulin, IGF, and insulin
and IGF, and certain tumors can be a mitogen or something that promotes cancer proliferation.
It seems that about two thirds of cancers seem sensitive to insulin and IGF.
So that mechanism is still in play.
But what we showed is it's equally plausible for cancers that have transporters of metformin,
and they're called organic cation transporters.
Not every tumor has it.
And that's why metformin doesn't work clinically as a great anti-cancer agent because lots
of tumors just don't have them.
But if they do have them, they'll take them up, they'll inhibit complex one, and that
will have anti-cancer effects right into the cancer cell.
The reason that's important, again, is our work genetically is shown when we knock out
complex one or three, tumors don't grow.
If we give them metformin, we can show it's anti-cancer effects are due to complex one
inhibition.
So if that's right, then could we design complex one inhibitors?
Wait, let me ask you a question.
Sorry to interrupt now.
What you just said a moment ago, when you inhibit complex three and tumors don't grow,
you have to inhibit complex three in a tumor cell or in a hepatocyte to produce that cell.
And the hepatocytes are normal.
Well, the way we...
These are genetically engineered where the complex three or one is only lost in the cancer
cell.
So this is the next experiment you have to do.
You have to be able to separate.
Listen to me telling you the experiment you have to do.
It's important, I think, to separate out how much of this is tumor specific versus
global metabolic.
And the reason is the implications are profound, not just for other therapeutics, but frankly,
for a more fundamental question, was what the hell should people be eating?
Right?
If in as much as you believe that nutrition can impact cancer therapy, the answer to this
question is relevant.
So we have now generated an unpublished work.
Can you talk about unpublished work on a podcast?
I don't know.
It depends when is it going to be published?
Not for a while, but it doesn't matter.
So we've generated a mouse that contains the yeast complex one in the liver.
Ah, okay.
So this is where you'll be able to do the experiment because there's really a two by
two that needs to be done here.
I think they're both working in concert, but the major thing is in that metformin may have
some anti-cancer effects, but what it's led to because of our work and others is the idea
that maybe we should target mitochondria inhibition for cancer therapy.
Now that's a little counterintuitive.
Yeah.
So this is again, you know, I mean, I'm sure the audience is like everything this guy says
is contrarian.
So let's just turn them off now.
But you know, our data is very clear.
Mitochondria are necessary.
Mitochondrial function is necessary for tumor genesis.
All right.
So let's take a step back and explain to the listener who hasn't heard what you just said
why that is going to rock some people's world.
I think you've talked about in some other podcasts.
So there was a observation made in the 1920s by a gentleman named Otto Warburg, one of
the giants, actually trained on scrubs, for example.
He won a Nobel Prize in 1931 or 32, basically for discovering an enzyme for respiration.
So he loved measuring respiration.
But he did it in cancer.
He did it in normal cells.
And he noticed that cancer cells, at least on the benchtop, not in vivo, not in a real
tumor, not in humans, just taking tissues out, that they made a lot of lactate and they
didn't consume as much oxygen.
And this didn't make sense to him because he's like, there's plenty of oxygen.
Why should it do that?
And it led him to think about perhaps that maybe the mitochondria are being suppressed
in cancer.
And this led to this long, long, long dogma that a very elegant, simple theory.
Normal cells use a lot of mitochondria and mitochondrial ATP, very little glycolysis.
So in other words, very little glucose to lactate, tons of oxygen.
Your heart does it, your brain does it.
But when you become cancerous, the mitochondria sort of shuts off and you upregulate tons
of lactate and you can see that huge uptake of glucose uptake by a FTG pet that the clinicians
do and you can see lots of lactate.
And that was this theory.
And then you target glycolysis for cancer because it'll specifically hit cancer cells
because they're so glycolytic and spare all the other cells like your heart, your brain,
your liver, because they're all mitochondrial dependent for energy.
Keep it simple.
Right?
Right.
So far so good?
Absolutely.
And I'll get into that story about 10 years ago and I've talked about this paper on the
podcast but Thompson and Matt Vatterhahn was the lead author.
But so, so Van der Heiden and Kant, Lee-
Just saw him last night in Madison.
He was here last night?
No, he was in Madison.
Oh, oh, you heard that.
Sure.
So Matthew and Lou Kantly and Craig Thompson wrote this paper in Science almost exactly
10 years ago and it proposed a different reason for the observation.
So it said the observation that Warburg put forth is what you just described, but maybe
a different reason is that the cancer cell is not optimizing for energetics because that
was always viewed as an energetically very inefficient and wasteful thing to do.
But the argument they put forth was, well, it's not doing it for energetic reasons, it's
doing it for growth reasons.
It's doing that to get the throughput of building blocks for cells.
So same observation, different explanation.
The one thing I will say is for whatever reason and including that beautiful review in science,
which the part that people don't highlight is what is the mitochondria really doing?
So people sometimes assume, oh yeah, all that glycolysis and it's for biomass and building
blocks.
Oh yeah, the mitochondria has a negligible contribution.
It's just sort of in the background.
It's the potato, as we call it.
In the Sabatini world.
Yeah, right.
It's just, it's a bystander.
And we did a simple genetic experiment said, let's just test this.
So we're going to take in a mouse with an intact immune system.
We gave the mouse, made it have poor mouse, got lung adenocarcinoma, lung cancer, right?
The biggest cancer in the most prevalent cancer in the world, obviously due to smoking.
And we genetically knocked out the respiratory chain.
So it can respire.
So now it's 100% glycolysis.
It's exactly what a tumor that Warburg would love.
Do you make bigger tumors?
According to him, yes.
If it's all about glycolysis, or do you make smaller tumors?
We made very smaller tumors, little, little, tiny little tumors, which told us that mitochondria
are necessary or mitochondrial respiration is necessary for tumor genesis.
But van der Heiden's hypothesis would explain that because if you knock out the mitochondria,
you don't have the biomass through.
But he didn't say that in that.
No, no, no, I know, I know, but I'm extrapolated from what-
Yeah, it's consistent with that.
Yeah, no, Matt and I completely agree.
It's just the way that review was written 10 years ago.
It was more glycolytic centric.
So I will give a cheap plug to a review that I wrote with Ralph Debradinis.
It's a very elegant review by the way.
2016, where we updated this.
It's called Fundamentals of Cancer Metabolism.
And it's really simple.
It just says, if you go back to your biochemistry books and you ask, how do you make a nucleotide?
Let's keep that simple.
You need to make new DNA because cancers proliferate.
You make one to two daughter cells, to four.
And there you go.
So where does that nucleotide, it looks like a structure.
It has a ribose as a backbone that comes from glucose.
Bingo.
It needs a variety of nitrogen atoms put on it.
What does that all come from?
Some of it comes from like a spartan and glutamine.
Where do they all come from?
They can come from glucose and they're amino acids.
But they're amino acids, but they'll come from mitochondria.
Yeah.
Right?
So in other words, they both are...
One of my favorite words, they're both necessary for tumor genesis, but neither is sufficient.
Oh, can we just pause for a moment?
Unnecessary but not sufficient.
If there's one thing that I loved in medical school when you were doing the basic science
classes before you got into the clinic, it's that when you were doing your physiology classes
and your molecular biology and things like that, these professors, they were so great
at explaining the importance of very elegant experiments that can demonstrate whether something
is necessary but not sufficient, sufficient but not necessary, neither necessary nor sufficient,
you know, all those other things.
Something happens in medical school when you leave the classroom and you start to go into
clinical medicine.
People start to forget that logic.
I would say the real logic people forget, everybody does.
We're all guilty of this.
And this is what you and I have talked extensively about, correlation versus causality.
So my daughter can bitch all she wants about how her papa hasn't taught her any math, but
her papa has taught her one thing, correlation versus causality.
But this goes even deeper than that, right?
You got to start there.
Oh, yeah.
Fundamentally.
But I think people...
I mean, this is...
And right now, even in my world where people see like mitochondrial function go up or down.
So like take your aging one.
Yes, mitochondrial function goes down.
So that's a correlation with aging.
That doesn't mean that decrease in mitochondrial function causes aging or drives aging.
It's just a correlation.
It could be adaptive or maladaptive.
That's right.
I mean, that's...
So see, to me, the second order point is the right point.
The obvious point is you can't infer causality.
But the second order point to that is if there is causality, it doesn't tell you if it's
adaptive or maladaptive.
That's the nuance.
And this idea of necessary but not sufficient to me is very important in biology because
you can have things that are causal, necessary but not sufficient.
I just told you one.
Exactly.
Causal, sufficient but not necessary.
And most of all, causal neither necessary nor sufficient.
And people love to dismiss those things.
I'll give you an example.
Smoking and lung cancer.
There's never been a trial.
I'm going to argue smoking is causal with lung cancer, just as I'll argue that smoking
is causal with cardiovascular disease through different mechanisms, endothelial dysfunction
in the latter.
But no one in their right mind would say that smoking is either necessary nor sufficient.
Lots of smokers don't get lung cancer.
Lots of smokers don't get heart disease.
Lots of people who get heart disease and lung cancer don't smoke.
So isn't it interesting that you can have something that is neither necessary nor sufficient
and yet can play a causal role in a disease?
Again, people might be listening going, what the hell is he making such a big deal out
of this for?
I make a big deal out of this for because when you get to complex diseases like cancer
and Alzheimer's disease and atherosclerosis, it is very unlikely you will find something
that is necessary and sufficient.
They're very rare to find those exceptions.
These are such multifaceted diseases and there are so many different ways to skin a cat.
You know, when you talk about cardiovascular disease, you've got like four completely different
things that have to be going on to cause this disease.
You have to have lipoproteins trafficking the sterols into the sub endothelial space.
You have to have the endothelial dysfunction to enable that to get in there and get retained.
You have to have the inflammatory response.
You take one of those things away, you change the dynamic of the disease.
And your other point is a great one.
Even if you can infer causality, it's not entirely clear what's adaptive and what's
maladaptive.
So our experiments really showed this mitochondria's necessary tumor genesis.
So it's interesting that paper you referred to, Mandarhan and I were graduate students
together in postdoc.
When I was starting my postdoc, he was sort of finishing his graduate training with Craig
Thompson and we were in the same lab and we actually worked together.
So he's an old friend of mine and obviously Craig's a former mentor and I like Luke Antley
a lot.
But that paper when it came out in 2009, right around at that point when it came out in science,
we had sent our paper to science and showing that mitochondria and is a tumor genesis,
they didn't send it out.
They said, oh, come on, this is no.
So then we sent it to 11 other journals.
No editors sent it out.
Cancer cells, cell nature, nature medicine, you know, nature cell biology, general clinical
medicine, nobody sent it out because the review didn't say mitochondria are not functional.
It just didn't mention anything about mitochondria.
It sort of just provided an explanation of the glucose, like glucose to lactate.
Why do tumors show that?
And it's for the biomass, not the energy, right?
That was the point.
And it didn't say it was sort of agnostic about mitochondria, right?
And the review if you go back, but people misinterpret that and saying, oh yeah, mitochondria
are not necessary.
It's all about glycolysis.
Let's target glycolysis.
So eventually the paper did get published in PNAS.
And I think that sort of started, I would argue, the revolution of looking at mitochondria
and cancer.
Other people were doing it as well.
But I sort of became a preacher just pointing it out.
Look, if you inhibit the respiratory chain, you can decrease tumor genesis.
Ten years later, to the best of my knowledge, and this is really important because it goes
back to the clinic, as far as I know, there are no clinical drugs in the clinic that are
necessarily targeting glycolysis.
Right now, there are potentially two drugs that target the mitochondria.
What do they target specifically?
So one of them is a complex one inhibitor that the folks at MD Anderson have generated.
And they just published two papers in Nature Medicine showing-
Different from Fennformin.
They're Fennformin, yeah.
They're different from Metformin and Fennformin.
They're much stronger.
They know the binding side.
By the way, they use the same yeast, NDI1, complex one that doesn't bind to Metformin
but doesn't bind to their drug as well to show-
Test it.
So how will they prevent toxicity?
Yes, yes.
So now they're doing a trial in AML.
And so this is a million dollar question.
And can you find a therapeutic window where maybe the drug gets taken up preferentially
by, just because of the properties, by leukemic cells or prostate or lung cancer cells, but
spares the brain, the heart and other organs where you could have toxicity.
So that's the big issue.
The good news is if you inhibit complex one, it will decrease tumor genesis.
The bad news is it might kill you, right?
So we've got to find that window.
And does it also work well with immunotherapy?
That's an open question, right?
Which is then the new kid on the block.
Does it help synergize with immunotherapy or does it prevent the immune function?
So all of this has to be worked out.
But my point is that there's some space in this area.
The other one is a drug by Rafaela Pharmaceuticals and full disclosure, I sit on their scientific
advisory board.
Thank you.
And I'm not pitching anything here simply.
In fact, they were already doing this stuff.
We're just sort of giving them some, you know, my little biological insight, which is I'm
trying to provide today.
But they've already done a clinical trial and I'll send it to you.
It was published in Landsend Oncology.
And it was in panicuretic cancer, just a safety trial.
Phase one.
And it targets alpha-keto, TCA cycle enzymes.
So it's preventing the TCA cycle from functioning to build that biomass.
And did they generate any data on the tissue specificity of that agent?
Not yet.
So this is the kind of stuff that needs to be done to try that drug and do the kind of
experiments where you can see TCA cycle metabolites changing pre and post drug treatment of a
particular tumor and then correlating that with success of remission and, you know, all
the usual parameters.
Now what's interesting about that drug, again, is why would that be safe?
Any of this.
The only way these drugs can be safe is they somehow preferentially are getting more into
the tumors than-
Or they're just so weak that they're not bringing you below the threshold of shutting
off the TCA.
Yeah.
And maybe they combine well.
So I can tell you, if you give the standard care of therapy cisplatin, one of the chemotherapies
or targeted therapies like BRAF inhibitors, is what happens, as you know, the primary
tumor sort of debulks, right?
It slows down and slowly you get resistance and then it comes back.
During that slow resistance phase, at that point, they're really dependent on mitochondrial
function.
So there might be a window to attack it with like BRAF inhibitors or cisplatin.
And again, like everything else, they're going to have to find that sweet spot.
See, to me, that's where I think this has to go.
I mean, I've always found immunotherapy to be the most elegant of all approaches to cancer.
I'm highly biased because that's what I studied.
But ultimately I think the Swiss cheese approach has to be the approach too, which is why would
we only take one modality of therapy?
If you're David and you're trying to slay Goliath in the fairy tale, one stone to the
head does it.
And in the real world, to take a Goliath down, I think you need to bang him at the knees
and when he bends over and complains about it, bang him in the other knee.
And when he's complaining about that, whack him in the hamstring.
And in other words, you've got to be able to do successive blows to a vulnerable cell.
And that's going to be, yeah, when is it most dependent on the mitochondria?
Okay, well, bang, now you hit with that therapy.
And then all of a sudden, to your point earlier, maybe at some point you begin to weaken it,
you make it more identifiable from an immune perspective and bang, that's when you would
hit with the immunotherapy.
The last point I really like, would the immune system recognize that tumor better if the
mitochondria of that tumor was not working properly?
Yeah, see that's, I mean, I'm super- Or maybe release that mitochondrial DNA, for
example, as it's dying.
As long as it were specific, right?
As long as it didn't create a diffuse immune reaction, but instead-
A localized-
Allowed the body to say that's not self.
Right.
And I haven't done a podcast yet on immunotherapy.
I want to have Steve Rosenberg on to talk about this because, I mean, who better to
talk about this with?
But anyway, so let's talk about another issue in cancer, right?
Which is, I mean, I think everybody agrees that most cancers involve somatic mutations.
There are very few cancers that involve germline mutations.
Those are the exceptions.
But the general one is these are acquired mutations.
Now some have argued, and this is a very minority opinion, but some have argued that
the somatic mutations of the nuclear genome are actually the result of the mitochondrial
dysfunction.
I think the majority would argue, no, it's the other way around that the nuclear genomic
mutations somatic are actually what leads to ultimately whatever's happening in the
mitochondria that may be dysfunctional, may be maladaptive, may be adaptive.
You would be in the latter camp, correct?
Completely.
100%.
And again, this is why this clinical trials are really important.
This is why the metformin trial is important, right?
So I've told you two things.
I've told you three points and it's that are quite contrarian.
We started with antioxidants, that there's no evidence that antioxidants in large scale,
the dietary antioxidants, just to be clear, vitamin E, vitamin C, have had any benefit
to mankind and womankind, right?
For human health and disease.
It just hasn't worked out.
So either we haven't built the right antioxidants or the theory that Ross and oxidants are bad,
that theory is off.
And I would argue that theory is off because if anything, normally we use oxidants as signaling
molecules.
The second thing I told you about is the fact that during aging, yeah, it might have conjured
decline, but that correlates and it could be adaptive, very contrarian point of view.
If anything, if you gave an agent that decreases mitochondrial function, like metformin, that
that could be a good anti-aging therapy, right?
It's not turning on mitochondria, but turning off mitochondria.
And by the way, Andy Dillon, a good friend of mine I was there with yesterday, who's
done beautiful work on worms.
Clearly in the worm, when you decrease complex one or three, you live longer as a worm.
Yeah, I don't know Andy, but David has spoken so highly of him, David Sabatini, you have
as well.
I need to meet Andy and hopefully interview him at some point and talk about all this
stuff.
Of course, it could be going back to your point that the inhibition of complex one,
which inhibits mitochondrial function inside of a non-toxic range might not actually be
part of why metformin makes you live longer.
That might just be a, it survives despite that, not because of that, the organism.
Yeah, I would argue that metformin being anti-inflammatory and-
I want to come back to you, Andy, inflammatory in a second.
Yeah, we'll come back to that.
So the third point is that like colitis is necessary, but so is mitochondria, that cancer
cells use a robust mitochondrial function.
And if that function doesn't work, the TCA cycle or the respiratory chain doesn't work
in most cancers, you don't get tumors.
Now there are these rare cancers where it has a TCA cycle mutation.
And so this is another sort of logic point, right?
So they look at that rare phenomenon, the exception to the rule.
And some people say, oh, there are these rare cancers that have a TCA cycle mutation.
Aha, therefore, cancers have TCA cycle mutations.
Oh, come on, this is illogical.
It's the exception to the rule of most cancers, at least that we've studied, whether it's
in cell culture, in mouse models, and my good friend, Ralph Debradinis, who's doing glucose,
he's doing trace certain experiments like Joshua Benowitz has done as well.
They can clearly show the TCA cycle is quite robust.
And so why those cancers can arise is an interesting question, but they're the exception to the
rule.
So I'm in that camp.
Well, and the other, I guess, point to it.
And if I'm right, by the way, then these drugs, if they make it in the clinic and really make
a difference, voila.
The other thing that I think would favor the genomic argument is a lot of the viral research,
because when we see viral vectors driving cancer, it's presumably nuclear DNA.
I'm not aware, are there viruses that are causing cancer through infecting mitochondrial
DNA?
I don't believe that.
I think it's all nuclear, personally.
So that would be another...
Yeah, if anything, so renal cell carcinomas are really...
So you know these oncocytomas, you know what they are, benign tumors, essentially.
If you look at renal cancer...
Just for the listener to understand, meaning they still grow in a somewhat unregulated
way, but they don't have metastatic potential.
So you're not going to die from these things, but they're benign growing tumors.
Even those, the major mutation that they have is in the respiratory chain.
So in other words, again, they're very rare, but sometimes you do get complex one loss,
but you don't get an aggressive tumor.
You get this benign tumor at best.
So again, it's almost a barrier to progression.
And that's from human genetic data.
So I'm in the camp, but ultimately we can do all these cute little mouse experiments
and the data is very clear in our hands and Ralph's hand and Josh's hands and lots of
people's and the mitochondria necessary for tumor genesis, TCA cycle activity.
The ultimate proof is, well, let's inhibit the TCA cycle for prostate cancer, for colon
cancer, for pancreatic, and does it make a difference with immunotherapy or chemotherapy?
So we'll see.
And by the way, the same one goes to metformin, which is that if metformin really does work
as a potentially as an anti-aging strategy and we can show that those effects are due
to complex one inhibition, then it's hard to think why that, you know, that might, this
idea that mitochondria rate limiting or declining to a point during aging that's injurious,
that idea can't hold up because you're giving essentially a weak complex one inhibitor to
turn on stress responses, which means you must have enough mitochondrial activity as
you age.
It's down, but not gone, right?
Right.
Enough to not be rate limiting.
And of course the antioxidant one, we've already won that battle, right?
Because the trials have all failed.
And for the person listening to this who's scratching their head and confused and says,
does this mean I shouldn't be taking my vitamin C or my vitamin E or my Whole Foods proprietary
antioxidant blend of blueberry skin?
I think you're right.
The answer is pretty clear that the harm of taking those things might not be great, but
the benefits seems to be negligible to nowhere.
That's a fair statement.
Are there benefits you think to the natural quantities of antioxidants we consume in our
food?
So, for example, berries do contain lots of antioxidants.
I would love to talk about those benefits without saying go up and take ground berry
capsules or something like that.
Do you still think there is a benefit in having ... In other words, if a berry doesn't give
you benefit in the antioxidant, there's not a hell of a lot of benefit in it because it's
basically just a vehicle to deliver fructose, which I could argue you don't need any fructose
in your life.
And it's a vehicle to deliver glucose, but you can get glucose in better forms or more
of it elsewhere.
So is there some other benefit?
So I don't know much about berries, so the best one is vitamin C, right?
Like how much should you take?
Okay, so let's talk about an orange.
Is there some benefit in eating an orange?
Yes.
Okay, so what's the benefit in eating an orange from an antioxidant standpoint?
Yes, so there are enzymes that control DNA methylation and other reactions.
So simply to maintain proper function of gene expression so that your genes turn on and
off properly, there are enzymes that are dependent on vitamin C. And you basically
need about an orange a day or a glass of orange juice.
Please please please.
Not orange juice.
Not orange juice, fine fine fine.
But what I mean is you don't need to take 10 oranges, right?
An orange a day is enough, right?
To give you enough vitamin C to make those reactions work properly.
And one or two oranges, but you don't need to then go and take 400.
But that has nothing to do with the antioxidant properties of vitamin C.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
It has nothing to do with the, nothing to do with the Ross and all of this stuff we
talked about.
It has to do with running some enzymes that are important for controlling gene expression.
I know those genes that have to get turned on and off are dependent on those.
And of course there are some people who might not be taking, getting into vitamin C due to
their diet.
They go, they go, they go.
Yeah, they go.
Pretty hard to do that.
Pretty hard to do it.
I mean, citric acid, I mean, you know, we have it a lot of places.
Would you be comfortable speculating that a cancer patient in particular should avoid
antioxidants?
No, no, I don't think, I don't think the dietary, well, let me rephrase my question.
I don't mean through dietary means, but through supplemental means.
Like if any patient could actually be harmed by an antioxidant, could it be a cancer patient?
Well, the, one of the trials, the lung cancer trial argued that I think was a vitamin E
trial and they did worse.
And in mice you can recapitulate that.
So why is that?
It's not clear.
So I personally don't take any of these supplements because I think I've got a reasonable diet.
So just like you.
So why don't you take metformin?
I will not take anything unless it's done, any drug, unless it's gone through a rigorous
clinical trial.
That's just my own bias.
Now some people would say, okay, you're aging now.
So you're going to, by the time they do a trial, you may not be around.
So why not take a chance, right?
Lots of people argue this about NAD boosting pills, right?
That you should just take any D boosting pill by the time people do a clinical trial and
all of that.
It'll take years and years and years.
And for those people who are already later in life, you know, go ahead and take metformin.
So putting your bias aside, because inherent in your bias is an assumption, which is the
risk of taking it is greater than the benefit of not taking it.
So either you don't think the benefit is that much or you think the risk is maybe greater
than some do.
And you're certainly somebody who's in a position to evaluate both.
So tell me where it fails.
Is it a not enough benefit or a too much risk problem?
Actually I'm not convinced about how much benefit.
For someone like me who exercises especially, right?
I mean, the best effect of metformin and it's still it's anti-diabetic effect.
And you and I both know you lift weights, you run, you're active, you sort of mimic
the effects of metformin in many ways.
Activist is AMPK, you get the muscle benefits.
So why should I take that?
Now you could say, well, maybe for as an anti-cancer prevention agent, maybe the data
as an anti-cancer, we'll see where that pans out as a large scale trial that's going to
come out.
Wait, you're not talking about tame, are you?
No, no, not tame is the anti-aging trial.
That won't be done for another five years.
There's a breast cancer.
Will that ever be done?
Yeah, I think so.
I think so.
But if you're healthy and you're active, it's hard to see why you would take it.
Now of course you could argue that as you've aged, you've gotten some indication that things
aren't working as well and therefore you should help take it as a compliment, whatever loss
you had.
Maybe you're a little diabetic, maybe the one place I'm rethinking about metformin a
lot is whether it's a mild anti-inflammatory agent.
So in other words, it sort of keeps inflammation down all the time and whether the effect of
that over 20, 30 years, if you and I are sort of in our 40s and that would have a benefit
20, 30 years later.
What's the mechanism by which, I'm glad you brought that up because I forgot to revisit
it.
And one of my favorite trials is the Cantos trial where they basically targeted IL-1 beta,
a pro-inflammatory agent directly.
And it didn't change the lipid profile.
But it reduced cardiac mortality.
Exactly, which tells you that inflammation is...
Oh yeah.
And there's going to be another trial announced very soon that I think will show similar results
using low-dothymacetrexate.
Of course, I could be proved wrong and maybe that's not, I don't know what the trial is
going to show, but that's the hypothesis.
Let's take as a fact, just for the sake of time, that lowering inflammation has wonderful
benefits.
What's the mechanism by which metformin will reduce inflammation?
So we think that reactive oxygen species, the free radicals, can serve as signaling
molecules to activate cytokines.
And metformin by inhibiting the respiratory chain, which is a major site of those reactive
oxygen species, decreases reactive oxygen species and decreases cytokine in production.
And again, a little bit, right?
It's a weak inhibitor of the respiratory chain.
So if you knock out the respiratory chain completely, you can never turn on the cytokines.
You've got a bigger problem.
You get a bacterial infection, et cetera.
So this is just, again, dampening it enough that if you get an infection, you can still
respond.
But just keeping the set point where you're at a little bit lower and whether that has
good effects over 30 years, 20 years of keeping inflammation down.
And then there may be some benefit to that.
So then one other place you might want to do it is if you live in Beijing or in Delhi,
because pollution increases inflammation.
That's well known.
It increases IL-6, right?
So in those sort of places, taking something that might decrease inflammation might be
helpful potentially.
And how robust are the data on the immune modulating or inflammatory modulating benefits
of metformin?
Is that relatively, I mean, it's not as strong as the other stuff we've talked about, is
it?
No.
I mean, I think there's not that many papers on it to be determined, but it's something
that we're thinking a lot about as a mechanism of why it might have anti-aging properties.
Well, look, speaking of anti-aging, let's go back to NAD because we sort of skirted
around a little bit.
Obviously, one of the most popular types of supplements being offered on the market today,
and there are several of them, are supplements that are aimed at delivering precursors to
NAD production.
So again, the logic here is it's generally well regarded that cells can't take up free
NAD.
They have to make their own NAD.
Josh and Rabinowitz and colleagues actually published a paper in June of this year that
demonstrated that the NAD must be made in the cytoplasm, not in the mitochondria, and
it's actually transported from the cytoplasm to the mitochondria.
And these supplements mainly went to the liver first.
Well, even before that, but just to explain the logic, the logic is you can make NAD from
NR or NMN, and NR and NMN exist in equilibrium, if I'm not mistaken.
And the de novo pathway, which is from tryptophan.
That's right.
As well.
So by giving these precursors, the cells can take those up and presumably make NAD there
and get more of that NAD into the mitochondria, where presumably it, I think the main argument,
if I'm not mistaken, is actually not around the ETC, the ethylene transport chain, but
more around having them as cofactors for the sirtuins, because the sirtuins of course play
these two roles of acetylating, deacetylating as gene regulators.
They're basically turning on and off genes.
So I think the thinking is, and again, I don't want to speak out of turn.
This is not my area of expertise, but more NAD should be an important cofactor for sirtuins,
which are a NAD dependent histone deacetylases, HDEX.
Is that, did I get the story mostly right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay.
I mean, that's the simplest hypothesis.
NAD levels decline in aging.
You lose sirtuin activity declines, which is not good.
Right, because you now lose the ability to control gene expression either on or off.
You boost the NAD as it's declining and you get a little bit increase in sirtuin activity.
Right, right, which so totally makes sense conceptually.
So I think what Josh did is a great experiment.
He basically asked when you take these supplements, where do they go?
And a lot of it goes to the liver.
Eventually it makes its way into other tissues, because there was this simple idea like it's
going to get into the brain easily.
It's going to go to your heart.
It's going to go everywhere and it's going to do exactly what you said and therefore
have all these magical properties.
I think the place where NAD supplements and metformin start to cross talk is two places.
The first is it goes to the liver.
So it might be having some metabolically healthy effects on the liver like metformin, similar
to like what metformin does, potentially.
It's a hypothesis, by the way.
The second one is I think it gets into immune cells.
You think that NR, let's just make it simple and talk about NR because that's the preparation
that's more commercially available.
You think that NR is being taken up by immune cells.
Potentially.
But wouldn't Josh's paper contradict that?
I don't remember if they looked at all the immune cells.
Well, I don't think they did, but it isn't the takeaway from Josh's paper that the first
pass effect is so significant that all of the NR was getting taken up by the liver.
But it still circulates in the blood, right?
And your immune cells are in the blood.
So I don't know.
And by the way, in Josh's paper, he also said that the liver, once it makes a downstream
products of NR, it distributes it back into circulation to the rest of the tissue.
What did it deliver, remind me?
Was it delivering NAD?
No, no.
It was delivering what downstream product?
I think it was NAMM.
Okay.
Yeah, I don't remember.
And can NAMM be taken up by the other cells?
Yeah.
And can NAMM work its way back?
I don't remember the paper, yeah.
Well, I'll put you on the spot with something that's not your world.
Well, no, it's not, again, pathways.
I'll talk with Josh.
But I think the more simpler point is, is what I think Josh's paper is getting at and
what you're getting at is, really, this stuff gets everywhere and has magical properties?
And then he starts to argue, well, it goes onto the liver or only to certain tissues.
And I'm just arguing that a tissue, if you can call it, is not really, but a compartment
that we don't think about enough of whether it's with metformin or NAD supplements, air,
the inflammatory cells.
So what would an inflammatory cell?
How would it benefit from having more NAD?
Well, I mean, again, for the same reasons, right?
The sirtuin reason?
Yeah.
Or some other NAD-dependent process that in an immune cell that might be important.
And by the way, there is an enzyme that gets rid of NAD.
It's an NADase, basically, CD38.
It's most abundant on immune cells.
Yeah.
So there's an immune connection.
I didn't realize there was much CD38 off immune cells.
I mean, depends.
Yeah, yeah.
No, I mean, I'm not disagreeing with you.
I just didn't know that.
I was a little bit out of my wheelhouse, but I'm just speculating that there might
be a connection between these supplements as basically working as mild anti-inflammatory
agents.
Now, of course, the other way that these things are typically delivered is through intravenous
NAD, which says, hey, you don't need to make it.
We'll give it to you.
We know you can't take NAD orally, so you have to do it intravenously.
There, I think it went everywhere in that paper, right?
But does it get into the cells?
Is there a cell that can take up NAD?
I don't think so, but again, I don't remember Josh.
I asked for the next podcast.
We have stated away from NAD biology.
It's been quite a contentious field.
As you know, Josh and others are doing really nice experiments.
We've avoided NAD.
What we haven't avoided is NAD to NADH ratio, right?
Because that's linked to complex one function.
That's what my performance tweak is.
And NAD to NADH ratio, to the best of my knowledge, isn't controlling sirtuins or we don't have
great evidence for that.
NAD itself might be.
But what NAD and NADH ratio is doing biologically, or how does a cell process that ratio, is
right now probably the thing that keeps me up at night the most.
My favorite new theory of life, as we know, which is tied to that ratio.
Now, speaking of supplements, you alluded to one earlier, I alluded to it, called MITO-Q.
I'm getting a lot of questions from patients about this.
Should I be taking this?
Can you tell us what it is?
It's basically CoQ.
It's CoQ-10.
So people take lots of CoQ.
What does MITO-Q differ from the regular CoQ-10?
It has a cation attached to it.
Those mitochondria are pumping those hydrogen ions.
They're quite negative in charge, like a battery, positive.
And so it will take a molecule that is very positively charged.
So by putting a cation on it, which is positively charged, you increase its affinity for the
cell?
Into the mitochondria.
Right.
The problem is that therapeutic windows are very tight on that because when we give MITO-Q,
we can shut off a lot of Ross production and all those beneficial stuff gone.
So you put it on stem cell.
Stem cells don't renew.
You put it on immune cells because they don't get activated.
And so I think, again, antioxidants get tough because they have normal biological roles.
And is CoQ considered an antioxidant?
Coenzyme Q?
The reduced form of it is, which is ubiquinol.
Yes.
And do you think so therefore reduced?
But they're hard, by the way.
You know this.
Super, super hydrophobic, right?
Yeah.
Most commercially available preparations don't even seem to have any bioavailability.
You can take a ton of them and you can't measure it in the blood.
But there are potent ones that make their way into the blood and you can measure those
levels.
I think the question is, is there benefit in that?
Again, your view is no.
My view would be no.
And your view is it could be harmful?
I think a lot of these antioxidants have poor availability.
So in the Peter Attia 2x2 is on the x-axis you think about harm and on the y-axis you
think about benefit.
But to simplify it, even though these are continuous variables, you go with two categories.
So on the x-axis, which is harm, you think about picking something up in front of a tricycle
versus picking something up in front of a train.
Obviously, one has much more dire consequences.
And then in the benefit, it's picking up a Bitcoin versus a quarter.
And so do you view most of these antioxidants CoQ10, MITOQ as picking up quarters in front
of tricycles where the upside, if they work, is probably not that big but the downside
is also probably not that big?
Yeah.
And do you put a metformin in that category or do you think metformin has more potential?
It has more potential.
But you still don't take it.
I still don't take it.
So you think metformin is potentially picking up a Bitcoin in front of a train?
Maybe.
Time will tell.
People are now doing clinical trials with metformin for anti-cancer.
I mean, clearly, it's still one of the first line antidiabetic drugs.
And people are now running them through inflammation models.
We've done some interesting work around pollution and metformin, which I cannot comment on.
So there's a lot of interest beyond the antidiabetic effects of metformin.
And we'll see how it plays out.
From our point of view, we want to really nail down is it by inhibiting mitochondrial
complex one?
Yeah, that's super elegant stuff.
So you've got to go back and do the experiment we talked about with the eucenic.
We're making, you know, we made mice in all of this.
So we're doing that.
Just to finish, you know, time is probably, we've probably gone over as always.
But so in my world, those roasts from mitochondria are beneficial.
And you don't, you know, there's not, I'm not sure if there's a window where antioxidants
get in to really scavenge them.
So I don't consider them harmful, Peter, right, for that reason.
So generally, roasts are good.
Again, very contrarian, but this is where the data is taking us.
So when is metabolism bad?
So my favorite new theory, which this is what I'm really excited about.
And I'm hoping somebody will give me lots and lots of money to test this because it's
way out there.
So if you think back about what causes pathologies like neurodegeneration, even diabetes, the
big idea for 20 years has been that proteins get misfolded or they aggregate the idea of
what's called proteotoxicity.
Let's clean up bad proteins.
So now they've done some trials in Alzheimer's and Parkinson's.
It hasn't quite worked out.
But you know, again, maybe they caught them too late.
Yeah, that's my argument.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
So I don't have a problem with the theory.
I think it's a nice theory.
I still think, you know, proteotoxicity is a real phenomenon.
It causes diseases, all that good stuff.
But what if, which is not a mutually exclusive idea, what if there's metabolite toxicity?
What does that mean?
That means that certain metabolites that are normally found and at low levels and they
do normal functions, if they rise, they can incur pathology.
So what's the evidence for that?
Well, this is where inborn errors of metabolism come in.
So they're, they're unfortunately, people have genetic mutations in metabolic genes.
And those pathways get altered and some metabolite increases or decreases is and that's causes
major pathology.
So we know that metabolites are at a certain threshold are sufficient to cause pathology
based on inborn errors of metabolism.
And so why couldn't it be that in Alzheimer's we have a particular metabolite or metabolites
that increase due to the tau and all the amyloid plaques that people talk about.
And those then are causing the early generation.
Again, not mutually exclusive.
Not mutually exclusive.
It's just a different way of thinking about it.
So one way you test it is, you know, someone's got to give me money to do this, but you start
screening metabolites in mice and rats and people and see if you see signatures.
And if you see certain signatures and you say, so I have one right now that I'm very interested
in is called L2 hydroxylglutarate, L2AG.
And I know that if a human has a mutation in a pathway that can't get rid of L2AG and
it starts to accumulate, they get a, they get neuropathology.
So could L2AG be elevated in Parkinson's and in Alzheimer's?
What's so cool about L2AG, and this is going to wrap everything up from the start, is if
mitochondria are not working, are not functional, the respiratory chain is not working, then
NAD goes down and NADH goes up and it will trigger L2AG.
That's the key trigger.
When NADH goes up and NAD goes down, L2AG gets made.
So is this why you don't take metformin?
No, because metformin is a weak, uh, use ratio has to change a lot.
This ratio has to change a lot.
So for example, are there physiologic conditions under which that ratio changes that much?
Hypoxia.
Ah, ah.
Hypoxia has been shown that L2AG levels actually increase and they can then function as a signaling
molecule.
So here is more where the organelle mitochondria is completely dysfunctional.
So complex one loss has been correlated with Parkinson's, dopaminergic neurons are not
functioning.
And so is L2AG elevated there?
So have you looked at, um, you know, the other patient population you should study this in
would be patients who undergo circulatory arrest in cardiac bypass.
So you're going to see, or even frankly, just bypass.
Because they're so hypoxic.
Yeah.
It'd be interesting to see, you know, quote unquote, this idea of pump head.
Can it be explained through any of this stuff?
Well, so one other thing that I like about this is, is that's an acute event, I think.
We don't see it acutely.
So you have a complex one and the NADH goes up, NAD goes down and a real severe inhibition.
It takes a long time for that to accumulate.
How long?
In cell culture with complex one, not 24 hours, a couple of days.
And you know, so you could imagine, let's just play fantasy here.
You get loss of complex one slowly in a dopaminergic neuron, which causes results in Parkinson's.
And then slowly over years, you get this accumulation of this particular metabolite.
And that could then cause the pathology.
Again, I'm very interested in just testing the broad idea that metabolites can cause
pathologies.
You know, like metabolite toxicity, like kind of like proteotoxicity.
Probably wrong, but at least it's original.
Well, I mean, it's just, I guess what the thing that would concern me is the ubiquity
of the potential signaling molecules and trying to identify like what the patterns
are.
Can that's a, I mean, look, there are no problems worth solving that are easy.
So, but boy, you have so many variables in so many directions.
You don't just have the number of metabolomics.
You have the time series in which they occur relative to an insult and then the amount
of exposure of each that's necessary to drive the disease.
It could be so easy to miss something with all of those variables, right?
Absolutely.
And that's why we're being very biased and going after this one.
Keep it simple.
Test that one.
But of course we could totally miss it because there could be five other metabolites that
might go up that might be causing the pathology and synchrony, right?
But at least this one is tied to mitochondrial function.
And so in mitochondria, really dysfunctional.
So we started with the powerhouse as people would say, well, mitochondrial dysfunction,
ATP goes down.
Okay.
I would say mitochondrial dysfunction.
Guess what?
L2AG goes up.
This two hydroxyglutarate.
So interesting.
So it's a new way to think about mitochondrial dysfunction that I'm very interested in pursuing.
So last thing I just wrote down when we were talking earlier and I want to come back to
it is talk to me a little bit about cortisol and your views on it.
How does cortisol interact with the mitochondria?
Yeah.
Well, I don't know.
Another one that I would love to work on.
So it's just a weird observation.
I don't know if you have this.
I mean, I think maybe in our circles we have a lot of kind of type A personalities who
exercise vigorously.
They wash their diet.
They do all this sort of stuff.
I don't know anybody that does that.
No, you don't know anybody.
No one.
Nobody.
But I always wonder if they're stressing themselves out by being so careful about everything,
you know?
And you know me, I am the opposite.
You've seen me eat and drink.
Yeah, but you're pretty fastidious with your exercise.
You play soccer every day.
No, I do.
And I don't overeat and I do time feedings, right?
I still fast 12 to 15 hours.
Most days closer to 15 hours.
I do watch what I mean.
But what I'm saying is I know people who get very, very regimented about these things.
And it's like the marathon runners who, you know, the old line that they die and don't
run marathons.
Well, I was with a friend last night and he was joking about this exact concept.
And he was talking about his, he's an orthopedic surgeon.
He was talking about his partner or somebody knows.
And he was like, the guy is so into yoga, but it's become, he's like, the way he described
it was really funny.
He's like, he's stuck in traffic and he's like, I got to get to my fucking yoga class.
Yes, exactly.
And it's like, yeah, no, of course there's the irony to that, right?
So, you know, your insulin levels might be fine and everything's fine, but you know,
what's your cortisol level?
So I'm fascinated by cortisol.
In fact, I'm fascinated by, I would love for you to basically develop a very simple
test that you can sell at Walgreens where you take a prick of blood and you can do it
as often as you want.
And you tell me my thyroid and hormones.
You tell me my insulin, my glucagon, my estrogen, my testosterone, my dopamine, serotonin, and
obviously cortisol, right?
These five or six, seven things that I just said, because it's about a lot of biology
or physiology can be explained.
Yeah, we're not going to be able to get it that way because cortisol is mostly bound
to albumin and cortisol binding protein.
So it's the free cortisol that exerts its metabolic effects and its physiologic effects.
And most of it's not free.
So you can only measure the free cortisol and saliva and urine.
And then the other, you know, of those other ones.
But you know what I'm saying?
Like, like I would love to have those, those hormones at my disposal.
I mean, is my testosterone too low?
My estrogen too high?
This too high?
Insulin.
You know what I mean?
Just having that data points all the time and then you could sort of modify your diet
and your exercise.
But I think the cortisol one is I pay more attention today to stress as than anything
else.
I'll be honest with you.
I mean, I still exercise and I watch what I eat.
Those things seem intuitive because I've done it for so long.
But I've been wondering if myself and many of my colleagues, especially because we fly,
get talks, you have grand pressures, a teenager daughter, she's lovely, lots of different
pressures we all have.
Right.
And if that somehow is being manifested metabolically through cortisol to the mitochondria, just
like we think about insulin.
Right.
So that's all.
That's the only reason I want to talk about cortisol.
No, I think I agree with that wholeheartedly.
I think certainly in the last three years as I've dug my heels into it, I think hypercorticillemia
is a problem.
And I think I wish people would think of these hormones through more broad endocrinologic
terms.
You know, it's very easy for people to think of hypo and hyperthyroidism.
We accept those as states.
You can be euthyroid or you can have too much or you can have too little.
And yet people have such a hard time thinking of insulin in those terms.
You can have too much, you can have too little.
There's a range in which this hormone makes sense.
And cortisol is probably equally important, if not more important in terms of the damage
that can be done, especially from too much with respect to everything from blood pressure,
which would then impact the endothelium.
What it does in terms of inhibiting melatonin secretion in the brain and melatonin obviously
plays an immediate role in terms of sleep, but also plays an indirect role in terms of
neuro regeneration.
So and that says nothing about what we just talked about, which was the role that cortisol
may even play in the mitochondria, which I'm just learning about, you know, literally
in the past couple of months.
So I don't disagree.
I think the challenge in many ways for anyone listening to this, if we're going to be brutally
honest, I think for many people it's easier to control what they eat, how they exercise
and exert discipline around taking medications, taking supplements.
But in many ways, one of the hardest things to control is our response to stress.
And I think that's an important distinction to make.
I don't think there's anything that's particularly troubling with being in stressful situations.
I think the difference is less about the situation you're in and more about the response you
have to it.
And that's probably where the greatest differences lie between people is there are some people
who can be in relatively low stress situations and yet they're sort of, they're not reacting
well to it.
They're not coping with it well.
And there are others who can be in-
They have different set points where they begin from.
Maybe.
I guess I just don't understand enough of this stuff.
I mean, I think-
But I don't hear too many people talk about it.
I don't know.
I think it's-
No, people talk about stress, but sort of like we talk about insulin all the time and
glucose levels and for men, testosterone, women-
You mean sort of in longevity circles?
Yeah, in longevity circles.
Like is that a variable we're missing?
No, I agree.
That's all I'm saying.
You're right.
I'm just pitching cortisol.
Well, part of it is we don't have a target for it, right?
No one's thinking about pharmacologic ways to manipulate this and we don't have great
obvious ways to curb our behaviors.
Like meditation probably is the single most valuable thing I've ever found to help regulate
this, but you also don't have the ability to measure cortisol levels that easily.
Every time you want to do one of these tests, it's, you know, you're collecting urine over
the course of a day and doing a bunch of other things.
So it's just, it's involved.
You don't have the-
Glass of wine?
Yeah.
You know, it's really funny.
There was a paper that came out probably about three months ago that looked at, basically
the punchline of the paper was look at any of those alcohol is toxic.
But you know, if you look at those events, it's like 950, 900,000.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, no, no.
It's like 954.
The point of it is there's no dose of ethanol where the ethanol becomes valuable, but the
toxicity takes a while to kick in.
So, you know, for some people, a glass a day seems perfectly reasonable.
There's no toxicity.
But the flip side of it is, and this is where I kind of try to have this discussion with
every patient is, look, I'm not going to tell somebody not to drink.
I mean, I'm not going to tell myself not to drink.
I probably have four drinks a week.
And you know, I pick and choose my shots.
You know, I have this rule called don't drink on airplanes because the alcohol on airplanes
sucks.
So I'm not drinking alcohol just for the sake of drinking alcohol.
But if you're sitting there and the alcohol is really great and it's something you really,
the downside of the ethanol, the hepatic toxicity of the ethanol can be offset by the emotional
benefit that could come from the enjoyment of having that glass of wine with your buddy.
That brings me to another one of those things we should always measure, ALT, you know, the
liver enzymes.
Yeah.
I agree.
How will your liver function?
How's your ALT this morning, by the way?
It's pretty good.
Yeah.
I went and checked it.
And so I think we're almost at the end.
Yeah.
So I have one question for you.
Oh.
To sort of wrap it up.
Wait, I didn't think that was part of the rule.
Well, it is because I'll tell you why.
So when I interact outside of the scientific circles, if I'm at a dinner party, if I'm
at a bar, if I'm on an airplane and whoever I'm engaging with, they ask me like, what
do you do?
Now, if I say I'm technically my title's professor of medicine and cell biology, if you say that,
they'd think, oh, you teach something.
And I do indirectly, but what we do is research.
So if I just say I do research or if I say I'm a scientist, they go, oh, well, that's
nice.
But the minute I say I'm a metabolism scientist and it's like, they light up and they want
the next question, which is, what should I eat?
You got it.
But wait, can I ask you a question?
Given that you know that that's going to happen, when you go to parties, do you go out of your
way to make sure that you don't prime people for that question?
Or do you enjoy being asked that question?
I think I enjoyed being asked that question initially as a way to tell people, look, science
is cool, metabolism is cool.
You know what I mean?
Sort of not think.
There's this image that people have about scientists.
As you can see, I'm pretty flamboyant.
So I figure, you know, something that they can relate to as a common language.
But now I regret it because all I hear about is, what should I eat?
What should I eat?
Oh yeah.
So let me give you a piece of advice on this now.
So first of all, I have the same problem whenever I'm in a situation.
Could be a wedding, could be a funeral, could be a party, doesn't matter.
So I've learned that there are two, I have two go to things that I tell people I do for
a living.
And I know enough about each of them that I can almost never get called out.
And the good news is both of these generate almost no follow up questions.
Now the difference is you're an extrovert and I'm an introvert.
So you at a party would like to talk to people.
I on the other hand don't.
I don't like to go to parties.
But if I'm dragged to a party, I don't want to be at parties.
I don't want to be at happy hours.
I don't want to be around anybody except two of my friends at a time sort of thing.
So I just tell people, I shouldn't admit this now because now if somebody hears this, they'll
know my trick.
All right, I'm not going to say it.
I'm not going to say it.
You're going to leave them hanging.
I'm going to leave them hanging.
But I have two awesome alter egos that whenever I'm at, and I, in fact, I busted one out last
night.
I was at a dinner thing last night.
I didn't know people.
And there were a lot of doctors there and there was a lot of butt sniffing, which always
happens at doctor parties where everybody wants to sniff everybody else's butt.
It's like kind of the dogs, you know, walking around sniffing each other's butts.
And there was a lot of what do you do?
Oh, I'm the chairman of this and I'm the chairman of that.
And I am the head of this and blah, blah.
And they looked at me.
What do you do?
And I just said, I'm a, and I said it.
And it was amazing.
The crickets are chirping.
Everybody is like, they don't know what to say.
And they said collectively nothing.
And then the discussion just went elsewhere and it was awesome.
I didn't have to talk about it.
All right.
So I do give an answer and I want you to tell me if this is the right answer or the
wrong answer.
I still like, and I know it got debunked a little bit.
I still like the Mediterranean diet.
Yeah.
I mean, not, I mean with curry, okay.
But generally that kind of died with nuts and avocados, a little red wine.
Well, when you say debunked, I mean, I'm not even sure I would agree on it.
No, I don't think it has.
But you know what I mean by that.
What you're referring to is the PradaMed study, which I'm guessing many people listening to
this will know what that is, but in case somebody's not, we'll certainly link to it.
This was a study that randomized something in the neighborhood of 7,500 patients, although
we'll come back to the word randomization.
I'll put a little asterisk beside that, into three groups, about 2,500 patients per group.
And they were randomized in a one to one to one fashion between a Mediterranean diet
that was high in extra virgin olive oil, a Mediterranean diet that was high in nuts and
a low fat diet.
And this was a primary prevention study, which makes it a very difficult study to do, especially
with nutritional therapeutics.
And the study was stopped early.
It was stopped at about 4.7 years if my memory shows correctly because the both Mediterranean
arms were outperforming the low fat arm.
Now, I used to view that as one of the more interesting studies ever done in nutrition
because nutrition studies generally suck.
It did have one major criticism that didn't get any attention at the time of the initial
publication, which I think was 2014 maybe.
And that was the performance bias.
So the groups that were getting olive oil and nuts had those products sent to them.
The low fat group, to my knowledge, did not receive anything, didn't get food given to
them.
Well, that creates the potential for a difference in behavior.
And that's problematic.
That's very problematic in clinical trials where you can't blind anyone.
But the more recent issue, the one that I think you're referring to is some irregularities
popped up in their randomization.
So some people doing post hoc analyses found, hey, these numbers don't make sense.
It's very improbable that these people were all randomly assigned.
And I believe, because it's been a while since I read the correction, that what they identified
was that a number of those patients were not randomized correctly, for example.
And it wasn't nefarious, but it was done through convenience.
So if you had a husband-wife team in the study, they were immediately put on the same diet,
which by the way is logical.
That's actually a better study design.
But you have to then change the statistics to accommodate for that because you have no
longer randomized each of those individuals.
They would be considered one randomization, not two.
To the best of my knowledge, even when you take into account those changes or those inconsistencies
or those methodologic failures, I don't believe it changed the results or the outcome of PREDIMED.
So we're still back to the initial limitation of were those representative diets and were
those subjects, victim for lack of a better word, but the victims of a performance bias.
So all that said, look, I think the Mediterranean diet, which is unfortunately not a very descriptive
term because what the hell is a Mediterranean diet?
Is that what people eat in Italy, Egypt, Greece, Spain?
So I guess the only opposition I would take to the concept is I like to be more specific
in my description of the diet.
What I dislike is high protein or a high carb or a high fat diet, like people love.
So the high protein people like is they want to look like a South Beach model essentially
as far as I can tell because you can lose weight.
The high carb, we know you talk about it all the time, why that's bad.
And sort of the ketogenic diet, I mean, it has some benefits maybe for the brain and
other systems, but it does make you insulin resistant.
I mean, there's data in mice.
Well, I would take issue with those data though, right?
So are there data that ketogenic diet make mice insulin resistant?
I don't think there's hundreds of studies in mice that people have done.
And so my favorite one, I think you should, I sent it to you where they looked at a whole
bunch of diets and essentially the best one was sort of a one third, one third, like 20
percent protein because we can both agree if there's too much protein, your mTOR might
be quite active if you need enough for your muscles.
But this is again, not in the elderly.
So again, not with the disease.
This is just primary prevention that we're talking about in healthy sort of 40 something.
So let's start with.
So it was relatively not high in protein and it was had about 40, 50 percent carbs
almost I think.
This is a mice study and then the rest was sort of the good fat, you know, avocados,
nuts and stuff like that.
And so I sort of liked that diet because it was a pretty good study in cell metabolism
published on these mice.
And to me, intuitively, some of this makes sense.
And so, you know, keeping protein not too high because you want to keep them closed
down.
And
Steven Simpson was the last author on.
Yeah.
Steven Simpson, I think.
Maybe there was like he's Australian.
Yes.
Yes, there was 25.
Again, I don't think there's a clear answer to this.
But you know, rather than answer the question, let me tell you my two cents on this topic.
One, I don't have a lot of interest in mouse studies for human nutrition.
I struggle with them because I think there are so many other issues going on and it's
very hard to make that.
That's a fair point.
The second thing is I always want to be sure that I'm distinguishing between short term
insulin resistance and long term insulin resistance.
So I think you're right.
In the short run, ketogenic diets in a non-trivial subset of people generate profound insulin
resistance in the muscle.
Again, I don't even know what insulin resistance means if we're going to be truthful.
Like if we're going to put me in the confession booth, I don't have a goddamn clue what that
term even means.
It's so ubiquitous.
Does it mean the failure of one type of cell but not another type of cell to respond to
insulin signaling?
I mean, all of these things.
But I think I know what you mean.
You can see huge elevations in glucose and insulin and basically a complete refusal of
the muscle to accept glucose in someone on a ketogenic diet when they first encounter
a carbohydrate.
But I think it's generally also regarded that after about three days of carbohydrate refeeding,
that effect goes away and that that effect is sort of a physiologic response to an individual
who's been so carbohydrate deprived that their muscles are basically saying, any glucose
in the system we're going to preferentially save for the brain since we now have all the
fatty acids and beta hydroxybutyrate in the world we need as metabolic substrate.
So the short answer is, I don't know, these days I find myself far more interested in
fixating less on the exact amount of this micronutrient or this micronutrient or that
micronutrient and more on the complete deprivation of calories for more prolonged periods of
time.
So people who are used to following me these days, I'm spending much more time thinking
about fasting than I am sort of sticking on one diet and sticking to it.
Yeah, so I basically eat a third of my calories probably from fat, carbs and protein.
And then the other thing is just the 15 hour fast every day.
But if you're getting a third from protein, that's probably quite a bit.
Probably I think.
I'll have to lower that.
I'm going to have to check your, check your torrid.
Well, maybe a third is too much but I eat a fair amount of protein probably.
Probably, you know.
At the parties, tell them you're a math professor.
They won't ask you any more questions.
I don't remember any math and we'll leave it at that.
Yeah, but hopefully they won't ask you the questions.
No, I'm an extrovert and I like talking about metabolism.
I don't have a good answer on the diet.
I have lots of answers on mitochondria and all that.
Then just tell them you're a mitochondrial expert but don't use the word metabolism.
Then people really look at you like, oh.
Anyways.
Hey, man.
Thank you so much for taking the time to talk about all this stuff.
I had written down a bunch of things I wanted to talk about and I think we actually got
through like half of them.
Oh, totally.
Okay.
Well, but that's the nature of this stuff.
It's so fun.
There's so many rabbit holes to go down.
In particular, I really love the double click deep dive on metformin which is something
I think a lot about myself.
Hopefully once we have some results and there's more clinical trials, we can come back and
we can really talk about some more answers.
All right, man.
Thanks.
Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com.
What's a nerd safari, you ask?
Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week
email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare
services including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own
risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical
advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they
have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash about.