Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode of The Drive. My guest this week is Sid Mukherjee,
who is a remarkable writer, in fact, a Pulitzer Prize winning writer and a remarkable physician
and scientist. In fact, probably there's nobody I know that combines those three things
as efficaciously as Sid does. His biography reads like I'm making it up. He studied biology
at Stanford. He then became a Rhodes Scholar, went to Oxford, earned his PhD in immunology,
returned to the United States to earn his MD at Harvard, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
Fast forward to today. He is an associate professor of medicine in the division of hematology
and oncology at Columbia University, which is where we met to do this interview. He has published
also and continues to publish consistently in both the New Yorker and the New York Times,
which in and of itself is quite a distinction as I would learn. Typically one is on either side of
those, but not both. And of course he's published in New England Journal of Medicine, Nature,
in addition to a whole host of other medical journals. I met Sid probably five years ago at
a dinner that was set up by Lou Cantley, someone I'll be interviewing very shortly, who will be a
guest obviously soon. And while I remember that dinner very well, I was surprised to learn that
it left such an impression on Sid and he described it as something to the effect of one of the most
interesting and perhaps important scientific collaborations in his life that stemmed from it.
As we kind of jotted out a napkin experiment that went on to become a paper that was published by
a group led by Lou and Sid. And that paper was published this past summer and we talk about that
in detail. That paper involved the use of ketogenic diets in combination with a class of
drugs called PI3 kinase inhibitors. We're going to go into great detail on that so I obviously don't
want to repeat any of that stuff here, but I think for those of you that are interested in cancer,
you're obviously going to find this episode very interesting. But the other thing with Sid is,
it doesn't matter if you have no interest in cancer. I think you'll find this discussion
interesting because Sid has a way of making everything interesting and that to me is part
of Sid's gift. When I got his book, The Gene, in the summer of 2016 when it came out, it's one of
probably only six books in my life that I was not able to stop reading from the moment I started. So
it's one of those things where everything else I was doing had to be put aside for a few days until
I could finish that book. That's just the way Sid writes and that's also the way he speaks. He is a
unique human being and I think that will come across in this interview. The other thing that
was a total pleasant surprise to me was in doing the research for this podcast was coming across
a book that I was ashamed to admit I didn't even know he'd written called The Laws of Medicine.
That's because it's called The Three Laws of Medicine and we talk about these three laws and
rather than even stating them now, I just think it's worth this podcast is worth the price of
admission just on the basis of understanding those three laws. So with that, I hope you will
welcome Sid to the show and I do want to just remind folks to please sign up for the email
list. I've been putting a lot of effort into those emails every Sunday morning they go out
and I hope that they're at least worth some value. I think they are and I like to be able to
kind of share things with folks that I'm reading or seeing along the way and they don't always
have to do with longevity. Keep in mind one of the things that I think takes up more actual time
than anything else with respect to this podcast is putting together the show notes. So Bob and
Travis work really hard on those and the feedback we've been getting is incredible. People keep
saying, my God, how do you make these things? And the short answer is I don't. I don't do any of it,
but Bob and Travis do, especially Travis. And I think that if you spend a few minutes looking at
that stuff, especially if you find some of the content challenging and when we get into technical
terms, which we do on some of the podcasts, you're pretty much going to find everything in the show
notes. Lastly, if you're enjoying this, it would be an honor if you would head on over to Apple
Podcast reviews and leave us a review, especially if it's a positive one, but we'll take a negative
one too, as long as you can be constructive in your feedback. So without further delay,
here is my guest today, Sid Mukherjee. Hey, Sid, thanks for making time. My pleasure. Thanks for
being here. Yeah, I don't get up to this part of the city very often. It's a bit of a hike.
Well, it's a massive medical school and it's hard to imagine it anywhere else except for
uptown in this way. You know, we go right all the way to the river. It's amazing. And the last time
I was up here was to see another one of your colleagues on the other side of the street,
Rudy Weibel, who's a good friend. And I used to be up here a lot more often. So it was nice to come
back. Most of our podcasts go really, really long. This one, I don't think we have that luxury of
time. So I kind of want to get right into things. But before we do, I certainly think for the
listener who doesn't know you well, your background, which I'll allude to a lot in the
introductions. We don't spend too much time on it, but you grew up in India, came to the US.
Did you do college here? I went to college at Stanford. Yeah. Oh, that's right. You went to
undergrad at Stanford. Okay. Then medical school at Harvard. Actually, then in the middle, I was
away for three years. I did a... You did a Rhodes scholarship. Yeah. Are you a Rhodes scholar?
I was a Rhodes scholar and that's where I got my PhD and my PhD is in immunology,
which is a subject that I left behind. Went to medical school at Harvard Medical School,
then did my fellowship and my internship, my residency at Mass General Hospital, fellowship
at the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, and then started my own lab and clinical practice at
Columbia University and have come back to immunology in a strange, widening circle of a way.
Yeah. The first time we met was a dinner that Lou Cantley had planned for us. This is about three
or four years ago. And I remember at the time, the topic that Lou is passionate about, that I'm
passionate about was sort of metabolism of cancer. And at the time, it wasn't something that seemed
as interesting to you as it is today. And I know today I want to talk so much more about that,
because the work you guys have done in the last few years is in many ways what I think is the most
interesting stuff to talk about. It was also a tough dinner because you don't eat most things.
It's hard to have dinner with someone when half the menu is off the menu. So anyway,
we somehow managed and scraped by and it was a wonderful evening. And actually led to...
What was that? Five years ago? Yeah. Led to one of the most interesting and perhaps important
scientific collaborations in my life. With Lou. With Lou. But it was that dinner which kind of
hammered. It was in a Japanese restaurant on the Upper East Side in a tiny little place.
You remember? That's exactly, I know exactly where you were.
I know exactly where it was. Well, because we wrote on a... It was a little bit like one of
these napkin experiments where you write on a napkin an idea. And that idea takes five years
to come alive. This thing that was sketched on a napkin that evening and is now leading to actually
kind of a massive clinical trial across multiple sites, very energetic teams coming into all of
this out of that little napkin on a Japanese restaurant. Yeah, that was a really fun night.
Prior to that, I had read The Emperor of All Maladies. I don't think the gene was out yet.
The gene was not out yet. I want to spend just a couple minutes on The Emperor of All Maladies
because if there's anybody listening to this who hasn't read it, you won the Pulitzer Prize for
that book, I believe. I did, yes. Yeah. So it's a must read. Having myself studied in oncology,
there was so much that I learned. I trained at Hopkins, which is... So we're in the Hallstead
School of where the mastectomy was created, where many of these things were created. But to really
understand the history of Bernard Fisher's role in the mastectomy, it's just an unbelievable story.
My only criticism was at the time quite a depressing story. Yeah. I mean, I'm not saying
that to be critical. I understand that. It's less a criticism of you than the field. No, no. It was,
to me actually, interestingly, people often bring this up idea up. For me, it was actually... It's
far from a depressing story. It's just the opposite. In fact, if we don't contend with the
question of how... I mean, The Emperor of All Maladies, just for people who don't know,
is a history of cancer, starting from its first description in Egypt, right down to my own patients.
Thousands of years of a journey against a disease that seems to morph and change over time. Every
time we look at it, it has a new form. It reflects our own diversity to some extent, our own
wyliness, our own imagination as humans. So to me, not a depressing book, because it is a way to
look directly at the face of the enemy. And I don't find that depressing. I find that clarifying.
And there are many, many high points in this journey. There's the invention of the great
surgeries that save tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands of lives around the world. The
dramatic advances against breast cancer and most importantly against some variants of leukemia,
where the mortality was 100% in 1950, and is five or 10% now. 95% change in mortality is a huge
difference in must rank as one of the great medical inventions of our time. So for me,
far from a depressing book, but to me, a clarifying book that tries to clarify why
we're here today, where we're going, what happens next, why we're not doing certain things, why we
are doing certain things. So that's my impression of what happened at the end of that book.
When did the idea to write, as it's really referred to the biography of cancer, when did
that idea come to you? Was it in your fellowship and your training at some point?
Yeah, I was training and it was a very simple moment. Actually, I remember a woman who I was
treating for cancer came to me and I was giving her yet another trial of targeted therapy, a new
kind of therapy. And she finally sat down one afternoon and she said, where are we going
with all of this? Why are we here? How do we get here? And she was of course asking me in a very
personal level, but you could take that question and make it a much, much larger question. Where
are we going in this battle against cancer? Why are we here today? What happens next? Why aren't
we elsewhere? How much of this is the wildness of this family of diseases? How much of this is the
capacity to use our, the greatest skills of our imagination against this illness? You know,
in the 1930s, 1940s, 1950s, when you asked a child what the outer limit of their scientific
imagination was, they would say, I want to be a rocket scientist and I want to send a rocket to
the moon. By the 1950s, 60s, 70s, if you ask that same child what the outer limits of their
scientific imagination would bring to the world, they would say, I want to cure cancer. It began
to define the limits of our scientific prowess, are the limits of our imagination, a world without
cancer. So there is a sense in which this is such an elemental illness. So much of our culture is now
defined through the lens of cancer. And what was shocking as a fellow, and I started encountering
cancer in the clinical sense, was shocking was that there was no such history, that it was all
ad hoc. And we knew little bits and pieces of it was like looking at the enemy through a
patchwork quilt with little holes in it. And the attempt here was to say, well, what is the full
story? What does the story look like? When did this start? Why did we end up here? What happens
tomorrow? What happens way into the future 100 years? What will cancer look like? And a lot of
thought experiments go into the book. So that's sort of the genesis of the book. And that's how
it came about. The research is also remarkable for a book like that. Anyone who's read it will
appreciate. And again, I think what's nice is this is one of those books where you can be an oncologist
and read it and find it staggering. And you can be someone who has lost a loved one to cancer,
but wouldn't know the difference between a sarcoma and a lyo myo sarcoma. Doesn't matter.
The book resonates, which obviously speaks to your ability to tell a story. And that's sort of,
to me, what's mind boggling about that book is the way and it's the same in the gene, by the way,
is that you weave in and out of a personal story, and then something that's very dense
scientifically. And on a personal level, this is challenging, because I'm in the process,
as you know, of writing a book and doing a pretty lousy job of it, I think. But it's
this challenge of you want to be able to do the science justice, but you need to be able to tell
a story. So how does the scientist, Sid Mukherjee, get along with the writer, Sid Mukherjee?
Well, I don't think there are two separate people. I think they're integrated into one person.
And that's very important. There are many people in my world. They wrote as a process of thinking.
Stephen Jay Gould comes to mind not to draw a ludicrous comparison. Charles Darwin wrote to
think. Oliver Sacks wrote to think. I would suspect that Atul Gawande writes to think. I
know Atul so. So the two people are fundamentally not different people in my brain in order to
do the scientific work that I do. I need to think it through, often through the essays that I work
on. And they inspire in a kind of yin-yang or roundabout way, circular way, ways to find new
ways of thinking about the world, the cancer world. So there isn't a conflict. I don't feel a conflict.
The process is probably of interest. I mean, the process is that when I started writing Emperor,
I sort of made a personal vow or a strategy in writing that this was my first book. I'd never
written a book before. I wrote down some principles or tenets that I would follow. And I've kept them
in every book since. The first one was that there will be no scientific abstraction,
at no place or point shall you go through five pages or three pages without there being a human
being in the middle of this. I'm a translational researcher. I'm a human scientist. And that meant
that I've made a personal promise that you wouldn't go through five pages without understanding what
the payoff of these pages that you've really worked your way through, often as a reader,
what the payoff is. So if you look carefully through that book, every five to seven pages,
the story comes alive in a human story, in a scientific story, and in a scientist story.
They all intersect. And sometimes through my stories, there are times that are tough.
And I'm writing about the description, the first cancer-causing genes, oncogenes,
and their mutations. It's tough to say, well, what's the human being? This is a laboratory
experiment in which you sprinkle tens of thousands of bits of genetic material onto cells and ask
the question, which cells become turned from normal to cancerous? And that's the way you trap
one of these cancer-causing oncogenes. What's the human story behind it? Well, there are two stories.
One story is quite lovely. It's the story of Bob Weinberg, the scientist who you know, walking
through Boston in a snowstorm and suddenly realizing, not in a one-to-one manner, but this
idea of sprinkling tens of thousands of genes onto pieces of genetic material onto cells,
like a snowstorm of genes. There's a kind of congruence to that story. It's not like Bob
Weinberg woke up one morning and saw a snowstorm and said, that's the experiment I should do. But
there's a kind of emotional congruence to the backstory of a scientist. But then the second
story that illustrates this point is to walk through a patient telescoping down, or rather
microscoping downwards from their outer cancer, a tumor, a lump, a mass that is about to kill them,
a real patient of mine, a man with lung cancer. And slowly in that same story of this man's illness,
begin to microscope down to the fact that he actually has in his cells this mutant gene
that Bob Weinberg once caught in this snowstorm of sprinkling genes on cells. And all of a sudden,
this man's cancer is sitting in a room in Boston surrounded by his family dying of metastatic lung
cancer. But at the heart, at the root of that lung cancer, is that very same gene, that very same
oncogene that was discovered, described 10, 20 years before in a paper, in a kind of dry, abstract,
scientific paper. And all of a sudden, that gene, the genetic material that can drive the growth of
a normal cell and make it malignant, make it metastatic, so metastatic, so malignant, that our
best medicine, our best minds can't stop the growth of this aberrant cell, all being driven in part by
that very same gene that was trapped 20 years ago in a laboratory experiment on rat cells. So all of
a sudden, this thing comes alive to you in a way that becomes consequential. If you didn't know the
identity of the gene, you would not understand why on earth this 70-year-old man in perfectly
good health is all of a sudden decimated by one or two or four or eight mutant genes in his cells
that suddenly take over and drive the growth of these cells. Anyway, that's one example that comes
up over and over again. That was the first tenet. That was the first tenet. So what was the second one?
There are many, so I'm not going to go through all the tenets. But the second one was that this book,
all these books, should be fundamentally readable by everyone. You talked about this already.
It should be like a kaleidoscope, that if you turn the book leftwards and you see it as an
oncologist, it's still interesting. The pattern changes. If you turn the book rightwards and say
you're an anthropologist, it still is interesting. If you turn the kaleidoscope upside down and shake
it and there's a new pattern that's formed, it's because you're reading the book now as a clinical
scientist. Or you're reading the book because your daughter has leukemia and you're the father
of a patient with leukemia. Or you're reading it because you yourself have been diagnosed with
breast cancer or your mother has and all of a sudden the kaleidoscope changes. But the point is
that the object remains the same. It's the same book, but you can read the book in various different
ways. You can come into it different ways. Often when I'm in, this sounds like a strange statement,
often when I come back from the words I reread my own writing to figure out what was I thinking
then in 2008 when I wrote those sentences and how does that change now? It's been 10 years.
So I should tell you that there will be a 10-year update to the emperor. There will be three
additional chapters. I assume one of them will be immunotherapy as an update. That's right. So
they're very broadly three sections that are updated and I've thought about it for a long time.
So there'll be an updated section on prevention. There'll be an updated section on early detection
and an updated section on treatment. So that's the very broad three big broad chapters. But in
every chapter there will be deeper dives into what's happened now since the last 10 years and
within the treatment section and potentially within the prevention section there'll be a huge
role of the immune system which was not fully appreciated in 2010. I thought that was the
biggest distinction between the book when I read it and then the PBS special, the Ken Burns special
which of course again we'll link to all of these things in the show notes here. But one, you got
to read the book. But two, I can't recommend enough the Ken Burns special. They did an unbelievable
job I think sharing your voice and that was the biggest. I remember watching it thinking, oh wow
there's a big difference here because there was a three installments or five I can't recall.
Yeah the third installment felt like it was half immunotherapy. It was half immunotherapy. Well
because part of the reason was that again this brings me to the next tenet in the book or writing
the book. The next tenet was that there's so much cancer research in laboratories going on everywhere
and the tenet or the principle was that unless that research has manifest itself in a human drug,
in a human medicine, in a in a reconception of how we think about preventing treating or
detecting cancer in a fundamental reconception of those ideas, it won't get into the book.
So tumor immunology of course had been around for a very long time, coleus toxins famously and
other such efforts very very early on. But in 2010 we were at the edge of that moment in which we
began to use tumor immunology in human beings as powerful medicines to change the course of the
disease. It was just the first trials that come out and in fact the book was complete in 2009
and the first trials had not even come out then. This is a little funny trivia story that I'd
almost forgotten about this until somebody mentioned it to me a year ago. I think the
first real paper that I wrote as a fellow was on CTLA-4. It was looking back at the series at NCI
of patients who had been given CTLA-4 and responded and this paper basically identified
the strong association between autoimmunity and their response to it. Right. Of course this will
be interesting later in our discussion because I want to of course talk about James Allison.
So we'll come back to that but you're right that was sort of when it went from you had interleukin
too that worked in maybe 10 percent 15 percent of patients but you couldn't predict why. That was
the bigger question. You didn't know why were some responding and why were they only responding with
certain cancers to where we are today where it's really been a transformation in the last 15 years.
Absolutely and so when we started the film version of Emperor with Ken Burns which I
obviously was very close I worked very closely with Ken. I should say that the gene is also being
made into film by Ken Burns. Oh my god it's like Christmas all over again. It's almost completely
shot we're sort of moving towards editing phases and so forth. When can people expect that? It's
already been scheduled I think it's winter or fall 2019 so it's on this it's about a year from now.
Yeah about a year from now yeah and we're working through footage and historical footage and archival
footage and so forth but to wind backwards the crucial piece that had been added since the book
was of course immunological therapy so much of what the last episode was around this new burgeoning
field I mean in the first meeting that we had around the transformation of the book into the
documentary film the first thing that was raised is what's changed and the answer was very obvious
what's changed is immunological therapy. It might have been emphasized as much in the book and I
may have just missed it or it's possible you also observed this as a change but I believe it will
factor into the 10th edition which I can't wait to get my hands on is the role of obesity in cancer
as if I recall in the documentary you said look this is now becoming basically the second leading
preventable cause of cancer after smoking which was again I was aware of that at that point in
time because of the work that I'd been doing and sort of my little echo chamber but I thought this
is a PBS special this is not something that I think most people would appreciate this is becoming a
first for many people to hear. That's right and the one thing that we should make clear is that
every word in that PBS document was vetted by some of the most important and thoughtful
scientists and cancer biologists and physicians and physician scientists and cancer advocates
across the world there's a backstory in other words the script was vetted over and over again
so that we wouldn't say things that were misinforming the public or because this is
this is documentaries for all time Ken Burns's work is evergreen hopefully my work is evergreen
so it was very very carefully vetted and it was quite clear by the time the documentary came out
that the signals that we were picking up around obesity and cancer were becoming extraordinarily
clear for some cancers obviously not for other cancers and the provocative statement that sits
behind all of this is that really since the last 20 odd years and maybe even 30 odd years we have
been struggling struggling to find preventable human chemical carcinogens of substantial impact
every word in that sentence is important we have certainly found chemical new chemical carcinogens
in humans but often in that affects small pockets of people who are exposed to those carcinogens
we have found lots and lots of chemical carcinogens which have moderate to very small impact if you
look at populations overall the bar might be smoking so smoking is a good bar this is a
smoking or tobacco smoke is a chemical carcinogen which is removable or preventable and it has
substantial human impact across populations changing smoking behavior can change fundamentally
the epidemiology of cancers across nations if that bar is smoking we have struggled for the
last 20 odd years to find things of that magnitude and effect the direct impact of that is when
people come to me and they say well what do you do to prevent cancer in yourself and your family
i have to sort of casually or not so casually admit that not very obviously i don't smoke
but it's not like i'm eating goji berries or or avoiding some fundamental thing that everyone
else is not in the know about because there aren't any i mean you know i'm obviously not
exposing myself to these rare unusual occupational cancer carcinogenic agents but i'm not doing
something fundamentally changed that's different from you or anyone else to prevent cancer
the exception to this rule of the 20 odd years of the hunt for chemical carcinogens is obesity now
you and i can have a debate is obesity a chemical carcinogen no not in the traditional sense is it
even preventable maybe but we have to think twice or three times about it there's a role of genetics
environment in all of this and even do we think it's obesity per se or hyperinsulinemia for instance
exactly first of all is it an endocrine problem is an inflammatory problem or is it a metabolic
problem there at least three yeah obesity is such a a such a crude phenotype that's right there at
least your point has at least three if not six underlying phenotypes that each of which
mechanistically would make a lot of sense for accelerating cancer is an immunological
phenomenon that is the cytokines the inflammatory all of these going back to your general point that
obesity was becoming identified more and more clearly as one of the potential causes of cancer
or i should say strongly correlated with the development of cancer so strongly that we think
that there's a causal link based on all everything that we know about epidemiology some cancers that
we began to take this seriously and we're still taking it seriously but as you're pointing out
there are several horns underneath that blanket of obesity that we understand very crudely and we
have to figure out which of these is driving the cancer risk i would like to spend the next six
hours discussing with you the tenets of writing for selfish reasons but instead i'll punt that to a
we'll do we'll have dinner in a couple weeks and we'll finish that discussion i want to talk about
another book you wrote that doesn't get as much attention which is the laws of medicine you wrote
that after emperor before the gene correct that's right so laws of medicine has a very different
mandate as it were and that's because the book came out in association with ted they had
commissioned 10 books by 10 thinkers around the world and they asked me to write a book on that
and i it's necessarily a small book it's really a you know the mandate was to write basically a 75
page book expanding on a single very very incisive idea so that's the laws of medicine yes if i if i
got them correctly the three laws are a strong intuition is much more powerful than a weak test
uh-huh how did you think of that and what is the most important application of that law to the way
you think about medicine or specifically oncology today this to me is one of the great neglected
ideas in medicine perhaps one of the great neglected ideas in the world this idea initially
comes from thomas bayes this is a bayesian idea thomas bayes was a cleric but by evening he was a
mathematician and an economist and he let his work leads to one of the most seminal and funny
thought experiments that i've ever encountered which is the following and i i sometimes quiz my
my daughters with it which is the following this is not thomas bayes's own example but it arises
out of thomas bayes's work and he one might imagine going to a street fair and encountering a man
who's tossing coins and he tosses coins and your job is to predict whether the next flip coin flip
is going to be heads or tails and so he tosses the coin 20 times and all 20 times its tails
so then he turns to the crowd and he says what's the next coin flip going to be heads or tails
now the mathematician in the crowd who's the professor of mathematics says 50 percent says
50 percent and you know everyone says absolutely right but the child in the crowd says no no you
don't understand this is a stupid problem it's the coins rigged the coin has only it has two heads
or two tails as case may be and the child's right and what's important about that insight
is that the mathematician imagines the world this in this case this is not a stab at mathematicians
in general but the professor of mathematics thinks of the world as having no history has
having no a prioris it's a world that's created de novo every time the coin is flipped and its
heads and tails equal every time but the child knows and i all humans know that in fact the
world doesn't behave like that everything has priors and you need to understand those priors
before you can understand the posteris there's wisdom in that idea and it took someone like
thomas bayes to figure that out that most of our lives we aren't living our lives like the crazy
mathematician professor we are living our lives like the child we're thinking to ourselves what
was the prior antecedent imagine this is true for any corner of your life the first question you
ask yourself when you're trying to solve a problem trying to understand the cosmos trying
to understand something you ask yourself what was the prior like did the sun set in the west last
night and how about the night before and maybe i don't need to create a formula to figure out
whether the sun is going to set on the west or the east tomorrow it's because it's set on the west
every time there are obviously loopholes and gaps to this kind of thinking there are surprises that
you can miss so bayes's fundamental idea was that you can only interpret a test in the light of what
that test is predicted in the past it's an extraordinarily important idea in the way we
think about about the universe that the past performance of a test tells you something not
everything but tells you something about the future performance of a test and you can apply
it to many many things in the world you can apply it to any kind of thinking economic economic
thinking climate change oriented thinking that the past is a guide to the future not only in a
kind of loose way but you're really using a rheostat weighted strongly by the past and this of course
applies to medicine and it's a forgotten rule in medicine although it does seem like one of the
things that i've always felt physicians innately do well without realizing it which is the opposite
of where i want to be not to take the pot shots but i think where we do very poorly is an
understanding asymmetric risk so naseem talab has written a lot about asymmetric risk and i think
he's absolutely right to be critical of not just physicians but basically most people so my argument
is we are innately wired to be bayesian we are absolutely not innately wired to appreciate risk
and both of these are important that's right so one of them we have to hone so much more because
i think it just doesn't come naturally i played a funny experiment which you'll appreciate i'll send
you the list and you'll have a field day with it it's 20 questions and each one is a quantitative
question with an answer but they're not obvious you would never it's not like how many you know
presidents were there or something where you might know the answer you ask the group we're
going to give you these 20 questions i want you to answer each question not with a number but with a
95 confidence interval you know the game no i don't know the game okay so interesting game so at
the end of 20 questions if you've done it correctly you should have 19 out of 20 of those
ranges correct i've never met a person who can come close you almost without exception get like seven
of the 20 right you can't even contemplate what that variability is so the second law was that
normals teach us rules outliers teach us laws so this of course these were very carefully i mean i
thought i spent a lot of time thinking about them of course this is the anti-vasian law this is the
exactly what you're talking about this is the idea that simultaneously in the medical brain
has to live the idea that the basian idea that when you hear hooves think horses not zebras
famous medical tenet hooves beats outside your window are likely to be horses they're very
unlikely to be zebras the second law is once in a while they are zebras and you need tools you
need special ideas special tools to figure out what these outliers look like who they are how
to find them and how to quickly find them so that you can identify them and triage them differently
so in some ways these two laws are yin yang they polarize against each other and what's interesting
about them is that they both in medicine can both can be simultaneously true in the same way as
our assumption of a symmetric risk is simultaneously true with the idea that our understanding of the
base of a world in the basian way is helpful and important so the second law is about how do you
identify outliers how outliers tell us about the nature of normalcy how they tell us about how
complex interactions can produce occasional far outsiders and how those outsiders really
challenge us to define what these interactions look like in real life i mean the simple example
is it's very very hard to figure out the genetics of any disease without finding the rare
people who have the disease as a consequence of a mutation the classic example of course is that
we would not have an idea how to regulate our body or to prevent heart attacks if we hadn't paid
extraordinarily close attention to a small family small groups of families that had a mutation in
the gene that controls cholesterol metabolism most people don't have this mutation because those
families are quickly extinguished we think because they die of heart attacks they have all sorts of
problems they die of heart attacks but by paying extreme attention to this one family that has a
mutation they're rare scientists all of a sudden uncovered a whole cosmos in which we understand
now cholesterol metabolism and because of that cholesterol metabolism other scientists eventually
develop the first statins so all of this you know the fact that hundreds of thousands of people in
the world are taking this medicine to prevent heart attacks tracks back to a rare family where
because of a genetic mutation they had a very very high risk of cardiac disease and of course
now we know there's a whole family of those people there's at least two thousand of those mutations
that produce that phenotype and these natural experiments are actually a remarkable thing and
of course bringing it back to the gene to now have a tool a probe to be able to explore that is
is amazing the third law for every perfect or exceptional medical experiment there is there's
a human bias that goes along with it again these are unique to medicine and what's interesting
about them is that they are unique to me at least what's interesting is that they're unique to the
day-to-day practice of medicine but they apply for every i think they apply to every corner of life
you don't have to be a doctor to realize that for every every time we think of something if you're
really skeptical thinkers we have to think about the bias that comes intrinsically with that thought
in other words every single declarative claim about the universe that we're making
must have necessarily a declarative bias that comes with it they're matched if you want to be
a scientist we want to be a skeptic your real job aside from being creative and designing experiments
is defined for every single declarative claim that you're making the bias that's drives sitting
like a little devil buried inside that declarative claim because i promise you everyone has one each
one of these claims has one and richard fineman who listeners of this podcast know is one of my
heroes one of my kids is named after him is he named fineman or richard his middle name is fineman
yeah and my wife at first was like why would we do that but then once she had read surely you're
joking mr fineman a couple of times because she'd read it once before she realized why but fineman
said eloquently right the job in science is not to fool yourself and you're the easiest person to
fool that's right so to your point the only thing i would disagree with what you've said
cid is i don't think these are unique to medicine i think these are laws of science right and maybe
laws of life on some yeah so the mandate here really was to use this book as a kind of springboard
to challenge the way we think about virtually all aspects of of how we live you're going to read an
article in the new york times tomorrow that will make some claims about some politician somewhere
in oklahoma or you're going to read about an economic paper that is now being presented to
the feds and your job is to be adequately skeptical about it and understand what are the
priors how do we explain this particular fact based on the priors are the priors do the priors
matter to use a very topical example does someone's past behavior in college or in school high school
tell us about how he or she's going to be a judicial candidate or does their behavior under
scrutiny in any way predict their behavior when no one's looking that's right that's another
question the second question that you might ask here is again it's an outlier question right
scrutiny versus not scrutiny are they do they become outliers to themselves if they're scrutinized
if they're versus when they're not scrutinized and the third question is when i read this story what
are my biases am i reading it because i'm a man am i reading it because i have a particular
experience of my in my own lifetime myself my sister my my daughter my friend my colleague
is that coloring the way that i read this particular story so absolutely and you know
this thinking goes on over and over again this these are circular processes do those biases
have priors do the priors have biases and so forth so you can use these i mean i i certainly
use these tools in clinical clinical practice yeah it's a beautiful as you said it's a very
short book but again we'll we'll certainly make sure people have this link to it because i i think
it's a great way of teaching people how to think and that's again i just don't think we're innately
wired for every facet of thinking now going back to your background in immunology very recently we
had a very exciting for those of us in this space very exciting nobel prize awarded i mean it was
as we were discussing before we started recording it wasn't so much around immunotherapy but a very
specific element of it which are the development of checkpoint inhibitors two of them in particular
were basically acknowledged here ctla4 which i mentioned earlier npd1 tell me why these are so
exciting they're exciting for many reasons they are exciting for again some history and some
background as the story as it were is exciting because if you ask the question in the 1990s
what's the relationship between cancer and the immune system you get a kind of diffuse answer
you get an answer which could be very unclear because there were all sorts of
complicated lines of evidence one line of evidence was that in patients with a complete collapse of
the immune system such as patients with hiv or complete collapse of at least of one wing of the
immune system they would get these cancers you nobody else could get but what's interesting
about them and this is where the thought experiment this is where the brain cells start
sort of ticking and wondering they would typically get viral cancers viruses that would
now get unleashed we now know many of them viruses like human papilloma virus they would
get cervical cancers they would get anal cancers so a lot of viral cancers but patients with HIV
did not generally get lung cancer i never even thought of that so we have enough data to know
that they either at no greater prevalence or even at a lower prevalence when when you start to talk
about you know for example lung cancer or gbm or pancreatic cancer i never thought of that yeah
it's very important so the data are mixed because of course in the 1980s they weren't living long
enough so all that we know is that the first groups of cancers that cropped up in these men and women
were not lung cancers that were not pancreatic cancer so at the first pass with that cut short
data set you might begin to imagine then if that's the case the immune system completely collapses
you only get a certain kind of cancer then what is the possible role of the immune system in in
cancer control and you might if you were a nailist you might have given up in the 1990s and said well
you know take the whole immune system away and nothing really happens even with this cut short
data set so maybe there isn't such a complex interaction well it turns out that people like
jim alison and his japanese colleague did not put the immune system away they put that data aside
this goes back to the laws of medicine they said sure it tells you a little bit but i didn't tell
you the full story the full story turns out there's one layer deeper the full story turns out that in
people who don't have a collapse of the immune system whose immune system is otherwise intact
cancer cells not not all cancers but some cancers make specific factors in fact they evolve that
the word make is the wrong word here they evolve so that they put up specific factors put up specific
signals that inactivate the immune system or that make the immune system no longer able to kill or
recognize the cancer cell and the identification of these specific pathways these specific factors
was what led to the nobel prize because in further work jim alison and again his colleagues this is a
big wide field showed that if you inactivate these specific factors if you drive nails through them
using a variety of methods then all of a sudden the cancers become
re-visible to the immune system and the immune system can attack and kill the cancer cells
now why is it exciting it's exciting for many reasons first of all it's important to realize
that not all cancers respond we don't know why some do and some don't melanoma is highly responsive
it's an immunologically engaged tumor is it because the melanoma has so many antigens that
it will suddenly be more recognizable is it because the skin is such a lymphoid organ is
the right environment we don't know all of these questions the other thing to realize is that people
have responses and some people continue to respond some other people sadly will relapse and they'll
go you know the cancers will start growing back in the context of their re-educated immune system
and that leads to the second question which is what happens then is there a second pathway and
this is an important idea i think that goes back to your first question which is about whether this
is depressing or not the important thing is once you drive a single stake through cancer's heart
it's like placing the first crampon on a climb you see if there's no crampon that's placed on the
climb you can't climb a mountain it seems like a wall it's a blank wall and you don't know where
to go left or whether to go right or what to do once you plant that first crampon and it sticks
and it sticks you all of a sudden the whole face of the mountain becomes it's a different mountain
it's a different mountain now because now you can ask the question because the first crampon was
planted in that particular place and it's stuck and it's stuck i have a new vantage point exactly
perspective has changed that's right and so this is the important piece to realize about cancer
research and perhaps about all research is that the first crampon or the first stake through
cancer's heart is an incredibly important stake because then you can ask what i call linear
questions before that first one is placed the questions are non-linear you don't know where to
place it the whole map is open once you drive a stake through the first question the world
becomes more linear you can now ask the question what's the mechanism of resistance to that
and when you do when you find that what's the mechanism of resistance to that and so all of a
sudden the perspective is different because you're we've climbed through that first and that's
usually where the Nobel prizes are given your Nobel prizes are given often for planting the first
stake through the heart of a disease through the heart of a problem and that's why this Nobel prize
is important it's not of course as you're saying this does not encapsulate the field of tumor
immunology in general there's it's a wide field our own lab does a whole bunch of work in tumor
immunology but we're put on the shoulders of those prior giants as it were and so that's the
recognition that's been given here you said something that i think is so important and worth
reiterating there's also something about immunology and immunotherapy that's quite interesting as far
as planting that stake which is the durability of response it is often the case that when you have
an immunologic remission it is a durable remission it is not always the case but it is
much more likely the case than when you say for example see a chemotherapeutic remission
or even a surgical remission on a personal level i have a very close friend who was diagnosed with
colon cancer 10 years ago at a very young age you know he might have been 40 and that was unusual
in and of itself i remember talking i went to the hospital when he had his colectomy spoke with the
surgeon after it sounded like a horrible case huge tumor the mesentery was full of nodes which i
assumed would be positive every 26 nodes sampled all came back negative my friend was adopted we
later realized he had lynch syndrome eight years later he goes on to develop pancreatic adenocarcinoma
unresectable so it's encased the mesenteric vessels he cannot have a whipple procedure
and as you know and unfortunately many people listening to this will know that is a death
sentence yeah it's a non-negotiable you will not be alive in nine months and he was put on an
anti-pd1 therapy because he happened to have as you would know these patients with lynch are going
to be much more likely to be susceptible to checkpoint inhibitors two years later he's
disease-free just unbelievable stories yeah and i think your point is an elegant one that i'd never
really thought of before which is focus less on the fact that we haven't solved the problem and
more on the fact that we have made a finite and real step towards establishing a new place a new
location for which to view this disease that's right so i describe this as taking a non-linear
problem into a linear problem now of course the answers are often not linear per se but it gives
you a route i mean we'll come back to the metabolism study that we did with luke cantley
that is a great example of taking a non-linear problem and converting into a linear problem now
i'll tell you about that in a second but any time this was the place with gleevec too let's
tell people what gleevec is yeah so gleevec is a good example of a drug where we learned to target
a mutant cancer gene and it's actually the gene product so in that case the cancer it's a blood
cancer called chronic myelogenous leukemia was also a death sentence and also gi stromal tumors
and gi stromal tumors yeah chronic myelogenous leukemia was a death sentence people had to
go through transplants i've watched probably a dozen in the pre-gleevec era a dozen patients
die of chronic myelogenous leukemia or the complications of transplant i trained briefly
as a transplanter and then all of a sudden through the work of many people including brian druecker
a drug was discovered so before that scientists figured out based on very careful genetic analysis
that the tumor was being driven by really the work of one gene and the gene was called bcr able
it's an oncogene it's not found in normal cells but found in these cancer cells and the product
of that gene became like a like an engine like a manic engine that was driving these blood cells to
go crazy and make more blood cells and proliferate and proliferate and proliferate and it was this
engine gone wild inside a cell and every time the cell asked the question should i divide
rather than looking at its normal state or nutrients metabolic state etc the only answer
we'd ever get was from this engine saying yes go ahead make another cell divide etc etc etc so
this was identified that the exact the gene product was identified the protein product of
the gene was identified and then through an elaborate series of experiments and circumstances
chemists found a way to actually jam the engine one molecule human beings may we stitch this
molecule together it's a remarkable achievement and once the engine is jammed which suddenly
turns out that the disease goes into remission this was one of the first examples there are others
of so-called targeted therapy where you take you synthesize a chemical to jam
cancer's engines in a cancer specific way it doesn't affect normal cells but what's interesting
about that is that some people develop resistance because the engine cancer cells evolve and they
find a way of resisting but that resistance it becomes a linear problem you figure out the
mechanism the resistance is and you drive a second stake through cancer's heart and when it becomes
resistant to that you drive a third stake and so forth so all of a sudden the problem which seemed
like a big blank rock became a linear problem so that that goes back to another example of how
that first stake or the first crampon really helps with the problem and and now for immunotherapy
immunological therapy the roadmap is much clearer why do some tumors respond and why some don't
respond is it a question of the environment that the tumor is sitting in is it blood vessels is
that tumor cells is it immune cells these are answerable questions these are so-called linear
questions but the first big step here was to define the problem this is really a nice step off to
exactly where i know we want to go which is we've got surgical oncologists medical oncologists
radiation oncologists in many ways a subset now of medical oncology is immunobased oncology
the work that you lu and many others are now doing is potentially a another branch of oncology
called metabolic oncology so you're beyond gracious in your suggesting i have even something
to do with helping that evening turn into a what sounds like a very productive collaboration between
you and lu and i'll be talking with lu as well in the next month i'm sure but let's talk a little
bit about what came out of that collaboration and certainly bring it back to ben hopkin's paper
that was in nature i believe was in nature yeah two weeks three weeks ago yeah so let's talk a
little bit about the question what were you trying to understand so the question is there's
a very wide question and then there's a very narrow question the wide question is how does the body's
metabolic state affect cancer it's a very big question because cancers like all cells are eating
nutrients as well to in order to grow and the question therefore is the cancer eating a different
set of nutrients than normal cells this work goes back to famous work by otto warburg done in the
early 1900s yeah 1920s is that right yeah where otto warburg was one of the first people to make
the hypothesis that there's something fundamentally different about i mean we won't go into great
details but it's fundamentally different in which the cancer cells metabolize compared to normal
cells they use fundamentally different pathways to metabolize and if you could find a way to target
these metabolic alterations in cancer cells you'd find an anti-cancer drug so but that question has
been hanging around our field for a long time and as our understanding of normal metabolism has
changed we've begun to identify not just one but dozens of nutrient pathways that cancers use that
may or may not be different from normal cells maybe slightly different from normal cells maybe
a lot different from normal cells so that's one big question the second question which is a slightly
narrower question is that when you give a drug whatever drug it might be your favorite chemotherapy
or favorite drug any drug does it change the metabolism of the cancer cell and does it change
the metabolism of the body and could this be a mechanism by which cancer cells become sensitive
or resistance to chemotherapy so these are two related questions again to reiterate one question
is how is the cancer cells metabolism different from the normal cell in normal circumstances
and the second question is how is the cancer cells metabolism differ from a normal cell in
the context of giving a drug yeah in other words can a nutritional state be exploited and or a drug
sensitivity be exploited through a nutritional care I'm sure those are the two questions so we focused
in this particular study we actually are interested in both I'm interested in both but we focused on
the second question and the second question in this particular case was that there was a very
promising group of medicines that was being used in clinic in fact I had used them as a trialist
they had come really out of Lou Cantley's path defining work he had defined the pathway or the
signals that these medicines attack and there was an enormous amount of optimism because this was
considered a fundamental pathway this is the beauty by the way of being in a place like New York or
Boston it's you can talk about someone doing this I mean Lou is in Boston when much of this work is
done he's now here in New York and you don't have to collaborate with a guy across the world you
collaborate with the guys on the Upper East Side instead of Chelsea that's right so Lou's work over
the last decades had been to define this pathway and ultimately led to the formation of the creation
of these new medicines they're called PI3 kinase inhibitors and they go by fancy names like duvelosib
and things like that but anyway when they came to clinic surprisingly there were some responses
but there was a lot of resistance in patients that tumors were resistant to the drugs and didn't
respond and that was a puzzle that Lou had come up with in his own work and then separately seven
miles uptown I was scratching my head about the same puzzle because I'd been using these same drugs
in cancer patients and finding that patients became resistant or were resistant to start
and so what was chalked out that on a napkin that evening was we had thought of lots of ways that
these patients had could become resistant we had thought oh maybe the tumor had a mutation
well and there's one other point I guess to add just that we remember but maybe it's worth
reiterating is a lot of the patients that were on these began to develop phenotype like they
looked like they were diabetic yeah so that's the point that I was coming to in a second we didn't
know if that meant that that was the source of the resistance that's right was it true true and
unrelated yeah the question was was it true true and unrelated I mean you can think of many other
mechanisms of resistance you can say the tumors became it got a mutation you could say the host
had some problem you could write down on the piece of paper thousand ways those were the traditional
ways that one would explain resistance the traditional ways of thinking about tumor resistance
mutation the host eats up the drug the non-traditional way and this is what the
innovation in the study was that what if there's diabetes that we were observing the high levels
of sugar and the high levels of insulin insulin being the most important piece of this what if
the drug was causing diabetes separately from the tumor given to normal people that the drug would
cause diabetes in some people worse than others and that diabetic phenotype that diabetic state
the hyperinsulinemic state was being used or exploited by the tumor to essentially become
resistant to the drug it's a little bit like in the analogy that I drew I remember on the napkin
it's funny I still remember the table we said I remember the table yeah exactly right the drawing
so Lou and I were batting this idea back and forth while you you were eating nothing
and the idea was that to me reminded me of the famous story of the woodcutter who's sitting on
a tree limb and chops off his own limb and falls down and I drew this picture I remember of the
woodcutter on a tree limb because what happens is that the body mounts an insulinemic response
to the drug that insulinemic response goes to the cancer and starts feeding the cancer
and then the cancer becomes resistant so you essentially undo all the good that you've done
with the drug by cutting off your own limb because of this intrinsic circuit and the long and short of
it is that that's basically an animal models that happens to be true so we showed it using
formal systems and formal methods that this insulinemia is a consequence of the drug has
nothing to do with the tumor has nothing to do with anything else if you give the drug the drug
goes into the liver and the pancreas and causes a sort of a pre-diabetic state that's often worsened
that if you're already in a pre-diabetic state this hyperinsulinemia is used then by the tumor
to become resistant even while the drug is present it becomes a pathway by which the tumor
becomes resistant and most interestingly that you can paralyze this resistance by putting
animals on a ketogenic diet so basically there's never any sugar source to drive the insulin you
blunt the insulin response so acutely that you can no longer get the insulin high again this is not
to be confused with with the idea that this is a sugar feeding tumor idea this is not a sugar
feeding tumor paradigm because to be clear on a ketogenic diet your glucose levels might go down
from normal but it's not an enormous reduction even in a complete fast you'll still maintain at
least three millimolar of glucose it's the insulin that becomes virtually unmeasurable that's right so
this is an insulin feeding the tumor question and so i think there are three points that need to be
made about the study to be very clear first of all it's an animal study we're now launching a human
study that will launch in november with patients with lymphomas endometrial cancer and breast cancer
particularly triple negative breast cancer i'm very keen on studying because this is a cancer
that has so few options that's right there are very very few options so that's the human study
the second point that is worthwhile making is that it's sort of like folks don't try this at home
this is a very particular study with a very particular drug on cancers combined with a diet
the study only worked when the drug and the diet were combined it does not mean that the ketogenic
diet is going to prevent cancer we don't know this it's an open question we're actually studying that
separately yeah and i want to talk just a little bit about that paper because that's boy i sure
want everyone to make sure they hear that loud and clear because few things upset me more than
when i spend a little too much time on twitter and i come across people who seem to want to claim
that if you're on a ketogenic diet you can't get cancer or if you have cancer just go on a ketogenic
diet you're going to be fine that's not in fact to be very clear well the study in fact demonstrated
that that was not the case not only that the study also demonstrates that some cancer models
including leukemia is accelerated on the keto diet in fact we have a big follow-up study to try to
figure out why some cancers are accelerated by keto alone but when you combine it with the drug
they actually go back down into deep remission the third point to make is that it seems to be
mutation agnostic and that by that i mean this is a very important idea which is that 12 tumor models
responded 12 i was not aware that it was that high yeah 12 and actually all 12 that we tested
responded every one of them responded and it didn't matter what oncogenes you had or what
tumor suppressor genes were mutated they all responded to different levels leukemia has
respond they become then they relapse at least in the models endometrial cancers we can't get them
to grow pancreatic cancers respond extremely strongly so it's another example where you're
not targeting it seems a mutation this is not like gliwek in which you're driving a
stake into the engine of the cancer or that engine this is a much more global yeah it seems yeah it's
a much more global assault in fact in some ways it's parallel akin to this immunotherapy in the
sense that it the immune system doesn't care if you have rass or doesn't seem to care at the first
approximation whether you have a mutation in one gene or another gene rass or not rass it will kill
the tumor cells based on its characteristics of what it sees in the tumor similarly here the
the metabolism seems to be tumor-wide but not single kinds of cancer specific we don't know this
to be the case the 13th model that we try will maybe this was the one that won't work but this
has generated a lot of excitement for this reason you know i have a friend who has definitely her
two new positive maybe er positive pr negative but has stage four breast cancer is in a pf3k
inhibitor trial out of dana farber has been on the trial for probably five years she's the only
survivor here's the interesting thing she's been on a ketogenic low carbohydrate diet the entire
time while she was taking inhibitor yes okay she's still on the inhibitor and so what's interesting
is i've told lou about her case because she's fastidious in this and she's able to get her
hemoglobin a1c now under six which for many of those patients is very difficult very technically
when you me and sid had lunch once about two years ago this is the very first time you ever
showed me the data yeah that's right we brought a computer we were at that indian place or the
chinese place on second avenue that's right yeah and when you showed me those data i just immediately
thought of her so it's actually been on my list to introduce lou because she doesn't live in new
york but i would love to meet her i want to bring her out and i want you guys to meet her because
the combination of this p i 3k inhibitor and this dietary choice she's made going back to your second
rule right she's the outlier that is that is giving you something to probe yeah we hopefully
will have many such patients i don't know you know this is why we're running the study sid as you can
probably imagine i could spend another 12 hours speaking with you but i want to be respectful of
your time i know we're a little late in the day we got a later start than we wanted and you've got
a long trip home and i want you to get to see your family the last question i want to ask you really
is one that i need you to be a little bit immodest with which is how do you do what you do i don't
meet a lot of people that i look at and realize that on every level of their life they are better
than me you know usually i meet people and it's like yeah they're better at me at those three
things but i can do this one thing better and and i'm sure i could think of something i do better
than you but it's many things do you know my sense of balance i can probably shoot a bow and
arrow better than you but when i think about how you balance the devotion you have to your patients
to your family to your research to your writing it humbles me i don't know have you put any thought
into that the fact that you created these tenets around writing is very interesting to me it says
that you you weren't just a natural gifted guy that fell out of the sky who figured out how to
write you know you had to work at your craft yeah so how do you work at this craft of just
excellence in general the simple rules that i have is i'm a very question and project driven person
if i set projects i'll usually fulfill them again it's the same sort of crampon in the mountain
rule which is that in order to write a book you have to write the first line of the book
and inevitably that's not going to be the first line that survives in order to do research you
have to do one experiment and inevitably that experiment is going to not work out you're going
to do 10 15 iterations of it etc to me the fundamental rule that that works for me is just
to throw something at the world the first line the first experiment the first idea and then
keep at it i keep at it over and over again i come back to it i come back to it over and over again
and i keep asking questions and then at some point of time and that's another moment of
sensitivity is to figure out when the work speaks back to you the experiment starts talking back to
you have to be really open your ears have to be really open and that's really the skill
of a scientist i think the scientist i think has or even a writer they have really two skills and
that they mix together the first one is the creative step putting out the first line thinking
of the idea you know i'm going to write a biography of cancer i'm going to write the history of
genetics etc but the second one is to be open enough to realize when the work starts speaking
back to you and let that happen let the experiment start talking back to you be skeptical of it have
a conversation with it those i think are the two skills that i sort of bring to my puzzle the rest
of it is just like everyone else trying to balance eating a meal versus you know writing in two more
lines stopping starting sleeping the usual well sit i don't expect this will be the last time
we sit down and do i hope it's going to be a lot more stuff to talk about i can't thank you enough
i consider you lou i mean some of the other folks who talk about real mentors of mine and
it's it's a it's a privilege it's a real privilege to call you a friend and to be able to sit down
with you and just get even the tiniest insight into your work thank you you can find all of this
information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast there you'll find the show notes
readings and links related to this episode you can also find my blog and the nerd safari at peteratiamd.com
what's a nerd safari you ask just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more maybe
the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week email where
i'll update you on what i've been up to the most interesting papers i've read and all things related
to longevity science performance sleep etc on social you can find me on twitter instagram
and facebook all with the id peteratia md but usually twitter is the best way to reach me to
share your questions and comments now for the obligatory disclaimer this podcast is for general
informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine nursing or other
professional health care services including the giving of medical advice and note no doctor-patient
relationship is formed the use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the
user's own risk the content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice
for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their health care professionals
for any such conditions lastly and perhaps most importantly i take conflicts of interest very
seriously for all of my disclosures the companies i invest in and or advise please visit
peteratiamd.com forward slash about