Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode of The Drive and Happy New Year to everyone.
We took a week off as you probably noticed, so hopefully everybody's ready to jump back
into this fun stuff. My guest this week is near Barzillai. And if you're at all into
the space of longevity, he'll be no stranger to you. Near is the founding director of the
Institute for Aging Research, the Nathan Schock Center of Excellence in Basic Biology at Albert
Einstein. He's completed two fellowships, one in metabolism at Yale, the other in endocrinology
and molecular biology at Cornell. He directs the Longevity Genes Project. And in my estimate,
Near is probably the most knowledgeable person ever on the genetics of longevity. And we
talk a ton about that during this episode. He also is leading the effort to test metformin
in a prospective clinical trial for non diabetics with respect to aging. And this is referred
to as the TAME trial. We get into that obviously in detail here and also we'll use a lot of
the data for that in the show notes. This is in many ways, I think Near is probably
one of the most insightful people when it comes to understanding the clinical benefits
of metformin. And we talk about that a ton. We also talk about insulin resistance. I can't
resist the urge, no pun intended, I guess, to get into sort of a detailed discussion on what IR is
with sort of people who are really deep in this space. We talk a lot about IGF and growth hormone.
And I got to tell you, this is a topic that you've probably heard me waffle on a little bit because
I'm still really kind of on the fence about this relationship of IGF, GH. I think the centenarian
data point in one direction. I think the epidemiology outside of centenarians point in a different
direction. And of course, none of this really speaks to the question I get asked constantly,
which is, do you think administration of growth hormone is beneficial from a lifespan or
health span perspective? Or do you think it's harmful? And truthfully, I've always leaned
towards the harmful side, but we get into this in detail and NIR offers some great insights.
Certainly for me, I was really helped by this process. We do go back and talk about the
centenarians. And because I'm in the midst, as some of you know, of writing this book,
I'm knee deep on all that literature. And so it was really great to kind of clarify a few things
that I think even if you're not steeped in this stuff, you'll find very interesting. And of course,
we talk about all of my other favorite topics like autophagy, colorwork restriction. We even get
into a little bit of the stuff around NAD and nicotinamide riboside and things like that. So
overall, I think this is a bit of a technical episode, but not that technical. We've certainly
done more technical stuff. The show notes will be valuable as always, especially for a show of this
nature. So with nothing else to add, please welcome to the show NIR Barzilay.
Hey NIR, how are you? I'm terrific. How are you? I'm good. I can't believe not only did you make
it down here on time, but you made it down here ahead of me at my own place. Nice to stay young.
Yeah, this is, I don't know, these days, this weather is so unpleasant, but yeah, you beat me
here. I was a bit of a bear. It's unpleasant for you because you're in California most of the time.
Yeah, yeah, I think that's part of it, but you're from Israel, so this has to be unpleasant for you
too. Israel was too warm for me. I'm okay. Got it. Well, speaking of which, so you were born in Israel,
you spent how long there? Did you serve military time there? Yes, I served military time. I was
a nurse and a medical student. I went to the Technion Medical School. I went then to Hadassah
Hospital for residency, which I finished. And only then I came to the United States. I was
at Yale with Ralph DeFranzo doing metabolism. Actually, I was looking at the mechanism of
action of metformin in 1987 before it was approved for use in the United States. There's a
serendipitous connection to that later. And then I went to Cornell for an endocrine fellowship,
and then I was recruited to Einstein. And so my first part of my life was metabolism, but then
I started doing what I really was interested in, and this is aging and the biology of aging.
And I remember reading a quote once from you that said, maybe paraphrasing, but metformin is
the reason I came to the United States. Well, in a way it was, but this is life in retrospect,
right? I wasn't really expecting. I was done with metformin in 1988. I was done with metformin
until it started again about three, four years ago. Well, I can't wait to talk about metformin
because they're probably, I'm trying to think, if I think of four or five exogenous molecules,
which is just the terminology I use to describe anything that you ingest or take that comes from
outside the body. So I would include drugs, supplements, hormones, anything in there. But
when you lump all of these things together, if I were to say what are the three or four of these
that I am asked about the most frequently from patients, or frankly anybody, if I'm at a party
and I let it slide what I do for a living, the first question is, should I be taking metformin?
And there's usually a handful of others that they want to know about. Should I be taking
nicotinamide riboside? Although they usually don't say that. They usually say, should I be
taking NAD or something to that effect? So it's wonderful that we will be able to speak today
because few people can speak about metformin the way you can. And so I'm really looking forward
to that. But before we go down that path, I do still want to kind of understand a little bit
more about your journey and your interest in endocrinology. Did you know from day one,
when you entered the field of medicine, that this was the area that you wanted to study?
Yes. I was interested in aging from the time I was pretty much 13 and spent
weekends with my grandfather who was telling me his life story. And his life story wasn't easy.
And he did lots of physical things and he dried the swamp and he did this and that.
And I'm looking at the man who was then 68 years old that walks slowly, his obese white hair,
and he just didn't look like somebody who did everything he told me to do. And they say that
children have imagination, but most kids don't see their grandparents as what they will be.
They see them as, I don't know how they got there. And this really stuck with me. And I started to be
interested in the biology of aging. For example, when I did my residency, I always was interested
in how, not what's the age of the patient, but does he look older or younger than his age? I
kind of realized intuitively that there's a chronological age and a biological age. And
what is this differences between the biological and chronological age? And of course, as a physician,
it looked like endocrine is a good place to start because you knew that there's a lot of
endocrinology in aging and you assumed that hormones are going down or some are going up,
but if you could fix that, maybe you could fix a lot of aging. Now, everything that happened in
my life was fascinating from the biology of aging. Replacing the hormones wasn't really
part of it, but we'll get to it. Going back to the hormone thread, the most obvious example of
changes in hormones with aging, of course, occur in women where they have this very abrupt change
in one of their endocrine systems, this androgen system. Did you think about it even more broadly
than that? For example, what was happening in thyroid hormone and what was happening in
fuel partitioning hormones and other things like that? Oh, absolutely. Absolutely. But I'll tell
you to the point when there was a discussion whether to do the women health initiative,
many people thought this is a waste of time. We know that estrogen is good for women.
There's lots of studies like that. Of course, it's major in aging. I didn't look at this simply
for maybe two reasons. One is men are also aging and in several ways similar to women.
That's not an estrogen story. The testosterone decrease wasn't really as dramatic as the
estrogen decrease. I thought that there's a lot of aging that's done without estrogen. Let's
start with that. Also, you're replacing just one hormone with lots of hormones are changing. It
didn't look like a good study to me. Well, especially at the time, and I try to temper
my criticism for that study by trying to have some empathy for the fact that the investigators were
dealing with what the treatment protocols were at the time, but to use oral estrogen that's
conjugated equine to use synthetic progestin and not even actual progesterone. You could come up
with a list of 18 things that in retrospect are so obvious why that study was a failure.
Absolutely true. But the other part of that is that the way to show effect of estrogen in animal
models was to take their ovaries out and give them estrogen. Then you could do lots of provocation.
It was good. So estrogen is a good hormone on a young body. But then there were studies that were
hardly published, but I was aware of them, of taking old animal. So you could take the young
animals in just one center in Houston. They did it. You took the young animal. You took their ovaries
out. You gave them estrogen and you employed a stroke model. And when you gave estrogen,
the stroke was smaller and everything. When you did the same in older animals,
the stroke became worse. Okay. And they couldn't publish it for a while because they said, well,
it's old animals. So they have other diseases or other things, but every experiment that had
estrogen in old model was the opposite. Not only that it didn't affect, it was the opposite,
which what happened to the WHI in a certain ways. Yeah. Although I still think that it was probably
the breast cancer that garnered the most headline in the WHI. And actually that's an interesting
topic, which I'll be going into in great depth on another episode. There's a great book that just
came out that tackles this, that goes through the history of the WHI. At what point, well,
let's go back to the metformin thing actually. So it's 1987 and you're thinking like, okay,
metformin is the next line of agent we will use to treat type two diabetes. So metformin was
already in clinical practice in Europe. Is that correct? Oh, correct. For many years. How many
years? Like 20 or 30 years? So metformin few years ago was 60 years. So we're talking about
1950 or something, 1950, 1960. When I was in Israel, I prescribed metformin. That was the first line
for type two diabetes. What took so long for it to come to the US?
That's a terrible story that still continues. The FDA said, we don't know, we don't know that
metformin is going to be effective in the population in the United States. So you have to do the studies.
And it was Bristol Meyer really that got to do the studies. And basically they had to do a phase three
study again to show that metformin is effective as sulfonylurea as an indication for type two diabetes.
And if even then the idea was that it will be good only in obese people, which happened not to matter
much because all the type two diabetes in the United States were obese, but it was really
a matter of regulation. And part of having regulation was that the FDA asked more
studies to understand the mechanism of aging and metformin. And in a certain way, maybe they are
right because metformin mechanism of action is really complicated. And I'm not sure that today,
as a new drug, it would be approved. Interesting. Where do you think it would fail in safety or
efficacy? No, it's not in mechanism. In the inability to elucidate the mechanism. Right.
When you come to the FDA and you say, you know, we've done that and we've done this in animal and
we've done this in cells, and you're trying to show what is the major mechanism of action,
you would have failed. So what I showed in humans is that metformin targets,
a patiglucose production or the insulin sensitivity of the liver. And that's the major mechanism of
action. Unlike, for example, sulfonylurea that increase insulin secretion, right? Or TZDs that
increase the insulin sensitivity in the muscle more than in the liver. So this was a mechanism
that you could pack to the FDA, but it's really not the intracellular mechanism of metformin.
So at the time, was it understood what metformin's activity was on complex one of the mitochondria?
No, not really. This came later. I don't know what year, but it came later. It came when the
seahorses essays were developed to show really which mitochondria in which pathway of
mitochondria you have changes. Maybe for the listener, explain what a seahorse assay is.
A seahorse assay is an assay to look at mitochondrial action, whether you extract
mitochondria or even tissues. It really shows some relationship between oxygen consumption
in relationship to polarity. And it's very sensitive to look at some of the effects of
drugs that are interfering with mitochondria action or decreased mitochondrial activity.
It's almost like the indirect calorimetry of the mitochondria.
Right, right. Indirect because it's a provocative test for me. So yes.
Metformin was discovered from a plant as well, correct?
Right. It's a French lily.
And it was first lily, obviously. And this was discovered in the 40s or 50s?
Correct. The first thing that happened, there was a drug by the name of Fenformin,
a cousin of metformin.
Which apparently is much more potent.
It's much more potent because unlike metformin, it doesn't need a transporter to get into the
cells. On the other hand, it was associated with a lot of lactic acidosis. And it was considered
unsafe eventually. And then metformin was a safer part with much less of a lactic acidosis side
effects.
What is the mechanism by which metformin cause lactic acidosis? Because
in all the use I've seen of metformin clinically, I've never seen a case of it,
which is not to say it doesn't happen. I'm sure it does. And you could stack risks by
taking someone with renal insufficiency, giving them contrast and tons of metformin.
But in medical school, this was like the board question you got asked every single test.
What do you have to worry about with lactic acidosis? What's the putative mechanism by
which that happens?
So first of all, I would tell you that in my study in the 80s,
every patient that we gave metformin had an increase in lactic acid.
From what to what in millimolar?
Within the normal range. So if it's two was the...
Yeah, the cutoff.
The cutoff. So it was between went from 1.5 towards the two and sometimes even went over the two.
But it wasn't really anything associated with that acidosis.
And there was no change in pH?
No. No. No onion gap, not anything like that. And it probably has to do, I don't know that I can
tell you for sure, but it has to do with what happens when complex one, part of the metabolic
effect when complex one is inhibited. But there's lots of speculation and I don't really care
to comment on that. But I think what became clear, we call it endocrinology, it's called
it MALLA. It's metformin-associated lactic acidosis. In other words, we moved away
from metformin causing lactic acidosis to the association because it's, if anywhere,
it described more in people that have kidney failures or have heart attacks or something
and had lactic acidosis and were on metformin too. And that was kind of the association, but
it's not clear to me that there are truly people who develop lactic acidosis from metformin
that is just because of metformin and not associated with something else.
I'm glad to hear you say that. That's sort of generally been my bias, but I'm happy to be
corrected if that bias is incorrect. But yeah, I've always thought that frankly, so many of the
drugs that we're really interested in now as we look back from an aging perspective, whether it
be metformin or rapamycin, so many of the negative side effects that people typically associate with
those drugs are very difficult to isolate from the patients in whom those drugs have historically
been given. And so it's nice to hear that MALLA is now being generally recognized as an alternative
viewpoint to that. You know, metformin is to me an interesting drug from a diabetic standpoint,
because, and I don't know that this was appreciated in the 80s. In fact, I would suspect it was not,
because there's really two macro strategies for improving type 2 diabetes. You can, obviously,
the highest goal is to control glucose levels, so to regulate the degree of glucose in the blood.
But you can do that through, at the highest level, two ways. You could increase insulin,
either exogenously or through increased insulin production pharmacologically,
or you could reduce glucose. And of course, metformin falls into the latter category of that,
or increasing muscle insulin sensitivity to enhance glucose disposal. Today, it's generally
regarded that while both strategies will have an equal benefit on the microvascular, the glucose
lowering by insulin lowering, so the less glucose production strategy, has a superior effect on the
macrovascular. And therefore, metformin would be a better alternative to, for example, a drug
that's going to increase insulin production out of the pancreas. Was it appreciated at the time,
meaning when you were doing this in the late 80s, how potentially beneficial this drug was?
Well, at that time in the United States, it was all about insulin resistance. You know,
people like Jerry Reven, Ralph DeFranzo, the people at the NIH, Ron Kahn, were all, you know,
discovering the insulin receptor, discovering insulin resistance, discovering the association
of insulin resistance with the metabolic syndrome. So it was all, we all had the bias that the major
problem with type 2 diabetes is insulin resistance. And you know, we know now that it's a total
collaboration. Yeah, you increase insulin resistance and the pancreas have to secrete more
insulin. And we humans, at least in the condition of our environment, obesity, everything,
many of us, I would say 40% cannot deal with that. And we become diabetic. There is this
startling curve of the pancreas, you know, like for the heart, that you increase insulin
secretion and at some point you cannot increase insulin secretion, you become diabetic and then
insulin secretion decrease. And so insulin resistance was a major way and that's why
metformin was a good place to come with, you know, at least it affects mainly the hepatic glucose
production rather than the muscle. Although I have to tell you in vitro on muscle specimen,
it's an insulin sensitizer in the muscle too. Let's talk about this idea of insulin resistance.
I think there are a few terms that leave me scratching my head more than that one. So this
is an example of something where maybe five years ago I thought I really knew what insulin resistance
was. And I think today I'm pretty sure I don't know what it is in the sense that when you take
the typical phenotype of someone who's insulin resistant, what do they look like biochemically
and anthropomorphologically, right? So they're hyperinsulinemic, they have elevated levels of
glucose, they probably have some degree of obesity or adiposity. So what does that mean?
Because clearly their fat cell is quite sensitive to insulin. If the fat cell ever became resistant
to insulin, you could not reesterify fatty acids and you would have an endless stream of lipolysis
exiting fatty acids from the fat cell. So you'd actually be quite lean. There's something going
on in the muscle that clearly is resistant to the effect of insulin, but of course there are both
insulin dependent and insulin independent means by which we can dispose of glucose. And this is
where, coming back to what you said a moment ago, I actually wanted to ask you that question,
which is, we'll park it, but the question was, does metformin participate in the AMPK driven insulin
independent modality of glucose disposal? You're nodding, so I think that's a yes and we'll come
back to it. And then there's the liver. And this is the one to me that is the most complicated and
the one I'd like to begin with. So before I ask you to elaborate on the specifically what is
meant by insulin resistance in the liver, am I a complete moron for not understanding this?
No, but can I make it a little bit more interesting even because I need to bring it to aging. Yes.
I would love to talk about diabetes, but let me just put up front. I'm not sure that the diabetes
property of metformin are really the aging properties of metformin. Okay. This is my
provocation. But let me go back to insulin resistant because in 1997, a science paper appeared
that made it the best day of my life and the worst day of my life. Okay. What was the paper? The
paper was taking a nematode, okay, so a primitive model, decreasing the insulin sensitivity.
This is known as the DAF2 model. And when you do that, the nematode accumulates fat
in their intestinal cells. So they are becoming visceral obese and they live several times longer.
So why is it the best day in my life? Because you could with one genetic manipulation
extends lifespan significantly. That meant going from hope, actually from nothing from-
Was this Cynthia's paper?
No, that's Gary Rufkin. But at the same time, Cynthia had their DAF16. Tom Johnson had the
age one model. There are several papers that came and all of them said, hey, we can change
lifespan. And the example was always insulin sensitive.
And this mutation, to be clear, because between DAF2, DAF16, and the dietary manipulations,
there are several permutations of that C. elegans model. But just to make sure I know which paper
we're talking about, this was only attenuation of DAF2, nothing to DAF16 and nothing to dietary
change. Right, right. Can you just, for the listener, define what is the analog of DAF2,
DAF16 in us? DAF2 is the insulin receptor and DAF16 is the Foxo transcription factor.
But the point is, at that time- Yeah, you took a worm that normally lives two weeks and you
turned down its insulin receptor slightly, not off, correct? Right, right. But you made
it insulin resistant and it was accumulating fat. And what was I bringing in to the field?
I was saying the major reason for aging is this insulin resistance syndrome. And the main part
of the insulin resistance is accumulation of visceral fat. And so the premise was good.
The example was disaster to me. I had the JCI paper at that time in press, really showing with
MRI pictures how caloric restriction decreases the visceral fat. I was talking about the
biology of those fat and stuff. And it was a major paradox for us in the field and how we continue
if we're saying insulin resistance is good for longevity and everybody in diabetes knew that
this is a disaster. Why am I telling you that? Because I learned later, I was thinking later on
experiments that I've done. Oh, so first of all, the experiment that I've done that was very
conclusive was I took a bunch of rats, 150 actually, and all of them underwent surgery
after puberty. In some of them, I removed their visceral fat depots by surgery. And in the other,
it was a sham procedure. So I just moved it but didn't remove it. And we had three groups in the
experiment. One was ad libidum feeding. The second was caloric restriction. This is the control.
They would leave 40% better. And the third group was ad libidum feeding of the rats that their
visceral fat was removed. And I said, without the visceral fat, even with nutrients, they live
longer. And they actually lived significantly longer than ad libidum by 20%, but not as much
as the caloric restriction. So just to make sure I understand, you had a two to one ratio of your
animals because you had- No, I had three groups. Three groups, but one of them was all ad lib feeding
of the visceral fat removed. That was- Right. And then of the ones that had sham surgery,
they were randomized to ad lib versus CR. Correct. It really showed that visceral fat,
the removal of visceral fat had major effect. And when the animals who had the visceral fat removed
were autopsied or whatever the word is for rat autopsies, had they figured out a way to
reaccumulate visceral fat or where had they accumulated fat? No. In fact, when you do this
procedure after puberty, if you do it before puberty, they accumulate visceral fat. Otherwise,
they don't accumulate much visceral fat. Did they have changes in subcutaneous fat?
That's a good question. Mice have it when you do it and rats do not. What did they ultimately
succumb to? They all die from the same thing only at different times. Which is what, cancer? Yeah.
It was sprig doling. So kidney disease and cancers were the leading cause of death.
So you basically got half the benefit of CR by doing this operation.
By eating ad libidum, but without visceral fat. Yeah.
So you understand it's very- Sorry, one other question here. Was there any change in their
health span or their spryness? Yes. There was a health span. In fact, what happened to the ad libidum,
ad libidum starts losing weight at the end of their life. And the ad libidum with visceral fat
have still gained weight after the others. It was a significant change in weight. And then there's
a whole health span, their insulin levels and other things that we've done in parlors. So they
were healthy and they were healthier for longer, which is kind of the experiments that we do
with animal models. Is it possible to take one of those rats
and either through caloric restriction or other dietary restriction, get it to puberty to the
point at where you did the surgery, but without any visceral fat. And then ask the question,
if they've gone through that period of development without developing visceral fat, do they have
somehow protection from the diseases that come even if you feed them ad libidum thereafter?
So we did this experiment in Zuker fat animal, Zuker diabetes animal, and we took their visceral
fat. Tell people what the Zuker rat looks like. So the Zuker rats are rats that are really,
really, really obese, hungry all the time. So they have hyperphasia. They can't stop eating. Right.
Because they don't have the leptin receptor. So they are hungry all the time. And they're
nasty because you try to come close to them. They think your finger is food. So they're eating
all the time. And we did surgery on them before puberty because they became obese really much
before puberty. And what happened is by six months, they all become diabetics. Our animals up to four
months did not become diabetic. And then between four and six, they became diabetic, although we
took their visceral fat. But what we found out that 80% of the visceral fat grew back. So we
actually had the perfect experiment. As long as they didn't have visceral fat, they didn't develop
diabetes. Once they got the visceral fat, they developed diabetes. But I want to make. And sorry,
one other thing. If you took that group and who already developed diabetes with visceral fat,
and you just removed the visceral fat, can you reverse the diabetes? No, I we've never done
this experiment. Don't know. Because we're interested in aging. But I'm telling you all
that to make one point because so far, the paradox just got worse, right? The nematodes with insulin
resistant visceral fat leaves longer. And we showed that mammalian's live longer if you take
this visceral fat and make them insulin sensitive. Whenever we take visceral fat, we make them more
insulin sensitive. Okay. Until I realized one thing, it takes me a few hours to make red insulin
resistant. I give them glucose, I give them free fatty acid, I give them some other things, I can
make them insulin resistance very rapidly. So at first, I used it as you see, we can do the chronic
insulin resistant in a few hours. Okay, you just load them with nutrients, you become insulin
resistant. But then I thought of the aging part. When you get glucose to the muscle, the glucose
goes into the muscle. If you're not moving the muscle, it's not going to turn more glucose to
energy, it will switch from free fatty acid to glucose, but there's no more glucose burning.
So it goes to glycogen, right? And it goes to glycogen, but you keep on putting glucose in the
muscle. And there's just so much glycogen that the muscle can store. So the muscle has to become
insulin resistance. Okay, it's a protective mechanism. There's no evidence that the muscle
can in any way, shape or form undergo de novo lipogenesis and create any of the fatty acid,
is there? To create any of the fatty, let's say, no, not there any evidence that muscle can carry
out the novo lipogenesis. I don't think so. I don't think so. I'll have to think because I
have a different, I have to think about it. But the point is, okay, I understand your point. I
don't think if anything, there's no much. The glucose, the muscle tells the glucose, you go
somewhere else, you go to fat. Okay. So the only organ that can take in completely excess amount
of glucose in the end has to be the liver because it at least has the capacity to turn excess glucose
into fat. Whereas all of the other organs are going to be saturated. That's true. And that's
part of, I think where the glucose is going. Okay. To fat and to liver. Okay. So what am I telling you?
I'm saying that insulin resistance is a protective mechanism. It's a modulator. It's a stress response.
It's something. So now I understand why a stress response mechanism in one animal caused them to
live longer. And in another animal, it's a pain in the butt. So I went and I wrote this review with
Luigi Ferrucci. I wrote this review where we took all the animals that had problems with their
insulin sensitivity, the animals that are insulin resistance and live longer and the animals with
insulin sensitivity that live shorter. And there's a huge list of it. Rapamycin is an example, right?
Rapamycin causes insulin resistance and the animals is the best intervention in rodents.
There's a PTP1, a transgenic animals. It's very insulin sensitivity and it has half the lifespan
the lifespan of a wild type animal. When you say insulin resistant or insulin sensitive, are you
always referring to muscle? Are you referring to liver? How are you defining them? Well, in this
sense, it was everything. It was IRS, for example, IRS one, IRS two knockout, some of them only in
the brain. So it was really insulin resistance everywhere. Is IRS one found in the muscle and
not the liver? No, IRS one and IRS two are everywhere, but IRS two is more in liver.
Yeah, they sort of have selective expressions. Right. Right. Yeah. So I'll just translate
IRS one insulin receptor substrate. So let's talk about exactly how the muscle takes in glucose.
So we are walking around. If I bolus you with glucose right now and your blood glucose rises
from wherever it is right now, 90 to 200, let's say I give you an enormous bolus of glucose,
I double it. So you're up to 180 milligrams per deciliter. This is a very high screaming high
level, which by the way, only amounts to an extra few grams of glucose. But nevertheless,
what is the chain of events that leads to insulin being secreted and the muscle ultimately disposing
of that glucose both actively or passively? Well, there'll be obviously a secretion to insulin
that's relative to your glucose level. So the beta cell is the sensor and outcomes insulin. And now
what is insulin doing to the muscle? And insulin through the insulin receptor will get translocation
of the glute for those are the glucose transporters that are the major glucose transporters in muscle.
It will go from an intracellular pool into the plasma membrane, integrated and starts getting
glucose like crazy into the cell. And that happens quite passively, meaning once the glute for
transporter is translocated across the cell membrane, glucose can passively rush in. Correct.
It doesn't require ATP to bring it in against a gradient of any sort. Correct. And in fact,
it has its own intrinsic activity that's not the energy dependent. So it can go faster or slower by
different ways. Now, is there another method by which without insulin, we can get glucose into
a cell that somehow relies on AMP kinase? Not on AMP kinase, but there's non-insulin mediated
glucose uptake. In other words, there's a way for glucose to get up without the insulin. And we know
that from hyperglycemic clamp and from other things that when we can move the insulin or keep
insulin level at basal and still there's a substantial glucose uptake that's happening.
So yeah, we know that. What's the mechanism of that? I'm not sure I know. It also seems to be
enhanced by exercise. That's true. That's true. This ninja is the non-insulin mediated glucose uptake
is something that is exercise dependent too. And it seems to. That's why now I understand your
question. Is AMP kinase part of the day? And I don't know that. Yeah. I only have one patient
in my practice who has type one diabetes, but he is such an interesting patient because of his
incredibly strict dietary control and his unbelievable appetite for exercise. And
I've never seen a higher level of adiponectin in a human. I've never seen a higher level of sex,
hormone binding globulin in a human, which are basically and we know how much insulin he has
because he injects it and he injects so little insulin into himself and yet can seem to, you
know, he has a hemoglobin A1C below six using six to eight units of insulin a day. And so what got
me, that's what got me very interested in this non-insulin dependent glucose uptake. Yeah. I'm
not doing this research anymore. I used to be in front of that. I glucose itself can modulate
glucokinase activity in the liver. There's a lot of things that happening. And of course, there's
coordination between the fat and the liver. And then I started being interested because we can
do things to the hypothalamus and take over this insulin and muscle and fat and liver. We can do
it all from the brain. Isn't that amazing? Well, just because I'm so fascinated by this, and I
think it will help the listener to understand the complexity of what you just said. If I took an
animal and put a lesion into the ventral part of the hypothalamus, a normal animal, what could that
do? What would that change about its metabolism? Well, that would increase basically food intake
and change a lot of the peripheral physiology, but we do basically the opposite. We give
insulin to the hypothalamus or glucose or IGF or leptin. Okay. And then we see what happens to the
peripheral. During the periphery, those hormone levels are not increasing at all. And not only
that, the liver is a good target to follow because what you can do with the liver, you can do
selective hepatic vagotomy. And everything that you did through the brain doesn't work anymore
because it needs the nerves. Right. So I'll explain to the listener what that means. So the vagus
nerve connects the body through this parasympathetic system. And of course, if a patient has a liver
transplant, or if you do an operation where you sever the vagus nerve, you sever that connection
between the central nervous system and the periphery. Correct. And so we can do it experimentally
and it will help us see if it really- How much of it is vaguely mediated versus not? Or yeah,
or more nerve only. It's the nerves because we do, it's not only vagotomy, we do a little bit
adrenergic too, but it's through the nerves and not through a chemical reaction on the liver.
You see, this is the problem with metabolism near. The more I go into it, the less I know. It drives
me nuts. My absolute knowledge increases incrementally and my relative knowledge falls
precipitously. Well, I think I realized that you know what to ask. So you're undermining your own
abilities, but it's really the integrative metabolism is really very confusing to explain.
So we will define insulin resistance at the muscle, whether it be from an aged phenotype
or a diabetic phenotype as a scenario under which a fixed amount of insulin hitting the insulin
receptor produces fewer Glut4 transporters. Is that a fair definition? Well, the definition of
insulin resistance is really different and very simple. It's all about the glucose uptake in the
muscle really. It's all about the ability of insulin to clear glucose. That's the only way
we define clinically insulin resistance, although that totally misses the point because those
insulin levels have different effects on different tissue. But for us, the insulin
sensitivity is totally related to the glucose uptake. So let me give you an example. So when I
use an oral glucose tolerance test with my patients, I'm a bit of a stickler. So if they take their 75
grams of Glucola, I measure their glucose and insulin at baseline, administer the Glucola 30
minutes later, 60 minutes later, 90 minutes later, and if I'm feeling aggressive, 120 minutes later,
we re-measure the glucose, the insulin and the FFA, and maybe even the C-peptide. But for
simplifying it, just the glucose and insulin. So let's assume you have two patients who start
out with a fasting glucose of 90 milligrams per deciliter and insulin I use of six.
They both get their 75 of Glucola. And let's again, simplify this by just looking at one
hour. What happens? Both of them at one hour have a rise of glucose from 90 to 130 milligrams per
deciliter. One of them did so with a rise of insulin from six to 20. The other did it with
a rise of insulin from six to 90. They've both disposed of glucose with equal magnitude.
Would you describe them both as equally insulin sensitive? It's a little bit complicated. You know,
first of all, so let me just say for aging, 120 is not enough. In elderly, the glucose tolerance
goes. So the rise in insulin is changing throughout normal physiology and throughout individuals.
And you might have missed some of the insulin peaks earlier on or later on.
Yeah. Looking at 30 versus 90 is a big insight. And you're right. I mean, Joseph Kraft, who is a
pathologist, who has done a lot of work on this, he samples to five hours. Now, again, clinically,
that's challenging in the regular day to day practice, but in the laboratory, that's feasible.
And you're right. You can see so much happening beyond that. But I tried to pick an example that
was as egregious enough in its difference that what I'm trying to get is the difference in
hyperinsulinemia and whether that factors into how we think about insulin resistance.
Right. No, I don't think the clinical world is thinking like that. So I'm actually an active
endocrinologist. I still see on Thursdays if I'm in town teaching fellows in diabetes clinic in
one of your hospital. So I am involved very much in this field. And I'll tell you
that we rarely measure insulin in any of our patients, but that's not really your patients.
Okay. I'm talking about what's the use of measuring insulin in type 2 diabetic patients.
So it's a different issue. But yeah, this sounds like there's a different insulin response
to lower the glucose to the same extent.
Because the hypothesis would be that the patient with hyperinsulinemia
is now demonstrating. I mean, that's basically a harbinger of the first one who's going to
struggle with glucose disposal. That would be my hypothesis is the one who needed 90 units of
insulin to dispose of glucose with the same efficacy as the person who needed 30 is sooner
rather than later going to have a harder time disposing of glucose.
Well, you know, there is another possibility that those are the people who get other diseases for
a slayer like heart attacks or stroke. In other words, their insulin resistance
will affect a lot the way they do the aterosclerotic plaque and, you know, this hyperinsulinemia on
organs that might not be insulin resistant even, right? On cells that not coming in.
So I would say that they could either the one who become diabetic or the one who are going to get
microvascular disease much faster.
Which brings it right back to our observation of glucose versus insulin,
micro versus macular vasculature. That's a very good point. So how does insulin
signaling work to get glucose into the liver?
The liver has a different glucose transporters, the GLUT2, that is not translocated.
And that is the major way by glucose gets into the liver.
So it's a little bit different, but it's not stimulated the same.
So it's constitutively expressed across the membrane.
It's not stimulated really by insulin as much.
So it's more gradient driven to get the glucose from the circulation into the liver.
Yes. And that's where the portal blood is. So there it's very sensitive to the
increasing glucose concentrations.
Well, that's very interesting because it's certainly, I mean, there's lots of evolutionary
reasons why that would be a fail safe, right? Given the importance of, you would never,
ever want the liver to be denied glucose, given that if you ever shut down the liver's ability
to make glucose, by my calculation, you could live about six minutes.
Yeah. Look, I was an intern of Sheila Sherlok. She's named Sheila Sherlok in England and a
Royal Free Hospital, very non hepatologist. And she asked a group of us, what's the main
role of the liver? And I raised my hand and I said, it's to produce glucose.
That would be my answer by the way.
And everybody laughed at me and she threw chalks at them and stuff. And she said,
just a minute. Why are you saying that? I said, because if you take the liver out and clamp
the vessels, the guy will die from hypoglycemia, which is absolutely true.
Yeah. Yeah. It's, you know, maybe it's just because I'm in the midst of writing this chapter
for my book about the liver. But I literally yesterday I sat here in my room and penned out
the calculation of 180 pound person with blood glucose of 180 milligrams per deciliter,
clamp the liver, how many minutes until they die? It's about four under those, under those
conditions. Can you imagine that? Think about like what this beautiful organ has to do.
But you know, another thing to consider in your example, right? So for example, elderly
have enough insulin to suppress glucose production. Glucose production is easier to suppress
than it's suppressing lower level of insulin than stimulating glucose,
uptaking the muscle. The liver is more sensitive than the muscle. And so elderly have the ability
to suppress a particular glucose production because they have enough of insulin to do that.
But when you start giving them food during the day, they fail and they become glucose
intolerance and diabetic. They might have diabetes, although their basal level are well,
just because of this enough insulin to suppress glucose production and not enough
to increase glucose uptake. So the sensitivity of the tissues to insulin is really part
of what you're describing. If you look at the basal, it's very different when you look at stinging.
Yes, the challenge. That's such a great point. And I won't go down that rabbit hole anymore
because I would love to, but there's so many other things I want to talk about near. Let's
go back to metformin and let's do it now through the context of an anti-aging drug. So there's
going to be some people listening to this who already know everything about you. If for no
other reason than the efforts you've put into tame, obviously I want to have plenty of time
to talk about that, but let's back up for a moment. Tell me when you first realized,
Hey, this metformin drug that I worked on 30 years ago, it's not just a great drug for people with
diabetes. This could actually be a drug that helps someone without diabetes live longer.
What was that epiphany for you? So first of all, there were studies on the biology of aging
in rodents and the first guy, which I'll be embarrassed now to forget, he's a guy from
Leningrad that was the first to say, I've done a rodent studies and animals with metformin
Anatoly. I'll remember it maybe later. And he showed that a life extension
increases in variety of animals to which he gave metformin. That led to some studies.
What was his hypothesis? Do you remember? What drove him to do that?
There was never any high hypothesis. It's even wasn't related to glucose metabolism necessarily.
He thought that maybe there's an anti cancer effect and he looked at that, but then he got
models that were hypertensive and they also live longer. So he thought those are different effect.
And then he considered to aging. But at that time, this was in the eighties when he started that.
And bothers me that I don't remember his name. I should take more metformin.
And he was pushing, he was showing up in meeting and showing. And so people have tried to do it
in the United States and they showed that there is a significant effect on insulin. By the way,
the effect of insulin in animals is 10%, not like rapamycin is 24%. So there's a milder
effects, but in every study, they showed that health span is improved, you know, by 50%.
So the effect on longevity was less than the effect of health. By the way, that's perfect
for what I'm trying to say. I'm not for longevity. I'm just for health span, right? So if we can
leave healthy, healthy, healthy, die, that's fine with me. Yeah. The so-called squaring of the
long-term. Right. Square of the longevity. So he started Asimov, his name is Asimov.
So that's what Asimov showed. People have started looking at that. There are several studies,
three studies that gave it also to nematodes. They also lived longer. And there's several
effects on health span in the biology of aging. Now, the reason, there's a lot of needle threading
here in my story here. Okay. But I want to tell you the moment that I knew we have to do this
study was a publication, not in a very high impact journal, but it was an amazing study
that could be done only in the UK, because in the UK, you can go into pharmacies
and look at prescription that they gave. And you could follow the mortality of those patients.
Because the NHS system allows you to centralize everything from prescription to usage to mortality.
Exactly. And they're probably, they don't need to be de-identified after mortality. When you're dead,
you're not private anymore. Okay. So they did this study. So what they've done,
they're forearms to this study. They came and took patients who are on sulfonylurea, 12,000 patients.
Okay. And they matched them to 12,000 people without diabetes. Okay. Same pharmacies, same doctors,
controlling for some other things. And of course, the people on sulfonylurea had higher mortality
than their control. You know, double. Right. Because of course, they had a reason to be taking
the sulfonylurea. Right. They had diabetes. So that's okay. Then they took 78,000 people on
metformin and 78,000 people who were non-diabetic, again, matching them. And the 78,000 on metformin
was metformin monotherapy. Monotherapy. First line. Right. And they watched their mortality.
So just to underline again, the people on metformin had diabetes, their control didn't have.
They were more obese than the control. They also have more diseases than the control,
but they had significant less mortality, 17% less mortality in the metformin group.
And, you know, the sulfonylurea group was okay. So if you get less mortality with metformin
when the setup is diabetes, that really shows that metformin has a very important effect in
humans as far as aging. What was the median dose of metformin in those populations? They were over
a thousand milligrams. That's it. Just a thousand milligrams. Well, they intended more, but the
average was about 50 milligrams. You know, I don't. The average was 1500. Yeah. No, a thousand
milligrams. I'm sorry. They, this is a discussion there. I don't think they really could validate
the dose. Because an elegant thing to do if you have 78,000 in your database is now stratified by
dose. Absolutely. They who's taking 500, 1,000, 1,500, 2,000. They couldn't do that. And I really
cannot answer you if you can get back to the data or not. I really don't know. The dose, the dose
we chose came from other studies, but, you know, that's not the only thing we know about metformin.
What was the time course of that, by the way? Do you know how many? Five years. Five years more
time. So five years exposure to metformin or five years of prospective mortality following?
No, it's fine. Well, it's all, it was all a prospective study. Okay. It was all a prospective
study when they started. Okay. They went back, they looked at everybody on metformin. Oh, I guess
what I'm asking is, do we know how long they needed to be on metformin to achieve the benefit? No, no,
we don't know. Okay. So we followed them for five years of mortality in a prospective cohort, but
they could have been on metformin for five years or 25 years. We don't know. No, no, it's newly,
it's newly prescribed metformin. They were not more than five years. Oh, so we have normalized
by duration as well. Absolutely. Absolutely. No, they haven't been on metformin before. Those are
newly diagnosed type two diabetes. So, so near, that's a pretty, to be blunt, goddamn staggering
result. So my metformin moment, nowhere near as dramatic as yours, basically came out of
a research project I did with two analysts in 2013. And I don't even remember what prompted
the question, but there was a question we had internally about what was the benefit of metformin.
Oh, no, no, now I remember the question. The question was, was there a relationship between
hyperinsulinemia and breast cancer? This was the question we wanted to ask. And as we dug and dug
and dug and dug and dug, something kept hitting us over the head over and over and over and over
again, which was with or without diabetes, with or without obesity, with or without hyperinsulinemia,
any way you sliced and diced the data of people with type two diabetes with and without metformin,
they got much less breast cancer, which then dug us down a rabbit hole if they seemed to get much
less cancer, which was, you know, that was a big aha moment. Right. And there are hundreds of
studies that show the association between metformin and less cancers and not only that,
less all cancers, except prostate, by the way, prosthetists hanging there, maybe a little bit.
And when we went, and I'll tell you later, but when we went to the NCI to make them partners
in this TAME study, it was really interesting. Can you tell people what TAME stands for?
TAME stands for Taming or Targeting Aging with Metformin. And it's a study that's designed to
prove the concept that aging can be targeted, but also or mainly for me is for the FDA to give an
approval to an indication that's like aging. The first time I heard about TAME was actually
here in this city. I was having dinner with Steve Osthead. It must have been in 2015,
maybe 14, 15. Steve is a gem of a human being. I consider him certainly one of the most important
mentors in my exploration of this field of aging. We're partners in many ways. He's a great guy.
He is. He is one of these guys that has his knowledge is out of control. You can't ask him
a question that he doesn't know where to go for the answer. I have the highest respect for Steve.
I can't wait to interview him here as well. But I remember him telling me about this.
And my first thought was, Steve, that's a crazy idea. The drug is free. Who the hell is going to
pay for this study? NIH can't pay for it because they don't consider aging a disease. Pharma can't
pay for it because there's no way to make money on it. I mean, I might pay like 10 cents a year for
my supply of Metformin. It's a free drug. I said, you're doing the wrong study, man. You got to do
this with rapamycin. So talk to me about the challenges of this. This is you're proposing
something that has really never been done before. Can I just ask you, are we going back to
Metformin? Because you asked me about diabetes, but not Metformin action. Will you ask me later?
Absolutely. I cannot wait to dive into Metformin. Yeah, we're not going to get off this topic for a
while. Yeah. So, so look, if I'm answering now, why Metformin and not rapamycin? Oh, you don't
need to answer that question. I was just sort of teasing Steve that day. Well, there are people
who are asking, and of course, Metformin, we have preliminary data. We have the cancer. We have
clinical studies, you know, clinical studies of Metformin, the diabetes prevention program,
it prevents diabetes. The UKPDS, it prevents cardiovascular disease. The Alzheimer literature,
there are two clinical studies to suggest that in mild cognitive impairment, it improves some domain,
by the way, like name recalling, Asimov. We'll up your dose after dinner. So there's lots of, and
safety, look, if we're going to have a new indication, we don't want to kill anybody on
the road. With rapamycin, we won't be sure. And it causes diabetes and it causes testicular atrophy
and cataracts in animals. Okay. So we have to play it safe. So- I would only add one caveat in
defense of rapamycin, which is with constitutive dosing. Right. And you're aware of the studies from
John Manick, right? Yes, of course. The last ones. Yes. Okay. So my view on rapamycin is it should
not be dosed every day. Exactly. It should be selectively dosed to target mTOR complex one,
leave complex two alone. Exactly. And I'll, we'll get back to that because I'll tell you what we've
done with metformin for the biology of aging part. So that's why the fact, you know, look,
we are a bunch of professors, including Steve Austin. We go to the FDA, by the way, a beautiful
movie by Ron Howard. He went with us to the FDA, to the Senate. Wait, has it been released yet? This
documentary? A year and a half ago. It's called the age of aging. It's national geographic. It's
the best movie that was done ever on aging. It's really quite incredible. Ron Howard is narrating
it. I remember, I'll tell you what, I was having dinner with Steve at some point during, he was in
New York for that being filmed. Yeah. So, you know, so we're a bunch of professors that are coming to
the FDA and kind of telling them, you know, you know that aging has biology, but this biology also
can be targeted. And they said, so what? We said, well, if you slow aging, then you prevent a bunch
of age-related diseases altogether. And I said, well, we're interested to hear. And we went through
this discussion with the FDA. I would say that the most interesting part and you'll appreciate it
because you're diabetes centric. I see you're. I'm actually not. I'm purely age centric.
You're metabolic.
But I'm diabetes. I think of diabetes as a great example of what happens when you don't fix things
earlier. So we told them, basically we came and we said, we'll do a study and what we're going to
see is cardiovascular disease and cancer and Alzheimer and mortality and diabetes. And I said,
not diabetes. He said, what do you mean not diabetes? He said, no, diabetes. Look, you diagnose
diabetes. First of all, you diagnosis on a chemical, on a chemical test, you know, you decide.
And only 40% of them, 10 years later will get complication. We're really not interested in
diabetes. Wait, wait. Did the FDA actually say this? Absolutely. Absolutely said that. And,
and by the way, I should add that there's another bunch of people who came to tell the FDA that they
should allow metformin for pre-diabetes because the DPP said, yes, forming prevents diabetes by
30%. And the FDA said, well, if you think that's important, why don't you make the diagnosis of
diabetes in 5.8 and probably been in one C, you know, it's not up to us to, to do that. And they
wouldn't give them an indication for pre-diabetes. That's a very counterintuitive point of view.
When you consider the long-term, not short-term, the short-term cost burden of diabetes is
relatively trivial, but it's that long-term cost burden that becomes quite elaborate.
You know, it's very boring with you because we have the same views. You're right.
So yeah. So, okay. But, so we had to adjust our study. We had to take diabetes as one of the
outcomes and put in and, you know, just increase the number and take diabetes out. It's not that
we're not going to follow diabetes, but the FDA is not interested in diabetes. So the, really,
the challenge was how do we define aging in a clinical study? Because one view is, well,
let's. Because you can't use survival overall mortality. Well, there's no, there's no biomarkers
to aging. All the diseases are, are there major risk factor is aging, you know? So how do you
define it? And we basically did a lot of work and published a lot of work and showed that,
okay, let's, let's take somebody who has survived cancer and he's 65 to 80 years old.
What's his chances of getting cardiovascular disease, cognitive decline, mortality, right?
The other things. And let's say it was 10. Okay. And okay. Now let's switch it around. Let's take
somebody who had cardiovascular disease. What's his chance of getting cancer and all the others?
10. Okay. Let's take somebody with Alzheimer. What's his chances? It really with aging,
it doesn't matter. The disease you get first depends on, you know, your genetics and environment.
If you have a mother who's diabetic and you're obese, you'll get diabetes first. Okay. But really,
because, because we age biologically, you know, in different way, whatever it is, the next disease,
you're going to get the next disease and we don't know what's the next disease,
but that's what we're going to prevent. That's sort of, it's a really interesting
idea you propose because it's in lending, you would call that asset value correlation. So you'd say,
well, let's say near comes to my bank and he has a credit card and he has a car loan and he has a
student loan and he has a mortgage and he has a personal business loan. Which one is going to
default first? Eh, I don't know. I mean, I could sort of tell you typically people are going to
stop paying their credit card before they stop paying their car and their mortgage. But boy,
once you default on one, those dominoes start to fall very quickly. And so that would have what we
would call a very high asset value correlation of default. Yeah. So it's sort of like, this is the
same for disease. Yeah. I think you're right. I'm saying it a little bit different. I'm saying I'm
agnostic to the disease. To which the first one is, yeah, it's just. I'm agnostic. It doesn't matter
what you come and what you're going to have, I'm going to prevent whatever it is. That's why we
have a composite. Okay. A composite. And people get very prickly about composite outcomes. Very.
And I got it. I'm going to get on my soapbox for a minute here. Cause this pisses me off to no end
when people get all bent out of shape about how you can't have a composite outcome.
And this is the bias against aging, really. Because in the end, what matters is how long
are you alive and how long is your health span optimized? So I'm sorry for, I made that rant as
short as I normally could. Normally that would be a 10 minute rant. Well, that would be a 10 minute
rant for me too. Okay. Yeah, absolutely. And this is where we get into trouble. I'll tell you what
the other pieces, but we had our grant reviewed at the NIH and unfortunately.
And is this inside any of the groups except NIA? Like is NCI weighing in on this?
Yes. Yes. I'll tell you what we've done. I'll tell you what we've done in a second. Let me
just make sure that I say that. So our reviewers were not GRS up because we, everybody's involved
and we have 14 centers. Okay. So everybody's involved. So the reviewers are from other
place and they just, they just, just a minute. You're saying that aging can be targeted and
one drug can do it. You're crazy. Okay. There's no such thing. Why don't you do three studies?
One study is metformin cardiovascular one study is metformin cancer one study. And we're saying,
no, because what are we doing? We're trying to give aging an indication. Suppose we do.
It's just such an anthem to the way they think. And I, I'm not saying that to be critical of them,
right? But they're in a silo. I know. Which is if you come to NCI, how can you care about anything
but cancer? Right. I know the silos are really, are really killers, but for us, so you could say,
well, let's do all those studies, but for us, we're calculating the power.
I was just about to say the power analysis on that study is going to quadruple your budget.
Well, for what they do, for us, it's not only, it's not only the budget. We don't want to stop
this study. Let's say that we show in two years that we, we delay cardiovascular disease. It's
significant. They'll stop the study. And they said, no, everybody now has to be on metformin,
but we wouldn't be able to show the FDA that we are, that we're aging. For us, aging is stop
telling us diseases. We are going to have a cluster and we're just going to delay the aging.
So we'll get, we'll get the health span extended by two, three years. That's what we're trying to
show you. And the significance is the, for the cluster, not for the individual disease. And if
you tell me to do individual disease, I need triple the, the budgets and I'm not going to get
to the FDA with the indication for aging. So it seems to me that the biggest challenge here
is not the funding. It's not the study design. It's the conceptual leap. It's, it's a completely
different paradigm of how we think about delaying death. Correct. Correct. Where do you stand today?
So I'll tell you a few things. First of all, we conceived it. I got my friends to what I call a
prison, a French prison in Spain somewhere. We were in a para door in the middle of nowhere in
Spain for several days saying, what do we have to do in order to open the field for aging to allow
us to get to treatments? And we decided several things, but one of them is to go, to go ahead with
things. By the way, I'm saying French prison because the food was good, but it was in Spain.
And we started, and I started getting those people, those clinical people together. And we
started really thinking through for what it takes for what it takes. And we had this whole academic
and wrote papers in order to say how we're thinking, how we're thinking of cluster of diseases,
how we're doing power calculations for targets, aging and stuff like that. We really spend a lot
of time with the best people. Now our friends came to us and said, just a minute, your study is
$70 million. If the National Institute of Aging is going to spend $70 million, that means this,
the National Institute of Aging is very small. It's just 3% of the budget, although we are 80%
of the diseases, right? Then we won't have money for the grants. And I said, well, what I'm going
to do is two things. First of all, half of the money is going to come from somewhere else. That's
my association with AFR where Steve and I are the scientific directors. And for AFR,
I got the other half. So the 45 million is already raised and that's mostly philanthropic.
Right. And then we went among the institutes and. So NCI should chip in a bit.
NHLBI, NIDDK. They didn't commit because first they have to see the review, okay? Or they have
to have the decision that the NIA wants. I would tell you though, that the NCI director who's a good
friend of mine is waiting for Taim to come. He's like, where's Taim?
So the NCI has committed. It's basically a bunch of contingent commitments.
Yeah. I just want to say committed is the wrong word because they didn't have a budget yet and
the grant didn't come to them. But I know that they will give them money because their head
will do it. Yeah. So that's good to hear. So
realistically, when is the soonest you would begin enrolling for Taim?
You know, I'm waiting for something to know next week. And if next week goes well, so I just want
to let you know that we have an alternative. The alternative is not for profits. That the reason
they haven't joined us is that their charter is not to fund anything that the NIH funds. They
want something riskier. Of course. So if the NIH is not funding because they feel it's risky,
those will fund. So we can start anywhere. And the answer is early 2019. Okay. We're basically
all our centers are ready to go. How many centers?
14. How many subjects? 3000.
Age? 65 to 80. Any limitation on comorbidities? No, in fact, well, there are a lot of limitations,
but we're very inclusive. But no existing diagnosis of cancer? No, unless they're cured.
Okay. So you could be in remission, but you can't have active cancer. Is it secondary
prevention or primary? You could have cardiovascular disease in the past if you're okay now. You could
have mild cognitive impairment and low speed walk will be a criteria. So in other words,
we don't want the people like in my study who will become centenarians because we're wasting
time on them. We want people who we know are kind of in the midst of aging. And we know that it's
never too late to target aging. And that's where. So 65 years and up, five years studied, and you're
going to randomize one to one or two to one, one to one and the placebo versus what dose of
metformin two grams? 1500. So, you know, the, so first of all, I should tell you that Merck
company from Germany is giving us the placebo metformin. Right. So the drug is free. So when,
when you say nobody's interested, it's true. It's generic, but actually Merck has the worldwide
license for metformin. And they're actually giving supply to lots of studies because they
kind of realize that this is good. And do you think there's a difference between generic
metformin and branded in terms of efficacy? Is there any reason? No, so they're really,
this is kind of a, this isn't necessarily a creative to them because one can buy metformin
generically anywhere. They're not going to make more money from giving us this. Well,
you know, I should say even now a lot of the metformin suppliers have higher sales
and a lot of them are non-theabetic. Yeah. So this thing, which is, which is bad for me,
because I don't want too many people to know that, right? I want to do this study. I don't want,
and I don't, I want people. Well, you'll have, you know, I don't think, hopefully it won't
impair your, your recruiting and the power analysis. I mean, it's funny, honestly, near,
I would have guessed, but this is, this speaks to the non-linearity and complexity of estimating
power. You can't do it without the tables. I would have guessed you needed a bigger end than 1500
in each group. You are using 80 or 90% power. 90% power. But I should tell you, look, for every
disease, we have almost a 30% effect and we chose 22% effect. Okay. For every disease, we have
preliminary data for the same. Got it. So you lowered your threshold to call it 20% from 30%.
And at a 90% power, you've hopefully powered this. Right. You've got buffer both on your power and
effect size. Right. And, and again, we don't want to stop the study early either for one effect.
So we carefully thought about it. We asked for a grant for six years because we don't want to
overdo it. Okay. So it might finish in four or in six, but we have the flexibility to look at that.
Any non-US centers or are they all US? No, we decided to do only in the US because of
communication. And because, look, outside of the US, people came and said, you know, we'll fund
TANE. But how, you know, if they say after two years, we won't fund them, you know, it's very
different because, because if it's a center, they need to be part of the part of the power and we
cannot afford to lose them. So we, you know, those and other considerations, we decided to stick with
the United States. So let's go back to what we really glossed over, but now I want to dive into.
Why do you believe at the cellular mechanistic level, metformin is an anti-aging drug?
So let me take you through that in a, I don't want to say schematic way because we don't have the
scheme here, but in a way that maybe I think will be easy to think. So I want to start by saying
that studies have shown that some of the effects of metformin are through AMP kindness and some of
them are independent of AMP kindness. Okay. Is it important not for metformin, but I don't know
which are the ones who are relevant more for aging. Okay. And it's hard to know and it'll get
complicated in a second more. So metformin gets into the cell through a transporter that's called
OCT1. Okay. This transporter is not equally equal in every cell. So unlike FENforming that goes
without a transporters and affect everything metformin is peculiar in this way, but we have
the preliminary data and it binds to complex one in the mitochondria. Does it do so preferentially?
Does it gain entry preferentially into the liver in humans? Only in the sense that there's a nice
concentration of OCT1 in the liver, but not, not, but it's not, I don't think it's the top other
organs have. So basically it's more about OCT distribution and expression, maybe than tissue
specificity. It's more that I want, I want metformin everywhere. Okay. I want metformin everywhere. And
I'll tell you how I kind of proved that. So now metformin binds to complex one in the mitochondria.
I'll tell you that metformin has some action, epigenetic action that are independent of the
mitochondria. You can do it with what's called row zero cells. You can, you can deplete mitochondria
and see and measure things and you can measure things even without mitochondria. Okay. Again,
do I need the mitochondria? What type of epigenetic changes do you see in the row cell?
In histone deacetylation. Okay. So I cannot argue that this can be important. It's not important if
we use metformin, but it's important if you want to ask me are the mechanism of metformin AMP
dependent, mitochondria dependent. So there's an HDAC property that we may not have even thought of
before. Right. Okay. So it gets to the mitochondria and in the mitochondria, it basically changes ADP,
ratio. And that's a lot of it is important in the liver, but not only to the extent that there is an
activation of AMP kinase. And Nier, is there a demonstrable reduction in NAD to NADH in that cell
when complex one is inhibited? Yes. Yeah, absolutely. Those studies have been, have been done.
So there's a lot that's going through AMP kinase. And I would tell you that downstream of AMP kinase,
there is mTOR. Okay. And it depletes, it decrease mTOR activity and increase autophagy. And there's
a whole pathway that will go to the pillars of aging. You know, I asked David Sabatini this
question a month ago and we're, he doesn't know the answer, but I'm hopeful that maybe one of the
postdocs in his lab will start to figure this out. I'm very curious about what the dose equivalent is
between in terms of purely looking at the readout of mTOR inhibition. What is the dose to dose
equivalence of metformin via AMPK versus RAPA directly? And I haven't, I mean, David didn't
know the answer, which tells me nobody probably knows the answer. Right. Look, it's, it's really
difficult. First of all, for example, lots of the non-AMP kinase activities are on much higher doses
of metformin. Well, that's my point is can you clinically match them and, and. No, because you,
you really don't know at the end how much metformin is in the cell. What we're doing now, we're doing
isolated cells. In other words, we treated animals with metformin and we're taking isolated cells
to just see the variability of, of metformin in individual cells.
Even amongst homogeneous tissues. Yeah. Like we take hepatocytes and look at the.
The variability of expression. Yeah. Right. So it's all kind of a important question, but,
but the story is still, I'll tell you the story because at the end I'm going to answer you what
is that doing for aging. Okay. And I don't want to rush this story because this is a great story.
You take your sweet time. So think about it in a scheme. You have the metformin in the middle,
getting through the plasma membrane, getting to the mitochondria. And on the left side,
let's say there is the MP kinase. Okay. Now in the right side. Oh, sorry. Just for the listener,
explain what a MP kinase does at the high level. It's, it's a hormone of what it's a hormone of
nutrient deprivation. And therefore it tells the body to do what like when you don't eat for a day,
AMPK goes up. Why? Well, but it's also an exercise mimetic pathway. Yes. That's what happens with,
with exercise. Really. That was the, the hope of what the MP kinase is doing, but it's a nutrient
sensing that is in part upstream of mTOR. Okay. But the other side of metformin
is what happens to the mitochondria because in a way, and I hope I won't regret saying it here,
but metformin is a weak cyanide. Okay. Look, what cyanide acted at complex for.
Right. But right. Oh, you just mean more broadly speaking. Right. It inhibits. So there is less
R O S production. Okay. And then there is less inflammation and there is other things that's
going just because the mitochondria is less oxidative pathway going down.
So this is a great example of why binary thinking doesn't very,
it doesn't do very well in biology, right? It can't be all or none.
Well, so now I can go on and on and connect all those, please do to eventually the pillar
of aging. But I want to insert another thing because other things are happening. For example,
insulin levels goes down, right? Why is it just due to the reduction of hepatic glucose output?
I'll tell you why I think. And then also inflammatory factors are going down.
And there is a whole NF kappa B action of metformin that might be part of the R O S and part could be
independent even without mitochondria. Okay. It's that confusing, but this is the point I want to
make. I don't know which one of those is important for aging, but parts of what you're measuring is
the following. You fix the aging on a cellular level. Okay. So the younger, the cells are younger.
A lot of things are correcting themselves. So I think at the end, the lower insulin levels,
the low inflammatory are not necessarily a direct effect. And that's why we're, we're fighting all
the time about what metformin is doing, because you can measure lots of things, but the things
you're measuring are because aging was fixed. And once aging is fixed, then there's whole
hemodynamic readjustant or whatever you want to call it. And then you're measuring that everything.
And this is not only typical to metformin. This is with rapamycin with resveratrol. You also can see
that there's a lot of things that are improving themselves. And I think we have to get used to
the fact that when you have a drug that we argue what it's doing, because everybody is measuring
something, some of it is true, but it's like secondary. It's you fixed it. How did you fix
it? True and unrelated. And it's funny, you mentioned those three, which again, I think speaks to an
advantage you have with tame. So when you look at rapamycin, resveratrol, and metformin, the big
advantage of metformin is you already know the dose and the frequency. With rapamycin over dinner
tonight, I'm going to give you my philosophy on the dose and the frequency, and we can discuss it,
but I can't demonstrate it to you with anywhere near the validity that you could do the same with
metformin. I had a wonderful discussion with David Sinclair and bioavailability came up on resveratrol.
Right? So maybe all the trials that say resveratrol is meaningless are simply not looking at what
happens if you get enough resveratrol in the right place. And again, it's amazing to me how many times
in biology we can make mistakes of the first order because of a third or fourth order omission.
And this, I guess I don't think I realized that until you just gave that explanation, the value
of effectively millions of patient years worth of data on metformin, not just from a safety standpoint.
By the way, billions. It's billions years. Is it billions? Yeah. So billions of patient
year data on metformin. I know that from an FDA standpoint, the highest priority is safety. That's
a low bar to cross. The more interesting one from the standpoint of this study is actual efficacy.
And it seems like if I'm hearing you correctly, metformin is an amazing B student. Let's not be
insulted by that. What do I mean? Are there better ways to inhibit Ross if you want to hammer the
Ross chain? Probably. There's clearly better ways to inhibit mTOR if that's all you want to do.
Are there better ways to modulate HDAC? Yes, I'm sure there are. But it might be that maybe part
of metformin's beauty is it does so many things at a B plus level. Never it's an A student, but it's
not a D student. And it's never, I mean, I'm sort of thinking about this sort of in a tongue in cheek
way, but it seems to do so many things reasonably well. Well, I call metformin a tool from my
perspective. It's just a tool to show that we can target aging because I think that there'll be much
better drugs and combination drugs and other in the future. Human lifespan is 115 years. We argue.
Maximum lifespan. Yeah, maximum lifespan. We argue because there's somebody 122, but there's a
statistic thing. So, okay. We die before the age of 80. So there are 35 years that as a species
without, not that we cannot change more, but just now without thinking too much futuristic,
low hanging fruit that we can do. And metformin is the perfect tool to start showing the proof of
principle here, but the future is much better. It's just, you have to pave the road here.
This is a beautiful pivot to something else I want to discuss with you because unfortunately I could
talk about metformin for three hours, but there's so many other things I want to discuss with you
near based on your work. And you just alluded to one, which is the work that you and your
colleagues have done on centenarians has been very influential in my thinking. So as I think about
aging clinically, I ask the question, start with the existence principle. What does it mean to live
a long life? Is there proof of this having existed? And there is, we have centenarians,
they exist. My hypothesis when I first started reading your literature, which was only about
five years ago, my hope, I should say not my hypothesis, my hope was that whatever genetic
benefit they had, which it became very clear to me very quickly that this wasn't about what they
did. In fact, they seem to have almost near immunity to the worst behaviors imaginable.
My fear when I read your first paper, which was a review paper, I can still see it. And I still
remember where I was sitting in a Sheridan hotel reading it. My fear was whatever blessing they had,
it was not, it had nothing to do with chronic disease and it had to do with something nebulous
and they had complete immunity from chronic disease and they just died in car accidents.
Like they eventually just died because something else tripped them up. And what I took away from
your work was no, their genetic gift was a phase shift. And when they got chronic diseases,
they still died of heart disease, they still died of cancer, they still died of Alzheimer's disease.
They simply got a 20 year bonus, if not more, maybe 29 on average, you could calculate,
call it a close to 30 year bonus. Well, of health span. You know?
Yes. Because completely functional life. Because they had compression of morbidity. So it's not
only that they lived longer and they lived healthier, but they died quicker at the end of that.
And you know, it's interesting, the CDC, the Center for Disease Control, have looked at the
last two years cost of life of people with different stuff. So they looked at people who
die at 70 and after a hundred and the cost of dying after a hundred was third of that of dying
in 70. So it's not only in our study, there's actually evidence to suggest that the medical,
and by the way, those when they were 70, they didn't go to the doctor. Okay. So, and this is
the base of this concept that's called the longevity dividend. Okay. What will happen
to society if we'll actually be healthier for two and a half years and the benefits
are immense. You think only of, you know, so we pay social security more and stuff, but
there are seven trillions dollars just in saving of medical costs. If you could just
leave healthier. So I know you don't spend an enormous amount of time anymore thinking about
the centenarians, you know, your literature followed very closely. You, you definitely are
spending much more time talking about and writing about the things that we just discussed. But
if you could go back in time a little bit for me, by the way, that's not true.
Maybe it's just selectively where I'm reading. Well, no, I think that's what's interesting to
people now. And I'm very happy about that, but I just got the, you know, the longevity,
the Epson longevity price. And my talk was actually about centenarians with a little bit
of my hypothesis stuff that was related to something, but the centenarians are, and we
have lots of grants on the centenarians because, you know, there's that talk, by the way,
is it something that people can watch? No, no, it wasn't recorded. Oh, it's a shame.
It's a real, I thought about, about this talk. It was fun for me to give because it was reflective
a little bit to, you know, one of the things that's always funny for me is people say, oh,
you know, I have, I can measure this thing. I'm sure that centenarians, they have, they have high
level because high levels are good. And I had to put into rest the fact that the genetics of
centenarians is really great for me. But the phenotype is not because you have a hundred
years old and you can measure something that can reflect what brought you here or the fact that
30% of them are going to die in the next year. So it could be a marker of, of death and not of
longevity. The other phenotype makes, doesn't interest to me. That's why I have their offspring
because their offspring will have the phenotype or half of their offspring will have the phenotype.
But those things were something that was nice because so many people are saying, you know,
we should measure in centenarians. No, we are, we're doing a longitudinal study on their offspring
and their offspring are equal everywhere to our control group. They just have half of the diseases.
Although you, by the way, that's a really interesting point near. I never once thought
of that. I never, what you just said that if I have a hundred year old centenarian in my study and
he or she has a CTEP mutation or an APOC3 mutation and I look at the predictable phenotype,
because I know what you should have if you have that mutation, hypo functioning APOC3 should have
low triglyceride. But technically without a little more longitudinal legwork, I don't actually know
what I'm measuring as a result of that. But that said, there must still be some benefit in,
you know what, now that I'm saying it, I realize you can't do it. The dream state would be to have
health records and phenotypes for centenarians that go 30 years back. In other words, it would
be beautiful to follow a centenarian from 70 to a hundred with phenotypic data.
So that's why we have the longevity study. It's a longitudinal study of offspring of centenarians
and people without longevity. And we're going forward. We're already 10 years into the study
and we're starting to see the differences between those guys. It's different population. They are
aging slower. Okay. The children of centenarians. So we have some of these things in mind.
What are the most important genetic differences between those either centenarians or offsprings
of centenarians and the rest of us? So it's very interesting. And so this is a part that you
haven't heard so from, but it's actually the growth hormone IGF axis. We have probably 60%
of our centenarians have genomic reasons. So let's explain the normal path of that. So the
pituitary gland makes GH. It tells the liver primarily to make IGF. Right. It binds to a
receptor, right? And the liver and IGF. And so some of the effects of the growth hormone system
are through growth hormone itself. And some of it is through IGF-1 level. Both of them are decreasing
with aging. So in this system, more than 60% and I think I'm underestimating. Okay. It's more,
it's probably more, but I didn't really calculate who has several mutations. You know, I can calculate
how many mutations there are, but not the overlap of the mutation. So I'm saying 60%, but it's the
most common genomic alteration in our centenarians. And I have to tell you. And where is it specifically?
I'll tell you in a second. And I want to just to tell you, I never, I wrote grants on that
because I thought, because there's preliminary data in nature, right? The small dogs live longer
and the ponies live longer. And when you mutate growth hormone or they're born dwarf, they live
longer. And when you give more growth hormone, they live shorter. So there is a lot in nature,
but the human data was really confusing. Some diseases, you know, when you have a high IGF,
you have more cancers, but you have less Alzheimer's disease, less cancer, I mean, sorry,
less heart disease and less diabetes, but more cancer, right? And mortality,
immortality, it's like in the middle, you know, a little bit tending to more from, you know,
from cancer. By our analysis, which I think pulls all of your data, we found that there was in
a U-shaped mortality curve with the nadir being between 60th and 80th percentile of all cause
mortality. So I want to tell you the problem with this association. On one hand, an individual that
age quickly, okay, their growth hormone IGF goes down quickly. Okay. So you would measure falsely
low IGF one level. If you catch them on the wrong side of their aging curve. Right. That wouldn't
fit our theory that low IGF is good because that's their accelerated aging. So this is a
problem with an association study like that. We discovered first of all, that when we take
our centenarians, so they're in our study because they've been healthy at age 95,
living independently. We take them at any age, but that's what they have to do. And we just look at
those with the highest IGF and the lowest IGF one level. Those with the lowest IGF one level
live twice as long. Those are already the centenarians, but only women, men do not. And
every example that I gave you, there's a sex difference. The growth hormone IGF is very sensitive
for women or for females. So let me ask you another question. It's very difficult clinically to measure
GH because it's pulsatile. Right. So whenever you're saying growth hormone, are you really
saying IGF, which is easier to measure? No, because I'm going to talk sooner, but not what I'm
measuring, but where the mutations are. Okay. But to repeat what you just said, the difference
between men and women, was that based on IGF level or GH level? IGF levels. Okay. But we discovered
in aging, we did a huge faux pas, okay, that we are now correcting. We studied in our labs
males only. We had excuses why females are menstruating. We don't know their effects.
And we're all discovering, look, even rapamycin that really works everywhere is better in females
than males. But acerbos is in males, right? They're examples where we totally miss the sex
effect. And growth hormone IGF is a perfect example, except those mice that are the snail
mice or the Ames miles, they have a pituitary problem, which makes them, I think, sex confused.
So they have so many other alterations, but sex difference is important. We also showed that those
women with the lowest IGF one level has much less cognitive problems. A third of the cognitive
deficiencies of those with the highest IGF. All right. Okay. So we had to grab our second
round of Topo Chico there, which by the way, I didn't even ask you upfront. This is your first
time having Topo Chico, right? Yeah. I'm in love. I mean, this is, there are a few things that bring
me as much joy as introducing people to this bottled water. The perrier is much milder. I like
to feel the bubbles. Well, I would, I think one thing we should consider for tame is if we can
have an arm that also includes Topo Chico. So there's a placebo, there's a metformin,
and then there's a metformin plus Topo Chico. And the question, the hypothesis will be,
does that somehow enhance lifespan? Because even if it does not, I predict it will enhance happiness.
Well, I have to tell you, I'm an advisor to the prime minister of Singapore.
Singapore is a place that can, you know, plan the future. And before going, I said, why don't you
ask me questions? And one of the questions, shall we put metformin in the water or in sodas?
Now, good to ask, you know, the answer is no, obviously, but it's good that you're thinking
that way. So metformin. And should you change your mind, I think you now know which soda it
should go into. Can you get it in Singapore? Oh, I'm sure we can. Yeah. So back to sort of
what you were saying, this IGF male-female disconnect, let's keep going down that rabbit
hole. So I was saying that one of the worries about low growth hormone and IGF is the effect
on the muscle because people think that growth hormone affects muscle function, muscle size.
And we found that in females and males, the IGF-1 level is not associated with better or worse
lots of muscle function, including grip and getting out of chair and, you know, other things.
So maybe the effect of low IGF and aging are just as good as having a higher effect of IGF on muscle.
Just weighs itself out. Okay. But then our study is genetics. Okay. That's what we try to do. And
just several years ago, almost I guess a decade ago, we found clusters of mutations in the IGF
receptor. Those were new mutations that haven't been found before, but we found them in nine of
our assentinarians, which was 2% of our assentinarians. And that was kind of a proof of concept
for us that clusters of mutations that are functional is what we really need to look for
rather than like everybody's doing, doing GWAS and find, you know, something infra-genomic somewhere.
And this was also the first proof of concept that the growth hormone IGF could be relevant to human
human aging. People that those 2% of our, those nine people had higher IGF-1 level because they
were resistant, right? It's the IGF receptors, they were resistant to IGF. So their level was
a little bit higher, but they were significantly shorter than others. Which is a great explanation
of how that phenotype would play out. You would say, well, how can they be short-statured with
high IGF? And the answer is if the IGF isn't as effective at the receptor. Right. But remember
that most of our people with low IGF are doing better. By the way, we take the people with the
IGF- Men also or just women? Two men in those nine people. And by the way, then there are dwarves,
human dwarves that called La Ronde dwarves that live in Ecuador and Haseco and Volto Longo and
some of the people in Ecuador were looking, basically were trying to find if they live longer,
too few of them to really know. But they have less cancer and less diabetes, you know, significantly
less. So there's other evidence from humans came after ours that there is at least less age-related
diseases in those people. They certainly didn't live a better life in any way that we could assess,
correct? I mean, we always joked that they weren't happy with the fact that they're short,
so they drank a lot and that's the alcoholism. And then when they crossed the road,
nobody saw them. So they died of more trauma. But I think it's really not true. So I met some of
them. We were in a Vatican conference. Everybody asked to bring his patients and Longo brought
somebody from Ecuador and I brought a centenarian from Rome. And the guy that he brought told a
different story. He wasn't unhappy. He was also happily married with a big woman and had children.
So I don't know. And is the defect in them at the growth hormone receptor in the liver?
In the liver. So they make normal amount of growth hormone. Their liver doesn't acknowledge it. High
amount of growth hormone because it doesn't work. Yeah. So they have lots of growth hormone,
but it's not being expressed through the liver into IGF. And so they have no IGF.
So we published last year a paper that took us 10 years to write. And basically,
we were looking at a relatively common mutation. I'm saying common because it's like three,
four percent in the population where they have a complete deletion of exome three in the growth
hormone receptor. Okay. So one of the exomes, one of the things that are important for the
integrity of this hormone, right, is deleted. And of course, you would think that that means
that the growth hormone is less effective. And Gilatzmon, who was fellow with me,
brought me this data to suggest that while it's three, four percent in our control population,
it's 12 percent in our centenarians. So I asked, so what's the IGF-1 level? And he showed it's
lower. And I said, and what's the height of the people? He said, well, that's the problem. They're
much taller. So I said, I cannot do anything with this study. It just makes no sense. I don't know
how to write. So the people with lower IGF, but the mutation was in the exome of the growth hormone
receptor. So they had lower IGF. So it was a dysfunction of the receptor in theory. So less IGF.
And we know that it was fully penetrant all their life. In other words, there's no chance that it
didn't start showing up until they were an adult. Well, we'll come back to that. But the mutation
didn't change. And by the way, just give me some numbers here. How low were their IGFs?
I don't remember.
Directionally. Are we talking about less than 100?
No, less than 200.
Yeah, 100 is about the median level of IGF for somebody over 65.
Yeah, I think in the studies that I told you, the average or the mean or whatever was 94,
something like that. I don't remember to answer about those people. Okay, now? Okay. So he said
what to do. I said, well, first of all, what you do with genetics, you do replication study,
you know, you go to other populations and you see what's going on there.
And second, you do a functional study. Let's see if it's really a functional mutation.
So it took almost 10 years, right? And in 10 years, we replicated the data in three other
populations in Amish, French, centenarians in the CHS here in the United States. And in all studies,
the people that live the longest had much more of those homozygosities in the growth hormone
receptor. So that was a great validation. Second, the functional. So Hassey Cohen, my partner in
USC, we send him the lymphoblasts of our patients, the affected and not affected. And he
is a growth hormone IGF expert. So he incubated them serum-free, so without stimulation.
And with growth hormone and looked both at activation and proliferation by growth hormone.
So in serum-free without stimulation, they had less activation and less proliferation, half
of normal, suggesting, yeah, that's the mutation. That's the function. When he incubated them with
growth hormone, it totally switched. I'm sorry, but going back, you talked about proliferation,
but was there a functional difference in the lymphocyte in addition to its increasing number?
No, there's, yeah, the first was activation by phosphor and some of the, okay, some of the-
But non-specific activation.
No, no, no, specific to what growth hormone is doing, but the proliferation, it's a cell data.
Yeah, that's an easy one. Yeah.
When he incubated it with growth hormone, it was the opposite.
Rather than this low proliferation, low activation, it was high activation, high proliferation.
So what's going on? Well, what's going on? When do we have high growth hormones for puberty?
So with high growth hormone, something has changed in the activation from low activation,
you jump to high activation for reason with the molecular, the real mechanism we don't know,
really, but that's what happened when you have high growth hormone. So they all were taller.
And then when growth hormone got down for the rest of their life, they shut off.
Okay. So, okay. So this is 12% of our people. Then Yuxing Sun, who's a geneticist that's working
on this, she was interested in microRNA. That's another epigenetic thing that comes. We haven't
been thinking about it, but those are RNA that comes from certain region of the gene and they
bind specifically to active region of the gene and they modulate it. Well, 30% of our centenarians
have clusters of microRNA that are overexpressed by a lot, by 40 times, you know, just immensely
activated. One of them, for example, microRNA, microRNA 142, that's increased by 35 fold.
When you incubate it with cells, it prevents the phosphorylation of the IGF receptor,
decreases some other signaling, foxal signaling, and some other stuff
dramatically. So there's a microRNA targeting of the growth hormone IGF receptor in about 30% of
our centenarians. Then 22% of our centenarians have mutation in FOXO3A. That's a common mutation in
centenarians. So you start 2% and 12%. Yeah. Tell people what FOXO3A does.
FOXO3A is another, how would I say, just housekeeper that lets in good stuff and change
things and put things in stop. It's too complicated to go more, but it is part of the insulin IGF.
It's very important, the transcription factor at regulating homeostasis, cellular homeostasis.
Right. Right.
That's not a great explanation, but isn't FOXO the most prevalent genetic difference? If you were to
just isolate them by genotype, if you look at CTEP and C3 and FOXO and GH and IGF, I mean,
my recollection is that FOXO might be the single most prevalent of the-
Well, FOXO, I'm not sure that it's true, but FOXO3A is common in all centenarians population
around the world. Not every population has the same mutations. In fact, what we're doing now,
when we have the exome sequencing of all our subjects, almost 3000 exome sequencing,
the important thing to do is to assign them to pathways because we're doing something really
silly with genetics. When we had this GWAS, we said we have million SNPs around the genome,
we'll find the diseases, every disease in the world. One of the stupidest thing we did, we took
one SNP at a time. Okay. Let's see if this SNP is significant, but we're not billed of one SNP of
a time. In certain population, there's down this pathway, there'll be another SNP that will change
the function. Our analysis now is totally different than how we started.
I agree with you completely, but I don't think most of the world is listening near. If I had a
dollar for every time one of my patients came with their complete sequence and they want me to
interpret them, I have the same discussion so many times. Okay, you have 20,000 genes. To my last
counting, maybe 78 of them have a deterministic relationship with a disease. You have none of them,
and we know you have none of them because if you had any of them, we would know by now.
There's no chance you got here with Huntington's disease and we missed it, or there's no chance
you have some inborn error of metabolism that somehow got missed. Then we get into this whole
GWAS morass. It's hard to explain to people how multifactorial these issues are. I find myself,
maybe you do as well, somewhat frustrated by these discussions and the overemphasis on this
genetic ... It's a little bit of the drunken the streetlight problem, right? When the guy is
standing below the streetlight and you say, what are you doing here? He says, I'm looking for my
keys and you say, did you drop them here? He says, no, but this is where the light is.
Let me not increase the complexity, but give you another ammunition. We did,
now several years ago because of funding, we did our 44 best first centenarians,
their whole genome sequencing. Think about it. We have a study without control. We just have
44 centenarians and we do the whole genome sequencing. Our question was, do centenarians
have this perfect genome? Maybe one out of 10,000, they just don't have all this crap
from the GWAS, those SNPs for heart and Alzheimer's and stuff. They're just great.
We went to this dataset that's called ClinVar. ClinVar then had the 15,000 pathogenic mutation
that most probably will cause a disease. Now they have about 30,000. Our hypothesis is that
our centenarians don't have any of those. We'll support the perfect genome. 44 centenarians
had more than 230 mutations between them, another five to six mutations that should have caused
them diseases. None of them had this disease in 100 years of life. Some of those mutations,
I'll give you the best example. They're for Parkinson and cancer and everything, but
ApoE4. We have two ApoE4 100 years old people that the textbook would say they're
demented at 70 and dead at 80 and they're not demented and not dead at 100.
Do you think this at all explains the LPA uptick we see? Because one of my favorite topics is
lipidology and of course, LPLiL-A is a very virulent lipoprotein and yet centenarians seem
to have more of it than the general population. Exactly. We actually showed in a paper because
we found a way. Obviously, we can have mutations that are protected because they have slow aging
or longevity genes that protect them. How do you prove that? We noticed that when you look
cross-sectionally, I hope I can make it very simply, when we put any genotype cross-sectionally,
in other words, we have all the ages from 50 to 112 is our oldest. We see patterns.
If we see pattern that the genotype is declining with age, we know it's killing people.
If we see that it's monotonically increased with age, like with the
Yeah, it's concentrating.
Yeah, then means the people who are surviving are surviving with this mutation. That's why we have
it more in 100. Like the example of rotomon receptor going for 3 to 12 in a monotonic way.
We looked at LPLA, exactly.
This is the most confusing of them all because I don't see any compelling evidence that LPLA
is anything other than atherogenic. It begs the question, why would it concentrate in centenarians
as opposed to just rise commensurate with the population?
Exactly. This is the answer. First of all, we show cross-sectionally that LPA drops
until the age of 80 by half. In other words, it kills half of the people.
It's killing you like crazy until it's not.
And then you look at that and you kind of try to understand, just a minute,
now this thing that killed, now all of a sudden centenarians have even more.
Right. It should stay flat after 80.
It should be flat. Why is it increasing? Well, because it's a protected aging gene. In other
words, it was obviously during evolutionary times. Are you saying that the thing that LPLA did for us
500,000 years ago that is no longer beneficial in this lousy environment,
the centenarians have managed to tap into its properties of?
No. So what we did, and it's all published in computational biology journals,
we took every one of the longevity gene that we have and we did gene to gene interaction.
In other words, we tried to see if there is interaction between the bad genotype
and the good genotype, the good longevity genotype. And we did it to a variety of those
U shape. I'm telling you, there's a U shape. It goes down with aging and then it's good in
centenarians. And we really found statistically significant that LPLA is protected by people who
are homozygous to a CTP mutation that is a longevity mutation that we found before.
That's the VV mutation.
The VV mutation. In other words, most of the people with the LPLA that are centenarians were also CTP
mutation.
So can we tell people what that phenotype is? So I've talked on this podcast a lot about CTEP
and its role in reverse cholesterol transport, et cetera. Talk to me about what does the lipid
panel look like for someone who is CTEP VV plus or minus LPLA?
So those with CTP VV, they have higher HDL levels. They have larger lipoprotein particle size,
and they have lower CTP levels. That's their phenotype. And this CTP has been protective
against several age related disease. The most dramatic is cognitive decline.
And by the way, the two APO E4 are also CTP VV carriers.
So really the question is, it sounds to me like if you are CTEP VV, that's a very protective
phenotype. And the difference, if I remember the data going from 70 to 80 was basically flat.
If you're CTEP VV, it really goes up when you turn 80, meaning the concentration of
CTEP VV.
The genotype.
Yes, the genotype goes up significantly once you hit 80.
It goes in 55, it's 8% of the population and at 100, it's 20% of the population.
So it's also important to know that not, first of all, the 8% that have VV, I don't know how many
of them will be centenarians, right? And also not all centenarians are VV, but it's really,
it's still very impressive.
Because the problem with HDL cholesterol is it's just such a dumb ass metric. It's so useless.
It's so far downstream that it doesn't tell us much. But the hypothesis here would have to be
that these people have far more functional HDL particles. Because, I mean, we don't have to
rehash this, but anytime you pharmacologically increase HDL cholesterol by inhibiting CTEP,
nothing good seems to happen.
Right. Because you're actually impairing the reverse cholesterol transport.
Right.
So it has to be with effect, right? That's why it's so-
It has to be a functional-
A functional thing of the HDL probably, or the lipoprotein particle side, or something else.
So I understand all of that. Here's the part I still don't understand here.
Why wouldn't the LPa phenotype or the LPA gene flatline after 80? In other words,
I understand why CTEP VV is protective. I don't understand why LPa should concentrate.
I think because the CTP is common and is very protective and that's why you do it. Look,
it's a cross sectional. By the way, it's a good question. That's what we ask, why it's not flat.
But for a person who's born and is going to be a centenarian, for them, it's really not so,
so they don't die when everybody dies.
I need to do the math. We could do this over dinner. We'll sketch this out on a napkin. You
take a hundred people who are going to be centenarians, a hundred people who are not,
8% of each of them, call it 10% of each of them have LPA. We should do the math on if it's-
Are we being fooled by the age? Because I do have one alternative hypothesis, by the way.
Oh, I'll show you. I'll show you dinner. I'll show you the actual calculation.
The computation. Okay, so this will be good. This will answer my question because the other hypothesis
I've often wondered is, depending on- I'll start with my question and then I'll go to my hypothesis.
How much phenotyping have you done on the LPA? Do you know how much heterogeneity is with their
karingal repeats, for example?
No. I don't have their LPA level. I have just their LPA genotype. So the things that we've done
are though we can do- Actually, we've done a little bit on the CTP levels or we've done, but
those calculation are on gene to gene interaction. Okay. Taking out the people without genotype and
without genotype and seeing who are the people, who are the centenarians that stayed with the
bed LPA genotype. They were only the ones who are CTP also.
I see it. Do you have serum stored on these subjects?
Yeah, but I have proteomics done and maybe we can have some measurement. I'm not sure.
I wonder if there's a clue to a very vexing question, which is why is it that some people
with high LPa do not go on to get premature heart disease? Many do. Most do. A significant number
do not. And it appears completely uncoupled from the level of their LPa, which makes me wonder,
are there virulent and non-virulent phenotypes that at the level of expression by number or
molecular weight aren't captured? And my question then becomes, is the non-virulent one the one
that is concentrating in the centenarians and are they the population in which we should understand
that phenotype so we can better risk stratify the rest of us schleps walking around today,
10% of whom have elevated LPa, but we don't know how aggressively to treat them.
Yeah, I didn't know that there's virulent or non-virulent LPa. My explanation is totally
gene to gene interaction. In other words, you do another phenotype. I guess the answer is
different. What's the LPa? What's their CTP level? What's their HDL? What's their HDL particle size?
And maybe you can see that generalize that if you inhibit CTP, the LPa is less interactive.
I mean, I think the problem we, I agree with what you're saying. The challenge is we do not have an
HDL functional assay. So right now we can measure HDL cholesterol, we can measure HDL particle number,
and we can measure HDL size, but none of those come close to telling us how functional the particle is.
Well, I have a collaboration with Dan Rader.
Yep.
Who's doing HDL efflux and stuff like that.
Yeah. I mean, Dan is a God in this field.
Yeah. So maybe, but that's not my, this is a past life for me. I moved on. So I don't really know
to answer you. I didn't realize.
Let's go back to the IGFGH thing because this one still creates tremendous,
let's bring it back to clinical stuff. So I'm often asked by patients, hey,
should I be on growth hormone? And my answer is I don't think so. But if I'm going to be brutally
honest, I really don't know. I really have no insight into whether growth hormone is exogenous,
administered growth hormone is harmful, helpful, neutral, or what, because the clinical data
certainly don't give us the answer. Right. So the epidemiology, if you're in sort of, you know,
Vaulter's camp is, that would be the worst thing you could ever do. Growth hormone is bad because IGF
is bad. But again, the epidemiology tell a different story, tell a much more nuanced story that has to
do with how high is too high at what age and for what gender and with respect to what disease.
So of course, how can you manipulate IGF? Well, you can manipulate it. The two easiest ways to
manipulate IGF, the three easiest ways to manipulate IGF or to manipulate growth hormone
exogenously, manipulate IGF, diaterally, predominantly through amino acids and
manipulate insulin to indirectly impair or enhance IGF binding proteins.
Well, let me tell you, we just published a paper in Nature a month ago, a study that we're going
also for a while. And what we did is we got from Amgen. Amgen, as much as other pharmaceuticals,
tried to develop antibodies against IGF receptor because IGF receptor is expressed in many cancers.
Yeah, this was the disaster drug that they tested against metastatic pancreatic cancer.
It failed. But if I recall, there was a very special little gift, which is no CNS penetration.
Am I thinking of the right one? Yeah, right. So it failed. But we're interested for aging.
Yes. And not only we're interested for aging, our hypothesis was that IGF, you know, that you need to
decrease IGF action in the periphery, but increase it in the brain because of the data.
So we asked them to morenize their antibodies. Morenize means to make it available for a mouse.
Right. And we got it and we did a longevity study that we started at 22 months.
By the way, remind me in the human study, how much did it lower IGF in the periphery?
It increased.
I'm sorry. I know. I'm sorry. How much did it lower IGF activity in the periphery? Was it a
reduction by what fold? Like, was it a two fold reduction?
It's very hard to measure. You don't measure it like that. You measure it in, you know, in vitro.
It's very hard to measure how much.
Got it. Okay.
And they rebounded a little bit with IGF, which is not the case with aging, because with aging,
you don't have the growth hormone secretion. So we gave it to 22 months old animals that are 70,
75 years of age equivalent. We increased their health spend dramatically and we increased their
life spend by 10 percent at an older age. Okay. So this is a drug that's already was.
And you were able to demonstrate. I'm sorry, I missed this paper. It came out a month ago.
So I'll be inhaling it this time tomorrow. You basically showed that you didn't change IGF
levels in the brain or you actually increased IGF levels in the brain.
We really don't know. There is a little increase in IGF-1 level in the periphery. And we're assuming
that we didn't make it a big, I'm telling you what we thought we didn't make it such a big deal. But
obviously the antibodies do not cross the blood brain barrier. But the IGF wasn't lower if
anything was high. Right. So if anything, IGF went up in the periphery because it was being blocked.
And therefore a little bit more into it. So you could have had more CNS activity,
less peripheral activity of IGF. Now, again, those were aging. By the way, it was in females. In
males, we started to do the studies in males. And since we didn't see any major effects and we had
relatively little, you know, those are months of studies in many mice. So we eventually did the
longevity only in females. We don't have data on males, but the extent of health span, and you'll
see the paper. It's really, it's a great paper with lots of studies. And it's impressive how much
they did better the females with that. So there you have an example. We have all the
paths where you ask, what do we do? Here is, it's been in humans. Okay. The IGF receptor
antibodies there. The only problem for us is aging could be an indication what what's before aging.
Like we need another indication in order to start selling it before. But what's your hypothesis in
those mice, in the female mice that they, you said they live 10% longer and watch healthier.
And much healthier. So they had compressed morbidity as well. They had a cardio, you know,
they had the cardiovascular protection. They have cognitive advantage, functional
advantage. There's a whole thing. The interesting thing between male and female, the difference
is the mice, the female mice that were treated with IGF receptor antibody had a lot of
of inflammatory markers, right? When we started, they were 22 months and those inflammatory
markers were really decreased with aging in males. We had a little bit more inflammatory markers,
but they increased with the IGF treatment. So maybe the fact. And both the males and the females
had an increase in peripheral IGF, presumably the antibody was working in both of them. Right.
But somehow the inflammatory response in males was different. So it's all driven. So I'm answering
you two things. First of all, what do you do? Here's a good example of a drug that was in
females. And we have preclinical proof of concept that it's good. But the second is in males,
all those have not been shown. And in fact, you know, the functional that I told you,
functional in women, it looks like the function was better for men with a higher IGF and not with
lower, not statistically significant, but you could see that it might happen. So I'm telling you from
human studies, from genetic studies, I'm telling you growth hormone treatment is not beneficial.
It should be dangerous for elderly people, for elderly women with men. I'm ready to say that I'm
not sure, you know, I'm not sure. It's not that I've shown that low IGF or growth hormone is better
in males, not in my rodent studies and not in my human studies. But it's hard to say that giving
growth hormone is bad when, you know, by the way, the growth hormone receptor story is a lot of them
are males. That this is so interesting. I mean, this is such a layer of sophistication to this
question, which I've largely sort of decided that I can't come up with a compelling reason for
exogenous growth hormone. But I also can't see much evidence clinically that it's killing people.
But of course, I think disproportionately the data are in men. What do you think explains this sex
difference between men and women? I think I'm really if you look at this inflammatory panel,
lots of cytokines and lots of animals, I'm not sure we don't have the intellectual link
to say what happens. But this is something we want to actually go on and examine.
Because if for some paradoxical way that is sex dependent, low IGF, increased inflammation,
we want to do we want to know why and we want to know how we can affect it.
It would be great if you could repeat the study with younger mice, both male and female again,
because I mean, the most obvious example is the biggest difference between the men and the women
of the sex hormones. And the older they get, that difference is still there. I mean, women will,
you know, the female mice would go from having some testosterone to zero testosterone.
But gosh, the men would probably still have more estrogen than the males have more estrogen than
the females post menopause. Right. Which makes me wonder if the estrogen that projects on the
testosterone are somehow predict a protective of the inflammatory effects. So there's a, you know,
we're working on a grant because the sex issue is so interesting. We started working on there.
Lots of models where you can change X and Y chromosomes and stuff like that. And, you know,
we're looking at the way to look at the, because it's, I don't think it's usually as simple
as the sex hormones. You know, I think we're missing a whole biology, a whole biology and
whatever is the sex hormones, I don't understand the inflammation in that either. But by the way,
your idea of doing it in young is good. Amgen sold this IGF receptor and we cannot get more
samples, but we're interested to maybe do our own. Wait, wait. Amgen sold the rights to the human
antibody. Right. Their whole section, actually. Their whole section. To who? Which company owns
it now? To like a private company that we're unable to get people to. Though I have to say,
it's not our major priority now, but, and we have some consultants that are trying
to get it together with those people. So, you know, it's still an issue, but I'll tell you
if I had to develop a treatment, I would rather use the micro RNA 142 because the IGF receptor
antibody didn't work in cancer, but maybe the micro RNA penetrates better in another way. And
maybe that's the way to decrease IGF receptor in, you know, in cancers. So anyhow, but I really
answered you is that, yeah, there are things that we could do to affect the pathway. I mean, what do
you think about sort of all the, to me, the most obvious way to manipulate IGF is through fasting.
So about once a quarter, I fast for a week with just water only. And it has a profound impact on
my IGF level. So for my age, I think I should know these numbers off by heart, but plus or minus
two standard deviations of IGF at my age is about 90 to 250. And if I take my, if I measure my IGF
level before a fast right before a fast, it might be 180 to 200. And right after the fast, it's
80 or 90. And six weeks later, it's maybe one 4150. So it sort of falls precipitously during the fast
and then slowly rises and then falls precipit and slowly rises. And there's part of me that just
wonders if a cyclic approach to IGF is a healthier approach than say, constitutively being calorically
restricted and just, you know, cause you could starve yourself of methionine and eat no protein
and live at a lower IGF level of maybe 110 forever. But I wonder if the real game is sort
of figuring out this sort of cycle and periods of just, just as we think of autophagy, if you're
always in the state of autophagy, that's a bad thing. If you never have autophagy, that's a bad
thing. So, you know, about the calorie or the caloric restriction that the NIA funded in three
centers. Yeah. Eric Ravison at Pennington was one of the main PIs. One of the things is that IGF
level wasn't decreased in those people. Right. And we think IGF decrease is really important part of
longevity, but we, we've, we learned something else and maybe I'm digressing because I'm sure you
talked about it more that what we're doing in rats wasn't really caloric restriction. We're doing
intermittent fasting because in our rodents, we would bring the food in the morning. They were
hungry. Right. They would eat all the food, you know, the 60% whatever we gave to at Libidum,
and they were fasting for 23 hours and they had low IGF one level. But in Eric Ravison's studies,
they didn't have low IGF because it wasn't caloric restriction like that. They gave them just less
food throughout the day. Okay. And I think that was a big mistake that we realized we were doing.
And it doesn't answer this. They're circulating. I think what we're trying to do at Einstein is
we're doing a study. We know that autophagy is improved quite fast in fasting rodents.
We don't know the timeline for humans. Okay. So we're trying to figure it out. And by the way,
we can do with Anna Maria Cuervo, we can take T. lymphocytes and look at the autophagy on a
time course in humans. And they actually reflect also autophagy in the brain. There's a lot of
advantage in doing that. What are you looking at specifically in the assay? Well, there are several
things because there are several autophages, right? So macro autophagy or or chaperone mediated
autophagy. So there are several things. Can you measure my topology also? Yeah, we can do, we do
that. Yeah. How sensitive is it to meal timing? You know, like, for example, if a rodent is fasting
for 24 hours, especially a mouse, I mean, that's, gosh, that's probably the equivalent of a human
fasting for a week. Presumably autophagy is highly, highly, highly upregulated. If you give the mouse
a little bit of chow and then measure that assay, does it obfuscate? Does it erase the fact that
does it create the illusion, I guess I should say, that it's erased that they've had this
high period of autophagy? Did you transiently truncate it? You know, Ana Marec Cuervo did,
and I don't know the answer. I don't know the time course. But the important thing is to find
the time course in humans so that we can really say, for example, what I'm doing basically is I'm
trying not to eat after dinner until like lunchtime the next day. But do you really, I mean,
so first of all, how hard is it to get an IRB at Einstein to study this in healthy
concierge? No, we have IRB. We just wrote a grant. We need money for that.
Yeah, I guess, you know, I have a whole framework around nutrition, which I'm happy to kind of walk
through as we inhale our dinner tonight. Have you decided, by the way, if you are an Indian,
Turkish, Persian, Greek, all of the above? Yeah, that sounds good. You know, because it's
raining out. So I guess one of the things we could do to the closest. We'll figure it out.
So my concern with time restricted feeding, which I practice quite liberally,
is I'm worried it is not a significant enough deprivation of nutrients in humans. In other
words, I think Sachin's data is so impressive in mice, you know, but I think that for a mouse to
go 16 hours without eating is an enormous task. It might be the equivalent of us not eating for
three days. And now that said, I'm struggling to see a downside of time restricted feeding. And I
know that, you know, Walter and others have said time restricted feeding is somehow bad.
I don't accept those arguments. I don't, I'm not convinced by those data. But this is a very
interesting question you're asking. I would argue it's the most interesting question of all,
because if we understand the time course of that, all of a sudden we can program nutrient exposure.
And have you looked at that assay in the presence of rapamycin or metformin?
I didn't, but metformin, Ana Maria Quervo is using metformin as the control for autophagy.
Okay. It activates autophagy really well. Okay. So let's say I'm talking about in vitro assays.
Okay. But we haven't measured it in, in patients. The, the one thing I should say,
I just don't want to forget anything. Can I, can I absolutely, and it's, it's back to the
metformin just reminded me it's back to metformin studies. So our reviewers were saying, you know,
okay, all the data on the biology that you showed was from rodents. And we don't know
that the biology is relevant to humans. Okay. Although of course the preliminary data in humans
are much better than in rodents, right? The association with diseases. So we had a clinical
study, a small clinical study, which we took 15 people that are 75 years old. And we gave some
of them metformin for six weeks and other placebos, and then we crossed over and it was blinded. And
we took it at the end of each period, we took biopsy from their muscle and biopsy from their
adipose tissue. Okay. So not liver. And we looked at the transcript and the metabolomics, but mainly
the transcripts in the tissues to see effects on metformin. And there are three interesting things.
First of all, when they brought me their clinical results, you know, insulin, HOMA, glucose and all,
there were significant effects in many of them, statistically significant effects, but I was
expecting more. I started to try and break it down. And then we found out that the people who
were last on metformin, although it was half of the people had much more significant results
than the whole 15 people. Wait, explain that again. The people in the crossover who started,
who went placebo to metformin had better effects on metabolic parameters relative to themselves
or to their peers. Relatively to themselves. Because this was a person to person. This was a
paired T test. And the reason is that probably the two weeks wash over is not enough when you
fix the assaging, it lasts for a while. Okay. So if you got metformin and then placebo, you didn't
really, you went halfway back. Also by the way, because metformin is associated with weight loss
and they lost a little weight that on itself really made them on the second. Yeah. Yeah.
And what, it's funny you bring that up. I'm glad you were mentioned that. What do you think
explains the weight loss phenotype of metformin? So when I started taking metformin, which was 2010,
I didn't mess around. I just went straight to 2.5 grams a day. I didn't even mix it up. I don't
think I took it BID. I mean, I took two, 2,500 milligrams first thing every morning. And after
a month, I lost quite a bit of weight, but I was also nauseous 24 seven. I mean, the thought of
eating was repulsive to me. I still ate, you know, I was exercising a lot and doing all my usual
shenanigans, but I clearly ate less just because of that low grade feeling of nausea. Today, when I
prescribe metformin to patients, I have them start at 500 QHS, then 500 BID, then 50, you know,
500 in the morning, 1500 before bed, then one gram BID is sort of standard dose. And I
see far less of that nausea and I see far less weight loss. What other mechanisms do you think
it could explain the weight loss? So could it be lactic acid going up, you know, just like ketones,
you get a substrate, an additional substrate? Yeah, I don't know. But look, I started metformin
several years ago because I was pre-diabetic. My doctor did it. So it's before, I'm glad that he
did, but it was before I thought much about it. And I was just surprised after three months to
realize that I lost, you know, seven or eight pounds. I was surprised because I couldn't,
I was nauseated. I wasn't anything. I must have eaten less. I was less hungry. I reacted better.
I reacted better to my body, right? To my leptin. Maybe I reacted better and I probably didn't eat
as much, not totally not noticing it. It was a surprise. Yeah. It's funny. I tell patients not
to expect that because I don't, I don't like the idea of patients thinking of this as like a weight
loss drug. To me, that sort of is not the right way to think about it, but I've never had a great
explanation. And by the same token, I have had, I should be clear. I've had also some patients who
they've come back and they've lost 10 pounds. And these are patients who were not overweight. This
is not, you know, this is someone that by everybody's standard would be completely normal weight,
BMI is 24, body composition is reasonable and comes back in, you know, in three months and
they've lost 10 pounds. But I guess for, in my, at least in my practice, that seems to be the
exception and not the rule, but very, very interesting to hear. You know, I guess, of course,
you wish that was more than a two by two, two week. You wish that was a 12 week by 12 week.
We're doing the same thing with Acrobos now. And we're doing longer study with longer washing
period because we want to get away from that. But back to metformin, I said that's one thing
is this metformin last issue. The second thing that we showed that most of the transcripts changes
were relative to this, to the tissue. You know, in fat, it was more free fatty acid metabolism and
the muscle was more pyruvate metabolism. So it was appropriate. In other words, there wasn't
the metformin, you know, the metformin part, but in both tissues, there were genes that are not
metabolic genes, you know, like BRCA1 or myofibril genes and other things that are related to aging,
but they are not metabolic. They change by metformin. In other words, the concept that
metformin is not only metabolic, it's aging. Okay.
Like BRCA1 changed?
Yeah. You know, some other gene, genes that are associated with DNA repair changed significantly.
The second-
Did you see in the muscle, by the way, if you still have biopsies, I'd be very curious to know
if the lactate transporter out of the muscle, I'm blanking on it, it's MCT2. In other words,
as people make more and more lactate in the muscle, do they get more and more efficient at
shuttling it back to the liver? And if so, you would expect MCT2 transport-
The gene expression changes by that.
Yeah.
You know, we have the raw data. It didn't come up, I'll tell you, it didn't come up as a winner,
but that doesn't mean it's not changed.
And you looked at genome or you looked at messenger as well? You looked at mRNA?
Only message. It's transcript.
It's all mRNA.
Right.
It's all mRNA. Okay. So you should have seen it if it happened.
Well, if it was highly, I mean, there are hundreds of changes, okay? So-
Yeah, maybe this was underpowered to see that difference.
Significant changes. So I can still answer you, I can still answer you specifically.
And it's RNA6, so it's really good. It will be good. You know, if I take that and see that it can
be without taking into account that there are 400 other changes, it can be significant.
The other thing though, what you do with transcript, you look at upper regulators
of the system and there's a way to do that. That's what everybody does now.
So if you look at the upper regulators, you get back to the same things that are affecting aging,
AMP, kinase, mTOR, all those pathways were affected by metformin, except that
what you measured below is the tissue specific effects, but it was all related back straight to aging.
You know, it breaks my heart.
And so we really connected not only the clinical data, but the biological data in humans
to the tame study.
Yeah, it's wonderful. You know, a few years ago when my father was diagnosed with cancer,
I immediately put him on metformin. And, you know, in his infinite wisdom, his primary care doctor
took him off it, because, you know, why would you put him on metformin? And in the end, my father
decided his primary care doctor knows much more than I do and so remains off metformin. But
certainly this discussion, because I, you know, I probably know more about metformin than the
average person, but this discussion has been completely illuminating. There's one other thing
I want to ask you about, which is all of the discussion around NAD. I mean, you know quite
a bit about this. What is your take right now based on the state of the science that we have,
which admittedly, I think we're just scratching the surface of as far as first and foremost,
just at the mechanistic level. What is your belief that orally administered nicotinamide
riboside can actually make it into a cell? I don't know if you've seen it, but Joshua Benowitz's
paper over the summer would suggest, no, most of this is going to deliver. So wouldn't this sort
of call into question the companies, there's two of them right now, Chromadex and Elysium, that sell
basically nicotinamide riboside plus or minus teristilbene. What do you think explains the
reported efficacy of those agents in light of Rabinowitz's NAD Tracer study? First of all,
the Rabinowitz study was also criticized, okay? Time course and other things, which,
okay, I'm just saying that. But I think really the biggest issue here, I want just to use this
opportunity to say that a lot of what we're doing is not based on clinical studies, okay?
And it really just underlines the fact that unless you do a clinical study, you can remain guessing.
Now I'll tell you, I'm taking a good preparation of NMN, okay? Tell the listener the difference
between NR and NMN because they're both precursors to NAD, but there's a subtle difference.
Yeah, and I don't know to explain that really well. I don't care that much about that.
Okay, but in theory, one is slightly more stable than the other.
Right. It's a stability issue, availability issue, but they'll fight and we don't know which
is the better and we don't know which gets to the tissue, right? Yeah. But what I wanted to say
is the following. So the answer is it could all be water, okay? It could all be this.
You say that as you hold up the bottle of Topo Chico.
Right, sorry. You didn't see that in the microphone? Okay. But what I'm doing now is
I'm opening my Fitbit, okay? And one of the things that the Fitbit has is sleep, okay?
Do you use Fitbit?
No, I use something called Aura, which works much better.
Okay.
Yeah, this really measures sleep well.
Do you get also the deep sleep and the REM and all that? Okay. Since I started taking NMN,
and it might be a coincidence, so I have to stop it and start again, but my sleep has been much
better. That means I have in the beginning of the night, I have much more deep sleep and at the end
of the night, I have much more REM. And I thought if there's anything I can say about it, is that
just because of this association, okay? But I don't believe it, right? Because it's not a,
it's a smile, it's me and-
It's empirical and anecdotal.
Many things could have looked, I was in vacation. I don't know. Many things could have happened.
Do you take the NMN by itself or do you also pair it with Terrestil Bean or-
No, just-
Another Surtuin activator.
No, just NMN. But it's a good suggestion maybe. Okay, but then I run into
Imai. Do you know who's Shin Imai? He is from St. Louis and he has his own
patents and studies in Japan on NMN. And he tells me unprovoked. He says, I have 200 subjects and
one of the interesting thing is their sleep patterns improve. They get more deep sleep in
the beginning of the night and more REM at the end of the night. In other words, he tells me
what I've noticed and it makes me just think and maybe believe and maybe hope that something is
getting into the cells and that there's a real effect, at least on sleep. He didn't tell me any
other things. But really my answer is we don't really know enough. It's very hard to measure
effect because this NAD goes and goes away and what system can you do? It's very hard to measure
that. And without clinical studies that are really well controlled, I think it's going to be hard
to just support that. And that's me as a conservative scientist and one who says
that even metformin that everybody says, you have enough data. No, we have to do the clinical
study to prove that. And that's where I really stand. And it seems to me that intravenous
administration of NAD is also not particularly helpful, though it seems quite popular in the
sense that I haven't seen compelling evidence that giving NAD intravenously makes its way into
the cell either. So I think the development, the interesting development will be to develop
a drug and the drug will be a precursor that will get into the blood outside of the liver.
Outside of the liver. Yeah, exactly. So if you could give NR or NMN sublingually or intravenously,
that strikes me as very interesting. Saying that there's a lot of data in rodents where also you
look, you give it in different ways. You give it some in water, but some are gavage and maybe
that's different because one of the problems, maybe if you go deep enough, you can bypass
the portal circulation. Right. You can bypass something. But the in vivo studies are good
studies. You just don't know what it means to humans. Well, Nir, I'll do a time check here.
We've been going at this for a little while. There's a lot more I want to pick your brain on,
but we could also just sit down and do this again sometime. I want to make sure you've said at least
as much as you want to say about metformin because I think that to me is, you know, you're at this
point, arguably one of the world's experts on a drug that just to put this in perspective,
I think Lou Cantley, who is obviously a close mutual friend of ours and James Watson, who I
don't know personally, have both said quite publicly that metformin may have already saved
more patients lives from cancer than all other cancer drugs combined or something to that effect.
This is a drug that I think with each passing day, more and more people are beginning to learn
about beginning to ask questions about. And my hope is that if nothing else, this podcast is a
place that people can listen to this episode if they can't go and read 16 of your papers and they
don't necessarily want to get, you know, that far down the rabbit hole. But to hear it from you and
not from me or some other schmuck who doesn't know much, I want to make sure that if there's
anything else you want to say about metformin that you say so. And so is there anything else
that you want to add? Well, let me do one practical thing and one a little bit more philosophical.
Okay. The practical thing that really surprised me, I was giving a talk somewhere for lay people.
So it was organized by a university and they invited people and to their surprise, there
are 300 people in the audience. And by the way, my talk wasn't about metformin. My talk,
the titles of my talk is usually How to Die Young in a Very Old Age. That's what my title is. Usually
if I can get away with it, that's a good title. So people are coming and as they're entering,
some of them come to me and say, so how much metformin should I take? Okay. So I started talking
and all of a sudden I said, let me ask you something. Who here in the audience is non-diabetic
and is on metformin? And please, you don't have to just if you choose to. So how many?
Half of the people. Where was this talk? What university? I don't want to. Okay. What city?
Can you say what city? Was it in the United States? No. Okay. Fair enough. So you know,
in other words, the prophecy is out, which makes me a little bit worried about the study.
When we first, Wall Street Journal is the first that picked on Tame, wrote an article the next
week, we had 3000 phone calls and emails of people volunteering to the study, which is what we need
to do the study. And I thought it was just cut your work. You trim that budget from 70 million
down to 65. You cut all the recruiting costs out. Exactly. Except that then you realize. Yeah,
it's a bias sample. Then you realize just a minute. Those people, first of all, we didn't advertise.
They had to find my phone number and email. And second, they'll do, they're doing other things.
You know, it's like with the estrogen bias, they're probably exercising and stuff like that.
And then when I started getting emails, like I'm volunteering to the study, as long as I'm not on
the placebo, I thought, you know, if people care so much, if they'll figure out they're not on
mid-forming, they'll just get mid-forming. So from recruiting the 3000, we, we outlawed those. Those
are not in my study, right? So I want to say that still we haven't done the study. Okay. We haven't
done this study. So you're between 65 and 80. Okay. Just know we haven't done the study. We don't
know if it's safe as it is in young people. And so we don't have really a clinical study with evidence
that this is good. And I'm, I'm just worried now that part of the reason to do this study is because
if it's not good, people should know also, right? And not take another drug. Okay. Not that I believe
but it is possible. The second thing that is more philosophical. So I said before that I was
invited to the Vatican. I actually was invited twice the second time. And I'm very close to
Cardinal Ravasi, who's a number four in the pontiffs. He's in charge of science and
on arts that is including science. And it's interesting because the Vatican basically says,
we don't want to be in a Galileo Galilei situation again. We don't want to be in a situation where
the science is so right and we're so wrong that we don't know what to do with it. Okay. And so they
called me and they said, you know, we have a meeting in the Vatican. We'd like you to talk about
aging. Could you come and say, I said, sure, sure. I'll come. And then I'm going on and saying, am I
the keynote speaker? They said, the keynote speakers are the Pope and Joe Biden, who was vice
president. I said, okay, sorry, sorry, I'm still coming. So that's how it goes. Joe Biden goes up
and explains his cancer initiative and how difficult it is because when you have cancer,
you have in the cancer, maybe five other genomes and they're also different than every other cancer
like that in the world. It's really a mess. Then comes the Pope and says, you know, I still hope
that there'll be one little peel cheap for everyone in the world that will cure whatever cancer they
wear. Appropriate. I hope so too. But then I go up and I say, well, there is actually a cheap
peel like that. And I don't know if it cures any cancer in the world, but it can prevent a lot of
the cancers in the world. And actually it has a side effect that it also can prevent a lot of
other diseases in the world. So it was like, you know, going back to aging and the risk of aging
for age related diseases and how impactful and cheap it could be compared to treating cancer
or something like that. So I think the prevention of aging is really a good place to be. And I
think because we went from hope to promise and we have to realize the promise, the thing in life is
going to be very different in the last next decade with our advance. Last question, and not to end
on a downer, but let's try to figure out where a blind spot could be. What could, where could we
be wrong? Obviously you and I share more in common in terms of philosophy and points of view than I
even realized before we spoke, but where could we be wrong? So, you know, I'll tell you what's my
optimism. You know, we have the European have nine pillars of aging and we have seven pillars of
aging and they're all inter connected. And when I say interconnected, I just spent the time with
Anna Maria Quervo this morning when she fixed autophagy, she fixes also metabolism. Okay. There,
when, when you start doing things in any one of those pillars, you start improving the others.
Now where we could, could be wrong is we don't know what is the impact of each of those
pathway in humans. Okay. Most of our data is kind of animal data, but I think our fallback is that
we all age. The advantage of in aging is that aging is universal. Every, every animal
has the skin, the hair, the skeletal, the frailty. It's very universal. And those treatments are
mid-form in Rapamycin. You give it to any animal, it almost delays the aging there. So I don't think
we're going to be wrong. I think that maybe some pathways will not be so effective. Some of them
will be harder to treat maybe, but I think we have to effect three, four, and we're right on our
way to do better. And that's just the beginning. And in the tame study, will it be one to one,
male to female? Yes. So we'll also avoid that other, and have you powered it such that men and
women are different animals? Well, no, because all our data on mid-forminin, we looked carefully to
the DPP and other, they didn't see any gender effects on any of the outcomes. So we're assuming
that- So you're powered as though the genders don't have a significant- That there are different,
right? Like we would do maybe Rapamycin, you know? Yeah. Well, Nir, this has been fantastic.
I was sick the last two days. My voice is gone. I feel like crap. I was like,
ah, maybe we should postpone it. But then when I woke up this morning, I was like, there is no way
we are postponing this discussion because I cannot wait to have this discussion. So
thank you so much for coming over. It was great. It was great because you asked really great
questions. And also I'm now quite hungry and I'll be happy to have dinner with you now.
We are going to put together a seminar on how not to calorically restrict-
Tonight, only tonight. All right. Thank you, Nir.
You can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
and the nerd safari at peteratiamd.com. What's a nerd safari, you ask? Just click on the link at
the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my
subjectively non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to,
the most interesting papers I've read, and all things related to longevity,
science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions
and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes
only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient
relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the
user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare
professionals for any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of
interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise,
please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.