Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia. My guest this week is one of my best friends
from medical school, a guy by the name of Eric Shayhab. Eric is an orthopedic surgeon
specializing in sports, but overall knee and shoulder. He's an assistant clinical professor
at the University of Chicago. We met obviously at Stanford and he went on to do his residency
in orthopedic surgery at the hospital for special surgery or HSS as it's known in New York City.
It's generally regarded as the best orthopedic facility in the country, if not the world. He
did his fellowship with the New York Giants before settling in Chicago. He was also mentored at HSS
by a guy named Russ Warren, who anybody listening to this who knows a lot about or a little bit
about orthopedic surgery will understand the significance of that. Russ is generally considered
the godfather of sports medicine. This interview was also really informative for me because I,
as you know, think about longevity through the standpoint of living longer but living better
and a big part of living better is not getting hurt. What I love about talking to orthopedic
surgeons, especially people like Eric, who are just so cognizant of what the demise looks like
at the end of life, is I think by understanding where people fail later in life, you can understand
how to mitigate that earlier in life. So we get into a lot of detail around the common joint
injuries. So what's going on with knee pain, especially from incorrect form in a loaded
fashion. We talk a lot about shoulder injuries, especially with weights being used overhead,
elbow, wrist injuries, ankles, what's going on with the Achilles tendon. Obviously we talk about
lower back stuff, which for many people is also, you know, I think it's almost impossible to get
through life without at least one lower back flare up. We revisit sort of my injury, which I've
talked about actually in the past. We talk about all the complications that can come from it.
And we talk a little bit about how you can decide when PT makes more sense than surgery, which
unfortunately for lower back injuries is almost always the case. We get into some of the real
controversy stuff like meniscus surgery, which some of you may be aware of. We talk about the
origins of pain. So a lot of times people present with joint pain, but it's not really clear,
is the pain matching the thing you see on the MRI? And again, I have an example of where that
was not the case. We get into PRP, stem cells, sham surgeries, and all sorts of things like that.
The other thing that probably comes across though, not as much as I would have liked is Eric is
probably one of the funniest human beings I know. He actually sang at my wedding and I think we even
discussed that story early in this episode, although I didn't get him to sing. So that's
probably one drawback. Anyway, the show notes will be linked to a ton of awesome stuff that follows
up and goes deeper on some of these things. And obviously if you want to learn more about Eric,
that's great. But the reality of it is this is mostly just a way to kind of help people think
about orthopedic surgery and more than anything else, these types of injuries and what we can do
to prevent them. So I hope you enjoyed today's episode and here we go. Hey man, what's going on?
Not much. Good to see you. It's been a long time. I feel like it's been two years since I've seen
you in person and we did get to spend an hour finding a place to record this. So that, that
gave us a good chance to catch up. Where are we sitting right now? We are sitting in my Womat office
for Illinois bone and joint and Womat. We're actually in a patient exam room, I think. We're
in a patient exam room. It's like the only room we could find that didn't have an AC unit blaring or
something like that. Well, Eric, there's so much stuff I want to talk about, you know, mostly about
orthopedic stuff because in the spirit of sort of trying to live longer, you've probably heard me
talk about it. There's no point living longer if you're not living better. And a big part of living
better is your exoskeleton. And for a lot of people that you probably see, and certainly I see
it to a lesser extent, you know, once that quality of life deteriorates, meaning once they don't have
the strength, mobility or freedom from pain to kind of carry out the activities of daily living,
you know, for many people, they don't actually care that much if they're going to delay their
heart attack by four years or something like that. It stops mattering. So I mean, let's go back to
the beginning. There's so many goofy things I want to talk about. Did you grew up in New Jersey? I
don't think I knew this. Yeah, I grew up in New Jersey. I was born in Omaha and moved to New
Jersey when I was three. And is Bruce Springsteen still probably one of your favorite singers?
He's my favorite. Yep. There is this, I think I put it up on social media a little while ago,
but there's this awesome video. It was from 2009 in Madison Square Garden where Bruce Springsteen
was playing with Tom Morello. And my son, when he watches the video thinks I'm Tom Morello,
he doesn't get that I'm not. And it's like, no, no, no, actually, daddy looks like him or he
looks like daddy, but that's not mean. He's like, what do you mean? That is you. And he can, he's
like, why do you know how to play the guitar? But you never play at home. There's, there's one song,
which we'll have to link to the ghost of Tom Joe that they play together. It's like an eight minute
thing with Morello doing like a three minute guitar solo at the end that is out of control. But
there's something about Bruce Springsteen's voice that like he might kind of be the coolest guy ever.
No, he's definitely the coolest guy ever.
How many times have you seen him live?
Five, six times. First concert I went to was Bruce in 84 at Brendan Byrne in New Jersey. And it was
as he was kicking off the born the USA tour. It was summertime. There were about five or six of us.
We were in eighth or ninth grade and it was great. Fantastic. And then I saw him, I lived in Milan
for a year. I was teaching high school and he was playing in Verona on Easter Sunday. And he was
supposed to play in an amphitheater in Verona that Guns N' Roses had played in like a month earlier
and basically nearly tore the place down. And one of these amphitheaters that had been there for
2000 years and sure enough won concert and no more concerts. So he played in the soccer stadium in
Verona on Easter Sunday for about five hours. And I remember I was on a bike tour. I was taking my
bike through Tuscany. I was by myself on a mountain bike and it was Easter Sunday morning. I was in
Florence and there was the Easter parade and I had this one ticket to Bruce and I'm like,
how the fuck am I going to get to Verona? So I ditched my bike someplace. I get on a train
of Verona. Turns out there were a lot of Bruce fans on the way and there were translations of
Bruce's lyrics into Italian, which I always wonder how like working on the highway and drinking warm
beer in the soft summer rain translate into Italian. But anyway, and I get there and this show goes on
as usual for about five hours. And I get on a train at three in the morning from Verona,
head back to Florence, pick up my bike around nine o'clock in the morning and then keep riding.
Because it was so pumped up and jacked up from having seen this fantastic Bruce concert and
just kept riding for the rest of the day. So that was one of my favorite Bruce concerts was that
Italy. I saw him in Oakland with my wife with Lynn when we were dating in medical school.
And that was sort of tempered by the fact that she wasn't much of a Bruce fan.
So my good buddy Mark Pomerance was at that concert too. Yeah.
Oh, is that right? Yeah, we're up in Oakland up in the nosebleeds. And then I saw Bruce
most recently with Lynn, who now is a fan in Milwaukee on his river tour. And he gives such
a great show. The river tour is fantastic. And so he plays the album and then he goes on for another
two or three hours with just great songs. And he's so good live. I saw him at Wrigley right
after Clarence Clemens had died. And they had that tribute where they at 10th Avenue Freeze out,
they just stopped the music on when the big man joined the band and they have a
large shadow silhouette of Clarence from the Born to Run album. And it's really moving. I mean,
he must have done that about 50 times from his death to that concert, but it's still very genuine
and very moving. And the whole place goes quiet. And then it erupts in sort of cheer and laughter
and tears as it was really moving. And that was what I think, that must have been four years ago
when he played at Wrigley. And yet I'm sort of a JV Bruce fan compared to my roommates in college.
You go, my one roommate, Owen, had probably been about a hundred concerts. And he tells a great
story of... This is the Owen that I know? It's the Owen you knew. He tells a great story of punching
someone out on the Bruckner Expressway on his way to the Bruce concert. So I'll let him tell that
story. It's a successful New York. Yeah, no, it sounds like the guy had it coming. So I don't
really have any problem with that. Owen was a, like wasn't he a Navy SEAL or? He's a Marine and he's now
an undersecretary of defense for General Mattis. He does special ops and very busy game.
Do you notice over time as you go to these concerts, like, does the fans seem older to you?
And so for me, Pearl Jam is the band that I've seen more than any other band. And I just saw them
recently in Fenway. And I got to tell you, it was the first time in a long time I've been in a
concert where I had as much joy out of watching the other people there, because they were older
than me, some of them. But you could tell. So when 10 came out, I was maybe 17 or 18. But you can
tell there were people who were 30 when 10 came out and probably still found it amazing. And so
now they're, you know, in their late fifties and you can see the emotion in them when Eddie Vedder
gets up there and plays something that from 91 or something like that. So it must be the same with
Springsteen, but even greater because it's a greater time period. Yeah, no, that's another
funny thing when you're at Wrigley and you see the fans to your left and your right. And they're
pretty old. And then you'll see some of them holding their 10 year olds. And that's the fun
part of it is that there's a sort of intergenerational thing. You have these younger kids
growing up loving Bruce because their parents love Bruce. And so but yeah, no doubt the crowd is
older. It's funny you mentioned Pearl Jam. They opened for U2 in Verona in 92. I was still in
Milan and I saw Pearl Jam open for U2 on the Zuropa tour. And. So Pearl Jam U2 and Bruce
Springsteen in one trip to Italy? No, no. Well, I lived in Italy. Oh, we were there for a year.
I lived for a year, but same venue, same and fabulous venue. And the lead guitarist for
Pearl Jam was licking his picks out like he does. Yeah. Mike McCready. I've almost caught a Mike
McCready pick once in DC. I was in the third row. I was like, that was my one shot at catching the
pick. And I didn't. He also had a disposable camera. And he takes pictures of the crowd. So
it'd be great if he still had one that would be kicking in old school. But the disposable camera
in the crowd was great. We could spend the next two hours talking about music because we both
love it so much. The last music story I do want to tell though is, remember what you did at my wedding?
I hate to tell you weren't the first. I still feel special. You should. I mean, you're the first that
I use the buck teeth for. But pretty much everybody's wedding I've got up and sang with the band or
whomever. And for whatever reason, they let me do it. And I don't have any talent. I don't have a
voice that's worth listening to, but I certainly think I'm great. And I have a lot of verve and
energy. And so at your wedding, I sang a bruise. Yeah. Fire of course. And I had my teeth in,
so I was lisping pretty badly. Those buck teeth that make. Yeah. We're going to explain what these
are in a moment. So anyway, I had those Dr. Buck teeth in and sang fire to you and Jill. And I
could tell there was kind of like, what the hell is going on here among the whole wedding crowd? And
but hey, we were all in and it was great. And you had to, I remember that. I remember that wedding
also talking to Conti because he was driving from, was it then that he was driving from? No, he had
just driven from Jason Pyle's wedding in Los Angeles to Boston in 30 something hours. Right.
So he was planning to do it without stopping, right? But his wife or I wasn't his wife yet.
He'd taken Pro Vigil, which is that I gave him 400 milligrams of Pro Vigil, 800 milligrams of
ibuprofen. And he said he was going to be fine. And I was like, that's crazy. And she finally
made him stop in Cleveland. Yeah. Yeah. And it was 36 hours to get to Cleveland before she made
him stop for eight hours before they finished the drive to Boston. I asked him, I was like,
come on, you must have suffered like 24 hours. No, eight hours got up, drove the rest of the way.
Yeah. When you sang Fire at our wedding, it was one of the most amazing things because it was kind
of like Camp of a Blanknote. It was a Dan Flaherty, you know, the Dan band. Yes. It was that experience.
Because like at one point you threw in a couple extra fucks. Like it was fucking fine. Yeah. Yeah.
I did actually. That was so good. That's the part I love. Yeah. I wish I had done something more with
it to be honest with you because obviously it's been a great career for that guy. I actually got
to meet him at a party two years ago. You sent me the selfie. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I just glued
myself to him the whole night. I was like, I can't freaking believe I'm sitting here with this guy.
It's incredible. So where'd you go to college? So I went to a little school back East. Oh,
where abouts? That's East of the Mississippi. Okay. What city? Oh, I can't go city so quickly.
Oh, what state? It was in Massachusetts. This is Massachusetts. Yes. Eastern Mass. Oh, so near
Boston. Near Boston. This is a little school outside Boston. Boston College? No, that's in the city.
Harvard. So you were the first guy I met that took that to another level in terms of the complete
buffoonery of the too cool to say Harvard. Yeah. No, it always struck me as odd when people
couldn't say that they went to Harvard. And I remember being in the backseat of a car with
Duncan and his brother Hunter. And this dude is there with me and I'm like, Oh, so hey,
we're in school. And he starts out with Massachusetts. And I'm like, Oh my God,
you got to be kidding me. So I play along with it. I'm like, Oh, we're in Massachusetts on the
West side of Massachusetts or the East side of Massachusetts. He's like East side. And so he's
so happy. He's not coming out with it. And then finally, we wither down to Boston and then
Cambridge and then Harvard. He finally lays it on me. I was like, Oh yeah, dude, I went there too.
And then but I've got to admit very lucky to go. And there's not a chance in hell. I'd go to a
place like Harvard or anything like that these days as my 16 year old is going through this.
It is a different world for college admissions and all the breaks that I had to get there,
you know, the door was still much wider open than it is for kids today. It's just a different world,
more international kids and highly more competitive. They're much less wed to
schools that they've used to admit to. They're much more open and for kids all over the place
and all the words, I think is a great thing, but it's just not the same. I mean, there's no chance
in hell I'd be in a school like that little school back East if I were applying today.
Well, we used to joke about this so much that it stayed with me forever. So even when I left med
school and wound up anywhere, I would go there after now I became I was always looking for the
person who went to the little school back East. And so finally, so fast forward, maybe 10 years
after we're done with medical school, I've got this friend, his name is David Bataro, incredibly
talented artist, going to be talented at everything basically. And he went to that little school back
East and he thought that was the funniest shit on the face of the earth. And I said, David, I need
you to design little school back East t-shirts. So I want the sort of the Harvard shield, but I need
you to find the exact font that it normally says Harvard, but you have to just say little school
back East. And of course, David, because only David could do this, he probably spent the next,
I don't know, three weeks designing the font to make the t-shirt that I sent you. Yeah. So he made
10 of them because I had 10 friends who had gone to Harvard or whatever, or at least who I thought
would appreciate the joke. There were some who I didn't want to piss off too much. So do you still
have your little school back East? Yeah, of course I do. Yeah. That's so great. I should have worn it
during a reunion just a couple of years ago. That would have been good. So did you know when
you went to college, you wanted to go into medicine? I had a pretty good idea. My mom is a
nurse. My father, who I'm not, I didn't grow up with my dad. When my mom and dad divorced,
he went back to Lebanon and I really didn't hear from him until I was 16, 17 years old. How old
were you when they split? Three, but he's a physician and my grandfather was a physician. And
so I always grew up around medicine with my mom being a nurse and the doctors that she worked for
were terrific people. I had a bunch of injuries as a kid. So I saw Dr. Taylor, I remember like it
was yesterday in his office for some of the knee injuries I had as a kid. So I was exposed to
medicine probably more frequently than most people. And so I had a pretty good idea, but I took a
little bit of a circuitous route after college where I taught chemistry and physics in high
school, but I did it overseas. I spent a year in Milan. That's where I saw the great concerts and
taught in American school there, which was a terrific experience. And then came back the
states for a year to a private school in DC called St. Albans and all boys school there. It's very
prominent, great preparatory school. And then went back overseas to Bulgaria of all places and
taught in an American school there. So these three years that you're teaching kids in high school,
did you still think you were going to go and do medicine or was this a part of deciding if you
still wanted to do that? No, I was pretty sure I was going to go, but it's interesting. The teaching
was fun, but I felt like there was more that I could offer, I guess. And I was basically a high
school chemistry teacher and enjoyed the kids and loved working with the kids. But I just felt that
medicine would be a better fit because I'd still be able to teach and still be able to help people.
But it was a little bit more challenging, I guess. It was just more up my alley and I think it was
sort of a calling to go and do it. But the teaching was a great experience. It was a great way to see
the world. It was a great way to learn how to become an adult from college to earning a living,
getting a paycheck, paying your bills, paying back your student loans, and then directing your life
in a way that, geez, I really want to make something of this. And so then you go back to school.
So that time off between college and medical school for me was invaluable in terms of maturation.
And it's hard to imagine. I mean, knowingly in medical school, I don't think I was the most
mature dude on the block, but believe it or not, it was still maturation.
No, you know, Conte and I actually did a podcast a while ago, which I just actually just came out.
And we talked a little bit about this, that there was just a group of us that became very fast
friends. And I think we were viewed externally as sort of these testosterone knucklehead guys.
But we all had this thing in common, which was it all kind of taken a bit of a winding
path to get there. And I think on the surface, while it looks like we were just a bunch of
idiots, I think there was probably more to it.
Yeah. Do you remember the last time you and I interviewed?
I sure do. It was me interviewing for med school.
Yeah. I was your student in an interview.
Yeah. That was my first interview. So I was beginning like the circuit and doing all that,
but it was also my first time in California. So I'd never been to California until that interview.
And Stanford was the only school I applied to that was not in the Northeast. And I remember
leaving there and I think I went either Duke or Hopkins or Hopkins Duke and sort of worked my way.
But I remember thinking, you know, in part because I met you and I really connected with you.
And in part because I remember it was February and it was 76 degrees out. And I,
having grown up in Toronto and going to school outside of Toronto, it didn't occur to me, even
though intellectually I understood you could live in a place in the winter where it wasn't freezing.
To see that, I was like, wait a minute, this is a different place. But when you went to
med school, my recollection is we kind of thought you were going to wind up doing internal medicine
or ortho. There was a bit of a toss up there, right? Yeah, that's right. I was undecided pretty
much until the 11th hour between internal medicine and orthopedics. And the appeal to internal
medicine was the idea that you'd have these long-term relationship with patients. My guess is most
people who are struggling between ortho and something that other something is not internal
medicine. It's generally surgical for sure. I don't know. Maybe I shouldn't be admitting this
among my orthopedic colleagues. Well, there's a joke. And I remember when I was going through my
rotations, you had the attending and the senior resident or the fellow and the senior resident,
junior resident, all the orthopedic team walks into the patient's room post-op day one. And
the nurse says, I think so and so might have broken out into AFib last night. So I'm going to
call the cardiology consult. And the attending says, come on, we're doctors here. You're not going
to call a cardiologist to tell us our own patients in AFib. Give me a stethoscope. And he reaches in
his pocket, doesn't have one. He looks back at the fellow. The fellow doesn't have one. He looks back
at the chief resident, doesn't have one. All the way down. Even the med student for the ortho
rotation, not carrying the stethoscope. So then he's like, yeah, just call the cardiology.
Well, there was a sign at the general outside of the weight room that said ortho library.
And there's a stereotype, right? I mean, all the jocks go into ortho.
Yeah, no, it's a definite stereotype, but it's sort of an unfounded stereotype. I mean, obviously,
there's some of it that's true. I mean, most of the guys in orthopedics are athletes or have been
athletes at one point. But it's a pretty thoughtful specialty. It's not simply bone broke me fix. And
that's that. And I'm really glad I made the decision I did. I mean, I really can't imagine
not going to the operating room, not seeing patients, not seeing sort of the fruits of my
actual work. I think being in internal medicine is for some people, it's great for me, I think it
would have been ultimately a poor fit. So I'm very happy with the decision I ended up making.
I remember you let me read your essay for residency and you talked a lot about Bill.
Yeah. Who was Bill?
So when my mom and dad split, we moved back my essay moved back. My mother's from New Jersey.
We moved back to the town where she grew up. And it's a beautiful town near the shore called
Rumsen. Very well to do place similar on par with Greenwich, Connecticut, some other places that
people hear about. And when we moved back, we moved down to a smaller street. And across the
street was a guy, Bill Hensler, who was living with his aging mother. And he was a longshoreman.
He had worked on the docks. He'd been a caretaker. He'd been married three times, had kids and but
had been estranged from his daughter for a while. But anyway, he was our neighbor. And he took a
liking to my mom and my family and sort of ended up being over time a father figure to me. And like
I said, I didn't really have any contact, really had no contact with my biological father for
between ages three and 16. And Bill was that that role. He was that father figure. So the real
turn of the relationship actually happened in I think 1978, close to there where my older sister
Karina, we were all out playing in the street and Bill at that time was an alcoholic. He was a World
War II veteran. And I think he had PTSD. And like many other World War II vets basically suffered in
silence to some degree and his family, they were brewers in Newark. There was Hensler beer that was
brewed in Newark. And Bill passed out. And I think my sister was like trapped under his leg in the
middle of the street. And I mean, it was just a whole scene. And my mom said, Hey, enough. And
she took him to a place called Carrier Clinic in New Jersey. And he sobered up in 28 days. And
that's the last time he had any alcohol to drink. And he was sober since he came to all my popcorn
or football games, he would drive up to St. Paul's in New Hampshire, I went to boarding school and
come to some of those games there. And he got remarried in 87. And I was his best man. And that
was you would have been what 18 as 18 years old. Yeah, and it was the honor of a lifetime to be his
best man. And you know, we were very, very close. And part of the reason why I chose to do my training
in New York and leave California was so that I could be closer to home and closer to build,
because by that time he was in his late 70s. His health was failing, he'd had a cabbage and cabbage
for the listener is a bypass surgery of the heart coronary artery bypass graft. So he had, you know,
he was aging, and I just wanted to be closer to home. And then he died my fourth year of residency
about five days before my youngest son JJ was born. And those last six months were rough for him,
but I was very happy to be there. He actually broke his hip, which is an end of life injury for
many, many people, and it was for him. So he broke his hip in March. And it was actually right after
we had come back from Key West, Florida, where his daughter, Annie lives and works. And his
daughter and he had been estranged for a long, long time. But his wife, Jay, who I had stood up
for at the wedding, she had gotten Annie and Bill back in touch and they were close and they were,
they had reestablished their relationship. And so I had a week off from residency and Lynn and I
decided to go to Florida and our plans had fallen through at the last minute to be in a place near
Palm Beach. And so we said, let's go to Key West and let's bring Bill down to Annie. And so we did.
And then he ended up staying planning for a week, ended up staying for about six weeks. And then he
came back to New Jersey. And then shortly thereafter, he broke his hip. And I went down to see him
immediately in the local hospital in New Jersey. And they had him so medicated that he couldn't
talk. He wasn't him. And I said, this is not going in the right direction. So I brought him up to
New York to special surgery. And Matthias Bostrom, who's one of the greatest guys at special surgery,
did his hip, did his hemiarthroplasty. And then the nursing staff really took a liking to Bill and
everyone really, you know, he's a hard guy not to like. So he ended up staying for about two weeks
in the hospital after his hemiarthroplasty for no other reason than people like hanging out with him,
which is unheard of, right? I mean, and then, you know, when I was on call over the weekend,
we used to take call basically from Friday to Monday and be in overnight. And so we would go
up onto the roof on a nice day. And this was now in April, weather was turning nice. And we went up
on the roof on the sunny days and I'd hang out. My pager would go off. I'd bring him back downstairs.
And then whenever we had a minute, we'd go back up to the roof, we'd cruise around. And then he got
out of rehab. He went to the home. He was on his own, but he just got scared. And then he,
I forgot to mention this, he ended up having a liver cancer, HCC. So he had a paticellular
carcinoma. So he was becoming cacti. He was losing weight and he was just becoming scared.
And so the summer was sort of miserable for him. He was on his own at this point. Jay had died about
a decade earlier. And, you know, he went in the hospice and about two days later he died. But
Bill was probably the most giving and nicest person you could meet. He was always quick with
a laugh. He was a ton of fun. You know, when he'd come up to St. Paul's, he'd make fast friends
with all these other people. And again, you know, they'd be like, are you his grandfather? He's like,
no, he's just my friend. But he was that father figure that I otherwise probably wouldn't have
had. And he made all the difference in the path that I was able to take. And so, you know, I did
write my essay about Bill, partly because I just wanted people to know who he was. You know, if I'm
applying to be a part of your medical school, I mean, I didn't want to just list my resume. That
seems sort of stupid. I just wanted to give an insight. So I would talk about, I think on that
time I Jay, if it was in my application for residency, Jay had passed. It was about two months
after she died and I was at home for the summer. It was between my second and third year of medical
school. So I was in New Jersey and I wanted to take him on a, just wanted to get him away. So we
went up to New Hampshire like we had done when I was in high school. And we drove, he called it a
sponge door when he was younger. He talked with his buddies. They would go on a sponge door where
they go from house to house and place to place and sponge off their friends or their friends'
parents. And so we kind of did that. We stopped in a few places and then we went back to Cancad.
We were joking in the car, Concord, New Hampshire, but the way the folks in Concord say Concord is
Cancad. That was something I'll never forget. And then we went to Winniposaki where Mike Love,
who's one of his family friends and who was one of my first bosses, I bused tables at Mike's
restaurant in New Jersey and Mike moved up to New Hampshire and opened a restaurant in
Moultonboro on Lake Winniposaki. And then he opened another restaurant in one of the other
Lake towns off of Winniposaki called Love's Key. And so Bill and I saw Mike and Mike consistently
stay with him and we really were sponging from place to place. And so by the time we got back
to New Jersey about 10 days, two weeks later, we had gone on this nice ride and just had a chance
to kind of normalize his life again. And that was in the late 90s. And so I think that's what my essay
was about was the sponge door that I had with a guy who had just had a big loss in his life
and a way of sort of healing through time and healing through laughter and healing through
just normal daily activities. That's what sort of struck me about it. I remember this because,
you know, I remember going through because you were a year ahead of me and I'm sort of putting
that stuff into my own thought at the time, which was like, what do I want to write about? You don't
get a lot of space to tell your story when you're making these applications. And I remember thinking
this isn't what you'd expect from a guy applying to orthopedic surgery. And there was some stuff in
there about ortho, right? Which was like returning functionality to people and things like that. But
I was very touched by this story of Bill and yeah, I had forgotten until you mentioned it again,
but that you were his best man at the, you know, at the ripe old age of 18. I love that story.
And your oldest son is named after him. He is. So my will, we call him Will, is named after
Bill Hensler. And he was tickled pink about that. He would have loved to have met JJ. I mean,
sort of a hell raiser character like Bill was. And I think about life as somewhat serendipity.
And it is serendipitous that we happened to move into a house across the street from this man.
And that we took such a liking to one another and it was really all by chance. And I sometimes
think would it happen in a day and age like we have today where everyone's so suspicious of people
becoming close. Anyway, the bottom line is, it was a great stroke of fortune to know Bill. And I did
write about him an awful lot because he was probably one of the most meaningful influences
in my whole life. Are you close to your dad today? No, no, I've seen my dad probably total of about
four weeks. And you know, it's funny you mentioned that because he's recently, we were here in the
office right now doing this interview. And so he's been sort of raising hell through the office
because I get calls from the hospital pager. I think your dad is on the line. And then I get
calls from my secretary. I think your dad is on the line. And we don't talk very much. And he lives
in Spain. He was in Beirut for the majority of the civil war during the 70s and 80s. And he
refuge from Beirut to Spain in the mid 80s. And in 86 is when I saw him again. And he was in a small
town and Antonyante now lives in Alicante, which is a beach resort town about five hours south of
Barcelona. And I think he also suffers from PTSD. I mean, he was living in a war zone and he's an
OB guy. And, you know, he tells the story of having a woman on the table who he's doing cesarean
on and then someone comes in with a machine gun asking to save his brother's life. And, you know,
he became somewhat of a trauma surgeon as an obstetrician. And that's a big leap. And, you know,
I just think it got too much and he misses being at home. He misses Lebanon, I'm sure of it. But the
fact is, he's sort of anxiety riddled guy. We never really had a meaningful relationship. So
he got in touch with me again when he was hounding the office. I called him and
we talked for an hour, but I think the bottom line is, is at a point in his life where
he's not going to change very much. I'm probably not going to change very much. And it's hard to
bridge the gap. I wonder sometimes whether I want to expose my kids to that type of relationship
with their father. So I go back and forth on that. And then I did make a point of seeing him. The last
time I saw him was when I was engaged to my wife, Lynn. And I told her, look, you got to meet the
gene pool before you come into this whole thing. Cause he's a little nuts. So that was the last
time I saw him physically face to face. My sister random, my oldest sister went to see him and it
was a real brutal visit. He's starting to lose it a little bit and he's just not fully there. So
it's tragic. It's very sad because I think. Well, he was at Hopkins. He trained at Hopkins. He was
one of the former medical grads. He had gone to the American university. He was at Hopkins. He
did his OB guy. Is that where he met your mom? He met my mom in Roosevelt hospital in New York,
where he was training. I think he was doing some of his residency there or somehow they met there.
I'm not sure if it was during his residency afterwards, but they met in New York. My mom
was working as a medical assistant slash nurse anesthetist at that time. She was worked as a
medical assistant her entire group. But I think about him in his mid twenties. He's got his whole
life ahead of him. Everything's very promising. He's a young medical student. He's becoming a
resident and becoming a doctor. He has his family and then fast forward 10 years. It's all fallen
apart. Like he's lost his family. He's back in Beirut. He's with his, you know, his, his four kids,
his wife gone back in New Jersey. He's in Beirut. And then he basically gets burned out in Beirut
during the war. And since then really hasn't done much. He's taking care of a few people locally in
Spain as an obstetrician for some of the community that are refuge there, essentially,
but not really doing much. It's a derailment of his life at a time when things were really
looking very promising. And when I see him and meet him, I can see how that can happen.
And then I just don't want that for myself sometimes. So maybe I'm just turning a blind eye to it.
Yeah. Again, I probably a deeper discussion that we could have off mic, but I have so many thoughts
about this, right? I think, but I think that, you know, on the one hand, it's, I have found myself
more and more empathetic to sort of the situations people are in that on the surface might look like,
well, you know, that's a cut and dry case of, you know, he left his family and X, Y, and Z. But you
start to realize that there are, there are other bits of baggage that people are carrying with them
that, you know, you can make a wrong decision in a moment. And that, that decision can, you know,
two people can make the same sort of wrong decision, but one comes with far greater consequences.
You know, one of the other people I had on this podcast weekend, Corey McCarthy, and it was a
really, really interesting discussion about his life and how he wound up in prison. And it made
me reflect even more on how close I could have come to going to prison too. Like when I was in
eighth grade, the kid I looked up to the most in high school, and he took me under his wing. I mean,
he really liked me and he was the toughest kid in the block and blah, blah, blah. And, you know,
by the time I'm in 10th grade, he's in 11th grade, he's in jail for armed robbery. And I've always
thought like, what if I was out with him that night that he decided to do this really dumb
thing and hold up a liquor store? Like you don't have enough of a prefrontal cortex at that age to
sometimes go, wait a minute, this is a bad idea. Like in the moment that can seem like this is a
great rush. Like we're going to get some money. Now that said, you've brought up Lynn a couple
times. So I got to get one story out of you. There's probably, if I had like top 27, shayhab
stories, this one's on the list. So do you remember your first date with Lynn? Now Lynn was one of our
classmates. So you knew Lynn, but you finally figured out a way to get her out on a date.
Yeah, our first date was a real winner. So I finally sort of mustard up the balls to ask
Lynn out on a date. We were going to go out to dinner someplace. It was over Thanksgiving break.
And my buddy Josh Edelman was at the ed school at Stanford at the time. And he called me up as a
Sid. Some of my friends call me Sid for Sid Walski from the old Bud Rising. He said,
I heard your mom sent you one of those hands. It's halftime at the Menlo Atherton game. I'm
wondering if I can come over and have some of it. Like, Hey Josh, I'm sorry, man. I got a date with
this girl. I really dig her. I can take her out to dinner. He's like, dude, dude, come on. I'll
be over in like five minutes. I'm like, all right. So I call up Lynn and I say, Hey, Lynn, I'm sorry.
I got to cancel dinner. I've got Josh coming over here to eat my ham, but you know, maybe we can
meet at the goose. Jesus Christ. I know. I know. Like that again. I mean, like, what is going
through your mind in that moment? I'm just thinking, I want to give all my ham to Josh. And so anyway,
and so she goes, are you kidding me? I'm like, no. And then she goes, okay. And I'm like, well,
do you want to meet at the goose? She goes, we're not meeting at the goose. You can pick me up when
we go to the goose. I'm like, okay. And the goose was the dive bar. You've been there a million times.
But for those who don't know, it's a dive bar outside of Stanford. It's still there. It's still
up and running. Is it still there? Yeah. Same. First place I ever ate when I came to Stanford.
Yeah. No, you'll never forget it either. It's probably still working its way through you.
So Josh did come over, he ate most of the ham and then I picked up Lynn and we went to the goose
and we were talking and chatting across the table. And I don't know if I should talk about this part
of it, but I had gas and I was just trying to sniff it one way and blow it the other way.
And just trying to divert it from getting near her nose. But I don't know, she says to this day,
she knew exactly what I was doing. I thought it was very subtle. So after that, I drove her home
and my car at that time was, this was 96 and I had an 83 Honda Civic semi-station wagon with,
where you could see the road through the floorboards. I had sheepskin on the seats because
they had worn completely through. There was no radio and there was no air conditioning. And this
thing was a, I bought it for like $1,300 and there's a story about selling it too. So anyway,
I took Lynn back and we're sitting in the car on the sheepskin and I asked her, Hey, can I give you
a kiss? And she's like, once again, are you kidding me? I'm like, what do you mean? Am I kidding you?
She's like, why do you have to ask? I was like, I don't know. I thought, and so anyway, we kiss very
awkwardly and she bolts out of the car again night and she leaves and I'm like, Oh Jesus Christ,
I really fucked that one up. And so I get in the car. Cause you're sort of three strikes at this
point. Yeah, no, I'm beyond that. Blowing off the dinner for the party. I'm going to get the ham and
three strikes. It's a no, like 27 ounces. Like a no hitter. So I'm leaving and I'm driving. I'm
literally like, I don't know, fourth way home. I'm like, fuck, shit, how are you idiot? So I turned
the car around and I, this is the story. This is the best line. So guys, if you've listened to
nothing else in this story, this is the money line. Yeah. So I knock on the door and she looks,
she opens the door. She looks at me and like, Hey, Lynn, I'm so sorry. I got halfway to the safe way.
And I'm like, fuck, she had me with it. And so I turned around and I decided I just got to tell you
how I feel. And she goes, well, how do you feel? I'm like, I think you're hot as shit.
And I said, and I don't, I said to myself, if I don't care if I have to sleep on the couch
or in your bedroom, but I'm not going home. And she goes, well, you can sleep on the couch.
So strike, strike 10. And then the balance of the things just sort of happened from there.
So, I mean, I slept at home that night. We did kiss and it was much better kiss.
And then, you know, things just took off and lucky me. But that's the line. I mean, I think
we're in a new era now. I still think that you're hot as shit is not going to get you a me too offense.
I don't know. I can't imagine why it could. I think it's reasonable. Yeah, no, it's objectifying.
It's authentic. It is authentic and it's sincere, but it's objectifying and it's using swear words
and stuff. So there's certainly something that could be me too about it. That's, I just love it.
So you've alluded to it already, but just for those who don't know what HSS is. So the hospital
for special surgery in New York is the apex facility for training orthopedic surgeons.
I mean, even though I wasn't interested in orthopedic surgery, even I knew what HSS was
from the first year of medical school, because if you wanted to do orthopedic surgery, you wanted
to go to HSS. So you end up there. But I mean, just for someone listening to this, what the heck
made HSS so special? They had some giants in the field of orthopedics. And so number one,
it was an all orthopedic hospital. It was all orthopedics. And so they were a think tank of
orthopedics and they were. I'll let the oxymoron there slide on the think tank of orthopedics.
I'm just kidding. But the development of joint replacement, that was a big, they played a big
role in that. Some of the giants in the field of joint replacement, Chip Raunewat, Tom Sculco,
Philip Wilson were part of it. The spine surgeons, I mean, every field within or every subspecialty
within orthopedics, HSS had a player in that field. And again, it's just a really unique
environment where the reputation of the hospital is well-earned and well-deserved. Patients come
from all over the tri-state area to get their orthopedic work done at special surgery. The
hospital work now we have 20 operating rooms. And we have a lot of patients in the hospital.
For all the subspecialties, there were 20 inpatient operating rooms alone, all for orthopedics. So just
through that incredible volume, you can't help but learn just through osmosis. And they were very
dedicated to resident education. I remember one conference that we were getting a little bit
scolded because not everyone was showing up to conference. Obviously, it's funny when people
scold the people are actually there for not showing up, right? But anyway, I remember one of
the guys saying, look, we don't have to do these teaching conferences every morning. We'd be just
as happy to crank up the hours at 730 instead of 830. But they did do that. They would have these
conferences every day from 730 to 830 about some topic of orthopedics. And by the end of four years,
again, simply by osmosis, you'd absorb so much knowledge. And then the operative experience was
second to none because the operating rooms were humming all day long and sometimes well into the
night is not unheard of to do 10 joint replacements and be doing your last one at 10 in the evening.
And they just that was the ethic of the place was you took care of people you did, there was no sort
of end to it. And they had an endless demand and an endless volume. And they still do and they still
have the same giants in the field. They've developed some really young talent and influencers in the
field. So who were your mentors when you were there? Well, there were several mentors, but Russ
Warren, I would consider a mentor. I'm probably the not his pride and joy. He's had several he's
trained half the NFL team physicians. And he's been he's still as prolific as he ever has been.
And he's got to be pushing into his mid 70s now. And he's a Vietnam War surgeon. It seems like all
those you probably met him at Hopkins, but these old time Vietnam War surgeons were just incredibly
gifted, ballsy. They were just great surgeons and they really knew how to take care of people. And
I think their training in wartime was a big part of that. So Russ Warren, for sure. What did he
specialize in specifically with the North? So he's one of the godfathers of sports medicine. And one
of the earlier developers of ACL reconstruction, and he was a pioneer in arthroscopy and arthroscopic
reconstruction. And he's written more papers than any orthopod alive and probably more papers than
all orthopods combined. I mean, he's been he's he never stopped moving and working. If he wasn't
seeing a patient, he was reading a research paper, he was coming up with an idea. And I remember one
night, his driver, he had I worked with him as a fellow with the Giants when he and he's still their
team physician. And he had a driver Ernie, who would take him every place. And we had a late
West Coast game, we got back to Newark at three or four in the morning, and Dr. Warren spend the
night above his office, and then start seeing patients at 8am. And Ernie, he asked me if I
want to lift back as a dad, that'd be great. Thank you. Because where I live is two blocks down from
the hospital. And Ernie dropped off Dr. Warren, and then I was in the car with Ernie. I said, Hey,
Ernie, man, how does Dr. Warren do it? I mean, he's always working. And and I'm like, How do you do
it? He said, Well, Dr. Warren takes very good care of me. But he once told me, all I got is time,
and I'm not wasting it for anybody. And when I heard that, it put everything in a perspective
of the way Dr. Warren work, the fact that he never let a minute go wasted, he would constantly
either taking care of patients or thinking of research. I remember on a West Coast trip,
he met with some engineers at Stanford for a type of bracing, he just was constantly thinking
orthopedics and advancing the field. So he's obviously a huge influence. And anybody who's
ever worked with him will tell you he's the number one guy. And then Dr. Polici, Paul Polici,
he's another joint, he's a joint replacement surgeon, a sports medicine surgery surgeon,
was the most gifted joint replacement surgeon I've ever seen, he could do a total hip replacement,
45 minutes to an hour. What do you mean, skin to skin? Yes. And he just put in a perfect total
lip every time. And he was the doctor's doctor. He did anybody in the area, anybody in the hospital
and need a day replacement was getting it from police. I mean, he was just a very, very gifted
surgeon and everyone knew it. He's also one of the funniest people you can possibly meet a big Bruce
fan as well. And a Bon Jovi fan and turns out Jovi played it in an honorary dinner. And Bon Jovi
was playing at this dinner for in his honor. But Polici, terrific guy. And Wickewitz, Tom
Wickewitz, who was the director of our fellowship, again, super good guy, Scott Rodeo, who's the head
team physician for the Giants now, who's a phenomenal research clinician. And those are
hard to find the clinician scientists are sort of a dying breed. But Dr. Rodeo certainly embodies
that. And he takes terrific care of people, including my mom. And I don't know, I can go
down the list. I mean, well, before we talk about leaving New York, you spent a year with the Giants.
You did your sports fellowship. What did you learn there? I mean, it strikes me as an interesting
crash course of sports medicine, because you're really seeing the finest tuned machines under the
greatest destructive forces. Yeah, that's a great way of putting it. So with the fellowship that Dr.
Warren had, he, Dr. Warren's fellowship, he picked two guys and you would alternate a week at training
camp. And so once the Giants open training camp, that was also coincided with the beginning of our
fellowship just by just by chance. And I grew up a Giants fan like a rabbit Giants fan. And Bill
Hensler was a rabbit Giants fan. LT the greatest linebacker of all time. Yes, without question. And
one of the greatest people. I mean, so Bill and I used to go to Giants games, that was our thing. And
one of my first Giants games was with Bill in 1983, when Scott Bruner was the quarterback. And any
Giant fan will remember this when the Giants scored in our end zone, and they went up by three points
against the Redskins. And it was pissing rain. It was 32 and a half degrees. I mean, I've never,
you can't really be much colder than that. And then the Giants kicked off and they squibb kicked
it. And so the Redskins got great field position with 40 seconds left, they get in the field goal
position and Mark Mosley kicks his record tying consecutive field goal. Then the Giants lose the
coin toss, the Redskins get the get the ball, they drive in a field goal range. And this is like
first score is going to win. It's 83. And Mark Mosley kicks his record breaking consecutive field
goal. And we go home so disappointed. And I think that was a game that Phil Simms hurt his
knee and went out. But anyway, Bill and I would go to all these games. And actually the night before
Bill died, there was a Giants game on and we had talked about it. And we like we always did, we
recall, you know, when I was in New York, or California, wherever we talk every Sunday,
talk about the Giants game. And I remember talking about that game with Bill and then and he knew
something was up because that following morning, he that's when he died. And we were crying on the
phone, and I love you. And you know, after talking about the game, and the game was again,
just another vehicle. So anyway, I had and Bill had taken me to Giants training camp when we were
driving up to St. Paul's, I think one time, and I was going up early for my own football
camp as a junior in high school. And we stopped in Albany for the Giants training camp where they
would have it. And we hung out there for the day and watched practice. And I remember that training
camp. And now I'm coming back about a year and a half after Bill died to Giants training camp.
And it was a bizarrely emotional time. I never spoke with the trainers, Ronnie Barnes and, and,
and Byron Hanson and Steve Canelli about this. I mean, they're three of the greatest guys, they're,
they're, they're unbelievable practitioners and caretakers of these athletes. But it was a kind
of an emotional moment where I'm in training camp, having all these memories of Bill thick and man,
he would be he would love to get you imagine the pride he would be so happy. But okay, all that
aside, the first thing you do realize is that these guys are freak athletes, like beyond
anything you can imagine. They're so physically gifted. It is beyond belief. I remember I had a
poster in my bedroom when I was a kid of Jerry Rice standing in the end zone and he's holding
the ball up and at his feet is a player. I think it was someone in the Bengals and he's like,
got his ankles, but he's completely like laying out and obviously failed in his attempt to stop
Jerry Rice. And I remember one of my best friends in high school who was himself a fantastic athlete.
We were like sitting in my room one day sort of shooting the shit and he, he said one of the most
astute things ever. He looks up at that poster and points to the Bengal laying prone and he's
like, do you realize that guy's a better athlete than we'll ever be like the dude at the feet of
the guy you're worshiping? Well, the guys in the league are freak athletes. The guys trying to get
into the league are freak athletes. The guys at the top of the league are freak athletes. And it
is a razor thin margin that separates the guy who's a superstar in the league and the guy who's
not in the league. And again, it is such a narrow margin of, you know, this athlete versus that they
are all tremendous athletes. So that's the first thing you recognize is just how fast, strong,
powerful, gifted, graceful all of these guys. And longevity matters. You know, I mean,
Ryan Flaherty, who's a friend of mine that I do need to get on this podcast at some point,
I've talked about him in the past, but you know, Ryan is really the guru of speed training and he
does two things. Basically trains guys in college who were, you know, the top sort of 10 recruits
that are going to go to the combine and do really well. And then also trains guys once they're in
the NFL. And he said to me once, you know, the focus changes so much after the combine to what
you care about. So when you are in college trying to get there, it's all about performance at the
combine and performance to get in the league. And that predominantly comes down to speed. And then
he said, but once you get in the NFL, once he's working with these guys that are there, it's
longevity. It's just don't get injured. And he changes the strategy is completely dedicated
towards maintaining how long they can stay healthy. And that's a huge challenge. It is so
violent on the sidelines. It's very, very difficult to really get a sense of how violent
it is unless you're right next to it. But the hits are massive. I mean, when they talk about
it being like a car wreck, it really is like a car wreck. It's an incredibly high energy
collisions that happen over and over and over again. I mean, the closest I've ever sat in an
NFL game is probably 20 rows back in the end zone. So you're far enough away. Like it's still great
to be able to, you know, I was watching Barry Sanders play the 49ers. That was like the only
time I've ever seen Barry Sanders in person. But yeah, I can't imagine where you're sitting
on the sidelines, just even acoustically what that's like. Yeah, I remember there was an
interception once and the Giants had thrown the interception and and then Chris Nee, who was an
all pro guard and Tom Coughlin son-in-law, as it turns out, he was married to Coughlin's daughter,
comes over and just wrecks this guy. I mean, and it was right at right in front of me and he
flattened this guy and this guy got up, but it was the most acoustically impactful. It felt like a
sonic boom when this guy popped him, like just really took him out. That's the other thing I
think people don't appreciate. I only appreciate this because I've seen him train how fast those
linemen can run. Like, right. You look at this guy and you think, ah, he's 320 pounds. He's got
a little bit of a belly. He's probably not that fast. And he's going to run a 40 in like five
seconds flat, if not four, nine. Right. And then I couldn't run today if my life depended on it.
So they would do gassers. Coughlin had them do gassers where they'd go 50 yards across the field,
50 yards back, and you'd have to do it in 18 seconds, 16 seconds, depending on your position.
So I was like, all right, let me give this a try. And I wasn't as good a shape then as I had been,
you know, five years earlier. I'd sort of fallen off the, you know, once the kids came,
the wheels kind of came off. But but I was trying to do the gassers and the linemen time.
And it was very challenging. And these guys can motor. They are exceptionally good athletes. They
are big, but they're also graceful and they're strong and they're all that they're coordinated,
you name it. But the freakishness of the athletes is certainly something that sticks out.
The stress that these guys are under, I don't think people appreciate it. I mean, people think
about professional athletes just sort of coasting, they're making millions and everything else. But
that's not, it's not anywhere near the truth. And particularly in football, where they're really few
and far between guaranteed contracts. So these guys don't see their money unless they stay healthy
and play. And there's so few games. I mean, I remember reading an editorial a while ago that
talked about imagine we just took hockey, basketball and baseball and made it a 16 game season.
Like think of what that would do to the intensity of every single game, every play, every game.
So that's exactly what it is. It is intense. And if you're in the league and you know that the,
you know, you're fighting with everybody on your team for a position, you're fighting with
everybody in the league for your position. You're fighting with everybody out of league, trying to
get into the league for a position. It's an incredibly stressful environment for a young
20 something year old to be exposed to. I mean, these guys are under a tremendous amount of
stress to just perform, keep their job, not get hurt. And it's an intensely difficult situation.
So that's certainly something that stood out. What were the most common injuries? Like I remember
reading and this is almost assuredly dated and no longer correct, but directionally, I'm sure it's
correct. But the median tenure of a player in the NFL was like, you know, three to four years.
Yeah, we hear about Tom Brady. I mean, it's great to talk. I mean, frankly, most of the players we
know about, you know, the great quarterbacks, you know, they've been around for a decade and you
sort of take that for granted. But that's not the norm. Not even close. I mean, it is positionally
dependent. The running backs have the shortest careers. Linebackers have shorter careers, but
they really, really, again, because everyone's trying to get in the league, everyone in the
league is competing. And there's attrition. I mean, these guys leak oil and they leak oil
relatively quickly because of the violence of the game. And it was funny, I remember at the combine,
the combine, you'd examine the 300 participants were in the combine. And would you actually
examine everyone? Or would the Giants say, hey, look, these are the guys we're most interested
in go examine them. It wasn't that they would cherry pick the players. They they got a grade
on everybody. So all the 300 participants, they got a medical grade. But what would happen is the
teams get into groups of four or five, and the docs groups of four or five. So the players are
going to seven or eight medical exams, they're going the same physical exam, seven or eight times.
Exactly. And if they had an injury history, obviously, that would be what would be of
interest. The docs would share the information among the teams. They were, they were, you know,
very much working as a group of physicians trying to evaluate the medical care that these players
had gotten in the past. But I remember, I mean, all these kids coming through had something.
And, you know, risk surgeries for scaphoids, stability surgeries for shoulder dislocations,
ACLs, meniscus surgery. I mean, it seemed like more often than not, these kids had already had
a prior medical history or prior surgical history. And I said to Ronnie Barnes, I said, God, Ronnie,
all these guys are somewhat injured in leaking oil. Yet these are the best guys coming through.
And he said, he said, they're all injured because they're the best guys coming through and they
play. And it's made me realize, boy, it's a very tough sport to play at a very high level without
exposing yourself to injury and that everybody gets hurt at some point. And it's usually those
injuries that slow you down just a little bit. That again, is that margin, that raise a thin
margin of being a star in the league and being out of the league. Do either of your boys play
football? My youngest does actually. JJ does. He's playing freshman football. Does it worry you
at all? Not just with everything you know, but also with all the CTE stuff we've since learned about.
Sure. It worries me like crazy. And, you know, he started playing football as he's probably the
only Jewish kid in the history of the world to leverage his bar mitzvah into a football spot.
Yeah, he was in seventh grade and he was preparing for his bar mitzvah and he was hating it.
And he basically struck up a deal. It's like, you guys, let me play tackle football. You won't
hear a word about the bar mitzvah preparation. I'll just, I'm gonna say word. And we took him up
on the deal and he was playing in a weighted football league. So 125 pounds is the max.
And they, everyone's acutely aware of CTE concussions, head injuries, the way the game
is coached has changed drastically among the youth level. And then when you watch the games,
it seems relatively safe. I mean, it's sort of kids bumping hips. It certainly doesn't seem any
more violent than the lacrosse and hockey. The kids are playing at that age and we let him play.
He then he played again his eighth grade year because he's a little bigger. And so again,
it was still a sized limited league. So he's a little bit more advantaged then. And then
sort of reluctantly he's playing as a freshman and simply because he loves playing the game.
And we look at the mentors who are his coaches and we have such admiration for his coaches. And
we look at his teammates and he gets an awful lot out of it. And I remember hearing Curtis
Martin's Hall of Fame acceptance speech. Oh, which I will link to it, but it is beautiful.
It's an awesome speech. So you're better off listening to it. I don't know if you want me
to spoil the punch line. Yeah. I mean, go ahead and paraphrase it for the folks who don't want to
listen. So Curtis Martin talks basically off the cuff about football and his closing line was,
and he came from very poor, disadvantaged environment, Pittsburgh, and football gave him
an avenue. And he talks about all the dangers of the game. And he's not certain whether or not
he'd let his son play football or not, but he says to himself, if football can do for your kid,
what it did for me, there's no question that I let you play. I mean, that's fundamentally the
punch line that there's a lot of pros and cons. You have to weigh the pros and cons for your own
kid and decide whether or not it's worth it. And for us, we felt it was worth it. And I
shit my pants nearly every game. I'm always worried about him playing.
But then again, I see the joy he derives from playing it. And it's hard to hold that now as
time goes on and the game gets faster and the kids get bigger. And he may decide this is for me,
or this is not for me. We'll see how he develops. And he's still just a freshman and still an
underdeveloped freshman. But it is something we let him do despite Lynn being a pediatrician,
me being an orthopedist and both of us being fully aware of the risk of playing,
because in the end, we felt the benefits outweigh the risks.
Yeah, I don't know. It's tough. I was actually, as I was on the way over here to meet you,
I was talking to my brother and my brother's really into mountain biking. And he keeps trying
to get me to do it. And I'm like, yeah, I just don't want to do it. Like I just, you know, just,
hey, I don't need a new thing to get into. But also it's like, just don't, the risk of injury,
like I don't, even silly injuries, like I don't want to break my wrist or do something like that.
But look, he's obsessed with it. And we have a mutual friend who he's much closer to who's
a motorcycle racer and used to do a lot of road riding. And whenever we would be on, you know,
road rides, this guy was the best descender. Like because he had been racing motorcycles all his
life, he could, he could basically rip hell going down a mountain when all of us would be a little
more tentative and on our brakes and stuff. And this guy's name is Jimmy. And now Jimmy's got
my brother into something I didn't even realize was an activity, which is downhill mountain biking.
So they go to ski slopes in the summer and you ride, you take your mountain bike up the ski
slope and you just come down. And I'm like, my brother's like, I know what you're going to say
before you say it. So don't say it. I thought it was crazy too, but it is the fricking best thing
in the world. And I was like, you couldn't pay me to do that. Paul, what are you thinking?
Riding a mountain bike down a ski slope. Like, I don't know. I think I'm just a pussy. I mean,
I think at the end of the day, I took a trip with my buddy Jim Barker from Telluride to Moab on a
mountain bike over the Uncompared Plateau. But we were such novice rookies. We even like, hey,
let's go mountain biking. Yeah. What do you want to do? Let's go to Colorado and go down some ski
slopes and barrel down on our mountain bikes. That's what we thought we were going to do.
Well, we think it'd be fun. It's like alpine sliding on a bike.
So let's talk a little bit about some of the nuts and bolts of orthopedic surgery,
because I can't imagine there's somebody listening to this who hasn't either personally,
directly or indirectly been touched by an orthopedic injury. And I don't know the right
way to go through it, but why don't we just start with the knee, since that seems to be a pretty
common joint that gets injured. Talk to me about it through the lens of an engineer. What is the
knee really good at? What is it bad at? If you could be God for a day, what would you change?
So, oh, that's a good question. So the knee is incredibly good at bearing weight
and supporting your weight. And it's incredibly stable for what it's being asked to do,
but it's an incredibly complex design with more moving parts. Every degree of freedom is in play
with rotation, translation. So if I were God for a day, I would make the ligaments. Actually, no,
I would make the cartilage immortal, because the cartilage wearing down in the knee is fundamentally
what will slow people down. I see. So you're not going to save the ACL tear, but you're going to
save the knee replacements for arthritis. Correct. And the cartilage is what, when that wears down,
that's when people have pain. People can live without an ACL. I've lived without an ACL in my
left knee since I was 12 years old. And I was able to play sports. Not everybody can do it.
So, when you were 12, you tore your ACL. Yes. And you, at the time, you could have had a
cat of Eric replacement. So at 12 years old, at that time, I was casted for... Or patellar tendon.
It was in the early 80s. So, I mean, when I was 12, and so ACL reconstruction was in its naysenses.
I'm not even sure anything was really being done on any sort of widespread level. And if it was,
it was being done through open incisions. And there was a five in one procedure where you'd
sling bits of the IT band around the knee, and certainly not what modern techniques would be of
reconstruction. Sometimes repairs were being done at the time that failing, basically trying to
sew the ligament back together. And so, you can live without an ACL, and you can live a very
productive active life without one. But you will be prone to instability. And the instability can
wear down the knee. The repetitive giving out episodes can start wearing through the meniscus.
And then once the meniscus starts going, the articular hard cartilage starts going.
And once the hard cartilage starts going, the knee pain, the knee swelling, the limitations...
So let's talk about, let's describe the joint, because now I'm realizing it's hard to do this
over audio, but you've got this thing called the tibia, and it has a plateau. And that's where the
cartilage sits, right? On top of the plateau, yes. And then the other end of the joint is the sort of
bottom end or the distal end of the femur. That's kind of roundish. Yes. And it actually kind of
looks more like a knuckle, right? Like it's sort of... Yeah. And there are two condyles, two knuckles
to it. Yeah. Yes. So you've talked about the cartilage, but then where does the ACL, MCL,
and menisci fit into that for the person listening to this? So again, like you said,
it's hard to describe. And we'll put cool pictures up so people can kind of look and see this.
So the MCL is on the inside zone of the knee, and it's actually a ligament that we consider
extraarticular. It's outside the joint capsule. And the MCL is a very stout ligament that controls
the knee from swaying side to side. So if you can imagine your tibia swaying out towards your hip
or back towards your other foot, the MCL controls that. The LCL, which is the lateral collateral
ligament on the other side of the knee and the outside zone of the knee, has the same function,
but just in the opposite direction. And then the cruciate ligaments are crossing ligaments that
are directly in the center of the knee. And the anterior cruciate ligament is crucial for
rotational control of the knee. And when people tear their ACL, it's usually a rotational injury
that does it. And it's almost a near dislocation of the knee that occurs. And so usually the outer
part of the femur will rotate backwards and even come all the way off the tibia and then rotate
back. And as it comes off and comes back, that's where the tearing of the ACL occurs.
Why do people tear the ACL more than the PCL?
PCL usually gets torn from a direct blow injury from falling onto the knee, but falling specifically
on the tibial tubercle. And it's not easy to do that. I mean, most of the time you're falling
more on your patella. But if you fall directly on your tibial tubercle, you will drive the tibia
backwards posteriorly. And that's what puts the PCL on stretch and it gives out.
But people do very well with a full PCL tear as long as they don't have any other ligament injury
in the knee. And plenty of the professional athletes, including a few on the Giants,
had complete PCL tears who were functioning at that high athletic level. So it doesn't have the
same rotational implications when patients tear their PCL. They typically, if they're having
complication from a PCL tear, it's from the increased contact pressures that happen in the
patella because the tibia is now sitting back and it's pulling the patella into the femur as
it sits back. And that pressure between the patella and the femur is what gives people disability
from a PCL tear. And then so where do the meniscus sit? The meniscus sit on top of the plateau.
They're rounded and they basically contour the flattish plateau into a more rounded femur. So
it allows for the contact pressures within the knee to be distributed evenly, more evenly.
And they're critical tissue structures, as it turns out. It wasn't long ago that we were
removing meniscus without really any thought consequence. There was no foreseen consequence
of taking out the meniscus or even parts of it. And it's become very clear that losing the meniscus
is sort of the beginning of the end for most people's knees once they start having meniscal
tears. And it's far more likely that at a younger age, their cartilage is going to wear down their
hard cartilage. And so when a person gets a knee replacement, the tibial plateau has that built in
little curvature up at the edges to mimic what the meniscus would be doing sitting on the actual
tibial cartridge. Is that necessary? With a replacement. So the meniscus is also stabilizing
structure within the knee. And again, it takes the flat tibia and makes it more rounded so that the
femur fits in it. And that gives some natural anterior and posterior resistance to translation.
And losing that meniscus puts the articular cartilage under a lot more pressure and it tends
to wear down more quickly. Now there are several other factors besides the status of the meniscus
that leads to loss of that articular cartilage, that hard cartilage that coats the end of the bones.
But when people end up losing that coating of hard cartilage on the end of the bones in the joint,
that's the cartilage that we really care about because losing that will lead to swelling and
pain and difficulty walking and feelings of instability and all the things that slow people
down as they're trying to live a long life. And that's where their health span and their
lifespan starts separating. As you know, you've taught me this whole concept about lifespan and
health span, but that's where it starts separating when that articular cartilage starts wearing down.
Now I tell all my patients, everyone's going to lose their hard cartilage. That's not an if,
it's a matter of when. And we all want to lose ours when we're 150 years old. And the things that
influence that are genetics, exposure to injury, trauma, but also things that are modifiable,
your weight, your exercise, things that really tend to help. And so when people have knee
replacement, the plastic that's put in between is really again for stability and to distribute some
force and to hold the knee in place. And they're different designs with... Is it still ultra
limo like the weight polyethylene? It is polyethylene that's used in hips. There's
more cross-link polyethylene to resist wear. The knee replacements tend to fail because of
loosening of the prosthetic from the bone. And one of the things that can lead to loosening is
particulate wear causing inflammation leading to a cascade that eventually results in failure of the
knee. And unlike changing the tires on your car, when you have a new knee, it's not the same as the
old set. It's not as durable. It's typically not as satisfying. It's not as flexible. And so people
don't have the same sort of euphoric outcome with their second knee replacement, for instance,
than they do with their first. What's the typical expected or median expected utility out of any
replacement? Again, it depends heavily, I'm sure, on the age of the patient and activity level, but
as a general rule, do you... We don't necessarily give a number because it does depend on the
activity. The younger a patient is, the more active they'll be and the more likely they will loosen at
an earlier age. And so for the people who need the knee replacements, the longest people in their
40s and 50s will have the shortest lifespan of the knee. And so a 40 to 50 year old, you'll tell them
just to set expectations, you're probably going to need two of these in your lifetime. It's going to
need a revision at some point in their lifetime. But it's a significant difference in longevity
for the 50 year old getting a knee replacement than the 65 year old. And so we try and kick the
can down as far as we can down the road so that if patients end up needing knee replacement, that
it's going to be... Their knee replacement will outlast them and that they'll only have one
operation on their knee. So it's not unlike the way you think about a heart valve. It's the same
age and we use tissue versus mechanical, different situation. Let's go back to some of the
modifiable factors you talked about. So weight, how clear... I mean, it's intuitively obvious.
How clear is the relationship? Is it linear? Is it nonlinear between... It may be geometric. I mean,
because every pound of weight loss up top is four pounds of weight loss through the knee,
which is walking and it becomes amplified. Why is that? That's just... Again, the mechanics of
the knee. So your center of gravity and how that applies torque into the knee is part of the reason
why that body weight is amplified. So it's not just pound for pound. So when patients gain a pound,
they're putting four more pounds of pressure through the knee, which is walking six pounds
more with going up and down the stairs, eight pounds more with running. So it's a significant
multiplier and there's similar multipliers with the hip and the back. And so we... So interestingly,
bring this up, we've been trying to help patients with these modifiable factors for their knee and
particularly their weight. And we started a program in our practice called OrthoHealth,
which is based off a lot of the work you do. And I don't know if you've ever seen the webinar I
give, but you're sort of an all-star in the webinar and so is Lin. But we're trying to help patients
sleep better, trying to help them manage their stress better, try and help them eat better,
and try to help them exercise more efficiently. I think people exercise way too much trying to get
it all in, burn all... They have a concept of burning all the calories as opposed to sort of
activating their metabolism. And so we're trying with this group of patients who are typically
overweight, BMI over 30, 35, 40, they're pretty ill patients. They're not just their knee that's
bothering them and trying to get them to turn their lives around a little bit.
So from an activity standpoint, is all things equal running harder on the knee than any other
activity a patient does? It is harder and puts more strain on it. But the body reacts to this.
There's, I think it's called Wolf's Law, where the body reacts to stress. So the more stress
that's put on it, the more bone that's laid down for instance. That's why we emphasize weight-bearing
exercise for patients in their 30s in particular before they start losing bone so that they can
build up their bone density. And so the body reacts. When do you lose the ability to increase
bone density through that activity? It's usually around 30 and women have an accelerated bone loss
in menopause. So the bone building is occurring through the first couple of decades of life and
then from then on it's down. But there's a big, big decrease during menopause in bone density for
women. And that's where pharmacotherapy is directed. Yeah, so all the hormone therapy and
all the exercise basically isn't to bring you back to where you were when you were 30, it's to slow
it down. Because it's an inevitable decline. What is driving that? Is it osteoclastic?
Well, it has to be to some degree because the osteoclasts are what are the cells that
resort bone. But how well understood is the why? Like what's the evolutionary reason that we would,
we're not short of any of the minerals that are in bone. We could certainly get them exogenously.
Why in the world would we just decide to enter a catabolic state at the age of 30?
I don't have a clue. And I don't know whether for women it's childbearing and building the skeleton
of the fetus. Certainly there's a transient osteopenia of pregnancy that occurs. But I don't
have the famous clue. And those are, that's a fantastic question that people are trying to
answer. And, you know, pharmacologically, we try and slow down the osteoclastic function, we try and
slow down the speed at which the osteoclastic bones are bone. I use that term technically,
I shouldn't have, I should have defined it. So osteoclastic is breaking down of bone,
osteoblastic is the building up of bone. And they're the cells that do that. Yeah.
And so the osteoclasts get inhibited by some of the pharmacotherapies, the fosomax,
boneva, the bisphosphonates that slow down and quote unquote build bone density. But it's not
necessarily building great bone. And so it's building denser bone, but there's concerns that
there may be fault lines in the bone that it may not necessarily be more torsionally resistant.
It's not more tension resistant. So you see tension side of failure of bone with
prolonged use of bisphosphonates. And so those are some of the atypical femur fractures that you see.
People get foot fractures with this. So it's not going to be the answer just inhibiting osteoclasts
to build healthier bone or to slow down the process of bone resorption. And is there
anything that's in the pipeline pharmacologically with respect to activating osteoblasts?
Great question. Most of it is focused on osteoclastic inhibition. And there are
thoughts about bumping up osteoblastic production with magnetic fields. And that's what's the
technology behind bone stimulators for when patients have hard to heal fractures, you can
use a bone stimulator, which is an electromagnetic field that seems to be stimulating to the
osteoblasts. But there's always concern that when you stimulate the osteoblasts, that you may be
provoking a cancer type situation, because you don't necessarily know where you're directing them.
Right. And so we don't use these bone stimulators in patients with cancer. We purposely avoid that
to avoid stimulating out of control growth. So if you're listening to this and you're not an athlete,
so many are like most of us, you're just your sport is life at this point, you exercise mainly to,
you know, help you perform through life better as opposed to playing the NFL.
It's relatively easy to avoid the twisting injuries, but it's these repetitive strain
injuries, you know, the person who's riding the bike that doesn't have their pedals and their
cleats fully attuned correctly or they're running, but they're doing it so inefficiently or
God, I see people that ride, you know, spend hours on ellipticals and their hips are jacked
because they're just in a lousy position. Is that the case or is that just my bias that I see towards
it? I mean, are you still seeing people our age that show up? Like, is it just as common to see
the guy who's playing pickup basketball and still tears his ACL through a torsional injury?
No, I share your bias. I do think people exercise incorrectly and I think part of it is because
there seems to be such an emphasis on volume of exercise and the volume of exercise and intensity
or not intensity, but getting in your volume of exercise within an hour because of your sedentary
lifestyle for the other 23. I think that is what leads people to injury. They do too much repetition
with poor form, like you're saying, exposing themselves to injury. So there's no question
that repetitive bad form will lead to injury. And especially under load. Correct. And then if
you have a torsional, if you just happen to be playing hoops and you happen to put your foot
down on a wet piece of turf or on someone's ankle and your knee twists, I mean, those are sort of
freak accidents that can occur at any point. And if you want to keep it as safe as possible and as
helpful as possible, then you should walk. I mean, walking will give you the cardiovascular benefits
that most exercises, most any other exercise will. I think the Harvard School of Public Health
has done an awful lot of work at looking at walking and cardiovascular risk and near 30 to 40% risk
reduction with walking. Yeah, I mean, you won't find many people that are more critical of the
Harvard School of Public Health. It's a little school back east. I don't know the answer. My
intuition is that those studies are so biased by the people who have the luxury of being able to
walk. Like in other words, there may be too many healthy user biases within those studies.
I think unfortunately to get to do long term clinical trials with randomization here is going
to pose a huge problem. It's not going to happen. So we are stuck with I think some combination of
short term clinical studies that can show us measurable changes in short terms coupled with
I think trying to do better epidemiology, which is that's sort of like saying trying to make
toilet water taste a little bit better. But yeah, I think I struggle with this. I mean,
yeah, my view is and again, it's so unlike me to say this because it's so sort of hand wavy
bullshitty. But I really do think that there is the less time you are sitting around the better.
And I think in part it's not just the benefit you get from walking around. It's the damage that's
done by shortening the hamstrings, by tightening the so and the hip flexors like that stuff starts
to translate into these other things that set you up for orthopedic failure when you actually
are doing your one hour of activity or whatever it is.
Very well put. So when you have, again, primarily sedentary life, but you're trying to make up for
that with one hour of exercise or two hours of exercise, I think that's the setup that leads
people to injury. Yet people have jobs and families to provide for and they are sitting
around and so then how can you get a moving more consistently through the day? I do think that that
sort of consistent movement is what leads to better orthopedic musculoskeletal health. And it's not
necessarily having to do an hour of exercise a day. I think it's more generalized movement for
the majority of hours of the day. So I couldn't agree with you more. And I don't want to get into
a thing with you of all people about any sort of epidemiologic study, but I don't see a lot of
patients coming to me who've injured themselves walking. And I do see a lot.
Oh, yeah, no, that I totally agree with. I think my question is, I guess I'm not at a point yet
where I know enough, even though this is a very high priority for me to understand this, can
walking be sufficient from a cardiovascular standpoint? In other words, if you told somebody
all you got to do is lift weights and walk, but you can skip any of the high intensity training.
You can skip doing your Tabata's and med ball slams or, you know, Peloton stuff like that.
There's like a type of exercise that's still in the middle of those. I'm still trying to,
I think, come to grips with what the relative physiologic benefits are. Because the way I think
about exercise and like all things, there's a Venn diagram, but there are certain exercises
that we are doing where the emphasis is on the exoskeleton. So maintaining muscle mass,
maintaining functional movement, maintaining bone density and doing so free of pain. And then there
are some aspects of exercise, as you alluded to, where really what we're doing is talking about
physiologic benefits. We're talking about what it's doing to the microvascular, what it's
potentially doing to the mitochondria, what it's doing with other hormones, for example,
BDNF and the role that that plays in the brain. I mean, that I think you can make a pretty
compelling case that there is no intervention that has shown a larger impact in mitigating
cognitive decline than exercise. And all avenues seem to flow through BDNF and increased microvascular
composure. So those are kind of like what I put in this sort of exercise to reduce the risk of
disease versus exercise to increase health span. And then of course, the sweet spot is when they
overlap. But then the question is where do they not? This is actually probably the thing I think
about the most in my free time. Is that pretty good question? Yeah. So I try and ask the
octogenarians that I see in my practice who look like they're in pretty good health, who get around
pretty well. And you know, what's the secret? I ask as many of the older people as I can,
what's the secret? How'd you do it? And totally see you doing this. And, you know, commonly,
they not saying some people say, I have been working out every single day of my life.
Some people say I make all my meals. Some people say I just go for a walk. And there's probably
such a, you know, everybody probably has their fingerprint or their metabolic foot fingerprint
that for some people walking is sufficient for some people, it's high intensity intervals that
would be sufficient to extend the life. Yeah, and it's probably a function of what's their sleep
like? What's their act? What's their nutrition like? And so it becomes such a, you know, huge
variable equation that you're trying to solve that I'm not sure it's ever going to be solved.
I hope it can be. But I do give the advice to patients, because I see a lot of injuries from
people trying to overdo it. That I mean, it really is important to start in increments when you're
just starting, it's very difficult to go from zero to 60 without exposing yourself to injury,
unless you are 20 years old. Yeah, that's an important point. I want to come back to the
joint stuff. But I, my patients will, they're pretty tired of hearing me say this, but I always
say sort of rule number one of exercises, you can't get injured. Right. Because if you get injured,
then you know, we're taking 10 steps backwards. I don't want to put you on the spot, because this
is a question that I should have asked you earlier to let you think about it. But top five exercise,
bad moves that end up coming into your clinic for adults. Let's let's take the let's not talk about
the high school and college kids who are doing crazy sports. But so probably the most common
thing I see is knee pain and knee swelling from excessive squats and lunges. And I understand the
core benefits and the quad benefits of doing squats and lunges. But like I said, it puts a lot of
strain on the knee. And some knees just aren't ready to absorb that strain or don't have enough
cartilage to absorb that strain or most commonly don't have enough muscle to absorb that strain.
And so they come in with an overloaded joint that's swollen, injured, and that
articular cartilage has been put under too much pressure and it might be failing.
And you get the sense that they're too anterior when they do these things, especially on the
lunges. I mean, the technique for a lunge is actually so counterintuitive, because really a
lunge, the front knee should be under no load. The front leg should be all glute based loading.
And my guess is if you're if you don't know that and you don't have a trainer who can put you in
the correct position, you end up being too far forward, you're going to load that knee. Is that
what you think is happening without a doubt? So and they come in with an overloaded knee
and knee pain from not using their glutes from overly relying on their quadriceps. And I mean,
look, most of the trainers in our area are kids who like to lift weights and they have their
clients. And so I mean, it's really important like you're alluding to, to have a trainer who knows
what they're doing, because it makes all the difference in the world. But I see a lot of
patients for having trouble with their knees from repetitive squats and lunges that are again,
probably done with poor form, which is what we were talking about earlier about repetitive
injuries being a result of poor form. And then I see patients with shoulder injuries using weights,
and again, being in significantly disadvantaged positions. And you know, when you're using weights,
you're you're trying to the ultimate weight training would be to activate the muscle without
loading the joint. And you can do that you can activate the muscle and not load the joint when
you use very light weights, but enough weight that the muscle gets challenged to just even the most
minor degree because once it's challenged, you can then over flex that muscle, you can voluntarily
flex the muscle beyond. So you need just enough weight to initiate the muscle activation and
contraction. And that's usually not very much at all. And then the joints not being loaded,
the muscles being activated, and you're getting a much safer workout.
Do most shoulder injuries occur from loading the shoulder above the plane of the neck? In other
words, an overhead type resistance? I think so. I mean, I can't say for certain, I'm not sure anyone
can, but it seems that most people when they come in with shoulder pain will have commented that the
biggest problem has been that they're having trouble with overhead, you know, they were doing
an overhead press, and it's usually a press over a pole, it seems like the bench pressing the
military pressing the inclines are causing a little bit more trouble than for instance, the pull downs
and the bench rows. So I think the, again, the joint load is much higher when you're doing a press
compared to a pole. So when patients are recovering from shoulder injuries or have sustained a
shoulder injury, I sort of generic advice sort of take home advice is, you know, try and emphasize
more of the poles and the presses as you're recovering. So what are the most common injuries
you're seeing for elbows, wrists, hips, ankles, that kind of stuff? So elbows and wrists are
typically tendinopathies, again, tendon overload, tendon inflammatory injuries. And I'm not sure
whether they happen because of inflammatory changes, just biologic and age related changes,
blood flow related changes. So around the elbow in the 40s and 50s, I see, you know,
endless it seems like epicondylitis, which is tendonitis around the forearm muscles that flex
your wrist and straighten your hand or bend your wrist and curl your hand. And those tendinopathies,
whether they currently wrist, the shoulder, the elbow, the knee, the ankle, I'm absolutely certain
have the same biologic mechanism. And I do think the blood flow to these tendons as they decline
between the fourth and fifth decade of life, that loss of blood flow, that loss of reparative
mechanism is what leads to this sort of, again, uniform biologic problem in these very joints.
So I don't consider elbow lateral epicondylitis or tennis elbow, golfer's elbow that much different
from shoulder tendonitis or impingement or that much different from patella tendonitis or achilles
tendonitis. From a biologic standpoint, I'm pretty certain they're exactly the same thing.
And I think, again, the common pathway is probably loss of microvascular to the tendons.
What about ankles?
Well, ankles. So ankles, again, it's usually the achilles tendon. That's the key to the foot.
It's the achilles tendon. That's the key with the foot. The most common sort of acquired
problem is poster tubialis tendon deficiency where there's attenuation and stretch of the
poster tubialis tendon. And that's the tendon that supports the arch. And over time, that
just starts getting stretched out, as you can imagine. It's a mechanical issue. And unless it
can keep itself in prime shape, it's going to stretch out over time just due to the forces that
it's under. And when it does, the foot starts changing shape. The foot starts changing how it
loads. And pain is the most frequent presenting problem with a poster tubialis tendon deficiency.
And you can help support that with orthotics. There are some very complex foot reconstructions
that can be done to help reconstruct the foot in such a way that the poster tubialis tendon isn't
playing as much of a role. But you know, those are difficult reconstructions to undergo. You're
non-weight bearing for six weeks strictly, and then gradually weight bearing. You're taking a
big chunk out of your life. And you're definitely knocking yourself down to build yourself back up
again. And whenever you do that, there's always a risk that you knock yourself down and you don't
bounce. That's the problem with a lot of the surgeries that we do is that we do set people
back. And not every single person is going to bounce back better than what they started. And
that's sort of the challenge and the difficulty. And what about the hip? It's a simpler joint in
the sense that it's a ball and socket. So it tends to just wear down, not to oversimplify it. Now,
there are some muscles around the hip that act like that we're much more familiar with because of
the accessibility of it, like the rotator cuff. So a lot of the abductor muscles around the hip
can act like a rotator cuff does in the shoulder. But because of the, again, the weight bearing
nature of the hip, the congruency of the hip, it tends to just wear down and that labral cartilage,
which is the soft cartilage of the hip can get frayed, but it's the articular cartilage that
really makes a difference. Now, there are some conditions around the hip that we can change the
natural history to. It seems that we can, where we can reshape the hip a bit so it's not banging
into itself as much. That's called femoracetabular impingement. And that seems to be a place where
we can make a difference in terms of long-term outcomes of those patients by reshaping the hip
to some degree. And, you know, labral tears, I think the jury's out a bit. It strikes me as one
of those things that's sort of a little bit like lumbar disc herniation where someone can have hip
pain. You do an MRI, they've got a labral tear. You're no further ahead than you were before. You
don't know if that's the cause, right? You're exactly right. So you and I can go on an MRI scan
and both of our hips are incredibly likely, 90% likely to have labral tearing on MR. And you put
a 20 year old in there and it's not 90%, but it's about 80%. So the odds are that high, it's very
high. So you're going to see some sort of labral malady on an MRI and nearly everybody put in. So
then you're basically right where you started from. You don't know much more than what you did.
So a lot of people will be given the test of time. They'll be put into physical therapy.
They'll see if this remains an issue. And for those people who fall out, then some type of
correction can be helpful. But again, you know, our experience with the meniscus is kind of a
good example of that where, you know, having a meniscus injury on MRI is essentially, you know,
in a 40 or 50 year old isn't very meaningful. It's much more meaningful that if you suspect
there's a meniscus that the patient hasn't been able to sort of write it on their own. They haven't
been able to use physical therapy or time to their advantage to get their knee right. And then those
people will typically benefit a lot from a procedure. Let's talk about this in a little bit
more detail. So this is still a kind of controversial area or is the controversy within the, you know,
esteemed orthopedic surgery community no longer a controversy, but it's taking a while to trickle
down to the rest of us. So no, I mean, it's a funny topic. So Gina Colada wrote that article
about how surgeons are addicted to use the surgery. I don't know if you saw that. Oh, I saw it. I mean,
I'm going to reserve my comments. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, that's fine. But she's a little
off base on this one in particular. It's not the only thing she's off base on. Right, right, right.
So there was a paper that my buddy did. He said, watch you Rob Brophy. He's a very accomplished
researcher and he's great surgeon, great doc. And they did a study that was published in the New
England Journal regarding physical therapy versus surgery for meniscus tears. And the punch line
was that there's no difference between physical therapy and surgery. And so Gina Colada interprets
that as, hey, it doesn't matter whether you do surgery or therapy. So why are we doing surgery
at all? We should just do therapy for everybody. Well, turns out in one of the arms of the physical
therapy group, there was a crossover to surgery for those patients who weren't getting better,
but it was an intention to treat models. So they were still counted. They were still counted. Yep.
They were still counted as physical therapy. So the take home message of the study wasn't,
hey, it doesn't matter if you do therapy or surgery, it'll end up in the same place.
It's more, hey, look, it's reasonable to try. It's reasonable to try both. Just to start with
physical therapy and start conservatively, but don't, you know, there are a subset of patients
that will benefit from crossing over. That's exactly right. That's exactly the message. And
that's exactly what I tell my patients. They look, you have a meniscus injury. Odds are,
it's probably going to get better with therapy and time and you should play those odds. If however,
the odds aren't in your favor and you start having pain or you continue that pain and you're
not getting any better in a month, it's go up your knee, take care of your meniscus.
What year was that paper? That was pretty recent. 2016. Yeah. Okay. We'll make sure we link to that
paper because I think it'll be good for people to see it. Again, we can go back and look, but do
you remember off the top of your head or even, nevermind that, just clinically, what do you say
to patients is how long a period of time do you want to give them on the conservative approach
before you cross over? So I usually give about a month or two, but when patients come in a month
later saying, yeah, I'm feeling a little better. I'll keep riding it out. Right. And even though
they might be just feeling a little better, there are other people coming a month later,
feel a lot better. I remember working with John Healy, who was an orthopedic oncologist at
Sloan Kettering. And I mean, he's really taking care of some very, very sick patients with
osteosarcomas, chondrosarcomas, they're younger, they're older, and he's an amazing doctor,
an amazing surgeon. And he once made a comment about people scoping for dollars. And I hate to
think that that happens, but there's no question that it happens. None of us like to think we're
the ones doing it. But the fact of the matter is that it has to happen. There has to be some
pressures for people to feel like, you know, that arthroscopy is the right thing to do,
even though the data is pretty clear that someone walking in your office with a degenerative
meniscus tear probably shouldn't be scoped as a first line of treatment. And so I don't know
what's motivating that person, whether their past experience of their getting better, which is again,
tainted by the fact that they were probably going to get better whether you did surgery or not.
So that idea of doing useless surgery, the fact is, I see where it comes from. Because we kind of as
a as a group can dig our own hole by making these decisions that are whether consciously or not,
are being influenced by outside factors. I think this is a really interesting point in medicine.
And I struggle with this a lot when you're not a proceduralist, which I'm not, the stakes are a
little bit lower, and the opportunities are a bit lower. But I don't know if I told the story before,
but this was a moment when I had a realization. So so one of the things that a lot of people in my
type of practice do is they also sell drugs, meaning they can get a license to become a
pharmacy, basically, and they can sell anything that's sort of compounded, and it becomes another
profit center. So you can start to sell whatever it is that you would be prescribing to your
patients. So you get to make the money instead of sending them to a pharmacy. And on the surface,
that sounds okay. But the problem with that is, and I realized it one day when I was really on
the fence about two different therapies for a patient, and they were they're different,
but one of them is actually quite inexpensive. It's generic, it's basically a free drug. And then
the other one is not. Now I was sitting there really wrestling with which one to put them on,
because of the age of the patient and a few other factors, it really wasn't a clear cut case of which
to do. And I remember thinking, holy shit, if I were the one selling both of these, do I trust
myself enough that subconsciously I wouldn't lean towards the more expensive one, because
I would make $10 on the Nothing Burger one, and I'd make like $400 on the other one. And I thought
to myself, you know, don't be so sure. It's probably a good thing that you don't actually have to make
that you don't have to think about that. Because it's not to say that you're a bad doctor. If you
fall, I think that's human nature. Or a bad person. Yeah. And it's harder for you guys,
because you're proceduralists. Yes. You get judged on this. You get judged on, you know, by the people
like who write about medicine, who like to sort of expose the surgeons as doing things that are
unnecessary, or the $50,000 diabetic foot that was talked about with Obama. I mean, this stuff is just
so crazy. I mean, the fact of the matter is most, if not the highest percentage of doctors are really
looking out for the best interest of their patient. But they're human, like you said, and
they may be influenced by other factors that have nothing to do with the best interest of their
patient. One of the things about orthopedics that I think actually makes it a little easier if done
in the right setting, and I'm sure this was the case at HSS, is it's so multidisciplinary that
you have these physiatrists who aren't getting paid to operate, and yet they're still a part of
the team that's sort of saying, yeah, you know, this patient probably does do better with surgery.
And so I don't know how prevalent that sort of that model is, but I've been lucky every time I've
been evaluated for a pretty, what I consider at least significant orthopedic injury, I've had the
luxury of not just having to talk to a surgeon, not that I can't talk to a surgeon, but it's nice to
be able to balance that with taking one layer of bias away. I think that's a great point. Not
easy to find, though. I mean, a lot of people don't even know what the desire is. Exactly. Like HSS
is one of the places where you get lucky enough that you're going to be able to see a physiatrist.
Yeah, or non-operative sports medicine. That's something that's been very prevalent. You know,
labral injuries, you had a labral injury, correct? I have a right shoulder labral tear that, you know,
I was weeks away from seeing Alchek for surgery at HSS. What's happened with it? So I was getting a
massage with my bodywork guy, and you know, this thing had been dragging me down for probably been
four years from 09 to about 13. And it was just getting worse and worse. And it got to the point,
you know, it started when I was swimming marathons. And so it was anytime I swam longer than six
hours, the pain became really unbearable to which any person listening to this is like,
why are you, what? Who cares, right? Start swimming less than six hours. Okay. But the point is it
very quickly turned into if I swam two hours, it hurt. If it swam one hour, it hurt. Actually,
swimming just hurts constantly. And you know, you can do 50 pushups. Nope. You can only do 30
pushups. No, actually, you can't do one push up when it hit that point. So that was four years
after the initial injury. I, you know, I thought, okay, well, I gotta go do something about it. So
anyway, so you and I spoke and you basically said, look, these are basically your two best guys in
the country, right? I forget the Neil. Alchek and Neil Allatrache. I forgot to mention that Alchek
is also one of those mentors. Yeah. I mean, a superb guy, great surgeon. Well, that's why
ultimately, I was gonna go see Alchek because and also because I'm in New York, it was just easier
to do. So I'm seeing my guy and he's working on me and he said, you know, I know you have a
labral tear. I mean, I can read the MRI, but he goes, I actually don't think that's why you're,
I don't think that's why you're in so much pain. I actually think the pain is due to the fact that
the labral tear caused you to move differently. And over the past four years, you have changed
the way you use this arm. And now it's actually in your tricep, your deltoid, your subscapularis,
and your infraspinatus. And he said, you know, the recovery from the labral tear is going to be
brutal. It's you're in a sling for six weeks. You're not going to be swimming for nine months.
I mean, for you, that's a big compromise. He said, I think in six months with manual therapy and PT,
I can get you better. And I said, OK, let's give it a try. And within three months, I was at 80%
of baseline. And today I would say it's hard to say I'm 100% because I've also aged like I. So
you're dealing with the declining curve anyway. But I there's really nothing I can't do anymore,
like including like any number of push ups or, you know, sort of any activity. I have to be careful
with certain things. So one thing I've learned how to do correctly is when I do pull ups, which I love
doing, I never do a full dead hang without a scapular retraction. And so I'm always protecting
my shoulder. I don't do any overhead pressing activities. I do a lot of static overhead stuff.
But yeah, I consider that that along with the I.T. band injury I had that basically ended me from
riding a bike in medical school and almost ended me from riding a bike a second time. And I was
again right ready to have surgery on my I.T. band before this same guy was like, actually, it's not
really. I mean, yeah, your I.T. band is Jack, but it's because, you know, the real issue is your
glute meat and your TFL aren't firing correctly. And as a result of that, your vastus lateralis
and your quads are moving the I.T. band in an imbalanced way. And it was the same thing. I mean,
I think within two months I was better to have someone that skilled with evaluating balance and
musculoskeletal balance. They're few and far between. I don't claim to be one of them.
Yeah, these guys are gods. And I'll tell you just to give you the flip side of that story, of course,
this guy and now his protege really work with my patients. And that's, you know, so what I basically
do in my practice is try to find the people who are the best and just figure out a way to utilize
all of their time, you know, close down the rest of their practice. They now so. So. So Josh, who
now basically only sees my patients, you know, the flip side of that is I've sent patients there
where after one appointment, they say this guy needs a shoulder replacement, like clear as day,
like I could I could sit here and take a lot of money from this guy for the next six months and do
conservative therapy, but it's not going to work. And so I've always appreciated people who had the
ability from an out totally unbiased point of view. And that's working against his own invest interest.
The other thing that I will say against this, and this is just kind of me on my soapbox about how I
get a little pissed when people sort of say all surgeons are incentivized. You know, it's like,
you know, when you're a hammer, everything's a nail. Great surgeons aren't looking for business.
Right. Like the great practitioners are so overbooked. They don't have to do that. So, you know,
in the case of this guy, his name is Brian. Brian doesn't need any more patients. So it's easy for
him when I send him somebody who he thinks needs a shoulder replacement to say you need a shoulder
replacement. And similarly, like I actually sent a patient up to Stanford recently to get an aortic
root replacement, an aortic valve. And it was a huge operation. And he was a little reluctant to
do the surgery. And he said, you know, I'm a little worried because the surgeon says I need this
operation. But, you know, he's a surgeon. And I said, let me give you a little secret about this
surgeon. He's God. He doesn't need you. He he he has an infinite number of patients who need his help,
whether you are or are not one of them. So I promise you this guy's he doesn't make one more
or less dollar as a result of your existence. The recommendation to have surgery is because of the
physiology of your disease. But that said, I'm sympathetic to this. And I think it's I don't have
a good answer to it other than this sort of multidisciplinary approach. I think there's
something to be said when it's available to be able to be evaluated by more than one individual,
but that those individuals are working in your best interest, not their own. And that that doesn't
grow on trees. Yeah. Again, I like to think that most people in our profession are genuinely
working in the best interest of their patients. And again, I think it's the overwhelming majority
of physicians who do that, at least in my experience here. But there again, like you've
also mentioned, there are some unforeseen influences or unrecognized influences that
affect all of us because we are human and may be tainting our decisions in a way that
may not be fully within the best interest of the patients. So there are a lot of things in
orthopedic surgery now that are quite popular and they've become almost rampant. And I don't have
enough of a sense of their value. So for example, like PRP and stem cells, like let's talk about PRP
for a moment. So maybe just explain for someone who's listening to this who hasn't heard of it.
What is it? PRP is a super concentrated portion of your blood. It's a platelet rich plasma. And the
procedure itself is quite simple. We basically take a needle, put it in your vein, take some blood out,
and then put that tube of blood into a centrifuge. And the heavy portions of your blood go to the
bottom, the lighter portions go up top, the platelet rich plasma is typically in the middle. And you
take the platelet rich plasma and you inject it into a knee, a shoulder, a tendon for healing
purposes. And the idea is that the platelets are rich in healing factors and VEGF and platelet
derived growth factors so that you can stimulate and accelerate vascular endothelial growth factors.
So another one of these growth factors that would promote growth. So again, the idea being that you
can accelerate healing, you can take the body's natural healing responses and really supercharge
them to some degree or super concentrate them to some degree. So the studies about PRP are somewhat
imperfect because there's so many different commercial preparations of PRP and there's
sort of general categories. There's leukocyte rich PRP, so high in white cells, is leukocyte poor.
Those were deliberate design choices or those are just methodology differences? Yes,
yes, design choices. And then again, several different types of preparations for PRP. So
you're dealing with a very heterogeneous starting point. And so one PRP injection doesn't, isn't the
equivalent of another PRP injection. But it's hard to really know whether PRP is making a big
difference in tendinopathies most commonly. It doesn't seem to be regrowing articular cartilage
when you inject it into a knee or a shoulder or an ankle or hip. It may be helping to stimulate
tendon injury, but that's a very hard endpoint to measure because most of the time we're measuring
pain and function with that. And it might be getting better in the tendon because of the
injection itself and the veg F and the platelet-derived growth factors are doing exactly what you
are hoping that they're doing. Or it might be because there's a placebo effect or it might
be because you're resting because it's pretty sore after you get one of these injections. And
you know, again, you don't really know the answer why. But the studies seem to demonstrate that
PRP has a marginal benefit for tendinopathies. It's not a make or break, which is why not
everybody's running to get it, which is why the insurance companies aren't typically paying for it.
And the endpoint for tendinopathy is pain or function?
Pain and function.
And the placebos used in these are what?
Saline or they might be head to head of a cortisone or they might be head to head with,
if you're doing an intrarticular injection with the visco supplements, the hyaluronic acid
injections. And each of these has their own limits too, by the way, of their own efficacy.
One of the challenges with this space is it's so nascent. And if I were going to make the case that
PRP is better than the studies let on, and I'm not making that case because I actually don't know.
But if you believe that PRP is better than the studies suggest, you'd probably also believe that
the reason the studies are under finding benefit is that they're underpowered because of the
heterogeneity and approach and the inconsistency in patient selection. So I suspect that with all
new procedures, you know, if you had a crystal ball and you could look into the future in a decade,
you'd say, well, actually, we now know that like a third of the patients we did this on should have
never had it. And so now you've reduced your patient population to a more homogeneous,
because in medicine, it all comes down to the more homogeneous the population you can treat
and study, the better your outcomes are going to be. Now, in the end, we're all heterogeneous.
So yeah, the better your outcomes will be, but also the better your science will be.
Yes, that's my point. The better the science will lead to a better inference about who to do it.
But so it always makes me wonder, like we're still in the wild west of a lot of these things.
And I do wonder if, you know, will this stick around long enough to get rigorous enough to
actually understand what are the patients that are best suited for this procedure? And is there
a way to standardize and optimize really the preparations and the technique? And where do
you think if one out of 10 is when it's starting and 10 out of 10 is when it's fully dialed,
where are we? Probably three out of 10. And we're still I think there's a long way to go on the
biologics. But I mean, they are the most promising intuitive avenue to go down. How do you think
about it personally when you're treating patients? So patients ask me every day about stem cells and
PRP every single day. And I think the issue with stem cells is that we don't know why it works for
the people who it does work. But it doesn't seem to be working because it's regrowing their cartilage.
So that's the big issue. Now, it might be working as an anti-inflammatory, it might be working as a
placebo. And it turns out, as you're aware, the sort of the bigger the procedure, the better the
placebo effect. So the more you're digging, the more you're extracting, you are harnessing a larger
placebo effect. What is the placebo effect with that procedure? Is it viewed as about 15% benefit?
Because that's the all in typical placebo benefit. Yeah, I could have given you the number. I actually
don't know the number. But I think with stem cells, there is a lot of promise. And I hope it works,
because I'm going to need it myself. And we'll I'll need it. But right now, there are people who
I think are particularly in the orthopedic form, are taking advantage of the fact that we don't
have great treatments for arthritis, we don't have any reversal for arthritis, we have ways
of managing arthritis and maybe slowing down the pace of worsening arthritis. But we don't have
anything that reverses the course of arthritis, it turns your older knee into a younger knee,
your older hip into a younger hip. And the stem cells seems to be that sort of molecular fountain
of youth that people have glommed on to, they have this idea that they can regenerate their
hip, they can grow their native hip back to what it was when they were 20. And a lot of it, there is
promise in this, there's no question that there's promise in it. And the animal studies really
demonstrate it. But for instance, there's a local group that's doing stem cell injections here where
they take a bone marrow biops, a bone marrow aspirate from your posterior iliac crest, they take a
slurry of fat from from your abdomen, they take some PRP from your arm, they put it together, and
they inject it. And they charge five to $6,000 per for this procedure, cash. And talk about
incentives. I mean, they're highly incentivized to do this. And they will have patients come back to
them saying, I feel better. But again, there's no rigor. Are they feeling better because of the
placebo effect? Are they feeling better because there's an anti inflammatory effect, which you
can get with cortisone for 25 bucks? Or, you know, what's really the deal? But I don't think it's the
cartilage we're growing. And when they do those injections, those preparations, they're putting a
couple hundred stem cells in the studies that showed some benefit in rats and small animals.
It's about 10 to 20 million. So you know, we're orders of magnitude. Yeah, we're orders of
magnitude often. So I, and this is one story I do tell my patients as well. I had a woman who said,
I went to a stem cell talk, they offered a free steak dinner. And I listened to the clock, and I
decided to sign up for it. And I ended up paying $13,000 for three stem cell injections for the
steak. Right. Exactly. I'm like, how do you feel? And she's like, I feel a little better. And she's
like, what do you think? And I didn't have the heart to tell her, like you said, that she paid
$13,000 for a steak dinner. $13,000 or $1300? $13,000 for three stem cell injections. So these price
tags that come with it are so exorbitant. And I think there's some exploitation that's going on,
because again, we don't have the solutions. And it doesn't take a lot of anecdotes out in the community.
And I got this, I feel a little bit better. I feel better. I can do things I couldn't do.
And that's all great. But we don't know why you can't do the things that, why you now can do the
things you couldn't do. Is it because the stem cell is doing what is being advertised growing
new cartilage? Or is it because of an anti-inflammatory effect or a placebo effect?
Are there randomized trials going on looking at this?
Yeah. And most of the time they show some clinical subjective benefit, but again,
not a single radiograph or MRI showing rest, reconstituted cartilage.
And that's with not just PRP, but stem cells exclusively.
Correct.
There are RCTs that are ongoing.
There are randomized controlled trials. Now the randomization process might be a little bit.
Well, because I mean, this is the exact reason you actually have to have double-blinded.
Yes.
So these have to be complicated trials.
You're not doing this in Johnny's mind.
And again, there's nothing that's come through that says we should be doing this at this point.
I struggle with this. I get a lot of patients that ask me about this,
and I've had probably half a dozen patients that have had it done and swear by it. And
sort of like you, I have a hard time sort of having a straight conversation with them,
because deep down, I sort of think it's bullshit, frankly. But at the same time,
I'd like to think I have the humility to say I have no clue. And my first question is,
is it doing harm? And I say that specifically with the IV stem cells. So that's the one that
I'm most skeptical of. So question one is, what's the probability of harm?
And let's bracket harm as physical harm, financial harm. Like let's actually break this thing out.
And then we talk efficacy. In other words, you want to think about it through the lens that you
would think of drug development. Phase one, safety, phase two, efficacy, phase three, effectiveness.
I don't know. I hope that that level of rigor is being applied to this because I do feel really
bad. Like again, I don't know how wealthy your patient was that bought the $13,000 stake, but boy,
that would break my heart to think that that was a meaningful chunk of change to her.
Yeah. And in her case, she didn't get a big benefit. She felt a little bit better. And she
had a problem that pretty clear that it's a surgical issue. It's a surgical issue. But she
doesn't want any more surgery. She really wants to try everything prior to surgery. And so again,
the do no harm part is, again, I don't discourage when people ask, I just try to
steer them towards one of the academic medical centers where they are doing trials.
So that yes, they may get a placebo. Yes, they may get the stem cell, but they won't get fleeced.
And eventually we'll get an answer whether or not this is effective.
We talk about placebo effects, and particularly in orthopedics. There was a recent paper published
in the British JBGS, I think it was, regarding subacromal decompression, which is a very common
procedure used for shoulder pain, for shoulder tendonitis and impingement. And for patients who
don't have rotator cuff tearing, but have shoulder dysfunction and pain, traditionally,
subacromal decompressions have been a procedure of choice where you shave a little bit of the
undersurface of the acromion, remove the bursa, and allow for more space for the rotator cuff to
move. And it generally leads to pretty good outcomes as a result of the surgery seem to
be pretty good. Well, I was having dinner with a law professor at University of Chicago, Todd
Henderson. And the paper that was done looked at subacromal decompression versus sham surgery.
And there was no difference between the shams. Can you tell people what a sham surgery is?
Yeah, you make the incisions, you don't do anything. So, and you blind it to the, to the.
So it's a single blind, obviously the surgeon can't be blinded to a sham surgery.
Correct. But all the therapists and the patients, everyone downstream from the operating room is
blinded. And the results were the same between a sham surgery and the decompression, which would
speak to, you know, the decompression being worthless, except that both groups got better.
And so when both groups get better, his argument was the only ethical thing you can do as a surgeon
is to offer the sham surgery. The problem is, if you offer it as a sham, you might lose the benefit.
Right. So you can't do that. But then you are duping the patient, taking them to an operating
room for what they consider to be a procedure. That's a procedure when in fact.
Unless you explain to them that, look, the reason we would explain the equivalence of the sham to the
procedure is the post-operative care that you got. It's the PT, it's the, or it's some combination
of the rest, the post-operative. The forced rest from the surgery.
The forced rest and the forced PT, because you're going to take PT way more seriously
when you're in a sling and you've had surgery. Right. But then, so I will say that the patient
sometimes with meniscal injuries, Hey, let's cut out the middleman. It's probably the rest
and the therapy that's helping you. So why don't we do that? But you are also withdrawing the
placebo effect of the procedure. I would look what seems to be a placebo effect.
Now I do subacroma decompressions. I've done them and I probably will still do them because I,
yet the science, that's a reasonable study of randomizing patients and finding not much of a
difference. And so, and these studies have been done with meniscus.
How much better did the patients get? Do you recall what the absolute improvements were?
I don't know the absolute improvements. I don't recall.
Because that's the other thing that kind of has to be weighed into these things. I mean,
people who listen to this podcast have heard me sort of rant about the difference between absolute
and relative improvements and those things have to be.
Well, they're relative improvements by definition when you're doing shoulder surgery, but it is,
look, I, again, I thought that was a very interesting point. The most ethical thing you
can do is the sham surgery. Let's talk about what I consider the elephant in the room when it comes
to orthopedic injuries, which is lower back injuries. I, you, I don't, you probably remember
what happened to me. I totally remember what happened to you. You had a, you had a caught
Aquana. Yeah. I mean, I had that free fragment, the L5S1 free fragment stuck in the canal. I mean,
the whole thing was a disaster. I hate even talking about it. And then you got infected
afterwards too, right? I did have a little infection after. The bigger issue is that
he ropped around the wrong side. The first procedure he went, he did a left side.
I didn't know that.
It was a, or he, yeah, it was the left side of injury. He did a right side of decompression
and dinged the right side of nerves. So I came out with a right sided foot drop,
even though I went in with a left sided injury.
Fuck, I did not know that.
Yeah. Yeah. And had a bunch of redos. So it's something that's near and dear to my heart for
personal reasons. Cause I spent basically a year of my life recovering from a back injury,
three months of which I was debilitated, meaning I was, I couldn't move. My mom had to fly down
from Toronto to feed me. I mean, literally I couldn't even make a meal. And you know,
my roommate Matt was like, you know, he's still a med student. It's not like, you know,
he can sit there and feed me and wipe my ass. So yeah, I'm still partially sort of traumatized,
I think from that. But also I now realize that it was, and I've talked about this in the past,
it was the best worst thing that ever happened to me, right? It was the worst thing that ever
happened to me because it's just a year of being hooked on opiates and all this other crap that
comes with it. But it's also where you learn how to move again. And in many ways, I think
I feel very fortunate now that that happened to me when I was 27, 45 today. Never really had a
back issue ever since. Because it hurt for so long, I learned how to redo everything that you
wouldn't be able to relearn if you only had two weeks or a month of pain. So for example, like
I learned how to sneeze while protecting my back. I learned how to brush my teeth
while bracing myself over the counter so that I'm not just completely placing, you know,
a torque on my lower back by bending forward like little things. I remember a friend of mine
was over at my house and I was putting the dishes away and I put a fork in the thing and I did a
squat to bend down to put the fork in. And he's like, dude, what's wrong? Is your back hurting?
And I was like, no, it's exactly the opposite. My back doesn't hurt because I do this because I
never get caught picking up that piece of paper. Because so many people when they throw their
back out, quote unquote, throw their back out, it's usually the tiniest insult that does it.
It's not always the, well, I was doing the 400 pound deadlift, right? So that said, you can't go
far in life without running into a friend, a family member, a patient who's really suffering
from lower back pain. And I got to say, I'm not convinced that surgery is, there are clearly some
amazing cases. I've seen some spinal stenosis cases that, you know, the moment this patient
comes out of surgery, it's like, that's changed their life. But more often than not, I want to
say, and maybe I'm biased in my sampling, patients probably would get better without doing, you know,
a lumbar discectomy, for example. But again, that's now me speaking with a bias. I'm curious
as to your thoughts on this, even though I know you focus on joints and within the field of
orthopedic surgery, this is sort of like, it's a subspecialty. It's its own subspecialty of spine.
But, you know, look, you're, you know more than I do. So that's kind of go, if you go to an
ophthalmology conference, and you ask how many people do LASIK, most of the hands go up in the
air, and then how many would happen on themselves, most of the hands go down. If you go to an
orthopedic conference and ask how many people have done or would, or have done spine surgery, and
we've all done it, and we raise our hands, how many people would have it on themselves, and the hands
all go down. Because we see some of the very poor outcomes that can happen with spine surgery and
the difficulty that people can have with it. And low back pain is ubiquitous. It's the number one
reason people go to the doctor, not the orthopedist, but the doctor. And I didn't realize that.
Yeah. So it's the number one reason. And so when people have low back issues, there may be
mechanical issues, like you mentioned, a slipped disc, which the majority will resolve with time.
But when patients have neurologic compromise, weakness, there tends to be a greater urgency
to do something about it. Especially cervical, right? Correct. And because it can affect, you
know, people's balance, people's ability to walk, not just their hands. And I can show you,
I will show you, my friend Nick Horrigan moved to London and he was new to the area,
new to the healthcare system. And he calls me out of the blue. He's like, hey, they had,
and that's what you got, they had, I got a little problem here. And I got this disc and they're
telling me not to fly anywhere, not to go anywhere and have surgery on Monday. So I asked Nick to
send me the worst picture on the MRI that he could see. And he sends me the picture and he has
this massive disc herniation with signal within the spinal cord called myelomalacia, which means
that he's getting injury to his spinal cord and will lose neurologic function in short order.
And I said to Nick, Nick, do not fly like they told you. Do not go anywhere. You go into surgery
when they tell you to and sooner the better. And he underwent a successful cervical decompression
infusion. And he had a vertebraeectomy at the time and a big graft. And those type of spine
surgeries are life altering and life saving. And there are other spine surgeries where the
problem isn't so dramatic, but the intervention is so dramatic. And you've mentioned this to me
before you sort of introduced me to the concept of asymmetric risk, where, you know, when people
are functioning 70% and you do something as dramatic as a spine operation, you could take someone
from 70% to 90%. But you could also take someone from 70% to 20%. You can really drop them out
with a spine operation. And because it's your core, it's your axial skeleton. And if things go
awry there, they go awry for your entire body. If I have a shoulder surgery where I'm trying to take
someone who's 80% functional and make them as close to 100% as I can, I probably knock them down to
20%. And so again, if anything, they'll be a little bit worse or the same, but it's rare for
when you're working on the extremities to take someone way, way down like that can, but it's rare.
In the spine, it seems to happen more frequently. And again, you're taking people who are
reasonably functional, but not happily functional and trying to make them better.
And in the instances where you don't, you can make them all hell of a lot worse. And it's kind of why
I think joint replacement is such a successful subspecialty in orthopedics. You have people who
are 20 to 30% functional. They can't walk more than four or five blocks without pain. They have
pain all day long where they're sitting. None of the anti-inflammatories are working. Their life
is completely dominated by their hip or their knee pain. And you do a joint replacement and you make
them 70% functional. And they're the happiest people you're going to meet because you made
them from 20% functional to 70% functional. And you have an incredibly wide margin to improve them.
If you're in sports medicine where people are about 85% functional, I mean, you could do
everything except swim and do pushups, but you could do everything else in your life without pain.
And you're taking someone who's 80 to 85% functional, you're working with a very small margin.
And so it's harder to get the satisfaction that you can get.
Yeah, there's so much more downside than upside.
There's the potential. But again, because with the work that sports medicine surgeons do,
you rarely make someone from 80% to 20% yet in the spine because it's the spine,
you can take someone from 80% way down. So I think that's, I'm not sure if that's making sense.
No, it does make sense. What can people do? Obviously, you're my go-to guy for any orthopedic
question. I'm always calling you and I'm always sending you MRIs on my patients and stuff like
that. And you're always like, okay, what city is this person in? And you're always a phone call
away from the best person in that city, or if they're willing to go see the best person, period.
In that one case, we got really lucky that person had a foot injury, needed an ankle replacement,
and the best guy in the country happened to be one of your partners. So that's really nice.
But your connections through HSS has always been great. But the average person listening to this
doesn't get to call you up and doesn't get to say, Eric, here's my MRI, tell me what to do. So
it's hard to ask because if it's anybody that is your friend or family, you're going to be able to
do this for them. But if there's someone you can't help, but you want to give them the guiding
principles of how should they be screening orthopedic surgeons? What questions should
they be asking before some of the more common procedures? How would you navigate that?
Well, I think you alluded to it earlier with your friend who doesn't need the business or that
patient who is having the aortic root replacement. Volume does speak volumes. I mean, when surgeons
have high volumes, that's probably generally a good sign. Now, there are some surgeons who have
high volumes because they're scoping for dollars or other things. But in general, it's a reasonable
rule of thumb that they have a good volume. So let's talk about a couple procedures. If you're
getting your knee replaced, how you know, I and I, this is how when we were trying to find the best
surgeon to do my friend's aorta, this was a big question, right? It's like you don't want someone
who's doing one of these a month. So with a knee replacement, what do you consider the volume number
above what? Boy, I would want it to be 200 for a week, somewhere in that range. High volume is
considered, by the way, creating 30 in some of the studies, which is once every other week. But the
high really high volume guys are doing several a day. Wow. And so you're saying so someone who's
doing four of these a week, 200 a year, that's basically that should be all they're doing pretty
much right. They'll be doing that in hip replacement, you know, between four to 600 surgeries a year,
that's an incredibly high volume surgeon, those are the HSS type numbers. Yeah. You know, though,
those are the people who are going to be really at the top of the game again. And that already
introduces something interesting. You said if studies are considering anybody over 30 to be high
volume, you've already seen a great heterogeneity now in the studies, right? Because there's a huge
spread between 30 and 400. Right. So but I think the volume of cases that are done, obviously,
just asking around and seeing what other people's outcomes have been have been really helpful. And
you want to pick a surgeon who's not going to run from their complications, because we're all going
to have complications. And again, human nature does play a role. And, you know, no surgeon likes
complications. You don't feel good about yourself when your patient has a complication. It's one of
the most interesting dynamics between a patient and a physician because the patient feels horrible
because there's been a complication. The physician feels horrible because if they're even remotely
honest with themselves, they realize that something, whether it was entirely their fault
or some combination of things, something that they did led to this. And yet the natural tendency is to
run not because you want to abandon the patient, but because you can't stand facing the fact that
this happened. Well, there's a shame that's involved. I mean, when you have a complication,
you definitely feel completely responsible for it. And you know that shit happens, things happen.
But you feel responsible. It is your fault. I mean, you can't get around that. And you sometimes want
to cower away from it. And that is your first instinct to some degree to just, you know, bow
away from it. But obviously, when you're choosing a surgeon, everyone's had complications. And the
surgeon you want to have as someone who steps up when there is a complication, you know, we've
always been taught, you know, keep your patients close and your complications closer. And I try and
do that. I mean, I've had patients who've had infections, I've had patients who've had outcomes
that weren't expected. And they're the ones that I obviously remember the most, I can't help it,
there's an emotional component to it. But I try and be available in every possible way that I can
be both emotionally, being able to just call me text me directly. And I don't like to put barriers
between my patients in the beginning. But for anybody who's had a complication, I try to create
zero barriers, I try to make it as seamless as possible. So you want to have a surgeon who has
a reputation of, you know, being someone who will deal with complications. And I don't know how you
find that other. Because there's really those are two interesting traits, right? You're not going to
advertise your complications, right? Yeah. And it's something I think that patients have a hard time
asking physicians about. I don't have a hard time. You know, if I'm, when I'm talking to the cardiac
surgeon who was going to operate on my friend, I didn't have a hard time saying, All right, let's
talk about the complications. Like how many of your patients get AFib after surgery? How many
rebleed? How many redos? What's your 30 day mortality? But you know, I came from that world,
so I can talk in those terms. But for patients, is it okay to just say, Hey, what's your infection
rate? What's your re operate? What's boom, boom, boom? I think you absolutely should do that. I
mean, and the surgeon who can't answer those or doesn't want to, that's probably a harbinger of
something worse. I agree. I think most people with their salt welcome those questions are happy to
answer them. A surgeon who welcomes a second opinion. Yeah, please, by all means, I think
that's someone that, you know, you don't want someone who like, who shies away from having a
second opinion. I think that's a red flag for sure. So volume, the humility to answer questions
about complications, the willingness to participate and have second opinions. I mean, those are three
pretty good rules of thumb. Yeah, those, I mean, generally someone who's embracing those is concerned
more about your best interest than anything else is a concern about themselves and is more concerned
about your outcome, your best interest. But it looked choosing a surgeon is really difficult.
There's no metric. I mean, you can go into health grades and you'll see some of the people that
when we're in the know who we see operate who have great outcomes, who are gifted surgeons,
have terrible health. I feel like health grades should be taken away. I got to be honest with you.
I think there is no benefit to that service. And I, and I don't say that disparagingly about health
grades because I think they're doing anything wrong. I think it's a beautiful idea. I'm not sure
it translates into directing people to the people that they should do. It absolutely categorically
does not. It is a collection. You know, you're just going to, it's a bunch of extreme selection. Yes.
Great way of putting it. And it's like, well, my kids are huge fans of South Park and it reminds
me of the Alper special episode. But I know I'm pretty sure Alp. We'll link to that. I'm sure.
You should. It's unbelievable. But it's an imperfect, there's no perfect metric
for who's the best doctor. There's just like, you know, Tom Brady is drafted in the sixth round of
the NFL. And there are a lot of metrics for measuring athletic performance of how these
guys are going to do. And 32 teams made the same mistake six times over when Tom Brady was drafted
in 199. And they have 40 yard times. They have tons of film. They have, you know, pretty much
every metric you could want. And they still don't get it. Now let's take that in the medical world
where you don't have 40 times. You don't have how many times you can bench. You don't have any game
film. And it's in the best of circumstances, it's incredibly difficult to measure elite performance
or predict elite performance. And then you throw something in as complex as the medical world.
It's even more difficult. So it's very hard for patients to figure out how to select the best
surgeon. But then ultimately comes down to trust. I mean, I think again, there's a big trust element
and you have to trust that that person sitting across from you who is proposing to do a procedure
that's quite invasive, that you trust that they have your best interest, that they're going to do
a good job for you, that they're going to be there when you need them. And so there's a lot of
intuition that goes into it. I know that you're one of those surgeons who doesn't shy away from
the complications. And of course the irony of it is being so good, you have fewer of those
complications, but then you're kind of all in when they're there. I'm guessing the toughest
complications are the ones where they're occurring in people who have lost a non-trivial amount of
function when it's all said and done. Meaning, you know, it's one thing if, you know, God forbid you
have an infection and that means there's an extra two weeks where you need an antibiotic and you have
to be an inpatient and there's a bunch of inconvenience, but in the long run, it's going
to be the way it was before or better. But have you had those complications where either through the
complication or just the bad luck of the disease, they're worse than when they started. And they
can't do something that they could once do before. Yes. And it's very difficult. And it kind of leads
into something that I wanted to speak with you about and the idea of coping. And from a surgeon's
standpoint, when you have people who have complications, you still have the next person
who needs a similar procedure and you have to be able to cope with the fact that you had a
complication in one patient and move on to the next and do the best you can for them because you feel
it's the right thing. And that's not easy to do at all. For a patient who has a complication that
has left them with a deficit, coping becomes a big part of it. Our role as physicians is to help
patients adapt and cope with their new reality. And helping patients focus on what they're able
to do as opposed to what they're unable to do is a big part of helping them cope. And if you can
change the mindset, hey, from I no longer can do this because of the complication, I no longer can
do that because of the complication to I'm still capable of doing this, I want to do this, can I
do this more of a, again, focus on what you're capable of doing as opposed to incapable, then
I think you can help patients adapt to a new reality that again, there's a better acceptance
and a better way of coping. And it's not just complications. It's sometimes even without a
complication, you know, the natural history of the disease. Yeah, the natural history can be
just on a down slope and again, trying to help patients cope with that limitation. And again,
I think it's so critical to help people focus on what they're capable of doing as opposed to
incapable what they still have ahead of them as opposed to what they've lost from behind.
And again, it's very difficult. I mean, I've been, you've been in that situation when you've been
laid up and thinking about all the things you were unable to do. And now what you were able to
recapture, but some people don't recapture, but still have to look forward to what they're,
what they can do. And I kind of was exposed to this coping idea through the care of a family
member who has a form of cancer that requires ongoing treatment. And this family member through
this illness, I was exposed to a physician at Dana-Farber, one of the leading cancer centers,
who's a breast oncologist, Eric Weiner. And Dr. Weiner was the recipient of a lifetime achievement
award in breast cancer treatment. And he gave a lecture, it's the McGuire Memorial Lecture in
San Antonio in 2016, I believe 2016, December of 2016. And he talks about the state of breast
cancer and research and developments and reasons for hope and reasons for optimism. But he also,
for the last 15 minutes, he tells a very personal story about his own interactions with medicine and,
and what he feels his primary role is as a physician. And fundamentally believes it's
our role to help patients cope, whether it's with an illness, whether it's with an injury,
whether it's with a psychological, it's about coping and helping patients manage and helping
them continue to live their lives so that they focus on what they're capable of doing. Again,
he delivers it such a powerfully, and I don't want to spoil it. I really want people to listen to
this. I think everybody who wants to be a physician or is a physician should listen to it. I think
anybody who's receiving medical care has an ongoing issue should listen to this. It's an
incredibly inspiring message that he gives. And again, his own personal example is it's just,
it's tremendous. And his message is spot on. And so I see many patients who are in knee purgatory,
I call it, who aren't ready for joint replacement, who don't have a bad enough, aren't at that 20 to
30% point of dysfunction that they would benefit from a knee replacement, if they're sort of 60%
functional and you give them a knee replacement, they're 70% functional. They're not typically
happy with that because they have to go through hell to get it. So in that knee purgatory, sort of
60 to 70% functional, where we don't have a lot of options, it really is the emphasis on treatment
and management is on coping. Let's take an example of that. So the athlete who's in knee purgatory
probably can't run anymore. Yeah. Well, the athlete usually isn't in knee purgatory. It's usually
someone my age or above is in knee purgatory with a degenerative condition. Yeah, that's right.
I'm so used to calling patients athletes because I try to get this idea of like everyone's an athlete,
like you're an athlete when you're 90, you're an athlete for life. But yeah, I see your point. Okay,
so this person could be a 45 year old who's been athletic and all of a sudden now she just can't
run anymore. Like she, you know, she used to be able to run marathons and now the 5k trot with her
daughter at school is unbearable. Right. And then we don't have a lot of treatment options for that
person surgically and they are 45 years old. So you want to get them to 55 or 65 as we talked
about earlier. So I want to get them to a hundred. No, but yeah, no, no, I'm saying you want to get
them to there to do the joint replacement, but the long, long view is to get them to 100. You want to
get them to 100 and still mowing the lawn. Right. So coping is somewhat of managing the expectations
of what you will be capable of doing, but also not setting limits, allowing patients to try the
running and allow sort of the joint or their problem to limit them as opposed to you imposing
any artificial limits on them. So I draw a graph where I talk about thresholds and, and, you know,
above this threshold, if you're developing pain or swelling and below this threshold, you're not,
you want to be up against that threshold with your activity level as much as you can be.
And you can modulate your threshold. You can strengthen your leg. You can lose weight. Even
the person who weighs a hundred pounds and loses five pounds is going to benefit from weight loss
if they have a painful or extremity joint. Well, I'm glad you bring that up because I was going to
ask you about that and then we got off and I forgot about it. So even me, you know, I'm not overweight,
but if I lost 10 pounds, presumably it's going to be a little easier for me. Yeah. Things will feel
better. And I feel the same thing. I know when my knee, I almost know my weight by the pain of my
knee. I can gauge it that precisely because I know what weight I feel good and don't have pain and
what weight I don't. But there's typically a threshold. It's kind of a binary issue. And so
again, I try and get people to do what they can and then let them know that they can modulate
that threshold through effort. I mean, really through strengthening, through weight management
and through education. And the more you learn about your condition, your illness, your injury,
the better you'll be able to cope with it. Period. And what are some of those things that you will
recommend to those persons? So, you know, that 45 year old mother who's a star athlete, great runner,
probably played tennis in college, whatever. Do you say, if they keep hitting that threshold
so often, do you just say, look, I want you to try swimming or biking? Of course. Yeah. Yeah. And
again, if people are focusing on what they can do versus what they can't do. So if she's focused on
what, okay, I can swim and I can bike as opposed to I can't run anymore. That mindset makes a huge
difference in managing that and coping with that. And so helping to cultivate that mindset is a big
role of what we do in terms of, again, helping patients cope. It's not a biologic, it's not an
injection, it's not a cure, it's not a Jetsons approach to good health of being able to take
this pill and you're okay or take this injection, you're okay. And we're not pursuing the molecular
fountain of youth through this approach. But on the other hand, you can help people still live
better and move better if you can focus on what you're capable of doing as opposed to what you're
lost. Yeah. And this could be especially valuable if by switching to a different track,
you can slow the decline. You know, one of the fears that I have in that type of a patient is
they stop running because it just becomes simply too difficult, but they don't replace it with
something else. And all of a sudden they have a really precipitous decline in their physical
quality of life. Now, look, for a 45 year old to get sedentary doesn't mean that much. But by the
time they're 65, the difference between them having pivoted to a new sport or having done
nothing becomes enormous, especially for that woman because in five years she's going to go
through menopause and she's going to have another accelerator thrown onto it. And these are the
things that really, this is the problem that keeps me up at night. I was leaving my building
the other day, this was in New York and I came out and I saw a guy who I recognized because he's in
the building and he was in one of those sort of motorized scooters. And I was just coming back
from the gym and I was sort of running up the stairs because I live on the, you know, whatever
fourth floor. And there's a part of me that kind of felt guilty. I was like, God, I can't believe
like there's ever a day that I bitch about anything. When I just ran past a dude in his motorized
scooter and ran up the stairs and I thought, you know, he didn't look that old. He's probably 75,
truthfully, you know, maybe 80. But look, in today's world, you know, that's just not that old.
And yet he, you know, he has to get a doorman to hold the door open. He can't go through the
revolving door, not that going through a revolving door matters. But the point is like, I thought,
boy, once you get to that point, like, what would you give to go back in time if somebody says,
look, man, go back to when you're 45 and do these seven things different, you'll be on a different
trajectory there. And I wonder how much of it is this adaptability that you talk about, which is,
hey, you can't run. Great. You're going to learn how to ride a bike. Can't do that. That's fine.
You're going to learn to do X, Y, or Z. Or even again, changing the technique.
Oh, of course. Right. Right. And so whether it's barefoot running or getting analysis of some sort,
getting lighter on your feet, taking shorter strides, I mean, whatever it is that you lose
20 pounds. And right. And so aging is such a big part of what we treat in orthopedics. And we do a
tremendous job with traumatic injuries and the traumatic injuries that don't involve the joints.
Again, we do a terrific job with those. We can realign the bone. We can get the bone to heal.
We can get people's function restored. The injuries that involve the joints specifically into
the intraarticular portion of the knee or the hip, the ankle, or any of the joints. And we have a much
harder time. And those are the injuries that linger for a lifetime. So a long bone fracture
in the middle of femur, you'll pretty much recover from or in the middle of your tibia,
you'll pretty much recover from and not have much of a deficit, if any. But the moment you have an
intraarticular injury to the joint, it puts you on a different trajectory. And how to sort of
manage that trajectory and keep it as close to what it would have been had you not been injured
is obviously one of the goals and difficult to do. But then also when that trajectory prevents
people from doing what they want to do, having them focus on what they're still capable of doing,
I think will help them cope. Because if they keep thinking about the trajectory they were on
and compare that trajectory that they were on to the trajectory that they are currently on,
that can be a tremendous source of frustration. And so in the end, if they can just focus where
they are and realize what they're capable of doing, I think that's a big part of just preserving
health. And that fall must be bringing it back full circle to the guys in the NFL that you worked
with. That's got to be one of the greatest deltas between the former track of performance
and the current track when these guys retire. Well, you see all those horrible videos of like
Earl Campbell and these tremendous athletes who are aging so prematurely and so difficulty,
and they really have no quality of life. But you ask them if they do it all over again,
the majority of them will say yes. Yeah, it's so funny. I was actually just thinking about that
today on a totally different tangent, but I was in my hotel and there was a silent auction going
on and it was a picture of Muhammad Ali with the Beatles and I'm a big boxing fan. I remember,
I was up, so I go up my lobby, I'm shaving because I wanted to look good for you.
You do?
Thank you. And I remember thinking to myself, God, from about 1960 to 1980, Muhammad Ali had
about the most recognizable face on earth. You could argue that no athlete existed on a larger
stage than Muhammad Ali in those two decades. And yet in many ways he died very prematurely.
I mean, he died a few years ago, but given how magnificent his star was, all that he could have
continued to have done, his quality of life really began to decline precipitously in the mid 80s.
And I remember thinking to myself, so he was at his best from age 18 to 38. If someone waved to
magic one and said to me, you could have that life from age 18 to 38, but then it's going to
be a pretty quick decline. Would you take it? I guess for me, the answer is no, but I realized
that having never been there, I don't know what that high would actually be like, but I think
I'm just such a conservative person who's mostly optimizing on the back end of life. Perhaps that's
wrong, but it gave me a great sense of sadness to think about what would it have felt like to have
been Muhammad Ali when you were 60 and to realize that you were once the most gifted physical
specimen that ever walked the face of the earth. And now you couldn't tie your shoes. And similarly,
as you said, you look at these guys who are in their mid 50s, who were an enormous part of our
lives growing up watching football and now even ignoring the CTE issue, which is its own separate
tragedy, but just the orthopedic injury that I don't think gets enough attention. I mean, I think
CTE is very important. I'm so, I mean, nothing makes me happier than to see the attention that
is getting, but we don't see a lot of these guys whose brains are intact, but whose bodies are
destroyed. Yeah. And look, I'd never had a brightly lit star like that, but I played sports and I had
a great time doing it, but I'm carrying around the injuries now that I sustain then that aren't going
to go away and affected my quality of life and what I'm capable of doing. But I can't dwell on
what I wish I could be doing at age 50. I have to really focus on what I'm capable of doing now
and maximizing it and in essence, not giving a shit what gave up. And I have to say, even for
the sort of small time, good times that I had with athletics and where it's left me now,
I still want to trade it. And this is like the small time stuff because it led me to a group
of friends and a long list of memories that I wouldn't really trade for anything. So I guess
I would still make that deal. If I could take back that one cut that tour me sale, or if I can
take out that one jump that tour my rotator cuff, I mean, sure, I would do it. But if I had to give
up everything else, so I wasn't exposed to that risk to do, I don't think I'd do it. It makes sense.
And so it's a great question that you ask. I mean, I always admire the way you ask questions. You ask
the best questions. I remember one time you asked, I wonder what the first human being thought when
they ate an avocado. I don't even remember asking that. What was the context? Were we eating
avocados? No, you and Lynn were talking about health. And I think Lynn was talking about some
of the community health projects that she's doing. And you said, yeah, you know, I often think about
what the first human must have thought when he ate an avocado. I'm like, who the fuck thinks of these
questions? But these are great questions. And I actually just said this to my kids. I was like,
hey, the people who really make the world different aren't the people with all the answers,
they're the people with the questions. So, you know, think about some things that, you know,
how can I change this? What, why does it work this way? If you're asking the right questions,
you'll be making a difference. It's not necessarily that you have to have the right answers.
You always ask them. Great question. Speaking of questions, I will wrap this up because I'm
really excited that tonight is my first Yom Kippur break fast. I've only had a handful of these two,
by the way. When you told me that I had the opportunity to join you for that tonight, I
stopped eating a day and a half ago in anticipation of this. So normally, I would easily go 18, 24
hours without eating. But this time I'm going 36 hours because I just can't wait. Do I get to wear
a Yom Kippur by the way, or is that not cool? This is a non-Yom Kippur. It's a pretty low key. It's
my in-laws who are terrific. It's one of their very close friends who Lynn and I have become
friends with. She's been hosting it for the last, I think, eight, nine years that we've been here.
But they know I'm coming.
They do know you're coming, by the way. I did send an email saying,
I know this is not my place to invite a buddy, but can I invite a buddy? She's like,
of course. She's awesome. She's great. You'll enjoy it. I'm going to enjoy it. This is the first time
I've actually fasted for Yom Kippur and I haven't eaten since six o'clock last night, which is a
new for me. Fantastic. Isn't it amazing? It works. Yeah, it does. I feel pretty good.
Evolution at its finest. Last thing before we go, you alluded to it earlier and it's,
I can't believe we haven't given more lip service to it during this discussion, but
you introduced me to probably one of the three most important parlor tricks of my life,
which are the Dr. Bucks. How did you, and by the way, just for the listener, and we're going to
link to it, of course, it's Dr. Buck B-U-K-K. In medical school, you were walking around with the
Buck original. I became pretty obsessed. By the time I was in residency, I had at least five. I
had the Buck original, I had the cow catcher, I had the speed teeth. I still remember all of
these things. I think I had the gnarlies, but my Owen, our undersecretary of defense,
was the one who introduced me to the buck teeth. And I wish I could say I'd come up with it,
but Owen was the one who introduced me to it. Remember he had the bite in the styrofoam cup.
Oh my God.
Photo copy it, send it to him, and then you get your pair of bucks.
And back then, they were 40 bucks. I don't know what they cost today, but at the time,
for me to go low-
No, that was a massive chunk of change.
That was a huge chunk of change. When I was dropping, because I'd be buying multiple copies
of these. I wanted at least two of each of them, because I wanted to keep them everywhere. And
I don't know if you know this story, but when I got to residency,
this is kind of a ridiculous story. Makes me sound like I'm more of an idiot than I am.
I would wear the bucks everywhere. And I had convinced the entire pediatric tower at Hopkins,
which is called CMC, that there were two Dr. Attias.
The one with the good teeth.
The one with the bad. And we were twins. And when we were kids, our parents wanted us to get braces.
But Peter, me, I did. And my brother, I forget what his name was, Patrick, he didn't. We're
identical twins. We're the same in every way. We're both now doctors at Hopkins. But when you
page Dr. Attia, you got to be careful because you don't know which one's coming. It could be the
good teeth or the bad teeth one. And I was so egregious in my desire to do social experiments
with these things that the day I got to Hopkins, when we were doing orientation and filling out
our forms, I found the dental clinic. And I went in with my teeth and I said, Hey, I just, hi,
my name is Peter Attia. I'm the new dental fellow. Did you guys get my records? And you cannot
believe the discomfort in that room. Yeah. Because they're so real, right? Like they're so,
like if you're listening to this and you are even half curious what we're talking to,
sight unseen, just go buy a bunch of bucks. And I don't think you could be more amused for 40 bucks.
No. So you remember Ellen from medical school. Yeah. So she had a faux pas party. You might
have been there. I don't know if I can remember. I might've been too inebriated to remember it.
So I had the bucks in my pocket and I show up at her faux pas party and she's there. I said,
Hey, Ellen, we're in their kitchen. I take the milk out of the refrigerator and start drinking
from it. I put the milk back. I lift up my leg. I let one rip. And Ellen goes, it's a fashion
faux pas party. I'm like, Oh. So anyway, I had my bucks in later on and I was talking to someone
and I, you know, when you, when you flash the smile, you have to keep your lips pursed, but once
you flash the smile, the look on people's faces is priceless. And you taught me the look. Yeah.
You just, it's, it's the sort of shy koi. Yeah. And then you flash those teeth and oh my God,
Owen taught me the look. I have to say he's sort of the buck master. And then when I would take a
bite out of something like a piece of the ham, I purposely have pain. Oh God. And you know,
Oh, are you okay? Oh, I'm okay. And so Lynn was at the party and she goes, Oh Christ. She goes,
she goes, I overheard someone say, yeah, yeah, I saw him and he seemed okay. But then he smiled.
Oh, that's not the worst of it. He's at the dental school.
So I would, I got to the point where I would wear these, there was probably a three year period
where I wasn't not wearing them. I couldn't go more than 12 hours without putting them on.
And it drove everybody in my life nuts. Yeah. Because the very first time I met my wife's
father and grandmother and brother and sister was at like Easter, you know, one year, right? Or
whatever. Like after we'd been dating for six months or something like that. And as we're
driving over there, she's begging me. She says, please, Peter, I know you want to put the teeth
in, but just don't. And I was like, look, Jill, you got to let me be me. Like you got to let me
be me. I got to put the teeth in. And she's just, she's like, fine. I'm not even going to,
I'm not even going to acknowledge it. So we get there, put the teeth in. And her dad is a really
shy. He can't make eye contact with me. Like he gets one glimpse of this and he is in pure discomfort.
He's just, oh, uh, uh, you know, like not looking me in the eye and trying to talk to me. And it's
super awkward. So we're sitting down to dinner. They're still in and it's artichoke is the
appetizer. And her grandmother's legendary Italian grandmother makes these amazing artichokes.
And she's unfazed by my buffoonery. She just, she just, it hasn't registered that it is that
unusual. And so she picks up a big leaf out the artichoke and she goes, look, Peter, this is how
you do it. And she yanks it out with her teeth. And I'm like, oh, I got it. Okay. Let me do that.
And her dad at this point is under, like he's beside himself in discomfort.
I had a joke containing, how did she not like spill the beans?
Well, because at this point we've been dating six months, she had seen every minute of it every day.
Like she just like, this was like, it was more just annoyance with this. And then her brother
figures it out and he can't take it. So he gets up and walks away and he's laughing. And then
finally, like I decide, she says, look, she pulls me aside and she goes, you're not leaving here
without coming clean. So you can do it on your own terms, but you're coming clean before we leave.
So I do. And her grandmother says what everybody has said when I come clean, which is, yeah,
we couldn't understand how your parents had the money to help you go to college and loss or
whatever medical school, but you never got braces. Oh, okay. It makes more sense now.
You remember Carlos Carvero?
Oh, yeah.
I put the box in when he was my chief resident at UCSF, we were rounding in the ICU and
I was presenting a patient and he was in town a couple, like two years ago when he was telling
the story and goes, dude, I was looking at you with those fucking teeth. And I'm trying to
remember what you're saying about this patient, but I'm just focused on your fucking teeth. I'm
like, what's wrong with this guy? Anyway, they are an incredible, incredible device.
Yeah. Yeah. And so I remember when I was interviewing for residency, because that's
at the time that most I'd ever flown in my life because you were doing a round trip
every weekend, basically. And I it wasn't purely randomized, but I would just decide
on one leg of the trip with the teeth, one leg of the trip without the teeth. And I wanted to know
how I was treated differently. And I got to tell you, I was treated differently. When I walk around
without the teeth, the flight attendant was nice to me and she wanted to talk to me and blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah. When I had the teeth in, nobody, everyone was so uncomfortable around me and I
felt like a second class citizen. Oh, that's really well. Again, you ask all the good questions.
What's life like with the teeth? What's the people that we should do a second podcast just on the
teeth? Yeah, we should do it a video podcast. Yeah. Yeah, for sure. I also I would get to the
point where I I liked the way I talked with the teeth because you you you get a different talk.
You sort of have a funnier way of talking, which I love. Yeah. Your essays are a little bit more
prolonged. Yeah. Work around it. Yeah. And it got to the point where in residency I would wear them
during surgery under my mask, even though nobody could see it just because I liked the way I talked
with the teeth. And that's a little fucked up, but I love it. I never warm it. The best part of this
story is at my engagement dinner, which you were at, weren't you the night before the wedding? I mean,
you didn't get there in time. I don't think I was actually. Or not engagement. What's the night
before the rehearsal, rehearsal dinner? Yeah. The rehearsal dinner. The best part of it is
total surprise to me. Jill shows up with a set of teeth of her own. Yeah. And you know which one
she went with? No. Which were the funniest. Snaggle teeth. She went with you to man. Oh,
all one word. You know, the you to man. That's good. That's great. Yeah. For her.
Eric, thank you so much for setting aside three hours on a Wednesday afternoon or whatever it is
here to talk about this stuff. I know that, you know, for many people listening, we probably didn't
even scratch the surface of some of the really deep questions, but I also think that we gave
people probably a really good overview of this, this profession of yours, which is in many ways,
probably one of the few professions that deals disproportionately with health span versus
lifespan. So much of medicine is really geared towards how do you extend life? But orthopedics
is one of these professions that certainly disproportionately thinks about how do you maintain
that quality of life. And you know, I wish everybody could be lucky enough to have an
orthopedic surgeon like you. My hope is that unfortunately that while that's not likely or
real, you've given people some metrics by which they can at least evaluate for their own doctor.
No, hey, Peter, thank you. I love talking to you anytime. First time I've talked to you with
headphones and a microphone, but you know, we're very lucky to be able to do what we do. We have
a medical degree, we have a means of helping people, and we see a window into people's lives.
It's a very privileged view. And you know, you take that responsibility incredibly seriously.
I like to think I do as well. And I admire all the work that you do. You do incredible work for so
many people. And many of the principles that you have advocated over the years, we've adopted in
our practice to try and help people. And so your legacy and your tree spreads far and wide and
helping lots and lots of people. So I again, I have an incredible amount of gratitude to you
personally for how you've influenced my practice and my ability to help patients, again, cope with
their conditions and their injuries and live their life to the fullest. So it's a great opportunity,
a great privilege. And it's always great seeing you at any time. But thank you for allowing me
to share my perspective on my profession. Well, thank you, Eric. And that feeling is mutual.
My appreciation for you is as deep as yours is for me. Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode. You can also find my
blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com. What's a nerd safari you ask? Just click on the link at
the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively
non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting
papers I've read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the
obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing or other professional health care services, including
the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.