Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hey, everybody.
Welcome to this week's episode of the drive.
I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads on this podcast
and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support.
If you're listening to this, you probably already know.
The two things I care most about professionally are how to live longer and how to live better.
I have a complete fascination and obsession with this topic.
I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is basically
all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives.
Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy.
And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to me.
The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming.
I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information
with you.
To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own.
In fact, we now have a full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and the feedback
has mirrored this.
So all of this raises a natural question.
How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this?
As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads.
But after a lot of contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons.
Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you can trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being
paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it.
Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself.
I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for.
So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically.
So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can
work over time, and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest.
If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and support us at whatever level
works for you.
In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free.
It's that simple.
It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will
get back more than you give.
So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes, including
other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each episode.
These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many
of our shows.
Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me Anything
episodes.
That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to hear these
podcasts when they come out.
Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about, I want my supporters to get the best
deals possible on the products that I love.
And as I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to
do is work with companies who make the products that I already love and would already talk
about for free and have them pass savings on to you.
Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will find
enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for
members to support us at a level that makes sense for you.
I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen to this.
If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us directly
by signing up for a monthly subscription.
My guest this week is Francisco Gonzalez Lima, a professor of neuroscience and pharmacology
and toxicology at the University of Texas, Austin.
In this episode, we talk about Alzheimer's disease.
In particular, Francisco explains the vascular hypothesis of Alzheimer's disease, a hypothesis
that his colleague and collaborator at UT Austin, Jack Bellatorre, introduced to the
field about 25 years ago.
He makes the case that the central problem in late onset Alzheimer's disease is a progressive
neuronal energy crisis, meaning impaired blood flow to the brain and impaired mitochondrial
respiration.
If the problem is an energetic crisis, Francisco argues, then we can improve the supply of
energy and blood to the brain.
We could probably make progress in the prevention of Alzheimer's disease.
We of course get into great detail about all of this stuff.
To paraphrase my friend and my colleague, Richard Isaacson, who I've already spoken with on
the podcast a while back, as you may remember, and who directs the Alzheimer's Prevention
Clinic at Cornell, if you have a brain, you don't want to miss this episode.
So without further delay, here's my conversation with Francisco Gonzalez Lima.
Francisco, how are you?
Fine, thank you.
Thank you so much for making time to see me on a Friday afternoon.
My pleasure.
This is actually my first time to the university.
I've been to Austin many times, but I never seem to be north of downtown.
So it was beautiful to drive by the medical center on the way here.
It's kind of amazing.
I haven't even been to a football game, which I hope to one day do at some point.
So how long have you been in Austin?
I've been here as a tenure professor for 27 years.
Wow.
Yes.
And during that time, I started out in pharmacology and toxicology and moved to psychology, just
added that.
And the recruiting institution was the Institute for Neuroscience.
And now I'm a faculty also at the Department of Psychiatry at the New Medical School.
And we were talking a little bit earlier, you describe yourself as a behavioral neuroscientist.
Yes.
Tell me a little bit about what that title means, why behavioral.
My original training as a PhD was in anatomy and neurobiology.
And then as a postdoctoral fellow, I tried to understand how the brain related to behavior.
And I did that work as a Humboldt fellow in Germany.
And that was my introduction to the study of functional brain mapping and how we could
see behavioral functions reflected in brain activity.
This was the time where we developed the fluorodeoxyglucose autoradiographic method
in that German group in Drosstatt that later became the key to develop FTG PET, the first
functional imaging technique in humans.
It's interesting you say that because I noticed that a number of patients when I talk to them
don't understand sometimes the difference because I don't think physicians explain the
difference between functional studies and imaging studies.
And I remember feeling very fortunate in medical school during a radiology rotation where one
of the residents sat me down and explained the difference.
And the PET, of course, the FTG Positron Emission Tomography being a great example of a functional
study.
It's not giving you anatomic resolution, it's giving you functional resolution with respect
to glucose uptake.
And similarly, you now have functional MRI, which is doing the same sort of thing.
So yeah, that's a very important distinction.
Especially important if you want to be able to determine a disease in a very early stage
in which there are no structural changes in the brain that can be seen at least at the
microscopic level.
And having functional techniques, you are able to identify these functional changes
even before you have any other signs of the disease.
So I know you're a gentleman who has spent time all over the place.
You were born in Cuba, you left Cuba when you were quite young, you spent time in Costa
Rica, Venezuela.
I mean, where did you?
Puerto Rico.
And Puerto Rico, of course.
All of those things, at what point did it become clear to you that you were interested
in the brain?
I think my father was a veterinary doctor.
And originally my interests have to do with working with animals.
But soon I realized that an ever-system was so important for the entire health of the
animal and the behavior of the animal.
So I started to move away from just a more general interest to something that had to
do more with the brain.
But I would say my key influence happened as an undergraduate at Tulane University in
New Orleans.
When one of my professors, Dr. John King, dissected a brain in one of our classes,
and this was an undergraduate honors class.
And it was fascinating to me.
And I joined her lab to do an honors thesis working on the relationship between the brain,
hormones, and behavior in animal models.
It's so interesting.
I think back to my own time in medical school.
There were clearly a subset of my colleagues who were so captivated by the brain, which
in gross anatomy really doesn't depict a fraction of its brilliance, right?
Unlike the heart, where certainly microscopically there are things about the heart that are
relevant.
You can't see the Purkinje fibers.
You can't see the AV node or the SA node.
There's so much that is invisible to the naked eye.
But for the most part, you can appreciate the brilliance of the heart at the macroscopic
level.
There are other organs that, on the other end of the spectrum, get no attention like
the liver.
I mean, macroscopically, it's just a lump of whatever.
But of course, what's happening inside the liver to me makes it one of the most remarkable
organs.
But the brain is an organ that has such a unique look, right?
Grossly it looks so distinct.
The tissue looks so distinct from all of the other tissue outside of the central nervous
system.
And also, to this day, I would say our knowledge of the brain must be far, far behind that
of any other organ at the sort of physiologic signaling level.
I mean, is that a fair assumption?
Oh, yes.
I agree completely.
And I would say using the same analogies that you have, the heart, you can think of it as
a mechanical engineer, a pump, a hydraulic pump.
Because the brain is more of an electrical engineer where you have lots of circuits.
And the liver, for that matter, will be a chemical engineer where we break down all
of these substances that the body consumes.
I actually love that.
I've never thought of what you just said, and that is a great way to explain the different
types of engineering.
The kidney would be some sort of sanitation filtering engineer.
I mean, we could really...
Environmental.
Yeah.
And so in many ways, the brain is probably not only electrical engineering, but it's
computer science engineering.
There's so much going on there.
Right.
You hit in a very important point.
One cannot simply look at the brain the same way that you look at other organs.
Because of that circuit property, it allows the development of computational power.
So the brain uses the circuits, not just for communication, which is the most obvious
function, but to determine and compute outcomes that they are used to guide the other tissues
in the body.
For example, the musculoskeletal system cannot do anything on its own without the commands
that are the result of computations from the nervous system.
So all of our behavior results from how the nervous system process our experiences and
our current situations.
And it's become not in the same way as a computer works that is a serial device.
The brain is a very redundant parallel system where they have to be a lot of convergency
between different regions that are computing for that to be acknowledged as the way to
go in a behavioral point of view.
So for a person listening to this who might not have the luxury of knowing some of the
nuances about the brain that you do, when you're talking to an audience that is presumably
most people are interested in the brain because of brain pathology, it's, you know, once a
disease strikes the brain, everybody becomes well aware of how much it's doing because the
absence of that function leads to such an obvious downside.
How do you describe for people this notion of convergence and redundancy and overlap?
I mean, obviously there's a very strong evolutionary reason.
What are some examples of those and how those things are, these processes are preserved
in terms of, because you use, I like the use of, I'm an engineer, so I do like the use of
talking about serial versus parallel processing.
Maybe expand on that a little bit.
In reality, all of the anatomy is redundant and parallel.
At least, for example, we have bilateral symmetry, you know, everybody knows we have two hands,
two legs, two eyes.
We probably could have done it with one eye, but the way the system works is that it creates
redundancy.
And then, for example, the circulatory system is the same.
You have parallel blood vessels where you can get the blood from one point to another
in more than one way.
And of course, when you sit, when you put your elbow down, you can compress a blood
vessel, but there's still another route that can be used.
It's like coming from the university to the downtown area, you have many options to get
from one point to the other.
So in the brain, this is maximized to its extreme.
It's an organ specialized for this large amount of communications.
In other words, having so many highways and avenues where information can go through.
So in that sense, it differs from other organs where you have a pattern that repeats itself.
And the redundancy is only on that pattern.
Here in the brain, the redundancy is combined with the acquisition of new networks or circuit
auctions that are not possible if you only have one design.
So you have multiple designs.
If you want an analogy, for example, when NASA was sending the man to the moon, they
have like 100 computers doing the same computation.
And then they look at the output and they see which is the output that is repeated more
often.
And that's the one that those coordinates are the ones that they're going to pass on.
The brain uses that strategy.
And that's what I mean by convergency.
In other words, you have all of these multiple parallel system and they are doing these computations
but only the ones that converge on the same solutions are the ones that are acknowledged
and move on for the next stage.
When you look at other species beyond humans, how much of that redundancy do you see as
you go down the evolutionary chain or down the food chain maybe is an easier way to think
about it.
I mean, at what presumably chimps and cats and dogs are very similar, but is there a
point at which it very suddenly stops or does it simply diminish to the point where when
you're looking at a simpler organism like a worm, for example, I don't even know what
the nervous system of C. elegans looks like.
Well, definitely mammals and primates in particular where basic plan is the same.
And most of the differences have to do with which of the networks are more developed than
others.
So in primates, we have the cerebral cortex becoming the dominant component in the brain.
This is to a certain degree the same thing in all the mammals, but then other regions
of the brain have more similar contribution.
When you go down to, for example, reptiles or amphibians, the midbrain, the mesencephalon
is the largest part of the brain, not the portion where we have the cerebral cortex.
And what that means basically is in addition to this parallel processing that we have,
information goes through several hierarchical stages.
And at every one of these stages, similar processing is done and you add an additional
piece of information when you move it on.
For example, you can respond at the level of the spinal cord.
That will be the lowest level of response.
That would be, for example, a reflex.
Like if you tap somebody's knee, you transiently lengthen the patellar tendon, the knee kicks
out to straighten it or reduce the length.
And that is happening outside of the brain.
Yes.
However, when you tap the knee, the information also goes to all the levels of the nervous
system.
In that case, you saw the spinal reflex being manifested.
But the person still knows, they felt the sensation and they know what happened.
So the same was happening at different hierarchical level of processing.
So behaviorally speaking, when we respond to stimuli at very basic level, like what
you indicated, like the spinal level, we call it a reflex.
So that would be the most basic behavioral response.
But that means that you are not seeing what is happening at the other levels.
But for example, in a frog that is following an insect, a worm, as it's moving, the frog
would orient to the movement.
As long as the worm is moving in the same direction as the long axis of the body, you
have the same worm that is a fake worm where it's moving in a direction perpendicular to
the long axis.
It's long axis, yeah.
The frog will not follow.
So the pattern isn't recognized.
So if a frog sees a worm moving in the normal direction a worm moves, it knows that pattern.
If it sees the exact same food source standing up and walking on the side, it's not going
to pursue it.
It's not pursuing it.
So but in order to do that new computation, then you need the level of the midbrain.
So the midbrain becomes now the point our decision is made and with it to follow and
then eventually snap and capture the worm.
So the sub mammalian species primarily operate at that level and they have well defined.
Instead of being called a reflex, we would call this like release stimulus.
Release stimulus creates that generates a pattern.
There is a pattern generator that recognizes it.
But then in mammals, we have to move information to the level of the thalamus that is in the
middle of the brain, but higher than the midbrain.
And then from there, the majority of the mass of the brain is in primates and humans in
particular is in the cerebral cortex.
So we have to pass that information to the cerebral cortex and then feed that back down
to the output systems.
So it might be a way of oversimplifying, but one could think of it as the brainstem and
spinal cord are responsible for these reflexes.
For example, we breathe without thinking because our brainstem allows us to.
We recoil from pain without thought because of these things.
The midbrain took it up a notch by basically allowing for that stimulus response.
But the thalamus then becomes the gateway to the cortex where we can do this higher
processing.
That's probably an oversimplification.
And the main contribution of this thalamic cortical system is to allow us to inhibit
behavior.
In other words, not to respond in a more immediate short term matter.
So the ability to delay a response and to try to compute what are the consequences if
we were to make that response.
This is what really is brought up by our more elaborate cerebral cortex.
So the majority of the influence of the cerebral cortex on subcortical levels.
It's inhibitory.
It's not excitatory.
No, and engineers actually don't understand this very well.
When they, for example, try to create a prosthetic device to have somebody send neural impulses
to move a leg that is paralyzed, they try to create this as an excitatory type of phenomenon.
But what the brain is doing is not like that.
What the brain is doing is inhibiting all possible vectors of movement in a space and
then selectively releasing some of them by sending an inhibitory signal to that.
Yeah, it inhibits the inhibitory signal, thereby selectively, quote unquote, releasing activation.
Yes.
And when you do that, you have more control because you are actually for every movement.
You're not just working as a puppet or you're trying to only emulate those vectors.
You're controlling all of the other possibilities.
So you sort of curve a tunnel in a space which are the only vectors that are allowed
to be manifested.
So the engineering of the brain in this sense requires this more effort in order to achieve
something that could have been achieved by a more simplified system because it wants
that control.
So is it safe to say that more of the pathology that we see in the brain occurs in the cortex
than in the midbrain?
For example, Parkinson's, I guess, would be partially midbrain, right?
Primarily.
Yeah.
Are there great examples of common pathology in the brainstem?
Yes.
But from the point of view of dementia and neurodegenerative disorders with the exception
of Parkinson's disease, these are primarily cerebral cortex.
This is where you see, especially the initial functional deficits and later on the atrophy
and loss of tissue.
But most of the diseases of all age that affect the brain primarily target these cortical
regions.
And that's obviously the thing that I most wanted to chat with you about because you
and your colleagues, you have a different point of view on Alzheimer's disease.
And in many ways, it's when you read your work or hear you guys talk about it, it doesn't
sound that hard to believe.
It's actually quite a reasonable hypothesis.
Let's start with the conventional thinking on Alzheimer's disease, which needs to be
caveated with the fact that there is no disease for which we have had a greater failure in
our ability to treat it than this one.
Even cancer, which one could argue we're not exactly hitting it out of the park on,
we at least have some success.
We can point to very, very specific successes, not only in terms of prevention, for example,
simply the recognition that something like smoking could cause cancer led to an enormous
reduction and a continued enormous reduction in the onset of that disease, but also very
specific chemotherapeutic regiments for a subset of cancers, particularly liquid cancers.
And now more recently, we've seen some real breakthroughs with things like checkpoint
inhibitors on even solid organ tumors.
So at least with cancer, we have some sense of we're making progress.
Certainly with heart disease, we've probably made the most progress.
And yet with this disease, it appears we have not made a shred of progress.
What is the typical explanation for what causes Alzheimer's disease?
And therefore, by extension, what the path should be to prevent it or treat it.
You're completely right.
We have not made any significant progress in Alzheimer's disease research.
This is the largest failure of the biomedical research enterprise in the world during my
lifetime.
And the main reason is we have remained faithful to an initial observation that was done or
published at least in 1907 by Lois Alzheimer's that indicated that he saw these abnormal
depositions in the brains of an individual after that individual died.
This individual was 51 years old when he died.
But Alzheimer's was actually a psychiatrist, not an aeropathologist like it's pointed
out in books.
He worked in a psychiatric hospital.
It was part of the original group led by Crepling in Munich.
And they were studying mental illness.
And in those days, it was believed that what we call nowadays dementia was a form of mental
illness.
And he was surprised by this young patient that was showing these early signs of dementia,
you know, in his 50s.
And already by the time he died, that person had been suffering for many years.
So what Alzheimer's described as in the brain of that individual has Alzheimer's disease
is not the same disease that is happening in older people.
It is not the same disease that is the most common type of dementia.
And this has been the most basic misunderstanding from the beginning.
Historically, there was a competition between two groups, one in Prague, in Czech Republic
at that time was under German rule.
And Oscar Ficher published studies where, for example, he looked at 16 brains from patients
that had what was called senile dementia.
That is the type of dementia that was showing up in people after they were 60, 70, 80 years
of age, not these younger individuals.
And he described some of these same abnormalities that later that Alzheimer's published, but
for that single case.
However, Crepling was a rival of that group, especially about Ficher, who was Jewish and
so he published in the first book that talk about Alzheimer's, the first textbook of psychiatry
that was published by Crepling.
And then he say, oh, what we're seeing in these old people, this type of dementia is
what Alzheimer's described in that younger individual.
And from their own, there was a movement away from factors that were related to aging and
to say this is a disease that is invading somehow and it's not something that is building
up over the years.
Of course, this is actually not the case.
So nowadays they try to have a compromise and say Alzheimer's disease, there is early
onset or familial, which is primarily familial.
There's some evidence for inheritance, but nine out of 10 cases of what is referred to
as Alzheimer's disease, there is absolutely no inheritance or familial component, which
is one of the greatest fears of people when they have patients with dementia in their
family.
And not only that, it's aging related.
And because it develops very slowly over the decades, it provides an opportunity to intervene,
to determine what are the risk factors that are behind and to do an intervention.
If you take the other approach that this is a disease of these abnormal proteins and it
can happen early on, then you have a very different strategy.
So the whole field has been dominated primarily by what is called the amyloid beta hypothesis.
This hypothesis is completely, absolutely false.
It has no relationship whatsoever with what we see in the older people that develop dementia.
It has a relationship with some of these early cases that like the one that Alzheimer's
described and they have a familial component and that there is a somatic genetic component.
Let me just interrupt for a second to make sure I'm understanding.
This is obviously such an important point that I want to make sure I'm clear in that
the listener is clear.
Now, the case that Alzheimer's found in 1907, I have to assume that was a PSEN1 or 2 mutation.
That was what we now see accounting for less than 1% of Alzheimer's disease, but it is
probably the closest to a fully penetrant gene that results in Alzheimer's disease.
Has that ever been confirmed?
Are there any biologic specimens remaining from that particular individual who was so
young?
There are slides available, but it has never been confirmed.
The patient died in 1906 after many years with this chronic dementia in that hospital
in Munich.
He was deteriorated in every other respect.
By that time, he was unable to move and carry on activities of daily living.
He's been suffering from this for many years.
Which is not unlike what we can see in the rare patients that do have the PSEN1 or 2
gene, which is it can easily take hold in the 40s.
I unfortunately have a patient whose mother is debilitated in her mid-50s.
Now, it turns out she doesn't have the gene, which was a surprise to a lot of us, we assumed
because it had taken hold so early.
But the autopsy, the pathology that they could see, which at the time was limited to very
gross things relative to today.
Gross for the listener, I don't mean gross as in disgusting.
I mean gross as in visible through a microscope.
Was this the first time that amyloid beta was observed?
No, the first time was done by Oscar Fisher in the senile dimension.
So Alzheimer's was basically describing a phenotype, but without a pathologic explanation
or characteristic.
Yes, but because it was happening so early, then it moved the people away from the idea
that this has something to do with senility, with the older deterioration that happens
as a function of aging.
So they say, oh no, this can happen early on.
So aging cannot be a primary contributor.
So even though a very small percentage of people that are described as having Alzheimer's
belongs to this early onset, over 90% of the research is focused on that group.
And the reasoning is because it's the same disease, which is a false premise, if we find
out what's happening in the early onset and we model that in animals by doing this genetic
manipulation, then we can fix the more common senile, older age, late onset dimension.
And that false premise is what has been driving all of these failures.
Because yes, they have been able to detect genetic changes.
They can manipulate this.
I was able to work, examine the brain of the first amyloid precursor mouse model that was
developed.
And one of the first things that I noticed in the brains, even before there was any amyloid
deposition in that model that they had inserted, it was a transgenic mouse model.
They had taken away the native gene from the mouse and replaced that gene with one that
was abnormal for an patient with early onset Alzheimer's.
But even before that gene could start any observable deposition of amyloid, these brains
by that very manipulation were abnormal.
They had severe atrophy.
In for example, the corpus callosum, the bundle that communicates to hemisphere and the region
of the hippocampal formation has lost one third of its volume.
So the intervention itself may have altered the resilience, if nothing else, of the brain.
And of course, then these animals show all kinds of behavioral abnormalities.
But these things were happening even before there was any amyloid deposition.
So it was clear that having a gene with these abnormalities, even before you can see that
the product building up is enough to distort how the brain develops.
So this has been the main problem.
And because biology, just like when I started studying biology, my major was called cell
and molecular biology.
And that became the dominant orientation in biology.
So people who do this research oftentimes don't have a very good understanding of the
brain as a whole, and they just focus at that molecular level.
And in a way, they're trying to find the answer where the light is, that is the light that
they can use, and trying to ignore that this is really a disease of all age that involves
a long development, and that there is absolutely no correlation, no relationship between the
amount of, for example, amyloid beta deposition and the onset of memory deficits, cognitive
impairment, or the progression of the disease.
There are brains of individuals that I have the fortune to examine here in Austin, has
had primarily a neural anatomy, a functional neural anatomy, as I collaborated with neuropathologists
here.
And the brains of these people who were cognitively normal after they die, they couldn't deframe
shape them from the ones that were diagnosis Alzheimer's based on amyloid and neurofibular
retangle depositions.
That's an enormous statement.
It doesn't call into question the causality of amyloid, it just calls into it the necessity
and sufficiency of it.
In other words, it could be that you have to have, I mean, I'm making this up, but to
illustrate a point within logic, it could be that you need to have amyloid beta deposition.
To cause dementia, but that is not sufficient.
It is only a necessary condition and that you might need other factors to coalesce around
that the obvious example that comes to my mind is LDL and APO B, which is necessary
for cardiovascular disease, but not alone sufficient.
You still need an inflammatory response and an immune response.
I go beyond that point.
What I'm saying is against the dogma.
You're saying one step further than that.
You were saying that not only is the deposition of amyloid not correlated strongly enough,
it might not even be causally related.
Not not even, it is not causally related to what we call primarily Alzheimer's disease
with this majority of late onset.
That's not true for the early onset.
What I'm saying is that there are two different diseases.
The early onset, there is a role for this amyloid deposition.
You can demonstrate this.
In other words, if you take autopsies of 50-year-olds that die from heart disease, cancer, or accidental
death and you examine their brains relative to 50-year-olds who die from early onset dementia,
the relationship is more clear.
It is clear.
The amyloid beta is playing a causal role.
Yes, there is no question.
You can find the genetic mutations and you can induce it in the animal, but that's not
the case in the late onset.
The neuropathologists will tell you if they don't know what the clinical picture was,
they wouldn't be able to say that this was what they refer to as a probable Alzheimer's
disease.
When they see the sac to the same pathology and there's no evidence of cognitive deterioration,
they just diagnose that brain as possible Alzheimer's disease.
This created a circular definition.
To be clear, to close the loop on that analogy with heart disease, you would have to know
that there are cases where patients have significant dementia that by all other metrics is consistent
with Alzheimer's dementia and not Lewy body or something else and there is an absence
of amyloid beta deposition.
What percentage approximately, I know it's hard to know these things because we don't
always get autopsies, but in your experience, what percentage of patients who die with or
from Alzheimer's disease that is late onset do not have the histopathologic features of
amyloid beta?
The majority of patients that are diagnosed as Alzheimer's disease, pro-Alzheimer's disease
when they die have the same level.
It's not that they don't have because it's an age-related deposition.
The same levels of all the patients are comparable age and the only reason that they are labeled
as Alzheimer's is because they have the dementia.
The pathology cannot really tell them apart.
If you give these two pathologies blind to the medical diagnosis or clinical examination,
they won't be able to tell apart which are the ones that are actually demented and which
are not if you do it in a match.
There is a large degree of variability and pathologies are not quantitative.
Pathology is an approximation.
You look at only a few sections through the cortex and then you give a certain proportion
of the findings that you see as categories.
But even when I have done this personally, in 2001, we published in the journal Neuroscience
a study where we use brains from people who die from Alzheimer's.
The main difference from my study from what's been done before is that we were able to do
to obtain brains with only a few hours after the individuals had died.
We called a very small post-mortem interval and I was able to do this by collaborating
with the Institute in Arizona.
There is a city called Sun City, Arizona and they have a Sun City Health Center which actually
ascribes to these amyloid and neurofibular rectangle ideas.
But what we did with them was we traveled there and we, my PhD student, we collected
these brains, controlled brains and brains of people who have died of Alzheimer's.
Some of them we were able to collect them fresh right there.
And were you and your team also blinded to the circumstances of the death prior to the
autopsies being performed?
No.
What we did is we collected all the brains and I sectioned them into pieces and these
pieces were frozen and then one sample would remain there.
I see, I see.
So you did everything in parallel.
Yeah, we would be chipped here to Austin and once the samples were chipped, they were coded.
But when we were there, no, we knew when somebody died because I had a pathologist with me who
had to certify.
They were dead so that we could immediately.
But when the pairwise results were evaluated, the evaluator was blind to the clinical circumstances
of the patient's death?
Yes.
What we did in that study was we were not only interested in just looking at amyloid
plates and neurofibular rectangles being done, we were interested in seeing is there any
biochemical change that could account for this so-called hypometabolism, this decrease
in energy metabolism that is seen early in Alzheimer's?
Is it generally well regarded bringing it back to some of your earlier work in PET?
I assume it is generally agreed upon that patients who are in the stages of cognitive
decline have hypo-functioning metabolism.
So their PET scans show less glucose uptake in the brain.
Is that generally acknowledged?
And not only FTG PET, when you do also cerebral blood flow, you find the same.
When you do fMRI arterial spin labeling to look at blood flow, every technique that has
been used has demonstrated that first it was with mild Alzheimer's cases but more recently
also with the so-called mild cognitive impairment that nowadays also referred to as mild neurocognitive
disorder.
And in those cases there is hypometabolism and the hypometabolism is primarily not in
the regions that become atrophic later on in the disease like in the temporal lobe.
It's primarily in the posterior cingulate cortex, one region of the brain that is in
the medial part in the center of the brain.
This area is the one that you can see having earliest sign of hypometabolism.
And from a phenotypic standpoint, what does it control in the normal brain?
This region provides the major input to what is called the entorhinal cortex, which is
the part of the temporal lobe that then feeds into the hippocampal formation.
So what essentially is happening is you have a functional disconnection between the main
input to the entorhinal cortex.
The entorhinal cortex is the primary source of inputs to the hippocampal formation.
So when you functionally denervate a region in the brain, eventually that leads to atrophy
from the region that is receiving the stimulus.
It is receiving that.
Just like happens when you denervate a muscle in the periphery, there is a trophic action
and action that that region survives because it's being stimulated by the other one.
So people have missed when you study pathology, you don't study these functional changes and
you don't look at the system as a network of pathways or influence functionality.
You're seeing the end result.
What has happened after all of these processes are taking place over the years.
So by doing that, you cannot infer these other phenomena.
So if you take an animal like a mouse and you just take out the, it's the posterior cingulate?
The posterior cingulate.
If you lesion that in a rat or a mouse acutely, which is not the same as what's presumably
happening in this disease state, what is the immediate phenotype of that animal or behavior?
Well you don't have to lesion it.
You can functionally deactivate it, which is more similar to what is actually happening
in Alzheimer's.
It's not that this region is damaged structurally.
Right, it's just functionally not allowing the conduit.
Yeah, it's affecting the network that is providing the main input to the hippocampal
formation.
You get the same kind of memory deficits that are characteristic of the initial stages of
dementia.
And is that because of the role the hippocampus plays in the consolidation of memory or is
it to do more with the target in the temporal lobe?
It is because it's a network, not a single region.
In other words, for example, a long time ago in the 1930s there was a circuit that was
defined by an American neuroanatomy called James Pappas, also pronounced Pappas.
And he describes the connections between the cingulate cortex, this parahypocampal cortex
that we now primarily refer to as the endorhinal cortex.
And then from there to the hippocampal formation, from the hippocampal formation the main output
goes to a region called the mammillary bodies.
And then from the mammillary bodies it goes to the anterior part of the thalamus.
And then from the thalamus it fans out the projections back into the cingulate cortex.
So it creates a circle.
And this is often being referred to as the limbic circuit of Pappas.
And we know it has to do with emotional memory formation because events that have a large
emotional signature are the ones we store.
We create the greatest memories from them.
Yes.
So if you affect this system anywhere in this system, you get a memory disease and they
just have different names.
So for example, people that have chronic alcohol, they develop sometimes referred to
as Wernicke's Korsakov dementia, also known as Korsakov psychosis.
You can get this from B vitamin deficiencies as well.
B1 deficiency, thiamine deficiency in particular.
You look at the pathology of the brain, where is the damage?
The damage is primarily in the mammillary bodies.
So the mammillary bodies is the main output from the hypogempo formation.
So whatever the hypogempo formation is contributing, if you are knocking down its main output
target, you get the same thing.
Then in a second place is the hypogempo formation itself.
Then the entorhymic cortex and so on.
All you have damage in any part of the system.
There's also something called diencephalic retrograde amnesia that happens with thalamic
lesions.
This is when these lesions interfere with these anterior thalamic areas.
So really in order for us to see the memory problems that we have linked usually with
Alzheimer's dementia, you have to engage this system because that system is part of the
brain regions in which this is operating.
You use the term retrograde there.
For the listener, we should explain the difference between retrograde and antigrade amnesia.
I'll let you do that quickly, but of course my follow-up question will be in the earliest
stages of dementia, is the bigger issue the inability to form new short-term memories,
which would be a form of antigrade amnesia?
That would happen before the retrograde amnesia, which is later.
Let me explain.
In the early Alzheimer's disease, the main problem is not in this limbic circuit.
When that happens, when you can see the hypometabolism.
That's when you can see the behavioral changes in the individual as well.
But before that, in the prefrontal cortex, especially the lateral, we call dorsal lateral
prefrontal cortex, you have a functional deficit that is interfering with what we call working
memory.
So you can think of memories as having three modes or temporal stages, an immediate memory
mode where you can remember things for only a few seconds.
Tell me your phone number and I have to write it down.
That's the perfect example.
A clinician will do this by giving a string of numbers to people and people will be able
to remember approximately seven numbers.
So it is usually seven plus or minus two items.
And this is the reason why the telephone numbers have seven digits because most people
after reading seven digits, turning around to try to punch those numbers in the phone,
if they are more than seven, they drop some of them.
This is this immediate memory mode.
But for memories to happen, they have to move from this immediate memory mode to a more
recent memory mode.
So the immediate, the movement from immediate to recent is done by this prefrontal cortex.
So the initial deficit that you see in Alzheimer's and all of these types of dementia of all
age is in this more immediate memory mode.
And one way we refer to this is also working memory.
So for example, you come out of your house and you lock the door, but after a few seconds
you're working to your car, then you ask, did I lock the door or is it unlocked?
And then you have to go back and check.
So this is the first thing that you're going to have.
And it happens physiologically as a function of aging.
And this is the first one, this working memory things are.
So the prefrontal one is the initial signal that there is a memory problem.
This is before, and this is an enter rate memory.
In other words, it's a new memory that you want to form.
So this is the first thing that is affected.
But once the memory are in the recent memory mode, this, for example, would be your phone
number, which is one of the easy seven digits to remember because you're so familiar with
it that it's now become quote unquote permanent memory by repetition, by exposure to the same
items.
These reverberate in that limbic circuit that I just told you.
And the hippocampal formation has an inner circuit that is crucial for that.
So it is crucial for that forming.
And then you being able to retrieve that number again.
So when that circuit becomes engaged at any point, then you start having this retrograde
memory problem.
You cannot remember your number, which is interesting.
That's the point at which the family members tend to really notice what's happening and
become concerned.
Yes.
The patients tend to become concerned much sooner.
The patients become concerned with the integrate memory deficits.
You're absolutely right.
How do you distinguish between something you said a moment ago, which was this slight deficit
of formation of new memory is on some levels, not necessarily a pathological finding as we
age, but how do we differentiate between the pathologic or the appropriate age related
versus the potentially the harbinger of something pathologic?
It is difficult to draw the line.
This is one of the main reasons that this diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment has
been elusive.
I have asked this question to other researchers and I get very many different opinions.
And the main reason is that the only way to know for sure is to compare this to your own
history, to compare it to yourself.
So in this case, the patient and their immediate patterns, they are more knowledgeable whether
they're being a change.
If you just compare to a standardized age population, you may not see any difference,
but the patient will tell you, no, I know I am having more difficulty with, for example,
this working memory test.
So it is a challenge, but the beauty of this is you don't have to wait because everybody
goes through this cognitive decline is just to different extent.
And we all start out at a different level of cognitive performance.
So it's very difficult to have a standard.
So my approach is to try to intervene at that point.
And therefore, the main target at that point is to intervene in the prefrontal cortex,
the region that is just behind your forehead.
And that one engages, we call an essential executive network that for cognitive processing
that is involved in working memory, that is involved in problem solving, that is involved
in sustained attention vigilance.
Those are the things that are going to be seen first, having a decline as you grow older,
just like all kinds of tissues decline as you grow older.
This is a reality.
But it is possible to intervene then before you get into the limbic system problems.
And that's the approach that we have done in our interventions.
And I think this is what's going to make the biggest difference.
So let's go back to now the sort of revised hypothesis.
So if I can summarize, the actual nomenclature of Alzheimer's disease might be a bit of an
unfortunate artifact in that it was first observed in a subset of what would become
this disease that really isn't representative of the epidemic that we're seeing today.
Absolutely right.
And so we'll put that aside for a moment because despite how tragic those early onset cases
are and they strike me as among the most tragic things I've ever seen in medicine, by the
way, you have more experience with this.
The thing that's running amok right now is this sort of late onset dementia that it seems
to me that we are probably diagnosing it much more than we were before, but it also seems
to be increasing out beyond just the rate of diagnosis.
And it also seems to be increasing at a rate disproportionate to the increase in our longevity,
which is really not that significant.
I believe that human longevity is increasing at about 0.4% per year in the United States
and yet the rate of growth of Alzheimer's disease is growing much more than that.
So if you discount that somewhat for the rate of for the diagnostic acumen or urgency with
which we seek it, there's still a gap, which means on a real level, not just a perceived
level, this disease is becoming more common.
In your research, you talk about five areas of study that help you think about this, the
epidemiology of the disease, the imaging of the disease, the pharmacologic response to
the disease, the pathologic findings in the disease, and then the clinical course of the
disease.
You and your colleagues have a different hypothesis that pertains to the vascular system.
Yes.
This is actually the original hypothesis that was associated with senile dementia.
I don't want to take credit for the people who gone after that because in the early days
it was just an idea, not well formulated, but what seems to be happening is if you compromise
circulation to the brain, you're always going to get a neurological deficit.
However, in the case of what we're seeing as late onset dementia that I may refer to
as features dementia as opposed to the early onset Alzheimer's dementia, which is what
should be named.
There is a chronic hypoperfusion that is the brain is receiving less blood supply.
For example, it is known that between 22 years old to 60 years old, there is a decrease of
about 20% on your supply of blood to the brain.
Some people have calculated at approximately half of a percentage per year in statistical
terms.
I have a sense of why, how much of that ... I mean, because I think a lay person might
understandably but naively assume that is just due to a gradual and gradual narrowing
of arteries or something like that, but it strikes me that that's very unlikely the case
and that it's much more related to something within capillaries and or other metrics.
Because paradoxically as we age, we're seeing an increase in our blood pressure typically.
When you're 20 versus 60, you're generally running with a higher blood pressure.
If anything, you would think that should increase cerebral perfusion, not decrease it.
But of course, we're not seeing that.
What do you think at the level of vascular biology would explain even that observation?
Yes.
Unfortunately, the answer is all of the above.
In other words, the vascular changes happened at the microscopic and microscopic levels.
But it is the case if you, for example, only look like we have done, for example, the carotid
artery, the one in the neck that supplies the blood to the head.
This is where most of the blood is going to the brain from this.
You can use ultrasound imaging, knowing basically, and are able to look at the layers.
Even the intimal thickening of the carotid artery, which would presumably get a little
more and more and more as one ages, is going to play a role in this potential.
Yes.
There is a linear relationship between what we call the intima-media thickness, the layers
of the artery and the decline in cognitive function.
Now, why, I mean, this sounds silly, but why a linear relationship given that it should
be non-linear, shouldn't it?
Given that with increase in intimal thickening, you would see exponential change in cross-sectional
area, wouldn't that lead to a non-linear change in perfusion?
No.
Which I realize you were talking about cognition, not perfusion.
Cognition, not perfusion.
The reason there is not a linear change with perfusion is what you alluded to.
We have an auto-regulatory mechanism.
I get it.
Basically, can start to auto-correct, at least try to dampen it.
Yes, try to.
Yeah, dampens it from an exponential problem to a linear problem.
That's a beautiful, beautiful example of biology.
So as the artery becomes stiffer with the thicker walls, it's just like if you imagine
somebody having a hose that is releasing water and then you stick your finger in front of
the hose and you can see how the water is coming in a faster place.
So this is one aspect, but this is the auto-regulation.
The body is trying to achieve that.
It does that when the walls become stiffer because of the thickening.
When you have this systolic pump that they're supposed to comply, or arterial compliance,
they don't do that.
So even though you may see the lumen being the same size, in other words, the hole being
the same size, but it's not the same size when you have the pulse, the bolus of blood
going through that it has to open up.
However, when we increase blood pressure, we have a constant process of trying to increase
blood pressure to maintain that same level of perfusion.
This now leads to problems with the capillaries because these capillaries.
So the compensation for the macrovascular disease may actually be driving part of the
damage at the microvascular disease.
We're pushing now with a higher blood pressure through capillaries.
And this creates pathology at this boundary we call the endothelial walls.
And these endothelial walls are now subjected to mechanical pressures that they were not
designed to do.
And you have extravasation and you have cells that normally are only engaged when we have
like a hemorrhage, like the platelets to try to coagulate.
Now they start sticking to these endothelial walls and compromising some of the microcirculation
as a consequence.
So the auto-regulation cannot compensate and it creates additional problems as time goes
by.
And that's why you are actually better off with less blood pressure by controlling your
high blood pressure than with more, even though you're trying to make up for the decreased
blood supply.
And this has actually been borne out in very recent clinical trials.
Every five years or so we see more and more data revising how we think about blood pressure
regulation and the most recent results seem to indicate the best outcomes occur with a
systolic blood pressure below 120 millimeters per mercury, a diastolic below 80.
Formerly this used to be 135-ish, over 90 was accepted.
So that's a significant difference because many people walk around, many adults walk
around with a blood pressure above 120 over 80.
You're right.
And that is an index of this pathology that is developing in the large arteries like in
the carotid here.
But I'm using the carotid as an example.
When this happens at the level of the carotid is happening.
You know what's happening at the vertebral arteries and into the circle of Willis and
the main basically is happening more in the arteries that have the largest flow because
we get like about one third of the blood going into the head for the primary for the brain
function.
So there is a much more blood flow that is going through those arteries than the one,
for example, going through your arm, your brachial artery.
However, in the case of the heart, the same thing happens.
You have the small coronary arteries that are feeding the heart itself as soon as you
it pumps.
So they have greater flows.
The other thing that happens, these walls are not only thicker, but they become irregular,
especially the inner walls are no longer smooth.
And when they are no longer smooth, you start creating turbulence.
That is, if you look at the flow of liquid, when they hit an irregularity in the walls,
there is a little turbulence.
So these turbulence creates a system in which the position is going to be favored, like
when blood is going or in the blood that is usually the white blood cells.
Is it usually a macrophage that infiltrates as well?
Yes.
But even before infiltrating, they identify this area of turbulence as an area of potential
injury.
And they start aggregating there.
And because of the turbulence cells, they start then dying out against the walls.
And unfortunately, cholesterol levels then can add to it.
But they are not the problem.
The high total cholesterol is not the reason.
Again, there's confusing causality here with a consequence of this problem.
So lowering your total cholesterol is not going to really make a major difference in
this progression, which is, I think, one of the biggest misconceptions that is happening
in medicine right now.
But in any case, you have a number of phenomena that are taking place that are contributing
to the vascular hyperperfusion.
On the other hand, you can have a similar type of insult to the brain not coming from
this atherosclerotic process.
If the heart muscle itself is compromised in its function because of a process where
it weakens its ability to operate as a pump, you're going to have hyperperfusion that is
going to be developing.
And in that case, there would even be less likely that you're going to have an auto-regulatory
mechanism for that.
So you can have heart disease that is affecting the pumping, the force of the pump that can
lead to the hyperperfusion.
You can have arterial disease like atherosclerosis that is causing similar kind of phenomenon
with some more complications that are detected by this high blood pressure.
In the cardiac case, you will not see the high blood pressure, but in the other one,
you will see that.
So all of these things can be detected.
It is possible for cardiologists to advance and measure these things.
And once you detect this, the health of the heart and the arterial circulation in particular
is very closely related to the health of the brain.
So if whatever you do that improves cardiovascular health, wealth also helps the brain.
But there are some differences.
For example, the brain in some ways seems a little bit more exposed because the brain
is perfused during systole at a higher pressure.
The heart is the only organ that is actually perfused during diastole.
So in that sense, the coronary arteries themselves are less susceptible to hypertension than
the arteries in the brain or the kidney for that matter, which would be the two organs
that seem to be most damaged by hypertension more so than the heart.
The other thing that I'm hearing you say that creates a bit of a differentiation between
the heart is in the process of atherosclerosis in the heart, cholesterol does play a very
important role.
But you still have the initiation of the endothelial injury, which is necessary.
But once the lipoprotein can get inside the subendothelial space and becomes oxidized,
that's what elicits the immune response, which is what does the damage.
What you're describing in the brain is two different processes.
I'm hearing you correctly.
The first is cerebrovascular disease that leads to strokes, occlusive or hemorrhagic,
which that's a separate disease because it tends to produce an acute event that is the
result of an acute hypoperfusion that usually produces a much more functional deficit.
So it's almost like you can think of that as a quote unquote brain attack the way we
think of a heart attack.
But what you're describing that is now sort of unique to me is a different type of much
more indolent chronic hypoperfusion that actually seems to have a slightly different
pathophysiology from coronary physiology that doesn't produce an acute event, but rather
a chronic disease.
Is that, am I, did I summarize that?
You summarized that really well.
It is this chronic brain hypoperfusion, regardless of the particular cardiovascular cause, because
I told you with heart failure, you can have, you can simulate that aspect without some
of the other components.
So it is possible nowadays to pick this up and to intervene to try to resolve this vascular
problems or cardiovascular.
They involve the heart.
So the epidemiology states the first and most obvious relationship, which is so obvious
that it's not almost not helpful, which is there is no greater association with Alzheimer's
disease than age, just as there is no greater association with cardiovascular disease than
age.
So that's stating the obvious, but it's very difficult to draw a clear hypothesis or at
least confirm a hypothesis.
So the next layer of thinking on the epidemiology is what?
Is it the association with hypertension or is it the association with cardiometabolic
disease?
How do you then continue down that line of thinking on, just again, before we get to
the more interesting stuff, which I think is the pathology and the pharmacology, just
based on the epidemiology, what else can you infer?
What would be ideal to me would be what the main purpose of that circulation from the
point of view of energy is to bring oxygen to the tissue, tissue oxygenation.
It is only through this process of reducing oxygen to water that in mitochondrial this
process is linked, this cellular respiration is linked to the production of chemical energy.
So the more direct measurements would be measurements of oxygen consumption, but also could be the
enzyme that is responsible for that oxygen consumption.
And that's where it comes to our work and what we found in the brains of those Alzheimer's
patients.
We found that the enzyme called cytochrome oxidase or cytochrome C.
Which is complex for in the electron transport chain.
The electron transport is the last and the rate limiting enzyme and the one that actually
reduces oxygen to water that is linked to oxidative phosphorylation, the creation of
ATP.
Let's pause for a moment to make sure people understand this.
It's so important that even though I think I've talked about this before, it's worth
reiterating.
The mitochondria has an inner and outer membrane and these have four complexes.
Three of them span both the inner and outer membrane.
I believe it's one, three and four.
Complex two is only on the inner membrane.
These things are about the most essential elements of life.
Interrupting their activity for even moments at a time is the end of life.
I would say it's the key to aerobic life on the planet.
You can't overstate the importance of the electron transport chain.
As you pointed out, it is basically, we can't create energy out of nothing.
We simply change its form.
When we eat food, we're eating stored potential energy that is in a chemical form that is
generally between the carbon-carbon-carbon-hydrogen bonds.
As these things get reduced to simpler and simpler molecules, this process specifically
within the mitochondria takes these units and it, by breaking apart the chemical bonds,
creates an electrical gradient by shuttling electrons outside of this membrane as they
go from complex one, two, three.
Of course, they each come with their own reducing agents.
I spend my most time thinking about complex one, which is the NADH, NAD shuttle.
I believe complex four is NADPH, isn't it?
Is that what it's using as the electron acceptor donor?
Yes, I need to emphasize from what you're saying so people understand.
The whole purpose of that chemistry that is done with the foods that we eat is to generate
electron donors.
Electron donors are going to donate their electrons to electron transport.
There are only two of them, the NADH and the FADH.
The NADH primarily, it donates to different parts of the electron transport systems, but
the other one, the FADH, only to complex two.
You have two entry points, complex one and two.
That's why complex two doesn't span the full membrane.
It's sitting there only on the internal.
It's much smaller than complex one.
It's the largest one.
This is a biochemical key to this phenomenon because what we eat from an energy point of
view is just becoming electron donors.
Can we donate electrons to the electron transport?
If we could do that, we can accelerate respiration because the ultimate electron acceptor in
nature is oxygen.
That's what we call oxidation, the process of removing electrons.
Making water out of oxygen and these protons that are being donated is the ultimate byproduct
of respiration.
That's why we breathe out water vapor.
Of course, all of this is in service of creating an electron gradient to then fuel the generation
of adenosine triphosphate ATP.
What the mitochondria have done is coupling this affinity of oxygen to take these electrons
that are coming from the food that we eat into a closed system in which the electrons
when they are moving from one complex to the other, they are releasing what is called a
proton that is positively charged.
This is trapped in that intermembrane between the two membranes that you mentioned, the
outer and the inner one.
The matrix of the mitochondria, the more innermost portion is primarily negative in electrical
charge.
Ions are negative.
These protons are trying to move.
They are attracted towards this negativity just like when you have the pulse in a magnet,
the positive and the negative ball.
This is what we call electromagnetic force.
There are only very few forces in nature like gravitation.
This one is electromagnetic force.
The system was designed in such a way that the protons will leak through a hole.
That hole or pore is this complex V. Complex V is designed so that when the proton is
pushing through to get from the intermembrane space to the matrix, it clicks, changes the
conformation of that enzyme.
That movement generates the energy for a phosphate to be bound to ADP.
That phosphate is called inorganic phosphate when this is what in chemistry is called an
endothermic reaction.
It needs energy in order to happen and it's because of that movement.
Later on, when you need some other enzyme to work, all of these chemical reactions that
have to do with life are catalyzed or mediated by enzymes.
What this means is that you may have the reactants already in place but nothing is going to happen
in terms of products unless you provide energy to the system.
These are so-called reactions that when you remove that phosphate from the ADP, it generates
heat.
This is what we call calorie.
You can then have a quantitative relationship with how much food you eat, how many electrons
are donated, how many of these phosphates can be broken and generate the heat.
My heat is just like in chemistry when you had your reactants in a beaker and you have
a catalyst and nothing was happening and then you apply heat and then all the salt in a
reaction happens, it changes color for example.
When that phenomenon happens, then we call that an exothermic reaction that break it
and it fuels.
The key to the system is to be able, how can we facilitate that mitochondrial respiration?
This illustrates of course the most important point here.
What you're saying is the whole purpose of eating is to convert chemical energy into
chemical energy from one form to another.
To do it, you need an intermediary to translate and that intermediate has to turn the chemical
energy into electrical energy that then facilitates a conversion back to chemical energy.
That is the key to life and that is what the mitochondria do.
However, that is a way-
At least aerobically, we can obviously do this inefficiently and anaerobically later.
Correct, correct.
You can do this, especially in other tissues, not so much the brain.
You can generate ATP without using oxygen and this machinery.
But every organism including single cells on the planet that uses oxygen to obtain energy
relies on cytochrome oxidase.
They may not have mitochondria, but at least they need cytochrome oxidase.
Wait, I didn't realize that.
So red blood cells, for example, don't have mitochondria.
Do they have cytochrome oxidase?
Yes.
I didn't know that.
If they use oxygen to generate ATP, they have to have cytochrome C and cytochrome C oxidase.
This is the minimum requirement.
That's why you can look at cell lines from microbes and so on and you can identify these
proteins.
As long as it's aerobic, it's the only way nature found how to solve this.
But the interesting thing is that when the circulation is compromised and you have less
oxygen, you're creating a situation where these events cannot move on.
It doesn't matter how much you eat, and this is happening in older people.
It doesn't matter how much they eat.
In fact, their brain is telling them that they should be hungry because they are not
able to transfer those electron donors into electron transport and produce energy.
So they feel they're energy deprived, so they increase food consumption, especially if they
are attracted to carbohydrates, simple carbohydrates that can quickly break down and produce these
electron donors.
So do you think that this is the first insult then?
Because you talked about this slightly different type of microvascular disease that is much
more chronic and insidious and doesn't lead to acute changes like hemorrhage or occlusion.
How does that change ultimately impact the ability of the mitochondria to do its job
and facilitate electron transfer?
Yes, you put your finger on it.
This is what links this phenomenon.
Regardless of whether the chronic hyperperfusion or the more acute, one of the things that
happen is when we have a hypoxia situation, cytochrome oxidase is an inducible enzyme.
What that means is that our body only maintains as much as it's needed, as much as it's demanded.
It's a complex of 13 different subunits, three of them mitochondrial DNA derived and the
other 10 from nuclear DNA.
You can regulate it at many different levels, including both the nucleus or mitochondria.
But essentially, within minutes, if for example you have an area of ischemia, you occlude
a blood vessel, half an hour later you lost a significant amount of cytochrome oxidase
from being functional.
That's irreversible then?
No, it is not irreversible.
That's the advantage of the system.
The system works on demand.
It may not be immediately reversible.
It depends on the level of regulation.
In other words, you can simply inhibit the enzyme and the enzyme is still there.
Or you can disassemble the catalytic units of the enzyme, the ones from mitochondrial
origin, and then you have a partial enzyme, not the so-called hollow enzyme.
Or you can eliminate the other components and throughout the mitochondrial inner membrane
you have all of these graduations of stages that can be used for regulating this.
So you can regulate it a more immediate way or eventually you need proteins transported
from the cytoplasm to be shipped where the mitochondria are and incorporated into this.
Why was this done?
Because mitochondria have a symbiotic relationship with the cells that they live on.
And this was created to develop a dependency that mitochondria are doing this but they
cannot do it on their own.
The cell has found a way to obtain the energy but is conditional on then contributing a
component that is necessary for the entire machinery to work.
The important portion here is that these phenomena are coupled.
As soon as you have hypoxia, ischemia, you reduce, then this machinery goes down regulated.
Is that true of complex I, II, III as well?
Are they also inducible the way complex IV is?
Not as much as complex IV.
They are to a certain degree if you keep taxing the system it's going to happen.
But the one that has the more flexibility from more immediate to long term because of
this role has rate limiting is complex IV and that's the reason it is preferred modulator
of the system.
That's why I love doing these podcasts.
Every single podcast I get to learn something new in biology that I didn't know.
I had no idea that complex IV was inducible to a greater extent than the others.
As it is for example you may have heard for sure during your training about other inducible
enzymes.
Yes of course.
In some systems in the liver.
So the liver is P450, the most inducible of them all.
So it's a perfect example.
If you have more, if you drink more alcohol you're going to build up more of this cytochrome
enzyme.
So these are the most inducible and somatic complexes that we have.
Just never think of it in something so important.
Not that the liver is less important of course but the ETC is so fundamental for everything
that we do.
It's so interesting to think of that.
And it's also interesting to hear you say that at least in transient periods of ischemia
this is not irreversible.
No, it's not irreversible.
It's an inducible system just like you stop drinking alcohol.
These enzymes are going to be down regulated but if you start challenging the system again
they are inducible.
They're going to go back.
Of course you're going to suffer somewhat in between because at the beginning you're
not going to be able to meet the demand.
But they are inducible.
This is the key that I have understood from our investigation of the Alzheimer's brain.
In those fresh frosting Alzheimer's brain the main problem was cytochrome oxidase inhibition.
The levels of the protein levels of the enzymes were not compromised but you could see that
the enzyme was not in its catalytic functional state and you could demonstrate this using
enzyme histochemistry.
If you were able to extract at the moment those patients died their cells in culture
and now they're perfused would they have still been hypo functioning?
In other words would you still have been able to measure a deficit of oxygen utilization?
Yes, yes.
And this has been done.
Groups have taken actually what they've taken is mitochondria and they can then see that
these mitochondria are not performing this cellular respiration from Alzheimer's patients.
Give me a sense of what is the magnitude of the deficit to result in the phenotype that
we observe clinically?
Yes, this is a very good question because if you inhibit cytochrome oxidase after about
40% in an organism the organism dies.
You cannot cut.
But presumably it's a nomogram of duration and degree of suppression, right?
So maybe you could have a 40% reduction for two seconds but not a 40% reduction for two
minutes or something.
I mean I assume that's correct.
For example, the classic poison cyanide.
What does cyanide does?
Cyanide is complex for a cytochrome oxidase inhibitor.
It gets into a circulation, it inhibits cytochrome oxidase and minutes later you die.
So if that happens it's not compatible to life.
However, you can have many degrees of this reduction because the enzyme is so inducible
you not only change the catalytic activity of a particular...
In other words, cyanide is not binary in its ability to kill.
It seems functionally binary because it's so potent that even a trace amount of cyanide
will kill but presumably if you dilute it enough and enough and enough you could give
enough cyanide to somebody that they have a chronic illness due to...
It's almost like it's a thought experiment.
You could induce Alzheimer's at a low enough dose of cyanide to create a functional hypoperfusion
by inhibiting complex four without killing the organism.
And we did this.
I like when I think of things 10 years after someone else did.
This thought experiment was done and in fact Dr. Jack De La Torre, the one that wrote the
book Alzheimer's Turning Point that I highly recommend.
Yeah, we'll link to that for sure.
And we collaborated in that study.
So it works both ways.
In other words, if you compromise the circulation by partially occluding blood vessels to the
brain you get a downregulation on cytochrome oxidase and therefore mitochondrial respiration
and ATP production and so on and the animal choke cognitive picture that is analogous.
It's not the same but it's analogous to what you see in cognitive, neurocognitive disorders.
The other way around you can directly suppress the electron transport and in our study we
decided to use sodium as I because it's less potent than cyanide and when you do that,
yes, you have an animal that at a very low level of decreasing you can decrease up to
30% without seeing any neurological evident change.
The animals appear to be eating and behaving normally but when you test them with cognitive
memory tests they cannot perform well.
In other words, a 30% reduction in the oxidative capacity of complex IV shows cognitive impairment
when challenged even though behaviorally at the gross motor level the animal is still
fine.
It's an Alzheimer's patient that you will appear to be generally okay.
Until you test the system harder.
Yes, so these animals and in fact that was proposed as a model for Alzheimer's disease
that very same approach by ColixtoMine, the one that comes to mind, it's Rose and Bennett.
However because of the influence of this amyloid and tangled hypothesis all of these models
were based on biochemical and physiological phenomena where really not developed fully.
All the attention was in the genes and the abnormal proteins but yes, you can do this
in animals.
You can test these hypotheses in animals.
Does this lead to any change in the amount?
Let's assume you had an animal model where you could do this for a long enough period
of time before the animal would die and you had a control animal in which you were not
doing this.
Did you in those two situations side by side see a difference in amyloid beta accumulation?
No, the amyloid beta would not be a good reflection of these processes.
The amyloid beta is primarily a process that is compensatory when the cells are showing
atrophy.
So when cells are showing signs of atrophy we have a lot of amyloid beta that is released
embryonically during the development of the nervous system and it's because during development
of the nervous system you have faces of large proliferation of neurons but then you have
other faces of trimming where there is a lot of neuronal death and in those situations
you see amyloid that is formed.
So as you know probably the major signal for a cell to die in an aerobic organism is for
the mitochondria to release cytochrome C. Cytochrome C is a protein that carries the
electron to cytochrome C oxidase.
If that machinery is not working and cytochrome C leaks out we say the mitochondrial permeability
pore has been modified so that small cytochrome C leaks out.
That's a big signal for apoptosis.
Apoptosis or programmed cell death.
In other words if a cell mitochondria.
That's the surrender of the cell.
That's the white flag.
Here's my cytochrome C.
So what I'm telling you is if you compromise the system you're going to have neural degeneration.
You're going to have cell death and not just in the nervous system.
It just happens that there is more critical because in all the systems we have other ways
to get ATP but in neurons we don't have any significant amount of alternative ways to get
it.
Yeah that's exactly the point I was going to make is we're having this discussion and
it would be easy for a moment to say wow why is this all isolated to the brain.
It's not.
It's just the brain I think has two problems.
The first you know if you're going to be critical of the brain.
The first is an energetic problem which is it is simply the most demanding and therefore
it is the most susceptible to a reduction in total available energy.
The brain weighs about 2 percent of our body weight and yet consumes about 20 percent of
our total energy expenditure.
So that's a grossly disproportionate amount of energy.
And the second by the way would be the kidney which by the way is the second organ we tend
to see great ischemic.
When we see hypoperfusion clinically we see kidney damage and myocardial damage.
So the more energy demanding the organ the bigger the problem.
And then the second issue with the brain is this seemingly overreliance on oxidative phosphorylation
without an anaerobic escape route.
Yes you are right on target and this is what makes it so vulnerable.
And this is why we see these changes more as cognitive deficit before all the tissues
are really damaged or the brain itself.
But as you continue with this process as we just talked about if downregulation of cytochromox
they reach a certain level cytochrome C is going to start releasing.
There is this permeability change goes out and cells start dying.
So it is the direction of causality is completely different from the amyloid ideas that the
amyloid comes there because of a gene that is abnormal and then it's creating these cascades
that are leading to these changes.
No what we have is this problems with supply of oxygen that happen to the brain and it's
this high energetic demand and they could be due to the circulation or it could be due
to a cardiac effect on the circulation.
But unfortunately the vascular hypothesis of dementia is not exclusionary because you
can have toxic insults that affect the mitochondria that will for all physiological purposes will
do something similar to these cardiovascular insults.
In other words they are going to lead also to downregulation of cytochrome oxidase and
your inability to use oxygen to generate energy.
So that's why I have used that entry point into the system because it is completely consistent
with the vascular hypothesis of dementia but it also provides room for other insults to
the brain that are going to be reflected at that level and it's only when they are reflected
at the level that then they because of this energetic demand this vulnerability that you
alluded to that then this is going to lead to a cognitive.
Why a cognitive problem and not something else?
Because when we are engaged in these functions that I explained we these functions are not
limited to one region of the brain.
They are relied on interaction between different regions.
So when you're reading something that information goes to your visual system but then if you're
going to engage learning having to do with that then we'll engage other systems.
So the memory functions are more distributed.
So when you have a more distributed metabolic insult they're going to be affected.
It's just like people know somebody may get a blow to the head and then all of a sudden
they may have retrograde amnesia.
They may not remember what happened.
They may remember who they are and you may not see any significant level of structural
damage but you affected the way the systems were interacted in a more global way.
So this is one of the reasons we detect this primarily as a memory problem initially but
later on it becomes a neurodegenerative disorder when cells cannot longer work without this
mitochondrial machinery.
Do we have any insight into how much mitophagy or autophagy is going on in the later stages
of Alzheimer's disease?
In other words, is it possible that so much of this damage is now due to defective cleaning
up of the mitochondria because the more these mitochondria are damaged the more mitochondrial
DNA is getting released.
The mitochondrial DNA itself is actually looks bacterial so it elicits an immune response.
This probably accelerates the process.
It would seem that anything that would increase mitophagy or autophagy would at least be able
to curb the progression of the feed forward loop on this damage going and accelerating.
Wouldn't that make sense?
I agree.
However, it's too late.
If you already compromised the machinery for obtaining the energy, it's too late at that
point.
So my focus on the focus of Jack Delatorre and other people is how can we intervene,
for example, one way is in the risk factors that have to do with the cardiovascular compromise,
try to intervene with the risk factors.
Besides blood pressure, what do you view as the most important risk factors then?
I think atherosclerosis is a really important risk factor and the major blood vessels you
indicated like the carotid, the ascending aorta and the renal arteries.
They are the large blood vessels are the main targets of these arterocollortic processes,
especially at the bifurcation points.
The other factors that I would consider would be generalized trauma to the brain.
Yeah, I was going to ask you about this.
This seems to bear an uncanny resemblance to chronic traumatic encephalopathy where
the difference is if you're a football player or a boxer, you have repeated short bouts
of hypoxia.
It appears from my reading of the literature that every time you're getting hit in the
head, you're having a transient interruption of blood flow.
And also it appears based on at least the animal models, we're seeing transient insulin
resistance at the level of pyruvate dehydrogenase.
So a blow to the head will transiently make it harder for pyruvate to turn into acetyl
CoA, which is the opening substrate in the Krebs cycle.
And so while the patients we're describing, who presumably let's just make math simple
and say they never get a concussion or a hit in the head, they have this chronic insidious
disease process.
The athletes who are suffering this type of injury are getting punctuated by spike functions
of these, and it doesn't have to be a concussion every time.
It could be each play on the field or something like that.
Do you think there's an overlap in these processes?
Oh yes, completely.
This is what's called dementia pugilistica originally.
And often nowadays this is confused with Alzheimer's disease and Parkinson's disease.
In the case of Parkinson's disease, because with the blows to the head, there is a rapid
twisting of the head.
When you get a blow to the head, a rapid twisting, bending of the head with respect
to the neck.
Yeah, it's an angular momentum that usually causes that injury.
And this affects the midbrain and the upper brain stem.
And actually that's what leads to the knockout.
That would feed more into a Parkinsonian phenotype in the midbrain and the substantia nigra.
You will be isolated in that region as more vulnerable for this.
But it is the same phenomena.
All of these forms of dementia will have a common denominator at some point, regardless
of the many different ways that you can impact the system.
The most likely common denominator will be at the level of the mitochondrial respiration.
And therefore, another way, for example, the circulation may not be a good target for neural
trauma, but if you find a way to facilitate mitochondrial respiration, even if there's
compromise, hyper-refusion or some other condition, and this is what I've been working on for
many years.
And once we discovered that the main problem in the Alzheimer's brain had to do with this
inhibition of cytochrome oxidase, we set out to how can we intervene?
Is there any way?
And you have two interventions that you have now coupled that both work on cytochrome C,
but in a slightly different way.
Yes, cytochrome C oxidase.
Cytochrome C is the carrier, and cytochrome C oxidase is the large inside.
The large complex, yeah.
Thank you for clarifying.
So the first one, I use a pharmacological approach because I was more familiar with
those approaches, but I couldn't do it with regular.
Because of what is called neuropharmacology or psychopharmacology is really aimed at
neurotransmission, resectors and agonists and antagonists.
What's needed here is something is acting at the level of mitochondrial respiration
and reviewing all literature from the 1960s.
I found out that metal and blue commonly used compounds in the lab was able to act as an
electron donor.
And depending on the conditions, but if you make it a very low concentration, it acts
as an electron cycler.
It will donate, but it will also get electrons from other compounds and it will continue
to feed into the electron transport as an alternate route.
And in fact, if you block, for example, complex one with ruthenon that you're interested,
still the electron transport can proceed going through metal and blue as a bypass.
Because in a normal organism, complete blocking of complex one would be fatal.
You're saying with a high enough concentration of methylene blue, you can still get electrons
past the bottleneck of complex one.
We can prevent in animal models, degeneration.
We showed this in many preparations.
We first did it in the retina because it was more accessible and we could manipulate that
locally as a model of the brain.
And then we did it in the brain.
So this has an interesting history, right?
There's a guy named Paul Ehrlich who studied this, right?
And the only reason I remember this is-
One of my heroes.
Really?
Yeah.
Well, I read something that I love where expressions come from.
And so there's an expression balls to the wall, which means like going very, very fast
all out.
And most people don't realize, but it just refers to a governor and a train where the
governor, the faster that the train was going, these balls that were hanging on, you know,
basically cables would move further and further out as the centrifugal force goes.
And once they touch the wall, that's the mechanism that would regulate the speed and slow it
down.
But there's another expression that comes from Ehrlich's work, which is, is it a magic
bullet?
Magic bullet.
And he referred to methylene blue as a magic bullet.
And Ehrlich, Paul Ehrlich, he worked in Berlin, Germany, and he was able to be part of a very
progressive group at the time.
So before World War II, this was in the-
Yeah.
This is-
Actually, this is in the late 1800s, right?
No, no.
This is in the late 1800s.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
1886, he was working on this and he injected.
At that time, it was the beginning of the Industrial Revolution.
And the first thing in the Industrial Revolution that was developed were the textiles, being
able to manufacture clothing.
And one of the important things was the transition from using natural products for dyes to, you
know, develop chemists, developing synthetic dyes.
And actually, Germany led this process and methylene blue was one of these synthetic
dyes, blue dye.
And for many decades, it was the blue dye used in blue jeans and most of the other blue
clothing.
So one of the things that intrigued Paul Ehrlich was that he injected methylene blue, one of
these new synthetic dyes, into a live rat.
And then he dissected the animal after killing the animal, he dissected the animal.
And he found out that the methylene blue, this was a large concentration intravenous
injection, was primarily staining nervous tissue, the brain and peripheral nervous tissue.
So he created the concept there of a magic bullet.
This is a chemical that, remember this in the 1880s, this is a chemical that I'm giving
systemically, yet it is somehow finding its way to the nervous system.
And it's becoming trapped there, as you can see by the stain.
Later this phenomenon was called supra vital or vital staining.
And it was exploited, for example, by Santiago Ramn Iqal, one of my other heroes during
this time.
He referred to this as the Ehrlich reaction, to be able to stain nervous tissue when the
animal was alive.
But what does it mean, the animal being alive, the animal respiring, the animal using oxygen.
So methylene blue, they didn't know this, but methylene blue has affinity for these
redox reactions that are happening in a maximized way inside the mitochondrial in the electron
transport chain.
And especially at low concentrations, it becomes trapped for periods of hours inside mitochondrial.
It can work as a mitochondrial stain.
Does it become toxic?
What is it toxic that you look like at a higher dose?
At a higher dose, instead of acting as an electron cycler, it actually replaces oxygen.
You know, it competes with oxygen.
Remember that I told you oxygen was the one that was taking the electrons.
So he can be, you wanted to have it in a low concentration that is giving electrons
and taking electrons at the same rate.
But you're saying at a higher dose, it becomes a proton acceptor.
Little, little, yes, because it competes with oxygen and it oxidizes the tissues.
And actually, that was in part the first application that Ehrlich found for methylene blue.
So that's interesting because the only time obviously that I've ever seen it used is for
treating methemoglobinemia in the emergency room.
So someone is exposed to carbon monoxide, you know, acutely or even chronically over
a long period of time.
This basically breaks it apart.
So there you actually want it to sort of outcompete oxygen a little bit, right?
Is that what's happening there?
Yes.
No, what is happening there in the carbon monoxide occupies the in the heme molecule,
the pocket where normally oxygen finds.
That's right.
So you actually wanted a competitor.
Yeah, you wanted to get the carbon monoxide out.
That will displace it and methemol blue will do that.
But because you do this infusion, so methemol blue can be used to prevent or rescue you from
methemoglobinemia, this inability to bind the oxygen.
But a higher concentration induces methemoglobinemia.
Yes.
The same compound.
So this is typical of all of these three dogs chemicals that I studied.
They have this.
They have bimodal functional points.
We call these by basic dose response or a hormetic dose responses.
But essentially they do the opposite effects, low and high concentrations.
Now the color, the other, if someone's listening to this, they'll remember the high school
chemistry class.
How do you demonstrate this to your students?
Yes.
Well, when you add the powder of methelene blue into water, the water becomes very blue.
And then if you use a reducing agent and I use vitamin C ascorbic acid because it's an
effective reducing agent, but it's harmless.
When the methelene blue is reduced, it becomes transparent.
Reducing meaning it's accepting protons.
Yes.
It's no longer acting as oxygen.
So then you'll turn that vial clear.
Clear.
And this is then you'll refer to it as leuco, methelene blue.
Leuco actually comes from the same root like leucosides, the white blood cells.
Yes.
So you call it the leuco, methelene blue.
That refers to the methelene blue being in the reduced state as opposed to the oxidized
state that is the blue.
So methelene blue had major advantages, but one of the cosmetic disadvantage is that
once it goes through this process that I explained that becoming trapped, that was discovered
by air leach of becoming trapped in the nervous tissue.
So it has affinity for nervous tissue inside mitochondria.
Eventually it goes back into the circulation.
It takes half life of about 12 hours with a dose that is a low dose that produces this
redox benefit.
So it concentrates in the urine, in the bladder.
And actually here in the U.S. for decades before the antibiotics were available, if
you had a urinary bladder infection, you took methelene blue pills.
The methelene blue pills will start increasing the concentration of methelene blue inside
the bladder until it became a pro-oxidant while it was there and it eliminated any bacteria
or virus in a non-specific manner.
And it was a very effective, more effective way to eliminate urinary bladder infection.
For example, in older people have chronic problems that they go through round after
round of antibiotics that they rehabilitate them or create resistance.
You could use methelene blue.
And is it because the methelene blue would add a dose that was not toxic to the human
once it concentrates in the bladder, it increases its concentration and therefore is toxic to
the organism.
It would become oxidative and it would be toxic for the bacteria.
Also is it a Ross-induced injury to the bacteria then?
Correct.
So you're basically going after the mitochondria of the bacteria.
Yes.
It does the opposite, but it does it to the microorganisms that are inside the bladder
that are producing the infection.
So it has the potential to do this in all the situations, but here naturally concentrates
there.
So that provides the advantage.
But there are many things about methelene blue I will not go into, but Erlich himself
determined that the parasite that produces malaria, the Plasmodium falciparum had an
enzyme that was particularly vulnerable to not much large concentrations of methelene
blue were enough to affect this enzyme.
So methelene blue became the first and for a long time, the only treatment for malaria.
And this was a major breakthrough in medical research was in fact the first synthetic chemical
used for a medicinal application in the history of medicine and pharmacology was methelene
blue.
And all of the first synthetic medicines were derivatives of methelene blue, including in
particular the late 1940s, early 1950s, the development of chloropromase, the first psychopharmacological
agent that was used for psychosis or what we call now schizophrenia.
In those days they will call it dementia precause because they were thinking that it was the
same kind of dementia that was happening.
The older people happening, the young people.
Now we make a separation between dementia and schizophrenia, but chloropromase is a
methelene blue derivative and in fact there are reports as far as 1930s of physicians
giving methelene blue mixes.
The problem was that in the original way that methelene blue was synthesized for textiles,
there were a lot of intermediary products as a result of the synthesis and some of these
were likely chloropromase.
So they were seeing anti-psychotic effects from giving these methelene blue preparations.
Because I found reports in the 1930s and 1940s and then it was picked up by a pharmaceutical
company and by the end of the 1940s they developed chloropromase as the first anti-psychotic
medication and that would change completely the face of psychiatry.
And it may have just been simply a chemical contaminant slash intermediary contaminant
within the formulation of methelene blue.
So they thought the benefit was methelene blue, it was actually from a byproduct within.
And they discovered what the byproduct was.
Which is such a great story of chemistry in general, how easy it is to be fooled by something
that seemingly makes sense.
Now today the only FDA indication to my knowledge for methelene blue is methemoglobinemia, is
that correct?
Yes.
I mean there's clinical trials that are going on to study this in all fibrous diseases.
Yeah, let me clarify that because what happened is that methelene blue was being available
for 120 years plus.
So methelene blue was grandfathered by the FDA.
It preceded the creation of the FDA.
So the FDA has not been able to resolve well how they deal with these grandfathered drugs.
Being the first synthetic drug available, so it was used for many things.
I'm not going to go into all of them but malaria was probably the most important one.
Until some Spanish and French explorers in South America discovered from the bark of
the tree quinine and then that happened and it became the next generation after methelene
blue.
Nowadays they're bringing back the methelene blue, especially in Africa, because there
the Plasmodium has become persistent to quinines.
So they are combining it.
So there's a comeback for methelene blue in that respect.
So it is used medicinally for that.
But the FDA never really got to have a saying on it.
So what you're referring to is what has survived in what is called the US pharmacopoeia.
These companions of medications with indications.
And in the US pharmacopoeia, that indication of methelene blue for methemoglominemia has
survived.
Some of the others have been removed, like I told you, for urinary bladder infections
when the antibiotics became available.
But it's being used to protect the brain.
You mentioned cancer early before we started the interview.
Many of the drugs that are used for chemotherapy have side effects that affect the brain, in
particular mitochondrial respiration.
So methelene blue, given before or during chemotherapy interventions, have been found
to be life saving.
One example is one called Iphosphamide.
So Iphosphamide in deuce encephalopathy happens in this chemotherapy.
And there are many papers on this.
However, the problem is the FDA will not acknowledge these uses because there is no pharmaceutical
company who is bringing these materials.
I guess this is sort of an impossible situation to understand because the FDA can't really
consider the approval for an agent or a use without an investigational new drug filing
an IND.
Oh, yes.
There is no IND, I assume, for methelene blue because there's no economics in methelene
blue.
Yeah.
There is no company that wants to invest because it's not patentable.
They cannot protect their with a patent.
So anybody can manufacture methelene blue and prescribe it or use it.
In some countries like Canada, it's freely available.
Here in the US, it's unclear what its status is, but you can get it through the internet.
The problem is there are two problems.
One, you have different purities.
So you have at least three categories of purities for methelene blue.
The one that should be used in humans like in the emergency room is called pharmaceutical
quality or the US, we call USP grade.
The Europeans have a similar, but the one in the USP is actually more stringent than
the European methelene blue.
Then there is chemical quality that is used in laboratory for staining.
But that can go, for example, the one produced by Sigma has about 15% impurities.
It should not be given to live animals or humans and is readily available.
So I always want to warn against that.
And in many experiments with animals, they use that Sigma Prado.
So we don't know if we're confounding the results of the experiments with the impurities.
And impurities are very toxic.
He has lead, he has mercury, he has cadmium.
He has a number of neurotoxic impurities.
And then the other one is even less pure, it's the industrial.
Color the genes.
To color the blue genes and all the things.
And that is even more than 15% impurity and nobody knows for sure.
Now there was a company in Scotland several years ago that ran a compound, LMTM.
And the trial, which was announced, results of this trial were announced about two years
ago.
And that was a big hoopla because the study, which I went back and skimmed the other day
because I knew we would probably, I was hoping we would talk about this.
The study basically took patients in early stages of dementia, randomized them to various
interventions, but one of them was this agent, this LMTM, which they described as a methylin
blue derivative.
I don't know how far a derivative it was.
It might have been not much of a derivative.
It's essentially, you remember when I told you I added ascorbic acid, it used methylin
blue.
So they don't something like this.
They have reduced methylin blue, but they don't use the name methylin blue.
They use the name of a methyltionine chloride, which is a more chemical name.
And that's where the MT comes.
And then the L is for the leuco.
Because it's clear, it comes in its reduced form.
That's the form that is in the pill.
As soon as it's in the body, it's oxidized.
Yeah, it starts these redox cycles.
And those patients did void blue.
Oh, yes.
So it is clear that it's doing the redox cycles.
Now, what was very controversial about this was the primary endpoint of that study was
a neuroimaging outcome.
And the primary output failed.
There was no difference on neuroimaging.
There was a secondary outcome on cognitive function.
And in a subgroup analysis, which again, the statisticians will say, they cry foul,
right?
And understandable, you can't start parsing the data.
And I agree.
Yes.
But the argument was the subset in which this benefit was seen, which was about 15%.
And if I recall, it was only patients that received the LMTM in monotherapy.
So what we don't know, unfortunately, because this to me left a lot of questions unanswered,
right?
It certainly suggested there's something going on with methylin blue.
But are we being misled because the combination of methylin blue with other drugs obfuscates
the results?
Yes.
I think that's the most likely.
That's one.
Yeah.
That's a, you think that's the most likely.
Oh, yes.
However, let me clarify.
These individuals have never presented methylin blue or understood methylin blue from the
point of view that are being presented to you as a metabolic enhancer, or it could be
a metabolic poison too, but in low concentrations, the low concentrations as a metabolic enhancer
acting on the mitochondrial respiration, they have been presented these as an anti-towel
medication.
That's correct.
The entire company with whose name I forget now.
Yes, called towel.
It had towel in the name.
Yes, towel X.
Yeah.
That's the other thing that interested me, which was.
The hypothesis is completely wrong.
They might have backed into something interesting, potentially.
Yes.
And I say this here publicly.
It is unfortunate that they have done this this way because they are undermining the
potential benefits of methylin blue.
The biochemist who is behind the hypothesis are not going to name.
He found that in vitro, relatively large concentrations to based on what I'm telling you about mitochondrial
respiration, it prevented the phosphorylation and agglutination of tau in vitro.
So they then infer, or this is an anti-towel agent.
If you test methylin blue with immediate different compounds, depending on the concentration
of methylin blue, because it has reducing or anoxidating action, it will interfere with
all kinds of phenomena.
There's nothing specific about methylin blue.
This may be true, true and unrelated.
Its effect on tau, whether correct or incorrect, may not actually matter.
And not only that, the effect is dose-dependent.
In other words, in vitro, the more concentration of methylin blue had you, the more you interfere
with the tau aggregation.
In other words, you don't see this bimodal dose response.
No, because they were actually working on the high end of concentration.
Does that mean they weren't even looking to see what the toxicity was in the mitochondria
when they did the initial work?
They did some later work to address this when they wanted to move this to the FDA.
But the point is, in the first studies from this group, the most effective dose was the
lowest dose.
And it was in the monotherapy group.
No, no, this was before that study.
Before that study that you're citing.
Oh, this is the phase two.
That was the first study.
In the first study, they found some effect with a very low dose.
And in the higher doses that would approximate these anti-tau effects, they found no effects.
And they turned this around in such a way that in one of the papers published in the
Journal of Alzheimer's disease, that a friend of mine is the editor, they claimed that actually
the highest dose, there was a problem with the absorption.
And it was really a low dose.
And the lowest dose was more easily absorbed.
And it was really then the high dose.
And then they changed the result to indicate all the low dose was the high and the high
dose was the low.
And that's why it worked.
So in other words, they did not change their hypothesis that was contradicted by their
data, which is the same thing that's been happening with the amyloid people.
Their results do not support their hypothesis and they keep blindly moving forward.
So now what you explain was because they have difficulties getting a patent for this compound,
they created this reduced version of methyl and blue and did similar studies.
But in that study, they had the problem that the majority of the people, if you are having
Alzheimer's disease and you're in a hospital or being treated by usually neurologists or
sometimes psychiatrists, they would prescribe unfortunately, unfortunately, drugs that have
no benefit to the patients, but produce adverse effects such as cholinesterase inhibitors and
memantine.
And the idea being as well, this is the standard of care.
It would be quote unquote unethical to take these patients off these agents even to allow
them to enter another trial.
Well, that may be the reasoning that some people may have, but that's actually the opposite
of what's happening.
These drugs are ineffective and is unethical to continue to use these ineffective dose that
are having these toxic and adverse effects on people.
If you go back to the original studies that were used by the FDA to approve these drugs
and the reviews that were done subsequently by like the Crochain groups meta-analysis,
they all conclude very clearly that these drugs are ineffective and they do not improve
activities of daily living and that the disease continues and progress and people die.
In fact, in countries where they have more elaborate longitudinal data like in the UK
of administration of these compounds to patients with Alzheimer's, they know that they die
sooner if they're taking these medications that the ones that refuse to take them.
And the UK made an attempt.
In fact, they banned these compounds because they had evidence-based that not only they
weren't effective, but they were counterproductive.
And within a year, the public demanded to the politicians because if they're used in
the US, they must be beneficial.
And so this is a decision that was done politically, motivated to bring them back and make them
available even though we have all the evidence, just like we have against the amyloid hypothesis
that the cholinergic hypothesis of Alzheimer's disease is also irrelevant.
I actually, it's funny, I didn't realize people still subscribe to that hypothesis.
The most commonly prescribed medications are the cholinestarase inhibitors.
And then the FDA did not approve memantine for early Alzheimer's or mild Alzheimer's
or myocardium impairment.
They approved originally only for severe and then later for moderate and severe, which
was very unfortunate.
The memantine is preventing some of the excitotoxicity that is damaging those hippocampal cells.
But essentially what you're doing when you do that, you are rescuing from dying a cell
that is functionally incompetent.
Yeah.
So indirectly, which is interesting because there was a study that came out about a month
and a half ago on memantine.
And I remember, you know, this is obviously not my field of expertise.
So my level of knowledge in the literature is so much less than other areas.
But the problem with that could be that you're actually rescuing a cell that's going to
go on to send a signal that could cause more damage down the line.
It is completely counterproductive and is based on the pathology, pathology oriented
that you can see more of these neurons there when the people die.
But it's not a functional assay.
In other words, it's a neuropathological, which there's value in these things, but it
sounds like the real overarching challenge here is triangulating between neurobiology,
anatomy, functional signaling.
And then of course, ultimately clinical outcomes matter more than any of these other things
in the end.
I agree.
And that's what should direct all of this in the first place.
And it's not what's happening.
Now, I know this is a little outside of the work you do, but do you have a point of view
on the recent excitement around Herpesymplex virus 1?
Have you followed that discussion?
No.
I don't have a good point of view.
What I can tell you is we found another way to try to intervene with mitochondrial respiration
using light, in particular, infrared light that can go through the tissues.
And the photons in the near infrared light are absorbed by cytochrome oxidase.
It turns out that cytochrome oxidase, that's the name cytosil, but chrome color, is because
of its exhaust, certain wavelengths, and it reflects other sources, the chemical in
the cell that gives color to the cell.
And this property of photonic absorption we have used in conjunction with the laser delivery
of near infrared light transcranially through the forehead as a source of photons that actually
oxidizes, photo oxidizes, cytochrome oxidase.
And by doing that, the enzyme has more affinity.
That's the confirmation of the enzyme that has more affinity to oxygen for oxygen consumption.
Yeah, I just pulled out a picture that we'll make sure we link to in the show notes that
comes from one of your papers, actually, where it shows in the same figure a close section
of the mitochondria, and you can see the effect of methylene blue and also the effect of near
infrared light.
Now, it strikes me as interesting that you can get the wavelength just right because
you have to be able to get through not just the tissue, but the skull itself.
Actually, the skull is less of a problem.
It's easier to go through.
Because it's porous because of the bony matrix?
Yeah, because there is less circulation through it.
One of the big promo force that we have is hemoglobin.
I see.
So hemoglobin can absorb and reflect much of this light before it actually reaches the
neurons.
So what we try to do is we move away from this peak of absorption, so oxy and deoxy
hemoglobin, to one that is still can be absorbed by cytochrome oxidase.
To how many nanometers then?
We use 1,064 nanometers wavelength, so around 1,000, which is a wavelength that is not very
well studied in biochemistry.
Most of the spectrophotometers in biochemistry, they do not go all the way to 1,000.
Yeah, they're in the hundreds, usually.
Yes, they usually.
300 to 800 or something to that.
Yes.
The longer the wavelength, the more it penetrates to the tissues.
How do we know how safe that is?
I'm sure somebody listening to this is going to say, wait, that sounds like microwaving
my brain.
Like, ha, ha.
No, no.
Of course, it's a different wavelength.
No, I understand.
But as the sort of lay person, this sounds very scary, right?
Yeah, microwaves moving the other direction.
But the longer the wavelength, the less energy they carry.
So the less they can penetrate.
So they cannot really penetrate inside atoms like the ones that have short wavelengths.
But they are good enough to penetrate to the tissues, not very deep.
And only about 1 to 2%, if we do it transcranially through the head, actually goes through to
the surface of the cerebral cortex.
Once in the cerebral cortex, the white matter is also a barrier.
So the effect of the photons is primarily in the gray matter layer of the cerebral cortex.
And what it does is it you donate in these photons to the electron transport.
So you're bypassing the electron donors.
The photons are not identical to electrons, but they act in a similar way in the electron
transport.
So the photons and the electrons are very similar.
The difference is that the electron can carry a very small mass.
Photons essentially do not have mass.
And by providing photons to the electron transport, you keep the electron transport going because
these enzymes engage in the redox changes.
And the more photons you send to cytochrome oxidase, the more of the enzyme quickly goes
to the oxidized conformation.
And that oxidized conformation is the one that has more affinity to bind oxygen.
But I don't understand how is this actually making its way systemically to the brain through
a transcranial stimulation?
When you aim through, for example, the forehead, it goes through the tissue and reaches the
surface of the cerebral cortex.
And that's how it makes its way.
It's a more localized, it's different from, it's not a systemic administration like metal
in blue.
It's enough to just be able to hit the frontal cortex to create a clinical improvement without
impacting the mitochondrial function deeper in the midbrain or lower part of the cortex.
To create a functional improvement, we don't know yet about clinicals, especially I would
not say that in somebody with the degree of atrophy that many of the Alzheimer's patients
have, we're going to have enough substrate there to be able to stimulate and reverse
the disease.
So this will have to be tested with clinical population.
Are there clinical trials that are going to be looking at this near infrared light strategy
combined with methylene blue?
No, not combined.
You don't think of these as synergistic.
You consider these separate approaches?
Yeah, I consider them separate approaches.
The reason for this is the following.
Methylene blue can affect these photons.
Of course, that makes sense.
And this is actually used nowadays.
For example, dermatologists, if you have a melanoma, a cancer in your skin, or any other
lesion, they can inject methylene blue into that region and then they just shine light.
And the light.
It concentrates the light.
The methylene blue and the methylene blue oxidizes.
You've had that Ross reaction, the same thing that you see in the bladder.
And it kills those cells there.
This is called photodynamic therapy.
It has many applications because if you have a virus that you have no other way to kill,
you can always kill it this way.
So this is happening.
Even people don't know, methylene blue is injected into blood that is used for transfusion
so that you can then treat this blood with these bright lights.
And by photodynamic therapy, kill viruses like the HIV virus or the herpes.
Is there a difference between giving the methylene blue orally versus intravenously?
Yes.
For this purpose specifically.
The intravenous one, the first target will be the blood cells.
So you have to be more careful with the concentration because you don't want to promote the methemoglobinear.
In other words, to compete with oxygen.
So it seems safer to administer oral?
Yes.
The oral administration produces slower release and in low concentration is very safe.
And it's like I say, it's being done in thousands and thousands of people for malaria.
And it's studies that are being published in the last few years have primarily given
to children in Africa for killing the parasites.
And in that case, the oral administration at the advantage that many of these parasites
are in the gut as well.
Yeah, in the gut.
So you can have the higher amounts there.
So going back to this broader perspective, I mean, the clear theme here is, which I think
is that prevention matters.
In fact, we shouldn't be focusing so many resources on the treatment of clinically
evident apparent dementia for the reasons you've discussed.
So now what we want to do is prevent.
I was going to say prevent in high risk individuals, but as one of my friends who's a neurologist
would say, anybody with a brain is at risk.
So let's stop stratifying as who's high risk versus low risk.
Everybody should take a preventative measure.
Yes, definitely.
In addition to this idea of all the things that matter in the heart, so lower smoking,
lower blood pressure, better glycemic control, better management of lipoproteins, et cetera,
et cetera, is there anything that you see is unique in the brain specifically that is
maybe not unique or maybe not as important in the prevention of cardiovascular disease?
The only one that I would say will have to do with the ketogenic diet.
Ketogenic diet will facilitate mitochondrial respiration in a different way, but this will
contribute to targeting mitochondrial respiration so that the brain will benefit more than the
heart.
The heart will benefit.
Of course, all of these tissues will benefit, but because of the brain reliance on aerobic
metabolism.
For example, you alluded, for example, an insulin resistance.
One of the problems that happens as the brain ages, even in normal people, is that the transport
of glucose is affected.
So even though we can increase glucose levels in the blood or what we're eating, we cannot
get that glucose being transported to the brain as effectively as in the younger individuals.
That's why some of these studies with intranasal insulin administration show transient improvement
in symptoms, presumably because they're becoming resistant to glucose.
Now that's obviously not a long-term solution, but it illustrates a point.
And unfortunately, insulin primarily facilitates glucose transports in other tissues other than
the brain.
The brain actually doesn't require insulin.
It can boost its transport of glucose, but the reason for that is that when you wake
up in the morning that you have been fasting overnight, whatever levels of glucose are
circulating in your blood, then the brain tissue will be the only one that will be able
to take that up.
And it's only when you have large glucose levels that then insulin is released by the
pancreas and then all the tissues then can use it, can feast on it.
So the ketogenic diet, so ketone bodies can act as an alternative source for energy in
the brain.
And the important point is that even though glucose is a preferred substrate during aging,
this is compromised, this uptake.
However, the uptake of ketone bodies is not compromised.
Therefore, you could satisfy some of these nutritional requirements by adding the ketone
bodies to the diet.
Do you think it matters if a person is on a ketogenic diet or if they're on a non-ketogenic
diet, but they supplement with exogenous ketones?
I hope it doesn't matter.
As long as you have the ketone bodies available, you don't require to have the ketogenic diet
itself.
But this eventually will have to be resolved empirically.
And there is no question that this is going to promote mitochondrial respiration.
And we know, as you know, when we were born as infants, we rely primarily for neural function
and everything else on these ketone bodies produced by the liver.
Not because of the kind of lipids that we get through the mother's milk.
So essentially, what we're trying to do is bring in somebody who is in all age to rely
more on ketosis.
That is a process that we know exists under physiological conditions every day.
If we go beyond 12, 14 hours without eating, we start generating this.
But it's something that we know in infancy is the primary source for the brain.
I didn't realize that.
Is that more a result of their livers not being able to release enough glycogen via
an empataglucose output?
I mean, I know they have a very high demand for energy.
Can you measure the ketone in their blood?
Yes, but it is because of the source of food that they're taking.
I see.
So they're basically getting medium chain triglycerides through the milk.
Yes.
Medium chain triglycerides being the main source there for energy conversion as opposed
to some of the other triglycerides.
So the original bulletproof coffee is actually mother's breast milk before it is the fancy
coffees that everybody drinks.
Yes.
So I do believe that that's another alternative.
So in essence, you could potentially have pharmacological interventions that address
mitochondrial respiration, but they will not have to be classic pharmacology like neurotransmitter
based pharmacology.
There will be more of a metabolic pharmacology.
You can have near infrared light by providing this photonic stimulation.
However, that one is targeted is not systemic like you pointed out.
So one will have to find the target.
Luckily, the forehead is more accessible.
We don't have hairs and we can target that prefrontal cortex that shows the initial
cognitive difficulties as people become older.
And that's what we have been doing.
And then the third one will be through the diet, which you facilitate because as you
pointed out, the insulin resistance is because our glucose levels are going up because we
cannot transport it into the tissue, especially nervous tissue, which was a primary consumer
has effectively.
And then we have these high levels of glucose for longer times.
So there's more insulin that is being released and then this desensitizes the resectors.
So there is a natural development of metabolic syndrome as we grow old because of this phenomenon.
These manifest itself then has less substrate or energy for the brain.
And then you have a cognitive decline accelerated associated with obesity and hypertension and
this insulin resistance.
So it's all part of the same age related picture.
And probably people eat more because they are trying to make up for this lack of energy
that the brain is consuming.
And if any organ is more liable to influence our eating behavior, it will be the neural
tissue.
That's such an interesting thought because I've always believed as you've suggested that
I think our appetite is driven by fundamentally important physiologic processes and starvation
would be the most important among them.
And starvation in the modern world doesn't look like starvation in the prehistoric world.
Starvation in the modern world can be in the presence of obesity because we're not talking
about the obvious.
We're talking about the cellular level.
And so if cellular metabolism is deficient, which is often the case in insulin resistance,
an individual can be functionally starving and that can drive it.
Now I've always thought about it through the lens of the liver, but you're making an argument
that says there's also a central starvation that could be also driving these repetitive
changes.
Yes.
But there are also peripheral components, like you say, for example, the case of the obese.
An individual that has obesity will, by almost definition, will have down regulated the ketogenesis.
The ketogenesis enzymes will not be upregulated unless you're consuming your own fat.
And these are trainable enzymes, like endusable as well.
So if you don't go through periods of fasting, you cannot elevate these enzymes.
So somebody who is obese and suddenly stops eating is starved because his body cannot.
In the presence of hyperinsulinemia, it is a very painful transition into fasting.
You cannot use your body fat to feed, especially the brain, which is the first one that is
going to give you these signs and symptoms.
So the first thing that somebody has to do is start out by having a periodic period of
fasting that in my own case, I do it once a week.
Usually between Friday and Saturday, I fast for at least 14 or 16 hours.
It's not difficult to do if you have an early meal and then a late brunch, you will have
significant fasting and you can accelerate that process by consuming some of the circulating
glucose if you do a workout that morning.
So by doing that, I am allowing my body to build up these ketogenic enzymes.
And therefore, then during a regular day in the week, if I don't eat anything between
meals, I don't feel hungry because I can consume my own body fat.
And people who are obese cannot do that.
They don't have the biochemical machinery to do it.
So I believe that's probably the third way of approaching this problem.
If those three things could be used and like I say, it may not be possible to combine some
of them.
I will have to empirically determine how much metal and blue one can have systemically so
that to not produce a photodynamic effect when I do transcranial laser stimulation.
We hope in the future we may be able to do this with LEDs.
Right now with the LEDs are commercially available.
We haven't been able to find the results that we get, but we are investing time in trying
to change this.
So it will be safer and cheaper to do.
So right now, the only ones.
So my bioengineering colleagues has been able to collaborate with me and develop a device
that we can transcranially do imaging with near infrared spectroscopy and actually measure
the concentrations of oxidized cytochrome oxidase in vivo in the human brain.
We published that last year.
And this allows us to directly have a measurement that we are indeed engaging our target.
And this also will allow us to find what is the optimal dose response for that particular
brain.
Because like you indicated, different people have different heads and the transmission
would not be equivalent.
So this is what we're doing.
So we have obtained three major grants for doing this with the bioengineering group in
the Dallas area.
For example, Professor Henley Liu.
We are doing the development of these devices to monitor the physiological changes.
And this is a grant by NEIH that is called the Brain Initiative Program.
And then here with my colleague, Andrea Ann Halley, we have a grant from the National
Institute of Aging to test this transcranial near infrared light in older people and people
with mild cognitive impairment.
And then the third has been a benefactor who's giving us large amounts of money so that we
can pursue this line of work with the transcranial lasers.
And I can show you the endorsement from some of the people in the field.
Oh, yeah, I'll take a picture of this and we'll put this on.
In fact, it was actually Jack who directed me to speak with you maybe six months ago.
This is exciting.
You know, I want to add one other thought to this, which is I hope that if somebody's
listening to this who's involved in traumatic brain injury that someone ought to look into
a clinical trial of using methylene blue as a rescue agent during periods of traumatic
injury, because again, mechanistically, it's at least plausible that you could salvage
and rescue some of the transient insult and the damage that goes through that.
And again, there's another example of a disease for which we don't seem to have any solution
other than the obvious, which is avoidance of the injury, the insult.
But there's still a lot of people out there that are being exposed to repetitive head
trauma.
And, you know, as you probably know, there's been some interesting hypotheses around the
presence of ketones in the system before traumatic injury and potentially a salvage
after.
But it seems to me that this methylene blue story probably deserves a bit more attention
in other areas, given these properties you've described.
I actually agree with you.
And I would say because it's used in emergency rooms, I believe in every ambulance, you should
have methylene blue available.
And if there is any insult that compromises metabolic supply to the brain, you're going
to be better off infusing methylene blue at a low concentration.
We're talking about one milligram per kilogram concentration that is going to be neuroprotective,
regardless of the source of the...
It could be transiting its chemical track.
It could be any stroke.
We have done this in stroke models in animals using the methylene blue.
And we're being able to rescue the majority of the damage produced in the in part in
animal models, and animal models where we look at these longitudinally using fMRI.
So we know these works in animals.
I've just been unable to convince emergency physicians to start doing this to their ischemic
patients.
And not only for the brain, but ischemia affecting all the other organs, is being also trying
to protect the animal models of neurotrauma with similar benefits.
So the problem is there's no interest by the pharmaceutical company because they cannot
make money on it.
And unfortunately, the NEIH is also influenced by...
If you're using an old drug, essentially you're repositioning this old drug for these other
applications as a neuroprotective agent or more generally metabolic protective agent.
They are concerned that their investment is not going to pan out because when it goes
to commercialization, you're not going to be able to patent that medication.
And believe it or not, even though if it works, if there is no prospect that profits can be
made, they don't want to invest.
Yeah, it's a shame because I worry that we'll be in this state of limbo where we're not
really going to know the answer and we can't know the answer without clinical trials.
This is about as easy an agent as there is to study given its long history, its relatively
well understood toxicity profile, and in many cases, the speed with which you could see
a response, especially if you're studying ischemic events.
And I will tell you that just a couple of years ago, it was published last year, the
group that I collaborated with in San Antonio, we were the first to show the effects of methyl
and blue in the human brain using fMRI and measuring blood flow and measuring ball signals.
And also in those subjects, we did memory testing and we were able to demonstrate a
significant improvement in their memory retrieval just after an acute treatment with methyl
and blue in a blind placebo control study.
The first time that that was done, contrary to these other groups that are doing it as
an anti-towel agent in healthy and older people, we can improve memory and we can demonstrate
using imaging that we can do this through methyl and blue.
So the only problem is that there's not going to be any profit because I believe if some
company would like to develop this purity, pharmaceutical grade, methyl and blue, there
will be a huge market.
Other companies may imitate them, but there's enough for everybody.
Still, the cosmetic aspect of having urine that is a problem many people would not accept.
Yeah.
Well, Francisco, this has been great.
You've been very generous with your time and I really appreciate this discussion.
I've learned a lot and I'm guessing that people listening to this will have also learned a
lot.
So we will have a great set of show notes to accompany this where all of the papers
that we've talked about, a link to Jack's book and a number of other things will be
included so that hopefully it's a reference for anyone else you want to share this with
and certainly anyone listening.
So thank you very much.
Thank you, Pete.
You can find all of this information and more at petertiamd.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog at petertiamd.com.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week
email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram and Facebook, all with the ID petertiamd,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing or other professional healthcare
services, including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own
risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical
advice, diagnoses or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they
have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash about.