Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession
with this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information
is basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their
lives. Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the
podcast, that became clear to me. The sheer volume of material published in this space
is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing
this information with you. To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own.
In fact, we now have a full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and their
feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural question. How will we continue
to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know, the tried and true way
to do this is to sell ads, but after a lot of contemplation, that model just doesn't
feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know
I'm being paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling
ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time
advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about
something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically. So instead of selling
ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can work over time, and
that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience. This keeps my relationship
with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and
support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above
and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my goal to ensure that no
matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more than you give.
So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes, including
other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each episode.
These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many
of our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular
Ask Me Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and
also getting to hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm
really excited about, I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products
that I love. And as I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd
like to do is work with companies who make the products that I already love and would
already talk about for free and have them pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast
will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will find enough value in one,
the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members to support us
at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider
supporting us directly by signing up for a monthly subscription.
My guest this week is Dr. Ted Schaeffer, the chairman of urology at Northwestern University
in Chicago. He's a urologist who specializes in the diagnosis and treatment of prostate
cancer. His high quality work has earned him the trust of people like Ben Stiller, who
he's operated on and who have spoken very publicly about his own battle with prostate
cancer. In this episode, we go through all of the current and basic best practices for
the screening and treatment of prostate cancer, from the latest drugs to the surgical options.
The conversation naturally leads to our evolving understanding of cancer and the most exciting
areas of research in prostate cancer specifically. We also touch on the controversy around the
role of things like testosterone replacement in the development of prostate cancer and
even the controversy surrounding prostate screening using things like the PSA. And finally,
if you're an MD PhD student, which I realize might not be many of you, you'll want to listen
closely as Ted has some of the most pertinent and in my opinion, most important advice for
those who are deciding on how to thread this needle of being clinicians and scientists.
So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with one of my closest friends
from residency, Dr. Ted Schaeffer.
Hey man, how are you?
I'm great. Good to see you.
Dude, it's kind of weird when I go and visit my friends from residency and I see them in
their grown up clothes and their grown up offices. It kind of makes me feel like I failed.
Well, your office is stunning. The view over the lake in Chicago and admittedly, this might
be the best month of the year to be in Chicago, but it's like we're in the elevator coming
up here and I'm, I feel like we're supposed to be goofing off like we always did. And
I'm like, wait, we can't goof off. He's now the chairman of urology. We got to be serious.
It's true. When I, when I look at, I'm looking at you here doing this recording and I can't
help but just chuckle.
So we'll get to all the med school stuff or the residency stuff, because that's obviously
where we met, but let's talk a little bit about your decision to even do a PhD. And
you know, you have kind of an interesting story there because you weren't on the typical
MD PhD path, right?
Yeah. I, you know, people ask me about my life and how I got to where I am. And there's
a couple of principles I think about and they're common themes that we share together.
But one of the things I teach or talk to my trainees about is, you know, you never walk
by an open door without looking inside. And so that's how I ended up being at the NIH,
doing my PhD. But even before that, I think the way my brain was built was that I always
wanted to see what was inside the open door, inside the alarm clock, inside the watch.
And so conceptually, as I moved through my training, I liked biology because I wanted
to understand how things worked. I loved organic chemistry. I loved putting the puzzles together,
making things happen. And so as an extension of that, when you're in medical school and
you're learning about the pathology of why things, you know, fail, understanding that
at a cellular level just always appealed to me. And I loved the ICU. I loved the, you
know, the physiology of the human body and how you can measure all that. And so I think
about that a lot because I, you know, read and been following your blogs and your life
and how you analyze everything you do. And so for me in medical school, it was a lunchtime
thing. I went by this open door and there was this opportunity to apply for a scholarship
through Howard Hughes Medical Institution to really go study science at the NIH. And
I had started college and school early. So I had about a, I felt like I had a year to
kind of play around and see what was interesting to me. And it was something that was out of
the box for me, but I just, you know, when you find something that makes sense, it's
no longer risky to you. You're not exposing yourself to anything. It's really just exploration.
And so that, that came very natural because I'm not the type of person who likes to take
on risk, do different things. But for me, it wasn't a risk to just leave medical school
and go to the NIH. It was an opportunity.
When you were in college, did you know you wanted to go into medical school?
I think so. Yeah. I loved, I loved biology. I loved understanding the way things were
and how they worked. And you know, the most complex of all those things is the human body
and just a living organism, a multicellular organism is just incredibly fascinating to
me. So I was always attracted to that. And so I thought, you know, that was a natural
extension of it. I remember when I was in college, there was a very famous anthropologist
at University of Chicago who was one of these dinosaur hunters. And so I just, you know,
I loved, I loved the idea of just discovery. And I love that idea of anatomy and discovering
what dinosaurs were like and how they did that. I remember I talked to my father, who's
a physician, and I said, you know, I think I want to go off to grad school and be an
anthropologist. And he's like, you're gonna do what? You know, but that concept of discovery,
innovation, figuring things out, it's just something that I've always had in me. So you
don't just go to NIH. How did you wind up in the lab of a Nobel laureate? Well, it was through a
friend of mine. So when this program I was in, you know, you went and you interviewed in different
labs and you basically decided what you wanted to do. And some people, it was an incredibly
talented group, it was about 40 medical students from all over the country. So some of these people,
they're just amazing. They knew what they wanted to do. They knew what field, who they wanted to
work with and so forth. I wasn't sure what I wanted to do. I knew I wanted to pursue this
idea of discovery and pursue it at a high level. And I remember there's a guy named Jonathan
Ashwell, he was an immunologist. And I thought, well, maybe I should do immunology mostly because
I didn't really understand immunology very well for my medical school class. It was a weak kind
of class for me. So I went and talked to him and he said, you know, he's a really tough guy,
very successful hardcore scientist. And at the NIH immunology there was just really, really,
you know, just amazing. And he said, listen, you just got to pick a guy. He was really tough. He
just said, look, just can a man up pick something and you'll get into it and you'll love it. And I
thought, you know, that was actually good advice, you know. And so I was shopping around for somebody
who was motivated, who was driven and who was smart to work with. And a good friend of mine,
who's actually here at Northwestern, Grant Barish, you should look at this, go talk to this woman,
Pam Swartzberg. She's a postdoc in the Varmus lab and she's looking for a student and she's
really good. And so I went and interviewed with her and she was exactly what I wanted. I'm a
brilliant scientist and she happened to be in the Varmus lab. But, you know, the Varmus lab was a
bunch of postdocs who would be effectively associate or full professors at any other
university. They were just incredibly smart people. And I got to, you know, these individuals
are just amazing. So I met her and then worked through her with him. And the plan was always to,
she had already been offered a position as a researcher at the NIH and she was waiting to
transition to her own lab. So we, yes, technically I was a Varmus lab member for six or nine months.
And, but all along I was mentored by this woman, Pam Swartzberg, who was just a brilliant scientist.
And when she was a tech in her lab at Columbia, she was making, you know, she was had covers of
cell, you know, she was just brilliant. So Harold attracted people like this in his lab group and we
stayed part of his lab group, although independent throughout my kind of experience there. And I
always considered our group to be equal, but part of his group. So it was, it was a lot of fun to
interact with him on a weekly basis during lab meetings, just to see how he thought. I mean,
you know, like you, I like to surround myself with people who are just incredibly smart.
And by being a member of his lab team, I by default did that, not just him, but many,
many other people. So it was really fun. For the listener, of course, Harold Varmus and Michael
Bishop shared the Nobel prize probably in the late eighties or early nineties. It was like 88,
89, 90, something like that, right? They basically were the first people to elucidate the relationship
between viruses and oncogenes. Is that correct? Right. Yeah. So the concept of their, their prize
was, and I'll probably butcher this and the real scientists out there will kill me for it. But,
you know, the idea was that they described that there's this, you know, you could pass on a cancer
through a viral induction. And so these viral oncogenes was what they described. So they were
an active alteration in the cells, normal machinery to, to induce a cancer. You know,
I've never met Harold, but I did have the privilege of having dinner with Michael Bishop
once a few years ago. And it was a very intimate, you know, there's like four people there,
but everyone was either a Nobel laureate or will be a Nobel laureate sort of thing. You know,
Lou Cantley, David Sabatini, Michael Bishop. And, you know, it's just one of those nights. Like you
don't want it to end. You can't believe that, you know, cause we were at a steakhouse and we were
sort of sequestered in our own little room. And we probably spent like five hours there just talking
about their work. It was amazing. You said something a second ago that I love. I didn't
know this about you actually. So this is the fun thing of interviewing your best boys is you still
learned something. Part of the reason you retracted immunology is you felt it was a weakness. And
having spoken with a number of very good scientists, I find that to be a very common thread.
The great ones seem to go towards their weaknesses rather than away from them. Steve Rosenberg,
who was my mentor at the NCI, I always talked about the reason he did. He always knew he wanted
to be an immunologist, always non-negotiable, but he did his PhD in biophysics because he didn't want
to be intimidated by these differential equations when he read papers. Like he really wanted to
understand a field of science that didn't come, you know, sort of easily to him. So that's sort
of an interesting aside about you. Yeah, it was funny. I had a great mentor and worked hard and
on paper had a great PhD. And I remember was degree granted through the University of Chicago.
So again, I wasn't in a formal PhD program. There was an open door for me to do this great
program and opportunity at the NIH. I went there for a year. I just loved it. I loved the research
environment. And from there, I petitioned to stay an additional year and I didn't really know what
it meant to have a PhD. I mean, I wasn't going there for a PhD. I was going there to do science.
But I had friends that were in formal MD PhD programs at University of Chicago. And they were
like, man, you know, what you've done is PhD students would die for. And I was like, well,
I don't know. I'm just doing my thing, you know. So at that time I was an idiot and I was kind of
ballsy. So I wrote a letter to my Dean and I said, well, I think I should be, I should be,
someone should give me a PhD for this stuff. And they said, well, why don't you fly back and why
don't you give us a talk? And I did. And they were like, okay, yeah, you do know what you're
talking about. And what you had published, you have actually a very similar story to another
good friend of mine who, you know, was in a similar situation where he basically was in
the right place at the right time, right? Was in a great lab, very well mentored, great project,
and was willing to like go to the wall for it and ends up getting a first authorship in science and
nature. And it's sort of like, you just have to hand those in and that becomes a PhD.
That's the idea, you know. And so yes, all the critical thinking and how to develop and
come up with a hypothesis and test it. I did all those things. So I mean, I met all the formal
criteria for it. I just did it in a, I wasn't in a structured way. It just happened to be in a good
environment. What was the most interesting question you were asking during your time at NIH?
Well, I mean, I think immunology and really I think I was more in a cell signaling lab. And
so a lot of what we did was biochemistry. And the idea was, you know, well, you would take a
single protein and you'd knock it out or turn it on or whatever, and it would have a huge effect.
And I think at that time people were thinking really very linearly, you know. I had, I mean,
my PhD was pretty much the most amazing experience you can imagine. So on my floor in building 49,
it was- This was in the old center.
This is before- Before the new
middle center was built, which was-
But building 49 was a genome Institute. It was across the street from the NCI
buildings, which I think were 35 and 37 or something like that. So on my floor was Harold
Varmus, you know, Varmus lab. I was technically in our own lab with Pam, but we shared the
last space with Francis Collins. So, you know, it was just, I mean, you couldn't just pick a better
floor to have just people on. And so at that time genomics and transcriptomics and-
This is the mid 90s.
This is 97 to 99. So, I mean, people were just starting to do homemade microarrays and looking
at expression. And I remember people would like take a muscle cell and they compare it to a fiber
blast and they would be like, oh my God, you can see these different expression changes in these
homemade microarrays. And so that's when everything was just taking off. I remember Lou Stout, who's
still at the NIH, who was working on, there was a Howard Hughes student working on lymphomas and
just characterizing the different genomic phenotypes of them. And people still use that
stuff today. It's pretty amazing. And so I was there when all that was happening. I remember
when I went there, you know, at University of Chicago, people really weren't on the internet.
And then I show up and I go to the lab and there's T1 lines at the NIH and the internet. And
I remember downloading the Clinton debacle, you know, and reading that in detail. And so like,
there's all these just amazing things that happened in science and happened in
technology that were going on at that period of my life and that period in the world. It was pretty,
it was pretty amazing. So, the thing that's a long answer to the concept that when I went there,
I think people were still focused on single gene, single change. They're still looking for the like,
well, you have this mutation, you get this cancer, this mutation, you have this phenotype.
And you know, the human body is a polygenetic organism.
Yeah, at last count, if there's 20,000 human genes, I believe there's something like 73,
but I could be wrong. Let's just call it a hundred and round up. There were about
only a hundred disease states that result from single gene mutations out of 20,000 genes.
Yeah. So, you know, that was the big thing, the big transition in Francis Collins was really leading
that where there were people hunting for the gene for type 2 diabetes at the time I was there. And
of course, now we understand it's a complex equation. And so within immunology, when I was
there, it was also a transition. So, it turns out that the tyrosine kinases that I worked on in my
PhD are really involved in fine tuning the T cell receptor signaling. They're really rheostats.
They really fine tune the signal. It's not off or on just like, you know, you have a mutation in X,
Y, or Z off or on. And so I think one of the big themes of what was evolving at the time I was
there was this concept that was a fine tuning. And I remember we would do immunology retreats in the
road. So, another way to explain this maybe for the listener, because of course I hear rheostat and
I think about rheostats because I'm an engineer. Digital is a signal. It's on or off. That's right.
Zero or one. Analog is like the volume button on your radio. You can go from nothing to full blast,
but an infinite number of iterations in between. And that's what you mean by modulating the signal.
Right. And I think that that was a period of transition in science where maybe people
always thought that that happened, but people were developing the tools to begin to test that
and understand that. And you think about cancer immunology and the Rosenberg lab was a huge
player on campus when I was there, which was 10 years before you were there and they were
hunting for single tumor antigens, right? But then they were realizing that it's a complicated
thing and there's multiple factors that come into the role and into play there. So,
for me, that was maybe conceptually something people had always thought about,
but the tools to explore that, the tools to test that on multi-gene levels were kind of coming
online in science at that time. So, it was a pretty fun time to do that.
Talk a little bit about a tyrosine kinase. I mean, these are so ubiquitous in biology
and they just come up over and over again. So, explain to someone who doesn't understand what
that is, what it is, and why it's relevant and maybe where it shows up.
You have your DNA, everybody's born with it. It's in every single cell in your body,
but the skin cells in your body make a certain amount of melanin that make you darker than I am.
And so, within between different people, there's variability in what the individual cells do with
the DNA and then within the human body, there's different cell types and they use the DNA,
the code differently. That code then is incredibly, it's modified by exposure to the environment and
that's the epigenetic change and what results is a protein. And so, once you have a protein,
that's really what kind of constitutes a lot of what's in our cells in our body,
but they're not inert. They're constantly changing. And so, one of the ways that they change and one
of the ways that the signals change within an individual cell, how the cells communicate with
each other, etc., is by having kind of temporary modifications to those individual proteins. And so,
one of the ways that happens is through these kinases and there's different pieces of the
proteins that can be modified. So, one of them is a tyrosine kinase, but there are other types of
kinases and these are temporary modifications that happen within a protein, within a cell,
to typically transmit a more acute or change within the cell or between two cells and so forth.
And of course, these have become a very attractive target for drugs.
Yeah. So, one of the, obviously the idea in cancer biology is to find alterations, to find mutations,
to find changes that you can quote unquote target to do precision oncology, precision medicine. And
so, these are one of the ways that we're beginning to think about advancing the kind of medicine in
that special way. GleeVac targets a tyrosine kinase, doesn't it? It does. It targets a specifically
altered fused gene. So, it's not just a random tyrosine kinase. It's a tyrosine kinase that's
altered by specific mutation within a cancer. I mean, that was how I was originally described.
And so, yes, it will target those and have a specific effect and that was work done
on the West Coast in part by Charles Sawyer's who's now a memorial who's an idol of mine,
but he wasn't the only one involved in kind of identifying this fused mutation.
It's sort of one of those exceptions to this rule, right? Where if you have that mutation,
which basically is, if I recall, is only showing up in CML and GI stromal tumors, correct?
That's right.
Then you do have the one hit wonder. You do.
This drug is, at least in the CML, it seems curative. I don't recall if it was actually
curative in GI stromal tumors or if it was just basically could render it a chronic disease.
For the GI stromal tumors, it's not my space, but yeah, it works. But there is resistance
that develops, I think, in both models now. But in general, for the liquid tumors, it's
much more durable. And for the GI stromals, it does help to suppress the growth of those tumors.
Some of them do recur and come back. And that's the concepts of how we manage and we've converted
HIV AIDS from a lethal disease to a chronic condition, really, those basic principles of
multi-targeting of the particular cell. So for cancer, a single agent like Levek
isn't going to work because the cells change and alter, but doing double or triple targeting will
be an effective long-term approach for those, just like we've learned from HIV management.
I'm sure today, you're now the chairman of Urology, so you encounter lots of residents
and medical students. And if one of them came to you and said, hey, Ted, or I guess they'd have
to call you Dr. Shafer, but I'm really thinking about doing a PhD. And what advice would you
give them to select a good lab? In other words, you describe so much of your trajectory is you're
the beneficiary of having been exceptionally well mentored. And you've talked about PAM
now and before. I know we've talked about just when you have an amazing mentor, it's like
everything works out. And yet there are countless students who go into labs that just couldn't waste
more time. They don't actually learn how to think properly. They come out as dumb as they were when
they went in and the field has not advanced. So in as much as surrounding yourself by the right
people is the best first step you can take, what guidance would you give somebody to, what questions
should they be asking? What things should they be looking for, either positive or negative, to help
them think through that? Well, I think you've had an opportunity to interact with brilliant scientists
all along. And for me, it's the brilliant scientists, it's brilliant clinicians, it's just
brilliant people. So what are the essence of those people? That's how I would think about it.
And mentorship matters, obviously, brain power matters, motivation matters. So, you know, why is
it that some PhD students are not successful? Sure, you can attribute some of it to mentorship,
but I really think that it has to do with motivation and drive. And that's such a critical
part of it. So then you'd say, well, why is somebody not motivated? Why aren't they driven?
I mean, I guess some people are biologically built that way. But I also think maybe, you know,
if you wanted to be nicer about it, you could say, well, maybe they just haven't found what
they're passionate about, because I think that drive, passion, they're very, and then they come
from the same part of your heart or your brain. And so I think part of that is just that, you know,
have they found the right area? Now there are still, having said that, there are people that
are just super passionate about something and they want to do it and they just can't, you know,
maybe they just need to kind of move along. But I think that in my experience in grad school is that
there are, usually you can, it's not that hard to identify grad students that aren't successful.
It's pretty easy to find out, well, they're missing a major, one of those components.
So you head back to University of Chicago, you wrap up your last two years of medical school,
at which point you have to decide what you want to be when you grow up and you pick urology.
Yeah. So I went to University of Chicago undergrad. So I spent 11 years at University of Chicago.
And the first four years were the toughest years of my life, for sure.
The undergrad.
I learned only one skill set and that was how to use my brain, how to think, how to think
critically. You know, that's why we became, I think friends instantly at Hopkins was that I feel
like that's how your brain is built too. And you've simplified that throughout your whole career.
So for me, I went there, I learned how to think, I decided I wanted to pursue biology at a deep
level and I wanted to pursue human biology. So then I went to medical school. Now for me,
I think one of the key components of having an effective research career to data, I guess,
would be that I had a clear understanding of this idea of translation. So you can do science
for science sake, but to me, to make really big impacts, you have to be able to translate that
to the human condition. So I did three years of medical school before I left. So I went away
after my third year and then I came back. So you already had a year of clinical medicine under
your belt. Yeah. And so for me- So that's also very unusual. It's definitely different,
but I encourage all students who are MD PhDs to do clinical time before they do their PhD.
So that might be the nugget of the podcast right there, because I don't think I knew a single MSTP
student who didn't go straight into their PhD after the preclinical phase. Right. So for me,
it was just so impactful to be, I guess if you say in hindsight, well, what was the distinguishing
factor of the Varmus lab crew? They're all MD PhDs. They had all done clinical. So they knew
really key nuances that were important questions to ask. And it doesn't, you don't have to be an
MB to get that. One of my good friends is his PhD who developed a genomics company that we may
talk about later. And he's a straight PhD. He shouldn't know prostate cancer like he does,
but he really gets the nuances of it. So I did three years of my med school. I went to the NIH.
I did pure science. I didn't think about humans at all. Thought about mice and signaling in mice
and T cells in mice and so forth. But in the back of my brain, I was always like, okay,
how are we going to change? How are we going to think about the human condition, human disease,
breakdown, rebuilding, all that. So from my perspective, I had a jump on the other straight
PhDs in the group because I had an idea. Now, why did I choose urology? Well, this goes back to
just an early childhood imprinting. So there's a couple of facts. Number one, my dad is an
incredibly famous urologist. My father was the chair of the department of urology at Northwestern
for 25 years before I took over the job. And he's an incredibly successful scientist, doesn't do
cancer biology. And I didn't really even know he was a urologist as a kid. I just knew him as my dad.
But one of the backstories was that when I was in seventh grade, eighth grade, and beginning high
school, we used to go visit my dad's parents. They lived in Northern Indiana, which is about
an hour and 20 minute drive from where we were. And over that time, my grandfather got sick.
And I have these vivid memories of seeing him and there are really snapshots in my brain,
I recall weekly, of just becoming sicker, becoming more frail, becoming bed bound, and then dying.
And I never really asked what he died of. And I don't think I was, I don't think I could have
processed it what it would have meant anyway, if I had asked. But when I was in medical school,
and I was doing my PhD, I asked my parents what he died of, and he died of prostate cancer. So
I was at the NIH, I was doing science, I had done some clinical work. I realized what people in DC,
not in science, but in politics were interested in, they're interested in cancer biology.
And they were interested in prostate cancer. So I saw what other people were interested in.
And I had this very vivid memories of my, you know, that my father, my grandfather having
prostate cancer and dying from it. And I decided that that's what I wanted to do.
So when I came back to medical school, I knew already that I wanted to be,
to be a prostate cancer biologist and understand the disease. I also knew that I wanted to be a
surgeon. And so I didn't want to be a medical oncologist, although that appealed to me a lot.
And I'm always flattered when people think I'm a medical oncologist, because those guys were
smart. But I knew I wanted to do something. I love working with my hands. So for me,
the idea of being a surgeon scientist was just, it just made sense. I love the biology. I love,
but I still love the idea of not just conceptually deconstructing something and putting it back
together, but actually physically deconstructing something and putting it back together. So it was
a perfect fit for what I wanted to do. For the listener to put some things in context,
at the time that you and I began our residencies, I don't really think there was any debate about
what the best urology program was in the United States. I think there was a good race for number
two. There were lots of programs that would have competed to be the second best urology program
in the country. But, but Johns Hopkins was hands down in a league of its own and they only take two
residents per year. So if there are 400 or 500 medical students graduating who want to go into
urology, only two of them get to go to Hopkins and you were one of them, which perhaps isn't
surprising. Did you want to go to Hopkins for reasons other than it was the best program? Was
there something about the environment there that drew you to it? Yeah, it was the people. It's an
amazing place that I think about it all the time. So I interviewed there and the chair of
the department at the time was, is the godfather of my field. He made all the contemporary modern
discoveries in prostate cancer. And it was real simple. He looked me in the eyes and he said,
I looked at your CV. I know what you have the ability to do and I want to help you get there.
So Pat, we all selected you in as much as you selected Hopkins.
I guess you could say that. Yeah. You know, it was a perfect fit because as we've talked about
mentorship is just so much of everything. It's everything in life really. If you're motivated
and you have drive, it's, you know, even if you're not motivated and you don't have drive,
you need a good mentor. So for me, I showed up for the interviews. I'd interviewed all over the
country. You know, there was places I could have gone that I could have made a good opportunity,
good experience for me to be trained. But when I showed up at Hopkins, I was like, okay, this is,
I got to go here. So, you know, I think it was a good fit. He was interested in having me train
with him and I was interested in training with him. So it was perfect. Did he know your father?
He must have. They must, I mean, they're both chairman. Yeah. It's an interesting story. He,
I met him at a, I met him at a function in the fall before I started. So before I had interviewed
and he was, I was at a function with my father. And so my father introduced me to him and he said,
well, you know, and what do you want to go into when you finish your medical school? I said, well,
I'm actually interested in neurology. He said, really? And he said, well, where are you applying?
And I said, well, I've applied to all the great programs. So, and he said, well, did you apply to
Hopkins? And I said, I sure did. And he said, that's wonderful. And then I find out from my father
that he grabbed my dad when I had walked away and he said, I just learned that Ted applied
to our program. Did we give him an interview? And so I made me feel good that, you know,
I had gotten this interview at the best place in the country without using my father's coattails
to kind of get the job. And then I showed up and it was just an amazing, I mean, Hopkins was an
amazing place. I know, I know you have many fond memories of the place and I'll never forget just
the pursuit of excellence is something I think about all the time. And that was really the
epitome of Hopkins for me. It was the pursuit of excellence among everybody there, to be honest
with you. Even the chairs of the departments, they pursued excellence and, but it trickled down,
you know, it trickled down to the everyday employees, the physical plant people, the people
who clean the floor, they had a pursuit and a passion for excellence that at the time that we
were there was amazing. I remember also being so struck by that when, you know, when I arrived,
because of course we're each thinking about it through the lens of what we're going to do. You're
going there because of urology. I'm going there because of general surgery, the neurosurgery guys
were going there, but we all had this common first year. We were all, I don't remember how many,
there must've been 28 of us doing internships in general surgery. Six of us would go on to do that
track. Two of you would go on to do urology. There might've been three guys in ENT and ortho
and neurosurgery, et cetera. But within about a week, I was like, oh my God, this is like the
all-star game. Like these three guys that, you know, and I still remember everybody's names, like
those three guys that were our classmates who went on to be neurosurgeons were out of control. They
were so good. The ortho guys, you know, ortho guys get a reputation of being kind of the jokers.
These guys were fantastic. Yeah. You know, they were, everyone was just so exceptional. So yeah,
you're right. It's, you pay a little bit of a price. You got to go to Baltimore. Yeah.
Call us pay to spade. That's right. Although we both met our spouses there. So,
I had my kids there. So there are some upsides to it, but the reality is that, you know,
it's funny because Pat Walsh, my mentor there always would talk about that. He would always say,
well, it's negative selection. People come here because they want to pursue excellence. They don't
come here because there's a good nightlife. They don't come here because of X, Y, or Z. They come
here for that single reason. And that's- That's a great point. I never really thought about that
way, but it's so obvious because I remember being so sad about having to leave California to train
there, but at the same time realizing and talking a lot about it with Steve Rosenberg,
that was like who had done his MD and PhD at Hopkins, that, you know, you only get one
opportunity to train at this. This is the phase of your life to do this. So go to the best place
you can go that fits with how much you want to work. Let's talk for a moment about Pat's work,
because I don't think it can be overstated. And I don't think, I mean, in many ways,
I think Pat Walsh was a very unique mentor to you specifically, but in many ways, the field of
urology today is different because of him. And I don't think, and I've thought about this,
knowing that we were going to talk today, I've spent the last couple of weeks thinking about this.
And I have a hard time coming up with people in the modern era that rival him,
John Cameron potentially being one with respect to pancreatic surgery. But I can't think of someone
in the last 30 years that has so fundamentally changed the course of one operation, its impact
on one disease as Pat. Now, am I missing an obvious example? Well, within urology, I think,
I think I can't think of anybody within urology. And the other point is, I'm sure that there are
brilliant outstanding people that have changed an operation in a way that alters the course of those
individual patients. But one of the things I think about a lot is that Walsh would always tell me,
you know, you can't make important discoveries unless you work on important problems. So
prostate cancer is an important problem and it's an incredibly prevalent problem. So yeah,
there's probably some guy out there who came up with the best way to do a knick-knack, whatever
surgery, but if it doesn't have a high impact, it probably is not noticed. So yeah, I think that
what he did in our field was, you know, really was never been done before and probably won't
be done again. And he did it for a problem that was incredibly important. So let's talk about the
state of prostate cancer surgery for men prior to Pat's work. If a man had prostate cancer,
what would be back in the early 70s, even late 70s, right? What were the treatment options for him?
Well, at the time that Walsh was training, very few people with prostate cancer had surgery.
And that was because it was a potentially life-threatening operation. People would die
from extreme blood loss. People were incontinent. People were for sure impotent. Let's stop there
for a second because this is one of those things that I think if, unless you've been in an operating
room, it's hard to understand why the blood loss from prostate cancer surgery could be so deadly.
It's the same reason until you see a trauma where somebody is shot through the pelvis. You can't
understand how did that person die? People get shot in the chest and they walk away sometimes if
it's, you know, not through the heart or a pulmonary artery or vein. And yet a cross pelvis
gunshot wound is often quite fatal. What is it about that anatomy that makes it so deadly?
It's the large number and variable distribution of veins in the pelvis in general.
And why is it the veins, not the arteries?
I love that. I love that. I get to do this with you.
I mean, you know, the vein is just the wall of a vein is as thick as a piece of paper. So it's
prone to tear and it's hard to repair it if you do tear it. And an artery is much thicker. It has
much more resiliency to it and it has to do with the amount of flow going through both of them and
pressure. So yeah, there's a lot of veins in the prostate, in the pelvis. There's a lot of veins
around the prostate and the distribution, the exact location is incredibly variable. So there
are more like venous plexuses versus an actual vein that you can name. But if you get into the
inferior vena cava, man, you're in trouble too. There's no doubt about that. That's happened to
me a couple of times. So point is that anytime you, you know, an artery is the real deal, but it's
just easier to control it. And oftentimes if you cut an artery, it'll go into spasm and it won't
even, it'll just stop bleeding on its own. And that's not true for veins. So for one, and then
also there's the depth, right? There's the actual exposure is really tough in the pelvis. You know,
it's one thing to, you know, look at the kidney where even though it's in the retroperitoneum,
you can be staring it straight in the face without too much work. That's not really the case in the
prostate. Yeah. So, I mean, the way that Dr. Walz describes it is that, you know, people had done
anatomic studies for many, many years, right? I mean, for decades before surgery for the prostate
kind of was attempted to be performed. But the anatomy, when you fix a body and you study it,
it really compresses a lot of these sinuses. And so you don't really fully appreciate where they
are and what's happening and so forth anatomically an artery is preserved, but these kind of venous
plexuses were not. So the anatomy of the pelvis was not appreciated. But I will say that in 1904,
at Johns Hopkins, the first radical prostatectomy for cancer was performed by the chair there at the
time. And he did it through a perineal approach, which is the space between your scrotum and your
anus basically. And when you do the surgery that way, you avoid... And the reason is that's the
closest place that the prostate gland is to the outside world. That's right. And if you do it that
way, you avoid a lot of the veins that bleed just, you know, catastrophically when you approach
the prostate from kind of above versus from below. And so that operation had been, was in, you know,
was being performed and it was considered to be, you know, it was definitely safe. I mean, this
life-threatening blood loss did not occur. And the problem was it wasn't a very good cancer
operation. Why is that? Well, it had to do with exposure. Number one, I mean, you're doing,
you know, the prostate is very deep in the pelvis. So for the lay people, the way I explain
Wolber is the prostate. I explain to people that the pelvis is like a ring of bone and off the ring
hang a bunch of muscles and those muscles form a hammock. At the bottom of the hammock is the
prostate. And so it penetrates through the muscles and then that's where the urethra, the tube that
you urinate through comes through the pelvic floor muscles and then goes out of the body.
So it's deep in the pelvis. It's hard to access. It's hard to access from the perineum and it's
hard to see what you're doing and it's harder to kind of excise tissue widely in that area.
The exposure is tough when you do it from above, but it's even tougher from below. So the life
threatening bleeding wasn't there, but part of the reason that the bleeding didn't occur when you
did a perineal approach was because they were leaving part of the prostate kind of in place.
They were staying away from the area where the big veins were. And so when you do that,
it would be safer for the patient, but less oncologically sound.
So, and I can't believe I'm blanking on the forefathers, obviously Halstead, Osler, Kelly,
who was the, and Kelly was the gynecologist, obviously Osler, the internist,
Halstead, the surgeon. What was the name of the urologist?
The first urologist at Hopkins was one of Halstead's trainees that was Hugh Hampton Young.
So Hugh Hampton Young was a Halstead trainee. And so people probably don't realize, but many
subspecialties of medicine came out of the Halsteadian era at Hopkins. And so orthopedics,
radiology, urology, these were all subspecialties that basically were Halstead telling Hugh Hampton
Young, I think we should start an institute or program for people with urologic problems.
Now Kelly was doing some of that also at Hopkins, just more on the female side, but that concept
came out of Halstead really assigning Hugh Hampton Young to do that. And the story is that he
literally bumped into him in the hallway and told him, you're going to go work on this. And
he didn't really want to do it because at the time it wasn't very sexy, but he did. And so
from there he really began the whole specialty of urology. Yeah. That's sort of the other thing
about Hopkins that never got old actually was to walk through Blalock and look at the photos of
all of these old photos of people who literally created the field of surgery. The lineage there
was sort of staggering. Yeah. I think one of the things that you, I certainly didn't appreciate
was to really take it all in at the time. I mean, I had the pleasure of being at Hopkins.
It's hard to when you're sleeping, I think an average of 28 hours a week or wherever we slept.
Right. Exactly. But the idea of what we did was pretty amazing. I mean, remember we had Sunday
school, right? Yeah. Oh, I loved Sunday school. We would show up. Can you explain to the listener
what Sunday school is? You and I might've been two of the, there weren't many people that probably
loved Sunday school, but you and I had adored it. It was great. So when we were interns at Hopkins,
there was no work hour limit. And the expectation when you got there was that you'd work seven days
a week. You would work eight days a week if there are eight days in the week. And so Sundays was the
day that you would go in and you'd sit with the chair of the department, one of the most famous
surgeons of all time, really. And he would lead the discussion on a topic for the day. It often
started with history, right? We would do history of surgery, history of surgery at Hopkins. And
that was, those are some of my most favorite kind of discussions was him just talking for 45 minutes
about somebody. And then we would present cases and then we would talk, we would practice our
suturing. I remember we, I remember I think Julian Sosa, who's the chair at UCSF now was taught me how
to tie a square knot. You know what I mean? And also once a year, we each took a turn presenting
something back to the group. I still remember what I presented on. I presented on the war in
shunt, which was an operation that I never got to see because even by the time we were residents,
interventional radiology had completely nullified the need for that operation. But
as a medical student, I became obsessed with the history of that operation because of how
dangerous it was and how complicated it was. This was an operation for the folks who maybe
don't spend a lot of time on the at war and shunt Twitter handle. There's probably no such thing.
Hope someone creates one after this. It's an operation that was done for people with elevated
pressures in the liver. And this is something that happens when people get cirrhosis. So
this was basically an operation that would alleviate that by creating a shunt in the liver.
But I still remember that. And I remember typing it up. And this was back in the day when I would
cut pictures out of textbooks and tape them on and make photocopies. This was old school.
Yeah. So that was eight to 10 every Sunday morning, right?
Yeah. And so those kinds of things, I wish I could just, people say, I wish I could go back
to high school, wish I could go back to college. In many ways, I mean, I'd do an internship all
over again. I would. I mean, we were there at what, 130 to 136 hours a week. But man, I would
do it all over again. It was awesome. We did have amazing times. And I feel fortunate. I mean,
there was just a great group of people we met. You and I met immediately on day one and then
worked together. We were together September, September of our intern year, we did pediatric
surgery together. And Karen Cling was our fellow. She is now in attending in San Diego. I bumped
into her in the grocery store like a year ago. She was great. She was incredible.
Yeah. She was awesome. John Vogel was our senior resident.
Taught me how to put an NG tube in that served me, an asiogastric tube for the listener is a tube that
you sometimes have to put in a patient's nose down behind the pharynx and then into the esophagus and
into the stomach. This is something that is so ubiquitous in surgical care, but so wildly
uncomfortable for a patient because the patient is usually wide awake when you're doing this.
And I remember one day Vogel, I remember where we were. It was just at the ground level of CMC.
He sat us down there in the playground and said, look, you two knuckleheads,
you have got to learn how to put an NG tube in without killing somebody. And he didn't mean
literally killing, but he just meant tormenting. And do you remember the Vogel technique?
I do still. I remember him telling me. It was like, because everybody thinks that you're
supposed to put the NG tube up the nose, right? And he's like, it's straight back.
That's exactly right.
And so he's like, you get the cup of ice, you get the ice water cup, you put the NG tube in,
you put a wicked bend on it, you put the lidocaine jelly in, and that's exactly the key point. Do not
go up, go directly back, and you curl it down and then you give them a little straw and you tell
them exactly once you hit the back of the oropharynx, take two big sips. And this was a game changer,
Ted. It was. For the rest of my residency, I was throwing NG tubes in. If you looked at me,
you got an NG tube and it didn't hurt. The thing that the listener will not appreciate is the
layer of comedy associated with this, because this was done in what you described as the
first floor of the pediatric hospital, which was called the zoo, right? Yeah.
And so this is a brilliant surgeon, John Vogel. He's the head of colorectal surgery
in Colorado, teaching Peter Attia, brilliant surgeon Ted Shafer, just getting by in front of
life-size stuffed animals of giraffes and lions. It was hysterical, right? It was just comedy.
Yeah. That entire, that might've been certainly the best month of my internship.
Yeah. That was fun in terms of-
I had great-
Many great months.
Yeah, pure jokes. So let's go back to Pat. I got us a little off topic. Actually, I got us way off
topic because we were talking about the bleeding, but there was this other enormous complication
of a prostatectomy, which was it virtually guaranteed that a man would not be continent
with respect to urine and would not be able to regain erectile function. And so I'm guessing
that many men when faced with an operation that's going to leave them in a diaper, unable to have an
erection might opt for not having surgery. Yeah. So people had radiation and radiation has changed
a lot too. So it was bad radiation or a bad surgery effectively. But when you can actually
see what you're doing, just for the listener, doing something when it's pitch blackout versus
daylight, it makes all the difference in the world. And so you would go into the operating room with
him and he had just a mastery and he could control, he understood where the veins were. He
controlled them by suturing them before they started bleeding. And by doing that, you could
actually see everything. And once you could see everything, it was obvious. You'd be like, hello,
why aren't people doing this or that? Now, the ability to maintain potency and preserve
sexual function was something that it's not so obvious how to do that. But he figured that out
by working with some anatomists and really just studying and talking to his patients and listening
to what they had to say. He also recorded all of his cases, which I do now too, and I study them.
And he learned how to kind of- I didn't know that about Pat. He would record all the operations and
study them. And I didn't realize that you were doing that either. I do now. It's much easier now
for us. I mean, we just hit the button, but every single case I record it. And we're working on,
I'm working on with one of my residents just making a photo video library. So what was hard for him
and he's published and he put out on DVD his operation, you can see it on YouTube and it's
a brilliant thing. But one of the things that makes doing any surgery fun is that there's so
much variability in anatomy. So what I'm working on now is a video library. So 10 bladder necks,
15 of these, because there's so much variability in how the tissues present themselves to you.
And then how do you handle that? And that's part of what taking a surgical skill and hours in the
cockpit do for you. So we're doing with one of our lab residents this year, we're just taking all
these videos. And so whenever I do a case and the anatomy was really nice for X, Y, or Z,
I'll tell them, they pull that case and it's in the third 20 minute clip and pull it and make
a short, just make a clip of that for particular steps of the procedure. Was there a moment when
Pat realized he was onto something and that this was, we were basically witnessing a paradigm shift,
which is such an overused term, except here it's not at all. It's actually an understatement here,
but such a paradigm shift and how an operation was going to be done. I mean, this would have been
in the early eighties, I'm guessing. It was, yeah. Well, mid to late eighties or late eighties,
early nineties. And so it was, I think he knew all along he was onto something and he was very
confident. He's not a shy guy and he'll tell you that. So he was incredibly confident that he was
onto something and that what he was doing was the right thing to do and was very convinced of that
and was convincing of that when he spoke about it publicly. I think that the general community was
less convinced that that was what he had done was really happening. But I mean, I saw it. I mean,
I was really training there at the heyday, the peak of Brady Urology, Johns Hopkins Urology. And so
I got to see it in real life and I never saw bad surgery. That's the thing. I mean,
we trained at this place and it didn't really rarely did you see people do a bad operation. So
part of learning is to see the good stuff and the bad stuff and put it all in the perspective. And
we didn't have most of the time that didn't happen there. So I saw it and I think he was
convinced of it from the get go. So you're saying it just kind of took a little bit of time for the
day to speak for itself. I mean, the results. So if a patient today goes to a highly trained
or competent urologist and is going to have a prostatectomy and this, it's a 60 year old man.
What can you guesstimate about his probability of regaining sexual function? It's not a hundred
percent and it's not a hundred percent because it used to be zero, but now it's, well, the nerves
that we preserve at the time of surgery to optimize recovery of sexual function are not
myelinated. So they're incredibly sensitive to any kind of manipulation, any kind of trauma.
So one of my good friends is a hand surgeon and he does microvascular nerve graphs all the time
and the nerves regenerate and regain function. They do that because they're myelinated and
incredibly protected. I didn't realize there were such thing as non myelinated nerves.
Are there other places in the body where these exist besides the prostate? I'm sure there are.
I just, I'm below the belt guys. So I don't know. Is there an evolutionary reason that those would
not be myelinated? I don't know, but we can, I'll call Pat Walsh up when we finish this and he'll
tell me for 20 minutes what an Indian I am and how I didn't know that. Can we record that discussion?
We could.
Okay. So that's a very interesting point that I actually was unaware of and I can see now why
that makes it that much more difficult. Right. Because you can preserve this tissue and you can
do it in a way that's minimally traumatic for the tissue, yet it's not a guarantee that there'll be
a hundred percent recovery of function or any function recovery. Right. And so that is the
variable and that's the fact that it still hasn't changed. You know, like Dr. Walsh would always
tell me if, if we could do the perfect operation, there'd be no dispute about doing prostate cancer
surgery, perfect operation, 100% cancer control and no side effects. So I think in this day and age,
you can be nearly perfect for kind of urinary control. You're never going to be perfect. So
when people say that none of their patients have urinary leakage, it doesn't make any sense
because if you actually survey 60 or 165 year old guys, 4% of them will have urinary leakage.
I mean, so incontinence is something that happens. It's much more common in women,
particularly aging women, but it's also occurs in aging men. So to say, well, I do a hundred percent
of my cases and there's no urinary incontinence, that's kind of means. Yeah, it's better than the
baseline. So it's hard to believe. Yeah. But you can get people up to very, very close to that
number. So I always tell people for me personally, 98% of my patients are totally dry, wear one small
pattern line or day, which often people just wear for protection when they're out and about,
functionally totally fine. Now for a 50 year old man, I think there's over 90% chance that you can
recover. Sexual functioning. Yeah. But with each deck member, erectile dysfunction is a disease
of the aging male. So for each decade that somebody gets older, there's decline in sexual function.
So even if people say that they're totally potent and they're 70,
they'll tell you if you ask them, oh my yeah, I'm not as good as I was when I was 20.
So there's that component of things. And the other factor is prostate cancer. And it's not like
there's the prostate, there's five millimeters of tissue. And then there's this nerve bundle.
There's the prostate. There's no capsule or lining encasing the prostate. And then there's
the neurovascular bundle of Walsh named after Dr. Walsh. So you have prostate. The prostate itself
has different zones or different regions. Prostate cancers develop in the peripheral region or
peripheral zone. So right at the edge of the prostate. So you have a tumor at the edge of
the prostate, and then you have the nerve bundle. And so you're talking about one or two cell.
So that's kind of a cruel trick of fate is to have the cancers not develop centrally.
They don't develop centrally, they develop peripherally. So I understand why patients by
listeners just say, well, I don't, you know, why don't you just, you know what, I don't get it.
Because in many cases today, we I've published on this a lot now, you know, there's prostate
cancers that we pick up today are just bulkier, they're more aggressive. And so when you have a
tumor that you know is going to be outside the prostate, you know, it's extra prostatic.
It's involving the nerve bundle a lot of the times. And so you have to remove part of it.
You have to remove, you know, the tissue around it to try to clear your margins. And so
when you do that in a 65 year old guy, and you take out half of his nerve on one side,
it's unlikely that he'll be able to regain sexual function on his own. Now these days,
I try to be very upfront about that. And I try to set appropriate expectations.
We can we have special tools that we have in neurology that will enable a man to get
total satisfaction sexually. So we can maneuver around that, so to speak. And these days,
many of the people I see have very aggressive cancers that are, quote unquote, the real deal.
So we really have to be careful and you know, our number one goal for doing cancer surgery is to
get the tumor out. Let's talk a little bit about prostate cancer, because it's not a cancer that
comes without its controversy. So let's start with the biggest controversy, certainly one of the
biggest controversies or things that would confuse the layperson, because about every year,
the advice changes on this thing called PSA. So what is the prostate specific antigen?
PSA is a protein, it's made by the prostate. And its normal function is to liquefy semen.
So it's highly expressed in the process. So the way I explain the prostate to people,
it's the best analogy I can come up with is if you think about it like a sewer system,
you have the main sewer leaving the city. That's the urethra, that's the tube that we normally
urinate through. But this channel also delivers semen out the tip of the penis. Off this main sewer
are slightly smaller sewers that go to different neighborhoods. Within the neighborhood,
there's a sewer that comes out of the individual house. And the individual houses in this analogy
are prostate epithelial cells. They make components of the semen. And the semen is used to
give nutrients to the sperm while it's trying to fertilize an egg to enable the sperm to
penetrate the cervical mucus, these different functions. PSA is a protein that breaks down
the semen and liquefies it. And people think it's important for this whole process of fertilizing
an egg. So that's what it does. And if you look in the semen, the PSA numbers are 100 million
per ml. I mean, the numbers, the amount of this protein in the semen is astronomically high.
So that's what it is. That's what it does. So how do we use it as a tool to screen for prostate
cancer? Well, we check the values of the PSA in the blood. So since the prostate is a sexual gland,
if you check the values of a PSA in a eight year old boy, it would be zero because there's no
testosterone in that boy. There's no sexual development in that boy. And therefore there's,
I mean, there's some, but effectively no. Before puberty, there's very little levels of testosterone.
There's no effectively prostate epithelium and there's no PSA. As a boy goes through puberty
to become a young man. And then as he goes through the aging process, his prostate develops. And then
it starts to produce PSA as part of the components of the semen. Now, there is a certain amount of
leakage of the PSA fluid into the bloodstream. It's not quote unquote supposed to leak into the
bloodstream, but it can. And as the prostate gets bigger. So think about this concept of this
underground sewer system, the New York city sewers, right? They're getting older, they're getting
leakier. And the bigger the prostate gets and the prostate gets larger as we get older, some of these
pipes get leaky and some of the PSA leaks into the blood. So it was discovered in the eighties
that there's this prostate specific protein that you can pick up in the semen and you can also see
in the blood. And so it is not cancer specific. It's prostate specific. And it's actually a very
good biomarker for prostate size. The bigger the prostate, the more leaky it is, so to speak.
And the leakier it is, the higher the numbers can go in the bloodstream.
So there's two variables that can progress over time. The size itself, which you could talk about
that independent of size. So two 30 year olds, one guy's got a five gram prostate, the other guy's
got a hundred gram prostate just to make it extreme. You should see a difference, but also
two guys with the same size prostate that are two decades apart, you might see a higher PSA
in the older. That's right. So, and if you do, for example, like we were always taught in
residency, even though I wasn't a urologist, you still once in a while have to, we still did a
urology rotation. If I recall, you wouldn't check a PSA on a man right after doing a rectal exam on
because in theory that could artificially have raised the PSA, presumably by creating more of
an insult and increasing that flow. Pushing some of it into the blood, the bloodstream. So what can
make the PSA rise besides just having getting older and having a larger prostate? Well, if you
get an infection in your prostate. So think about that. Like you got your city, you have your sewer
network and there's an earthquake. All the pipes are ratted a little bit and they all are extra
leaky. And that's what an infection is. It's not infections in the prostate or either all or none,
really. They're not focal. So the whole prostate gets more leaky and the PSA number can go way up.
The other way to think about it is if you have a cancer and the analogy would be, well, there's
a city block that has the pipes, the sewer systems clogged. There's more backflow into the
bloodstream and that's how I pick it up. That's not really how it happens, but that's a good way
for patients to think about it. So what is a normal PSA? Well, a normal PSA is age adjusted.
So a normal PSA for a 40 year old is around 0.5 to 0.6 nanograms per ml. For a 50 year old, normal,
meaning this is the median for all the population. For a 50 year old, it's one. And so it kind of goes
up stepwise by decade. So there are age adjustments that we do for the PSA number. Now, what are PSA
numbers that tell you you don't have a cancer? There's no PSA number that is 100% no cancer.
But there is a proportional rise in cancer detection with rising PSA numbers. So originally,
the cutoff was set at a PSA of four. We think about things more based on the individual
scenario. So if you're a younger person, if your PSA is more than 2.5, that's usually considered
to be abnormal and you may need further workup. You don't need a biopsy right away these days,
in my opinion, but you need further workup. So it depends on the age of the patient and depends on
how also their prostate size. Now, many guys will go and when they get their PSA checked,
there's another thing that gets checked called the free PSA. And then a number is reported,
which is the percentage free, which is obviously that if their PSA is three and their free PSA is
one and the percent free is reported as 33%. What does that mean? These are different ways for
urologists to try to fine tune this prostate specific antigen test to make it more a cancer
specific test. So again, PSA just goes up when you have an every man has, it's not cancer specific.
So percent free PSA was the first way that urologists began to look at, well, what's the chance
that a PSA of four is coming from a cancer versus a PSA for coming from just benign overgrowth.
So remember, there's a lot of factors in play. One would be, if you had a man whose prostate
volume was 80 grams, that's big, and his PSA was four, well, that's a low ratio. That's something
called PSA density, how much PSA is made per gram of tissue. So you'd say, well, that guy,
it's very low chance that he has a cancer. That guy would also have a high percent free PSA.
So percent free PSA is another way to just look at how much of the PSA is produced from benign
cells versus cancerous cells. So if two guys have a PSA of four and one has a free of one,
so he's 25% free and the other guy has a free of three, which is 75% free,
what's the different physiologically in those situations? Well, there's less bound PSA in the
lower percent free, and that's more often associated with prostate cancer. So that's just a correlation.
So it's not like it means that... In other words, it's hard, we can't infer what, because I would
have assumed that the binding protein is in the periphery. It's in the plasma, right?
Yeah, it's bound up when it comes out of the epithelial cell. So it's just how it's processed.
So PSA's process is not a full length protein when it's born. And so the other way that we now... So
just for the listeners, so we have absolute cutoffs for PSA for an older man, 2.5 and younger man,
but they're all really case specific in my opinion. Percent free PSA was the first way to say,
let's try to fine tune what the PSA means. So a high percent free PSA is associated with a big
prostate, less of a chance of prostate cancer. A low percent free PSA is associated with a higher
likelihood that that PSA is produced from a gland with prostate cancer in it. The other variables
that we use are PSA density. So that's highly predictive of what's going on in the prostate.
So an easy threshold or cutoff for you Peter, we talk on the phone about some of your patients.
Percent free PSA density more than 0.1. It raises a little bit of a red flag. A PSA density of more
than 0.15, that raises a red flag. So think about it. And that median prostate volume for a 60 year
old guy is 40 grams. So 40 gram prostate PSA less than four. It's probably, it's pretty safe.
A PSA of six, six, that raises red flags. And you know this from your own patients that, okay,
that guy probably has something going on. So that's how I think about it. Now think about the 80
gram prostate with the PSA of four. Oh, you have these patients in your practice. They don't have
cancer on average, right? Percent free PSA helps with that. There are two other new tests that.
Yeah. So you got me onto the 4K two years ago and I really consider it a game changer for the guys
like me who were in the peanut gallery. So I don't, you know, I make it my job to know as much as is
knowable with the time that I have about every possible disease that could afflict my patients.
But that means I need to spend as much time thinking about colon cancer as I do coronary
artery disease as I do prostate cancer. So for me, the 4K, which again, you didn't, I mean, you did
me a great service. Not only did you get me interested in it, but you introduced me to Andrew
at Memorial Sloan Kettering. I'm blanking on Andrew's last name. Andrew Vickers. Vickers, yeah.
Amazing guy. Yes. And I mean, the guy couldn't have been more generous with his time. I mean,
he just gave me the schooling tutorial on this topic. He's a brilliant guy. So good. You know,
we put together a patient handout on this thing and he even edited it for us.
I feel like not, I'm worried not enough patients understand that and I'm worried not enough primary
care physicians understand the importance of the 4K test. Can you explain how that has changed
the way we do things? So this test you're alluding to, and there's another test that
performs equally well called the Prostate Health Index or PHI test. These both leverage off this
idea that prostate cancer cells make PSA differently than benign prostate cells.
And so the 4K score is the four calicrine tests. It takes PSA, percent free PSA, intact PSA,
and HK2. It takes those four prostate specific proteins produced and it has a calculator to
really just discriminate between a cancerous cell and a benign cell. PHI uses the similar concept.
It uses something called minus 2 Pro-PSA, which is PSA for all the scientists out there plus two
amino acids on the five prime side of it. So minus 2 Pro-PSA, right? And you measure those specific
PSA based proteins in the blood. And the 4K score is great because Andrew Vickers and Hans
Lillia developed it with this other great urologist, Peter Scardino Memorial. And what they
looked at was, well, what's the chance that this person is diagnosed with and has high grade
aggressive lethal prostate cancer? And it gives you a percentile chance. So when you get the 4K
report, it's actually a really nice report. It'll say 2% chance, 20% chance, and so forth. And so
now as you start using this in your practice, they now also give you the PSA. So you can see the PSA
and then you can say, wait a second, this guy's PSA is six, but it's 4K scores two, it's safe.
What I really like about it is, and so when we do our, usually with our patients in their second
year, sometimes in the first year, but usually in their second year, we do a cancer screening
program where we kind of walk them through every single cancer that you could possibly die of.
And then we go cancer by cancer, risk by risk. And it's a very lengthy process on the back end.
For the patient, we simplified it, takes about 90 minutes to go through it. But for the males,
when we come to this, I always view this as one of the better, I said, I wish every cancer had a
test like this because as we'll come back to, pretty much every guy is going to die with prostate
cancer, but fortunately most men will not die from prostate cancer. Our job is to figure out
when a guy has prostate cancer, as you alluded to earlier, is this the bad one?
Yeah.
Or is this the one that if you muck around with it too much?
And so what I guess Vickers and his team have been able to do is figure out that there's now
enough data that you can basically turn this into a binary test, so PSA would be a continuous
variable. And when you want to test the sensitivity and specificity of a continuous variable, you have
to use something called a receiver operating characteristic curve, and it becomes quite
complicated because the question becomes what cutoff? And as you alluded to, it's very difficult
with PSA because it has to be age and volume adjusted. So now it's a three dimensional
receiver operating characteristic curve where you would have a different AUC area under the curve
for each point in time and volume. I mean, that becomes almost inconceivable. And yet the 4K has
basically allowed us to say the following, if your 4K score is less than 7.5%, and I might butcher the
numbers a little bit, but- That's the right number, yeah.
But if it's less than 0.5%, the probability that you will be alive, the probability that you will
die of metastatic prostate cancer is 1.6% in the next 20 years?
Yeah, it's almost the lifetime of the patient. And that's based on this data from Andrew's
partner, a co-developer Hans Lilja, where they had this incredible-
They had a database.
Yeah.
From Malmo, Sweden. So they could track it.
And then the reverse is if you're greater than 7.5%, I think it's like 16 or 17% chance in 20
years. The binary cutoff is 7.5%. But it's a continuous variable. But above that, it's
continuous. It's not like if you're above that, it's a 50%. So it varies based on the number.
So where are we today? Let's take a journey backwards in time. In the late 1980s, 40% of
men who were coming in with prostate cancer had metastatic at the time of presentation.
Just like a lot of cancers, other cancers that we diagnosed today. And that was how it was then.
There was an epidemic of deaths from prostate cancer. We were getting a better handle on how
to control cardiovascular deaths. People were coming in with aggressive advanced
cancers. Prostate was one of them. Tom Stamey took this PSA test, and he first made the
observation that you could use it to actually follow men after their cancer treatment.
And if the number went up, gosh, that meant that their cancer was back. It was just a game changer.
This is the first time this was ever done. And then Bill Catalona, who's one of my partners here,
one of the other godfathers in the field, he said, why don't we use it to screen people to
pick up cancers when they're early and curable, not when they come in in advanced. So the change-
And what year was that? That would have been-
1990 FDA approval. So they set up arbitrary cutoffs. This is what this idea of mass screening
took off. And it's been sold to the public. Will the urologists route there just to make money?
This is what we are doing and to get rich? No, it wasn't that. It was because at the time the test
was developed, it was the first biomarker for cancer. Pick up a cancer early if you pick it up,
treat it and cure that patient. Now over the 1990s and early 2000s, what we realized is, well,
guess what? We're picking up a lot of cancers. We're treating a lot of cancers. Number one,
we're increasing and reducing the deaths from prostate cancer. We're reducing the incidence
of metastatic prostate cancer at presentation. It was 40% in basically 1990, 40% of men coming in
with prostate cancer metastatic at the time. By 2000, it was 4%. Now the skeptic is going to say,
and this is such a controversial topic, so it's so good that we're doing this. The skeptic will say,
well, that's just lead time bias. I mean, all you did was catch a bunch of men earlier. So you have
a much bigger funnel, right? Right. So by the way, the same controversy exists on mammography. So I
can't wait to actually sit down with the Ted Shafer equivalent of breast cancer at some point,
because I realized that an episode like this is probably a little bit more geared towards male
listeners or probably the female listeners who have male spouses or people that care about going
through this. But it's interesting to watch the rise of mammography and the rise of PSA go through
this parallel thing. And colonoscopy though, to a slightly lesser extent, but really being the big
three mass employed screening tools. Well, it's been written about. Peter.
And you've written about this. Well, Peter Albertson is another Hopkins alum. He's a
chair at Connecticut and he's an anti-screener effectively for prostate cancer. And he wrote
about this and he showed that if you just look at incidents of metastatic prostate cancer,
incidents of metastatic breast cancer, there's no change with the implementation of mammography.
There's a huge drop in the incidence of metastatic prostate cancer with the implementation of PSA.
So why is he an anti-screener? Well, he just, he was historically, he wrote this paper
and showed that there was a huge difference. So now with screening, you have increased detection
and what we've learned is unlike, let's say pancreatic cancer, where most of the time,
if you picked it up early, if you did nothing, you would die. Not everybody who has prostate
cancer has a lethal variation of it. And so initially we developed a biomarker to pick up
all prostate cancers. That was the PSA blood test. We picked them up, we treated them,
we reduced deaths. We also over treated people, people who had a cancer that would never have
been lethal in their lifetime. That's the dying with, not the dying from. And this is something
you and I used to talk about nearly 20 years ago. I remember sitting in the cafeteria,
because even though we were still interns and basically two knuckleheads, you knew you were
going to do this and you were always head and shoulders above everybody else in terms of what
you understood. I remember asking you, I was like, I don't get it. Why do some guys get prostate
cancer? And it seems to be relatively uninteresting. And then other guys get it and they're dead in two
years and it's as devastating as pancreatic cancer. What is it about the biology of that?
Because it strikes me as more a function of the biology than the environment or the host,
but I could be wrong, of course. But I remember talking about this a lot and really coming away,
scratching my head thinking, I don't have a clue what's going on with this disease.
Yeah. I mean, I'm still scratching my head about it because that's what my whole research program
is all about is, well, what's the molecular biology of lethal prostate cancer? So we'll talk
about that in a second. But to circle back to our story, so we diagnosed many men with prostate
cancer. We treated men and we saved their lives and reduced deaths from prostate cancer period.
It's not debatable, but along the way, there were people that were pulled in and were treated
who did not need treatment. But there's a lot of smart people who have studied the biology of
prostate cancer and we realized that not everybody who was diagnosed with it needed to be treated
from it. And so the 4K score and the prostate health index help us identify men who have
life threatening or potentially lethal prostate cancers. And so those are great
screening tools. They're not considered or the government doesn't like them as first line
screening. So they recommend you do a regular PSA blood test if it's at all abnormal. Remember,
70% of men have normal PSAs if they're such a thing. And by the way, do we have a sense of what
percentage of those men can still harbor a lethal prostate cancer? Well, Vickers would know that
data and they've published on that. It depends what you say normal and not normal is. Yeah.
I mean, a PSA below three, there are still men that have, if you just do one test, it's...
Assuming it's not a lab error or you miss something. Yeah. No, no, below three, I still
think the 4K data says it's somewhere around, I want to say 10 or 15%. So it's not a single
digit thing. And another big opposition in the screening world is the quote unquote unnecessary
biopsies. And I say quote unquote, not because I'm diminishing or minimizing that, but the idea is,
look, a prostate biopsy is a transrectal procedure for most men. It's a morbid procedure,
it's not comfortable. And just as it's not comfortable for a woman to have a needle put
into her breast. And the fear is, hey, we're doing too many of these. I want to circle back to that,
but my view on that today is diffusion weighted MRI and the MRIs that we have today have really
cut back on those biopsies. But I want to get your... That's just my take as a non-neurologist
with my patients, but I want to come back to that. Well, so the government said in 2008, first
for people over 75, and then in 2012 for all men that you shouldn't do PSA testing. And when the
internist got to go ahead and not do it, I mean, it's easy to not do it, right? You just don't do
it. So what would you predict would happen if you stopped screening for prostate cancer? Well,
you would predict it would go up and it would depend on the time horizon of the disease.
So if you stop screening for prostate cancer, you'd predict that the detection of prostate
cancer will go down, right? You're not looking for it. But you're going to have a greater number
of late presenting diseases show. More lethal disease. So we published, and some of my good
friends in neurology have published that, yes, that in fact has occurred. So if you look at
starting in 08 or in 12, when these two big shifts occurred, since that time, there's been a rise in
the incidence of more advanced prostate cancer. So the cancers that are picked up today, even with
this short window where we stopped screening aggressively with the internists, that there's
now more aggressive, more lethal disease. As of today, I still believe that the formal
recommendation for screening for prostate cancer is each physician and patient should discuss
together. There is no formal recommendation because when we go through each cancer with
our patients, we show them what the ACA, what the American Cancer Society says, the US task
force on preventative services, the NCI, the New England Journal of Medicine did a review on every
cancer and there's one other group. Oh, the CDC is the fifth body to weigh in. And we show them,
here are the recommendations from all five of these for every cancer. And I remember when that
shift changed to for prostate cancer, there's no more recommendation. Well, the recommendation is
talk about it with your doctor, which is a bit of a pass the buck. Besides the, I think the American
Academy of Family Practitioners and they don't recommend PSA screening still. I'm not sure why,
but that's a different discussion. But the bottom line is that almost all the guidelines now say
it's a shared decision making process, which I think makes perfect sense. That's how I view
modern medicine. Yeah, it does. In theory, it makes great sense. What I worry about, Ted, is
there's a bunch of patients that get caught. They don't have doctors like you or me who are
willing to be able to have the luxury of the time and the ability to educate themselves to do that,
because I still see a lot of patients that show up and they're not getting screened because their
doctor's basically saying, well, obviously this is quote unquote controversial. I sort of remember
hearing that we shouldn't have been screening, so we're not going to do it. And that's sort of my
fear with these things. Well, I think shared decision making, it requires... Well, so then
to me conceptually, it makes a lot of sense. In reality, what does that actually mean? Well,
that's the next question. That's the next unknown, right? Is well, how's our shared decision making
process? How does it occur? And when a patient sees you, that's different than when a patient
sees an average internist, let's say, and it's different when a patient doesn't see any doctor.
So, the idea that there's the bus that rolls up that just does your blood work and sends it back
to you in the mail, that's terrible. I mean, I did that when I was a resident, they paid me 50 bucks
and go man, the bus and do that. That's not really doing that patient, those individual men,
they're not helping those people because you don't know their whole health history and all that.
So, I experienced that and I got into it with Otis Brawley about screening and he raised that
point and it's valid. I did that when I was a resident because I was told to do it and it wasn't,
that's a mistake just bringing up the bus and doing blood tests in the Walmart parking lot.
That's not a good answer. Having a discussion with the physician is, their internist is a good
answer because I have many patients. What were the bus parameters by the way? Men between age?
Any guy who showed up. Literally any dude who shows up could get a free PSA.
Yeah. You know, and then they'd say, how did I not know you were doing that?
I did it once or twice, you know, when I was a lab year resident and they'd say,
go ahead and do you want to earn 50 bucks? And remember I drove to some civil war
town in Northern Virginia. It was a cool town. I did it on a Saturday for half day and I did it
and it was like in hindsight, you say, okay, I get it. It was worth doing because now I understand
how bad that was and what a mistake that was. Now, conversely, I have a lot of patients that
rolled in. They're super healthy, 68 year old guys with PSAs of 20 and they have a bad rectal exam.
They had a PSA when they were 60 and it was three and they'd come in and I've had a couple of
experiences where the spouse is just hysterical because she's like, how could this guy,
her husband's internist just stop the test and not discuss it with us?
And to be clear, where is the screening recommendation on rectal exam? Well,
it's variable. I mean, I think a rectal exam adds value. Many of the internist societies say that
you don't necessarily need to do it. I do think it requires experience, but I think it's part of the
physical exam. So you should do it. If you do it enough, you'll get an idea for what's really bad
and what's not. And so I have a lot of really good internists that still do it and they do a great
job. And so I think it's regional and it's also varies by the country. I could probably use a
tutorial on it, but I do it a lot and I realize that it's-
Can you insert like a zipper noises? I'll show you how to do it.
Perfect. I want the technique, but I can see that if it's something you're just not doing
frequently, if it's something you would only do on someone who shows up with a high PSA,
you're not getting the reps. You got to sort of know what normal feels like.
The same thing is-
What does a 20 year old prostate feel like?
Listening to a heart.
You don't need a 20 year old prostate exam, but you listen to the heart of everybody and that's
how you know when you detect pathology. It's the same-
But in trauma, you got all of those.
You did.
Yeah. In trauma, you got to see a lot of normal
prostate.
So I think that the guidelines have come to a medium. The pendulum was both ways.
I think that prostate biopsies are these days a relatively safe procedure. They're not overly
traumatic for men. There are some men that have complications. I think that that's a little bit
overly dramatized by people who are anti-screeners. The other thing that
urologists are doing today is now doing transparanial biopsies. So they're not transrectal anymore.
So if a patient's listening to this and they need to go and get a prostate biopsy, one of the things
I always tell patients is you should always... It's one thing to know what the average
complication rates are, this risk of infection, this risk of bleeding.
It's also important to ask your practitioner their personal risks because medicine is not
homogeneous. It's quite heterogeneous. So what would we say nationally would be the risk of
infection or bleeding from a prostate biopsy?
Well, I tell people most men have some degree of bleeding after the biopsy. When you have a bowel
movement, there may be a little bit of blood.
Let's say bleeding that requires...
Yeah, right. So that's my point. So if you go on blogs about non-anti-screeners, they'll say,
oh, 80% of men have bleeding in their rectum and 100% have blood in their urine. Yeah, sure. There
may be a little bit of pinkness or redness, or if you do a microscopic exam on the urine,
there's blood. That's ridiculous. Of course, you can have that. But is it requiring admission
to the hospital? We wrote a paper on that looking in the Medicare age population.
The numbers, it's hard because you look at these big data sets, it's hard to know granularity.
They say about 7% of individuals will be admitted to the hospital or seen at the ER within 30 days
of a biopsy. That number seems high to me. I tell people at our institution, we monitor our biopsy
infections, it's 0.4%. Got it. So somebody shows up at Northwestern knowing that seven out of a
hundred guys are going to be back in the hospital a month, and you can say, actually, in our hands,
our series, it's four out of a thousand. You feel a heck of a lot better. Yeah, with an infection.
I would say that it's probably about one to 2% show up at the ER, something for an evaluation.
Because you can have some problems urinating because your prostate can get a little bit swollen.
So overall, it's low. You tell them the results. And as you alluded to before, in my practice,
I don't biopsy everybody. I biopsy people who I think have clinically significant prostate cancer.
So I start with the PHI test. We have it within our system here.
And so I use the 4K. Yeah, that's the same.
Is there any reason to switch from one to the other? Are you pretty agnostic?
No, Hans Lillian and Andrew Vickers show that they perform identically in the same serum.
What patients, so the 4K was developed on a cohort of what sounds like pretty
homogeneous patients, right? What was the PHI developed on? What was their cohort?
Similar. I mean, most of these tests are done and developed in Caucasian men.
I was going to ask you, do we run a risk here if I have an African American patient,
and can I be misled by his 4K? Shouldn't I be-
Well, that was a good question. And the OPCO team just published a paper based on
validation cohort of VA patients where there was 50% African American,
and it performed as well or slightly better. One of my partners here has a prospective trial.
It's him and myself looking at PHI and African American men, and the early take-home messages,
it looks like it performs as well or better. So this is a gift. I mean, you don't normally get
this in biology. This is exactly the kind of test that can go awry because you can get fooled by
differences. And so I'll give you an example, right? You look at non-alcoholic fatty liver
disease and FLD. I mean, if you want to study that disease in Hispanics and then try to make
even the mildest inference about what's going on in African Americans, you're hosed. I mean,
they're not even the same disease. In fact, even diabetes is quite different across races. So to
think that something as ubiquitous as prostate cancer, even though it might be a different
disease, because I know that African Americans, we're going to talk about this, I'm sure, have
a different disease. But even from a screening standpoint that they could be, you could have
one tool that is so good in both is fortuitous. Yeah, they're good tools. And then so after,
if there's an abnormality in the PHI or 4K score, then I moved to an MRI. And then there's been good
data. And can you just, because I mean, we geek out on this stuff because I'm super nerdy about
what type of MRI to do for what thing. But for a patient listening to this Ted, who's going to go
to their doctor and whose doctor is hopefully cooperative enough, what do you recommend? Because
not all MRIs are doing the trick here. Yeah. I mean, on paper, what you want is a
multi-parametric prostate MRI. The most important phase, the most important parameter in the
multi-parametric MRI is actually the diffusion weighted imaging, which is the most operators
dependent. So it really requires a skilled technician and a skilled interpreter radiologist
to look at those DWI images. That's the most important one. So we do give patients contrast,
but people have shown you can get a lot of value out of just a non-contrast DWI based.
The one we use, no contrast, but it's their DWI is exceptional. I've sent you the images. I think
if they're Schaeffer approved, I'm happy. They're very good. Yeah. T1, T2, DWI,
multi-planar MRI. So if you're listening to that and if your doctor refuses that, I think those
are the kinds of things that make me think you need another doctor. Because at this point,
and look, your insurance might not cover it. You may have to foot the bill for that. And that's
horrible if your insurance wouldn't cover that. Well, that was true, but there's recently reported
a large multinational prospective clinical trial looking at the utility of MRI to use for screening
for prostate cancer. And the study was half the men got an MRI. And if there was a suspicious
lesion, they got that lesion biopsied and they increased the detection of high-grade cancer,
reduced the over-detection of low-grade prostate cancer. So it was a quote unquote positive study.
We haven't had problems in the Midwest and Illinois getting MRIs approved, but that
randomized trial based out of reported out of the UK, that really has changed a lot about what
companies are approving for MRIs for screening. That's great to hear. So if somebody has an MRI,
if there's an abnormality on the MRI, I'll recommend a biopsy. Now, there's a lot of data
that says you shouldn't just sample the suspicious lesion, that you should do the suspicious lesion
plus doing a sextant biopsy or kind of what I tell patients is right, left, top, middle, bottom.
That adds value, not just in the detection of cancer, but if someone is going to move to
surgery, for example, and I don't do a biopsy in a 90 year old guy, even if they have an abnormal MRI,
do it if I think that person's going to live long enough to benefit from treatment. In those
scenarios, I do those systematic biopsies because I want to know exactly where the extent of the
cancer. And one of the problems with MRIs, it doesn't actually see the true boundaries or true
borders of the tumors within the prostate very well. So they're often- Especially the DWI,
because it's not really an anatomic test. The way a T1-weighted image is anatomic.
So if you take the lesion on T2, for example, it often undersizes the tumor by between 5 and 10
millimeters. So pretty significant for a prostate, which is generally pretty small. So I do those to
get a better roadmap. I put it all together and then I'll talk to the patient about what the
treatment should be. So my algorithm is if you have an MRI done and you have an abnormality,
you need a biopsy. If you have an MRI done and it's negative, no lesion, but this is your quiz
for the day, Peter, but what is high? Your PSA density is high, so you have nothing suspicious
on MR, but a high PSA density, you need a biopsy. And sorry, in that situation, Ted, do you further
stratify by 4K? Well, I've done the 4K or PHI upfront. Which is high enough. So you were already
talking about a subset of patients who have a high enough. I think something's going on based
on the blood test because 20% of the time, MRIs false negative. Got it. So now you're using the
prostate density. And you and I actually shared an email exchange over this about six months ago.
PSA density is so easy and it is so good. So high PSA density, usually I would say more than 0.15
depends. Sometimes it's 0.1, depends on the age of the patient and their scenario.
They need a biopsy anyway and 20% of the time MRIs are negative. But if they have an MRI,
no lesion, high PSA and a low PSA density, they don't need a biopsy. So we published our series
on that. It's not a randomized trial, but what we showed was that when we looked and compared
the doctors that use that algorithm and those that did not, you reduce biopsies by about one third,
you reduce detection of low-grade cancer by about one third, and you actually don't compromise the
detection of higher grade disease. So again, we have great tools building off of this very
simple PSA blood test to, I think, offer people very sophisticated screening for their prostate
cancer. We've talked about that a bunch. Yeah. So let's talk a little bit about the biopsy because
every patient here who's had a biopsy or knows somebody who's had a biopsy, there's this word
Gleason. What's your Gleason? That could be like a t-shirt. So Donald, you guys need to do a
fundraiser here. That could be the urology fundraiser at North West. There's a lot of things
you could put on t-shirts. Yeah. I mean, let's take a step back from it. So as you know, one of
my best friends from medical school, my roommate from medical school, Matt McCormick, is now an
excellent urologist up in Reno. And I just saw Matt a couple of weeks ago and we were kind of just,
we have a patient in common by total luck. So the patient came to see me and he lives in Reno. And
I said, oh, that's so funny. My roommate from med school is up in Reno and his name's Matt
McCormick. And he's like, Dr. McCormick is my doctor. I couldn't believe it. What a small world.
But I remember in medical school, like one of the things that drew Matt to urology,
because we all thought Matt was going to be an orthopedic surgeon. There was just,
it's like the most amazing athlete in the history of civilization. Like this guy's going to be an
orthopod because that's what you expect your athletes to do. But then when we all started
our doing our rotations, he sort of fell in love with urology. And I think a big part of it had to
do with two, there were two things. One was, it's a field where you can't take yourself that
seriously. Like in the end, it's a funny, funny field. Like there's just a lot of dick jokes.
There's no way around it. And if you find that, if you don't think that's funny, like you're not
going to want to be in that. You got to make it funny. And the second thing was the patients are
so grateful. And again, I think if you're a medical student and you're listening to this,
you've got to be able to think about what kind of patients you want to interact with. That has a
lot to do with your chosen profession. I remember there were people in my class who loved being
around older patients and they wanted to go into cardiology for that reason because they're like,
look, my bread and butter, the patient I'm mostly going to see is going to be like my grandmother
and my grandfather. And that's why I came to medical school. That's what I love. And that's
what I want to do. And there's just something about that urology patient. And again, urology
is a broad field because there's male urology, female urology, cancer, non-cancer. But for the
most part, as you said, you get to fix things in people that are causing them real trouble. And
again, I'm not minimizing the stuff that I was interested in, which is like pancreatic cancer.
But when you take a person's pancreatic cancer out, they don't necessarily feel any better.
That's true. They usually feel worse because it's a big surgery.
It's a huge operation. And it's a lethal, I mean, I think that there's a lot of urology that,
I mean, look, the patients that we take, the people in urology are great. And so going to
work every day is just a blast. I mean, everybody's smart. Everybody's fun. They don't take themselves
too seriously. That helps. The patients are wonderful people. They're incredibly grateful.
And then urologists also, you know, we own the diagnosis. So a lot of other surgical specialties,
let's say colorectal surgery is an example. Very few of the diagnoses come from the colorectal
surgeon. And therefore, if you own the diagnoses, you own the pretreatment, the pre-diagnostic work,
you do the intervention and you follow the patient afterward. And so one of the nice things
in urology is that you have this great longitudinal care with patients. And so many of my patients
followed me from Baltimore. And you know, my nurse, Marie, who's fabulous, she hates me because,
you know, I'll have like a 15 minute return double book, but it's one of my old Hopkins patients,
you know, I'm in the room for two hours, you know, and she's like, what were you doing in there?
I'm like, oh, we're talking about their kids or the goats or the whatever, you know. And so
that part of it really makes it super fun. I forgot about the goat.
Yeah. I love the goats. Yeah. So I've been trying to get goats.
Goats are...
I've been trying. I'm not winning.
They're not allowed in your town?
No, I just, I can't convince the family to get the goats.
Oh my God. You got to go to, pig me goat, cutest thing ever. They're so cute. They stink,
but they're super cute. And they're incredibly smart and they're very social. So they do not
like, you can't just get one goat. They really, they actually, they don't, they do terribly if
they're just by themselves. So anyway, so, you know, that's the fun part about urologists. You
get, you know, you get these patients and they all have a mate. I mean, I learned, I love just
talking to my patients. Dr. Walsh, he had a way to do a history. And one of the second thing he
asked is what they did for a living. And it wasn't to kind of do a checkbook check. It was just to
say how are you going to talk to this person? And for me, it's, I like to ask them that because I
love to just learn about what they do. There are so many cool jobs out there, you know, so,
you know, sound engineer for a big theater in Chicago, this or that. It's just awesome. Super
cool. Yeah. You've had quite an illustrious career that's not even close to being over,
which is also includes, and I know, I know you don't think much about this and I think it's more
of a nuisance than anything else, but you've also now basically become the urologist to
anyone in power that seems to need, you know, just as Pat was basically when we were at Hopkins,
every VIP on the planet came to Hopkins. And I can't even as a general surgery resident rotating
through urology, I can't believe the people that walked through that hospital, which was also true
in pancreatic surgery and, you know, all sorts of other surgeries. But, and so of all of the,
the sort of people I don't, I, again, I don't want to use names because I don't know how many of them
have ever publicly talked about it. The only one who I know has publicly talked about it is Ben
Stiller because of course you and Ben went on Howard Stern together. So how did you even get
introduced to Ben Stiller? And I know Ben was very private about this for a couple of years. You
guys went, if my memory serves me correctly, it was probably a year or two after his surgery that
you guys even went on the show together, right? Yeah, it was two years or so after that. And I
met him through his internist, this great, really one of the best internists I've ever interacted
with Bernie Kruger. You're telling me like, I don't know who he is. I am. I know. I'm just saying it
for the audience. Bernie's great. So for the listener, Ted introduced me to Bernie four or
five years ago when I was starting to practice in New York. And he said, Bernie's the best
internist I've ever had a referral from, probably because he trained as a medical oncologist,
but he said he's really freaking smart and he knows his stuff. And if you're going to be in New
York, you got to meet him. So you introduced us. I went to meet Bernie. We hit it off like
in seconds. Yeah. And he just said, why don't you just come in my office? And so to this day,
I still sit next to Bernie. Bernie's great. So Bernie was taking care of Ben and Bernie was
the guy who did all the right stuff. He did the blood work and it was abnormal for him and his
age and got biopsied in New York. And then he came and met, he met with Dr. Walsh because Dr. Walsh
wrote this, has this amazing book, Dr. Walsh's Guide to Surviving Prostate Cancer and Ben had
gotten it. And so he came down to meet with Walsh, but Walsh wasn't operating anymore at that time.
And so that's how I met him was through Bernie and through Walsh. I have a copy of the book for
you by the way, because I convinced Dr. Walsh to do a final edition of it. Just came out in May.
It's really, really good. So all the listeners out there, it's a great resource. So that's how
we met. And then he had interviewed with a bunch of folks and he decided to have surgery with me,
which was, I was honored to be able to do. And then he did great. And so he's been an amazing
person for the field because he's not afraid to talk about his journey and what he did. And
he really, he's an amazing person. He's just a down to earth good guy. So for me, I view each
of my patients as VIPs, you know, really honestly in my heart of hearts do. And so yes, I take care
of people who are, you know, important in many different professions and walks of life. And so
it's fun to help all of them. And it's fun to go on Howard Stern with Ben Stiller. That was a great
experience. Yeah. So by the way, it sort of occurs to me when you say this that you were still
relatively junior as a urologist. You'd probably only been out of your training for six, seven
years when you operated on Ben. Did that ruffle any feathers at Hopkins that you became the heir
apparent? I mean, people tell me it did. You know, I never really thought about age in that way.
You know, I've always pushed myself to be the best surgeon I can be and always tried to
measure up to Pat Walsh or one of my other mentors was this guy, Val Carter. These guys
were the brilliant surgeons at Hopkins. And so to me, it didn't matter that they had been doing
it for 20 years and I had done it for one year. I wanted to be as good as they were just like,
you know, you were the same way. And so that's how I always viewed it. Right. And so,
and it was just the environment I surrounded myself with. So for me, when Walsh said, you know,
listen, I want you to become my partner and eventually want you to take over my practice.
When I started quote unquote, as his partner, he was still top of his game and was the man. And I
benefited from that because he was so busy. I, you know, he would refer me cases. And at the very end
of, you know, our relationship or time at Hopkins, you know, he wasn't operating anymore. And so I
would, if he had patients that needed surgery, I would do it. And everybody, I think on the outside
thought that this was this easy thing. It was a gig. But listen, when a guy you operate on,
not only reports to you how he's doing, but how to Pat Walsh, how he's doing, then that's serious.
You know, you got to be on your game. Yeah. It's like an eternal fellowship that you never left.
Right. Right. So, you know, he would call me and say, you know, so-and-so says his incision is
crooked. And I'm like, Oh my God, you know, so like, you know, you couldn't get away with anything.
And so it makes you better, right? It definitely makes you better. So let's go back to the t-shirt
raffle thing. And what's your Gleason? So what is this Gleason score? So Donald Gleason is a
pathologist. He was a pathologist and many people, including the folks at Hopkins, were coming up
with a way to grade prostate cancer. So we grade cancers and that's a way to measure how aggressive
they are. And usually cancers are kind of high grade, low grade, or a one, two, three kind of
system. And Gleason came up with a way to grade prostate cancer based on the appearance of the
gland. So if you go back to our analogy or discussion of the sewer system, effectively,
you know, there are these channels that the prosthetic fluid comes down and out of. And
these channels will grow abnormally in a cancerous state. And so Gleason was describing how these
channels appeared under the microscope. Now, one of the interesting things about it was,
unlike a lot of other cancers where they would describe the grade of a cancer based on a high
power view, like a very, very close view, Gleason graded his prostate cancers in a lower power
view. So he got a better sense of the- More of an architecture. It's an architectural thing.
So it's the tree, not the leaves. Whereas a lot of grades are the, what does the leaf look like?
Yeah. What's the edge of the leaf look like? So he did it. And so the way he did it was,
he said, well, what's the most common looking abnormality? What's the most prevalent abnormality
on the view of the tumor? And then what's the second most common kind of glandular architecture?
And so the Gleason sum is those two things, the most prevalent and then the next most prevalent.
And that went from, and so it was a one to five scale. So the lowest Gleason score originally,
Gleason sum- So there are 10 combinations.
Yeah. The lowest Gleason sum would be a two, the highest Gleason sum would be a 10. That was how
it started out. But then over time- So meaning a one plus one or a five plus five.
That's right. So over time that evolved and the lowest Gleason sum would be a six, a three plus
three was the kind of typical read. Meaning because if you're already at the point where
you're doing a biopsy, you're not going to see ones. You shouldn't be seeing ones and twos if
you're doing a biopsy. Is that the thinking? I think that there were some general organizational,
architectural features that everybody just agreed were low grade, not aggressive. And yes,
you could occasionally, occasionally even at the Hopkins, I'd see it on final pathology report
a Gleason with some pattern two in it. And they would try to explain to me the subtleties of the
difference between a pattern two and a pattern three. I think most pathologists call it a,
they would just call it a three. So that's where it was for a long time. But there are some subtle
differences in the Gleason sum that actually have real big differences for what the patient's
outcomes would be. And so in 2015, in late 2014, the International Society for Urologic Pathologists.
So we're talking about dork central here. I mean, real super geeks, but really good pathologists,
they are kind of people. Yeah. They got together along with RadOnks, radiation oncologists,
medical oncologists, urologists, and said, we need a better way to transmit this information to
patients and to internists in a way they can understand. So now there's a great group. And
the great group goes between one and five. The original kind of old school Gleason sum of six,
that's a one. A Gleason three plus four equals seven is a two. A four plus three equals seven
is a three. A four plus four equals eight is a four. Four plus five equals nine, or five, five
is a five. So this stepwise gradation into five bins of aggressiveness called the great group
actually translates very nicely into stepwise clinical outcomes. So that's the new kind of
way that we talk about it. I talk about with my patients, just the great group. So you're a great
group one, two, three, four, or five. So do you do any other testing? Do you use oncotype or any
of these other genetic testing algorithms to further stratify or do those only become things
that are done post-surgery to determine adjuvant care? So I think that they can, yeah, that's a
good question. So I generally speaking don't because I think I know what the patient, what they
need. So what do I mean by that? Well, you taught me when we are interns, you don't order a test,
don't do a test unless you know what you're going to do. Well, and yeah, it's so funny,
I was just having this discussion with a patient yesterday. Don't order a test if it will not
alter your management. Right. So I don't do a prostate biopsy in a 95 year old guy who's got
an LVAD. I don't do it. The urology consult to this coronary ICU. So I don't do the test unless
it's going to change what I recommend for the patient. So prostate biopsy, I'll do it if I
think I should change something. So I don't do the test unless it's going to change something
I recommend. And for me, there's not many cases where it will change what I recommend. So meaning
what do I mean by that? Well, again, we don't actively treat all prostate cancers today.
People who have grade group one prostate cancer, generally we recommend active surveillance,
monitoring the tumor to see if it becomes more aggressive versus... And to be clear, these are
patients who, these are the quote unquote Gleason 3 plus 3s. That's right. And we're saying we're
going to actively monitor you. And once you have the pathology in your hand, that grade group or
the Gleason score, does anything before that matter anymore? In other words, does it matter
in your thinking that this guy had actually a 4K of 7.5% versus 20%? Yeah, it does matter. And the MRI
results matter. So this is the ultimate Bayesian experience. Yeah. I mean, you know, that's why the
genomic test, it's funny, if you measure and you compare a genomic test, and there's a bunch of
them out there, head to head with PSA density, PSA density performs pretty much identically well.
Right? It's pretty amazing. And do you get the grams? I mean, the MRI does a great job at doing
that. Can you get that? Can you get that off ultrasound? If patient has an MRI? We measure
at the time of the biopsy, we'll measure it. But the, you know, generally speaking-
Yeah, we get it off the MRI. MRIs is what I use. So a Gleason 6, I generally will recommend
surveillance unless they're super high volume 6. And I know in my brain that-
And that's independent of age. So a 40 year old, I mean, we have a mutual patient who
was a Gleason 7, I believe, at the very young age, like 45, correct? Yeah. Did his age,
being 45 versus 65, change the way you managed him? Well, so he came in with a single core
7 and really wanted to do surveillance. And that would be one opportunity to say,
let's do a genomic test on this individual. And let's see how aggressive the tumor looks
under the true microscope, the molecular profile of the tumor. And so we talked about doing that
and his biopsy, the molecular test was favorable, but you don't forget about those patients. You
actually follow them active surveillance. So we rebiopsied him after a repeat MRI and he had a lot
more. His MRI was actually pretty favorable. This was an MRI invisible lesion and he had multi-core
7. So we then, we took him to surgery and he did very well. Yeah. I always think of his case as
just one of those examples of, I don't know what the term is, because I don't want to use the term
precision medicine because that's become so stupid and meaningless. And I don't even want to use the
term multidisciplinary because it really wasn't multidisciplinary. It was mostly Schaeffer
disciplinary. But I guess it's just the nuance of the field. That's the medicine. That's right.
Yeah. That's the hard part. That's the part that you don't necessarily figure out in residency.
It's so easy, I think, to go through residency, learning the technical stuff,
learning the surgical judgment. What do you do if this person's got a post-operative bleed versus an
infection and who do you sit on? Who do you take back to the OR? Those are very important skills.
But this is like next layer judgment stuff that aside from talking with your colleagues and
surrounding yourself by people who are, you try to surround yourself by people smarter than you,
how do you continue that evolution of learning? We have what I call adult-only journal club every
other Friday morning. So it's all the oncologist in our group, med-onks, rad-onks, urologists,
urologic oncologist. And I call it adult-only because it's not really for the residents. It's
during their teaching conference. And we just pull articles that come up every day. So every
Friday morning, I get a feed from the NIH about new prostate cancer articles. Any article with
prostate cancer in it, I get that link. It's about 180 to 200 papers a week. I review that list,
and anything that looks good, I pull it, and I'll look at the abstract error. I'll pull the paper.
And so I send those to the group. And on Friday, two days from now, we'll go over my prostate
articles, plus my partner's bladder cancer articles or kidney cancer articles. I don't read those.
So I have them tell me what's important in those fields. So that's how I... It's really fun,
because it's just like, you know, what we... It's being in school again. It's being in school.
It's this idea of continuous learning. So that's how I think about it and try to keep on top of it.
Meetings are okay, but I think that people get bogged down in just the politics of a meeting.
So I think reading is what I try to do most of. So let's pivot to another topic that's germane to
prostate cancer, which is kind of a two topic that goes hand in hand. The first is the role of
testosterone. The second is the role of dihydrotestosterone. So we can explore this in any
order, but I want to definitely touch on the notion that is there a real or perceived effect
of patients who are on five alpha reductase inhibitors? So for the listener, males make a
hormone called testosterone. Testosterone is converted via an enzyme called five alpha reductase
into a very similar molecule called dihydrotestosterone, abbreviated DHT. DHT is actually
a slightly more potent steroid and in men who... 15 times more potent. Yeah. Yeah. So it's a big
deal. In men who are susceptible to baldness, DHT drives that process. DHT also probably plays a
role in the enlargement of the prostate. Is that correct? Most of the five alpha reductase enzyme
is in the prostate. So yes, reducing androgens in the prostate by reducing, effectively reducing
DHT production reduces the size of the prostate. So a lot of guys take medication to reduce DHT,
either to reduce prostate volume size, so something called benign prosthetic hypertrophy,
or to minimize hair loss. And it's usually the exact same drug given at slightly different
doses. And then sometimes even come up with different names for the same drug. So Proscar
is finasterid at five milligrams and I think Propecia is the one milligram. That's right.
Okay. Now I remember many years ago, and I'm sure this has been revised a hundred times,
but maybe 10 years ago, maybe less. But a paper came out that said, look, in guys who have
suppressed DHT levels, when they get prostate cancer, they're more high grade. Am I remembering
that correctly? Yeah, there's been definitely case reports of that. It's hard to really study that
over a big number. I got it. So what is the current thinking on
five alpha-productase inhibition and that relationship to prostate cancer? Well,
there was a very large randomized trial to see if you could take that medication with the idea
that if you reduced the relative amount of androgens in the prostate by preventing the
production of this potent androgen, DHT, could you reduce the risk of prostate cancer in those men?
And the answer was if you took that medicine that reduced potent androgen, you could.
There was a study. I'm sorry, this was in men starting out who did not have cancer?
That's right. So it was called the prostate cancer prevention trial.
And it was over seven years that the trial was conducted. Ian Thompson was the PI on the trial,
it was a big study. It did reduce the chance that a man would develop prostate cancer
over a reasonable amount of time. But one of the problems was that there was increased
detection of more aggressive cancers in the men who are taking the finasteride. And so then the
question was, well, what is that from? Is it inducing a more high-grade cancer? And whether
or not that's true or not is true. Or is it selecting for it because any cancer that comes
out of a low DHT environment? Well, yeah. So I personally think that what you were just saying
is true. So yes, and there's case reports that people with low testosterone or for example,
people with low PSAs because PSA is only made when there's testosterone around, for example,
that those individuals have more aggressive cancers. Now, this is what I've been focusing
on in my lab for like the last four or five years now. And so one of the cool things we did
in this collaboration with this company, Genome DX, and this great scientist, Eli DaVincioni,
was to look at the biology of prostate cancers, how aggressive they were,
and compare the aggressiveness of the prostate cancer with the androgen output of the tumor.
Another nuanced way to normalize things a bit.
Yeah. And so we had this hypothesis that the tumors that had the most amped up androgen
signaling, the most androgen output because prostate cancer is an androgen driven tumor,
that they would be the most aggressive. And I say it that way because you know, the answer
is the exact opposite. The tumors with the lowest androgen output are the most aggressive tumors.
So it somewhat relates to PSA, but not entirely like it's not a true linear correlation.
So the high androgen output tumors, they can be aggressive, but they are not as aggressive
as the ultra low one. So it's this bimodal distribution. And this is a good way to segue,
talking about these molecular tests, because this is a commercially available test from Genome DX.
Can I tell a funny story about Eli before we go down there?
Sure.
I've told this story before, but now we get to put a name to it. So I hope he doesn't like,
like, I hope I don't upset him that I'm telling this story.
He'll love it.
It was, Eli's the guy who called me one day when I was in the airport. And he's like,
Peter, my wife just got me this book. It's a great book and you're in it. And I was like,
what? I had no idea what he was talking about. And he goes, yeah, it's called Biggest Tools.
And I was like, wait, do you mean Tools of Titans? He goes, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's it.
That's great.
That was Eli. I know I've told that story.
So to this day, like anytime I'm talking with Tim Ferriss, like I'm like, look,
I expect to be referred to as the biggest tool.
That is, I love that story.
He called me too. He's like, dude, I'm reading this book, but he didn't call it Biggest Tools.
That's awesome. That's really funny. So Eli started this company that was,
genomically transcriptomically. So looking at the RNA levels within prostate cancers. And so
he has a commercial product that's very, very good to just tell you the aggressiveness. It's
basically a genomic Leason score. It's more sophisticated than that, but that's effectively
what it helps you to do. But when he looks at each tumor, he captures about 1.4 million data
points on each tumor. He uses 21 of them for his test, but we use the other 1.3999 million of those
data points. And so we developed this algorithm to look at this. The thing that's pretty cool is
we've been able to model and show with Eli's group that, because it's one thing to have a kind of
prognostic biomarker, like your prognosis is good or bad, but precision medicine is really the
predictive stuff. So we've been able to take all this data. We've been able to show that these
low androgen output tumors are the most aggressive tumors. Now high androgen output, very high
AR output tumors are also aggressive, but as you would imagine, the tumors are sensitive to
different drugs. So a high AR output tumor, they're exquisitely sensitive to androgen deprivation,
which is one of the main states of treatment for metastatic prostate cancer. Low androgen output
tumors are not dependent on it. They don't use it as their fuel for growth. And we've been able to
model other compounds that they are sensitive to. And so we're moving those things into clinical
trials. It's actually pretty exciting times. So what is the current state of the art or the
current thinking on testosterone replacement therapy? And again, I'm referring to this in
the confines of what we would call physiologic testosterone replacement. So you've got a guy
who's walking around with a free testosterone at seven nanograms per deciliter on a lab where the
upper range would be 25 and he's replaced to 20. My reading of the literature says I'd have a very
hard time making the case that's increasing his risk of prostate cancer. I agree with that.
And I think my data suggests that the tumors that we don't know how they develop, but the tumor,
we segued like five times. But the idea is that our data shows us that the most aggressive tumors
are the ones that have low androgen output. Now, does that mean that they developed in a low
androgen state? Maybe. We don't know.
That's my question.
We don't know. But for sure, it's telling me that I don't, and like you said, the literature that
we've discussed on the phone many times, I don't see any clear evidence that physiologic replacement
of testosterone is going to accelerate or cause a cancer to develop. What do you think the role is
of estradiol in this? Some have argued that as estradiol is going up, that may be playing a greater
role in prostate cancer, either through its direct interaction or indirectly through its receptors.
I think I don't know the answer to that question, but I do know that it's not just a testosterone
thing. Remember, when we just talk about benign urologic conditions, testosterone values decline
over time. And I oversimplified the whole PSA discussion earlier. So remember that PSAs rise
over time, but at that same time, testosterone values are declining. So I do think that a lot
of the prosthetic growth, not cancerous growth necessarily, but benign growth are influenced by
the ratios of T to E, so to speak, testosterone to estrogens, androgens to estrogens, which ones-
Yeah, because it seems to me that you're at your highest risk when your testosterone is going down
and your estrogen is going up. Yeah. Now the question is, what's the lag time? So in real time,
yes, that's true, but we know that all cancers, prostate cancer for sure among them,
is something that occurs from mutations to the DNA from decades prior, probably. So yes, at the
time of diagnoses, there's probably higher estradiol, lower T, but I think about it like,
well, what happened to that in that patient 10 years beforehand or 15 years? Is there anything
about the mitochondria in the prostate? I mean, the prostate has so many odd things about it,
and we're going to talk about the difficulty with immune surveillance in a moment, but
is there anything about the mitochondria within the prostate that are unusually
either ramped up or ramped down relative to other epithelial cell-derived tissues?
Yeah, it's a great question. And-
And I hope you know, I try to ask great questions here, man.
I say that because we just had, last Saturday we had our kind of a prostate cancer working group
meeting where all the kind of deep thinkers get together, we got together on a Saturday.
Yeah, I was just about to say, the fact that you guys do this on a Saturday is just another
bit of evidence to the level of obsession here that I love.
Yeah, so I roped in this brilliant radiation oncologist named David Gaius. He works on
hormonal dependency in breast cancer, and what he focuses on is on the mitochondria,
and specifically these superoxide dismutases that really get rid of reactive oxygen species.
And so he has a whole model and he knows about luminal B breast cancers and how they can become
resistant to tamoxifen and so forth. And it's driven by basically the mitochondria.
And so-
Do the mitochondria in the prostate cancer follow the Warburg effect? Do they
favor anaerobic metabolism over oxidative phosphorylation?
You know, it's hard. People don't, we don't know. People don't know a lot about the metabolic
environment of the prostate. I've had a lot of thoughts about where, what about the, I mean,
it's a very dense organ. There's not a lot of blood vessels in it. It's not a big blood supply.
And so I thought a lot about just, for example, are there regional differences in the pH within
the prostate? And is that what's causing these? Because I think about it in relationship to these
androgen dependent tumors. My brain has defaulted to this idea that, well, the high AR output tumors
are ones that are occurring in oxygen rich parts of the prostate. I mean, I don't know why,
just assume that, you know, and that these lower AR output tumors are occurring in regions of the
prostate that have lower PAO2s, different pHs, and they're forced to use an alternate growth
pathway. It's hard to test that. You know, I've thought a lot about it. There's nothing published
on it really. It's hard to test it, but this guy, David Gias, has a lot of really interesting data
looking at the sirtunin pathways through mitochondria, regulating the hormonal dependency
or hormonal regulation of prostate cancer. It's a brand new area for him. So in other words,
the sirtuins, which of course can either turn on or turn off genes, the idea is, and this is SIRT2
or a different SIRT3. SIRT3. I see. So it could be up-regulating or down-regulating
antigen production, basically. He has a SIRT3 manganese superoxide dismutase pathway worked out
and it regulates resistance to tamoxifeniluminal B breast cancer. So, and he's made these
observations. He first published this in Cell in, I want to say, 07-08 on sirtunin 3 in breast,
but he's had some data in there in prostate. So I kind of, we hang out with him when I want to
hang out with like a deep thinker. So he has this preliminary data and he has some more interesting
data that there may be a role for this. So I do think that there's something about
metabolism in the prostate. I think it's hard to study. It's a tough, it's hard to model that
in a mouse at all. Like you can't do it. You cannot model in a mouse. I do think that there's
some good people on campus here who think about it and are going to be able to study it well.
He's the guy. I'm seeing Nav Chandel tomorrow who is a mutual friend. Didn't you go to med
school with Nav? No. He was in grad school when you were in med school or something.
He says that he was my TA in undergrad, but I just know, you know, known him. I think we figured
out I've known him in 19, I met him in 93 or 94. So he's really one of my oldest friends I have.
Anything I should know about Nav? I know him of course, because we played
paddy cakes on Easter Island for a while. Do you know what his nickname is?
No, that's the thing. There was a nickname. What's his nickname?
Well, just for the listeners, Navdeep is this, he's about what, 6 foot 3?
Yeah, very suave, good looking guy, long hair. So his nickname was suaveep.
I've never seen a TA class where it was like 90% women who had questions for him afterward.
You know, it was awesome in med school. He's great.
And did you also go to school with Matthew Vanderheiden?
I did. He was the smartest kid in my med school class.
Yeah. Matthew, I mean, I know Matthew, obviously not as well as you, but-
I don't know him that well. I just know him and Nav really broke open the field of cancer
metabolism. Yeah. I'll be, I gotta get out to Boston to see Matthew, who actually works
and collaborates very closely with another very, very close friend of mine from medical school
named Mark Pomerance, who's a medical oncologist. Yeah, I know Mark. Yeah, he's great.
All of these independent circles of my life have overlapped in prostate cancer and cancer in general.
Yeah. What is the most exciting area of research that you think of with respect to prostate cancer
specifically? Maybe I'll even prime the question by saying immunotherapy seems to finally be coming
into its own a little bit with some cancers. But of course the prostate is kind of a weird
immune protected odd organ. Like does immunotherapy play a role in this or are we talking
metabolic therapies or is it all going to be coming down to earlier detection of lethal cancers?
Certainly, early detection of lethal cancers is important. I think the most exciting stuff in
urologic oncology is really moving beyond these prognostic biomarkers to predictive biomarkers.
And so there's a lot of really cool new things that are great. So there are some
predictive biomarkers that you can pick up in the DNA of a tumor or the DNA of a patient,
particularly BRCA1, BRCA2, ATM lost these different kinds of DNA damage repair pathways
that people didn't really think matter for prostate. We now know within the last three
years that they really matter. So I didn't, that's news to me. I never really understood
that BRCA1 and BRCA2 should be looked for in males as well. I mean, I did from a breast
cancer standpoint, but not from a prostate cancer standpoint. Yeah. So there's one of my heroes in
urologic oncology is this guy, Pete Nelson. He's at the Hutch in Seattle and he published a paper
and they looked at the germ lines of men with metastatic castrate resistance. So at the most
end states prostate cancer. And what they showed was that in contrast to the general population of
men, that mutations in these different DNA repair pathways were significantly enriched in individuals
who had metastatic prostate cancer. So about 11 to 12% of men with metastatic castrate resistant
prostate cancer had mutations, particularly BRCA2, BRCA1, ATM, RAD51, these different pathways that
are involved in DNA damage repair. If you look in the tumors of men with metastatic castrate
resistant prostate cancer, it depending on where you look over one third of the tumors, the cells
will have mutations in these pathways, which makes them incredibly sensitive to PARP inhibition.
So that's a huge game changer. The other thing that people now look at is kind of the total
genomic score or the alterations in the genome of the individual cancer cells. And will that make
them more sensitive to immunotherapy or not? That's more coming online. But the idea that
there are things in the somatic DNA of the tumor cells and in the germline of individuals
that you can use to screen for not only prostate, but breast, pancreas, etc. That's a huge game
changer. And then as we touched on earlier, those are not just prognostic biomarkers, but they're
predictive of drug response, which is pretty amazing. And then I think Eli's test, the version
2.0 or the beta version of it, which has a lot of these built in biomarkers that predict response
to drugs that now are being tested in clinical trials with the idea that let's test the ability
to predict response. It's pretty amazing stuff actually. So obviously you specialize in prostate
cancer. The field of urology is so much bigger than that, right? We haven't even talked about
renal cancer, bladder cancer, and to do so would only be to do it in injustice. Given that we've
been talking for a little while, and I know you've got a hard stop here in about 20 minutes,
I want to talk a little bit about benign stuff. So I'll tell a very personal, maybe somewhat
embarrassing story, but it's a good illustration of this. So-
Is that when you were treated at the extra large penis clinic that happens?
Is the micro-penis-
... reduction surgery.
Yeah, yeah.
You had the penis-
... reduction surgery clinic.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. See, those are the kind of jokes we can only tell in the urology office.
So about two years ago, I remember calling and I was like, Ted, I don't know what's going on,
man. Every time I pee, it's just burning like crazy. I did a quick check. I don't have a UTI.
I've never had a UTI. It seems unlikely I would. I've been fumbling around and I'm wondering,
I must have prostatitis, right? And I guess my question is, Ted, what antibiotics should I take?
And I remember I was actually in Baltimore at the time, but I was heading up back to New York,
because I was going to work in New York that week where I spend quite a bit of time. And you said,
well, first of all, you're in luck because my dad wrote the paper on prostatitis. And I forget what
year it was, but it was in the England Journal of Medicine. And I downloaded the paper and I read
it on the train ride up to New York or maybe I was still in Baltimore because I remember you had,
anyway, you'd written me for some Flomax. Well, the long and short of it was I came away from
reading the paper and I said, well, my takeaway on this is I need a prostatic massage, not an
antibiotic. And you said, yep. So go ask Bernie to give you a prostatic massage. And I had been
in pain for a month. And he did that to get a sample from the prostate, because when you do a
urine check for an infection, you're sampling predominantly the fluid, the urine, and the
bladder. So I said, yeah, fine, your urine culture is negative, but let's check your prostatic fluid
for an infection. I think it was clear. It was clear. And here's the amazing part of the story.
I had been suffering for a month and Bernie being the great Bernie, he didn't just give me a little
bit of a prostatic massage. I mean, he eviscerated me. It was one of those Chevy Chase moments where
I was like using the whole fist there, doc. Moon River. Actually, I will say it was one of the
most painful things I'd ever experienced. This was a different level of pain because it wasn't the
rectal, it was like the prostatic massage to generate the fluid. It's very sensitive, yeah.
Especially when you're inflamed, as I would later come to realize. Well, here's the most amazing
part of that story. Within about three days, everything was better. I didn't need a single
antibiotic. And somehow that massage probably somehow turned over some of that inflammation.
There was something, yeah. I mean, we had you on some anti-inflammatories and we had you on some
other symptomatic stuff. But yeah, I mean, it definitely... So we don't really call it
prostatitis anymore. It's kind of binned into kind of this chronic pelvic pain syndrome kind of
concept. But within that concept, you can get acute bacterial prostatitis. That's what happens
for people after prostate biopsy. So they get very, very, very sick. High, high fevers, 103,
104, like, you know, bad stuff. That's an incredibly rare thing. But what you can get is
basically non-bacterial prostatitis, inflammation in the prostate.
That's the thing I think a lot of people don't understand. Itis means inflammation.
That's right.
You can get itis with an infection, but itis does not imply inflection. So prostatitis, mastitis,
these things don't necessarily imply that there's a bacterial infection that can be sterile.
Right. So people will have acute inflammation in your prostate, which is what I thought you had
on the phone. I said, look, have Bernie do an actual culture of the prostate. Then typically,
for most people, that goes away. We don't know what causes it. We don't know what it is that's
causing that inflammation. That's what my father, who's a very prominent researcher in this field,
that's what he works on. But we know we try to treat the symptoms and ride it out. And then we
try to adjust risks that we prevent it kind of from coming back and so forth. So some of the
things that can cause it, we talked about this constipation. So one of the ways it's easy to get
constipated is just go on a transcontinental flight because the air is dry and those little subtle
changes make a big difference. So those things come into play. Now, that falls within this
greater scope of something called chronic pelvic pain, which is a field that has some work in it,
but it's still evolving. It's really just been recently described. My father was one of the
people who described that with some other folks. And so that involves just burning or pain in the
urethra and the bladder. Women, it used to be called interstitial cystitis in women. So
some foods will trigger these things. We don't have a good handle on it at all. So we try to
manage the symptoms. And then from there, we try to just prevent. What's the state of the art with
using injections within the bladder of Botox to alleviate women who have interstitial cystitis?
I don't think.
There's some discussion about that.
Yeah, it's not. We use Botox in the bladder for people who have hyper contractility of the
bladder, but we don't use it for people who have interstitial cystitis. For people, there are people
that have deep seated infections in their prostate that we can document or sometimes we can't document,
but we have a suspicion of them. And in those individuals, you can actually directly inject
antibiotics into the prostate. Or in fact, my feeling is that actually the typical
nidus for this persistent infection is actually the seminal vesicle, which is attached to the
prostate. So we'll have these individuals who have recurrent bacterial infections, same bacteria,
same sensitivity to the drugs, so they don't become resistant. They're equally sensitive all
along because-
So there has to be a bacteria that you aren't clearing that's outside of the field of scope.
That's right. And so I feel like those are often, or you can't get the concentration-
High enough into that.
Into that tissue. And so those cases will do intro-
So is it difficult? You do that-
Transrectally.
Transrectally or perineal.
But it actually works.
Under ultrasound guidance.
And how easy is it to hit a seminal vesicle?
Super easy. Even you can do it.
Even I could do it?
Yeah.
That's hard to believe.
Let's do it. Let's go across the street.
I was going to ask you about that, so thanks for bringing that up. I was going to ask you about
interprosthetic injection.
You need to come do a share day with me.
Wouldn't that be awesome?
Oh, that'd be so much fun.
You've never actually been on the robot, have you?
No.
We got to do it. Oh, man.
How many?
Yeah, going back to that for a second. So I mean, we didn't really get into the deep
surgical technique, but I do want to link to any videos that we can. But what percentage of your
prostatectomies do you now use the robot for versus open?
100%.
You're 100% robot now?
Yeah.
And Moe's 100% robot, obviously. So most men now getting their prostate removed will do it
via the robot.
I mean, I think that there are very few people out there that actually can comment on which
one is better robot versus traditional open. But I've done, I don't know, 1,500 opens and
2,500 robots. So I have a good idea for which ones are better.
When was the last time you did an open case?
Three years ago, two years ago.
Is there a party that's sad that if you went back and did an open tomorrow, you wouldn't be as good?
I wouldn't be as good, but even when I was good, robots, I'm better using the robot. It's just
incredibly precise. I'm just a super type A guy. You get four arms to control. I only got two hands.
So you can just retract everything exactly the way you want it. The magnification, the optics are
just unbelievable. And you would just die. It's just like wearing-
Is it still the Da Vinci?
Yeah. It's like wearing 20X loops. You think about it, you had your 2.5s that you used to
walk around with. Hey, I upgraded to 3.5.
Those are tough. I had some 4Xs and it's harder. But it's amazing, right?
Well, it depends on the case.
But even anything, I mean, I wear my loops for every open case I did. But even the difference
between 2.5 and 3.5 is a big difference. So think about 10X.
I just put a 4X magnifier on my bow. So you have a clarifier that sits in the peep,
and then you have a magnifier that sits on your scope. And I'd been shooting probably up to 70
yards naked. And then I went to a 2X and I was like, oh, this is good. And then I went to the 4X.
And I just don't know if I could ever go back. That's the thing. One of my mentors,
surgical mentors is this guy, Bal Carter. And he always did his cases without loops.
And then Pat made them switch. And so we would talk about it. And he said, it's just literally
a different operation. And so people who do open prostates without loops, I don't know what they're
doing. Because you just see everything, right? You see it all. Now, think about the robot. I mean,
I can dissect out individual little arteries that are one, two millimeters.
Has this made it difficult to teach residents?
It's easier to teach them. You got to come by tomorrow. I'm doing a case.
Seriously.
I'm talking to Nav tomorrow. How am I supposed to do that?
Not at 7 AM. That boy doesn't roll out of bed before 9.
I'm going to have to take you up on that.
Yeah.
There's a lot of other stuff I want to talk about. I know we're getting real close to you.
You've got a hard stop in 10 minutes now. Do you know anything about male contraceptives?
Is this a topic that... Is there a male contraceptive on the horizon outside of a vasectomy?
I mean, the only way to really prevent sperm production is to block testosterone in the
testicle. So that's the way to do it. And there's a couple that are coming online. They've been
tested in smaller groups of men. I don't know if they're really ready for prime time. And I don't
know if men are ready for that. What about vasectomies?
They work. What's the reversal rate on them if you need to worry about that?
Well, I mean, I have a partner here, Bob Brannigan, who's one of the top three guys in the country.
And yeah, if the vasectomy was done correctly the first time by a professional, so to speak.
So not in the parking lot. There's a surgeon. I'm not going to do it.
What do you mean by a professional? Who else is doing vasectomies out there?
GB. There's a guy who just think about... There's a surgeon at Hopkins. You know what I'm talking about?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. I'm not saying he did them, but if there was a urologist like him...
Yeah. Yeah. Nickname Hodad. Hands of death and destruction. Any Hopkins resident from our era
listening to this knows exactly who we're talking about.
That's right. So as long as you don't have a Hodad...
Yeah, they can be reversed, but the reality is that...
That's what, 80%, 90%?
The patency is, yeah, I think it's over 90% for a good microvascular...
So if you're a guy who's deciding who's sort of waffling on this, it seems to me that donating
a bunch of sperm, putting sperm into a bank, having a really good person do the vasectomy
is a surefire way to just go ahead.
Yeah. I mean, most of the time, you can have... I mean, the reproductive technology is just
ridiculous. So individuals who have Klein filters where they really almost have no sperm production
who were told 10 years ago, you can't have a child. Now you can do these procedures under
the microscope where you can find individual nests of sperm within the testicles of these men and you
can allow them to have kids, which is amazing for them.
I had no clue someone with Klein filters could do that. And then of course, you're doing it anyway
because you want to be selective for... That's right.
Make sure you're getting the right chromosome.
Right. So I mean, I think there's nothing wrong with vasectomy. It's a very effective way to do
contraception. I think if you're single and you're dating around, I think you should also use
protection, not just contraception. So to me...
So this will be our public service announcement, not to be confused with the other PSA. This will
be the shape for PSA on where a condom... Yeah. I think not just for protecting or not having
children, but for all the other reasons to do it. Is there anything else that we can talk about in
five minutes that's not going to get one of us in trouble? Well, there's lots of fun things that we
can talk about, like watches or pens or cars. Yeah, you and I have shared that from the beginning.
That's five minutes isn't going to work. It's not going to cut it.
All right. So on each of those, if someone walked in the door today and said, Ted, I'll buy you
any watch you want within a reasonable price frame, don't just pick the most expensive watch. But is
there a watch you'd love to just have sitting on your desktop when you walk back into your office,
courtesy of some Santa Claus? I notice you're wearing a beautiful Hulk today.
I do. I wear that on my non-clinical days. I do like it. I didn't wear it a lot. I would say,
I'm in the market. See, I always just ask you, I'm in the market for an elegant dress watch.
That's the thing. I have to say that I'm pretty satiated from watches these days. I'm good.
But I don't know. I want an elegant dress watch, but I could travel with it and it would have GMT.
That's my challenge to you. Oh, for heaven's sakes. You had to throw the GMT.
Because I want to be able to wear a dress watch to a meeting and I want to be able to go to the
meeting, change my time zones. I want to go to the meeting and now have nobody know what the watch
is. Because I can get that in a Rolex or whatever, but sometimes it's nicer to just not know.
I will take this on as a personal challenge. If you're willing to give up the GMT, I'm really,
I don't have it. I might never have it, but I'm really obsessed with two Vacherons out there.
One is the Ultra Thin and the other is the 1921, which is a remake of the famous driving watch.
Yeah, those would be, but you're not going to get a second time zone on either of those.
I just think you travel a lot too, right? It's so nice to just know what your time zone is at home.
And that's what I like about that. I like that. That's my newest thing. I love that.
So I'm looking for a GMT watch because that to me is so important. So if you could get home
to San Diego and find any car in your garage, what would it be?
It's a tough question. And I assume you mean a car that will only be driven on the street is not
going to be on the track. I'm not taking it to the track. This is for you, for San Diego.
You've definitely got me more and more interested in Porsche. And I think that the 911 Turbo,
so when that, I don't know, let's just say I could, if I could get an early jump on a 992 911 Turbo,
that might be- Yeah, that's a great vehicle.
That's so well engineered. Yeah, they're really special cars. And they're so drivable. I mean,
other cars that I know you and I have driven, we have friends who have beautiful cars that have
given us their 488s and 458s and all those things. And they're incredible. I mean, I actually,
I love the 458, but you're not going to drive that car every day. And there's something else
that comes from it, which is, I guess I just deep down always feel a little self-conscious,
pulling or driving around in the bright red Ferrari. And I don't think you just don't have
that same level of being self-conscious driving around in certain other cars. But that said,
the 488 is a blast. See, I don't fit in. I have a long torso and I can't get the seat right. So I'm
not looking at the head, the head red, the A pillar. Yeah. So, but it's a great car and there
are great cars out there, but as a daily, you just can't, I mean, that 911 Turbo's, they're
pretty amazing. Yeah. I've never actually driven a McLaren. I don't know if you've-
I haven't, but I've heard those are really fun too. Yeah, I have a couple of friends that have
them and I always have an open invitation to go visit them and drive them McLarens in other cities.
And those look like really special cars, but part of that's emotional too. I think I just
have an emotional connection to McLaren because of Senna. Yeah. So-
I don't like the Senna though. I don't like the looks of that car.
Oh, I think that thing's going to be just a beast. I can't wait to see it perform.
It's a beast, but I mean, it just, it doesn't, I like the functionality that they put in their cars.
Do you think that the Senna looks better or worse than the P1?
I think the P1 looks better, but I haven't seen either of them in real life. I've seen a 720 in
real life. It's a cool car. Really cool. Yeah. The arrow.
720s look great. The arrow in that car is a cool one.
I saw a P1 in person once in New York City of all places, which I've never understood that lot.
Yeah, right. What would possess you to- It wouldn't matter how much money you have. What
would possess you to drive a P1 in Manhattan? Yeah, it's crazy.
It's like a Tomahawk. I knew somebody who had a law, had a 918 and a P1, and he sold one of the
three because he said it just wasn't fun to drive around. Let me see if I can guess. I don't know,
maybe the LaFerrari? The P1. Because it's just too much of a race car. So he said that you just,
you know, on the track, it's just ridiculous, but he said that he sold it because on the streets,
we couldn't even begin to enjoy it. Wow. It's so cool though. I actually think all of those
hyper cars, like I love watching Chris Harris take those cars around. So for the listener,
certainly the last generation of hyper cars were those three cars, the Ferrari, LaFerrari, the
Porsche 918 and the McLaren P1. Only one of them ever broke a minute 30 on Laguna Seca. Do you know
which one? I would guess the P1, but I don't know. No. It was the 918. Went one minute 29 seconds
0.89 seconds. By 11, 100 seconds, the 918 broke a minute 30 on Laguna Seca, the only production
car to ever do so. Now, my favorite little tidbit. And I'll tell you, so the 911 Turbo S
is faster than the 918 at the ring. I know. So unbelievable. Unbelievable. But then of course,
there are $50,000 track cars that'll go a minute 19 on that Laguna Seca, which again,
is always the great thing for people to understand the difference between track cars and street cars.
Yeah. Ted, this was awesome. I know this was a bit more of a male centric episode, but I think one,
guys will get a lot out of this. But also I think for women who know a man who's going through this,
or will go through this, I mean, I think there's a lot here and we'll be sure in the show notes to
link to a ton of the stuff that was discussed. It would be great to be able to link to any videos
that you have on your surgeries. If people want to learn more about you, I mean, obviously at
Northwestern, the website will link to your bio, your CV and all that other stuff. If they Google
Dr. Edward Shafer, they'll get all the links. But NM or Northwesternmedicine.org is a good way to find
me. DR-Shafer.com is another way to find me. Okay. Do you do anything on social media?
My handle is at Edward Shafer. Okay. Cool. Ted, this was awesome. Thank you for making the time
and for your hospitality with insights. Yeah. Thanks for having me, Peter.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame
once a week email, where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social,
you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually
Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory
disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition
they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.