Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives.
Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast,
that became clear to me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming.
I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information
with you. To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a
full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and their feedback has mirrored this.
So all of this raises a natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support
this? As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of
contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most
important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something
when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason
selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time
advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about
something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads,
I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can work over time, and that is to create
a subscriber support model for my audience. This keeps my relationship with you both simple and
honest. If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and support us at whatever level works
for you. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that
simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get
back more than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show
notes, including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts
for each episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature
of many of our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular
Ask Me Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also
getting to hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited
about, I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said,
we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies
who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them
pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of
you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive
for members to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a
moment to listen to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please
consider supporting us directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Dr.
Tom Catena. Now I want to preface this by saying something that, you know, on the one hand is a
little bit embarrassing to admit, but I think it also speaks to sort of the significance of Tom.
I've been very privileged over my life to have met many quote unquote important people, people
who are very rich or people who are very famous or people who have accomplished great things
athletically or otherwise. For whatever reason, I've never been nervous going into the first
meeting with somebody who is quote unquote special. Not sure why, maybe just deep down and
kind of get that we're all kind of the same and just because one person's smarter or runs faster
or, you know, made more money, you know, in the end it doesn't really matter that much and we're
all the same. But I got to say I've known about Tom for about three years. We've exchanged emails
in the past, but this interview was the first time I met Tom in person. And I only know how to say
this just bluntly. It's the first time in my life I've ever been nervous to meet a human being,
which of course is ironic when you meet Tom and this will come across in this episode because he
is quite simply the most humble human being you could ever meet. But I suppose I see in Tom what
I consider to be the greatest of any qualities or characteristics of any human being. And so it
humbled me and intimidated me to meet him. Since about the year 2000, Tom has been a missionary
physician in Africa, initially working in Kenya. And then in about 2008, he moved to a region of
South Sudan called the Nuba Hills or Nuba Mountains, where he continues to take care of
about three quarters of a million people. He's the only physician in the area and there's a
single hospital there that he runs with a, it's hard to describe how few resources he has to run
it. And I don't want to get into that because the episode will cover that in detail, but
I can only say that it is nothing short of a miracle what he and his very limited staff are
able to do. His accolades are so numerous that I don't even think it's worth getting into them.
I will say he is the recipient of the Aurora prize for awakening humanity. This is a prize
that awards $1 million to the charities of Tom's Choice. And needless to say, that is about as high
an honor as anybody could receive for the type of work that he does. He's been described by one
Muslim man as Jesus Christ, which I think also speaks to the impact that he has had on the
community that he serves. Now in this episode, we talk about a lot of things and obviously talking
about kind of the unimaginable suffering that he sees and how he himself copes with death and how
he himself copes with being in a situation that I don't think any of us can understand. And certainly
no physician can understand because none of us really practice medicine alone. And yet in many
ways, that's what Tom is doing. We talk about a crisis of purpose. So it's easy, I think, to look
at what Tom does and feel sorry for him or feel sorry for the people he serves. But I must admit,
I came away from this interview actually feeling more sorry for us. And Tom so eloquently without
judgment explains some of the differences between people with all the privilege in the world, like
most of us listening to this and the people that he serves and talk about the sense of community
that exists in Nuba. And what you start to realize is that the way that we die in this country and
the way that we live in this country is so different from the way that people live and die in that part
of the world. And it's not just on the obvious things. It's not surprising that people there
don't die from complications of type 2 diabetes, but they die from infectious diseases and trauma.
But there's a more subtle point here, which is we in many ways are prisoners of our own world,
our own minds, our own possessions, these things. And to see the way Tom describes the freedom from
that, it gives me hope that if someone like me can realign the way I think about these things that
in many ways enslave me, perhaps I could even capture a fraction of the satisfaction, the
happiness, the purpose that someone like Tom has. Tom's work is so important to me. And I want to
be sure that anybody listening to this can get access to all of the notes we're going to put
together on this. And so normally our show notes are only available to subscribers, but for this
episode, they're available to everyone. I don't want anyone to not be able to see this under any
circumstance. So I really do recommend that everybody take a moment and look at some of the
videos that we link to. If you don't make time for that, but you are still sort of interested,
I can't recommend enough that you watch the documentary, The Heart of Nuba, which is based
on the work that Tom does there. I think you'll come away from this episode understanding why
I could feel so nervous meeting Tom for the first time. And so without further delay,
please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Tom Katana. Hey Tom, thank you so much for making the time to
come over here today. Sure Peter, my pleasure. Yeah, there are a few people that would be giving
up more that they deem important work than you. So I know your time is tight. How often do you
come to the US? Well, this is my first time out in more than three years. So last time I was in
the US was November 2015. I was here for about five days. I was in my hometown of Amsterdam, New York.
And it wasn't much of a trip. I was, you asked about malaria. I was sick as a dog of malaria.
So I was like in bed with malaria the whole time. The last day I felt a bit better,
just in time to go back to Africa. So it's been, it's been a long time since I've been back.
You grew up in upstate New York. Yep. Your pedigree is like the star, right? You went to
Brown, you played football, you went to Duke medical school. Right. At what point did you
realize you wanted to do something a little different vis-a-vis working, you know, outside
of the US, for example? This desire to do this kind of work really was planted in, when I was in
college, when I was at Brown. And I always want to do some kind of mission work. And that term has
several connotations, but I, you know, wanted to be a missionary, whatever that meant. I wasn't quite
sure what meant at the time, but I just had this idea. I wanted to work in other cultures in the
society, do mission work. But I was, as you, a mechanical engineering major, and that didn't
really fit with doing mission work. This was in the 1980s. And most of the jobs then were
in the defense industry. They were, you know, they were good jobs, but I didn't really want to
do that kind of work. So I graduated college and kind of floating around for while I was offered a
job by GE, working with their kind of nuclear submarine program, it would have been a really
good job, but I just wasn't interested in that kind of work. And then one day it was kind of odd,
I thought it was coming back from my great aunt's funeral. I was with my brother Felix, and I did
just kind of popped in my head, I should go into medicine, because that could, if I do that, then
I could do mission work. And, you know, I'd like the sciences, I could stay in the sciences, do
mission work, help people, just kind of that general idea. And ended up going to medical school,
and kind of kept that desire to mission work. And that kind of evolved into wanting to work in
Africa, work with people that don't have a lot of options for healthcare, you know, 15 years later,
ended up in Sudan. So you started out in Kenya, is that right? Right. So, you know, when I finished
medical school, then I did five years in the US Navy, I had a Navy scholarship for medical school,
so I had to pay that time back. Then went to my residency, I did family practice in Tarahou,
Indiana. Now it was time to kind of be free and do what I want. So I thought, well, let me just go
and let me do this thing that's been kind of an itch for so many years. So I teamed up with
Catholic Medical Mission Board, and I said, okay, we have an opening in Kenya at this mission
hospital. Maybe go there. I said, okay, I'll go for one year. I'll see how it goes. If I like it,
maybe I'll stay longer. Otherwise, maybe I'll just come back and start a practice. And went down to
the Kenyan, fell in love with the place and decided to stay. What was the first thing that you
remember when you got there, as far as how different this was from the way you had trained?
Because you did your residency in the United States, right? Right, did my residency in the US,
and I did family practice. And the program I went to was kind of geared towards rural health. So I
thought, okay, if I want to do admission medicine, I got to be doing more than just kind of outpatient
office stuff. I need to do something with a little more meat to it. So a little bit of obstetrics,
we did a bit of surgery, mostly just C-sections. So when I first got there, I think what struck me
was just the volume of patients. I mean, I was a resident. And in clinic days, we'd see
like five or six patients and get all every little detail down on each one. And now,
I'm in this rural hospital in Kenya. And I mean, you're seeing 50, 60 patients, you know,
huge numbers, the clinic, the wards are full, you go do ward around. I was in charge of the adult
ward. And there were, you know, at the time, I thought it was a huge, I mean, like 30, 40 patients
there. And I was responsible for all them. It's just this sheer volume of patients you had to go
through every day in the variety of diseases. So not only the tropical stuff, which I didn't know
much about, I mean, here's malaria, TB, lyshmaniasis, all this kind of stuff I had no idea about, I had
to learn about when I was there, you know, learned to thank God some, a couple more senior doctors
there like I learned from, but just a volume of patients and the variety of diseases you had to
face. So what year did you get to Kenya? I arrived in Kenya, January 17, 2000. That's so interesting.
I arrived at NIH when I was in medical school on January 17, 2000. No way. Yeah.
Yeah. That was, which was NIH, being at NIH while I was in medical school was one of the
sort of more formative parts of my experience. So how long before you went to Sudan and what
led to that transition? I'm trying to think of my geography, right? Kenya is south of Sudan,
correct? Sort of south east of Sudan? South, right. South and a bit east, exactly. Okay.
And much more stable, right? I mean, Kenya is a relatively safe place to be. Right. Sudan is not,
right? It's divided into these provinces and my, the one that got all the attention was Darfur,
which is the furthest west. Correct. Exactly. And that basically was a war zone. Right. I mean,
a killing field, right? So Bashar was basically killing his own people there, wasn't he? Right.
So to go from Kenya to Sudan, what were you thinking? I think maybe the modus operandi
in my life was always looking for, what's the opposite of greener pastors? I'm looking for
browner pastors. When I was there in Kenya, this was, as I said, I got there in January 2000.
The civil war in Sudan was really raging at that time. And I was in Kenya learning a ton of stuff,
really enjoyed the work. And I kept hearing about Sudan, the civil war in Sudan and how it's so
terrible. And the conditions there were terrible. And the, you know, there's such a lack of any
kind of health services. I thought, man, I'd really like to get involved in that, in that struggle,
just to go and work with the help the people there, just because it was so health facilities
were so limited. I thought that's kind of the place I want to go to. So I had this general
thought. This is 2000, one thousand two. Now, this woman in June of 2002, I left my first
posting, which was in a rural place called Motoma was there for two and a half years.
I went up to Northern Kenya, a place called Turkana. I was at the Kakama mission hospital,
which is up in the Turkana desert near the refugee camp, a woman named Deidre Burns. So Deedee was,
I think, her first time up in Turkana. And I was talking to her. She's an American,
she was doing a kind of short term mission there. She's a surgeon and a family practice
doctor. She did both, was doing primary surgery. And she said, look, there's a bishop I know,
who's Bishop Makram Gossis, who was building a hospital in Sudan. I think he might be interested
in going there. And that, say, whoa, that's exactly what I've been thinking about doing,
you know, for the past couple of years, some back in 2002. So she said, look, he's got an office in
Nairobi. He's living there in exile. Maybe you can make contact with his office because I was due to
go to Nairobi and start working there. Anyway, to make a long story short, I ended up working in
Nairobi, linked up with his office. And we started kind of making plans for the hospital and how it
runs, staff who would need all that kind of stuff. And then took six years, but six years later.
Who funded the hospital?
It was all funded through the Catholic Diocese. So it was the Catholic Diocese of El Abaid. Bishop
Gossis was the Bishop of the El Abaid Diocese. And he and his office were able to get funding
through the church mechanism to fund the hospital.
So now it's 0809 and that's when you go.
Right. So I went to Nuba Mountains, arrived there March 10th, 2008. Was there, landed there in
Nuba Mountains.
Tell the listener a little bit about where Nuba is. I mean, I know it's in the southern part of
Sudan. It's to the east of Darfur, but it's pretty rugged country, isn't it?
Right. So the Nuba Mountains is probably one of the most remote places in the world.
It's a region which for many years in Sudan was kind of kept off limits before when Sudan was a
kind of a colony, was under the, called the Anglo-Egyptian condominium, partly kind of administered
by UK and by Britain and by Egypt. They decided to kind of keep the Nuba separate. They said,
these people have a unique culture and unique people. They didn't really allow a lot of open
tourism or people to go in there. It was kind of a closed area. So they really kind of have maintained
this separateness and this isolation over centuries. It's difficult to reach. It's semi-arid.
It's got this thing of rainy season. It's got a dry season, but more hills. They aren't real high
mountains, but sort of 3,000 foot hills, that kind of range.
My history is not great, but I sort of remember that basically Sudan was granted sort of,
I forget the term, but when you're given your independence, for lack of a better word,
that would have been in the 50s, right?
Right, 56.
Okay. And then what was the religious sort of map of Sudan and did that figure into how it was
divided and was that partly why Nuba was, was it religiously diverse? Was it mostly Muslim,
mostly Christian?
Yeah. Sudan is a very interesting place. It was one country up until 2011 when they divided
the North and South. Now, the religious makeup is in the North. So North of Nuba mountains,
it's primarily Muslim, almost all Muslim in the North. The South is primarily Christian.
Nuba is right in the middle. And interestingly enough, Nuba is a mix. It's about, let's say,
half Christian, half Muslim. And everybody's anatomist, but half are Christian, half are Muslim.
And the Nuba are unique. I think a unique tribe in the world where you have families which are
mixed. You have Nuba, you have Nuba Muslims and Nuba Christians, and there's no conflict
amongst them. For instance, my wife is a Nuba. Her father, both her parents, when they were born,
they were just followed the traditional religions. The Christianity in Islam had not been introduced
yet into the area. Now, as they got older, her father became Muslim, mother became Christian,
they married. Her father's a polygamist, so two wives, both wives are Christian. Their oldest son
is a Muslim. The rest of the children are Christian. And nobody's really bothered by this.
That's in Nuba. Now, the country itself, this difference between Muslim and Christian was
really a big issue in the previous civil war. We had the Southern African people that were
mostly Christian against the Northern Arab people that were all Muslim fighting each other. And there
was very much a religious context to that previous civil war. And also in Nuba mountains, the Nuba
people joined the Southerners. They're all African in Nuba. They joined the Southerners fighting the
Northern Arab Muslim people in the North. And in the 1990s, there was a jihad against the Nuba
people. So there was a real genocide in the 1990s against the Nuba. Who issued this jihad?
The ideologue behind this is a guy who just died last year. His name is Hassan Al-Tarabi.
And Tarabi was a member of the Muslim Brotherhood, very bright guy, went to Sorbonne in Paris,
and was kind of intellectual, but really kind of an evil genius, if I can use that word.
He was a real ideologue in the Muslim Brotherhood. And he managed to
convince some of the imams in the North to sign off a fatwa to allow jihad against the Nuba.
And many imams rejected it. They said, well, you can't do that.
Even though he'd be killing Muslims within Nuba.
Right, exactly. His response to this was, okay, you can have a jihad because the Christians are
fair game in the jihad. And then the Muslims are apostates from the religion because they
associate with Christians. Some of them eat pork. Some of them drink local beer. They're not real
Muslims. Like this thing with the Nuba are very much communal. And to have Muslims and Christians
together at functions, it was an atma to him. The fact we could have Christians and Muslims in the
same family was a huge scandal to him. He just couldn't tolerate that kind of stuff. So he said,
no, these guys are also fair game because they're not real Muslims.
So what year was that fatwa issued?
That was in the, I think in the early 90s, have been 93.
So Bashir was already in power, right? His coup was like late 80s, right?
He took power in 89. And this guy, Tarabi helped him in this coup. He was kind of the brains behind
the coup. And Tarabi, I mean, he was, you know, he was kind of a power hungry guy. He said, okay,
his figure, he figured if he helped Bashir get into power, but she was a military guy.
And he thought, okay, if I help Bashir get into power, I'm much more intelligent than Bashir.
I'll just kind of find a way to get rid of him and I'll take over. And Bashir said, look,
I'm the one in power. You're not, you're not taking over. So he kind of always kept Tarabi at
a distance. And they're always these, he would always, he was always throwing Tarabi in prison
afterwards because Tarabi started speaking out against him. So we put him in a quote unquote
prison, maybe, you know, it would be some luxury apartment in Khartoum, but they kind of were at
odds with each other. But Tarabi was the ideologue behind a lot of this moment. He's the one that
invited Osama bin Laden to Sudan in the early 90s. So bin Laden lived in, when bin Laden was exiled
from Saudi Arabia, which is in the early 2000s. Right. Well, that was before then he invited,
what's his name? He invited bin Laden to Khartoum. So he lived in Sudan for a while and a lot of,
you know, Kaida had a lot of training camps in the desert in the north of Sudan.
I had totally forgotten that fact. That's the chapter of Volkaita that I'd sort of forgotten.
So you basically have a bunch of incredibly evil people who are deciding to kill their
own citizens effectively. Right. You got there in, oh, wait, you said, or 09? Oh, wait. So he arrived
March, 2008. So historically that was the interim peace period. So since they got independence in
1956, Sudan has been at civil war, various parts of it have been a civil war for almost the entire
history. That's it has 60, that's how many years 62, 63 years, most of the history they've been at
civil war. So this was one of the brief periods actually wasn't even priest them because their
forest started in 2003. Their for a rebel started fighting against the government in 2003. So this
wasn't the whole country was not a piece of the time, but the big war between the south and north,
the peace agreement was signed 2005. So when we arrived in 2008, the peace agreement was still in
effect, and there was no active fighting. And then we were kind of waiting for this referendum to take
place referendum, the way the peace agreement was signed up was southerners. So South Sudan would
have the choice for self determination. And that will be done by referendum. So the people actually
have a vote, straight up vote, the majority vote to succeed, they succeed, the majority vote to stay
and stay as one country they stay. Now 2011, they have the vote and like 99.99% vote to succeed from
the north. So South Sudan separates in the peace agreement. I'm sorry, is Nuba considered south or
north in this cessation? Right, this is part of the problem because in the peace agreement, Nuba
was separate. Okay. And what they said was, okay, South Sudan will have a referendum. The Nuba
mountains was not included as part of South Sudan. Nuba and Blue Nile were separate regions. And they
said in these two regions, they're called the two areas, they will have what's called a popular
consultation, which was a very vague system where there'd be committee set up, they would go and
they would talk to people in the villages and kind of get their opinions on things and see what they
wanted to do. If they wanted to separate stay, it was very vague. And I think it was purposely vague,
because the government knew it was kind of a bargaining chip for the north to allow South
Sudan to have this referendum. They said, okay, because they knew in the end, they will keep the
Nuba mountains because this thing was too vague, you know, and they would be able to manipulate it
enough, they will keep the Nuba on their side. So South Sudan separates. There are elections in
Nuba mountains in 2011, in May, the candidate for Bashir's party, of course, wins the governorship
in the parliament. This is a side note. Before that election, the guy's name is Ahmed, Ahmed Haroun,
who was running against the guy named Abdulaziz. Anyway, Ahmed Haroun was the candidate for Bashir's
party, National Congress Party. And before the election, Bashir said, Ahmed Haroun is our candidate,
and he will win this election, whether by the ballot or by the bullet. So going into it, it
doesn't look like it's gonna be a free and fair election. Right. And Bashir at this point, does he
already have basically a warrant out for his arrest? Right. So he's got the warrant for his arrest.
That was, I think, 2009, I think. Ahmed Haroun also is indicted by the ICC for crimes. He was one
of the architects of the genocide. Genocide, yeah. So Ahmed Haroun, who's our governor,
as under, is indicted by the ICC. Bashir is indicted by the ICC. It also was the defense
minister, was indicted by the ICC. So Ahmed heard wins. They go and say, okay, now our party is there
in South Kordofan state in the mountains. There are still SPLA soldiers, like Southern soldiers,
living in this region. The Northern Army came and said, you know, did a forced disarmament
of these SPLA soldiers. And that's when violence broke out. So June 2011, June 6, 2011, civil war
breaks out in Nuba mountains against the government. Now, I've heard you speak about this in the past.
It was overnight that most of the staff in your hospital left. So prior to that, leading up to
the referendum and the breakout of war, you've got this three year period where you're in the
hospital, you're working there. As far as Nuba can be tranquil, this is the greatest tranquility
you've seen. The staff is what? It's you, it's what else? Right. So at this time, we started
the hospital in March 2008. We went there with about eight expatriates, including myself. So I
was the only doctor. We had a few nurses, an esthetist, a lab person. We had those eight expatriates.
They're mostly from, they're all from Kenya or Uganda. Those eight expatriates, myself, we had
15 local staff, Nuba. And the Nuba, I think the most educated person had finished primary school.
They were not nurses. They were just kind of local people that could read and write a bit of English
and they could speak English. So they had to be taught everything. We first started, they couldn't
weigh a patient. They couldn't take a temperature, let alone give an injection or start an IB. Anyway,
with time we got these guys trained up a bit. So they had some pretty good skills. A lot,
most of that was done by these expatriate nurses. Now we still kept expatriates, but over time we
added more and more on the job trained people. We kept adding more primary school graduates or
eventually we got a few secondary school people. Started training them on the job. We didn't have
any trained Nuba nurses by the time the war started in 2011. So now war starts June 6th,
2011. By June 16th is 10 days into the fighting. Things are getting pretty hairy. There's a lot of
fighting within Nuba, Arab bombardments all the time and the diocese. And this is all from the
north? The north and the north, right. Fighting within Nuba mountains. The resistance is posed
by whom? Is it former southern who have not seceded or are trying to basically, are the north
and the south now fighting for Nuba? Right. So what happens is the south Sudan is totally separate.
So within Nuba mountains, you've got a lot of soldiers that were southern soldiers,
SPLA soldiers, a lot of whom were Nuba. Most of them were Nuba, but you also had other southern
tribes in the mountains kind of leftover from the previous conflict and they were there in the
barracks. So that all those kind of trapped SPLA soldiers are fighting the Sudan army. Now they
call themselves instead of SPLA, they're called SPLA north. So from that point forward, these guys
are called SPLA north. They have kind of a new identity as a separate military force from the SPLA,
which is in south Sudan. So fighting is going on, Arab bombardments. June 16th, the diocese says,
look, we're having, we're sending a plane in and this plan is going to come in to evacuate anybody
who wants to get out of there. Okay. And the plane was going to go to Uganda or to Sudan?
The plane was flying into Nuba mountains to pick up whoever wanted to get out and they would get
out and leave. Now this was a bit dicey because at this time there were a few flights coming into
Nuba mountains, mostly getting people out, but they have to change the airstrip. There are a few
airstrips around, but they would give the location of the airstrip at the last moment and they would
have like a code name for it because if there were a lot of spies around and if the north found out,
they would come with their bombers and come and bomb the airstrip. They would try to bomb the
plane on the ground, they'd bomb the people that were trying to get in the plane to escape.
So all the stuff was top secret. A plane comes in and they say, look, we come in, we land,
we're taking off in 10 minutes. You better be at the airstrip waiting, get your butts on the
airplane. We have to be out by 10 minutes or else these guys will come and bomb. And they do this
at night, I'm assuming. No, they did it early, early in the morning because you can't, there's
no lights or anything for the planes to land. So it's all just by sight. So they would come
early in the morning, land and they would get out. So all of our expats that were there with us,
they had all the knowledge. I mean, our anesthetist, our lab person, pharmacist, the nurses that were
awarded in charges, the ones that were doing most of the work and doing the leadership,
they all decided to leave. Now, did you all sit down together and have this sort of heart to heart,
which is each of you had to make a very difficult decision, which is you feel committed to this work
you're doing, but now your life is at exponentially greater danger. Right. So yeah, we met with
everybody. We had a group talk and we met individually and say, look, this plane is coming
in. This is the last plane that the diocese can send in. This is it. Once this plane comes and once
it leaves, you might never get out of here. Because you have no idea what's going to happen the next
day. You don't know if the Syrian army is going to overrun us and this is the last chance. How
did you think about that? I mean, was there a moment when you thought maybe I should leave and
go back to Kenya or go to Uganda or go somewhere else? I mean, what was that thought process like?
Right. So, you know, I was encouraged to leave by some different people. I said, look, why don't
you come out? You stay in Kenya for a while. Then when things blow over, then you can go back when
it's safer. I thought, and I thought, geez, you know, first time you have no idea, this is just
total chaos. You have no idea what's going to happen. What I did know is that we were getting
people wounded or all the structures that were ever coming in all the time, you know? So I knew
if I leave, it's not like they can go somewhere else. There were no other hospital surgical
capability. Okay. There wasn't a single one. There was another small hospital nearby run by
a German group that could do some inpatient stuff and outpatient and some minor stuff.
But really if somebody needed a C-section or something more serious, they would just die.
Okay. And that says nothing of the casualties that are going to start coming in as a result of this
attack. Right. So all these people that came in that were wounded would just die a miserable
death. And I knew that. So for me, it was a very easy decision. I thought, you know, there's no way
I can in good conscience leave this place and go out. It was a very, very stark reality. And to be
honest with you, it was not a difficult decision. I think the sisters that were there, the two
kamboni sisters that stayed, the priests that stayed, we all were of the same mind. We all
thought the same thing. Let's just stick it out. We're here as missionaries. Let's do what we're
supposed to do and take care of the people the best we can and come what may. We have faith in
God. We'll see what happens. And it wasn't, you know, we didn't feel like it was some big thing.
It was just like, well, no, we can't go. You know, we got stuff to do here. And, you know,
the other expats said, look, I've got a family. I've got this, I've got that. And we said, look,
we're not going to hold anything against anybody. This has to be very individual decision. If you
guys want to go, we'll find a way to keep going. Don't worry about it. So we wanted to give them
full latitude to lead in peace and not feel they were abandoning people there. So I think
everybody's pretty much at peace with the decision. The expats left. And I mean, sure enough,
they left June 16th, the morning of June 16th. They left around six in the morning. They had to
get out there early because they had to get the, you know, get this plan and just get out of the
place. And we had to keep everything secret. So all of our staff didn't know these guys were leaving.
We had to keep it a secret from everybody. And they have been left. And then the staff came to
work at 7 30. And so you, you had an anesthesiologist that was one of the people that left.
Right. So talk to me about 10 o'clock on that morning, the first time or whenever the first
surgical case comes in, who's running anesthesia? That was the biggest problem. So these guys leave
around six, eight o'clock casualties start rolling in people that were, there's a bombing from one of
the Sudan air force planes called an Antonov that has barrel bombs. They bombed in a location near us,
maybe an hour, a couple hours away. We hear these in the film, the heart of Nuba, right? Which we'll
talk about in a few minutes, but right. So like two hours later, all these mangled bodies start
coming. Yeah. Describe what this, I mean, so I did my training in Baltimore. In many ways, trauma
was a feature of the training program because if you're training in surgery, you know, one of my
mentors said, you know, to be able to train at a place like Hopkins is a great honor because
you really get to understand surgical anatomy in trauma. And it's penetrating trauma in the United
States is mostly gunshot wound and stab wounds. But I have no idea what you were seeing. So what
explain to me what things you actually saw, what types of injuries are you seeing? Right. So this
was very stark because when Antonov bombs, there are huge shards of metal. I mean, weighing, you
know, 10 pounds, I've got a bunch of the scraps. I have them as a souvenir, Megan Nuba. So imagine
a scrap of metal weighs 10 pounds, red hot, just going through your body. So it slices off legs,
slices of arms, cuts through people with just massive tissue loss and massive trauma. So I'm
here one young lady. She was 16. Her name was Ursheline, which means Jerusalem in the Arabic and
her arm was just totally mangled. I mean, just shattered. She came in, her cousin came in, his
hand was his whole hand was blown off by the Antonov shrapnel. So these guys both in amputations,
the girl, we did a disarticulation on the shoulders. So we had a couple of our on the job
trained nurses there. And they had done something they've been taught how to do spinal anesthetic
by the anesthetist. See the smiles they couldn't do GA for the listener GA general anesthetic,
meaning they couldn't intubate and put the patient fully to sleep. And I, I had never
intubated a patient before. I remember when I was in the military, we intubated and intubate goats
for as part of our atls training. I think if I remember, I never done it either. It's like,
what the heck? So I'm so afraid. Like, what do I do with these people? You know, so I remember
reading the book, we have a book there, kind of basic anesthesia book, so I bring you through the
protocols. Okay, first, give some ketamine, you knock them out with that, they go to sleep,
give it a little bit of pain, you give succinylcholine to paralyze them, intubate,
and you give pankaronium, you have a healthy anesthesia, put the two bands, the side intubate,
like, okay, okay, let's let's do it. So we took some of these guys back. And you know, I would go
and give the drug, I had a nurse there, kind of on child, it's okay, give the ketamine, you would
push it in, push the succinylcholine, I would intubate. And I guess I should explain for the
purposes of listening to this, because we use these terms so commonly. So intubation is a very
important step where if you screw this up, you're going to kill a person, literally, you will kill
them, but you have to put a breathing tube into the endotracheal space. So this is now to allow a
machine to breathe for someone while they're under anesthesia. And we do these things in medical
school, we did them in residency, a lot of our critical care training required that. But I have
to tell you, and I was not trained as an anesthesiologist, I never intubated somebody without
being incredibly nervous, because it's so easy to put that tube accidentally into the esophagus,
and you think you're doing it right. And all of a sudden, you know, you get the tube in, you hook
it up to the ventilator, you think everything's going well. And by the time you realize you're
providing oxygen to their stomach instead of their lungs, it can be too late. And then of course,
the panic that ensues is often what kills the patient, right? Because you're getting nervous,
and then you can't do it, you're starting to shake. You know, the problems might, as I said before,
my training was family practice, I did an internal medicine internship, you know,
in the family practice, I never intubated somebody, I never did anesthesia rotation in medical school,
that was not part of our training at all. So I was very green with this. Anyway, by the grace of God,
managed to get the patient intubated, connected to help, we have a really primitive structure called
an OMV, Oxford miniature ventilator, it's got a set of bellows, it's like turn of the century kind
of stuff, turn of the 20th century. So, you know, intubating, so we have to get to manual ventilation
for the patient. Throughout the whole surgery? Yeah, throughout the whole surgery, as long as
they're paralyzed, you got to you've got to ventilate manually. Usually with the hella thing,
after you manually ventilate for about 20 minutes, they can breathe on their own. And it's a bit of
an art to try to keep them under enough, where they can breathe on their own, but they're not
in pain. So it's a big art to this kind of work, but it's all manual. I just have to go off on a
tangent for a moment, which perhaps only the people listening to this who have medical training will
appreciate what you're saying. I'm guessing you don't have blood gases? No. Okay, so you can't
measure a patient's PAO2 or PACO2. And yet your anesthetist has to figure out how to ventilate,
which again, means how much oxygen the person needs, and how much CO2 you take off. And if
you screw either of those two up, you will kill someone. Right. And if you told me to walk into
Mass General or NYU or pick your favorite hospital and said, Peter, we're going to do
everything for you. We're going to intubate the patient. We're going to do this. All you have to
do is be the guy that manually ventilates them. I wouldn't be able to do that. Like I would
overdo it or underdo it. There's no way you'd hit that sweet spot. Yeah. You'd cause an alkalosis
acid. And then to be able to not have the laboratory tools to know when you're off the rails.
Right. Yeah. In those days, we didn't have a pulse ox. Now we have a pulse oximeter, which can measure
the percent of oxygen in the blood. The oxygen saturation. Oh my God. That time we had no pulse ox.
Some of this stuff, maybe ignorance is bliss because you can't measure it. So you just hope
and pray that things are going okay. But we managed to get the guy intubated. I mean, you couldn't do
veterinary medicine like this in the United States. Right. Yeah. You know, it was pretty hairy. We
managed to get through and this went out. We eventually got an anesthetist to come. This was
after about a month or two. Well, and in that month or two, what types of casualties did you see?
Oh, I mean everything, abdominal trauma, lots of leg trauma. We did a number of general anesthetics
during that time. We had a baby that came in with intersusception. This was the worst case. It was a
nine month old baby who came in who had an intersusception, which is kind of an intestinal
obstruction. Yeah. Explain what that looks like, the telescoping part. Right. So intersusception
is when the intestine telescopes on itself and basically causes a blockage of the intestine. And
then the longer you delay, that intestine can die and the person will die, the baby will die from
from infection. And we made the diagnosis and I'm just like, Oh God, you know, we're supposed to do
with this kid. So anyway, we take the baby to the outbreak and we said, we got to try something.
So I mean, intubating an adult is hard. A baby is really, really hard. We managed to get the
kid intubated. So I didn't debate the baby. He started on the ventilated pelothane, went out,
scrubbed for the case, came back. We opened the baby up, did a bowel resection, put it back together,
closed the baby up and he did great. He's a, how old is the baby now? He's like baby, he's eight
years old now, eight, nine years old. So he's cruising. But that's kind of one of the many
miracles we've seen. And when these bits of shrapnel are going through people, I mean,
you're seeing liver lacerations, you're seeing bowel injuries, hema pneumothoracies, head trauma.
I mean, give me a sense of the mortality. There are some cases that obviously just can't be saved.
Right. Well, you know, I'll tell you Peter, I think what happens sometimes people say,
why do you have so many extremity traumas? Because they're the ones that make it in.
The ones that survive. So, you know, the ones that get a really terrible trap with the chest,
they bleed out in the field because we're, you know, we're six hours. Sometimes these
patients come a day. We've had people with penetrating abdominal trauma with multiple
holes in their intestines come three, four days afterwards and survive. So imagine that.
You're leaking feces into the abdomen for three or four days. So imagine how strong these people
are. And they come in, it's just a mess and you open them up and some of them pull through.
You know, anemic dehydrated, they haven't eaten in several days and these guys can survive.
So some of the people are just tough as nails, but we get a lot of penetrating. I mean,
kidneys get torn to shreds, liver lacks, massive kidney trauma, liver trauma. I remember one guy
had, we counted, he had 23 holes in his intestines that we had to, you know, resect here, resect
there, stitch this one. It just took forever. How did you learn surgery? Right. So, you know,
I trained in family practice and when I went to Kenya, we were doing a lot of, you know, tons of
tropical medicine, a lot of obstetrical care, did a lot of C-sections. But I realized a lot of the
disease burden in Africa was surgically related. A lot of it. I mean, a lot of it courses tropical
medicine, like, okay, do all those things. And I said, well, a good, like half of what we were
seeing was surgically related, either just wound care, miscarriages, laparotomies, imputations,
kind of the run in the middle kind of surgical stuff. There's a lot of it. So I thought I really
need to learn how to do this stuff if I'm going to stay here longterm. So luckily, where I've been,
both rural Kenya and Nairobi, I met up with people that were willing to teach me things.
So really, it was like doing another residency. I mean, I would, there was Nairobi, I had a whole
day in the operating room, and we would do tons of cases. And there was an American missionary doctor
there named Mike Johnson. So I'm like, would you sit there and teach me stuff? You know, I would do
just like you did in residency, I would do the case, he would assist me and just kind of walk me
through it. There was a Kenyan surgeon there, Dr. Rucho was a fantastic, he was like a magician.
He was not so hands on. But if he was always, he was there in the operating room, he would say,
go ahead and start the case. After he had a little bit of experience, he'd start the case,
he had a problem, call me. So I'd start open up, look around a bit, say, okay, I'm stuck when we
come in, look around, say, I'll do this, do that, I do this and that, and things will go ahead.
Before you know it, you're doing thyroid and laparotomies and reciting bowel and stitching
liver and taking kidneys out and doing amputations. And I mean, you know, it is just kind of once you
learn a few, you have a few skills, you can add the next case, the next one, the next one, then
I mean, it took I was there for seven and a half years in Kenya. It was like doing another residency.
I mean, at some point, though, you have to be making mistakes that are harming patients,
because even in our, and I say that not being critical, right? But just saying like, that's
the nature of medicine. I mean, I think of every time I hurt somebody, even, you know, I remember
once causing a hemoneumothorax in a patient when I put a central line in them, it was my 500th
central line. So at this point, you'd think I could do it blindfolded. And yet to cause that
complication, which in my case, I'm lucky enough to have an x-ray to see that I've caused this
complication. You don't even I mean, you're missing so many of the basic tools that could act
as sort of a safety net. So what was that process like? I think what I wanted to make sure of when
I was in Kenya, I think those whole seven and a half years I was in Kenya, I always had either
somebody assisting me in the case, or somebody in the room or in the next room over. So I think I
was pretty well covered during that time. And by the time I was finished seven and a half years,
I felt pretty confident I go out on my own and do surgery. I think it's this concept, you know,
better than I do about 10,000 hours, you know, and I think in residency, you have like a thousand
cases, suppose like a thousand cases at least, but that's like a minimum. Yeah, maybe 1200 or
something. Yeah. So I did, you know, but time I finished my time in Kenya, I done. But for you,
it's harder because you're doing a breadth of cases that like, even if you took something as
broad as general surgery, I mean, you're still doing basically orthopedic surgery as well.
And obstetrics, right? A lot of urology. There's a mix. And I think maybe the trade off is the
surgery in Africa is much broader, but less depth. Like we don't have any laparoscopic stuff. Of
course, we have any of the da Vinci, yeah, and all that and all this high tech stuff.
You trade off kind of depth of surgery for breadth. I felt after doing around 2000 C-sections and
over a thousand other major cases, I felt, okay, I think I can do whatever we're doing in aerobic,
I can do that, I think safely in Sudan. I mean, obviously, you know, we have complications and
other problems and there are a lot of limitations in terms of going into the case. So you tend to do
more laparotomies because you don't have a diagnosis. You don't have a CT scanner, right?
No CT scanner. You don't exactly what's going on to get a tissue diagnosis might take you six months.
So you say, go, Hey, let's do a laparotomy and see what that thing is. That's, that's your CT scan in
the end. But that's about the best you can do. So I think what I always, what I try to do when I
approach a case is, you know, the premium known known cherry first do no harm. So if you think
you'll make the patient worse by doing this, like, okay, I'm not an expert doing this case. And
sometimes I say, I'm not going to do it, you know, I won't, I won't do it. If I think I really cannot
improve this patient's health, I think, okay, this is too much of a risk. Sometimes I look, I just,
I'm not really comfortable doing this, but usually I'll say, okay, I think it's better. If we
try to do this operation, I think we can, the patient can improve and we'll go ahead and it
works. I mean, it only works out pretty well. I was talking with my wife and my daughter a couple
days ago and about how we were going to be speaking today. And they had so many questions,
you know, we all watched the heart of new, but together. And one of the questions my wife had
was how do you deal with exactly that type of situation you described, which is what we would
consider quote unquote, end of life here in the United States or palliative care. What do you do
in a situation where somebody comes in and your judgment says this person is not an operative
candidate, but also by not operating, they need to be palliative. I mean, they're not going to,
they're not, it's not like, you know, they're going to walk home. How do you deal with that? And more
importantly, I guess, then medically, how you deal with that, it's emotionally and how is that
communicated to the community because you're still a foreigner, right? Right. Right. I'm still a
foreigner and we'll always be one. So I would say when we first started 10 years ago, people did not
trust us and it was incredibly nerve wracking, something we just got here. People kind of have
this because they've been, these people have been traumatized and oppressed for so many years.
They're not going to trust some foreigners showing up saying he's there to help them. So you got to
prove yourself something. Well, you know, it comes with these operations. What if we have bad outcomes?
You know, what happens? So it was really nerve wracking for all of us and, you know, thank God,
things went pretty well. We went ahead. So the issue with palliative care, you know, we try to
just talk to the family, talk to the patient, say, look, I think we can't do much for you. And
as if you go home, we'll take care of the pain and other things we can do. One good thing there
is the people, their expectations are extremely are low. And I'm not saying that negative, I'm
saying a positive way. They don't expect, they don't really expect miracles. They want to be
treated as a human. They want that human touch. They want to talk to us and talk to you and say,
okay, what can we do? If you tell them, look, we can't do much. They're not saying, they're not like,
they're not very demanding saying, no, you got to get it. Send me to Nairobi for a second opinion.
They're very accepting. I think that's just because of their lives are very hard. They're not used to
good outcomes. So I think first off, they're very accepting. So when you tell them, look,
I think there's not much we can do. We often will talk to the relatives culturally, usually
relatives will say, well, just, you know, they don't, they don't like telling the patient,
which is very different from here in the US. So we just talk with relatives and they're usually
very accepting. They say, okay, we, you know, we see a dumb jacan, we'll do, we'll take them home,
we become comfortable there. They have some of their local traditional things they might try with
the person at home, but there's usually very accepting of negative outcomes or bad news. When
you're kind of at the edge of survival all the time, when you get this kind of bad news, it's not so
shocking to you. It's like, well, you know, that's what happens. People die, you know, and
people have bad outcomes, bad things happen to you. So it's not so unusual for them. You know,
in the US, we're kind of anesthetized that everything has to be perfect. And we're not
supposed to die, we're supposed to, you know, have this kind of outlook on life. It's, it's a very
different way of doing things. So they're fairly easy in that respect. They understand this stuff,
you know, most people have some level of faith, whether Christian or Muslim, they can accept this
stuff in a theological sense also, it's not so difficult. When you showed up, how primitive
was the extent to which people were receiving, I don't know how to describe the type of care,
but there must have been local traditions and shaman and stuff like that, right? Right. And
at some point you're showing up and you're coming from a place of science as sort of simple as you
describe your work in medicine. It is still grounded in the fundamental principles of Western
medicine. And you use antibiotics, for example, you wash your hands before you operate. What was
the landscape like as far as the other types of medicine being practiced? And are they still being
practiced now? Yeah, they're still being practiced. So their scope of medicine, you have kind of the
local level in the home. And what they'll do is almost any febrile illness. So some kids got a
fever, someone's got a fever, they burn the person so that everybody there, my wife included, they
have burn marks. They look like cigarette burns. They're not cigarettes, but they take a round
thing that's put in the fire and they burn on the back of the wrist, back of the neck and the elbows.
There are certain points where they burn the person to try to release the whatever it is,
the spirit of evil humors that are causing the problem. When they see that kind of smoke and they
see the fat underneath the skin burning, they feel relief. Okay, the thing is gone now I'm better.
So they burn, they cut. A lot of people have cut marks in their arms or in the abdomens where they
think that'll also release things. They cut down to cause some blood loss. That'll release some of
the problem. And that's usually done in the home, usually by the father or the mother or the
grandparents will do that kind of thing. That's kind of the local treatment. That is still
practiced less so than when we came, I would say. I mean, everybody, all of our staff have burn marks
when they were kids. Now, we still see patients come with the burn marks. Someone comes with a
simple malaria. They've been at home four days and they've been roasting the kid. It's like,
why, you know, just gives a chance. Anyway, so burning, cutting, that's one level. They do have
some herbal remedies that don't seem that prevalent. They were there, I think traditionally,
some people still use those. And I don't know, you know, some they still swear by it. If you use
the neem tree or this Kayla, this plant that they use for malaria, they still swear that thing works
for the, for that. A lot of kind of local fruits and vegetables they use for, for GI problems or
other things. And those seem to work okay. And the third level is the, what's called the Kudur.
Kudur is like a shaman and the Kudur is like the priest for the, for the village.
The traditional legendary is ancestor, kind of ancestor worship. It's, it's communion with the,
with the ancestors. So if you're sick, if you have a problem, whether it's physical, psychological,
whatever, you go to the Kudur, you have a little ceremony with the family, all get together.
Kudur will talk with your ancestors and then kind of give a report back saying, well,
your kid is sick because you, your goats wandered on this guy's land and ate his crops.
So you need to make up with this guy and you go and give him something. And then you pay the Kudur
something. And then this thing is kind of lifted, child should get better. Those three things were
kind of traditional treatment. The Kudur is still very, very prevalent in this society. And they
still often go to the Kudur and they still will often delay in treatment when they go to the Kudur.
So how many people does your hospital serve?
Ketchman area is roughly a million. Anywhere from 70,000 to a million people is in our Ketchman area.
And the physical region is around the size of Austria, somewhere in that, in that range.
The people there, I, for example, how many of the people that you serve would understand
what you meant if you were going to New York? Like how big is their world?
Well, it's interesting you asked that. I mean, even the ones that have finished secondary school
wouldn't have an idea. Like if they ended up here or I mean, it would blow their mind.
Maybe I'll give an example. My mother-in-law is probably in her 70s. So we went to talk to,
my wife was talking about writing a book. Actually she started writing her book
and we went to my mother-in-law and we said, let's go and interview her mother as part of your book.
You know, I can write on it about her life. My wife didn't actually know a lot of facts about
her mother. They don't have that, you know, mothers and daughters there are not like buddy,
buddy, you know, the girls are, you know, once they, once they get weaned from the breast,
they start working, carrying water and firewood and everything else and cooking for the family.
So we went to talk to her mom and my wife asked her mother, her mother only speaks the tribal
language. She doesn't speak Arabic or English or anything else. So we talked to, she's talking
on the tribal language saying, do you know where Tom is from? And she said, she thought from it.
She says he's from Kenya. And she said, that's the furthest place she can imagine.
Right. Because she's heard of Kenya. So in her mind, anybody who's not from Nuba Mountains
must be from Kenya. It doesn't matter who you are, you know? So that's the outside world. And we say,
well, no, he's from America. You ever heard of America? No, she never heard of it. Had no concept
of America. Have you ever, you know what an ocean is? No concept of an ocean, no concept of a lake,
no concept of Africa. She didn't know she was in Africa. So what she knew was her local area,
just a few of the villages there. She'd been to Khartoum once. She's, my wife's mother has
leprosy. We've treated her for leprosy and have amputated, I think all of her fingers at one point
or another. She's really quite disabled. She got in the Khartoum some years previously to get
treatment there and ended up not getting treated. But besides that brief trip to Khartoum, she'd
never been out of that local area. A lot of my wife's siblings have never been out of this
15 square mile radius. You can't imagine the worldview. Presumably your wife also hadn't
experienced things outside of that until she met you. And what was the first time she left
or traveled with you? The first time? Especially that you don't travel much. Right. So the first
time we traveled was after we married was just this past June. We went to Armenia. So that was
really her first time out of rural Africa. She went to nursing school, but that was in South Sudan
in a while, which is, I mean for South Sudanese, they call it a city, but it's a village. It's a
big village. So imagine we went from either a refugee camp down to Juba, which is the capital.
I mean, Juba's more or less a city, but it's really not very nice. Then we fly from Juba to Dubai.
And we were in the Dubai airport. Which I was just there a month ago, even for someone who's,
from the United States, the Dubai airport is an overwhelming. Yeah. It's terrifyingly huge. It's
a city. It's a major city. So we get there and her eyes are the size of saucers.
Has she seen that much electricity in one place? No, I mean, not even close. Not even close. Has
she seen fresh water to that extent? No, I mean, I try to get, if she'd ever seen a tap. No, we had
taps in the hospital. We have a pump that pumps water up and we have some taps in the hospital.
But flush toilets, she never seen before about all this stuff. Elevators. So that was one of
the things we get in there. We're at the airport. We get in this pressure button, this door opens,
we get this thing and press the button, then the thing goes up and we get off. She's like,
what was that? So no concept in the elevator. We got in the escalator and she's falling over the
place. We go to get off the escalator. She's like, how's this thing moving? I think when she was in
there, she's going, wow, I think they had one set of stairs. There might've been a second floor,
but just the concept of walking up stairs is something strange, little moving staircase.
So all these things were very new to her. Now we get to Armenia and I mean, just being in a city,
I mean, the air van is a capital of Armenia, not like New York, but very different experience for
her. Now she came to the US for the first time just this past October. And I mean, she was in
Times Square. I mean, saw the ocean for the first time. She went to my brother lives in near Boston
on North Shore, Boston. So that was the first place she went. So first place she went to,
went to Boston and our hospital was getting an award by a group called Medicines for Humanity,
which supports us. And they were giving us an award for the work that our outreach team is doing.
So nobody can make it. I couldn't go. My other staff couldn't go. So my wife went to accept the
award on behalf of the staff. So she lands in Boston and the first thing she does is goes to
the Harvard club to get this award. It was very opulent place. It was my brother's place. He's
up in Rockport, Massachusetts. This is the ocean for the first time. She's a train for the first
time. Goes to malls to Walmart. She loved the dollar store. And my family just went crazy with
her. They had so much fun being with her, seeing all these things for the first time through her
eyes. And I mean, she has a very calm infectious joy to her and they really kind of tapped into
that. And it was really- And the flip side of that is we can sit here and have this discussion. And
of course, most of us would be thinking how amazing at all the things that they don't have.
But I'll share with you a story that I suspect will resonate and you will understand it.
This past Christmas, my daughter's school, each grade picks something they're going to do. And
that grade decided that they were going to buy Christmas presents for all of the kids at the
Sudanese Community Center in San Diego. And so they're basically all refugees. And this was very
interesting because we had already watched the Heart of Nuba, which was her first time even.
She didn't know what Sudan was and she certainly didn't understand why there would be refugees
leaving this place. So on the day that we take all the presents there and the kids have done
an amazing job, right? They've bought like four or five presents for each and every kid there. And
we spend the whole day there. So we go, it's my whole family. So it's me and my wife, three kids.
And our youngest is like a year and a half old. So there's another little kid there, a Sudanese girl,
who's also about the same age. So the two of them are playing together. But you feel like you've got
to sort of keep an eye on them because they can fall off the stairs or hurt themselves.
So there's a woman that's holding the Sudanese girl and she's sort of keeping an eye on our son
as well. And so that gives us time to go and do these other things and see the other kids and do
all the other stuff. And about four or five hours later when we're leaving, my wife goes over to the
woman who's has been holding this little Sudanese girl the whole time and says, what's your daughter's
name? And she says, oh, I don't know. This is not my daughter. I don't even know whose kid this is
basically. And we couldn't stop talking about that, right? Which was talk about a different sense of
community, right? There was nothing odd to this woman who was probably 20 to just say, hey, there's
like this little 18 month old running around. I'm going to take care of her. And by the way,
she's taking care of our kid too. And so for as many things as they lack, they have something we
don't have. Right. That type of centipede or something, you always hear about the negative side
of places like Sudan. People think of Sudan, what are the images, war, poverty, disease, starving kids.
The positive side is not shown. And some things that always stick in my mind. One is we'll have
patients that will come to us that it's a seven or eight day walk to reach us. And on the way,
like they'll start their journey and start walking. Now, at nighttime comes in the society there,
you can stop in somebody's hut and knock, you know, just kind of knock on the whatever or just show up
and say, look, I'm going, you know, I've got a long journey. Would you mind if I kind of spend the
night with you? I don't know. And we're safe. So that family will take this person in total stranger,
giving place to sleep, give them food, get some water for them to wash, take care of them that
night. The next day, I'll continue on his journey. Next day, stop at another total strangers place.
That stranger will take this person in, give him some food, hang out. This next day, same thing
until they reach the hospital. And this is the normal way of doing things there. The concept
of community and what stuff belongs to you. What is a stranger totally different than our outlook
here. So when you're there like, well, geez, who's really, really has it all and who's doing the right
thing, which society is on the right track, you know, it's really, it's really mind blowing. Well,
especially for you, because I guess it's one thing to know nothing that but you've seen both worlds.
And I've read enough about you to know, I've seen enough interviews to know, I mean,
correct me if I'm wrong, but you've described being more at home there than anywhere else.
Which I have to admit, you know, Tom, when I watch the videos of that, the first thought that comes
to my mind is not, I wish I was there. I realized that probably just speaks to me being sort of a
vapid, shallow person. But if I'm going to be brutally honest, right? I don't look at that and
think I want to be there. I think I would never want to give up my family. I would never want to
give up my comfort, my safety, my whatever. You couldn't fake it. I mean, so it's obviously so
genuine for you and any, you know, the other people like John, who are serving as missionaries there.
I know that on some level, you'll say the answer is faith, but there must be more to it than
simply your faith. Well, you know, some of it, Peter, I think is just, I think everybody is
kind of geared a bit differently. So, you know, we grew up in a big family and, you know, my
brothers could never, could never be there. But at the same time, I could not do what they're doing.
So I think, I think all of us are really, we're kind of wired a bit differently, even people in
the same family. So I think I'm very comfortable there, but I couldn't maybe fit working in New York,
you know? But I think the good thing is I don't attach your value to all this. Everybody has
something to contribute. I really, I really believe that. It's not just kind of blowing smoke.
My thing is being there to my mountains, you know, it's a part of the puzzle. Somebody else might be
in New York, but you're doing a podcast. You're helping us in Nuba tremendously by helping get
the message out, you know? If you're in Sudan doing the same work I'm doing, we don't have this,
you know? So I think everybody has something to offer. And if we try to get in this thinking,
like, gosh, I'm not doing what he's doing. I should be doing what he's doing. I think we
missed a point. We miss out on our shared abilities. You've got unbelievable talents
and a brain twice the size of mind, and you're using it in an area that you are comfortable with
that is probably maximizing your abilities. I think it's good to be aware of what's going on
in the world and everybody should think about their brothers and sisters elsewhere and contribute
and do something to help other people. At the same time, don't spend too much time
stressing that you're not doing enough, you're not doing anything. Do something,
but it shouldn't be something which is agonizingly painful. You know, I think just the way I'm
geared, that kind of life is a pretty comfortable fit for me, you know? So I don't see it. Yeah,
it's a sacrifice. It is. And I miss the family like crazy. And I'm missing a lot and not being
with my, man, I've spent more than three years since I've come here. I'm missing my parents,
my nieces and nephews, my brothers, my sister. I do. I miss all that stuff. But I'm pretty
comfortable in that weird remote setting in the mountains. So I learned about you through
my really dear friend Rick Gerson, his brother Mark Gerson, and ultimately
met John. And I think they learned about you through a piece that Nick Christophe wrote in
the New York Times in 2015. How did Nick come to find you? Because that story, we're going to link
to that story. The story is amazing, right? It leads off with about a 10 minute video that
I watched over and over and over again. And I came home and I made my family watch it.
And I sent it to my family back home. And there's a part in it that just says everything about it.
I mean, first of all, I think Christophe did an amazing job framing the story. And he was there,
which is in and of itself, I want to actually understand how someone actually gets there.
Because that strikes me as quite a challenge logistically. But he ends the article with a
story of a Muslim man who proclaims that you are Jesus Christ. And I always, it's the title of the
article, if I'm not mistaken, he's Jesus Christ, which coming from a Muslim man also speaks to the
religious harmony that you've described. And for people like me who aren't especially religious,
it makes you think, well, I guess that's what religion should be about, right? It shouldn't
be about most of what we think of religion as religion has has its taboos here. But I think the
point Christophe makes and makes it beautifully is, if you want to be critical of all of the religious
hypocrisy, by all means do so. But you can't then fail to acknowledge the times when in the name of
religion, people are doing these incredible things in the name of all religions, by the way, it's not
just your religion. I mean, as you know, it's people of all faiths that are doing these things.
But in many ways, I think that story brought amazing attention to your work that it breaks my
heart to think are there other toms out there whose stories are not being told? So how did
Christophe find you or how did you guys find each other?
He has an interest in Sudan, I think he's had it for a number of years. And I think for him,
he saw this, what Bashir was doing as such an egregious affront to humanity, that he felt
obligated to go and see firsthand what was happening. So he made a couple of trips into
the mountains, you can fly into Juba, then he got a flight up to the refugee camp in Eda,
and then managed to come into the mountains. You don't come in with official permission of the
Sudan government. So you're sneaking into the country. Right, because he's sneaking in, you get
a permit from the rebel government, and they allow you to come in. And I think he just has an interest
in that part of the world and really wanted to do something that shed light on the situation there
against Bashir. And he'd been into Nuba, I think, one previous time, and heard about the hospital
on the common see us there and see what kind of work we're doing to see for himself. And was there
for a few days. He's a really intrepid traveler and incredible journalist. I mean, he's unbelievable.
And what I respect about him the most is he can disagree with you, like, you know, whether
whatever, religiously, politically, not agree with your beliefs, but he can realize what you're doing
has benefit. You can look at it objectively and say, okay, you know, I don't believe in this
religion, but I see what these guys are doing and highlight that, you know, not many people are
willing to do that. I thought it was very elegant how he framed that in that piece in the New York
Times. And that video, though, it's only about 10 minutes. That was really my first introduction to
you, God, about three and a half years ago now. Right. So the world's a better place. Certainly
the Nuba mountains are a better place because of Nicholas's work. Right. And he tends to highlight
people that are kind of not well known. And there are others that are out there. And it's actually
part of what we're trying to now with Aurora. Aurora's focus is on highlighting what they say
is unsung heroes, but people that are kind of operating in the weeds that nobody knows about.
So shine a bit of spotlight on them, not so much for publicity, but to help them both in their,
in their work and to raise by raising their profile, you raise the issues that they're involved with.
So tell people a little bit about what the Aurora prize is and what it means for you to now be,
you're the 2018 recipient. Is that right? 2017. 2017 recipient. So what is the Aurora prize? I
know it's based on, I know a few things about it, so I'll fill in the little bits that I know.
It's a prize that has a finite life, correct? It was began in 2015 or 16 and it will run until about
2022, 23. And that duration, if I recall, is meant to commemorate the length of the Armenian genocide
in 1911-ish, 1915? Well, it's a hundred years onward. The genocide went on for about eight
years, 1915 and 1923. So this is a hundred years, henceforth, those eight years, those eight years
of the Aurora prize will be given out. Yes. And it's a, it's a substantial prize. You were selected
and my understanding is, first of all, it takes an act of Congress to get you out of Nuba to be doing
this other work, but it speaks to, I think, your understanding of how valuable this will be to the
broader mission that you're serving. Right. What I saw was I'm very comfortable being in Nuba and
doing the everyday medical work. And I definitely want to go back to that environment longer term
and get involved more with teaching the local people. And when these guys, once these guys come
back from medical school that we have out there, really working with them to get their skills up.
But I thought maybe using Aurora as a vehicle, it was time to come out to kind of see what was out
there with Aurora to try to expand the model that we have in Nuba mountains. So find a way to bridge
the gap between say big donors or people that have resources and small organizations, small people on
the ground that are kind of doing a lot of the grassroots work and doing it very efficiently.
Because I think there are a lot of other people that are doing the work nobody knows about.
And there should be a way to try to connect them to resources. So through Aurora, that's one of my
main goals. I wanted to come out and try to expand what we're doing. I felt that was we're in
Nuba doing our thing, but maybe a little bit pigeonholed. How do we expand that and get outside of
Nuba, get into South Sudan, to Central, from public to Chad, Tunisia, other places which are
really neglected parts of the world, hopefully into some conflict zones. That was my main thinking
coming out. And my time now I've got three months out of the mountains. I'm traveling all over the
place speaking on behalf of Aurora, kind of doing some basic of some promotion for them,
but also meeting a lot of people trying to formulate which direction we need to go in
Aurora. So I'll be physically out for these three months. It'll be three months later in the year
from September through November. Besides those two or three month periods, I'll be back into
the mountains, do my usual work at the hospital. What does more money solve in this problem? I
remember recently Mark sent us an update about sort of where the dollars were going. And it was
sort of hard to believe that so much could be done with so little. And I don't think the stats
are, I think they're so overwhelming that it's almost hard to put it in context, but it's worth
trying. For about a million dollars as an annual budget, what have you been able to do in the past
year? A million dollars is pretty generous. That's probably more than we'd need for the basic work.
But let's say if it's a million dollars, we can see about 130,000 outpatients. 130,000 outpatients
do close to 2000 operations, see maybe five, 6,000 inpatients. I mean, vaccinate tens of thousands
of children. I'm not sure what numbers of maternity and antinatal clinic patients, but a lot,
several thousand eternity patients for that. A lot of that million dollars, I mean, most of that,
gosh, I think it's the number that comes that I use is about 750,000, but somewhere between
750,000 and a million, if I'm being conservative, if someone gave us a million bucks, we could easily
run the hospital for a year and probably expand quite a bit of what we're already doing. That'd
be a very generous amount of money for us for one year. Which is very interesting. Anyone
listening to this who has some understanding of the economics of the US healthcare system
would find everything you just said to be sort of comical because of just the costs here are
so artificial and so inflated and so ridiculous. Now, when you think about where those dollars go,
I mean, how do you get these supplies? I mean, where do these things come from? I remember once
asking, I knew somebody who was, I think, on the board of Doctors Without Borders and I said,
hey, how come you guys aren't in Sudan? Because I remember once reading, you guys couldn't even
get certain vaccines and antibiotics. You just physically couldn't get the supplies.
So you're really doing the work that nobody else can do here.
Yeah, it's tricky. I mean, our number one problem, when people say, what's your biggest
problem there? I always say logistics. It's the hardest thing because-
You don't have infrastructure.
Infrastructure is not there. And if we want anything, you want chemotherapy drugs, you want
antibiotics, you want the role of gauze, you've got to buy that in Nairobi. Nairobi is two
countries away. It's South Sudan and Kenya. So it's got to come from Nairobi. Like this past
shipment of drugs came from Nairobi by truck up to actually through Uganda, up to the border with
South Sudan, where they just harassed the heck out of the drivers and all kinds of people.
You have to bribe the guards?
You've got to bribe the guards and they give you a hard time and they don't want you going through
and they say, no, they're always changing the rules. You know, there's a duty, you've got to
have all this paperwork. I mean, just reams of paperwork to get this stuff through. So we've got
some people that are in Juba that don't actually work for us, but work for the church that help us
through all this process to get this truck through. Now, from there, there are, I don't know, 30 or 40
checkpoints from the border of Uganda and South Sudan up to the refugee camp in Iida. And it takes
a few weeks. It takes about three weeks to get up there just because of the checkpoints and the
delays and everything else. It can take three weeks to get up to this refugee camp in Iida.
Then from there, it's offloaded. We've got to go and pick it up. We've got to find a way to get it
from Iida up to our place. Wait, not you personally? No, not me personally, but we've got to get some
trucks or something to go down there and pick it up or find someone that can carry it for us.
And that's about six hours. It's not really a road. It's a dirt track. I mean, there aren't
roads there. These terrible dirt tracks you get from Iida to where we are. That's about six hours
on the best day just during the dry season. So rainy season, which runs from about June through
October, you can't go with the trucks. You can't really even go with a, like a Land Cruiser. Usually
we don't move at all. If you really had to get in or out at that time, you've got to go with a quad
bike. That can usually get you in or out, but sometimes even then if it's a flash, it was a
heavy rainfall and you have a flash flooding, these dry river beds, if that fills up with water, you've
got to wait. Maybe it's the way today, a few hours. So in the hospital on any given day, how
much do you have in terms of IV fluids, gauze, antibiotics, soap? Right. I mean, things that we
just, we can't even imagine not taking for granted in an American hospital. Right. I mean, if we have,
if this truck makes it through, because we make our order and we make a fairly generous order,
just because we know it's so difficult to get stuff out there. If that stuff makes it all through,
we're in pretty good shape. For how long? For a year. So we try to make it one full year on that
supply that gets sent in. And the problem comes because sometimes you order stuff in the Roby and
it's not in stock and you know, you just can't, you can't order one off things. There's no, there's
no system to get stuff up to us. That's really hard. If you can't load everything on that truck
for this one go, we're a bit stuck. You've got to really be creative trying to get these other small
things up. Is there like a chief logistics officer that is in charge of the ordering and
the procurement and the management of this product? Because that sounds like a, I mean, that's a,
that's a bottleneck, right? Yeah. It's a terrible job. So John Fielder through F commission healthcare
has a woman who's in his, he's gotten off the small office in Nairobi. They got a few staff.
So she did all of our procurement. So we sent her the list of things we needed. I mean, it's,
it's, it's a lot of items, a lot. So she has to go out and source all this stuff and get it in Nairobi
from a few different vendors, get the trucks or less stuff, get it through.
We've got a couple of people in Juba that help us with logistics that are not employees of ours,
but they're just kind of, they're helping us out. Just kind of random people and they can help
shepherd that stuff through. But it's, it's, it's really, really difficult. It's a lot of work for
those people. What does the pattern of mortality look like in Nuba? My guess is infant mortality
must still be quite high. Right. How much of that is due to challenges with prenatal care versus
the actual deliveries and postnatal care? I think a lot of the neonatal deaths are just from
difficult deliveries. You know, their baby gets asphyxiated, baby's born and dies. Is it still
born or die soon after birth? And there are very few deliveries done. I mean, 99% of women there
still live at home. To deliver in a clinic with maybe a traditional birth attendant is rare,
let alone in a hospital. So I think a lot of it is just due to, you know, most of those people
probably would end up in a C-section with a C-section if they were at a hospital in the U.S.
or even in Kenya, if they had access to care or they would have the C-section. We are, you know,
we have one place to do C-sections. There are actually two now that do C-sections. How many,
how many babies do you deliver in a typical year? I think there are maybe three or 400 in our hospital,
somewhere around there. Like we came with the exact number. So it's, you know, it's really, it's not,
it's a very small number compared to the number of deliveries. So the vast majority of women still
deliver at home. But you're doing presumably more of the high risk ones. I mean, if a child is
breached, is there, can you deliver a breached baby at home? That's, I mean, the risk would be
enormous, right? Right. Some make it out, but a lot of those babies are going to die because they
just get, they get stuck, they get asphyxiated and maybe dies. So I mean, when we do our antenatal
clinic, you know, these women will come and the midwife there fills the card out for them. It's
okay. They've had 10 deliveries and four living children. You know, this one died at birth, this
one died at birth, this one died from diarrhea, this one died from fever, you know, this kind of
thing. So it's a lot of- And what about the mothers? What is the maternal mortality like?
I don't know. That's something I really wish I could have a grip on because you hear occasionally,
you know, it's not that often we hear about it, but once we hear, oh yeah, this woman died from,
she bled to death, you know, after he'd been birthed to the baby at some remote village.
There's not really, it's so remote and people are so spread out. There's not really a system to
collect that kind of information. So I don't really know. It's got to be, it's got to happen because,
you know, we have a lot of women that we ended up doing C-sections on that would have died
without that. You know, how many times a baby is stuck? The mother's already septic and, you know,
we have to do a C-section or something. And this says nothing if preeclampsia and all of the other
things that would just show up even under the most normal, you know, circumstance. Right. And
getting women with eclampsia is not uncommon. So if we get a clampsia at home, especially young,
you know, Muslim are our prime whips that are very young, they're not going to survive when
they start convulsing. And to get to us is a chore. I mean, it's really hard to reach us.
What are the patterns of diseases like there? I mean, when we're watching, and again, I keep
mentioning this because it's just such an important film, The Heart of Nuba. You see these things that
you're doing, Tom, that just, I mean, they blow my mind. And maybe because I know enough about
medicine that I can watch what you're doing and appreciate, you know, the partial nephrectomies
you're doing on kids with, you know, tumors in their kidneys. And like, how did you even learn
to do that operation? Even within the realm of surgery, that's not a trivial operation to do on
a child that size. Yeah, I've done some nephrectomies before, total nephrectomies on for tumors or for
trauma or for whatever. So meaning remove the whole kidney. So I wasn't so worried about that,
but I was worried about was the other kidney. It's harder to take part of the kidney out because
you have to be able to preserve the blood flow to the part that remains. Right. And you know,
they can can bleed it. So if it was just say the tumor was partially involved in the kidney and
say you're doing the operation and you can't stop the bleeding, your backup is just to take the whole
thing out. But you couldn't do that in this case. Because this child had one kidney that had to
fully come out and then there was a partial note. So you basically, this kid would die if you
couldn't save half of the remaining kidney. Right. Exactly. So it was lower, the tumor wasn't lower
pole of the kidneys. So I had to take out half the kidney. So there was a visiting, actually a
visiting as a friend of mine who was visiting, he's a family practice doctor, Corey Chapman was there.
And we talked about this case and going back and forth and he said, let's look on YouTube.
If there's something, because I read, I'm reading about it and everything I was reading was talking
about all these fancy things. You know, there's some kind of a slush, like an ice slush that you
have to bathe the kidney in to get the metabolism way down. So you can do the operation, just
different things we didn't have. So we looked on YouTube and I'm just, when I think about it now,
I wonder how we did it because normally we can't watch YouTube there because we have internet,
we have a satellite dish, internet, but the speed is very, very slow. So normally we can't watch any
videos because it's just too, it's just too slow. But for some reason we were able to see this video
and it was this group of Polish surgeons that were doing the partial infrectum aid
and with a fairly low tech approach. So we watched that and said, okay, I think, I think I can do it
following what these guys are advising. We kind of followed their system, managed to put these
sort of buttresses like on the lower pole, the kidney to kind of staunch the bleeding and it
worked. And the kind of the child did very well. That was held by YouTube. I mean, I think that
really helped us out in that case. Like the Khan Academy of surgery. That's right.
How long do you just spend rounding? I mean, how many inpatient beds do you have in this hospital?
Yeah, it's 435 beds. And what's your typical capacity? I mean, your typical utilization,
how many patients are in there? I mean, it's, it's about a hundred percent occupancy. It's,
it's a bit less now than it was saying the peak of the fighting. When the peak of the fighting,
it was crazy. It'd be five, 500 people there, 550. So there were, you know, several children's
were several to a bed. We have wounded all over the place. I mean, not even in beds, just
wherever we could, we could fit them. It looks like when you see movies in war zones and you
see the tents that are serving as, you know, hospitals, and you just see amputation, nose
completely missing, you know, sort of the most gruesome things. That's what it looks like you're
in. I mean, you are literally in a war zone. I'm thinking back to residency. If we had to round on
20 patients in the morning, we were moaning and groaning like it was going to be the end of the,
oh my God, I'm not going to have time for breakfast today before the OR I've got to round on 24
patients. Yeah. So you're rounding on 300 patients. I mean, how, I don't even know how you do that.
Now probably 300. Those days was more. I mean, I remember one time we had this measles epidemic
and just on children's ward, we had 225 patients. So a hundred normal cases,
malaria's bowel structures. You don't have vaccines. I'm guessing. Is that the reason
they don't get the measles? We, with the first three years of the fighting, we didn't have them.
So the usual provider stopped providing them. The usual big organization that provides them
stop providing the vaccines. Why? Just logistically couldn't get them in. Logistically. And they,
we were in rebel held territory and a lot of these people, these big organizations don't
want to violate the sovereignty of the, of the host government by providing something as simple
as vaccines. This is just how it is, which really shocked me. The sovereignty of a government that
kills its own people. It needs to be respected. It's the theater of the absurd. It's crazy.
So, yeah, I mean, Ron's were just, they would take hours and we started at seven 30 in the
morning and two o'clock I'd be finishing up and just try to get through all those people.
But then you're, aren't you being interrupted every hour by some trauma that comes in?
Right. There's stuff coming in. There's stuff, there's other emergencies. I mean,
the other stuff was still coming. I mean, somebody comes into a woman who comes in,
was having a miscarriage, bleeding, we have to break into a C-section on somebody who can't
deliver. So all this stuff was still going on. It was, it was pretty crazy. I mean, it was,
you really had to just go as fast as you could. It was a lot of just putting out fires and we
weren't, we weren't able to spend a lot of time with these patients. Obviously it was really
got to go pretty rapid fire through all those cases. It was exhausting. Psychologically,
it was, it was rough. One of the other questions my daughter wanted me to ask you is,
what's the most afraid you've ever been there? You know, she was sort of taken aback and we told her
before the movie, I said, look, Olivia, this is, this isn't a Disney movie. You're going to see
people getting killed. You're going to see bombs dropping on innocent people. And it's not a movie.
It's real. Right. So are there times when you are just afraid for your own safety?
Yeah. You know, I think every time they bombed the hospital twice and they bombed our local region,
kind of within a half kilometer several times. So the first time the area was bombed,
we were at church and the church was just outdoors. It's not really church. It's kind of outdoors
thing. And we were finishing up and the, the catechist was up there talking to people and we
heard the airplane overhead. We were used to it because every day the airplane came overhead,
but we'd never been immediate vicinity. They never had never been bombed. So we just got
the airplanes over heads going to bomb somewhere. And is that because you had this belief that said
even these people as wicked as they are, wouldn't actually bomb a hospital. Or is there some sort
of view of we'll respect at least one sanctity of life. So that was, that was the bit in the back
of our minds. And we had him in bombing. And this was, this was a couple years into it. All right. We
had him in bomb directly. There weren't commercial flights. So anytime we heard an airplane, it was
going to bomb somewhere. And then we hear the, we hear the airplane. Then invariably a few hours
later, one day would show up a bomb somewhere and people are wounded in the wind. They show up.
This day it was a bit different. We heard the airplane overhead and the mass was over. We're
kind of standing there. All of a sudden somebody says, everybody get down. So we, we just dive on
the ground. They were just lying flat. And I heard the airplane drone overhead, you know, this
Antonov sound. Then I heard the pitch change. It sort of high pitched, like a whirring sound,
almost like a jet engine noise. And then boom, this incredibly loud explosion. It felt like it
was two feet away. I mean, it was like half a kilometer away. It wasn't right. But it was so
loud. And it circled again. Then I realized that what that whirring sound was, was the sound of
the bomb falling through the air. So then I now, so now I know what that sounds like. Then it's
happened six bombs, six times. You kept hearing this thing comes around again, bombs. And you're
lying there terrified thinking you just, you feel like you want to burrow yourself into the ground
and disappear. You know, we just lying flat exposed thinking what, you know, what happens?
And the thinking is not even so much being killed, but what if, what if my, you know, what if my leg
is blown off or my arm gets blown off, you have no control over this. You're totally at the, at the
mercy of these people. And you feel like you're, you feel like you're just in like a hunted animal.
That's the, that's what I felt like. I felt like I'm, I'm a hunted animal. And at that time, since
we hadn't been bombed, we didn't have the, the foxholes dug around. So immediately after that,
we went and we dug foxholes all over the hospital grounds. And that's what you see in the film.
There's actually one point when you're being interviewed and the bombs start coming in,
you guys have to jump into these foxholes. Right. Right. And then another time we were
bombed, I was in the hospital and just down on the, on the floor of the hospital, you know,
you're thinking, well, you know, you're just, you're just thinking this, this might be it.
This thing might, cause you can't tell where it's going to fall. You hear that whirring sound
and we hear that whirring sound. You don't know if that's going to fall on top of you.
It's going to fall right next to you and, and, and just then shatter your body.
You have no idea. So it's really, it's, it's really terrifying. I mean, there's no other
way to describe it. And I mean, you know, when you see this stuff that's happened in Syria,
people living in these cities, I mean, you can, you can imagine what that is like and the kids
that were in that situation. That's something you'll never, never outgrow that fear and that
feeling of, of being bombed. You really, you feel like you're a hunted animal. I think it's the
closest thing I can, not that I've ever been hunted or I'm an animal, but you just feel like,
I remember thinking to myself, we were down, this is after, this is a few bombings later,
we're down in the foxhole and there was a Sukhoi 24 jet going overhead. Sukhoi 24 is a supersonic
jet bomber, you know, bombing villages, you know, huts. And thinking, what are these people doing?
I remember thinking to these guys, I say, how can they bomb us? Don't they know there are people
down here? That's what I felt. You know, like it was some exercise where they made a mistake.
And of course they knew exactly there are people down there. That's why they're bombing, you know?
But I, I really hope someday I will meet these pilots. Not that I don't even feel any animosity
towards them. The feeling is never as strange. You don't feel anger. You don't feel animosity
towards these people. Just kind of wonderment. Like what are they doing? Like why are they doing
this? So I would love to meet these guys someday and say, what, what were you thinking? You know,
what, what did they tell you before you did your mission? You know, I was a flight surgeon in the
Navy. So I know you have a briefing before the pilots fly out. They discussed the mission today.
We're going to fly here. We're going to bomb this target. This is our objective. What were you told
in the briefing room? They say, okay, today guys are going to bomb a hospital. There are a bunch of
civilians there. I mean, presumably if you're, if you're trying to put your psychology hat on,
you have to believe that they are being told that the people that they are bombing are somehow
a threat to them or their sovereignty or supporting rebels. I mean, you, you'd have to
concoct a story that's so orthogonal to the truth. Right. Maybe that might be it because I mean,
after one of the times the hospital was bombed, one of our staff heard a radio broadcast from
Ella Bade, which is a city in the north. And the way they portrayed it on this radio was they
admitted they bombed a hospital. They said we bombed an American church hospital in Cowra,
which is the kind of capital of the rebel held territory, hospital taking care of the rebel
soldiers. That's how it's portrayed. So you're an American hospital and America of course is a great
enemy. It's a Christian hospital. Therefore they're no good and it's taking care of rebels. So you're,
you're justified in this, in this act. And my guess would be that's what these guys were fed.
Who knows that the pilots were true believers. I know work with a lot of pilots in the U S military
and they would, they would not go along with the mission that they said, you're going to the
Obama hospital with civilians. They wouldn't do it. We say, look, man, we're not doing this.
I know these guys, they were not, these guys, they had, they loved the fly and they loved the
country, but they were not interested in killing civilians. And, uh, I still hope someday I can
meet these guys and just have a talk with them. And, uh, just to know what they were thinking and
what, what went on in their brains, like whether they know this, how did they feel about it? I'm
just interested in what they would, what they would say. How do you cope with what I could only imagine
is stress and anxiety aren't the right words, but just sort of the gravity of it. Like, you know,
when you describe a day in your life, you know, getting up at five 30 in the morning, making rounds
at seven operating. If you said, Peter, you got to go do this for a month. I mean, first of all,
I could provide no assistance to you. That's the unfortunate reality of it. Despite my medical
training, all I would, I mean, I could, you know, put IVs in patients and that's about, I mean, I,
I don't think I could provide any benefit, but let's assume I could even magically provide
benefit. I can't imagine how physically, but more so emotionally exhausted I would be
at the end of 30 days. Right. Even thinking back to my training where, you know, you'd have
every other night call, but on one of the nights in between, you didn't get to go home. And so you've
been in the hospital for three and a half days and it's been one trauma after another. Like even that
feeling is just as physically tired as you are. There's something different going on, which is
just an emotional depletion. Right. So to imagine that you're now eight, no more, you're coming up
to 11 years into this and this is just in Sudan. Right. I don't understand how you can do that.
I think it hit the nail on the head. I think probably the emotional trauma and upset is
probably worse than the physical degradation your body takes by just always being on call and just,
even when you're not called at night, it's hard to sleep. You know, there's a lot of
kind of fear and worry about things, but there's always that less so now because they're not
bombing, but there's always that sense of worry about there being physical danger. But even when
you're out of that, when the physical, the risk of physical danger is not there, it's just the
psychological thought of always being responsible for the, for the patients and not having a
psychological rest. Like I can't refer these people somewhere. There are other colleagues
we can talk to or get an advice on or have somebody else see these patients. It is very
draining. And I don't know. I just, you know, a couple of things is one, of course, is I do draw
on my faith all the time. And I think that does help me keep centered a lot. You know, I go to
church every day and that's, I think helps put things in a bit of perspective. That's just how
it is. And besides that, I think you see the people there, they see the strength and resilience
of the Nuba people. You say, well, okay, if they can put up with this environment and keep functioning,
keep going ahead, let me just try to keep taking care of them as best I can. So I definitely get a
lot of strength from the people there and their attitudes. They've been in this for their whole
lives and they're, they're not giving up, they're pushing ahead with things. So let me see if I can
also just keep going. It's not easy by any stretch, both physically and mentally and emotionally. It's,
it's, it's very, very draining. But I don't know, it's weird. I mean, you get up in the morning and
you, you know, had this huge number of patients to get through and you kind of say, man, I'm sure
if I can, so I'm tired already. Like I feel like I kind of see the first few and then you, before
you know it, you're finished with the children's ward. Take a deep breath. Okay. I got through all
the children. Now we go to the female ward, you get through there, you pick up pace a bit, you get to
the male ward, you go through them, see the maternity patients. Now it's one o'clock. Okay,
I finished the rounds. We go to clinic, go to clinic and there's a big line of people.
How many patients would you see in clinic typically? Uh, maybe 40, 50. Again, I don't even
know what that means. I mean, I think most U.S. physicians would have a hard time seeing that many
patients in a week in clinic. Do you have any blood tests you can do? Can you do CBCs or UAs even? I
mean, what's the extent to your diagnostic toolkit? So until recently you had nothing. I mean, now you
have an ultrasound. Right. We've had the ultrasound from the, from the beginning. Okay. So we've had
that the whole time. That's been hugely helpful. You don't have an x-ray machine. X-ray we do now.
Okay. So we just got that about a year ago. So you can do a chest x-ray at least if you want some
assistance with, does this person have pneumonia or a pneumothorax or something like that? Right.
So prior to a year ago, we didn't have the x-ray. Now we do. It's, it's been a help. Lab has been
difficult. We can do a urine, we can do a stool, we can do a hemoglobin. Sometimes we can do a CBC,
but the machine always seems to be broken. You know, we'll get in the machine, work it for a while,
then it just stops working. You can't do a CBC. Chemistry tests, we can sometimes do a creatinine,
but then the machine breaks and you know, you can't do a creatinine. Sometimes you can do
ALT, ST, machine breaks, can't do anything. But would those things matter? In other words,
if, if, if someone's listening to this and says, well, gosh, if it's $50,000 to buy a new lab,
piece of laboratory equipment, can we have one of those, you know, brought in with next year's
supplies. Would that change, would that make life easier for the care you guys provide?
It would help. And you know, like there's a, just saw this chemistry analyzer, it's called a piccolo,
which is supposed to be kind of built for these remote locations. It's pretty doctorproof. I mean,
you kind of have this thing, it's pretty hard to slip in a disc, you put a drop of blood on it,
and it gives you results. So our guys in lab can do that. Not our lives, our guys in lab can do the
other tests, but the machines are just very, it's less about the human. It's more about the, you need
a robust machine. A very robust machine. So this is kind of a thing. And that's about 14 grand. If we
have one of those and some of the discs, which have the reagents kind of embedded in them.
So if you had a year's supply of, of test strips or reagent discs, and then the machine,
you could do a CBC and a chem seven or a metabolic panel of some sort. Right. That would, yeah,
that would definitely help. We're pretty limited. We can do a peripheral blood film. So taking blood,
guys can do the film. We can look at that. So you're a pathologist now too. Yeah. And a very
hematologist. I'm terrible at it, but I can pick up like a chronic leukemia, chronic myologist,
chronic mycocetic or an acute leukemia. Those are, if it's pretty obvious, we can pick those up. But
a lot of blood films, I'm baffled. And when you have a child that has leukemia, I assume you send
them to Kenya. It's impossible. Why? It's too far. It's too expensive. It's too difficult. Like this,
the administrative stuff to get them there and the chance in Kenya of them being, I mean, maybe at a
higher end hospital, they could get decent care, but they're just, we just can't do it. So what do
you, can you treat with chemotherapy, a child? Not with leukemia. If a child has leukemia, we often
will give steroids to try to, you know, sell them a bit of care for leukemias for chronic leukemias.
These are again, are usually adults. If it's a chronic liposylic leukemia, we'll treat them with
cyclophosphamide. We don't have tablets. We'll give periodic injections and that can kind of
wail them a bit. CML, chronic myosinable leukemia. We don't have treatment for, I would like to have
at least, at least some hydroxyurea, which is kind of an older drug for it. You know this drug,
GleeVac. Yeah. It's just about to say GleeVac would cure most cases of CML. I mean, it's a very
expensive drug in the United States, of course. That's the problem. So with GleeVac, I was so
excited like a month or two ago. I'm reading that GleeVac is now in generic. Oh my God, maybe we can
buy GleeVac because we get a few a year. We don't get a huge number of CML patients. We get a few.
I'm thinking, man, we wouldn't need a huge amount. You know, so
to look it up and it's okay, GleeVac is going on generic. So the price went from 8,000 a month
to 7,000 a month. Yeah. This is another one of these ridiculous systems, you know, problems,
which is a lot of times when drugs go from being branded to generic, there's virtually no change in
price. Right. We just can't do that. You know, there are a lot of things that are just beyond
our scope of being able to pay for it. That's something that to me is,
it's really difficult to consider. I mean, if, you know, we can be as critical as we want of the US
healthcare system for all of its buffoonery, but in large part, it's because we can be buffoons.
Right. Right. It's because we have infinite resources, though we don't, right? But in the
short term, we have infinite resources. And so we never have to ask the question of what are we
optimizing for and how do we triage expenses? On the other hand, you're faced with that decision
every single day. Right. So you would look at a patient with CML and say, we're not going to
spend $80,000 a year to save this person's life because as much as we believe every life is equal,
we sort of know that $80,000 can save a hundred lives in another way. And are you the one that
has to make that decision by yourself? Yeah, it's agonizing. It's absolutely agonizing. That's,
that's, I mean, that's just one example of money. I've got a woman that comes all the time with CML
and she's got a huge spleen that hurts. She's anemic and she got a bunch of kids. I got to
talk to her in clinic and try to figure something out with her. And she walks, I don't know how long,
how far she walks to reach us. I mean, it's absolutely agonizing. I cannot send her anywhere.
There's just this totally impossible. You just can't do it. So if we had, we wouldn't need
mountains of GleeVac. I mean, a small amount would be enough to at least get her through a year.
There are a few people that have CML. It's a few. It's not a huge number. If someone's listening to
this and they say, I'm going to tell you a story in a moment called the starfish story, but I want
to save one starfish. That's, that's, I'll tell you the story. Logistically, would it even be
possible for someone to provide one year's worth of GleeVac to a patient in your hospital? Is that
something that they could do through the American, the African mission? How would someone even
logistically go about providing specific or project-based funding to your mission?
If they could get the drug, certainly had access to the physical drug here in the US. Maybe if
they sent it to say the Catholic Medical Mission Board, which is my sponsoring lay sending agency,
and they also help us a lot with logistics and with the overall managing the hospital,
they might be able to find a way to get it down to us, at least get it to Juba and then we could
figure out a way to get it up to us. If they could get the physical drug, there was a program when I
was on Armenia the time before last, we met some guys and there's supposedly some GleeVac program
that you can register. Like the patient can register and they can get drugs at either low
cost or no cost. So we went through all this thing, counted the person, she said, okay, all you have to
do is take, fill out these forms, have the patient go to a cartoon, get the drugs. That's absolutely
impossible. We can't get the cartoon. That's on the other side of the enemy lines and you just
can't reach there. Which gets back to your point of providing the money is half the battle, but the
logistics of actually getting it in there. And I mean, just spit balling, you can't have these
things air dropped or air lifted in because the enemy fighters will obliterate anything that's
trying to, it's not like you can fly the Cessna in there to get this stuff in there. There's been no
non bombing aircraft in our airspace for, it's been since November, 2011. So, so even foundations
like the Gates foundations, which do a ton of great stuff in Africa, I mean, Sudan is basically off
limits. You know, so they were able to provide money for a bunch of GleeVac. One of the problems
and one of the problems I've, I've decided to go with Aurora is a lot of these funds are kind of
unassailable. If you're like, I'm an individual or even a small organization that's trying to apply
to one of these big organizations to just get through that application process to get funds
and then to account for it and do monitoring evaluation and follow up. It's a very daunting
task. You need, you need people who are trained in this area of writing proposals and monitoring
evaluation, all this sort of stuff to really follow through with all this. It's very difficult
to access some of these big funds and big organizations. You know, a lot of these bigger
groups are set up to do that kind of work and their administrative size has grown exponentially
because in order to get these, this funding, you need a big administrative staff to apply for the
funds and follow up and accountability and accounting and all that kind of stuff. Right.
And you, I mean, you've got tons of extra time, I'm sure to do that, right? I just can't, I just
can't do it. I just can't do it unless it can be made fairly simple. Or someone's okay, if I got
the drug, I'll send it to Catholic Medical Mission Board and then Catholic Medical Mission Board will
send it down and we get the drug, you know, at least as far as Juba and we can try to figure
out a way to get it up. But it's just, it's really, there's a problem with access and just getting
through the administrative things you have to do to get some of this stuff. There's, so there,
there are several kind of different levels of, of difficulty. So going back to the sort of state of
diseases you see, if a person makes it out of their sort of the young life, right? If a person's
sort of your age or my age, what are they going to die from? Middle-aged people, we have a lot of
cirrhosis liver cancers and that's, there's a huge, hepatitis B. Yeah, huge. Like we do, we screen all
of our pregnant women for hep B. Do you guys have a hep B vaccination program? We do, we do. The
reason we started screening the, the pregnant women is just to get an idea about the basic rate. And
it's about close to 20%. Hepatitis B positive, just in general populations are people who are
not sick. They're pregnant with children. So what we're doing is we encourage the mother when the
baby's born, we give the baby hepatitis B vaccine immediately after birth. And we hope with that,
that we'll stop preventing this baby from getting hepatitis B as it get older and prevent all the
complications from that. We haven't really scaled up to the point where we have so many
heavy positive people. And can you only vaccinate the women who are coming in for deliveries or are
you able to get the vaccine into the community for the women who are still delivering at home?
No, we haven't, we haven't reached that point yet. So you're only scratching the surface then
because the majority of these birds are outside of your hospital. Right. Exactly. I mean, eventually
we like to have kind of midwives these places and have the testing capability to test all these
people for hepatitis B. Or if people delivered in these clinics, you say, look, we can't do the test
thing, but we just give the vaccine. We'll assume the kid has hepatitis B, give the vaccine because
they have to get hepatitis B anyway as part of the pentavalent series. So after that first shot,
we continue with pentavalent, which is DPT, diptheroid apoptosis tetanus, hepatitis B,
and amylolus influenza B. I've heard that kids actually can get diphtheria in Africa. Yeah.
Has there been a case of diphtheria in the United States since the forties? No, I think that I think
I don't even know what diphtheria is. I mean, like, I'm, it sounds stupid to say that, but I remember
learning about it in medical school and I know we all get the vaccine for it. What, what is the
disease? What is, how does it manifest? We've only had, from what I remember, one case, and I think
she had the diphtheria, it was in an adult, but it's a grinding bacteria, nithyrii, and it's a
bacterial infection. It affects the throat and they get like a, it looks almost like a thick scab
that forms in the throat. They kind of die from airway problems. You know, just think it's thick
and they can't, they swallow, they can't really breathe well and they can die from airway problems.
It's a horrible, really a terrible disease. And you mentioned your mother-in-law has leprosy. Right.
Again, I've never seen that in my life. It's a bacteria as well. It's, is it in the tuberculosis
family or something? Exactly. It's mycobacterium lepri. It's a mycobacterium and it's transmitted
by respiratory droplets. Oh, it's not by touch. I thought leprosy was sort of contagious through
touch. Yeah, that's, that's, that's, Is that a wives tale? Yeah, it's really transmitted by respiratory
droplets and it should be prolonged close contact. So somewhat similar to TB. It's not a real,
it's a very slow growing organism, but prolonged close contact respiratory droplets, you can affect
it. It affects the nerves in the skin and with that nerve infection, people lose sensation. They,
they get cuts or wounds and they don't take care of things. They burn themselves. They don't pay
attention to it gets infected, bone gets infected and you have to amputate the digit. Are these
people prior to your arrival that were kind of outcast and they would be not touched or anything
like that? Yeah, there was definitely discrimination against them. They didn't have like separate
places where they would make them outcast, but people would kind of avoid them. Like my mother-in-law
still, I think a lot of it was the people themselves would kind of withdraw due to shame
and due to the fear of giving it to somebody else. Like my mother-in-law kind of withdrew. She stays
by herself. She doesn't eat with the other family. They keep telling her, look, come and eat with us
is okay, but she will not come and eat with other people. She always insists to kind of eat by
herself. She does it herself. She's kind of self-isolation from society. She's pulled herself out.
So she'll talk to you in chat and interact with you, but then with eating and with more social
interactions, she'll kind of pull back and eat by herself. And how prevalent is tuberculosis?
Very, very prevalent. And for our place, our HIV rate is quite low. Which is what? It's less than,
much less than 1%. Oh, wow. Maybe point something, maybe 0.1%.
And is that an artifact of where you are geographically? Or is that as part of the
benefit of some of the aid relief that made its way in the early part of 2000s?
Yeah, I think the main reason is our isolation. Is there drug use there? Prostitution, I mean,
which I assume would be the two most dominant modes of transmission? No, prostitution is not
really part of that society. And IV drug use is unheard of. It's all through, like with most of
Africa, is through heterosexual transmission. And I think just the starting to get a little bit of
a toehold in Nuba, but still our rate is very low. I'm worried that if peace comes and the place
opens up and you've got more movement of people in and out, the rate is going to skyrocket. That's
what happened in South Sudan. The NITIS is there because we have a lot of STDs. Ghanri is very
common syphilis. Do you see tertiary syphilis in really advanced cases? I don't think so,
but maybe some of the stuff we're seeing is just undiagnosed tertiary syphilis. I don't know.
I don't think we see it. What I see as syphilis is we do a VDRL test and we have a lot of VDRL
positives, which are not a very accurate test. We have a lot of false positives. We have a lot of
VDRL, or RPR positive people. We do that screening. We're just screening now with the
pregnant mothers for VDRL and we have a lot of positivity. We don't see the shankers or the
secondary syphilis. That's really, really rare, but the VDRL positives are very common.
We talked about liver cancer. Do you see heart disease?
No, heart failure. In the older population, we'll see a fair bit of heart failure. Somebody may be
in their 60s, 70s, that's in heart failure. It's like bacterial or I remember there was some
bacteria like shagas, something or other that would weaken the heart muscle. Is it that type of a
heart failure? Yeah, no, we don't have shagas disease in our area. It's just old age. Do you
think it's atherosclerotic in origin? I don't think so. I've never seen anybody that could say,
I think this person had an MI, just not a single one in 10 and a half years. Some is hypertension,
just kind of untreated hypertension. We'll let people come in with blood pressure of 250 over 180.
Really? Yeah. How prevalent is obesity over weight type 2 diabetes?
Obesity about 0.0001%, almost non-existent. An occasional person is a bit over weight, but
really, really rare. How often do you see type 2 diabetes?
We'll see it. Not so prevalent, but it's definitely there. Somebody's see older people
come in and just new diagnosis of diabetes. Maybe someone has 40s or 50s.
Do you ever see fatty liver? Like when you're operating on a patient, do you ever
see that the liver is fatty? No, I can't remember a single case when I've seen fatty liver.
You do so much cancer surgery, especially in children, but they're cancers. We don't see that
much here. What types of cancers do the people in Nuba get versus basically not get? In the United
States, of course, you'd have lung, breast, colon, prostate, or the lion's share of cancers,
followed by pancreas. Those are the big five. How prevalent are those cancers in Nuba?
Not so. If we go to kids first, or burka-sling-phoma is fairly common.
That's an EBV related, if I recall. Epstein-Barr virus is?
Epstein-Barr virus. You really just see that in Laryaholo endemic regions. We're in that,
it's called a burka zone. That's a great cancer because it's curable with just cyclophosphamide.
Six courses, cyclophosphamide, and you cure a cancer is great, very satisfying,
but it's rare to have a cancer you can cure, obviously. For adults, liver cancer is probably
most common. That's all I think all- That's a paticellular carcinoma?
Paticellular carcinoma, and probably all related to hepatitis B positivity. They drink a fair bit.
There's a local beer they make sorghum, but the alcohol content is not very high. It's fully weak.
It's a hep B related cancer with liver. We have a fair bit of cancer with the cervix.
For females, probably cancer with cervix is the most common.
Can you screen for HPV? You're the local gynecologist as well.
Can you do a pap smear? No. Pap smear would be a little bit impractical because we have to do
a swab and get that sent off and do it high level, get it off to a pathologist.
Again, if someone were listening to this and said, oh my God, if I could have an impact on
eradicating cervical cancer for these women, is that even feasible to have the equipment there
after you do the swab assessed for HPV? No. For cancer cervix, two approaches.
One would be this Gardasil, the HPV vaccine, were made available either at very low cost or just
giving us part of, I think it's actually just heard today as part of the WHO package. So they
can be integrated into the system where HPV is given to young girls, even young boys.
But then we're back to the logistics problem. Even if the WHO or any of the foundations came
along and said, we want to provide HPV vaccination en masse to Africa, you're still somewhat excluded.
We give other vaccines. If they can be lumped into your annual supplies.
Just do it to get stuff out there. But if you do it in one big push, get it out there. It's got
to be all cold chain. It's really hard, but it's doable. Get this stuff out there, one big push.
That will make a huge difference. We'll start with that. The treat cancer, the cervix treat
earlier versions, they call it a see and treat technique. I've not done it, but it's not.
There's probably a YouTube video on it.
There probably is, I think. I think there is actually. You paint the cervix with something.
I can't remember. It's iodine or some substance and you look for irregularities in the cervix
and then you freeze it. You have the little liquid nitrogen cylinder with some probes,
put that in the cervix and you freeze it, make a nice ball of the cervix. Then you kill those
pre-cancerous cells and hopefully those people will not go on to develop invasive cancer,
the cervix. You would need some personnel for that because that would be pretty labor intensive.
That's more of a preventive medicine thing. We come in, examine them because you're not
treating people with the cancers. You want to get the pre-cancerous lesions. You get the screen and
do a lot of these screening things. We paint the cervix with some substance.
Look and see. You don't even need a colposcope. It's something even more simple than that.
I know they're doing it in Uganda and they have this equipment.
So that might be covered in between thing before Gardasil becomes available. At least we do a
screening of young women. Check the cervix, see what it looks like when you paint this stuff,
and then treat with liquid nitrogen. We don't have the equipment. I think that stuff is there
nor the knowledge to do it. What about breast cancer? How prevalent is that?
It's definitely there. The problem with breast cancer is by the time we diagnose it,
we only diagnose so we can feel a lump. No one's getting a mammogram.
Right. No mammograms or we don't do other stuff to diagnose it, memorize what we have.
So women present with a palpable mass that they're feeling and they show up.
Right. So usually they come with a palpable mass and they already have a nose and things that look.
So in that situation, you still do modified radical mastectomies?
We do. We usually do a modified radical mastectomy and then follow with Adriamycin,
S
I really don't think it's doing much. So it's really frustrating.
Would getting a mammogram machine add value? I mean, of course, there's all the futility and
the controversy around mammography per se, but I'm just sort of thinking of like,
what are some finite resources that could be added to, I mean, you're serving a million people
basically that live in a world we can't even imagine as far as even the simplest acts of
prevention. Right. The problem with that to do the screening, the scale up to that level.
Yeah. You need a whole new staff to get people through.
Right. And the same thing with cancer, server screening, it's maybe possible. So it's not just
a matter of supplying the machine. You need the radio. You need someone who's dedicated to reading
mammograms all day long. Or I mean, I guess the other option is, I mean, AI should actually make
mammography. This is probably one of the most important applications of machine learning is
actually reading x-rays. And you wouldn't even need a radiologist at some point. There will be a
day when you could run a million women through a mammogram in a year and there's a machine that's
reading it and basically giving you the answer. And then now you still need the logistics of a
person taking the patients through the machine and operating the machine. But anyway, we got to think
big, Tom. We got to think of these other ideas. I think these are areas where technology and
medicine and developing, there's not always a good marriage, but there are some areas where
you have technological leaps. Like for instance, our x-ray machine, part of it, the reason we
waited eight years to get one, first of all, they were as expensive as heck. How much did it,
does it, I don't even know how much an x-ray machine would cost. This one costs 33,000.
Which of course in the United States, that's the cost of like getting your gallbladder removed.
Right. I mean, literally that's about the cost of a cold cystectomy. Yeah. So it was, I mean,
for us was a big expense, but we do a lot, quite a few x-rays now are operating. The guy's actually
taken the, or x-ray texts are the operating room guys, but the guys in the operating room,
my lab, my assistant's in the operating room are the ones we taught how to take x-rays and they
did a pretty good job. We waited that long because we wanted a model that we could use. It was very
small, lightweight, simple, or you didn't have to use the chemicals and developers and all that sort
of stuff. And we just waited. Now we have a model where. Is it digital? It's digital. So it's a tiny
little device mounted on this little thing. And I can actually select the size of a small,
like a tiny box that has the x-ray tube in it. And it's a laptop and the screen is a operates
by Bluetooth between x-ray machine and the computer. Take the x-ray that shows up on the
computer screen and it's all there. And you can take that x-ray and adjust it. You can darken it,
lighten it. You can focus in a certain areas. I mean, it takes a beautiful x-ray and you can
play around with this. You really get a nice picture. And there's very little variable cost
at this point. It's all a fixed cost that you've covered. And now the more you use it, the better.
You're getting more read. Absolutely. And the power is also the other thing was the power
needed because we're 100% on solar. We've got a backup generator. It's 12 and a half kilowatts.
How long does 12 and a half kilowatts last the hospital if the panels were to go out?
We could run things on it. The problem with the rate limiting factor there is the fuel.
Right now, I think we're left with maybe. Oh, so if you have enough fuel for the generator,
you could run indefinitely off it if you needed to. Yeah. But I mean, we'd have to give probably
big breaks of time. It's a fairly good size thing. And the hospital is the only thing that
has electricity. You don't have electricity in your home. No, there's no grid. So it's just the
hospital has power. We run on the solar, I mean, pretty much 24 seven. We really don't need the,
as long as the batteries are there and everything's functioning, we don't need the generator at all.
And we try to find the time when these batteries are going to order a new set and new panels,
wherever you need to re-up that. So we're, I think, three years into this set of batteries.
What about colon cancer? Do you see that?
Pretty rare. We've had what maybe two or three cases in 10 years. I mean, it's really, really rare.
The folks who are the most elderly within the community live to what age? I mean,
what is considered old? Nobody there knows the rage. They don't have any
birth records. Even my wife doesn't know her age. She's somewhere in her thirties probably.
So they don't really know their exact age, but I would guess they're probably,
an older person, they were probably in the seventies, his or her seventies. I don't think
they, they live much beyond that. And do you see cognitive impairment in that population?
Really rare. You rarely, as somebody who say, I think this person has Alzheimer's. Really,
really rare to see that. I mean, I think they should die of something else before they reach
that stage. You just don't see it.
The point you just made that reminds me, there's a new movie, which you may have seen,
I think it's called A Good Lie. It stars Reese Witherspoon. It's a beautiful story.
After we saw The Heart of Nubo, we watched that because I wanted my daughter to sort of
understand the history of the Sudanese refugees. And that's one of the points from the movie that
I remember being very sort of moved by. They were all assigned the same birthday because
nobody knew their birthday. Like even something like that that we would take for granted. Do they
celebrate birthdays?
No, nobody does. I mean, you know, my wife, we kind of invented a birthday or she invented one
of November 21st. So when that day comes around, we'll usually do something. She's always surprised
like, what, what are you doing? Oh, okay. So she doesn't give me a hard time for not buying
flowers if we could buy flowers. So it's pretty easy to be married to a Nubo lady. She doesn't,
the expectations are very low.
How has your life changed since you've been married? I mean, do you have a greater sense
of obligation to not die, to put it bluntly?
Yeah, I would say, yeah, definitely. So I'm like, you know, you can't be so heavily with things
because I've got a wife and I wanted to kind of look after her and make sure she's okay.
There's been a little bit of a change in perspective with that. And I think if and when we get
children, I think that'll change another degree up for sure.
Do you think you could do what you do if you had children?
I think we could stay there. And if things aren't really hairy, we'd have to see how to proceed.
But just in terms of, I mean, your wife is a nurse, so you have the luxury of working together. So
as focused as you are on your work, she is there with you.
Right.
When you have children, they will not work with you for quite some time. I just wonder, would it be
challenging to sort of now be torn between two obligations that for many years will not
overlap at all?
It'll be difficult. You know, I think one thing, and one thing I remind my wife of is that,
you know, I finish work late and I'm always, you know, often preoccupied with things and things
with the hospital and all that sort of stuff. But at least I'm there every evening. The weekends,
we have a little bit of time on a Sunday, but together. And even though the work is very much
all encompassing, there's no commute and there are no distractions. You know, we don't have,
there's no TV, there's no radio, we don't have other things that kind of occupy our minds. So
when we're together at home, we really can be present to each other. And I would hope that if
we have children, I'll be able to use that to really spend time with the kids and not be always
in work, you know, if life continues like that anew, but there's not any travel involved. I'm
just there. You know, I'm a stone's thrower.
You know, it's funny when you say it that way, it's actually, you may actually spend more time
with your kids than many of us do here because of our distractions and our travel and our this
and our that. Yeah. Life here is much more hectic. I mean, it seems almost ironic to say that.
You feel out of place here, even though you grew up here. I mean, when you walk down Park Avenue
or Madison Avenue, are you sort of like, what in the hell is this place?
I do. I do feel a bit out of place. In a sense, I do enjoy it. Like I've never even when I was
like, grew up in upstate New York, I never spent time in New York City. So this is really kind of
it's exciting. I like it, but I don't think I could I could stay long term. I mean, a lot of
people I'm sure say about New York, but I do feel much more at home and then mountains where it's
very quiet and kind of sedate and your time is your own when you're off. What possessions do you
value? I mean, I know you have some textbooks and things, but I mean, your home is very modest.
Obviously, by the standards of someone living in the United States, it would not really you
wouldn't even really call it a home in the same way. Right. But you don't give the impression that
you're wanting. No, I really don't. I think that was my character since I was a kid. I'm very much
I think I'm very much a minimalist since I was born. All these clothes you see me wearing that
from the well the socks, the trousers, both these shirts I bought when I came out of Newville last
month. So I have scrubs. I had scrubs. I won pair of trousers. I had a suit, a few t shirts,
and that was it. And they're like, Hey, look, you got to go and meet people. You can't be wearing
scrubs around. So I had to buy all this crap when I came out. It was painful for me to buy clothes.
Like I don't I just don't like it. When I go back, I said, Look, when I go back to mountains,
all this is winter coats and this stuff. I'm not taking this stuff back with me. I'll keep it in
Armenia. Let someone there use it. I don't know. I don't want it. My suit. I do have one suit.
That I wore to the ceremony in Armenia, the world prize ceremony. But I bought that suit in 1985.
So I haven't. I haven't bought one since then.
Probably when you were interviewing for medical school or something.
Well, I was interviewing for jobs like for engineering jobs. That's the reason I bought it.
So it was when I had someone who was for interviewing for medical school. And then
I've used it when I come out for this sort of prize ceremony, I'll take it out and
see what the blue shirt and the tie. But a ball of crap in 1985.
And I know that you it's absolutely against your nature to sort of be critical of
anyone. But do you spend any time thinking about the way the world works here and how most of us
are somewhat attached to our possessions? Yeah. And the more possessions we have,
the more complicated our lives get. I mean, you certainly hear people talk about minimalism.
Few people can apply it to the extent that you can, of course. But
I mean, what have you learned about this and how could you speak to somebody like me who,
you know, loves his possessions as much as the next person and can't imagine
giving up these comforts? I mean, help me understand, because you don't look like you're
miserable. No. And you look even happier in these videos in Nuba. I'm sure that this is about the
hardest thing you've had to do all year. Yeah, it is. You've slept around New York and talk to idiots
like me. No, I'll tell you, Peter, I really do believe that the more detached you become,
not like in this Buddhist kind of nirvana sense, but the more detached you are from things,
the easier life is. It just simplifies your life. I mean, for me, I look at a lot of possessions
and things and attachments as just adding more complications. You know, life becomes so
complicated. It's much harder here in the US. I see my sister and how she's interacting with the
kids. There's a reason why advertisers are good at what they do. What they want to do is convince
you to buy something you really don't need, and they're very good at it. Why does Madison Avenue
exist? Why is there a huge bill in Madison Avenue? These guys are very good with what they do.
They're convincing. They've managed to convince all of us to get things we really don't need
and convince us that we'll be only happy and fulfilled and satisfied if we have those things.
So you get all this tsunami pushing against you. For me, I think just because I'm in a place where
you can't have anything that kind of realize, well, geez, I don't have any of this stuff and I kind
of like it. It just makes things much easier for me. I've always been a bit of a minimalist even
when I was younger, but I've come to kind of feel that that's really, I do feel better with less.
And I think everybody is looking for some kind of meaning in life, you know, this book, this man's
search for meaning, this Victor Frank, that was something that was one of my, is one of my favorite
books. And it's like the of logotherapy. But we all really do need a sense of meaning in our lives.
That's extremely important for our psychiatric makeup. Whatever that is, it's different for
each person, whether it's kids, whether it's your pets, whether it's your job, but to try to get
something in your life that's meaningful. And if you're looking for it, this is me philosophizing,
certainly I think if you're looking for in material possessions, I don't think you'll find it there.
So if I can make a bit of an aside, something I talked about earlier with a talk with the
Catholic Medical Mission Board volunteers, my favorite Bible passage, I can't remember the book
and the verses, but the basic story is there's a guy, the guy's a very wealthy young man. And he
goes to Jesus, they says, they try to justify himself and says, look, what do I have to do
to get eternal life? And Jesus says, well, follow the prophets, you've got all this stuff there,
follow the Ten Commandments, follow the laws of the prophets, and you'll be okay. And the guy says,
well, I do all those things. What do I need to do to really become perfect? And Christ said,
sell everything you have, pick up your cross and follow me. And it says something very, which I
think is very beautiful, it says the man went away very sad because he had many possessions.
He couldn't do it. I think he wanted to justify himself, see, I'm good, I'm doing all the things
I need to do, I should be okay. And Christ kind of turned that on his head and said, okay,
if you want to be perfect, sell everything you have and come and follow me. And I think what he's
saying is, look, if you really want to be perfect, really want to be happy, get rid of, I mean,
it's a bit of pie in the sky stuff in a way, and not practical for people. But in some way, get
rid of your baggage and come and follow. Yeah, because it could be metaphorically get rid of
your stuff. Right. I don't think it's necessarily literal, right? It doesn't mean throw your couches
out. But it can be, it means don't be wed to these things the way that I think we are. Exactly. And
the theological meaning is exactly that. It's not that you can't have things, but what's your
attachment to those things? You know, is this thing where you put your values, you know, is your value
in the car you drive and the, what kind of beer you drink or whatever, or is your value more in
people and what you're doing and how you're helping people. There is a bit of values in that. And I
think I'm sure some people can do it very well. They're very wealthy. They have a lot of stuff,
but they're, they do have a sense of detachment from that. I just think it's more difficult.
You know, it talks about this passage about it's more difficult for rich men to enter the kingdom
of heaven than it is for a camel to go through the eye of the needle. That's kind of something
you say, well, I have the needle, it's supposedly where the camels were and to keep them out of the
city. They had a thing that looked like an eye of an eagle and the camel couldn't go through there.
It's not saying being rich is bad. Rich people are bad people. That's totally, that's nothing
that's missing the point. It's just very difficult because it's very difficult to be detached from
things when you have a lot of possessions. You know, I'm trying to say that without coming across
as being judgmental. I don't mean that, but certainly for me, I feel much better having less.
I really, really think that. Well, it's funny at the outset you talked about this idea that
even in college you were sort of struck by this idea of you wanted to be a missionary and you even
said something to the effect of whatever that meant. And it's sort of funny. Like if you say
to me, Peter, picture a missionary, I don't actually picture you. I picture someone going
into a remote part of the world and hitting people with Bibles. Right? Like that's sort
of the image we have of a missionary, but in the reality of it, I think what you're doing is far
more aligned with in as much as one believes in sort of religious values, I guess I think what
people like you do that is regardless of one's religious views, they can't help but respect it is
you're not preaching it to anybody. You're not hitting anybody over the head of the Bible. You're
just sort of saying, look, I'm here to serve you. And your example is what's actually doing the
talking as opposed to your words. Whereas I think most of us, myself included, are far too quick to
use our words to speak as opposed to our actions. Well, you're tapping into my favorite quote,
which has been attributed to Saint Francis. I don't know if he, Saint Francis is like many
people. He's my favorite Saint, a friend of Assisi who lived in the 12 early 1200s. He said, preach
always and sometimes use words. And I think that's, that's exactly what I think we try to do a mission,
show the love of Christ by who you are and what you're doing, and don't, don't get too wrapped
around the axle about how it's going to play out. Remember, if you're there as a missionary, you know,
God is the one that changes hearts. Not me. I'm not smart enough to do that. I don't have the,
I'm not a guy that's going to have just the right thing to say and to, you know, school somebody on
something. I can't do that, you know, but I can do my best to show the love of Christ to these people.
And that's what I feel comfortable with. You know, if you ask me why I'm a Christian, I can,
I can talk to you about it. And my words might be a bit jumbled and goofy, but preach always and
sometimes use words. Are there any cases of suicide in Nuba? We had one guy who's the husband
of one of our staff and yeah, he shot himself and that really shocked everybody. He, he seemed to
have some kind of psychiatric problem. He was kind of acting a bit strange a few days. They didn't
tell us, but he, he'd been in one of the, in one of the refugee camps, was acting a bit odd there,
came back to Nuba and was acting a bit odd at home. And then, then he was acting a bit odd. He
went and he shot himself as the only case I know of. It's, it's extremely rare, extremely rare.
I mean, to me, there are so many amazing contrasts between Nuba and America, right? I mean,
they're so obvious, they're not worth stating. It's these subtle ones that to me are interesting,
right? There must be a different sense of fulfillment, contentment, happiness, sense of
purpose there versus here. I mean, as you know, I'm sure you're not paying close attention to
statistics in the United States, but suicide is among the top 10 causes of death in every,
I may be incorrect on this, but I'm not far off in every age demographic except for zero to 10.
So once you get above, you know, 10 to 20, 20 to 30, suicide is always in the top 10 as a cause
of a disease. And that doesn't include, that's what we call fast suicide. Right. When you kill
yourself immediately with a clear, but then you have all the slow suicide. So the alcohol related,
basically people that kill themselves with alcohol and drugs. Yeah. So when you include all of those,
I've heard analysis that would suggest that self-harm would be sort of top five causes of death
across the board. What does that say to you, given that you live in a world that has one,
one thousandth of the privilege and for all intents and purposes, like shouldn't everybody
be killing themselves in Nuba to avoid being ripped apart by shrapnel? Yeah. It's very
interesting. And you know, my initial thought that comes to me is that people are, when you're really
gripped in this struggle to survive, so your life is based on, you know, every day is you're just
trying to survive. When you have that sort of primal instinct of survival, you don't, your mind
doesn't drift off to other things. You don't think about so much about your life is hard, your life is
this, your life is miserable. So I think you become less inward looking. Suicide is so inward
looking, so focused on your own misery that you can't come out of it. I mean, it's such a miserable
thing. I mean, it breaks my heart when I hear about these things. It really does because I think,
man, to get to that point when you just, life is so miserable for you and you are so miserable,
you kill yourself, for me is heartbreaking. Does that break your heart more than the tragedy
that you see every day? I mean, not to compare miseries, but like what you see breaks my heart.
Maybe I'm numb. I mean, and it's not to say that I'm not heartbroken by anybody who hurts themselves,
but what you see is so staggering. Do you see this as an even greater source of tragedy?
For me, I would equate that with. The five-year-old girl who's got the shrapnel ripping her arm off.
I would. I would see, I would feel the same sense of pain and heartbreak with that. Suicide is a
similar effect where, you know, if a child dies from this kind of thing, the effect you have on
the whole family is devastating the grief. Suicide, the grief you leave behind. I think that's really
tough and that really, really breaks my heart. Not only for the person who was so miserable that they
decided to take their own life, but for the people behind it. Oh gosh. And that's terrible. Man,
I would just never wish that on anybody. And yet it's almost impossible in the United States to not
have your life touched by suicide. I think it would be very rare that someone listening to this
in America wouldn't know somebody first or secondhand who hasn't taken their life either clearly and
deliberately or sort of slowly and maybe less deliberately. Yeah. Yeah. I think it's wrapped
up in that struggle for survival. There is a will, you know, a natural will to survive. And when
you're in this kind of daily grip, even when there's, when there's not fighting just to survive
there, the amount of work it takes to get up in the morning to make food, to cultivate crops,
to keep the animals out of your garden. I mean, it's a tremendous struggle. There's a book,
I think the book is called Tribes. Sebastian Younger, have you heard of it? Yes, I've heard of it.
I would love to read it. I can give you a copy actually. I have a copy here, so I'll give it to
you as one more possession to have. Right. But he writes about how post 9-11 suicide rates went
down in New York. And he talks much more eloquently about this than I ever could, but
I guess it speaks to what you're saying, which is when there's a real struggle, when there's
something and something that can bring people together in a common goal or something that
unites people, it can presumably distract from some of that pain that can otherwise hurt us.
Right. It's interesting because I fairly recently was hearing about this PTSD and,
and I mean, how many veterans have killed themselves. That's another heartbreaking
thing. Somebody's fighting in Iraq or Afghanistan, they survival that they come back home,
they get despondent, they kill themselves. What kept them alive during the fighting was a sense
of camaraderie togetherness fighting for, you know, for common goal. I mean, no matter what you
think about warfare and the horrible things that happen in warfare, at least they have some kind
of a common bond. They come back home to the US and people are indifferent to them. Nobody pays
attention to them. They've lost their, the common bond with their, with their comrades and friends.
And what ensues is despondency. And before I know it, we had this huge rate of suicide
amongst veterans that come back. Not so much from the trauma they had during the fighting.
You know, it wasn't like flashbacks to horrible things that happened there, but the sense of
loss of any bonds, that human contact with other people, that sense of purpose has gone.
So I found that quite interesting that, that thought that's what led to this.
It just makes you wonder if there was, if there is a way to, you know, we have these dating apps
here in the United States, right? You probably don't have a lot of them in the news, but.
Well, dating, dating is totally illegal there. The word dating doesn't even exist.
And then.
How did you meet your wife?
Well, we have what she calls secret love. That's not like in a scandalous sense for anybody, but
you know, there you can't openly date somebody. You know, if somebody, like I could never be
alone with her somewhere, like just chatting out in the public, people would tell her brothers,
hey, this guy is talking to your sister. What are you gonna do about it? They come and they beat me
up. They'll beat her up. And then this big scandal and they say, Oh, co, you know, you,
guys gonna get married or what's going on here? You can't, you can't be doing this.
So you have to do it. We did it very quietly. You know, it's got that it's, it's difficult.
We got to know each other kind of on the side and.
Our marriage is normally arranged. Is that why this dating process is unnecessary?
Yeah. Traditionally they were arranged now. They're not so much arranged, but the families will
meet together. Somebody, you know, someone might show interest to somebody else. Then they have
to approach the family, but there's not really a dating. They can't go through a public dating thing.
If you, if you're interested in marrying a girl, you've got to go and approach the family right
away and say, look, I want to marry this woman. Then they have to start negotiations with Dowery
and all that kind of other sort of stuff. You can't be seen together in the public sphere.
It's just not, just totally not allowed. So not so much arranged as there's some attraction between
the two, but they have to really make them move fairly early. So they don't, you know,
where the problems, you don't really get to know the other person very well. It's really difficult.
You know, they're good and they're bad points because you, you're not really allowed to go
through that, that, that process of dating if they know somebody and all that sort of thing
and then the family. Okay. So there's definitely no Nuba version of Tinder. So, so I think where I
was going with that was in the same way that we have these dating apps, it's all, which are
basically trying to pair people, right? Similar interests at a meta level. It's, it would be
interesting if, if there would be a way to pair a void that exists here in this country and, and
for much of the civilized world, right? The avoid of purpose with a part of the world where purpose
is not lacking, but resources are lacking. And in many ways, I think that's what philanthropy
sort of tries to do. But of course the question is, it's more than just that, right? I mean,
I don't think it's just giving. I think there's more to it, right? I mean, I, I, and I was sort
of thinking about this knowing we were going to speak today that, because my daughter asked me
another question. She said, you know, she said, well, can you ask Dr. Tom, like, what could a
10 year old girl in San Diego do to help a 10 year old girl in Nuba? And I thought, and I thought,
and I thought, and I was like, I don't know. Cause it's not like you going there is going to,
you know, be a practical solution and, or even provide value. I mean, even me, even if I decided,
Tom, please, I'm going to come for a year and work at your side, I would slow you down. I mean,
I would be a waste of, like you'd spend a year just teaching me how to get out of my own way.
So how can people help? I mean, giving is of course, the most obvious you've, you've outlined
so many clear, tangible examples of where even modest resources by the standards of our
healthcare system would have profound step function changes there. Is there something else people can
do to help? Yeah. First of all, never underestimate the value of a donation to someone you trust or a
group you trust or an organization you trust the amount, the impact that has is tremendous. We can't
do anything in our work without financial resources. Beyond that, I think one is just becoming aware of
the situations somehow in this environment, trying to understand how these people, how they live,
what their lives are like, that these really are individuals that have their own thoughts and
aspirations and everything else, trying to get them into their skulls a bit and understand what
their life is like and who they are. If you have kind of a knack for advocacy or work through
governments and this kind of thing, be aware of the political situations there, advocate on behalf
of some of these people that are oppressed or having difficult lives, whether it's working in
issues of poverty or poor health, poor education, I think people have a voice to offer and people
do have an influence over governments. So government policies, government funding
is a reflection of their constituents. And I just came to realize this full well in this trip,
because some of these people say, well, the government funding, a lot of these administrative
requirements, these beneficiary organizations have become more stringent and more difficult
because governments require these things because they're accountable to their constituents.
Their constituents are saying, are you sending so much money to Africa? They're wasting it or it's
a waste of money. So to give the money out, the constituents are holding the politicians' feet
to the fire. If the constituents were a little more open and said, look, let's help out. Let's
be aware of what's going on and try to help some of these people get out of their misery so they
can eventually help themselves through education, greater health, all these sort of things that
would free the politicians up a bit to allow more resources to go out into more aid and other
things, more benefit to give them. I mean, the goal in all this stuff is eventually let these
people who are beneficiaries now stay in their own two feet, maybe in the next generation, next
go around. This cycle of aid, I mean, everybody knows the cycle of aid and dependency is a bad
thing. Great, but how do you get out of that? So what are some creative ways we can do that? But
you can't do anything without some help at this point, but geared towards getting these people
to stay in their own two feet. Talk to me about food. I heard a funny story once that, is there a
word for food in Nuba? It's like it- Gumo. So Nuba has, I don't know, like 99 different languages
amongst the Nuba people. Does everybody speak Arabic? Pretty much. Most will speak Arabic.
You speak Arabic. Yeah, I speak Arabic. Yeah, shwaya, shwaya, shwaya. My wife's language is
tira, and this came from her. The local word for food is numo. And I would say, what did you have
for supper last night? And she said, I ate food. I said, what kind of food? She said, you know, food,
what are you talking about? I ate food. I said, what kind? I said, well, I had an asita, you know.
Asita is the kind of the, it's like a cake made out of sorghum, kind of ground sorghum boiled.
I mean, it's just totally tasteless. She loves it. She said, I have to have my asita.
So for them, the word food and the asita is synonymous. There's so little variety. So little
variety of foods. So what do you eat? First of all, what did you weigh? Because you were a nose guard
in college. I've seen pictures of you. You were huge. What did you weigh in college? In college,
I was 230, and this was 1985. By the way, 230. Yeah, what did you weigh when you arrived in Kenya
in 2000? Probably around 190, I would guess. And what did you weigh by the time you got to
Nuba in 08? Then maybe 170. And I got down, I was down about 150 up until recently. Now when I've
come out for the past month, I think I've gained about 20 pounds. I was down about 150. You've
gained 20 pounds in the United States in a month. Yeah. So you were down to 150 pounds a month ago.
Yeah. Talk to me about what you eat. Well, that's the thing. I eat, but my wife makes the food
there. So is this food. What did you eat before you got married? Then I was living in the hospital
compound. So we'd have a lot of, they would send them food in from Kenya normally, like once a year
they would send food in. So usually rice, kidney beans, some kind of lentils. So we'd have that
every day. Once in a while I'd have chicken, but usually it was just kind of rice and beans kind
of stuff. So now when I got married and moved off the compound, my wife makes a cecita and she has
some sauce on top of it. So the main sauce is this okra. Okra grows pretty well. They take okra,
they dry it and they pulverize it in the powder. They mix that in with water and some other stuff.
And it makes like a really slimy sauce that you pour over the sorghum paste and it tastes about
as good as it sounds. I mean, it's really pretty bland. Where's the protein? You know, I think the
sorghum actually has a high protein level. I think it's a grain. And I'm saying that because
the people are pretty muscular. Like that's what they eat. They eat that and they'll have maybe
some sorghum porridge in the morning. And that's pretty much it for the day. And I mean a few
peanuts, they have peanuts too, but not huge numbers of peanuts. What about fruits or other
vegetables? For fruits, they're seasonal. So you can get mangoes for maybe two or three months out
of the year. You know, a mango season is there. There are tons of mangoes. Then when they're gone,
they're gone. You don't see a mango for several more months. Then there's two seasons for mangoes.
Usually, but it varies quite a bit year to year. So mangoes are there periodically.
Lemons you get for fruits. That's about it. Oranges are not there. You know, pineapples.
Are there tomatoes? Tomatoes are there for a couple months, sort of towards the end of the
rainy season. You can get tomatoes and you get some greens. They grow a few kinds of greens there
and they'll put that on top of that. Like even the tomatoes will kind of cook up a bit and then make
the okra slime to it and put that over the aceta. That's not bad actually. We'll have that
quite a bit. Or the other thing we'll have during the rainy season is milk also. Milk is only there
for a couple months. The cows will only give birth during the rainy season and therefore they're only
lactating during the rainy season. So to get milk sort of towards the end of the rainy season, those
last couple months. And since there's no refrigeration, most times we'll have it sour, sour milk. So
get milk out, let it sit for a while and become sour. That'll also decontaminate it a bit. There's
a lot of brucellosis there. And it takes the sour milk, which is kind of curdled. And you know,
I think people have had sour milk before and you pour that over the aceta, over the sorghum paste.
That just doesn't sound tasty. It's not very good. It's really, it's kind of eating like,
oh man, you know, the problem is you eat it. You're kind of hungry a bit, but there's no way
of going back for seconds. Like, it's not great. That was enough. It's kind of going to bed, you
know, or go back to work. It's like, okay, I guess I'm finished. My wife really, she does a great job
cooking with limited resources we have, but it's pretty stark. Is there a food that you particularly
looked forward to having when you knew you were coming to the United States? Yeah. Like pizza.
You're Italian, right? Yeah. So pizza, eggplant Parmesan is my favorite food in the world. So my
sister made that when I was down there. Hamburgers, I just crave cheeseburgers, like just a good
sandwich, you know, some chicken sandwich or something. Is this really nice with a good bread,
you know, this kind of stuff. You've been sick when you're there. I mean, how many times have
you had malaria? Well, I've been there 10 and a half years. So I've gotten malaria every year,
except for 2018. How bad is malaria? It sounds awful. It's pretty bad. I mean, you sometimes
you're wishing somebody comes in and just shoots you and puts you out of your misery. You're pretty
sick with it. It's worse than influenza, right? Yeah. And influenza, anybody who's actually had
the flu will attest. That's 10 days of really bad living. Yeah. Malaria is pretty miserable. I mean,
real bad headache, nausea, vomiting, you can't sleep, just high fevers, body aches, terrible
body aches. And sometimes you get a bit lucky. You take medicine, you're over it in a few days, but
you know, a lot of times it'll drag on for a month. But you don't take prophylaxis throughout the year,
just or during the rainy season, which I'm assuming is when it's endemic. Right. I don't,
I don't take prophylaxis just because of the cost. And yeah, I just don't want to take the drug. I just
want to say, okay, let me just not take it and take it once you get it. Right. Once I get it,
sometimes it'll drag on a bit longer. I mean, sometimes you get it just for a month. You take
the medicine, you feel a bit better for a couple of days. Then next evening you start feeling the
chills and shaking and the headache comes again and just like, Oh gosh, still with me. It can
really drag on for a long time. So every year you've got it every year. That was an acoma a few years
ago. Just, uh, God, it was a strange night or it started feeling sick the night before it was on
a Tuesday night and started taking, I took some oral drugs, I think a co-arctum, which is, um,
artemisinin derivative. Took that at night. I went to bed, just kind of had a kind of fitful sleep.
And then I woke up the next morning and all these staff were in my room. I have an IV in my arm and
I'm an IV quinine. Like what, what's going on here? The doctor needed treatment. That's right.
But I was really out of it. It was like 11 o'clock when I woke up and I was really,
you know, they tried to get me up in the morning, some of the staff, because I was in the operating
room day on Wednesday. And, uh, our guy, that's our assistant there. I didn't show up, you know,
for the, I was on there by seven 30 and I didn't show up. So he came up to the room. He tried to
wake me up and I couldn't get up. Like I didn't respond to him. So he thought I was dead. He was
like, Hey, like, anyway, I didn't die. So I just, uh, that was out of it for quite a while,
but then I recovered pretty quickly. I can't even imagine. I just, I can't,
when you think back, Tom, about all of the people you've taken care of in the last
10 or 11 years, so just even just limiting it to the time in Nuba, is there any one particular
patient that just stays with you that haunts you one case, one story, one child, one adult? I mean,
I have those stories. I've got one or two, three, probably three stories that have stayed with me
from my training, right? That if I even think about these patients, I'll tear up. I mean, just,
you know, they're, unfortunately they're all bad outcomes as the ones that, but they're also,
they're not like the only bad outcomes I've seen, but there's just some, there was some emotional
connection that happened. And then it's maybe it's sometimes you're projecting what's happening
there onto your own life or something. But do you have those cases? Yeah, probably like you,
the ones you really remember are the ones that have bad outcomes or ones that didn't go well.
Gosh, we had one kid, I remember he came in on a Sunday morning and he had been, the Antonov
bombed in the shrapnel wet in his face and just tore his face to shreds. And he went to some clinic
somewhere and they put a few stitches in it, like chromic stitches. And he came a couple days after
that and his face was just mangled. So we took the stitches out and it was all just pus and dirt
coming out. I mean, just didn't, but cleaned the wound out. So we took all these stitches out,
cleaned the wound out well, put them on antibiotics. A couple of days later, we go on, he's got high
fever and he can't swallow. I'm like, no crap. He's got, he's got tetanus. So a kid gets tetanus.
I remember the day before then, I remember the Antonov came overhead, the Antonov is the airplane
that bombs. And we saw the kid, he was like a, maybe 10 years old. He was standing against the
wall, just shivering when he heard the airplane just shaking. He was so traumatized. He was so
traumatized. He was shaking like this. Then like the next day, he gets a real high fever. He can't
swallow. He put him in isolation, put NG2 down to feed him. And he just died from tetanus,
like overnight. He died from tetanus. And I remember this kid's face and how, and I said,
what the heck? He was a 10 year old kid with this thing. We had another kid, this is in
child youth, this was a few years ago. He was, he was bombed, he and his aunt, and it was an
incendiary bomb from Antonov. And I don't know what they had, napalm or whatever, but it bombed him.
And just, he had, I don't know, he had third degree burns on probably 60, 70% of his body.
Is that even survivable?
No, he lived like two months with this and both he and his aunt were the same. And I mean,
we tried everything with these kids, the amount of work the nurses did every day just to try to
address him and the agony he went through before he died. I remember his aunt would have these
scabs and I remember they were, her eye was burned with this thing. And I remember there
were maggots coming out of her eye, you know? And I think, what the heck are we doing? This is crazy.
What, who are these? These are civilians, burn to death, you know? There were other, six other kids
that were in an area that was being shelled. So they sit in and would shell their village
like all night and then they were bombed during the day. So they were, at nighttime,
they would sleep in the foxholes for protection. So right next to them was a straw,
rakuba, kind of a straw structure. So the artillery shell fired and hit the rakuba,
thing burst, rakuba was just like a, kind of lean to with made of grass and wood. It set this thing
on fire and it fell into the foxhole. And there were, I think, nine people in the foxhole all
sleeping. Three were burned to death immediately. Six of them came to the hospital with very degrees
of burns. And a couple were just like 80% full thickness burns. I mean, just, they lived for
quite a while before they died. Two of them, one girl started improving. They developed tetanus and
died from the tetanus. So these are the ones that really kind of stick out. Maybe one of the soldiers
I remember best is a guy that he was guy that I told you before he had 23 or four holes in his
intestines. We opened them up and we just, I mean, it's hours we operate in this guy. Post-op,
he was doing great. I mean, it was cruising and started feeding him. He sat in bed. The next time
I called down to see him, he's changed condition, as they say. And I went down and he's already dead.
He was a Darfur. He was fighting with the Nuba rebels. And I just remember thinking, you know,
what would this like for his, like this guy's got a family, you know, he's fighting in this place.
His family's somewhere in Darfur. What's happening? Do they have any idea what's happening here?
So many terrible things, you know, there was one young kid, he was about 16 and he,
the Sudan army was approaching in our area. So the rebels went out there to kind of repulse them.
And then people just kind of jumped on the vehicles to go out and fight, you know. So this kid just
jumped on the vehicle. He didn't have a gun. They were weaponing everything. He was just a civilian.
He goes out there. He gets shot in the head with, you know, a machine gun or something. He comes in
with, you know, part of his skull missing and his brain tissue kind of pulsating out. I mean, he
survived for two or three weeks like that. We have steroids and different things. In about
X try to count things down and ended up just kind of going south and dying. So these are all,
all people I'll never forget. And there are many, many, many beyond that.
If people want to get involved in any way, shape or form, where would you recommend they,
they look to as a resource? I think like an African mission, healthcare foundation,
there was something on their website about the hospital. That's one source to go to.
And their website is?
It's amhf.us, www.amhf.us. So that's a pretty good source to start. There's a group called
Take Heart Foundation, which was set up to kind of to harness the whatever support to be through
the Heart of Nuba movie, which was made by my friend Ken Carlson.
Which I recommend everybody watch it. I think it's a, I'm sure it was done on a shoestring budget,
but it's so well done. You know, it just sort of speaks for itself. So anything raised through
them goes to African mission healthcare, which comes to us without anything taken out.
Catholic Medical Mission Board is another good source. That's my, they're my sponsoring
organization. They're here in New York. They've been here for I think over a hundred years.
And there are cmmb.org I think is their website. These are probably the main sources for our work
in Nuba. You know, I'll close with a story, Tom, that I think in many ways kind of defines you.
I remember when I decided I wanted to go to medical school, I was applying for this
scholarship and in the end I didn't get the scholarship. But I remember during the interview,
this guy asked me a question. He said, you know, what do you want to be at the time when I went to
medical school, I wanted to be a pediatric oncologist. And I know what the guy was doing
in retrospect. I mean, I think he was just trying to push me. And he basically said like, why would
you want to do that? You can't possibly make a difference, you know, without dedicating your
life to research, you're not going to have a difference saving one kid's life at a time,
et cetera, et cetera. And, you know, I remember thinking of a story after, which in many ways
exemplifies you to an extent that probably no one else, which is, you know, in medicine,
you can do two things, right? You can, you can do something very scalable through research.
You know, you can devote yourself to working on, you know, treatments for cancer or developing
a new drug to treat this disease or that disease. Or you can be on the front lines trying to save
one life at a time. So the story is there's these two guys walking down the beach and it's after a
really high tide and the beach is covered in starfish. And the starfish are going to die pretty soon
if they don't get back in the water, which means they're pretty much all going to die. The two guys
are walking and every few steps, one of the guys bends down as he picks up a starfish and he throws
it back in the water. Five steps later, he does it again and again and again. After like the 10th
one, the one guy says to him, he goes, what are you doing? And he says, well, you know, if these
starfish don't get back in the water, you know, they're going to die. And he goes, have you looked
and seen how many of them there are? You can't possibly make a difference. And he throws another
one in the water and he says, well, it made a difference to that one. Right. And I think for
doctors that don't have the privilege of being able to affect the larger through research or
policy changes, whatever, for people on the front lines, I don't think there's a human being on this
planet who throws more starfish back in the water than you. In the end, medicine is individual. It's
the beauty of our profession and it's a huge privilege to have the opportunity to affect
one person. And in the end, you close the door and it's you and the patient, whether you're in
Nuba mountains, whether you're here in New York, and that's an incredible privilege. And I think
if we keep that focus just one person at a time, I think people can kind of relax a bit. You can
see that what you're doing for that one person. You know, I think people look at Africa and say,
you know, what you're doing is a drop in the ocean. I really like that story because when you're there,
you don't see a drop in the ocean. You see a person. You see a life one at a time. You see a
life and you see somebody that can laugh and can cry and can play and can, you know, has aspirations
and is a living, breathing human being. Think, man, we helped this one person. That's a huge thing,
you know? And I think that helps to stave off some of the burnout and the cynicism.
The fact that you are, this is a very individual thing. So one person is really a big deal. It's
everything to that one person, that one person's family. And I think we really have to keep that
in mind, especially with this growing realm of cynicism and sort of negativity that we see now.
Tom, I have been wanting to meet you for three years. I didn't know that I'd ever get a chance
to. So it's sort of beyond a privilege. And I know that for you, being outside of Nuba is
the toughest thing imaginable, which is of course the irony sitting here in the
plush New York City. And yet all you're doing is pining to go back to a place where your own life
is in danger. But, you know, I remember thinking, God, I really just, I'd love to be able to
interview Tom. And I remember thinking there's no way he could justify making the time to do this
when his time in the US is so short. So when I asked Rick and Mark and John, and they said that
Tom would be happy to sit down, I just, I couldn't believe it. And I might make the case
that of all the interviews I've ever done or will do, this is the one I feel most privileged to.
So thank you. Thank you so much. Yeah. Thanks, Peter. This has been a real privilege for me to
be here with you. And thanks for giving us the platform to spread the word of it. Thank you so
much. You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode. You can also find
my blog at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively
non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting
papers I've read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.