Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives.
Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast,
that became clear to me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming.
I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information
with you. To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a
full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and their feedback has mirrored this.
So all of this raises a natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support
this? As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of
contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most
important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something
when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason
selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time
advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about
something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads,
I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can work over time, and that is to create
a subscriber support model for my audience. This keeps my relationship with you both simple and
honest. If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and support us at whatever level works
for you. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that
simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get
back more than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show
notes, including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts
for each episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature
of many of our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular
Ask Me Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also
getting to hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited
about, I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said,
we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies
who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them
pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of
you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive
for members to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a
moment to listen to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please
consider supporting us directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Dr.
Jake Kushner, a close friend and a pediatric endocrinologist who specializes in helping manage
people with type 1 diabetes. In this episode, we go into great detail about type 1 diabetes. Probably
the biggest takeaway from this episode is that diet can help people not only with type 2 diabetes,
but also type 1. Jake discusses some of the recent findings in an approach that one of the pioneers
in this field, Dr. Richard Bernstein, championed for several decades now, managing carbohydrates
and protein to manage insulin and glucose. And if you're thinking, well, I don't have type 1 diabetes,
why does this matter to me? The answer is anybody with a pancreas is going to benefit from this.
And obviously those without a pancreas, which is effectively what is happening in type 1 diabetes.
We also discuss why many patients who control their blood sugar with high amounts of exogenous
insulin are at substantially higher risk than people who can control their blood sugar at lower
levels of insulin. This concept also has implications for everyone else, as I said,
because the word exogenous and endogenous can be interchanged quite easily when it comes to insulin.
We cover some of the basics, the history, the increasing prevalence of type 1 diabetes,
and more importantly, what we can do to help kids with this disease and their families and the non
diabetics out there learn from them and their disease. So without further delay, here's my
conversation with Jake Kushner. Hey Jake, thanks for coming over, man. Hey Peter, thanks for having
me. It's a pleasure. What do you think is the probability we will get through this
discussion today without one of my kids barreling into this room? Absolutely zero, especially given
that I met both of them and they're incredibly rambunctious and cute. Well, you met two boys,
but there's a girl too. She's much more well behaved. So you're in town, I guess we can't
talk about it, it's black ops mission, right? No, it's actually, so I'm an advisory council
for Sanofi and I've been an advisor about this drug, Sotycophilosin, which is part of a new
class of drugs that will hopefully benefit people with type 1 diabetes, these adjuvant therapies,
molecules that you take in addition to insulin. I've been involved in this program now for close
to seven years. And I know off mic, we've spoken a little bit about some of those compounds. They're
super interesting, not just for type 1 diabetes, but potentially type 2 diabetes. And frankly,
if you subscribe to the idea that lower levels of glucose and insulin are just better overall,
there may even be other applications. So before we get into that, we met, it's been three or four
years now, right? We met in Houston over dinner one night. And I gave you credit for this recently
on a podcast that hasn't yet released, but it will release. It was actually you who first told me
about CGM, although it was officially Kevin Sayre at Dexcom that got me fully hooked. So,
whenever I'm talking to somebody and they ask me about a question that has to do with type 1
diabetes, I generally say, I know very little about this condition, but you should meet
Jay Kushner because not only does he get it, but I think his outcomes are pretty unique. I think
we're seeing more people move towards the realization that you and people who think like you have.
So you're a pediatric endocrinologist. Did you always know you wanted to do that?
Well, I was trying to decide in between being a pediatrician and being a molecular biologist.
And my parents are basic scientists. And there was a well-worn path in between
molecular biology and endocrinology. So that was a really typical thing back in the mid 80s.
And I thought I would do that. And the classical path as an endocrinologist is to go and find a
rare disorder and discover the molecular basis for it and find some unique product that you could
then replace and provide it. And then you're good to go. And there's a lot of endocrinologists who
made quite a bit of hay on that paradigm. And so I was also interested in pediatrics. I was trying
to decide between all these things when I was an undergraduate at Berkeley and working pretty much
continuously in basic science research labs all the way through Berkeley and then for several years
afterwards as a research technician, first at UCSF and then Oregon. So I applied to medical school
and I get in and I think I'm going to be a pediatrician. And my mother was greatly disappointed
that I didn't become a basic scientist. She viewed science as much more compelling than
becoming a pediatrician. Or any doctor for that matter, right? I mean, there could be no greater
letdown to scientific parents that you would show something as low as medicine. And I was literally
the only kid in medical school whose mother was disappointed that I didn't end up going
to graduate school. It makes you feel any better. My dad was very disappointed that I went to medical
school too. I found myself there. I thought I was going to be a pediatrician. I did my clinical
rotations and it totally reinforced it. And I just love being on the wards and interacting with kids.
And then ended up as a pediatric resident at Brown and had again, I worked in molecular
endocrinology as a researcher before I went to medical school and was enamored by endocrinology
in general. And I applied and got into this program at Boston Children. So there I was in
this incredibly busy, rigorous, unbelievably complicated place. And that's when this crazy
thing happened in my life. And so I thought I was going to find some esoteric metabolic disease to
work on. And you were at the right place to do it because for the folks listening who might not know
this, there are probably what four major pediatric centers in North America, Boston Children's,
obviously in Boston, SickKids in Toronto, CHOP in Philly, and maybe Texas Children's. Would that
be in the top four? Yeah, and UCSF. That's right. Would UCSF actually make the top five? At the
time it did. Okay. Incredibly strong. So I sort of thought I would do this and I'd find some
esoteric disease, like maybe work on calcium or, you know, but as a first year endocrine fellow,
we're running around an incredibly busy service and we're interacting with families of children
who are newly diagnosed. And it's such a compelling with type one diabetes and it's so compelling. So
we would take call, the ER would call us, oh, there's a child who's been diagnosed. We come
in the next morning and meet these families. And, you know, there's a tearful, exhausted,
overwhelmed mother. There's a kid who literally looks like she's been like shot out of a cannon,
you know, with multiple IVs and scars in her, in her arms from blown IVs. And
we'd have to try to work through this idea that they were going to be insulin dependent for life.
And I just thought, wow, this is really an amazing and challenging problem. And it has so many aspects
of medicine that I appreciate as most importantly, human elements, but there's also basic science.
The diagnosis is, I mean, I had one experience with this before I got to medical school, which
was in college. I had a really good friend. I guess I won't use her name just in case I need
to protect her identity. And she was amazing. She was my lab partner. We're just great, great
buddies. She was a stud athlete. She was on the rowing team. She was like the perfect physical
specimen of, you know, and we used to sit together and we were in two classes together. And she
was like maybe four or five months into that school year and she couldn't stay awake anymore.
She was like falling asleep in class constantly. And I remember sort of nudging her and being like,
hey, you're burning it too much. Like the practices are killing you and the labs and blah,
blah, blah, blah. Like you got to get this shit under control. And she's like, no, no, no, I'm
fine. I'm fine. I'm fine. And she just couldn't stay awake to save her life. And she was losing
weight like crazy and she was lean to begin with. So she was, you know, probably six feet tall
and might've weighed 140 was her fighting weight. And, you know, she was now down to 125 or something
like that. And of course she was going to the bathroom all the time. And of course I'm just a
dumb engineer. I don't know anything. I don't realize this is such an obvious, you know, sign
of somebody who's going to be in a medical school and you can't die. But it's really difficult for
everybody. This was an undergrad before I even knew I wanted to go into medicine. But yeah, sure
enough, she comes back one day with, and she's like, Oh my God, you're not going to believe this.
I finally went to the doctor and all of a sudden for the rest of school, she takes insulin. And for
the rest of her life. And these are previously healthy people. They're cruising around,
living their lives. There's nothing obvious that contributes to the risk. And then they start
drinking a lot and peeing a lot and they lose weight. And they essentially are in a state of
profound catabolism and their bodies waste away because insulin is such a really pivotal signal
for directionality on metabolism. And they decide to break it down. And it's amazing. It beguiles
everyone who's up there close, there are so many misdiagnoses around type one diabetes,
about 30% of children still present with DKA. That is to say they've had prolonged illness and
no one's thought that they could actually be quite ill. So when, to be clear, when they present with
diabetic ketoacidosis, it means that they have somehow managed to slip through the cracks.
Nobody's figured out that their glucose level is through the roof or that they're becoming
acidotic or any of these other things. And what actually brings them into the hospital is a
septic like situation where their blood pressure is falling and they're becoming unresponsive.
They hit the metabolic wall. And at that point, they're only on this earth for a matter of days
or a week or two without insulin. And it's quite common for very young children to present in DKA.
It's less common in older people. They typically have more compensatory reserves. So they have
the autoimmunity proceeds at a slower rate as you get older. And so the diagnosis becomes more and
more confusing the older the onset of the disease. And this phenomenon actually progresses into
adulthood to the point where there are people our age who are diagnosed with diabetes,
not otherwise specified, who think they have type two and they're skinny, but in fact have
cryptic type one diabetes. They probably have autoimmune antibodies and they have some degree
of a loss of beta cells. And this phenomenon explains some of the adult onset diabetes that
you just don't quite understand. How is this person diabetic? And so fast forward a few years
from where I am and I want to come back to where you were, but by the time I'm in medical school,
I had only been exposed to people who had type one diabetes, which is ironic given the prevalence
difference between type one and type two. And I remember in a pathology class in my first year,
they said, well, you know, I forget what the number was at the time, but they said about 95%
of the cases of diabetes are what we call type two or adult onset diabetes. And I remember
thinking to myself, the professor must have made a mistake. I've never seen this type two diabetes
thing they talk about, but I've seen a lot of people, not just that friend in school, but I
went on to see other people and knew of other people though I didn't watch them through the
diagnosis. So what is the prevalence today? Notwithstanding this late onset type one diabetes
that we'll come and talk about later, but just directionally, how many people in the United
States have type one versus type two or indeterminate? Okay. So type one is approximately one
in 300 people in the typical age of onset is around nine and they live into adulthood and,
and many survive into their eighties or even nineties. They have, of course, reduced survival
because of complications, but it's an incredibly common illness. It's the most common life
threatening medication requiring illness of childhood. Yeah. Which is amazing when you go
back to where you were at Boston children's hospital. I'm sure for any pediatric endocrinologist
to be working on glycogen storage diseases or inborn areas of metabolism is interesting
intellectually, but the scale upon which those diseases afflict children is trivial compared
to what you just described. And when you're working in a fancy medical school, it's quite
sort of tempting to focus on a rare, unique condition that most people don't get a lot of
exposure to and sort of bypass the really common things. But for me, type one diabetes was the
elephant in the room. It was just so compelling. And I ended up being the first clinical fellow
at Boston children's in 10 years to go into type one diabetes. Were any of your mentors there
disappointed in the way that your mom was that you were sort of, and I want to say slumming it,
because I don't mean to suggest that that's what it was, but that you were stepping off the pedestal
of the esteemed academic institution. No, I ended up working on type one diabetes at the
Jawsland Diabetes Center, which was an amazing place. And there was also in Boston, also in
Boston. There was a long August tradition of academics there. They were a little surprised
that I was interested in going after such a tough problem. And again, clinically, type one diabetes
is an immense problem as we'll get into because the clinical treatments are just so difficult and
ineffective and variable in their response. So let's talk a little bit about the pathophysiology
of this. Presumably people listening to this who already know everything about it and want to get
to the fun stuff, we'll skip this. We'll timestamp it so they can jump ahead. But I think it is worth
understanding because there's definitely some confusion. You obviously alluded to the fact that
this has an autoimmune component, if not the main component. So what based on everything we know today
is the pathophysiology of this condition? Okay. Well, I guess we could say just from a very high
level, there are clearly genetic as well as environmental contributors. And so we know that
it runs in families and we know that certain regions or certain behaviors predispose. But
if you actually get down to the molecular pathophysiology, what you see is that it's an
autoimmune condition, largely driven by T cells. But there is also a contribution of B cells. And
because of that, you can detect antibodies in the serum that indicate autoimmunity. And so we
generally believe what happens is by some combination of bad luck and possibly genetics and
possibly the foods you eat to a very, very modest degree, this stochastic phenomenon begins to move
forward whereby the beta cell, which secretes insulin, begins to dump off antigens and the
antigens begin to provoke the immune system locally. And some of those immune cells start
to destroy beta cells and dump out more antigens. So let me take a step back for the listener. The
pancreas of course is this gland that sits in the retroperitoneum. So it's not in the abdomen proper,
but it's behind the stomach. And about 95% of the pancreas by mass serves this exocrine function,
which is it's mostly there for local digestion. It puts enzymes into the biliary stream that
ultimately aid in the proximate digestion of things coming out of the stomach. However,
about 5% of the pancreas by mass, including these cells called beta cells, but presumably you'll
tell us a little bit about alpha and delta cells. It's an endocrine organ versus an exocrine organ,
which means it's secreting systemic hormones into the system. So I remember learning that in medical
school and being surprised because I'd heard so much about beta cells. And I was like, wait,
they only make up 5% of this pancreas? Like there are relatively small contribution to this enormous
organ, right? And essentially insulin is only made there, except perhaps in tiny quantities in the
brain. And so the, yes, these islands of cells, these islets of Langerhans exist floating in a sea of
the acinar or exocrine component. And they make insulin uniquely unlike any other tissue. And
perhaps because they make these unique antigens or these unique cellular products like insulin
and some of the other apparatus that are required for glucose stimulated insulin secretion,
when they begin to dump off their antigens and provoke autoimmunity, you can get this sort of
death spiral where ultimately the end result is a progressive autoimmunity where you lose beta cells
over time. And I don't think that there's any one single, for instance, virus that can be
conclusively ascribed to autoimmunity and type one diabetes. It's clearly not related to,
directly related to your BMI or your body mass index or your body weight, though it's certainly
a contributor and also genetics. Which way does it seem to contribute, high or low?
In populations, again, it doesn't hold up in individuals very well, but in populations,
the heavier you are, the more likely you are to have type one, which implies either that the work
of the beta cells contributing to the autoimmunity or alternatively, the work of the beta cell and
the relative beta cell insufficiency reveals this autoimmunity that otherwise would have been cryptic.
We've seen a rise in the incidence and of course, then the prevalence of type two diabetes. That's
very difficult to ignore and I've written about that in other places and you can chase that all
the way back to the late 1800s and it tracks pretty well. What has been the relative change
in the incidence of type one diabetes? It's doubled since 1960 and it appears to be continuing to
increase. And so one possibility is that there are these environmental factors that are increasing,
for instance, obesity. Alternatively, there could be viruses or other things that we're exposed to
and another possibility is that we're simply better at diagnosing it. So we know for a fact
that some infants that are diagnosed now with nuance at diabetes would have been the kids who
you thought had died of sepsis back when you were in medical school. So we have a greater awareness
that this autoimmunity can happen to kids as early as five or six months of life. And at that point,
they don't present with the classical signs and symptoms. It's really incredibly aggressive.
They look like they have gastroenteritis and weight loss. And if nobody bothers to check a serum
glucose, you might never know that they in fact have life-threatening diabetic ketoacidosis and
nuance at type one diabetes. It's a disaster. I suspect it was because I knew we were going to
be speaking today, but last night when I was putting my littlest guy to bed who's about 16,
17 months old, I remember I was looking at him and I was playing with him and I'm biased. So I
think he's as cute as all hell. And I remember thinking, what would happen if this guy got type
one diabetes? How would we figure it out? How long would it take us to figure out, oh my God,
check his glucose? And it scared me actually, because it's like, I think about this stuff
night and day. And I realized it would easily escape me for a long time. And to your point,
they don't have the reserve. They don't have the physiologic reserve, which is just doctors speak
for they don't have the buffer between life and death that you or I would have.
And actually might have much more aggressive autoimmunity.
Meaning it comes on quicker. The rate of decline of endogenous insulin production is much faster.
Yeah. They might present with 90% of their beta cells gone because the autoimmune destruction
from 100% of their beta cell capacity to 10% could occur in a matter of months. Almost by
definition must in a kid who's six months old. But if I'm 53, if I got type one diabetes,
I could smolder along for years. And again, I have a friend who's my age, who is essentially
my height and weight. And he has new onset diabetes. And we think he actually has cryptic
type one and it's slowly smoldering. It seems to be slowly progressing. It's been very difficult
to precisely make the diagnosis. And I want to come back to that in time for at least one reason,
which is for people out there listening, there are people getting caught between these crosshairs
that are potentially being misdiagnosed outside of the intellectual exercise of getting it right,
which we love to do as doctors. Are there treatment implications that are more relevant? In other
words, if you have someone who's walking around with quote unquote type two diabetes, but they're
really late onset type one, are we also potentially caring for them incorrectly? So I'll park that
because there's so much I want to go back to in type one, but between the two of us, let's try
to remember to come back to that. So I didn't actually realize the B cells played a big role,
but I guess that makes sense. So I thought it was just a CD4, CD8, CD25 problem, but it's beyond that.
Yeah, there's this idea of an antigenic spread. So again, if the beta cells make very unique things,
and when you break them open and destroy them, you begin to dump them out. There is both a B
and a T cell response. And we know this because we can test for antibodies in the serum of people
with type one diabetes, and they make unique antibodies against insulin and GAD, glutamic
acid decarboxylase, as well as a protein tyrosine phosphatase called ICA-512. And so
those antibodies are commonly used in the diagnosis of type one diabetes, which we believe
to be a T cell disease. But again, that doesn't make any sense because antibodies are made by B
cells. So there must be some contribution in the definitive proof of that was in a New England
Journal article that was done by my friend, Mark Peskowitz. And he used in a huge clinical trial,
Rituximab, which alters B cell function, alters the ability of the B cells to make antibodies,
and they were able to delay the course of type one diabetes. So they were able to intervene in
a subset of patients that were progressing slowly enough. They presented with positive GAD antibodies,
but they still had beta cell production. You whack them with Rituximab, you at least take
the B cell component out of this. And if the control patient isn't having that, you now create
a Kaplan-Meier curve for a beta cell. That's right. That's right. And so they were only temporarily
able to alter. How much did they delay the onset? So Rituximab is quite potent. So the circulating
antibodies were reduced dramatically. They only gave a single set of infusions. And if I understand
remember this study correctly, they got a response, but it was not statistically significant at a year.
Based on one single dose. I'm not sure about that.
We'll pull it up. Yeah. Okay. Are there any other autoimmune diseases that share this phenomenon
that you're aware of where you have this B cell T cell component? Well, I think it's true of a
bunch of the other autoimmune endocrine disorders, such as, for instance, autoimmune thyroid disease,
where you can get thyroid peroxidase and thyroglobulin antibodies. And again, we largely
think that that's a T cell mediated disease. And by the way, autoimmune thyroid disease is
associated with type 1 diabetes or vice versa. Meaning patients who will go on earlier in life
to develop type 1 diabetes would be much more likely than patients without it to go on to get
Graves disease or some of the other autoimmune thyroid disorders. Yeah. Typically type 1 would
present first and then they can get autoimmune thyroid disease, but they can also get adrenal
disease. And we also see, for instance, rarely, sialitis, which is autoimmune disease of the
salivary gland and even rarely autoimmune oophritis of the ovaries, as well as pernicious
anemia, the ability to produce B12. And so that's presumably an autoimmune disease of the cells that
make B12. Wow. I didn't actually realize that there was so much overlap between these. Let's
clarify one other thing that I'm sure someone's wondering. One thing that parents I think are
pretty mindful of is what do we have to feed our kids to minimize the risk of them getting
anaphylactic reactions to nuts or things like that, given the consequences of such things.
Not to get off into the weeds, but it's probably worth explaining why that's a completely different
process than what we're talking about with the autoimmunity with respect to the endocrine. So
not to put you on the spot and I'm happy to fill in the gaps, but what is it about a kid when they
eat a peanut that leads to an anaphylactic reaction? And why is that a totally different
type of immune response? Well, I should just say in terms of anaphylactic reactions for peanuts,
it turns out that you probably want to eat peanuts to avoid the anaphylactic reaction.
That is certainly what we believe now. I think the literature has become crystal clear that early
exposure is better. But again, that's a very different type of immune response, isn't it?
Yes. That's mediated by IgE. That's a hypersensitivity more than an autoimmune
response, is that correct? Yeah. So borrowing from that though, do we believe that there are any
exposures that are withheld from kids that may be predisposing them to beta cell destruction? Or do
we think it has much more to do with these diffuse genetic issues, which I want to come back to,
these quote unquote environmental issues. And then of course, what seems to be the majority of it
seems to be stochastic. So there's no one precise thing. And moreover, I don't believe that parents
who are listening to this could say, okay, I want to make sure that my kid doesn't get type one
diabetes, so we're not going to eat any enriched carbohydrate and then we'll mitigate that risk
completely. However, that said, in populations, you can see these very subtle differences in
type one diabetes risk depending upon the body weight of children, which implies that the
standard American diet may be predisposing the population in aggregate ever so slightly
towards more type one diabetes, which is a scary thought. Yeah. The challenge of course,
is because the environmental contribution is so much smaller here than it is in type two diabetes,
we don't know if we could be looking at genetic differences that could explain that. In other
words, we can't do the experiment as easily the epidemiologic comparison, I guess, to be more
rigorous in my terminology of comparing a US population to pick a completely different
population that is genetically completely distinct and environmentally distinct. We could get fooled
by that, right? Yeah, but there is a pretty nice study using the T1D exchange data, which is a large
consortia of clinics around the United States. In fact, there's a paper that was published by Maria
Redondo and several other friends of mine describing explicitly these relationships in between
body weight and the potential risk for type one. Do you remember just directionally when a child
goes, I don't even know kid body BMIs. My little guy who you just saw who's like 97th percentile in
height weight and 95th percentile in head circumference, I was looking at his little
pediatric sheet the other day because he went to the doctor and he was like BMI of 19.4.
Kid BMIs mean, I don't know how to think in those BMIs, but I was going to say, what's the difference
between a BMI 16 and a BMI 20? How much of an increase in relative risk do you see? Pediatricians
like me never are able to memorize these things. You've got to put it on it. We have to plot it on
a chart. There's growth curves for both height and weight and head circumference and weight versus
height or also body mass index. It's just so complicated and there's different curves for
boys and girls. Yeah, yeah. Okay. Question one out of the way is, is there anything I can do or a
parent can do to reduce the risk of our kids getting type one diabetes? The answer is probably
not other than if you want the wind a little bit at your back as opposed to a little bit in your
face, if your kids can be closer to normal BMI than not. Being aware that it is a possibility
and being able to inform yourself and your neighbors and your school teacher undiagnosed
type one diabetes is very dangerous for children and we need to do a better job of detecting it
early. Yeah, with one in 300 kids getting it, that means in any given school, one to three
kids are being diagnosed a year. Which is interesting because I just don't have that
recollection, but it may speak to this issue you've talked about, which is we just underdiagnosed it.
We've talked briefly about genes, but obviously this is not going to fall in the category of
single gene mutations like the glycogen storage diseases or some of the other errors of inborn
metabolism. Do we have even a quasi sense of how heavy the genetic contribution is and what those
genes may actually do from a functional standpoint? We understand it pretty well,
and though there's still a lot to be learned. It's complicated in that there's essentially
two different themes of the genetics of type one diabetes. One are these HLA alleles, like this is
the human histocompatibility locus. There's certain alleles that are quite common in the
population that when combined place people at higher risk. There's something called HLA DR3
and DR4. These alleles tend to run quite frequently in the US population. As a result, people who
have type one diabetes typically will have about a tenfold risk of having a child with type one
diabetes relative to the general population. To be clear, is that assuming they inherit the
same HLA type or independent of the inherited pattern of their HLA? Because if you are HLA
to DR, is that a co-dominant inheritance? Is your kid 50% likely to get that assuming your
wife doesn't have that? Yeah, but what happens is it's so common that your wife may have that.
So just statistically, because children end up having it, the people who have type one diabetes
often have these alleles and also these other minor alleles that contribute each very small
amount, but in aggregate quite a bit. So the analogy I use is it's sort of like, let's play
a poker game, if you will. We're going to play a poker game where on your left hand, we're going
to play 21. And on the right hand, we're going to play five card stud. Okay? And so when you deal me,
and by the way, the winner is the one- So when you say 21, you mean Blackjack on the
right hand? Exactly. Blackjack on my left hand and five card stud on the right. And when you're
dealt the cards, you have the HLA alleles, which is Blackjack, because there's only a few and they
sort out however they sort out. And the right hand, you're playing five card stud. And in fact,
there's a huge number of combinations that could come in five card stud, but together, those two
hands determine the risk. And so it's quite complicated because you can't draw a direct line
in between one gene or a group of genes. But in aggregate, the statisticians think that
people are approximately six to tenfold at greater risk if you have somebody who has type one to have
a direct relative. And so if you're someone with type one, that's still not a reason to get
completely panicked because that means it's still unlikely your kid is going to get type one diabetes.
If you have a disease that's hitting one in 300 and you have a tenfold increase,
it's going to hit one in 30. There's still a 97% chance your child is not going to have type one
diabetes if you do, but it would have been a 99.7% chance hopefully if you hadn't if I'm doing my
math right. But there are these families, I've met them, you know, I met one family where all
three sons had type one diabetes. Oh, God. And was the age of onset comparable in each of these
children? It doesn't necessarily align. That's kind of an interesting and surprising element.
And actually, at one point cared for identical twins who were discordant for type one diabetes.
Well, I was going to ask you that. What is the twin concordance? Identical versus fraternal.
So identical twin concordance within the first few years is only around 50 or 60%.
By adulthood, what is it?
By adulthood, it's approaching 80%. So there's a big cohort that Dr. George Isenbroug studied
many years ago. So over time, those are the people that discordant genetically identical
twins are probably the people who would have, they have diabetes not otherwise specified,
but in fact, they have type one that's, that's cryptic.
And the fraternal twins, which would at least allow you to hopefully as much as possible,
normalize the environmental similarities, but somewhat reduce the genetic variability or the
genetic similarity. Do you have a rough sense of what the concordance is for those by adulthood?
I don't know the exact number, but again, I think it's they're approximately 10 fold relative to
the general population.
Got it. Wow. So let's fast forward a little bit and get back to what we talked about over dinner
in Houston a few years ago. Again, it was either three or four years ago, but it was the fall.
I remember it was definitely a fall. At that point in time, I had spent very little mental
energy thinking about type one diabetes because obviously I'm not going to take care of somebody
with type one diabetes. It's so far outside of my skillset. And so I sort of remembered a few
things because in residency, two of my co-residents had type one diabetes, which is, wow, that's
pretty unusual in a cohort because the categorical residents in general surgery for our year at Hopkins,
there were only seven of us. Right. And two of the seven had type one diabetes. And I, you know,
I talked to them a lot about it and I sort of remember directionally their target was a
hemoglobin A1c of about 7.5. And they lived on crackers and orange juice where they're sort of
staple foods to manage these bouts of hypoglycemia. And I certainly remember one of my buddies,
it wasn't uncommon if in the middle of an operation, one of the OR nurses would have to
come and put a little straw behind his mask and he would have to drink some orange juice
to sort of, you know, manage his glucose levels. And then when you and I sat down for dinner,
you said, you know, your average patient is walking around at something like 5.7, 5.8, 5.9
hemoglobin A1c. And that immediately caught me off guard because I was like, oh, that seems very
different from what I sort of remember. So how did you get from wherever presumably you finished
your training and entered your practice? I'm guessing that was sometime in the late eighties,
early nineties. I graduated from fellowship in 2000. Oh, okay. So over the last call it 15,
18 years, how did you evolve your thinking around targets for where the hemoglobin A1c,
and I guess I should take a step back and also explain for someone what the hemoglobin A1c is
since I'm so critical of it in general, by the way, you've probably heard me rail on the futility
of it. The hemoglobin A1c of course measures the amount of glycosylation or how much glucose is
sticking to hemoglobin. And if we take the assumption that hemoglobin has a relatively finite,
fixed, predictable life before the red blood cells themselves get broken down, we can measure the
hemoglobin A1c and then impute the average blood glucose. And that's of course the exact opposite
of what we would do with CGM where you are actually measuring the average blood glucose
and imputing what the hemoglobin A1c would be. So the diagnosis of type two diabetes is made today
solely on the hemoglobin A1c being greater than 6.5%. It no longer relies on the insulin or glucose
level during an oral glucose challenge. Remind me a hemoglobin A1c of 7.5 corresponds to an
average blood glucose of approximately what, 160? Yeah, I think that's right. We'll post the table
to it. It could be 150, but it's directionally in that ballpark, right? Right. So for someone
listening to this thinking, God, that seems a little high. Why was that chosen as such a goal?
Okay. So we should first just talk about the DCCT, which is the so-called diabetes control
complication trial, which after the discovery of insulin by Banting and Best in 1922 in Toronto,
in Toronto. That's right. So we're coming up on the 100th anniversary of the DCCT.
Of the discovery of insulin. Can we detour for two seconds and explain how Banting and Best did this?
Because it's really one of those beautiful stories in medicine. Yeah, it's so amazing. And there's a
book, by the way, which is by Michael Bliss called The Discovery of Insulin. And if anybody has a vague
interest in type one diabetes, they should run and buy this because it's just so amazing and
bring tears to your eyes. Prior to Banting and Best, what happened to children with type one
diabetes? Children or adults. So at least in the 19th century, nothing. So these people would
present with weight loss and history drinking and urinating quite a bit. And over time, they had to
manage their expectations and then they would expire. And it was, I assume, usually from
complications of diabetic ketoacidosis. That's right. Yeah. And so it would happen in a matter
of weeks, some cases days and some cases months. Then along came Alan and Alan created this amazing
so-called Alan diet. And that was essentially a low calorie, high fat nutritional regimen
that had almost no enriched carbohydrates. And if you use that approach, they were able to extend
life to a few months, in some cases a few years, but it required incredible precision. And Dr.
Jonslin and others had adopted this approach in a desperate attempt to extend life. But other than
that, there was nothing you could do when people just wasted away. So it was one of these things
that people feared greatly because if your kid got type one diabetes, that was it. You were going
to watch them disappear. And you said this earlier and I didn't interject, but it's probably worth
reiterating. You talked about how important insulin is. You use the term catabolic, but
in contrast to its role, which is as such an anabolic gatekeeper. And therefore in the absence
of it, you enter this catabolic state. So talk to me about what you mean by the anabolism of insulin.
Ultimately, insulin is a key factor that's regulating virtually every cell in the body.
And it's essentially deciding whether a cell is in a state of feast or famine. And so if you're in
feast, it's time to take nutrients and park them in the cell. And if it's famine, hey, let's mobilize
some nutrients and make them available to keep the organism alive. And so it's a master regulator of
your state of metabolism. And so if you take a normal non-diabetic human and you fast them for
24 hours, you discover that they're circulating insulin values, especially if a healthy young
adult are exquisitely low. But if you then take that same person, you give them a 75 gram
glucola challenge, you can get their insulin values to exquisitely high levels. So it's a
dynamic hormone. It's changing rapidly in response to meals and everything else. And it's helping you
to sort of take these nutrients and park them away. Now in the fat cell, I think most people
have a vague notion of what's going on. There's basically one door into a fat cell of
esterification or reesterification. And then there's the door out, which is lipolysis.
And insulin acts very prominently at both of those. So free fatty acids and triglycerides
are highly regulated by insulin at both ends of that adipose cell. What is insulin doing at a
muscle cell? It's promoting glucose uptake into skeletal muscle. And it's a dynamic process that
involves glute for these glucose transporters. And essentially the glucose transport is normally
sitting in the cytosol and they translocate to the cell wall. And now all of a sudden the muscle cell
becomes permeable to glucose and glucose is pumped in. So glute four is a passive transporter.
As long as it's going across the cell membrane, glucose enters freely. The active part of that
is the insulin signal that tells the glute transporter to go from the cytosol across the
membrane. Right. And then so taking the other extreme of that, which is when someone is
fasting or starving, which is effectively what's happening in type one diabetes at the cellular
level, they don't have insulin. How does the lack of insulin promote the breakdown of actual muscle?
So this negative nitrogen balance could be because I'm assuming that while a lot of that muscle that
breaks down is used for gluconeogenesis, wouldn't that patient, if you're measuring urinary nitrogen
levels also be in a profound negative nitrogen balance? Yeah. Every step of protein metabolism
is, I mean, many of the major steps are influenced by insulin as well. So you're either making
proteins or you're breaking them down. It also influences the glycogen that's in skeletal muscle
and heart and kidney. So in the presence of insulin, you're putting more glycogen into
skeletal muscle or in the absence you're going to break it down or also with just work. Boy,
it's a thin razor's edge, that hormone. Exactly. Too much of it, really bad stuff. Too little of it,
really bad stuff. As long as you can control it, it's a pretty wonderful hormone. And because it's
so fundamental to eukaryotic cells, it seems to also influence things you would never even imagine,
like for instance, lifespan and aging. And so it's really a deep and fundamental signal around
where cells are. Do you have a great sense of how insulin relates to IGF? It certainly plays a role
in the inverse relationship between some of the binding proteins. So we know that as insulin level
goes up, sex hormone binding globular goes down and therefore high levels of insulin will all
things equal reduce the level of circulating androgens because more of them are being bound up.
What's the relationship between insulin and the binding protein for IGF? IGF binding proteins two,
three, et cetera? I'll probably get this wrong, but I think it's IGF-1 can go down in the presence
of high levels of circulating insulin acutely. And it's one way to be able to diagnose a very
short term hyperinsulinemia. This is something that we often struggle with in pediatrics. We
bizarrely even have some people who will take away too much insulin trying to pretend that they have
hypoglycemia by some measure. And then we go and measure in the blood and you can actually measure
for IGF-BP1 and it can be down. So the BP-1 goes down. So in many ways IGF would go up then. If the
binding protein goes down, the free IGF should be going up with insulin, right? Assuming I remember
this correctly. It's been a while. Well, that's sort of what I see clinically, right? The more
hyperinsulinemia make a patient is all things equal the higher you tend to see their IGF. And
that's always been my assumption as to why just based on the parallel analogy with the, I'm
ashamed to say I'm too lazy to have like spent the time looking this up. Well, the other thing I
would just point out is that insulin and IGF-1 really are intensely overlapping in the way they
work. And insulin does not bind as a monomeric hormone. It's actually a dimer and it can be a
heterodimer. So you can have two insulins or you can have an insulin in IGF-1 or you can have two
IGF-1s and they can bind to receptors and there are even hetero receptors where it's an insulin
receptor and an IGF-1 receptor each bound by their cognate ligands. Derek LaRoytha at Mount
Sinai has done this kind of work for years. And when you block these heterodimeric receptors,
you can completely alter metabolism implying that the role of IGF-1 on glucose homeostasis
is really quite powerful. Yeah. And we probably won't get to it today, but there's also an
IGF and its relationship to growth hormone is actually quite interesting when it comes to
diseases because it seems to have very different effects on different diseases. There are certain
diseases that seem to go up in risk as IGF goes up and there are others that seem to go down.
Whereas insulin seems a little less confusing, but we'll obviously come to that.
So in the late 1910s when Banting and Bester working with dogs, do they know that they're
trying to isolate? Like do they have a sense of where to look for this hormone?
Yeah. So Banting has an idea. Actually, the story of how he comes up with the idea is amazing and
really surprising. So he's a surgeon in a dead end practice in London and...
This is London, Ontario.
London and Ontario. And he can't make his mortgage. He's a veteran of the world war.
At that time, there had only been one. And he's trying to get this general surgery practice going,
but he's bored and he doesn't have that many patients. And so he's a reader and he's thinking
about ways to try to contribute. And he reads in this journal article, which describes how
people who have stones in the pancreas end up with these strange islet like structures or islands of
cells. And so essentially what happens is the pancreas, for whatever reason, if it's obstructed
by a stone and it has a blockage, what you end up with in the residual after the pancreatitis
occurs are these weird round cellular structures. And so it had been known from a couple other
scientists that there might be something in there that was involved in diabetes. So he comes up with
the idea of, wow, maybe what I could do is block the outflow of the exocrine pancreas, which makes
these digestive enzymes, force the pancreas to eat itself alive. And then I will take this residual
muck that comes from the pancreas and try to purify whatever is within it to see if that
is some sort of medicine that might be useful for type 1 diabetes. It's a genius moment that
comes to him in the middle of the night. He writes it down. Michael Bliss actually found the
notebook page from his bedstand where he wrote this. And so then he goes to Uvresa, Toronto,
which is this very sophisticated place. And he meets and he knocks on doors and he finds this
guy who's a famous professor of metabolism. And he says, I got this incredible idea. I want to
isolate this thing that must be in the pancreas. That would be the treatment for type 1 diabetes.
And the guy's like, you're out of your mind. He's like, no, no, no, it's a really cool idea.
Let me tell you about it. And what happened is this professor is about to go on break for the
summer and to go off to Scotland. And so he leaves Banting with a very short lease. He says, look,
I'll allow you to do a few experiments and I can give you a few resources, but you basically got
to finish your experiments by the end of the summer. And so Banting is there. And then he
essentially gets a medical student who has the dumb luck to draw this crazy experiment with
Banting. And that's Charles Best. So there they are in this cramped, hot laboratory in Toronto.
And amazingly, they are able to isolate the substance that has the ability to lower blood
glucose in dogs. And they're doing this in dogs as well? Yes, that's right. So what they do is they
carry out this intervention. The pancreas eats itself alive. They get this this muck and they
are able to isolate some crude extract and then take it and put it back into a dog that they've
removed the entire pancreas of and lower the blood glucose. It's like this incredible moment.
I mean, and this is 1922. What's even more extraordinary is that they're able to take
this observation and then they eventually fairly quickly do an experiment where they lower the
blood glucose of a medical student who has type 1 diabetes with this super crude extract. So
they're able to prove that it works in man. And so then they write the paper and the paper gets
rejected. And then they're able to submit it to a Canadian journal and it gets accepted.
That low Canadian bar. I love it, man. That's the secret to any success I've had.
And they ultimately won the Nobel Prize. It's amazing. And if you think about 1922-
By the way, it's sort of one of like every year there is a Nobel Prize awarded in medicine or
physiology, I believe is the designation. There are a handful of them that stand out in a way that
can't be described. And this is one of them. The Banting and Best Nobel Prize is
one of a handful of places where the trajectory of clinical practice was altered dramatically.
Yeah. No, I think just by virtue of the fact that we're both physicians, we can be,
we can feel proud by association that our profession was able to do something so remarkable.
How long was it before recombinant insulin was used? Because after Banting and Best,
they were still using insulin from animals.
Yeah, purified from pigs. It's amazing. It went on for years and years and they would take these
giant vats and it was either from beef or from pigs.
It wasn't until the 80s, if I recall, that they figured out how to make insulin inside of E. coli
once Paul Berg. Genentech. Yeah. So there's an amazing article about the molecular biology
of modern insulin. And that was basically a race and it was a bunch of-
It really was. It's a biotech arms race to figure out. And it's some of the greatest stories in
science are of that arms race of the 80s. They knew that human insulin could be incredibly
useful for this population. And part of the reason is if you're taking a foreign product like pig
insulin, you can develop antibodies. And in some cases, those antibodies can be blocking to the
point where insulin, you start to have to increase the doses greater and greater. So human insulin
was known to be a goal and they were eventually able to produce it. Genentech did this, they sold
the rights and now there are multiple modern human insulins on the market.
Not to get into a controversial topic, but can somebody explain to me and you can opt out of
this question if it's too politically sensitive, but can somebody explain to me why the hell
recombinant insulin is still so expensive? Well, what's interesting about recombinant insulin is
it used to be cheap. So back when I was a fellow, a vial of insulin, which is a thousand units,
cost about 25 bucks. And that could last a well-managed patient for a month. A month or more.
Right. And today, what is a thousand units of recombinant insulin? 300 plus, maybe $400 US.
Right. Now, I don't know a lot about economics and I kind of forgot my tables of inflation,
but I feel like that has outpaced inflation a little bit. So how is it that we have more
competitors in the space, better technology today, and we've watched a log fold increase
in the price of this stuff that must be driving a lot of people nuts, including those who can't,
who don't have insurance. And frankly, the insurance companies themselves that have to pay this.
It's a disaster on many levels. It's really a disaster for people who are on the margins of
society, but want modern care and are willing to pay for it, but they can't get insulin at the same
price that, for instance, you could if you walked into a pharmacy in Spain, you could buy a vial
of insulin for 25 bucks there. It's three or $400 here. The difference, unfortunately, is that the
federal government is, how shall I say, a promiscuous customer. So they are, thus far, have not been able
to drive the price down because they're willing to essentially pay whatever the sellers charge.
And that's a big problem. And it speaks to the lack of market influence in things like insulin.
So now let's go back to where I distracted you from a long time ago, which is you finish your
fellowship. You're a card carrying pediatric endocrinologist who knows how to target high-ish
levels. And we were about to talk about the trial that explained the complications that
basically led to the why we care about this. Okay. So if the discovery of insulin is like the
first real modern chapter in type 1 diabetes, then the diabetes control complication trial is
chapter 2. And it's based on a brilliant and very clear idea, which goes, if people with type 1
diabetes are at risk for terrible complications, and we haven't really said this, but they're at
risk for all the complications that people with type 2 diabetes get. Cardiovascular disease and
kidney disease and diabetic retinopathy and blindness and limb amputations.
Well, actually, I'm glad you brought that up because I've been a little delinquent in my job
as host and taking things for granted. Can you explain why people with type 1 or type 2 diabetes
have so many of these complications that we refer to, I guess, loosely as microvascular complications
and we'll get to the macrovascular, of course, but just start with those ones you mentioned.
Why the amputations? Why the blindness? The blindness is from abnormal vessel growth. And
it appears that there are these weird glycations that can occur. And there's a series of damages
that happen in the vascular endothelium. And then there's new vessels that are created and the new
vessels are fragile and they can ultimately break and bleed. And the kidney, it's a very different
set of mechanisms, but basically very high glucose can alter the epithelia of the kidney
that's involved in filtering blood and making urine. And then why the amputations of toes and
things like that? Yeah, so that's altered healing from a couple of things. So one is that there's
something called diabetic neuropathy where the nerves simply don't work well and exposed to high
glucose, they lose their responsiveness. And so sometimes people will, for instance, have a wound
in their foot, but they're not able to actually realize that they have that wound. And so then
they also have abnormal healing because the microvascular isn't behaving appropriately.
And the sum total can be very bad diabetic wounds that fail to get better with antibiotics and
ultimately result in amputation. And this is the most common cause of preventable amputation in
the United States. It's also the most common cause of preventable blindness in the United States
and probably also renal failure. I was just about to say it's got to be the leading cause of kidney
disease. So the relationship between the average blood glucose, which we proxy by this hemoglobin
A1C, and these complications you mentioned, that's a monotonically increasing relationship, correct?
Pretty much, yes. So the DCCT really figured this out. So at the time they designed this trial,
they're thinking, well, all this terrible stuff is happening to these people with type 1 diabetes.
And so there was a group of people who thought, well, it's just genetics.
You know, it's obvious because we have two patients and one who has
pretty good control. The other one has pretty good control, but one gets complications.
What were the years of enrollment in the DCCT?
So this is in the late 80s, actually mid 80s, and it was reported out of the New England Journal,
I believe in 1993. And prior to that, you're saying it wasn't obvious that the differences
in these complications could be explained by the differences in their average blood glucose.
That's right. And there were endocrinologists who believed quite strongly that it was foolish
and perhaps even dangerous to carry out a clinical trial to test the basic idea. So the core idea is,
does tight control, i.e. near-normal blood glucose, confer protection from diabetes complications?
And the primary outcome measure was, were microvascular. It was kidney and eye.
And the reason that these physicians who we can look back at now, and obviously with the
benefit of so much hindsight, sort of consider that their views were silly, they weren't bad
doctors, right? They had something to be afraid of on the other end of this, right?
They were concerned about hypoglycemia.
So let's talk about that for a moment. That's it. Because there's got to be a really bad bogeyman
on the other side of this for people to be so worked up about letting glucose get really high.
So the issue with hypo-one diabetes is we think that hypo-glucosis are conferring
risk of complications, but the problem is you can't just throw in a bunch of insulin
and then normalize glucose because you will cause somebody to go low.
And with type 1 diabetes, the crux of the problem is the volatility in blood glucose.
So it's not just so simple that you can figure out the amount of carbohydrates you're going to eat
and take some insulin and your blood sugar is going to be normal.
Because even if you eat the exact same thing every single day, as anyone knows who has type 1
diabetes, and I only know this because of friends who have it, your level of stress,
how much sleep you had last night, how much exercise you've done or not done,
can even in the presence of the identical food stuff produce completely different insulin
requirements. And the other things in food like fat and protein also alter gastric emptying,
and the end result is a tremendous amount of slop and variance in the system.
And so we in the medical field often have this fantasy that, well, we can just come up with some
sort of formula for here's your insulin to carb ratio. And so I tell you that and then you're
supposed to follow it. And then if you come back and your blood glucose is aren't exactly perfect,
I, the physician would say, well, you obviously didn't follow it. You're, you know, they use this
terrible term of medicine, noncompliant, which means you didn't comply with what I told you to do.
It's grotesque. And no format or no arena is it more ridiculous than this one when you realize how
difficult this is. And as I learned from a patient of mine, actually, this was actually
probably the first person I was ever involved in the care of as a medical student. And we became
very good friends. He ultimately died from colon cancer, but he was a pilot. And after during one
of his bouts of, you know, sort of remission, he took me flying and he actually let me fly. Once
we got up, he, you know, he would, he took his hands off the stick. I had a stick and I was flying.
And he said, you got to look at the horizon. Don't look at the instruments. Because if you look at
the instruments, you're going to constantly be chasing them and you're getting into this
pilot induced oscillation. And obviously that's called instrument flying, which you learn to do
way down the line. But as a total rookie, you have to be able to fly off the horizon. And it was
amazing to me how much easier it was to fly that way. And in some ways that's what happens
when patients or physicians would get frustrated with this inability to manage this is you, you
tend to go too high, then too low, then too high, then too low. And then you are
vacillating wildly in these glucose levels. And again, yeah, you see these huge sine wave
excursions and, and some of them can be incredibly volatile. So I'm going to go back to the DCCT. So
they have this idea that they're going to somehow normalize blood glucose, but then there are some
people, physicians who say, well, that's a terrible idea because you can't actually normalize blood
glucose because you're going to make a bunch of people hypoglycemic. So there's a group of people
who are arguing against the DCCT. There's another people, including Elliott Joslin, are saying,
no, we need to understand if we can reduce the risk of long-term complications. So they carry
out this trial. It's intended to be a 10 year clinical trial. And they, it's 1441 patients,
they're relatively recent onset type one diabetes, they're largely late teen and adults. And it's a
very difficult trial to do because there were no established best practices to achieve neuro-normal
blood glucose at the time. So the average hemoglobin A1c for the population is around
9% at the time. That was just what, where they were. That's the lowest glucose you could have
to not have hypoglycemic events, right? Yeah. And sort of, that's where people were in order to not
dump massive amounts of glucose in their urine and sort of look okay. And in some cases, people
were taking insulin once a day. Quite often people were taking insulin once a day. And someone who's
got a hemoglobin A1c of 9% is not going to live a normal life. Their life expectancy is
truncated dramatically and their quality of life is going to be,
even by their forties, they're going to be quite compromised.
Yeah. So we know now from Swedish studies that somebody with an average hemoglobin A1c has about a-
Of what? Of 9?
Of 9% has approximately a six-fold increased risk of death and a six-fold risk, increased risk of
cardiovascular disease. And so that's shocking. And again, these are healthy people who are doing
their best, but the system just didn't work. So in the DCCT, they say, well, we want to normalize
blood glucose in the population and try to get them from nine all the way down to the non-diabetic
range, somewhere under six. And they put together all of these centers. And what they did was they
mandated conference calls. And on the conference calls, they shared best practices. They crowd-sourced
it, if you will. And so they didn't have any idea how they were going to achieve their goals,
but they ended up ultimately learning how to do it. And it involved phone calls and it involved
frequent visits and cajoling. And they're able to reduce the A1c from 9% to 7% in the population.
They intend to do this for a decade. There's a safety and monitoring board that's following
the curves. The primary outcome measure is diabetic retinopathy and diabetic nephropathy.
And the safety and monitoring board sees a huge difference in between the control and the
intervention group. And they stop the trial. And the reason is they felt that this was seven years
in and they felt that they- It was now unethical in the reverse. Yes. It was unethical to deprive
the general population of what they have learned. So they stopped the trial. There's a giant talk
at the American Diabetes Association that describes these immense differences. There's a paper that's
in the New England Journal of Medicine. It's an amazing, wonderful paper. And it changes type
one diabetes forever because it says that we can begin to reduce complications. And the work that
we do is incredibly important for this patient population. In some ways, it makes the field of
modern type one diabetes care because it says there really is something you can do other than
hold somebody's hand and look for complications. But on the other hand, it actually breaks the
field because we don't have the apparatus to routinely achieve the kinds of outcomes that the
NIH was able to do because they had near infinite resources. They spent over a hundred million
dollars for a relatively small number of patients. A hundred million dollars for 1400 patients over
seven years? Yeah. That's a staggering sum of money. Where did it go? I mean, and I'm not being
critical of that. I'm just saying like, what was so expensive about that study? Coordinating centers
and buying people's time to be able to care for them, to call them, to cajole them. There's a
lot of work that was done. Wow. I did not realize it was that expensive. And that's 30 years ago's
dollars. Yeah. I could have it wrong. We'll have to look this up. Okay. Yeah. We've got the team to
look that up, but I'm guessing directionally you're right that it was a costly study. It was a vast
amount of money. Yeah. Was there a sizable or noticeable increase in the hypoglycemic events
with that tighter control from nine to seven? Yes. There are many more hypoglycemic events and
there was weight gain. And so when they jack up the insulin, people found themselves eating more
carbs and eating out of the hole. And over time. Was that actually the case that they know that
the people who gained more weight consumed more of one type of food than another? No, not necessarily,
but practically if your blood glucose is low, the only thing that's going to get your glucose back
up is carbohydrates. Oh, so I see. So it's they were chasing carbs when they were overshooting
on insulin. Right. And this is one of the continual problems with type one diabetes is if
you jack up the insulin and your blood glucose is low, there's only one thing you can do to get your
glucose back up. I guess you could go out and you could exercise intensely, but it won't happen fast
enough. So acute carbohydrate is essential. So we don't really know not to get off on a tangent. We
don't know if those patients gained weight because of the hyperinsulinemia per se as a primary driver
or if it was sort of not necessarily a root cause, but more of a tangential driver that ultimately
forced more of this sort of hyperphasic response indirectly to compensate. You're asking a really
important question, which is, is the weight gain in type one diabetes absolutely obligate? Is it
coincident with tight control? And it was argued by many that the only way towards tight control
would be weight gain. And by the way, in the years since the DCCT, what we've seen is a huge
number of people with type one diabetes have gained weight and some cases uncontrollably.
And that is a really serious problem. And moreover, in the people who have gained the most weight have
had poor cardiovascular outcomes. There's a weak association. So I'm going to just talk about the
bigger picture of the DCCT so that the trial only happened for seven years. And then the cohorts
merged back to the same blood glucose and now they're followed for 25, 30 years. Wait a second.
When they merged, did they merge to seven or merge to nine? Yeah, they merged to eight. So what
happened was the people who had hemoglobin A1Cs of nine learned the benefits of tighter control and
they did their best. And the people at seven no longer under the grip of the best in class care
drifted up to eight. That's right. That became where people landed. Eight became the new normal
with a significant standard deviation within it. Some people just did better, worse. And then you
follow these people over the subsequent 23 plus years. And it turns out that there are immense
differences in major kidney disease and in cardiovascular disease and even death.
So the people who at least for seven years had tighter control versus less tight control, but
then for 23 years were identical to their peers still retained some benefit from the seven years,
30 years earlier. In cardiovascular disease, which is amazing and death. So that-
What kind of hazard ratios do you recall? I'm not sure I'll be able to remember it off the top of
my head. We'll link to all of this stuff of course. At least in the primary outcome measure for the
cardiovascular trial, it's approximately a third less of the primary outcome measure. So that's
really exciting. And it suggests that if you were able to routinely achieve blood glucoses in the
near normal range, you could drop your risk of cardiovascular disease accordingly to something
that was approaching a normal healthy non-diabetic person. That's pretty amazing, but it also puts a
lot of pressure on us as a field. So if you were to have a device, a magical device that could
measure someone's glucose in real time, and you were to put this on somebody 30 years ago back
when the standard of care was minimize the hypoglycemic events, we're going to tolerate
a hemoglobin A1C of 9%. Can you estimate what the standard deviation of glucose would have been
on that measurement? Do you have a sense of how high that could have been? Yeah, because I put
continuous glucose monitors on teenagers who don't listen to me. Okay, so talk to me about some of
those numbers. Yeah, so you might see blood glucoses of around, in some cases, 180 or 200 with a
standard deviation of 100. And so again, poorly controlled type of- You know my standard for
myself, right? Which is- Under 20? 90 plus or minus, if I'm fasting or on a sort of ketogenic
diet, I'd like to see it plus or minus less than 10. And when I'm just eating ad libitum, it's sort
of less than 15. Yeah. A hundred's amazing. A hundred means you're bouncing around nonstop,
which you're never normal. And you feel so bad for these patients because even if they intermittently
decide, okay, today's the day I want to get this right, like you just can't chase that down. That
is so difficult. I don't even know. It's hard for me to physiologically even think about what's
happening in those patients. And so that kind of volatility has driven everybody insane because
they think like, there's got to be a better way. There's got to be a better way. And you know,
anybody who lives with type 1 diabetes, they're constantly being asked, okay, well, what about a
cure? I hesitate to even use that word, but like some sort of definitive biological therapy. And
we've heard all along about the possibility of stem cells or some sort of maybe an auto loop
pancreas that would measure your glucose and administer insulin, or maybe some sort of beta
cell regenerative therapy or something combined with something that shuts down the autoimmune
system. So those three concepts are constantly trotted out as potential avenues. But from what
I can tell as a scientist, many of those things are years and years and years away, decades,
maybe even centuries. And so the problem was like, what do you do now to support people who
live with type 1 diabetes? How do you reduce that volatility? So I remember reading a paper a few
years ago, it was actually right after you and I met that I got more curious about this. And
especially then once I started wearing a CGM, which was shortly after that, and I've basically
never taken it off, I started to figure, I started to think, okay, well, from my angle,
it's how do you use these in people who don't have diabetes to drive better health? Right?
And one of the questions I wanted to understand was, was there any evidence that variability in
blood glucose per se beyond the average? So if you have someone whose average blood glucose is 100,
plus or minus 10 or 15 versus someone who's 100 plus or minus 30, is there a difference? Well,
the hemoglobin A1C would give you the same answer, and even the average glucose does.
And I believe I found some data that suggested that cognition was impaired during developmental
years by higher variability. Yes. And I think it was even independent of absolute glucose level.
And that was very frightening to me, not individually, because I was out of that loop,
but thinking about kids with type 1 diabetes, who now have yet another complication to be concerned
with, which is cognitive impairment, if the variability of glucose is too great.
It's well known that diabetes complications are increased with increasing A1Cs. A kind of
surprising piece of this is very short exposures to high blood sugars can completely change gene
expression in a whole bunch of genes, like endothelial cells. So there's a school of thought
that says that diabetes complications are really around the exposures to these weird toxic levels
of blood glucose that can occur. And what do you think toxic is? How high? Well, they always do it
experimentally by turning everything up to 11. So you never really know. But what you can say is
it is surprising and weird that a short, almost evanescent exposure to a very high blood glucose
could change the way genes behave in cells in a dish. And so that suggests to me that diabetes
complications may not be so simple as a sort of on off in between glucose and hemoglobin or glucose
and some other protein. You could have permanent profound changes in the way a cell behaves based
on intermittent exposures to very high blood glucose. So whether that's volatility or it's
an absolute level, we don't know. But it still puts it. That's just like nature to fuck with us like
that. I mean, you have to deal with some epigenetic change in response to a glucose. I mean, that's so
unfair. But in the end, it shows you that we had a very superficial understanding of diabetes
complications years ago. And again, now there's a whole rich field that's devoted to this idea of
these windows of hyperglycemia permanently altering these important cells that ultimately contribute
to diabetes complications. You're making me question my elaborate cheat meals sometimes.
Just admit this now to you and everybody else. A couple of days ago, I was like, you know,
I've been so good for so long. I've been doing my this and anything. And like there are just a
handful of junk foods I can't get enough of. And one of them is mini wheats. So I decided to have
a box of mini wheats. That's not a typo. It's not a bowl of mini wheats, a box of mini wheats.
Meaning if you have a big enough bowl, you can put the box in the bowl. So I had a box of mini
wheats in a bowl. And boy, if you really want to know why that's not a good idea, just wear a CGM.
And not to mention the splitting headache I had like an hour and later. Yeah, I get headaches.
I mean, I thought I was going to die. I'd feel better if I had six drinks, I think my head would
have hurt less. My blood glucose hit like 170. Now, again, that's in the grand scheme of things,
probably not that high for someone who's got type two diabetes or type one diabetes. But for someone
who's not diabetic, that's a pretty staggeringly high. I haven't seen a level that high in years.
And you think like, hey, these mini wheats are promoted as like part of a healthy breakfast.
And so imagine now-
Of course, no one's eating a box.
Box.
But yeah.
But if you think about this in the context of your kids, imagine dropping your kid off,
if your kid has type one diabetes, you drop them off at a birthday party and there's cake and there's-
Capri Sun.
And there's Cheetos and all this stuff is essentially carbohydrate. And if your child is-
And none of them are real carbohydrates. That's the problem, right? It's all like these fake
carbohydrates. It's one thing if they were like, all right, we're going to grind up some wheat and
you're going to have a piece of bread, which has its own issues. But yeah, these things that you've
described are basically IV infusions of glucose.
Let's imagine you drop your five year old off at a birthday party and you know they have
diabetes and you give them and they're wearing an insulin pump and everyone knows what they're
wanting, what they're supposed to do. And out of sight of all the adults, the kid eats two cupcakes.
That's the equivalent of the box of wheat thins. Is that what you're-
No, but it's funny you bring up wheat thins. That's one of my kids favorite things is he
calls them wheethens, but no, it's mini wheats.
Mini wheats.
Yes, it's just nonsense. It's basically breakfast dessert.
So again, this thing was really perplexing for me. And part of,
you know, when I really understood how challenging it all was, was spending time with people who
live with type 1 diabetes and looking and seeing what they do. And I didn't really get this as an
endocrine fellow. And we had this standards feel about, okay, you're going to check your blood
sugar before each meal and at bedtime. And then you're going to eat certain number of meals that
involve certain number of carbohydrates. And we had this fantasy that we're just going to sort of
make people live in what I call the diabetes ICU, which is a prescribed number of carbohydrates
and timing. And then we're going to sort of work towards making sure that everything was
very predictable and then bug glucoses would be near normal much of the time.
And I lived in that fantasy world, unperturbed by reality, until I became close friends with
several people who have type 1. And then I began to see what they do. So for instance,
my friend Marianne is a pediatric endocrinologist who works at Boston Children's. And one time we
were at this restaurant and we were at Bertucci's, you know, so pizza place. And she has type 1
diabetes and she's eating a Caesar salad. And I see her picking the croutons out. I'm like,
what are you doing? And she goes, oh, Jake, I can't eat these things. I'm like, what are you
talking about? She's like, if I eat those, these carbs, my blood sugar will just go loopy. So what
I discovered, and let's pause for a moment. You know, all of the molecular biology, you know,
how many grams of carbs are in that, right? You've been managing patients through their food with
insulin. And now you're watching one of your peers pull out what's probably 15 to 20 grams
of croutons. Like it's virtually like it's something that wouldn't even alter your blood
glucose. And yet she's saying to you, if I eat these things now, I'm really going to be chasing
this for a while. And she said, and I won't be able to figure out the right dose of insulin because
of all the fat that's in the salad dressing. She goes, I've just found that it's easier for me to
not eat this stuff. So I looked at that and I realized like, this is the ultimate hack. This
is somebody who figured out like the ultimate biohack. She's trying to make her blood sugars
near normal all the time. She discovered a group of foods that she needs to avoid. And so she
avoids them. And what did she figure out? I mean, presumably most of what she needed to avoid was
carbohydrates, but were there some that she found and I assume she did not have a CGM at this point
in time. That's right. So this is all on finger sticks. Yeah. This is doing it the really hard
way. She's testing 10 times a day or something. What did her, did they even have feeling left
in their fingers at this point? Quite often they won't. So they go after, people use finger stick
testing and will use one spot over and over again and it becomes numb. And that's a way to be able
to do it without pain. And I just know from when I'm doing a lot of finger sticking, like the bruising
and the discoloration and the discomfort. And I think to myself, it's one thing when I'm doing
this as a grownup who's choosing to do this, it's quite another thing for a kid who never signed up
for this to be going through this amount of pain. Yeah. And for their parents and for the parents
to think about all the other things that could happen. Like for instance, we, unfortunately,
we have kids who disappear. So we have teenagers who go off to college and they party with their
friends and potentially take the same dose of insulin that they would have taken and they have
fatal hypoglycemic episodes. And that doesn't happen often, but when it does, it's devastating.
It's really awful. And that sits in the back of parents' minds. And that kind of anxiety means
that nobody ever really just gets to be a parent or a kid because there's this constant fear of
what's my blood sugar? Is it high or low? And I think of it as a cognitive load. It's the burden
of having to think nonstop about your diabetes. And if you can imagine that volatility, the
rollercoaster blood sugars that are going up and down, you're going to have to think about it
nonstop. And I think that the cognitive load in some ways is probably a really pivotal factor
in the anxiety and depression that's associated with type 1 diabetes. So there's a whole category
of a very complicated mental illness that people with type 1 diabetes have, approximately 45 or 50
will have depression or anxiety. And it can be really debilitating. And of course, we don't really
have any way of knowing is what percentage or what amount or proportion of that debilitating
mental illness is resulting from the physiology of the hyperglycemia, the glucose fluctuations,
and the hyperinsulinemia or the relative hyperinsulinemia versus this much more difficult
to track metric of the cortisol levels that accompany the stress or other things that we
couldn't even measure if we wanted to that accompany that, as you put it, I like that phrase,
cognitive load. I mean, what's the current thinking on that? I didn't realize that the,
did you say 40% depression? That seems almost impossible to believe.
Well, imagine, let's imagine you have type 1 diabetes and you've lived with it for 20 or 25
years. And right now you're a little bit hungry and you're trying to figure out what your blood
sugar is going to be. And you look down at your CGM and you get a number and you're thinking,
well, like, what do I have to do? And when do I have to time the dose of insulin and will I get
it right? And think about the last time I gave insulin and I didn't give it right. And I had that
hypoglycemic episode and it was embarrassing. And so I mean, it's a big, really serious challenge
in that I try to quantify what I call the cognitive load using a diabetes distress scale. And it's an
adaptation of a published distress scale. And I basically say to people, okay, I want to talk to
you using a Likert scale, a 1 to 10 scale about your diabetes related distress. And so it's on
a 1 to 10 scale. And 1 means you know you have diabetes, but it's not holding you back at all.
It's there. It's in the back of your mind. It's not bothering you. You get to do what you want to do.
And a 10 means you have diabetes and you can't think about anything else. And it's pretty much
omnipresent and it alters your ability to carry out the things you want to do.
So if this is on a 1 to 10 scale. So what's the median score for a teenager who has had this
disease for five years or more? Who's on a high carb diet, seven or eight. And I've seen people
who have hemoglobin A1c's that are approaching 14 who are doing basically nothing to care for their
diabetes, teenagers who are really struggling. And when I described this to them, their answer
is tears pour out of their eyes. And because no one has ever actually asked them how do they feel
and they will say a 10. But they can't even admit it because no one has ever considered that they
have this terrible burden. What they think is, you know, this kid doesn't do what everybody wants
him to do. You know, he has got a hard head. He's not listening to us. But in fact, the kid is not
doing anything, is thinking about it nonstop and is wracked with guilt and shame. And this is not
just true of teenagers, it's true of adults because the adults want to do a better job,
but they lack the tools and the support to be able to carry it out and they blame themselves.
So this endless cycle of blame and shame and negativity is unfortunately in many cases
reinforced by the medical establishment because now you come in, you get a hemoglobin A1c of 14.
And what do you get? He gets panked. Yeah, you get a lecture about how you need to do a better
job. You're told you're not compliant. You might even be threatened with being fired by your doctor
unless you do a better job. You know, you might not be able to make appointments here. This is a
privilege to come and see the endocrinologist. And so people end up in this weird cycle of antagonism
towards the medical establishment who apparently don't know that much about type 1 diabetes and
certainly aren't empathetic about it. And then their loved ones who are like, well, why can't he
or she do a better job failing to understand who really complicated it is? And there's no well-worn
path in the general populace on how to get to a better spot. And so one of the really crucial
elements of this, which is so bizarre is that this diabetes distress or this anxiety or whatever it is,
is egosyntonic. And so it doesn't feel foreign. People are depressed or anxious. And they just
think that this is the way life is going to be forever. They can't imagine another world
where they would feel better. They just think that life sucks. And when you get them, I've
worked with people where I've actually had the privilege of working with a few people who have
dropped their hemoglobin A1Cs in half. And the experience changed my life. You can get somebody
from an A1C of greater than 14 down to under seven. And when they talk about it, they're astounded by
the changes in their ability to think and feel and see the world around them and the love that
all these people who were trying to help them have that they couldn't even recognize.
Yeah, that's very powerful. I don't have anything that I could even think to add to that.
Let's go back to the pizza store, Pizza Shop. You're watching your colleague, what was her name?
Maryann Quinn.
You're watching Maryann pull the croutons out of the Caesar salad and it plants a bug in your
mind, right?
Right.
So how long from then until you've discovered this continuous glucose monitor little contraption?
So only about four or five years. I was a fellow at Boston Children's and I worked in a
basic science research lab studying insulin signaling with Morris White. And then I go off
and I get my first job as an assistant professor at UPenn and I'm there and I set up.
So, okay. So you're a chop actually, right?
Right.
So you're bouncing around between the biggest children's hospitals in the world.
And I set up a lab studying beta cells. And my idea was that I was going to use basic science to
advance outcomes for people with type one. And I have this background and
a bunch of passion in trying to figure out ways to grow new beta cells. And the hope is we'll be
able to find some way to do that safely and reliably. And I also have a clinical practice
that's focused on type one and other endocrine disorders. And along the way, I become very close
friends with people who live with type one and I start to talk to them and follow them. And I
start to meet some of the reps, that is the sales representatives for various companies,
including one who herself has type one diabetes. This is Natalie Bellini. So she's an amazing
person who has type one and she's wearing this device, which is this black hockey puck. It's this
Dexcom thingy.
What generation was that?
It was the very first.
Wow.
And so this is approximately 2000, maybe seven. And I thought, well, this is amazing because it's
obviously a consumer device. It's approved and then you could give it to patients and they could
wear this thing and then they could figure out ways to improve their glucose excursions. And
actually several of my friends went on them and what they discovered was the devices were
incredibly frustrating because if you just wear the device and again, a Dexcom or is just one
that's a company that's making a continuous glucose monitor. And what they do is they take
a probe that goes into your interstitial space, say in your belly. It's a very small needle and
it sits in the space. And what it's doing is it's sampling the interstitial fluid, which is the
clear fluid that exists in between cells, which roughly correlates to blood glucose, but is
delayed by about eight or 10 minutes. And so the device essentially has glucose oxidase,
which is an enzyme and it's stuck onto this platinum wire. It's basically an enzyme on a stick
and so when glucose comes by and it does the enzymatic conversion, it generates a charge,
which is transmitted down the wire and the change in the wire charges is transmitted to this hockey
puck like device that tells you your glucose. So that's pretty cool. And it blows my mind when I
see it working regularly for patients. And my thought is, okay, so we're going to prescribe
these for all of our patients and then they're going to figure out how to make their blood
glucose is better. But as it turns out, the first generation of CGM was a dismal failure and the
uptake was incredibly, incredibly small in the population of people with type 1 diabetes. And
part of the issue is we didn't really know what to do. So when we looked in the toolbox of trying to
help people so they could live with type 1 diabetes, we didn't find much other than badgering
them to do a better job. You know, oh, you need to check your blood glucose 20 minutes before the
meal and give yourself insulin 20 minutes before the meal and do that in a very reliable way so
that your blood glucose is normal. But that's not realistic. And for that matter, no one really
knows that they're going to eat. So there's a major problem in that we live in this fantasy
world in medicine, where we think people just need to carry out their lives with more precision. And
that will be the answer. But the reality is variance is contained in human behavior. It's
just what we do. So that idea of badgering people doesn't work. And then maybe it's exercise. So,
okay, as it turns out, if you're a marathon runner, and you have type 1 diabetes,
your diabetes control is much, much better. And part of the mechanism is via this insulin
independent glucose uptake into skeletal muscle via AMP kinase. So there's a whole there's two
different pathways whereby glucose gets into skeletal muscle. One is via the insulin dependent
pathway. We've spoke about that before, that goes to glute for the insulin independent pathway is
working through exercise and work of muscle. And AMP kinase is this amazing enzyme that is sensing
the energy status of the cell. And if you if you alter the energy status of the cell through a
tremendous amount of work, you can basically drive a bunch of signals that go to tell the glute four
to translocate to the membrane and skeletal muscle. So now you get insulin independent glucose
uptake in the skeletal muscle. So it's still through glute four, right? But it comes from
inside the cell activation, I assume, yes, MPK activating AMP, K sends the glute for transporter
up. And in a non athlete, what is the relative difference between insulin dependent and the AMP
K driven glucose disposal in the muscle? I'm not exactly sure. But I can say that if, for instance,
I take a kid who has type one diabetes, and we have stable insulin doses, and then they go on like
a ski vacation with their parents, and the kids are, you know, mostly playing video games and
hanging out, and then they get they go off to veil and they ski for six hours a day. Those kids can
can require nonstop carbohydrates until their parents figure out that they have a problem. And
then they end up on insulin doses that are reduced by two thirds. So the effect can be dramatic.
In normal non exercise associated glucose homoestasis, I think a lot of it is insulin driven.
And so as you carry out more and more exercise, you invoke this pathway more and more.
Yeah, it's so interesting. I need to look into this more because I've never I can't believe it
didn't occur to me to look at the patients with type one diabetes to answer this question. I've
always wondered what the relative difference is in, you know, like if you're taking metformin,
which is activating AMPK, and if you're exercising like crazy, you should be able to dispose of
glucose with lower and lower insulin levels. Right. And so we can obviously measure this.
That's right.
In a oral glucose tolerance test. The problem is we don't know why. We don't know what it is.
That's is that they're more sensitive to insulin, which is that's a two hour discussion on end of
itself, which you and I'll have over dinner right after this. Or is it that no, they're
each unit of or heterodimer of insulin produces the same magnitude of glute four translocation,
but they're experiencing a benefit of this AMPK version. In other words, how much of the insulin
sensitivity is really less about insulin and more about AMPK. I think for people who are very
athletic and who are focused on trying to reduce their body fat, it can probably be a huge
contribution. And we have these adults who have type one diabetes who are down to 20 units of
insulin and a normal 70 kilogram person would be on 60 or 70 units of insulin. So the marathon
runners who are thin, of course they have very thin body habitus, but many of those people are
putting in 60, 70, 80 miles a week or on tiny doses of insulin. So again, so we got, I have a patient
by the way, with type one diabetes who uses five units of insulin a day. Wow. He walks six miles
a day minimum, sometimes 10. And he does not really consume carbohydrates outside of vegetables.
And how much body fat?
I've never seen a higher adiponectin and lower leptin in a human I've ever measured. He is a
lean, mean machine. Yeah. So those people are just my heroes. It's so, I'm thrilled to hear about this.
So if we're looking in the toolbox, we find like badgering people to do a better job,
maybe exercise, and then like, what else do you got? And so I'm looking around and I'm looking at
this and I'm trying to... So we're going back to the exercise thing for a moment. Do you see a
difference in, I don't like the term aerobic, but people know what I mean by aerobic exercise versus
strength training. Yeah. I think that people who are doing distance, who are, that they actually have
more contribution of this AMPK pathway and Lori Goodyear has studied this for years and years.
She's at the Jozlyn. And again, this AMPK exercise associated pathway is incredibly potent,
but it's all distance. I don't think it's strength. And then do you think there's a difference between
going out and running 10 quarter mile repeats at staggering intensity where you're burning through
glycogen in the muscle versus, so that would only be what, a total of two and a half miles of running
versus going out and running six or seven miles at a much lower intensity. Do you think there's
a difference between those two? Yeah, I think there's a huge difference, but what I hear over
and over again is the people who are the distance athletes or the people who are able to dramatically
reduce their total amount of insulin. But again, there's relative debate and this is not well
studied. So you'd like to really carry out a proper study with high intensity exercise versus
very slow long duration exercise. But this idea of trying to sort of hack the system
to reduce the total exposure to insulin and therefore reduce the volatility and the hyperglycemic
excursions, that's really exciting. And I suspect that the people like your patient who have, you
know, down to eight units of insulin, these people have really cracked the code. So when did the
Dexcom for you, was it around gen four that it really started to become a real impact? Yeah,
the G4 was a special device. So for me, it wasn't just that we replaced the hockey puck,
at least in my life that the transformative thing was learning about Dr. Richard Bernstein
in his book. And do you know Richard? Well, I only talked to him on a teleconference. I'm on a
low carb physician teleconference that happens once a month and I talked to him regularly then.
You got to get me on this. How am I not on this? I'd be very curious to just be a fly on the wall.
Is there any chance I can get invited? Yeah. So it's run by Virta Health and it's focused on type one.
It's on Virta. How did I not know about this? So it's low carb and type one and it's physicians
who are very much interested in the intersection of type one and low carb. It's really cool.
I've never met Dr. Bernstein, but I've read his book and I've spoken on the telephone with him.
He's very graciously extended an offer for me to come out to his clinic and spend time. And I
would give anything to be able to make that time. I just haven't been able to. But it's safe to say
he's kind of the guy who's spent more time doing this and has more clinical experience in this
than probably anyone else. And because he did it with himself, right? It's amazing. He actually got
a YSI blood glucose tester and has been using it at home forever. So he's been blood glucose testing
before anybody else did. And he had this essential core idea, which was carbohydrates
caused blood glucose excursions and that he has the so-called rule of small numbers, which says
that if you consume more carbs, you need more insulin and therefore there's a greater opportunity
to make a mistake. And so if you consume fewer carbs, you will consume less insulin and you'll
have fewer mistakes. It's a very simple idea. It's laid out along with a ton of practical tips in his
book. He's incredible. He figured this out. And we'll link to his book, but it's called the Dr.
Bernstein's diabetes solution. Yeah, it's a Bible. It's like it's a tome. And it's for type one and
type two. And it includes all sorts of pearls, not just on straight diabetes, but also diabetes
complications. It's really shocking. And he had, and again, this is like the 11th or 12th edition.
He's been doing this for years and years. So he has a private practice. He's in his 80s. He lives
in Westchester County, New York, and is working out and incredibly healthy. So he figured out that
if you avoid carbohydrates and if you give medium and long acting insulin to cover protein and fat
and basal metabolic requirements, that you could get blood glucose is very, very close to normal.
And he typically prescribes a low carb high protein diet. It's not low carb high fat. It's
not ketogenic. What have we learned from Bernstein's experience on how
insulin genic protein is? Cause that's somewhat debatable, right? I mean,
clearly protein stimulates some insulin and certain in vitro studies suggest it can be
very insulin genic. What does the real world experience tell us about that?
In my patients with type one diabetes who consume protein and don't cover it with insulin, they can
get these massive glucose excursions. And we think in general, there's a ratio of around
10 grams of protein end up being six grams of carbohydrate. But the problem is the kinetics
are not immediate. So you don't get gluconeogenesis in a matter of seconds. It's delayed over hours.
And doesn't it also depend on their nitrogen requirement? So in other words, you could have,
which is obviously true with glucose, but you could have two individuals who are similar
at the crude metrics. Say each of them gets 40 grams of protein, but one of them has just finished
exercising or lifting weights and the other one hasn't. And you're going to presumably see very
different glucose responses, correct? But the vast majority of humans were at homeostasis.
And overall, if you look at the USDA requirements, this is a suggestion we need to consume 56 grams
of protein. And then, and the net result of that is approximately six grams of protein that go into
metabolism. So excuse me, seven grams. So there's a net excess that's 49 grams that ends up being
approximately, what is that? 30 grams of carbohydrate. But on the other hand, if you're consuming high
protein, if you sit down to a 12 ounce rib eye, and it also has fat, which will delay the absorption,
the sum total of that could be 80, 100 grams of protein that turns into glucose. That is this
massive slow wave that rises and stays high for much of the evening after you eat it, which could
be very frustrating. So a lot of people who have type 1 diabetes think, well, okay, I'm going to do
this sort of low carb thing. So instead of eating the pasta, I'm going to have a piece of fish and
some vegetables, but there's no carbohydrate. Cool. I don't need to take any insulin. But then you get
this weird glucose excursion that comes from the protein. And the essence of the Bernstein method,
if you read his book, is to try to cover protein with insulin. And he uses regular insulin, not
short acting, hemalog or novalog. And the idea is the regular insulin was a, which is human insulin,
has a peak of onset within approximately an hour or two, and it lasts for six to eight hours.
And so it roughly, very roughly corresponds with the kinetics of what protein will do to your glucose.
So what's unique about Bernstein is he's using this ancient form of insulin,
regular human insulin, instead of these very rapid acting analogs, because the protein is absorbed
and turns into glucose in a delayed fashion. I've never really understood these rapid onset
insulins because they seem to get back to this oscillation problem of, I mean, so the first
observation of Bernstein is more carbohydrate means more insulin, more insulin means more
vacillation. But now you're introducing another effect, which is short acting insulin causes more
rapid changes in the glucose, which can more easily result in you making another decision after that
amplifies the signal instead of dulls the signal. Right. So to go back to your analogy of the plane,
potentially what it means is a plane that can much more rapidly gain or lose. Yeah. And you can get
into a lot of trouble. And unfortunately, the insulin pump companies and even the insulin
companies have advocated an approach that says, look, people who live with type one diabetes
have tough lives. We need to support them and they should be allowed to eat what they want
and they should just cover for it. And the problem is you end up with these crazy oscillations
and the oscillations are associated again with a tremendous burden of illness and this cognitive
load and this fear and this anxiety. And you'll have to forgive my sort of snarky-ism, but that's
a really wonderful business model if you want to sell more insulin too. Yeah, exactly. Because
you consume, well, first of all, everybody gets a pump and then they're told that this is the way
to feel normal. You run shots, you go to pump and then you can just eat what you want. And then
then of course you consume insulin and you gain weight and you need more insulin.
So, yeah, and I'm not, I am so not the conspiracy guy, but I also believe it's important to
understand incentives and I don't think pharma is evil. I think far more good has come from the
ability of being able to sell insulin and sell insulin pumps and all these things. I really do
think these are a net positive, but I also think we have to keep in mind there are modifications
that you can make and obviously you live this with your patients that can give you 80% maybe of the
joy that comes from eating. I mean, let's be honest. I think to eat a restricted diet, to eat a diet
that is far fewer in carbohydrates, you're giving up some pleasure. There's just no doubt about it.
But if you could give up 20% of the pleasure of eating and get 80% more benefit in your health,
those are the kind of asymmetric benefits that I think in the long run probably pay off, but
it's still not easy. I had to figure this out for myself and I had seen people do low carbon. I
didn't really understand it and I just started doing it myself. So I gradually cut back carbohydrates
until approximately four years ago when we went low carb as a family and my wife cleared out the
pantry. There were no more enriched carbohydrates in our house, but we had teenage girls who were,
one was in college and one was going off to college and I can remember the day. I had wanted
to do it, she wanted to do it. We just decided to try it. So we went low carb as a family and then
we've stayed on it ever since. So actually these days I'm probably ketotic. I wouldn't be surprised
if my beta hydroxybutyrate is well above one right now. So when did you start to, I mean,
I guess now that I'm thinking about it, it was, we were probably at the G5 by the time you and I met
and I remember you showing me data and I really think at the time your patients averaged about
5.7 and their hemoglobin A1C, which is as normal as normal gets. Yeah. And part of it, it took me
a while to understand the power of this. And you also noted by the way that they had fewer
hypoglycemic events than patients who were walking around at seven. Yeah. The incredible
thing is that you can reduce the excursions and people have very few lows. And again,
I read Bernstein and I also learned of a recent Facebook group, which is called type one grit.
T-Y-P-E-O-N-E-G-R-I-T. And so that's a group of people who are followers of the Bernstein method.
And it's an amazing group of people who are supporting each other and you see
CGM tracings and you see foods that they eat and you see happy kids or adults. And you might see
somebody complaining about their healthcare provider who didn't have a clue about low carb.
And it's just sort of a conversation that happens in private amongst people who live with type one
or those who have a loved one. And there's also healthcare providers like me who are part of it.
And again, so it took me a while to understand it and to understand its nuance and to start
to iterate it. But for me, the real turning point was changing the way I practiced medicine. So the
problem with endocrinology is the schedules were so tight and the only way I could see patients was
every 20 minutes or 30 minutes. And to try to talk to somebody about something as complicated as
living with type one three or four times a year and also renew their prescriptions and go through
their labs and document and all this stuff was impossible. And I just decided for my own sanity
that I needed to change my practice. And so at the time I had a very small amount of clinical
responsibility because I was mostly in the research lab and I also had administrative responsibility.
So what I decided to do was to make sure that when I saw patients, I only saw them at the end of the
day. And the idea was I'd see them starting at 4.30 and that we would just spend as much time as it
took. And then I added on other patients. But for instance, some endocrinologists will run from room
to room to room to room. I only need one room because I'm going to see a patient for an hour.
And then when we're done, they leave and the new one comes in. I don't need to run back and forth.
There's nobody else. So I made a conscious decision that I was going to be more inefficient,
that I was going to spend more time with people. It's possible I was going to spend much more time
doing clinical work for the few patients that I saw. But I wanted to carry out experiments just
to try to determine what sort of impact I could have. And the crux of the idea was if you have
limitless resources that you make available to a patient and you really try to listen and understand
and support people, could you have transformative outcomes? And fast forward several years,
what I've discovered is that some people who medicine is essentially given up on,
these teenage kids who have hemoglobin A1c's of 10 or 12 or 14, who are basically on a super
high-weighted death. These are the people who are going to have their first-heart attacks when they're
35. That you can do a lot and help them. And they feel paralyzed and they're looking for somebody who
can really understand how difficult it is and to provide a level of comfort and compassion. And
sometimes the first five visits, you end up talking about almost nothing at all. But you're
establishing a rapport and they get that you're going to be in a different mold than maybe the
other endocrinologist they've seen. And so I try my hardest, and this is really hard for me because
I love to talk, but I try my hardest not to talk and to just ask open-ended questions and to be
there. And in general, I found that if I'm asking questions and allowing them to have the space,
that we can open up. And ultimately they can begin to acknowledge that it's really difficult.
They're looking for new ways. They're eager to try it, but they are distrustful of this idea that
I'm just going to give them a short list, like a recipe, and then run away and expect them to do it.
So it requires patients, and this is especially true of teenagers, who that feedback loop of
giving them information and seeing them act on it is delayed by all their growth and development
and everything else. And especially with teenagers, it's so important to suspend disbelief and to be
there for them in a patient and loving way, even if they can't immediately respond in the way you
want. So we now have in the toolkit of treating patients with type 1 diabetes, we've got exercise,
we've got continuous glucose monitoring, we've got carbohydrate restriction.
Are there any other apps or technologies or things that you think are paramount to helping,
or foods for that matter, meaning packaged foods that are particularly useful? In other words,
if you're a parent and you're listening to this, or if you're a person and you're listening to this
who has type 1 diabetes, and you just, this is all news to you, you're listening to this and this is
totally blowing your mind, what do you need to go out and get to get started? Well, I mean, CGM is
essential. And I'm assuming, are there any insurance companies that are not covering CGM for type 1?
Plenty. And... Jesus Christ, seriously? Yeah, well, part of it is a huge fraction of people in our
country now have these high deductible plans. So they're on the hook for their healthcare expenses,
and when their kid is healthy and everyone's healthy, they're good, and all of a sudden,
kid gets diagnosed with type 1 diabetes, and it's like $10,000 a year? Yeah, $10,000 a year.
Right, the insulin cost alone can just kill these families.
But CGM is really important. And then in the toolbox, there's a few other key things, but the
most important thing is information. So you've got to have Bernstein's book. You should be following
type 1 grit, which is this Facebook group, which again, which is a wonderful place to learn about
low carb. There are wonderful podcasts and also some terrific YouTube videos talking about the
intersection between low carb and type 1. I want to put in a plug for an organization called Low
Carb Down Under, which is really a wonderful group of people. Dr. Rod Taylor in Australia.
In Australia. Yeah, Dr. Rod Taylor is an amazing character. He's an anesthesiologist in Melbourne,
and a passionate advocate and supporter of all things low carb. And his organization
goes around the world doing AV capture of low carb talks. And so on YouTube, they have a YouTube
channel with over eight million views on various low carb things, including some terrific talks on
low carb by, for instance, Dr. Troy Stapleton, who's a radiologist who got type 1 diabetes himself
and figured out how to hack it using low carb. Where does he live? He is in Brisbane. Oh, okay.
He's an amazing person. Very nice. So there's this growing community of low carb nerds who are trying
to help people with type 1. And again, there's a bunch of different places where it's happening.
Another really nice resource is Adam Brown's book, which is called Bright Spots and Landmines. And
he works for Close Concerns. And he wrote this book essentially as the manual for diabetes that
he wished he had been given. And it contains lots of tips and tricks about how to think about living
with type 1. And it's from wellness and to exercise, to sleep, all the way to very practical tips around
low carb and nutrition and type 1. How careful does someone with type 1 diabetes need to be if they
go on a ketogenic diet? Obviously, in patients with a normal pancreas, even those who are somewhat
compromised by type 2 diabetes, I'm not aware of any case of ketoacidosis, diabetic ketoacidosis.
But in patients with type 1 who have no insulin production, that would have to be a real concern,
wouldn't it? Well, I think that there are some interesting intersections in between a hardcore,
I'm not talking about generic low carb or low carb high protein, all of the Bernstein method.
But let's talk about the people who were trying to get into nutritional ketosis with a beta-hydroxy
butyrate that hovers around 1 to 2. Well, those people have a couple of unique problems. And one
is diabetic ketoacidosis, as you mentioned. Again, for the folks to understand why that's the case,
and you or me, even when I'm fasting and I fast for a week at a time, my beta-hydroxybutyrate
level will reach 6 or 7 millimolar. But it's not going to reach 10 millimolar. It's certainly not
going to reach 12 or 14, which is where we start to see the acidotic changes. Because eventually,
that ketone is going to elicit some response from insulin. Right. In the person who has
no beta cell reserve, that ketone can go unabated. So prolonged fasting in a person
who lives with type 1 diabetes is probably a bad idea because you could get your beta-hydroxybutyrate
to 6 or 8 or 10, and you could start to feel sick. Another issue is it's a new phenomenon called
euglycemic DKA, euglycemic diabetic ketoacidosis. And we're seeing this in these sodium glucose
cotransporter inhibitors, these SGLT2 inhibitors. And it's a very bizarre phenomenon, but in people
with type 1 diabetes who go on these sodium glucose cotransporter inhibitors, they can get
a strange form of DKA where their glucose is not elevated. And it has confounded the field,
and there have even been deaths associated with this. There's currently clinical trials,
and full disclosure, I've been a consultant on one of these programs. Does this only occur
in patients with type 1 diabetes or can patients with type 2 diabetes who are the predominant users
of the SGLT2 inhibitors also get this euglycemic ketoacidosis? We think it's mostly type 1s,
but it may also be type 2s. And the problem, I think it's probably mostly type 1s. And here's
the issue, like how do you get this? Patients with type 2 can get DKA, but largely it's at onset.
It's not established disease. The people who have type 1 who've decided to take these drugs,
by the way, this is all off-label, and I'm not at all advocating it. There are clinical trials,
and we're trying to develop appropriate safety and monitoring for this. Listeners shouldn't be
given free license to go on these things. So this is really complicated. But again,
if you're on a really potent glucose lowering agent, which is what these SGLT2 inhibitors are,
and you have type 1 diabetes and your insulin is infusing from your insulin pump into your belly,
and the catheter plugs and it stops infusing insulin, then normally you'd look at your CGM
and you'd see, okay, my glucose is rising. I must have a problem. But if the glucose lowering
agent is essentially dragging all that glucose out into your urine, essentially what it does
is it's dragging away glucose, which is the primary biomarker of life-threatening insulin deficiency.
Elevated blood glucose is the primary biomarker of life-threatening insulin deficiency for people
who live with type 1. So when you look at your glucose and you see that it's normal and you're
on an SGLT2 inhibitor, it creates a situation of what I would call cognitive dissonance,
where people just don't understand that they're in trouble. And there may be a delay
in between when they had the plug in their catheter or some other interruption of insulin
infusion and when they actually end up recognizing it. And so I think that they end up receiving
medical care way later. It's also possible that they have elevations in ketones from these SGLT2
inhibitors. The beta-hydroxybutyr is a little bit higher in the SGLT2-treated population compared
to the controls. Okay. So that phenomenon of euglycemic DKA might also extend in rare cases
to people with type 1 diabetes who are on nutritional ketosis. And the way I think of it
is some of them may have depleted glycogen because they're not fully fat adapted. And many of them
will have very little carbohydrate in their intestines because they just don't consume that
much carbohydrate. So those people, if they have a plug in their catheter, might not see the same
sharp rise in blood glucose that you normally would and they might have a delay. So this is
all associated with pump use. In other words, we don't see this in people who are not using a pump.
Well, we also see it in people who forget to take their shots. And oddly enough, people with type
1 diabetes do forget shots on occasion, especially the teenage kids that I've cared for. So, God,
there's so many more things I want to talk about. Well, one thing I want to just mention is the
intersection of nutritional ketosis and hypoglycemic awareness. So there are people who are in
hardcore ketosis who have circulated beta-hydroxyburetor 1 or 2 who become completely
immune to low blood glucose. And I had a patient call me up and he goes, Dr. Jake,
guess what my blood sugar is? I said, what? He goes, 25. I said, why are you calling me and not
taking carbohydrate? He goes, I feel fine. So he- What was his BHB? Oh, like 2 or 3. So he'd done
the George Cahill experiment where he had- Except Cahill subjects were like 6 millimolar,
7 millimolar. 2 or 3 is relatively low to be thriving at 25 milligrams per deciliter. That's
barely over 1 millimolar. And so he has hypoglycemic awareness. And so to quote Peter Thiel, like,
is this a feature or a bug? If it's a feature, well, he's hypoglycemic unaware, but he's fine.
He's cruising around and he had the gumption to call me up. If it's a bug, well, maybe the delta
in between his blood glucose when he called me up with a blood glucose at 25 and a fatal low
might be relatively small. I have no idea. There are many other things I want to chat about,
but based on some time constraints, I know we need to wrap this up. So maybe we'll have to come back
and do a discussion about two other things I wanted to get into, which is sort of the future of this.
I certainly remember being involved in the care of patients who got pancreatic transplants.
That's obviously a transient solution that often comes accompanied with a kidney transplant.
There are certainly beta cell transplants, which have really not been that successful,
though it's always one of those things where it seems like it's just a year away from being
perfect. There's xenotransplantations of beta cells when you take the beta cells from another
animal or something that's non-human. That has all of its own problems associated with the immune
response. You talked a little bit about stem cells. And then of course we've alluded to
fully implantable or even non-implantable, but fully autonomous pancreases.
So that's a whole other topic that would be great to come back and talk about.
But I'd like to close on one other question, which is if you were to reflect on everything
you've learned in caring for patients with type 2 diabetes, what are the most important
lessons that would extrapolate to the non-diabetic population?
When I look at the cardiovascular outcomes and the weight gain associated with hyperinsulinemia
in type 1, I'm really shocked. And again, I think you have this unique population where you see
the insulin that goes into them and you see its direct impact on weight gain.
So we know that people consume very high carbohydrate diets and gain a bunch of weight
in type 1 diabetes. They're at risk for cardiovascular illness. And to me, that just
says that there's something about the standard American diet that's making us sick. And
ultimately we will be at risk for cardiovascular disease. That's the primary thing that humans
will die from. What do you think it is about hyperinsulinemia that seems to drive this? Because
this is the thing that I've always found fascinating is that... So when you look at
something like... So let's look at the type 2 diabetic cohorts. When you have patients
who are using drugs like metformin, which are lowering glucose to achieve better outcomes,
versus drugs that raise insulin, because the patients with type 2 diabetes still have the
ability to make insulin, you can, in both of those examples, get the same glucose level,
but in one patient there's a higher insulin level. Those patients have equal microvascular
outcomes, but they have different macrovascular outcomes. That's right. Which is a sort of natural
experiment to suggest that the insulin is playing a bigger role on the macrovascular disease. The
glucose is playing the role in the microvascular disease. Yeah. And in the case of these SGLT
inhibitors, they're the first drugs that have really shown a profound impact on cardiovascular
outcomes. This is secondary prevention for cardiovascular disease in people who have
already had an event, who also have type 2 diabetes. So, EmpicoFlows is an amazing drug when
reduced the cardiovascular complications by 40%. And the drug essentially drags glucose into the
urine, and it suggests that circulating insulin values themselves might be in some way contributing
to cardiovascular disease. The simple answer is, I don't know, there's a lot, there's a rich debate
in the mechanism. Yeah. I mean, do you think it is due to endothelial injury? Some people claim
it's all about the kidney and fluid and the amount of salt retention and something else.
But to me, as a basic scientist who grew up idolizing Dr. Cynthia Kenyon and the amazing
work that she did in C. elegans from the Daft-Dauer complex, those papers suggest that when you make
a modest alteration in insulin signaling, the worm lives twice as long. And that fundamental
observation has now been borne out in organism after model organism. But she did that, I mean,
it's tough to, I mean, I'm so familiar with Cynthia's work, so I don't want to bore people
with all of my nuanced thinking on this, but it's hard to make that exact comparison to us,
right? Because that was a modulation of Daft-2 and Daft-16. So, they were, she was upping
Foxo effectively and downing IGF and to get the real step function change in longevity,
she had to calorie restrict the worms as well. So, there are so many moving pieces in those
models that I guess, well, if you don't know the answer, that means we've still got some thinking
to do on this. But I want to go back to your patient, the one you told me about who's super
healthy, who's on six units of insulin. Yeah. I think that those people may be telling us something.
He's thin, he's active, he's on very little insulin, and he's quite vigorous. And I just
wonder whether carrying out these tricks to try to reduce your circulating insulin could be
incredibly beneficial. Well, part of the reason I love the CGM is it's the best proxy I have for
what I don't have, which is an area under the curve of insulin. I'd love to, people ask me
sometimes if you could wave a magic wand and have something that doesn't exist, what would it be? And
my first answer is a metabolic signature for autophagy. My second answer would be every
night I'd like to go to bed and have a little readout that says, this is the total amount
of insulin your pancreas made in the last 24 hours. Can you imagine adding that to the list
of my aura ring, the CGM, all the other things I think are really, really driving benefit in terms
of health, but to be able to actually know the AUC, the area under the curve of insulin produced
every day would be remarkable. And amazingly, someone with type 1 diabetes gets that for free.
They just have to look at the syringe and know what they injected. So if there's one thing
that that patient with type 1 diabetes has over the rest of us that don't, it's that they can
know at the end of the day exactly what their AUC of insulin is. Well, we can only estimate it
tangentially by looking at the things we look at, which are, you know, meaning someone like me can
look at average glucose and standard deviation of glucose and just try to minimize those as an
indirect proxy for that AUC of insulin. These people are really amazing and the most successful
are so dialed into their physiology. They're doing quantified self before it was even a term.
Yeah, exactly. Well, on that note, Jake, I know you're super busy here in San Diego today. And so
I really appreciate you making the time to come over here and share a little bit of your wisdom
and your insights. We'll have to do this again at some point, because as I said, there's so many of
the things that I want to talk about and I'm sure there are other people listening to this who do as
well. So with that said, until next time. And thank you. It's an honor. I really love your show.
I've been listening every week. You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash podcast. There you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for
my subjectively non-lame once a week email, where I'll update you on what I've been up to,
the most interesting papers I've read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance,
sleep, et cetera. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.