Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Dr. Alan Bauman, a hair
transplant surgeon who is one of the few people who is actually board certified in hair transplantation.
There are lots of hair transplant surgeons out there, but Alan is one of the very few who's
actually board certified. And I've gotten to know Alan very well because one of my patients,
actually two of my patients went to him for procedures a couple of years ago. I was sort
of blown away by the results because the best hair transplants are the ones where after the fact,
you have no clue that the patient had a hair transplant. Got to know him better and was
impressed immediately by how open he was to all of my questions. And believe me, there were a lot
of questions before I refer one of my patients to another physician, especially a physician who's
going to do a procedure on them. I want to be able to vet the heck out of them. And I want to
understand how they're doing what they're doing. And internally, we put together summaries of the
stuff that we learned. And Alan was so gracious in his ability to share his data, share his insights,
acknowledge what he didn't know that over the past couple of years, I've sent more and more
patients to him who have inquired about both surgical and non-surgical solutions to hair loss.
And this is of course true for both men and women. So at some point I said, Alan, we need to sit down
and talk about this. And Alan is of course one of the experts in the world on this topic. He's treated
over 20,000 patients. He's done over 8,000 hair transplants. The thing about this that's
interesting is you come to learn as I learned that this is a problem that both men and women think
about. And so in this episode, we talk about what hair loss looks like in both men and women. And it
turns out that pretty much nobody goes through their life without some change in their hair
pattern. Now for men, I think it's a little more obvious we see the results of hair loss, but of
course any woman who's been pregnant knows that just there and then she's going to experience a
dramatic change in her pattern of both gaining hair and then losing hair post pregnancy. But of
course for many women, this changes as they get older and once they go through menopause. And
I think most women aren't aware of some of the solutions that exist maybe as much as men are. So
we talk in great detail about what the non-surgical or non-invasive approaches are. And
there turned out to be many more than I had ever understood or even appreciated. And I think Alan
does a great job of explaining those. And then of course there are many invasive things such as PRP
that would be even pre-surgical. And then of course within the surgical side of hair restoration,
like anything, I suppose there are many different techniques and they have advantages, disadvantages.
And Alan does a great job here of explaining the method that he has chosen and why I think
it certainly seems to produce unbelievable results in the cases that I've seen. This is an episode
that has been, I've been asked about a lot in social media. So this is a great example of
bugging the heck out of me over social media for topics that you want to hear about. And both men
and women have said, please interview somebody who's an expert on hair restoration. And so
with that said, please continue to ask about things that you're interested in hearing about.
And hopefully I'll be able to continue to find exceptional people with whom to bring
expertise to you. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Alan Bauman.
Hey Alan, thanks for making time today. Peter, thanks for having me. This is great.
Yeah. Well, we met actually through a patient because I mean, a lot of the doctors that I
know who are doing really cool stuff, I'm somehow finding on my own, but perhaps just as often
actually, now that I think about it, I come to meet somebody through the work they've done
with one of my patients. And then that takes me down the rabbit hole because unfortunately,
a lot of times, a patient will go and see somebody and the outcome for anything, whether it be a
colonoscopy or whatever, it's not what you want. But in particular, the patient that saw you had
such a great outcome. And because you're in Florida where I just don't really have much of a network,
I was intrigued by the outcome and the patient insisted that I speak with you. He was like,
you got to talk to him. He's your kind of guy. You're going to connect. And I was like, of course,
yeah, I mean, I'm happy to learn. And so the first thing that amazed me when we spoke was that you
trained as a general surgeon. Correct. And I don't know why I thought that would be so unusual. Is
that common for people who are doing hair transplantation to have done a complete residency
in general surgery? Well, there are many general surgeons in the field of hair transplant surgery
but I would say years ago was mostly dermatologists. But hair transplant is kind of a potpourri of all
different types of areas of medicine. I mean, we have people in the field who are psychiatrists,
urologists, as well as the commons, you know, ones that you would see dermatologist surgeons,
vascular surgeons, things like that, who have made a transition maybe from a previous type of practice
into hair transplantation. And is there a like a board certification for hair transplant the way
there is for general surgery or thoracic surgery? So the American board of hair restoration surgery
is not recognized right now yet by the ABMS, which is, you know, the American board of medical
specialties. So it's kind of in its primordial stage. When I first got interested in hair
transplantation, there wasn't even a board certification test anywhere on the horizon.
And so of course my parents thought that I was going down a deep rabbit hole, maybe with a dead
end because I would never become board certified. And they were very, very nervous about my interest
in hair transplantation back in the early 1990s. But now it has a certificate in the way that
transplantation or surgical oncology, which are not board certified specialties are still
certificates. Right. Even restorative dentistry has these types of boards. And so it's a rigorous
process, one that was a lot of fun to go through, to be honest, because before that, you know,
I never took a test that was specifically geared to my primary specialties. All I do,
all I've done for well over 20 years is hair transplantation. So to prepare for that was an
exciting time. It's rigorous, written exam, oral exam. And you guys go through that every five
years or how often do you research? Oh, got the recertification. You know, I don't know. I just did
my recertification. I should know it's probably like eight or 10 years or something like that.
So what got you interested in the space? Because it sounds like you're not,
again, I don't know if it's the exception of the rule, but you went into surgery to do this.
Whereas as you pointed out, there are a number of people who come to this probably as a second
career in surgery, right? Right. So I kind of fell into it almost by accident. My first love
was plastic surgery, constructive surgery. My first mentor was a plastic surgeon, pretty prominent,
plastic surgeon on the upper east side of Manhattan. And he was close friends of the family.
His kids were my age. They had no interest in surgery. And he kind of took a liking to me. And
I, he said, Hey, if you're going to go to medical school, you're going to be residency in New York,
Beth Israel and Mount Sinai is where I did my general surgery. But this is way back when I
was a teenager. He said, Hey, if you're thinking about going into medicine, you should come and
watch me operate. And I was like, well, I don't know what kind of operation he does, but, you know,
I went to go see him and he was a plastic surgeon. And that was the first time I ever saw surgery
because back in the 1990s, this was in the 80s, no YouTube, no discovery channel. I mean,
I didn't really know what surgery was, to be honest, as a teenager. And I remember being there
at Beth Israel, getting dropped off in the lobby and looking over shoulder in the OR, you know,
he dressed me in scrubs, whatever, stand here, don't touch anything blue. I guess the security
wasn't so great. But, you know, I was looking over his shoulder and he was doing his procedures.
And I was blown away. I was like, this is what I want to do. I want to do surgery.
And from there, you know, it was years and years of just shadowing him and being mentored,
often on vacation times and things like that. And I pursued general surgery through, you know,
my interest in going that route through plastic to get to plastic reconstructive work.
Yeah, because back in that day, I mean, today there's a combined plastics track where you can
do three of general and three of plastics. But presumably when you went through it,
and even when I went through training, those were the exception. Most of them were still doing five
years of general surgery plus two years of plastics, right?
Right. And that's just what I figured I would be doing. I did an externship while I was in medical
school that happened to be, not happened to be, but coordinated with one of the hospitals where
he was in attending. So I got some very, very close mentorship there. I was doing things with him
in medical school that he wasn't letting his fellows do in rotation in the hospital. So it
was kind of interesting. I felt like I had a nice leg up. I got to watch him interact with patients
in his practice, as well as see him operate. And he really was an amazing teacher and a great
mentor of mine and really changed the course of my whole life really into the surgical end of
medicine and seeing how he dealt with patients, seeing his passion for the artistry and getting
the results taught me a lot. He was a low CD, which is great. That's exactly what you want in
a surgeon. Yeah. I think, I think you want that in your engineers, your accountants and your surgeons.
For sure. So I remember just being ecstatic, just every time we were together, you know,
it was like, what are we seeing next? And so I always thought that plastic and reconstructive
surgery, that's kind of where I was headed. And it really wasn't until I met a patient
who had had a hair transplant, did I even consider looking at hair transplant surgery as a potential
procedure that I would even want to perform. I thought it was all painful or pluggy looking.
Like why would anybody ever want to have a hair transplant? I just, it was just totally out of
sight out of mind. And when I, when I met this patient and I couldn't tell that he had had a
hair transplant, I was basically blown away. I was like, well, we need, let's talk about this for a
minute. You know, and of course he was getting something else done at that day. And I was the
good resident doing the intake forms and the paperwork. And he was telling me about why he
flew here or there to get his hair transplanted. And he was a layman. He told me all about, you
know, what he knew about the procedure. And I'm looking at a scalp, you know, do you mind if I
ask you, where did you get this procedure done? Where did you have this procedure? And he said,
Oh, up over there in Canada or something like that. And I said, no, where on your scalp? He's
like, well, right here at the hairline. And so he started to explain to me in layman's terms,
the use of single follicles, I mean, individual hairs. What year was this? This was in the mid
1990s. And what year was your training? So I was in my second year of general surgery or the end of
my first year general surgery. I was thinking to myself just after that conversation, because he
was so ecstatic about it. And it was really something I never thought about before. And it
was kind of unusual that the result was totally different than what I expected. Because you know,
as a general surgery resident, you think you know a lot, you know, you think you know everything.
And first of all, why would he have gone to Toronto to have the procedure done when everything
is here in New York, you know, which is where I was trained. So, you know, a lot of things kind
of struck me that way. But it was it was exciting. And to see that, and to see that it could be done
in a way that was totally unexpected to me. And of course, I watched my dad go through his hair loss
process. So immediately I'm thinking maybe my dad should look into this. And I thought then also,
well, if this is that good, maybe I should look into it and perhaps learn how to do it so I could
add it to my future practice later on down the line. And so that started me on the path to like
looking into hair restoration, hair transplantation as something maybe I would consider doing.
Well, I want to come back to that because I want to know about the genesis of the
surgical perfection. I mean, to me, one of the fun things about surgery is
kind of understanding how operations evolve. You know, I chose the residency program I chose
because of its proficiency in doing this Whipple procedure. And so you would go in there, you would
learn everything about how barbaric that procedure once was and how over years of being perfected in
surgical technique, even the type of suture that was used, the mortality of that could fall from
50% to, you know, 0.3%. So I want to actually come back to this, but I guess I want to take
a step way back and just talk about hair loss in general. So how common is it, I guess, both in
men and women? Let's start with that. So hair loss is super common. Almost a hundred million
Americans are suffering from some form of hair loss. And we know now it could be as close to 80
million men and even 46 million women out there who are struggling with the hair loss process.
So there's a lot of people out there who are experiencing hair thinning. They may be
experiencing receding hair lines, loss of volume, loss of coverage of their scalp. And it's a big
concern for many, although very much undertreated. And is there data on how many people care? I mean,
or what percentage of men with hair loss care versus what percentage of women? Like, is it naive
to assume that this is even though a smaller problem by numbers in women, that it might create
more distress in women? Well, first of all, everybody cares about hair, don't they? I don't
understand the question. Yeah, perhaps, right? No, but certainly it varies because you could be
a young guy in your twenties losing your hair and be really devastated by it. Or you could be someone
who has a slower hair loss problem with the exact same amount of hair loss, but at a much older age,
and you may be at a different place in time where you may not necessarily be focused on that hair
loss. And remember that in men, it's socially acceptable. I'm looking at your bare scalp,
you shave down to number zero or two or one or, you know, with a, with a trimmer, maybe that you
shave once every other day, perhaps once a week. So, okay, so there you go. But the point is, is
that in women, there's no socially acceptable option for female hair loss. And so it can be
much more devastating for sure, even though it's easier to cover in women. So there's, there's a
lot of nuance there. Women can lose, you know, half their hair and you would look at them across
the room and think that they have a full head of hair. And that's how the physical optics of hair
fibers work, meaning that you can lose 50% of your density. And from across the room, the coverage
will be pretty much the same. Okay. Well, that's really interesting, right? Because yeah, some
people listening to this might say, or get a mental image of somebody loses half their hair,
like one half of their head is bald. The other is not, of course, that's not what you mean.
You mean evenly distributed across their head, half the density, you know, you, you, every two
follicles become one, that's pretty easy to mask the longer the hair is, right? Right. And of
course, you know, female pattern hair loss happens in a very specific pattern behind the hairline.
That's where that density loss can occur. So it's not equally, it's very rarely equally distributed.
And same in men, there's a very specific pattern that you can see basically progressing from across
the room. But it's a, it's a commonly accepted knowledge point that you can, we see it obviously
every day in the office that you can lose 50% of the hair mass. So that might be a number that's a
combination of the density and the diameter of the hair. If you lose 50% of that, that's roughly the
break point between coverage and, you know, maybe some see-through to the scalp. Does that make sense?
It certainly does. Yeah. So you alluded to something I guess I hadn't even really thought
about, which was, you know, someone losing their hair very young. So is there a definition for
premature hair loss? Like, cause you hear that expression thrown out there, but does it mean like,
everybody to the age of X is supposed to have perfectly normal hair volume and anything,
anyone that loses hair below that it's quote unquote premature? No, that doesn't make any sense.
Sort of a bogus term. Premature is in the eye of the beholder, obviously. If you think that
you're prematurely losing your hair, just like prematurely gray, right? So there's a spectrum.
Some people go gray in their 20s, some people go gray in their 80s, some people never go gray.
So how quickly you go gray is genetically predetermined. If 70 is the new 50, then maybe
you don't want to be gray at 70. So hair loss is very much the same thing. But you know,
when we see young men, I mean, hair loss can start anytime after puberty, right? 20% of men
in their twenties, 30% of men in their thirties, 40% of men in their forties have visible signs of
hair loss. That's a quick heuristic with percentage by decade. Yes. Pretty darn close. And so what
does that mean? Remember I said that you can lose half your hair by the time it's noticeable to the
naked eye. So immediately after puberty, that's when hair loss starts. And this is predominantly
more in boys than girls though. Correct. We were talking about male pattern hair loss, right? When
I give you those numbers. So the female hair loss, typically it's a little bit later on and there's,
it's more multifactorial. We can see other things that are affecting the hair loss process.
You know, women are just more complicated, man. Yeah. They do have that luxury. So
you mentioned for a moment ago, like that, that if you're graying, that's genetically determined.
How much is hair loss genetically determined? In men, it's, you know, 99%, 98, 99% is genetically
determined. How quickly it's noticeable to the naked eye where it progresses to somewhat of
the pattern, you know, is it more loss in the front versus the crown? You know, there's some
variations there genetically. Of course, there's 200 genes that regulate hair and that would include
color, curl, texture, and all of those play a role in terms of coverage, right? Because again,
those are the physical properties and then hair styling, of course. So if you're a 20 year old guy
and you know, with your friends hanging out in the bar on a Friday night and you are experiencing
some recession of the hairline, you may be one out of your group of friends that's having some
significant male pattern hair loss. So for you, that's premature. You're looking at the rest of
the guys in the group, four or five friends, they all look like they got pretty much full heads of
hair and you don't. So that can cause a lot of stress and anxiety. I think in this day and age,
you know, Instagram age or however you want to call it, people want to look good and feel good
and they don't want to be rushed into having to accept the fact that they're going to look older
than their stated age. And I didn't realize that there were 200 genes that played a role in hair.
I never counted them, but that's what they say. No, no, no, no. Directional, yeah. So it's not a
simple, if your dad or your mom's dad or something like you, I've heard these things that say that
that's the direction it tracks. It sounds like that's not the case. Right. So X-Link,
mom's dad should tell you whether you're going to go bald or not. That's really not the case
anymore. We know that there's other factors that come from both sides of the family, you know,
the genetic components that play a role in all those factors that I mentioned, you know, the
color, the quality, the hair and so forth and speed at which the hair loss occurs and the patterns
and so forth. And I have friends who are brothers who one has total hair loss and the other looks
like he's got the thickest head of hair I've ever seen in my life. And maybe one's good at football
and the other good at math, you know, and so everybody, that's how genetics work. It can skip
siblings, it's recessive gene. So it could skip generations, you know, or it can be a wipeout.
I mean, I have the grandfather bringing in or the dad's bringing in the grandfather and then the
kids come in and, you know, and it's like a whole family affair because the, you know, the force runs
strong in that family, if you know what I mean. Now talk to me a little bit about what's going on
with women because I am aware of this only in that, you know, I've taken care of more and more
women over the past few years. I realized that it's sort of like you say, like, I don't even notice
it, but they notice it, right? And they'll say, you know, do you think that this hormone is right
in me or this hormone or taking a step back? I certainly remember watching my wife go through
pregnancy, right? Where her hair would get very, very thick. You have a baby, a lot of that hair
falls out and then it just kind of all grows back to normal. So putting that aside for a moment,
which is, it must be clearly driven by hormones. Of course. So the amount of follicles that are in
antigen when you're in pregnancy is a much higher percentage. So antigen is the growth phase. You're
going to have more follicles staying in antigen, longer time in antigen. So your hair will be thicker
and fuller during that time in pregnancy. And then when the hormones crash back down after childbirth,
then those ratios go back to normal and a shedding phase and a fluvium or telogen
of fluvium can occur in about six to 12 weeks. But if you're prone to female pattern hair loss,
sometimes you don't necessarily recover from that dramatic effluvium. So you shouldn't,
shouldn't just say, Oh, well, it's just pregnancy shedding. And that's it. Because sometimes women
come in and they say, look, I had my kid three years ago. My hair never rebounded from that
situation. It changed right after that. And the other thing I hear women say a lot
is the thickness was never the same after. So it's, they don't, I mean, I don't know that,
that one of us, meaning me or the patient is skilled enough to assess follicular density,
but thickness is very easy for the patient to accept. And, you know, I've heard women say a lot,
you know, after my third kid, like my hair is so thin and they're referring to the actual hair
itself. Right. Well, they could be referring to the hair fiber diameter and that can change just
with age. Honestly, it gets thinner with time, but it could also be that they feel like their whole
head of hair is not as thick as it was. And that would be a volume issue. So that could be the
sheer numbers of hairs that are growing at any given time, giving you what's just called the
ponytail volume. You know, a lot of women will say, you know, when I was in my twenties, I put my
ponytail in the, you know, with a scrunchier or whatever or a rubber band and it, I could just,
I turned it two times and boom, that was it. It was like a, you know, a horse's tail. And now here
I am 10, 15 years later and I have, I can turn it three times. Meaning they need another wrap.
That's an interesting litmus test I would have never thought about.
Yeah, for sure. So, and of course now in the office, we have scientific methods,
ways, devices, tools that can actually quantify different areas of the scalp and give us literally
cross-sectional bundle measurements of scientific ponytails. And we can go back to the same area
again and again, but we may be going ahead of ourselves in terms of diagnosis and treatments
and such, but there are ways to measure that. When someone says, I have less hair, I have thin hair,
we need to figure out what exactly does that, what are they saying when they talk about that symptom?
Because shedding is also another confusing symptom. People say, I have shedding.
Well, shedding happens every day. Hair follicles turn on and turn off. Hair follicles will grow
for five to seven years, a long strong hair, and then turn off, rest for 90 days. And then
the cycle begins again and a certain percentage of hair follicles are in that growing phase.
I mean, let's call it 84, 85%. But all of a sudden, if you do something to switch
those percentages, then you're going to get a thinner head of hair, meaning that there's
less trees in the forest perhaps. So, going back to the males for a moment,
which is pretty strongly genetically linked, as you said, my overly simplistic view of the problem
is dihydrotestosterone is a hormone that will precipitate this in a genetically susceptible
individual, which is why two of the most popular systemic agents to mitigate male pattern baldness
block the enzyme that turns testosterone into DHT. Is that the only hormone that's playing a role
or is that just the one that we have a treatment for? Well, that is the primary trigger according
to the data that we see right now. And the data is very clear. If you put someone on Finasteride,
about a milligram a day, they have a 90% chance of looking the same or better into the long run.
Long run for pharmaceutical clinical trials, you know, is about five years. It's not infinity,
but it's five years. And that tells you that, you know, we're pretty close to, that's a pretty safe
bet that DHT is the bad guy, you know, responsible for a lot of follicular homicide out there.
Does that mean that, again, as a thought experiment, I don't think it would ever make
sense to do this. If the moment a boy went through puberty, he was put on Finasteride,
are you suggesting that there may not, like that might be enough to mitigate baldness,
at least in men, because I think in women it probably is different, correct?
Well, there's always, and the answer is complicated. Yes, I think that would help
in a huge percentage. I'm not advocating that, of course, but remember that even if you put
someone on Finasteride or even Dutasteride, which is a stronger DHT blocking agent, right,
blocking both pathways to DHT, you still squeak by with a little bit of DHT. So there is still
some of that happening in the body, even with those strong pharmaceutical blockades.
And these things are not without their side effects. I mean,
a subset of men experience sexual side effects with them. And I think the literature in the
prostate land is still very confusing about lower rates of prostate cancer,
but potentially higher grade when it strikes and all of this confusion around-
I can tell you how that's been explained to us as care surgeons by the urologists that were
involved in some of those studies. For example, Finasteride, five milligrams is one of the more
prominent treatments for BPH, benign prostatic hyperteria, a large prostate. You put somebody
on five milligrams of Finasteride, the regular prostate tissue shrinks. And so that's likely
what's happening also at a one milligram dose. And so what happens if the normal prostate tissue is
shrinking and you go to biopsy that tissue, you might be more likely to find some high-grade
cancer or cancerous material in there just because the normal tissue is less voluminous.
So that's why not everybody in the world gets a prostate biopsy, but everybody in a clinical trial
does. So that can skew the numbers. And that can, I don't know if I'm explaining right, but that
one of the ways it's been explained to us in the world of hair restoration surgery,
that you're not causing the prostate to become cancerous. And of course, thank God people don't
die of prostate cancer. It's a very slow moving thing. Obviously there's very good survivability
if you should be diagnosed. But the point is that you're shrinking that good healthy tissue and
then you're more likely to find something on the biopsy and that more likely be high-grade.
And high-grade cancers in prostate are very, very rare. So it doesn't take much to skew the numbers
from like, let's call it, and I don't quote me, but let's call it a quarter percent to three
quarters of a percent. All of a sudden it doubled. Could be just a couple of biopsies to throw it
off. So you talked about finasteride, which of course is the generic name. Proscar is the five
milligram formulation of that and Propecia is the one milligram formulation, correct?
Correct. Which are both now off patent, obviously, as you know.
Were they developed in parallel or was it first a BPH drug and then they noticed,
hey guys, hair is falling out less. Oh, we don't need to use as much of this. Let's create a new
drug. I will tell you that Merck knew from the get-go that it was going to be a hair loss drug.
They also knew about the effect on the prostate. They went after the prostate indication first,
got that FDA approval, and then did the, and had safety studies and such done for that,
and then pursued the hair loss indication after. And it was FDA approved for hair loss
as a one milligram dose in 1998. Got it. So it was not serendipitous as minoxidil was.
And some people confuse those two stories like, oh, this prostate drug, they figured out it grew
hair. No, no, that's not the way Finasteride came out.
Wasn't minoxidil at least systemically a blood pressure drug?
Yes. So I think back in the seventies, minoxidil was administered for hypertension. And it was,
I think it was people who were on dialysis honestly that were being noted to be on this
drug for a long, long periods of time. And the people running those clinics were seeing
patients on minoxidil, oral minoxidil, and they're literally growing hair on their knuckles almost,
and seeing hair growth in other places. And that's how they, and it wasn't really that great of a
blood pressure drug, minoxidil. And so that's when they decided to move into a topical.
One man's side effect is another man's indication, right?
Yeah, yeah, for sure. The story of Viagra, not quite as elegant, but similar. So we'll come back
to minoxidil because it's topical. And that's what Rogaine is by brand name?
Correct. So Rogaine was the first drug, Rogaine was a minoxidil formulation with propylene glycol,
and that was the first FDA approved medication for hair loss. So that is an important data point
in the history of hair loss. You know, when we write the history books, that really started
hair loss as something that we can treat and the beginning of the end, if you will,
of a snake oil era. So Rogaine is purchased over the counter, correct? So today Rogaine's available
in a number of different formulations over the counter. You can get 2% or 5% solutions or foam
versions. There's generic versions all over the place. But the problem is, is that most of those
are very, very irritating to the scalp. They can be very greasy or gooey. The foam versions,
if you have any kind of hair on your head whatsoever, it can be very difficult to apply
to get into the scalp. So those formulations have some issues. And that's why Rogaine,
if you will, or over the counter minoxidil is consistently ranked as the most disappointing
hair loss treatment ever by Consumer Reports. They had a big report on that a number of years
ago. And the reason is because it's very difficult to use. So I would say about 15 years ago,
we started looking at compounding pharmacies to really help us make a better minoxidil. Could we
create a minoxidil that was penetrating better, easier to use, less irritating to the scalp,
take advantage of some of the other knowledge that we have about the hair loss process,
like inflammation and so forth. What could we do to potentiate or accelerate the movement of
minoxidil across the epithelium into the location of the follicles where we need it the most?
And that's where we came up with some of these more sophisticated formulations like AD2M and
AD2F and so forth. All right. Well, I want to come back to that as well, because that sounds
super interesting. Going back to just close the loop on the pathophysiology in the women who,
and again, separating it from sort of the pregnancy cycle. You have a woman who 20 years
after or 10 years after having her last child starts to say, my hair is getting thinner. And
it's to the point where she's noticed that either just based on the volume of hair coming out in
the shower, brushing her hair on a pillow or whatever, and or even just able to visually
see the difference. What do we think is driving that acknowledging that it's going to be more
complicated than just her DHT, which is probably very low. Yeah. Her DHT levels could be very low,
but she can also be androgen sensitive. So there is about a 50% success rate when you apply
finasteride in postmenopausal women with hair loss. When you say apply, you mean don't take it
orally. Orally. Oh, I thought that it was completely contraindicated in women. Well,
women of childbearing age, it can be used off label in postmenopausal women because the risk
is to a developing male fetus. Yeah. And that's the main issue because, you know, DHT in a developing
male fetus is the driver that makes men look like men for lack of a better way to explain. So,
you know, we would never want to use finasteride in women of childbearing age. And it's not FDA
approved at all in women. And for those reasons in particular. And but we do know that there are
some studies out there that showed that 50% of women who are in these clinical trials with female
pattern hair loss postmenopausal, right? No risk to a developing male fetus at all. We're treated
with finasteride and they got some response from it. So their DHT may be a driver in some of those
patients. So what androgen sensitivity is something that is, I mean, we don't know the incidence,
but let's say 50% of women with hair loss have some degree of androgen sensitivity that could be
driving it. And, you know, if you think about, for example, the most common hormone abnormality of
women of childbearing age with PCOS, what are the things that kind of roll together in PCOS
syndrome? There's acne, there's here's herecitism, hair growth on the face and acne. Did I say that?
And hair loss. And so those are the, what are the, all of those have in common?
They're all androgen.
Correct. So, so there, it is, there is a common androgen connection.
So do young women with PCOS also experience hair loss?
Yeah, it's devastatingly bad.
God, I just, I didn't realize that.
Yeah, it can be devastatingly bad.
Very common in PCOS. A lot of our-
And you're stuck because they'd probably respond to a five-alpha reductase inhibitor,
but they're in childbearing years, so you couldn't use it.
Correct. They're under treatment typically to improve their fertility.
Yeah.
So it's a delicate dance, you know? So we're left with other non-androgen modalities. And so that
would be minoxidilter to directly stimulate the scalp, maybe low-level laser therapy to impart
energy to the hair follicles, maybe injectable treatments like PRP and so forth.
Do those women in particular, these young women with PCOS,
can their hair loss be restored or is it permanent?
Well, that's a trick question because-
Meaning if you resolve the PCOS, you know, you can treat them and they can
bear children and such, will they also regain the hair that they lost?
It's tricky. So here's the thing. If you can normalize their hormones,
many of their hair loss symptoms improve slightly. But remember that once the follicle is,
let's call it just damaged beyond repair, miniaturized down to a certain level,
it reaches a point of no return. So the terminal hair is a good, healthy oak tree in the forest.
That's the- your best, best quality hair is a terminal hair.
Velus hair is the type of hair you have on the top part of your cheek. It's invisible. It's less
than two millimeters long. It doesn't have any pigment to it. And it's very thin in terms of
its diameter. So if a follicle was producing a terminal hair and then it miniaturizes all the
way down to now creating a velus hair, you're out of luck. Meaning that there's nothing that we know
of that I know of that's going to revive that follicle and get it to regain any kind of
significant amount of growth. So whatever kind of hair loss you have, male, female,
the idea is that you got to take action soon to protect the functioning of the follicles before
there's that point of no return. That makes sense. You alluded to Rogaine being the first
drug or topical agent that actually had clinical efficacy, which therefore, I think you described
very nicely as the beginning of the end of snake oil, not the end, but at least the first shot
across the bow that this could be a legitimate industry. Correct. Just briefly, what are some of
the top three, top five snake oil things that were being peddled out there to people? Oh gosh,
well, we'd have to go back to the history books, but there were all kinds of tonics and such that
were promoted through advertising and so forth. When you look at old Meg,
there's always ads for exactly some tonic or some ridiculous chemical that you could-
Dr. Johns, whatever, you know what I mean? There's always a picture of a woman with a
beautiful long head of hair. What happened was that then, I guess it was Johnson & Johnson or
whoever it was that had Rogaine was then able to say, you can't advertise hair growth from that
kind of lavender oil extract because we have FDA approval for that now. That was the method that
kind of started to clear out the industry, if you will, moving some of those literally oil treatments,
tonics and so forth that had no clinical efficacy whatsoever out of the market. Because now,
if in order to advertise hair growth, you had to have that FDA clearance. You had to have that
FDA approval behind you. We don't have to do an exhaustive list now, but I would love to list to
an exhaustive link in the show notes. What are some of the snake oils you're seeing out there today
that people come to you saying, I've been on this and it hasn't been working or what do you think
about this? Well, there is a long list, but here's the thing. You have to be careful because people
say, oh, well, Rogaine didn't work for me. But remember we said earlier on that-
Yeah, application matters.
Application makes a big difference. Compliance. Most people, they pick up a bottle of Rogaine,
they're lackadaisical about it, they don't do it twice a day, they can't get it on their scalp,
they have some kind of irritation, they don't know that it's working. So a lot of it is expectations
too, right? So people say, well, yeah, Rogaine didn't work. Or this handheld laser that I bought
back in 1999, it was supposed to grow hair, but it doesn't. But well, the problem with, for example,
that small little handheld laser is just that you're trying to water your lawn with a watering
can when really what you needed was a sprinkler system, you needed a different type of delivery
system. So we kind of get into trouble sometimes saying, well, people thought that laser was a
bogus treatment. Even my colleagues for many, many years thought that low-level laser therapy had no
influence on the hair follicle. And obviously they're all proven wrong by the exhaustive studies
that have been done now and all of the FDA clearances, which prove not only safety,
but certainly hair growth. And we've seen patient after patient.
But what about biotin and things that you see people taking like these tablets or these makeshift
things? So biotin.
New York is full of doctors who, I just know this because when you do an intake with your patient,
you find out all the medications they're taking and there's like all these cocktails of pills
that they're taking for hair growth. And I'm obviously familiar with some of them like
finasteride, dutasteride, but I mean biotin, what is biotin?
Well, you have to know what they actually do. Biotin has been shown to improve keratin
production, not only in the animal kingdom, because it's used in horses who have hoof
issues. And a lot of that science is out there. You can put a horse on a high dose biotin and
their hoofs improve. And that would be important if you're raising thoroughbreds, for example,
because a hoof problem in a valuable racehorse is a big issue. So there's no question that
there's a lot of science and data out there. It's less honestly in humans. There's less data out
there. But you know, if you put patients on biotin, a high dose, let's say 10,000 micrograms,
nine times out of 10, they'll tell you their nails are getting stronger. And we know that you can do
hair tensile strength studies and put, you know, literally stretch and pull on those hairs and see
the strength improve. But remember that that's not going to improve your female pattern hair loss or
male pattern hair loss problem to any substantial amount. It may make the hairs that you have
stronger, but it's going to need to be coupled with some other effective treatment. And that's
where layering these kinds of therapeutic interventions are really, really important.
So have you ever had a patient come to you and say-
With a bag of vitamins?
No, no. Have you ever had a patient come to you and say, I'm 25 years old and everyone in my family
has lost their hair, you know, when they're in their forties. I'm, and it's male or female,
by the way, so feel free to answer the question differently. Is there anything I can do preventatively,
even though now my hair is still seemingly perfectly normal, but it look, if history
repeats itself in 15 years, I'm going to be losing it or it's going to be thinning.
Well, a lot of my patients come to me with that exact question and concern. Many of my
patients who we've transplanted or treated with other therapeutic interventions will bring in
their teenage sons or daughters and say, listen, I, you know, I got measured too late. Can you
measure my son or daughter? They're going off to college. They're going to grad school. Let's get
them measured. Let's see what's going on. And then the son or daughter may or may not have a concern.
Very often it's the parents, just like probably they paid for braces. So, you know, they're
concerned about keeping their, their child's hair intact or at least as long as it possibly can.
So we'll perform some evaluations and measurements. So we know that there's a hair loss risk in the
family. A father's hair transplant patient, obviously, or something like that. We'll use the
trichometers to do hair bundle measurements. We'll look at the areas that are permanent,
for example, in the back of the scalp. And we'll measure that and see what is their maximum
hair mass index. That's the, that's the term that we use for the number that is a combined
measurement of the diameter and the density in a given area of scalp. And then we'll compare that
area to an area that might be at risk, like the crown area or the frontal zone or in the temples.
And so it's normal to see a little bit less in the temple areas, but when you're going through
puberty, your hair mass is essentially all the same over the entire top of your scalp. So I can
pick up if they have a tendency towards hair loss very, very early on, way before it's noticeable to
the naked eye. They may not, young man may not even have a receding hairline. And we can tell
by measuring the instruments are so sensitive, we can tell already he's got maybe a, let's call it
20% loss in that frontal zone. Because you're sure that it's not just 20% less genetically.
Correct. It should be the same. You know, these areas are the same. I have patients that come in
and they get measured and they are the same. All of the areas measure A-OK. Now a lot of those
patients are, you know, really teenage years maybe, or women who have hair loss problems,
a different type of, not necessarily a hereditary hair loss problem, some other issue.
Is hair loss sort of like atherosclerosis where, you know, if you lived long enough,
everybody would get atherosclerosis. Is this one of those things where if you, you know,
because sometimes you'll see like, you know, like Ronald Reagan, even at the end of his age,
he looked like he had this thick mane of hair. If you did that high fidelity testing on him,
would you suspect you would have detected differences? I'm sure. Yeah, I'm sure that,
I'm sure that it's not the same. If someone figured out a way for people to live to be 500,
everyone's eventually going to lose their hair if they don't take some. I think so. I mean, you know,
there are a few exceptions. I have a friend of mine from New York. He's in the music business
and, you know, he's on the admin side, the managerial side. And man, he's got the hairline
that he had when he was a teenager. It literally goes straight across his head and it has not
budged. It has not moved and has not, I don't know what the exact density is. He doesn't let
his hair grow out. It's basically kind of like a buzz cut, but you can see that hairline straight
across. Now he, now I've come across tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands of people in
my life so far and I've never seen anybody else like him. So I don't know if it's 100% true,
but I would guess that it is something like that where over time you will see some kind of thinning.
So what are these risk reduction techniques that, or what do you recommend to patients in that
situation? Well, of course, in those early stages for men, sometimes the first visit to the doctor
is their visit to the hair doctor, honestly. And there may not be any other medical conditions
that we can necessarily pick up at that time that require, you know, drastic intervention.
But if we switch gears for a moment and look at a little bit of an older age category,
either male or female, when they start being on at the age where they're taking medications for
blood pressure or cholesterol, or they're on some mood modulators, those are some top, those are
like the top three types of medications that can really impact hair quality.
I didn't realize that. And is it always negative? I'm assuming.
Yeah, for sure.
So what were they again? So blood pressure.
So blood, yeah, antihypertensives.
Anti lipid.
Right. Cholesterol modulating medigates.
And is there a particular type, is it SSRIs or is there a particular type of,
you were a little vague in your description of that.
Yeah, I would say it's just in general, anything that decreases the blood that's
being used to decrease the blood pressure. I can't say if it's only SSRIs, but it's a general
rule. If they're on some kind of blood pressure medication, typically they can correlate. If you
ask them a point of questions, you can sometimes see at the time that they started that medication,
that there is some effect on their hair.
Now, how many of those things are sort of hypotheses you have versus documented facts?
Is that, I guess, I mean, not that I'm in this literature, but I didn't know any of those things
actually. I didn't realize that hair loss was a side effect of those meds.
Well, it's just been so clear. I mean, I've treated about 20,000 patients and many patients say,
you know what? When I started that medication a year ago, fill in the blank, you know,
cholesterol medication, that's when I really started to notice my hair changed.
And when women tell you that their hair has changed, unlike many dermatologists out there,
we believe them very much so.
You're going to upset the dermatologist. Why don't dermatologists believe them?
Well, the general feedback from most of my patients is that they've been around,
unfortunately, they've been around the block to a number of different physicians,
maybe endocrinologists, dermatologists, a primary doctor, family doctor,
whomever, doing all sorts of blood tests, looking for why their hair is thinning.
And no one has ever even looked at their scalp, measured their hair, or talked to them about
potential treatment options. Except maybe on the counter, Rogaine bottle on the way out the door,
hair catch. So a lot of dermatologists have a certain bias where they look at the woman who,
as we've talked about, looks like she's got a full head of hair and say, well,
you're not dying of cancer, so you're okay. And so this is not, I wouldn't say, it's a sweeping
comment that I've made, I wouldn't say it as appropriate for every single dermatologist
out there. And I think that many derms are starting to wake up to the fact that hair loss
is important, something important to treat. And then it can be devastating for many men and women
who are experiencing it. So my heart goes out to them if they've been to a dermatologist or several
and kind of been ushered out the door saying, well, we're here, we're lopping off cancer
growths over here, that's what we do. So you got all your hair, your hair looks fine.
Are there dermatologists in high volume places like New York and Florida that would be doing
what you're doing, which is they're taking a sort of either surgical or non-surgical approach,
but basically doing pure hair restoration. Like it sounds to me like one of the problems in that
scenario is, if you seeing a dermatologist who's mostly interested in skin cancer,
it's like you might as well be asking your radiologist that question, right?
Yeah. Well, unfortunately, dermatologists often hold themselves out as experts in skin and hair,
but yet they have little ability to diagnose the hair loss process. They have no interest in
measuring or monitoring or prescribing even a treatment regimen and keeping a patient compliant
with it. So it's just kind of like a doorknob conversation for them and they don't have the
time to do it, honestly. I mean, a good strong hair loss consult in my office takes at least an hour,
typically. Patients usually spend about an hour and a half in my office when they come in for
a consultation. You're not going to spend an hour and a half with your local derm, certainly.
You know, they're going to do a quick exam, you know, look for some funky mole and then
kind of send you on your way. So they don't have an hour to spend with you. So I think it's
part of it is that those practices are just not simply set up to treat hair loss.
So I mean, the takeaway is, I guess, if you go to see a doctor about a concern you have on hair loss,
find a specialist. Find someone who's going to do a bunch of measurements. You want to make as many
objective measurements as possible. Absolutely. Well, find somebody who does it full time.
That's their area of expertise and specialty. And yes, who has those tools at their disposal to
measure and monitor and figure out what's going on or whether it's genetic testing to look at
androgen sensitivity and that postmenopausal women. I mean, a lot of derms don't just don't
have access to some of that stuff. And what, so what were the tests again,
you do a test of tensile strength, you do density and then you, what sounded really interesting was
the comparison density test, right? Where you do density in a region where there's never going to
be hair loss, make that your control and then look at the crown. Yeah. Crown or frontal and
temporal areas or anywhere really that the thing is occurring. You know, you have to look at the
scalp and you have to see is the skin tone normal. And you know, we've spent a lot of time talking
about hereditary hair loss, but there are many other types of hair loss. So if you're figuring
out what's going on in each of these different areas, you know, requires someone to look at the
scalp and see what's happening. How many times do you look at the scalp and you see something
completely unrelated, like, you know, a fungal infection that can completely be treated and
ameliorate the whole situation? Quite often actually. And one of the things that we've
learned, I say I've learned over the past, maybe five to seven years is the impact on scalp health
to hair growth. And you know, we had kind of an inkling that maybe this was important,
but there is some good data out there, journal articles and such that talk about,
especially coming out of like the dandruff, if you will, treatment protocols of zinc,
pure thione zinc and some other treatment protocols for Malthy's the yeast overgrowth
that you get in the scalp that show that if the inflammation and the overactivity of those
populations are out of control, then you can get a detrimental effect on hair growth.
So we know that today, that's that scalp health is important so that the soil in the forest needs
to kind of be fertile. And if it's really inflamed or there's inflammation, you know,
if there's inflammation going on, that can definitely shut down the follicle and impair
hair growth. So that's important to look at that. If somebody has dandruff, do we have a sense of how
much that's increasing their risk of hair loss? So dandruff is kind of a nonspecific symptom,
right? So flakes, right? But flakes could be thick and yellow, they can be small and white.
Your scalp could be oily and dandruffy, they could be dry and flaky. So, you know, that's a
whole other deep discussion on trichology, which is the study of the chemistry of the scalp,
essentially, where we look at scalp pH levels, moisture levels, sebum levels, and really try
to assess what's the right protocol of scalp care, just like you would do that. An esthetician might
do that for your face, for your skin of your face. Well, we want to treat the scalp in that same kind
of way, figure out, well, what's the right protocol? How often should you shampoo? What's
the right shampoo for you? And that's not sometimes a simple question to answer, especially if you
ever, well, maybe for you it is. But if you walk down the shampoo aisle in any supermarket, you
see that there's thousands of choices, right? So there's got to be some confusion there.
Yeah. Do you have any takeaways on what people should be doing? Are there any do's and don'ts
with shampoos and conditioners? So I think the best thing, well, of course, the do's and don'ts. So
shampoos and conditioners, if you have any length of hair, you should always follow your shampoo
with a conditioner. Shampoo is like a degreasing, essentially. It's a cleanser. And if you shampoo
in a harsh way or with a strong surfactant, let's call it, then you're going to strip out a lot of
the natural oils of the scalp and also of the hair and a conditioner replaces those natural
moisturization of the hair. So it's kind of important to do both of those things.
But there's a huge spectrum of different types of shampoos. First of all, shampoo is not going to
cure your hair loss. So when you asked circling back about some snake oil type treatments,
there's no one shampoo that's going to fix your hair loss situation. But again, you have to
understand if we can rectify some imbalance at the level of the scalp and reduce inflammation or
tackle a fungal overgrowth, and we're going to start to improve some things. And if we have some
ingredients that maybe we want to apply in the shower while the scalp is kind of steamed, if you
will, you know, sometimes that's the right time to do it. But I guess the point is that finding
the right shampoo and conditioner regimen for you has to do with some of the variables that I just
mentioned, the scalp pH level, moisture level, oil level, what's your natural sebum production?
What does your hair care regimen look like? Does it require a lot of product or hairspray or things
like that that need to be rinsed and washed out? Are you in a dirty environment? Do you live in the
city where there's smoke and toxins and things like that, you know, and debris that you need to
wash out of your hair on a regular basis? So how does somebody, I mean, given that I don't think
about this problem, how does somebody who does think about this problem find out? I mean, is
this something where you can go to a website where there's like a, you know, if you fit these
criteria, this is the shampoo conditioner combo you should use? Well, there are just some general
guidelines, right? So if your hair is kind of long and curly, for example, let's call it even kinky
or afro type hair, then you need like durable conditioning. You need conditioners that kind
of stick around for a while. If your hair is on the other end of the spectrum, let's just call it
like thin and kind of limp, then you need very, very light conditioners and you want to make sure
you're using shampoo that strips out a lot of that oil so that you get some weightlessness to
the hair in order to style it. So there's, there's some general guidelines. I remember when my
daughter was little and I would give her a bath. I don't know what this might've been just a total
wives tale, but I remember that I was told shampoo is more important in the scalp conditioner,
more important. So you would start the shampoo at the head and work out to the ends. And then when
I would put the conditioner in her hair, I would start at the ends and work up. Is that total
nonsense? No, it makes some sense because the ends of the hair are the ones that are typically the
driest. It's, it's been around the longest. The hair doesn't self-repair. It's a keratin fiber,
right, that your body has produced. It's not alive. So when the fiber is long, it means it's
been around a long time. And so the tips of the hair is the part where you're going to see a
fraying of the hair, right? It's the part that looks the driest. It was the part that's been,
had the most exposure to UV radiation and everything else, a heat, or if you've done
a Brazilian blowout or some other straightening treatment or curling treatment or coloring
treatment, the part that's received the most amount of abuse is the tips. And so the tips of the hair
are typically the ones that look the unhealthiest and feel the unhealthiest. They may be rough. The
cuticles starting to peel up. The ends are starting to split and fray. And if that continues,
obviously, then that's, then it could lead to hair breakage, which can actually is a very common
problem for hair loss in women or trigger of hair loss in women. The hair breakage,
literally that they've, they've stressed out the fiber so much that the fibers are actually
breaking. And we see that with harsh chemical treatments time and time again, or the new
trends for flat ironing and such, you know, where you put the hot ceramic flat iron again and again
and again and again and again on your hair to straighten it, to straighten out the curl.
And so that application of heat and or other products can degrade the hair fiber. So you
should condition that hair itself rather than the scalp. But don't forget that sometimes the
scalp needs a little love too. And we have a bunch of different types of products that are for
exfoliation and for moisturization and inflammatory is and things like that. I mean, obviously,
if you have a severe psoriasis issue, we need to get those flakes out of there. We need to treat
that psoriasis, you know, that's a bigger bit of business than just trying to like, well,
what kind of shampoo should I buy at the supermarket? Right. So once we get to treatment,
when I think about this, I kind of create four buckets. So I don't know if this is right or wrong,
but you know, we've talked a little bit about systemic treatments. So something that you take
like a pill where it's going to act, you know, across your whole body, but you reap some benefit
in the hair follicle. And then we've talked a little bit about topical as well, like, you know,
minoxidil. I don't know if we would consider laser also topical, but maybe that could be
considered something topical. Well, let's talk about, for example, putting oral and topical
medications or pharmaceuticals in one bucket. And then let's talk about non-chemical therapies
in another. Okay. So our non-chemical therapies would be laser and or PRP. And so a lot of times
during a consultation process, we're looking to try to institute something that's going to help
someone's hair loss issue. And they may say, you know what, I just don't want the risk of side
effects of this drug. I don't want to apply this medication into my body. And I can certainly
understand that they may want to try something that's non-chemical, whether it's a real or
perceived value of less side effects. Laser has no side effects, for example.
I see. So you think of laser PRP topical as maybe something you would try even before you go
systemic. I mean, for a patient who wants to be stepwise, obviously you could do them together.
Well, for men and for women, it's going to be different. So for men, we talked about the fact
that finasteride knocks out the DHT level. And that's the primary treatment. It's a strong
treatment, 90% success rate, very low incidence of side effects. So for men, we're almost always
going to consider that. Correct. We're going to talk about that first. Now they may say, hey,
no way. I don't want to do anything that's going to lower my DHT level. And they may have heard or
read about side effects. Or they have side effects. They may have side effects. So there's ways to get
around side effects, changing timing of the dose, frequency of the dose, the amount of the dose,
moving that finasteride from an oral treatment to a topical with a prescription product, like
82F is a way to get around that. So that would be for men. Let's try to at least address the DHT
issue first. And if we're not going to go that route, then let's choose from the other tools in
the toolbox. Now for women, because DHT is not the issue most women are of childbearing age,
we're not even thinking about finasteride for them. We're going to be looking at laser light
topicals as kind of the first types of therapies and maybe PRP. So talk to me about why does laser
work? Why does it work? Or how does it work? Laser works by imparting energy to the follicle. So
we know now photobio modulation is a very serious science. Dr. Michael Hamblin did much of the
lion's share of the research at Wellman Center for Photomedicine here in Mass General in Harvard.
He described, and this is going back now almost 15 years or more, the mechanism of action of low
level laser therapy. How and where the photons of light in specific wavelengths are accepted at the
level of the electron transport chain in the mitochondrial membrane at the cytochrome C oxidase.
And what you get is a hyperpolarization of that mitochondrial membrane. And if you remember back
from basic science that those ions flowing back and forth into and out of the mitochondria is
really what generates ATP for kind of a simple way to think about it. ATP is the energy center
within the cell. And if you can charge up those energy centers, if you can make those mitochondria
kind of fire up and produce a lot of fuel, you end up getting a better, stronger, healthier hair
growth. Do we know that in people who are losing their hair, there's a deficiency in ATP production
at the follicle? Or is this something that we're doing to override whatever it is that's
potentially causing the issue? We're trying to override it. And it's the same thing with
minoxidil. When you apply a topical medication like minoxidil, you know that it has nothing to
do with the DHT, but you're basically pushing that gas pedal all the way down to the floor,
trying to push that follicle into the best possible growth. What is the mechanism? I forgot.
It's so funny. I've never seen a patient take minoxidil for blood pressure. And yet I sort
of remember studying this on USMLE part one. What is the actual mechanism?
Yeah, it's a potassium channel opener.
Okay. And so what is that doing to the follicle?
So that's a great question and probably beyond my pay grade, but there are some many physicians,
great colleagues of mine in the UK who have kind of figured all of that out and I can provide that
research for you. But essentially what minoxidil does is it keeps the follicle in the growing
phase. So remember we talked about the antigen, which is the growing phase. And then of course,
the catechintelegin, those are the resting degeneration phases of the hair follicle.
And we know that in a certain area of scalp, there's going to be about 84, 85% of the hairs
in a healthy area, 84, 85% of the hairs are in a growing phase. But as you get to a male pattern
hair loss or female pattern hair loss situation, many, many more follicles are in a resting phase
than in a growing phase before those ratios change and the hairs spend less time in a growing phase.
So the antigen phase starts to shorten. So that's one of the reasons why if you have someone with
thinning hair, whether it be male pattern hair loss in the hairline or female pattern hair loss,
let's say in the frontal zone right behind the hairline, typically you can make a part with your
comb and you can see these very, very short kind of spiky hairs. That is indicative of miniaturization.
And if you look at the microscopic level, you'll see even shorter, thinner,
weaker, wispier hairs than that. So what happens is that when you put somebody on minoxidil,
resting follicles start to kick into action and grow. So you're going to start to produce more
fiber. So fewer spikes, more of the long guys, right? And the guys who are already growing that
may want to turn off too soon are kept in the growing phase. So those, the antigen is going to
be delayed, meaning that the antigen is going to keep going. And we also know that the longer you
keep a follicle in antigen, the thicker the fiber becomes over time. So there's literally fewer
exits at the cellular level in the matrix at the base of the follicle near the dermal papilla.
The cellular material continues to aggregate in that area and almost like swell, essentially,
as long as you keep it in the antigen phase, you actually get a thicker hair follicle over time
and a thicker fiber as a result of that. So your question was, how does minoxidil work? It
decreases the amount of follicles that are in that resting phase, keep them in the growing phase.
And so you're going to get better, thicker, stronger, healthier hair from those follicles
that could be rejuvenated, that are not too far gone. Yeah. Okay. That was the next question I
was going to ask you. Thank you. So let's go back to something you alluded to earlier, which is
most physicians, this is one thing I know about hair loss. Most physicians I've spoken with
have said what you said earlier, which is you don't want to buy minoxidil off the shelf,
you should have it compounded. Correct. What? I didn't realize that there was foams and I didn't
know what the exact issues were. So that's obviously one issue you're trying to overcome
is create a different viscosity that makes it easier to reach the scalp. But what are the other
agents that they typically add to minoxidil to make it more efficacious? So Tretinoin, Retin-A,
is excellent to be mixed with minoxidil. Wait, doesn't, wouldn't that also aggravate the
scalp? Usually not. If the percentage is 0.025% that we're working with, you're not going to get
an aggravation, but there's a lot of good clinical data that shows that the combination of minoxidil
plus Tretinoin improves the hair growth. So there's some basic science that describes the
increased penetration. And then there's also on the results and increased hair density and hair
growth that you get from combining minoxidil and Retin-A. In, for example, the formula 82M product,
which is our most powerful, most popular treatment, most easily compliant version of minoxidil,
it's a prescription compound, obviously, you're going to have also a tiny little bit of flucinolone
in there. So it's a little anti-inflammatory. What is it? I'm not familiar with that.
It's a steroid anti-inflammatory. Oh yeah, that's one that you would put on your skin if you've had
like a rash or something like that. Yeah, it's very common in the dermatological world. There's
basically a whiff of that in the 82M formula. So even, you know, inflammation is such a big
topic on this podcast. It comes up in every disease. Interesting. I would not have thought
it was going to come up in hair loss. So I was part of a study in the University of Miami where
they looked at the microinflammation at the level of the hair follicle. We donated a number of
follicles from hair transplant patients from donor zones and recipient zones and such. And what they
determined is that there is an inflammasome, which is this mediator of inflammation that was
discovered and elucidated through some of that research. So there is microinflammation. It's very
well known male pattern, female pattern hair loss. There is a lot of microinflammation at the level
of the follicle. So we think that maybe not only could the flucinolone that's in the 82M be making
it more tolerable to the scalp, certainly people can have dermatitis from just about anything,
you know, you can put a piece of scotch tape on your head and have dermatitis from it. So maybe
it's keeping the scalp a little bit healthier in that way, but also addressing that microinflammation
right at the level of the follicle and shutting that down a bit. And that also helps us out in
understanding that there's some microinflammation also helps us understand some of the more
nutraceutical ingredients that we see. It also helps us understand maybe how some of our
sophisticated PRP creation techniques may improve hair follicle function. Once you understand that
there's some bit of inflammation going on, it kind of opens the door to some other modalities
of treatment. So we've established that for most guys, a combination of 5-alpha reductase inhibition
plus this type of a compounded topical minoxidil plus or minus the laser to hit. And it's so funny.
I'm totally familiar with that technology for some of the experimental use that's going on with
Alzheimer's disease for the exact same reason. It's hitting cytochrome C oxidase. By the way,
they're also using methylene blue, which is a cytochrome C oxidase activator as well. But I'm
guessing putting minoxidil methylene blue on the scalp isn't going to be a great idea because
every time you apply it, you'll have to spend an hour washing your skin to get the blue off.
Yeah. I don't know how that would work so well.
So that sounds like a pretty interesting regimen.
Unless you're coming here to Vegas to be part of the Blue Man Group.
Yeah. I saw a woman in the airport today that had that going on. So she would be fine,
but she looked like she had great hair. So I don't think she needs it. For women,
you've got those two options, which is the same compounded minoxidil. You don't have to make a
different formulation for women. We do not make a different formulation. AD2M works very, very well
in our female patients. Plus the laser.
Yes. They may use the laser. Plus or minus, they may or may not use low-level laser therapy.
One of the good things about the AD2M product, just for the women specifically, is that it has
a little bit of a skin conditioner and a hair conditioner in it. One of the main complaints
with over-the-counter Rogaine is that it just makes the hair nasty. It just makes it greasy
and gooey and basically unmanageable and styleable. And so the AD2M product goes on very, very clean
and dry. And we teach also how to apply it so that it's most active effect at the level of the
scalp and you really don't get it on your hair.
I've never really understood that. How do you apply it to... I mean, if someone's in the early
stages of hair loss or if it's a woman who barely has hair loss, how do you actually get it on the
scalp? Yeah. And it's a tricky bit of business. And if you're using a Rogaine foam version,
then forget about it. Most of it is not getting on the scalp. And that's part of the reason why
a foam is not necessarily such a great option for women. But what we do is we teach how to
part the hair. The bottle that the AD2M comes in has an applicator tip. So you actually put the
tip of the bottle directly onto the scalp when you apply it. So you're kind of parting the hair
and you're directing the application directly onto the scalp. So it may sound complicated,
but literally once you know how to do it, it takes you 90 seconds twice a day every day.
And that's the other piece of the puzzle. Most people who buy minoxidil over the counter
think that once a day is going to do the job. And that very, very rarely has any substantial
effect on hair growth whatsoever. And what is the requirement of the laser? How often
does that need to be done? So that depends on the type of laser that you have because the laser
energy that comes out of these different devices could be intermittent, meaning that there's a duty
cycle to the laser, right? How much time the laser spends on or off during any given minute
of therapy. And also how the lasers are kind of designed into the device to shine onto the scalp.
Is it something where it's a spot treatment that you have to move around? Like years ago,
we had the laser comb and you had to like move it all the way around your head every five seconds.
Pretty laborious. Today, the laser cap or cap therapy devices just sit on your scalp like a
baseball hat and the battery pack clips to your belt or sticks in your pocket and you could be
done in as little as six minutes. And you do that once a day or twice a day. So that would be, well,
different devices have different recommendations. So let's just start with the best of the best.
The capillis RX is really the top device. It's a physician only device. It has 312 diodes,
which is a lot. When you say physician only meaning you have to be in the physician's office
to use it. No, it's only prescribed and dispensed by physicians. Oh, I got it. You're not going to
get it like over the counter. You're not going to get it. You can't buy it on Amazon or Costco.
I mean, unless it's through the pharmacy or something. Not the 312. The RX device.
How much does one of these things cost? So the RX is $3,500.
Wow. But what do you say? Wow. I don't know. I guess I just think it's a lot of money.
Well, actually laser therapy is your least expensive treatment over time.
I guess because there's one cost and that's it. Correct. They last for 10 to 15 years. I have
many patients using the same laser caps that they did from 10 years or 15 years ago. All they've
done is swapped out about it. Yeah, when you put it that way, it's a buck a day.
Yeah. And no side effects, non-chemical. It's a great investment.
So let's talk about PRP. You alluded to it.
You did ask me how often you would do it. So the capillos or X is six minutes a day,
but there are other devices like the laser cap, which was 20 minutes every other day.
Got it. But it sounds like you can be doing something else.
The harder thing seems to me like the minoxidil because you have to apply it twice a day.
Yes. So sometimes, for example, we busy college students, kids just starting a job,
so forth. They may have difficulty applying something to their scalp twice a day. They're
living in the dorms and whatnot that may be difficult. So we may do something more like
laser or PRP for them. It might be easier for them to be compliant with that.
Although it sounds like it's harder to walk around with a laser cap in a dorm room than...
No, because it's covered by a baseball cap. Oh, literally a baseball cap.
Literally, it fits underneath a baseball cap. Geez.
Wow. Okay. I can't wait to link to a picture of one of this.
See? So, later on when we go down to the expo, you'll have a chance to see...
I'll stick it under my hat. Okay. You alluded to PRP. Now,
in say the world of orthopedics where PRP is used quite often,
I think the jury's still out on the efficacy. I think most orthopedic surgeons I speak with
believe there probably is some efficacy to PRP, though it obviously seems to be dependent on
two things. The technique used to basically create the formulation and the clinical judgment and
when and... Patient selection, basically, for lack of a better word.
For sure. Because think about it. If we relate it to the hair follicle for a moment,
if the follicle is dead and gone and you're hoping that your laser minoxidil PRP regimen
is going to do the job, what do you think that success rate's going to be?
Probably not pretty good. So, you can't come into a baldness clinic with total hair loss and think
that a PRP is going to solve the problem. It's not going to work. And so, I would imagine
orthopedics is pretty much the same. If you have someone who needs surgery because there's some
severe depletion of whatever, I don't know, it's cartilage or something else that's not going to be
gently fixed by a little bit of regenerative medicine, they're going to need surgery for that.
And PRP may not necessarily solve that issue. So, I think patient selection is a big
concern and as it is in hair loss and many other worlds of medicine.
So, I mean, you've sort of alluded to it, which is there's probably a sweet spot, right? Where
someone who's not experiencing any loss but is trying to be prophylactic, that's way too early,
and someone who's already experienced the death of the follicle, you're basically wasting time
and money. Correct. So, well, you're not wasting time and money if you have ongoing progressive
hair loss, right? But you may not reach your goal with PRP, but it may help mitigate future loss,
just like the use of minoxidilin laser is not going to bring back that receding hairline,
but it's going to keep it from receding further or faster.
Fair point. Yeah.
So, combination therapy, there's, again, thinking about what we do in practice every single day in
my office is part of the process is to prevent loss of the follicle function and enhance whatever
follicles you have. And then the other piece of the puzzle is to restore density to those areas
which are too far gone. So, PRP has a role in that, right? A PRP has a role in preventing
the loss of that follicle function. It enhances those follicles that are weak,
kind of like what minoxidil or laser might do for up to a point, right? And we would need to use
that over time. So, tell the folks listening how PRP works. I realize I'm sort of taking it for
granted that people know what PRP stands for, what it is, how you harvest. Can you spend a
minute just explaining if someone comes into your office and you decide that they're a good
candidate for PRP, tell me what the process is. So, PRP stands for platelet-rich plasma.
And platelet-rich plasma is an autologous treatment that means it's derived from your own blood.
So, in the office, we're going to take a sample of your blood and we're going to spin it in a
centrifuge, which essentially separates the formed components in the blood. So, red blood cells were
way much more than platelets do, right? Blood cells. And so, when you spin a sample of the blood,
you can then separate the blood components based on their mass, based on their weight.
And the reason why we want to do that is that platelets contain very powerful ingredients
called growth factors and cytokines. And their platelets are responsible for not only clotting
blood, like we've all learned in grade school, but platelets are responsible for tissue regeneration
and repair. They're like the orchestrators of repair in the body. If you get a paper cut,
platelets come to clot the blood and then they also orchestrate the repair of the skin in that area.
They're the first thing that kind of happens. Platelets get activated by that injury. They
release these powerful growth factors, which may call into action wound healing cells. It may call
into action or recruit stem cells into the area. They may then trigger other functions in the body,
like increasing new blood vessel formation and so forth. But what does all this have to do with
hair? So, what we found is that anything that helps out with wound healing tends to have a nice
positive effect on hair growth. And so, PRP was started, this dates back maybe, you know, 15 years
ago, PRP into the scalp, at least in our clinic, we were using it as a wound healing treatment in
conjunction with hair transplantation. And we, because I'm a born and raised general surgeon,
we know that anytime you want to cut the skin, you want to heal it. And so, hey, by the way,
low level laser therapy does that too. But PRP was one of the first indications was for wound
healing for chronic ulcers and to accelerate healing in diabetics and so forth. And so,
as a wound healing treatment, PRP works really, really well. And it was around this time,
some of our physicians were also noticing that when they applied PRP for wound healing,
they were also reporting some improved hair growth. And at first, I think many of my colleagues
were very skeptical about these early reports, but we were using PRP as wound healing adjunct.
I figured if we can get our patients healed a little bit more quickly, that would be a good
thing, less downtime, we'd get them back into their regular team more quickly after a hair
transplant, but we were noticing it as well. We were seeing this improvement in hair growth.
Let me ask a silly question perhaps. Presumably you were using it on the donor sites,
because that's where the incisions are made or were you using it on the like recipient site?
Both.
I see. Because, okay, makes sense.
Yeah, we were using it in both areas. The recipient zones, obviously, the ones that were
pretty much more visible at that time in, let's just call it on 2007, 2006, and that's really
when we got started with PRP. And our colleagues were also noticing that, as I said before,
that there were some improvements in hair growth. And so, we started to apply it a little bit more
aggressively in some of these patients and applying it into other areas of the scalp that
maybe we weren't transplanting. And lo and behold, colleagues and myself included were noticing
that there were some improvements in the thickness and the caliber and the length of
some of these miniaturized hairs.
What size needle do you use to inject it?
So, I use a 27 gauge half inch.
Is it painful?
To inject PRP. No, PRP is not painful because we use a complete local anesthetic block.
So, we're going to block the entire area that we're going to treat. People say, well,
of course, once the local anesthetic is in place, you won't feel anything on your scalp.
Obviously, that's how we do a hair transplant. People often say, oh my God, it's so painful.
Even if you put the local anesthetic in, that's going to be painful. No, it's not. We have a
ProNox device. It's a nitrous oxide delivery system. It's on demand. If you want to take
a couple of puffs on the nitrous, usually makes it 100% painless. And to be honest,
nine out of 10 patients say that it was dreamy when they had their treatment done.
So, the outcome should not be painful.
So, that's a good point for people to know.
Should not.
Yeah. I'm amazed you can get it out of a 27 gauge needle. I thought it would have been
too viscous to come out of that.
No, platelets are tiny. Platelets are super duper tiny. I mean, we can look up the exact
measurement, but-
Yeah, I was going to think of it there.
I mean, they're extremely small.
Yeah.
It's basically part of plasma.
Platelets are smaller. Yeah, but platelets are cell fragments that are smaller than red blood
cells. So, they're extremely tiny.
And just as a directional number, not that you're counting, when someone comes for a
quote unquote standard PRP therapy, how many actual injections do you think they require in
a typical treatment?
So, most patients want to know how many needles are you going to hit me with, Doc?
Yeah, exactly.
So, that's always the question. Of course, as I said, with local anesthetic applied appropriately,
applied painlessly, you will feel none of my PRP going in. So, you will feel none of the 700
injections that are required for the PRP.
Well, no, I wasn't asking from a pain standpoint.
No, I know.
More from a bleeding standpoint.
No, but for your listeners, they need to know that they're not going to feel any of the 700,
very, very tiny injections.
How long does that take you?
It takes only about 10 minutes.
Wait a minute. How can you do 700 injections in 10 minutes?
Well, actually, my nurse practitioner and I tagged team in the scalp, and so we do
half and half. So, but my thumb is pretty strong.
Wow. Each injection gets how much volume?
A tenth of a cc. It's pretty quick, to be honest. I mean, the whole treatment procedure in the
office is about an hour, start to finish. And most of that is honestly the preparation time
of the PRP.
I have patients who are being treated in New York, so they're not patients that you take
care of of mine who have had excellent results with PRP. And I know obviously our mutual patients
have as well, and we've talked quite a bit about it. Is it your expectation once you've decided,
or once, obviously, the persons that they're seeing in New York? I mean, there's lots of
good people out there. But once you're in the hands of someone who has a really good set of
patient criteria selection, are you pretty optimistic that PRP is going to move the needle?
Oh, yeah. I mean, PRP works well.
How often does one need to be treated that way?
Well, that's a great question. So, everyone's a little bit different in terms of the power and
strength of their PRP. Remember, this is not coming out of a bottle, this is coming out of your vein.
So, if you come to my clinic and you have 150,000 platelets per microliter,
you have a different platelet concentration than somebody has 250,000.
So, stop your aspirin before you show up.
Well, it is a smart idea. But remember that if you believe that the aspirin is simply just delaying
the activation of the platelets, I mean, as a surgeon, you know that all bleeding stops. So,
eventually, the platelets get activated. So, maybe it doesn't matter.
I'm not so sure that that's such an important, you know, hard rule.
So, remember how we used to give all those patients a ton of aspirin after splenectomies
and stuff like that when they were getting the macrocytic, or maybe it was the shape of
their platelets that was changing. I don't remember if it was the number of the shape, but okay.
I don't remember. But I'm not so...
You don't worry too much about that.
I really don't. I really don't. I want to know that I'm getting a good platelet concentrate.
So, I'll do a CVC at the bedside. I have a Coulter counter in the office,
unlike most physicians. I have the device as a Beckman Coulter counter.
And we'll do a CVC on the whole blood that comes right out of the vein immediately right there,
right before we do any kind of spin. After we do our, what's this called,
a proprietary protocol of spinning and separation and concentration of the platelets,
we'll do a final count on that. We'll use a couple of microliters, not much,
to get a final platelet count on what exactly we're going to be injecting. So, I can tell you,
if you come into my clinic, exactly how many platelets we're going to be injecting for you.
And I think that over the years, having done about 4,000 PRP injections,
I feel like we have a very, very good handle on how platelet count affects the outcome.
So, we're working on that down right now.
Something as simple as someone shows up with 150,000 versus 400,000, presumably the more that
they show up with, the better. Yes. And there's some good journal articles that describe the
effect of platelet concentrate on these biologic processes that we're interested in. So, physiologically,
we know that there's a dose curve. As you increase the concentration of platelets, for example, on
neovascularization, there is a dose dependent upward curve on that. So, the higher the platelet
concentration, the more neovascularization you're going to get. Now, there's a biphasic dose curve
on stem cell mobilization. So, as you go up on the number of platelet concentrates, there's a kind of
a sweet spot that occurs. And then if you go over that amount, then it starts to dip downwards.
So, what exactly is that concentration in both of those studies that I just said,
what is that concentration supposed to be? And according to that data, it says somewhere between
1.4, 1.5 million platelets per microliter is where that sweet spot exists. And what we're
trying to show in the office is that that correlates also at the bedside to the clinical response.
And I mean, I assume you're gathering those data. You've done 4,000 of these,
so you have your own prospective series? Yes. So, what I can tell you is that I think that there's
a strong correlation between the amount of platelets that you come to the table with and the amount
that we can concentrate. So, obviously, we have to maybe make some adjustments in our protocol
if you are kind of low on platelets. But again, there's some other things that we may not
necessarily be taking into account. Everybody has a different size and shape of platelets.
Let's say your platelets are low, but they're very big. We don't know what exactly do those
platelets contain. But again, there's some data in the clinical literature where we can correlate
growth factor concentrations with platelet counts pretty well.
This sounds to me like it's something that's still in its infancy where...
Absolutely.
I mean, that sounds like the crudest of all metrics, and it's probably an oversimplification
for what's really going on. And hopefully in 10 years, you have a different assay than just
something as blunt as the CBC, right? You can measure some cytokine or you can measure some
other functional property of the platelet that probably matters a heck of a lot more than the
number. Right. I mean, look, eventually, maybe there'll be a bedside PCR where we can figure
out exactly what exactly those growth factors are that are doing their job inside. But the other
thing that I've learned over the years of doing those thousands and thousands of PRP treatments
for nearly 10 years is the importance of the white blood cells. So the monocytes are a very,
very important component. I think they're underappreciated in not only in the literature in
terms of what they do in the body, but especially in PRP. And I'm a very strong proponent of the
importance of monocytes in the final PRP. And we say that our PRP is monocyte rich,
and I don't think that that's really a term that's caught on yet, but I think that it will.
And monocyte rich PRP might- Wait, so you can, obviously, it's easy to pull the platelets out,
but when you're looking at leukocytes versus monocytes versus eosinophils, you have a sensitive
enough centrifuge to get that banned? So the way that we've been able to do that is through a dual
spin process. So the dual spin process, for lack of a better way to explain it, the first spin is
kind of a gentle spin to take off the red blood cells. We don't want red blood cells in our PRP.
Red blood cells in the skin are extremely inflammatory. When those red blood cells
lyse, the heme is extremely inflammatory and there's a lot of-
Makes sense. Yeah, the iron would be devastating.
It's really bad. So we don't want that in the skin if we can avoid it.
So I prefer to have PRP that has less than 1% hematocrit. So the PRP may look pink in the
syringe, but it's a very, very small amount of red blood cells. Now, of course, when you're trying
to decant the platelets, decant the buffy coat, you're right up against those red blood cells.
So the first spin takes off the layer of red blood cells and leaves us with a plasma,
which contains the platelets. So the plasma-based spin, which is the second spin,
then essentially pushes the platelets to the bottom. So we've captured this maximum number
of platelets. We can take off the platelet pore plasma to as much as we would like,
leaving us with then a reconstituted amount of whatever we choose, concentration and volume
of PRP. So that process, that dual spin process, and I haven't found another one that has been
able to duplicate this, consistently removes the red blood cells, consistently gives me a very high
concentrate of platelets, and consistently gives me this bump or boost in monocytes.
And remind me about how many tubes of blood are you actually drawing out for the full treatment?
We take 60 cc's on the treatment. Okay.
So 60 cc's concentrates down to about seven and a half cc's of PRP.
Wow. That's incredible. And how many hours does it take?
What do you mean? It takes-
From the time you do that first prick of blood until you're injected-
It takes just an hour. They're walking out the door in an hour.
Okay.
They're out the door in an hour, man.
I obviously know very little about this specialty.
Yeah. So when you come in, you'll see.
Let's get to the meat of it, which is the transplant. So how do you think about-
You don't want to know how long the PRP lasts in my hands?
Okay, yeah.
Come on. This is really important because most dermatologists are spinning test tubes.
They're getting all two to three times concentrate. They're not getting seven to eight times
on the platelets. They're missing all the monocytes. And besides all of that,
they're booking their patients for every other month or every month treatment.
So the treatments that I just described to you that we do,
that proprietary protocol is essentially about once a year. And so people say,
well, you know, you could claim five years, you could claim six months. How do you know?
Well, we know because we measure. So we know that 90% of our patients get a positive response from
the PRP that lasts about 10 to 14 months. And that there's a small percentage of patients,
maybe 5% that need it more often than that. And then I have another small cohort of patients that
can get away with it almost every two years and that's it.
And what's the percentage of patients that are not responding?
Well, everybody responds to some degree. The question is, are they responding where they want?
So if someone comes in with a receding hairline, they say, hey, doc, I really want PRP here at the
receding hairline. If they're hoping for some regrowth, chances are that they're not going to
get too much action there because why we talked about that, that there's just less follicles in
that area. There's not enough trees in the garden, so to speak, when we are plants in the garden,
when we go to fertilize, but the other zones that they didn't even realize we're thinning,
we're going to get a 20 to 50% boost in volume in many of those areas. And that's pretty typical.
And when they're leaving, obviously you're putting them on the regimen that is medical, topical,
plus or minus laser.
Could be any of the above or just one. Many patients are doing monotherapy to start. They
don't want to do two, three, four different things. And then other patients come in and
they want to do kitchen sink approach. So it varies. It varies on their motivation,
sometimes the beauty budget, sometimes it's just their time effort and energy involved.
Their desire and their goals, honestly, some patients come in and they say,
you know what? If I just stayed the same as I am right now, I'm pretty happy the way I am right
now. If I stayed the same, I would be cool. And so we make a plan for that. But then there are
other patients that say, hey, we want to turn the clock back. And that's where the transplant comes
in.
So is it more often the case that the patient says something to you that makes you say transplant
is really the only option here? Or is that generally the inevitable path for most people
once they start going down the treatment?
Well, I think we're so clear about what these treatments do that the patients will typically
say, Hey, you know, in order to accomplish what I want to accomplish, it sounds like we need to
transplant. So very much patient driven process. My patient is our priority. We have a patient
centered practice. So it becomes very, very clear after spending the time with the patient
for the patient, the patient knows what they're going to need, essentially. So they may say, well,
hey, you know what? I think I'm probably going to need a hair transplant. It's now is not the right
time. Maybe it's going to be next year. Let's see what we can get with the non-invasive therapies.
And I'm cool with that. But if somebody comes in and says, Hey, you know, I really want to fix this
hairline with PRP and laser. I mean, I have to be honest with them and show them with the microscope
look, man, we can wish and we can hope and that's okay. But you know, wishing and hoping is not a
strategy.
So let's go back to that first patient that you saw who had gone up to Toronto. Where did they go?
What was special in Toronto? Having grown up there, I'm curious because I didn't think much
was special in Toronto. So what was happening?
Other than the Scholl Dice clinic for hernia repair.
Interesting.
That's very special.
Yeah, for sure. So things that were happening in the early, I would say the mid 1990s were that
hair transplant surgeons were learning to use single follicle implants, meaning that instead
of a plug or a punch or four millimeter biopsy of skin, they were cutting down and dissecting or
getting down to literally a one hair follicle graft. And what that enables you to do, if you
angle and orient that appropriately in the right position in the scalp is to create a result that
looks like mother nature made it make it look natural. It's soft. So you can't put them in a row.
You can't put them perpendicularly in the skin. You have to angle them. But there are ways to work
with single follicle implants to make your end result look 100% undetectable. And that is why
that gentleman traveled from New York to Toronto, because there was a gentleman up there who was
doing that work and his doctor Seager at the time is the surgeon that was doing that work.
And he's since passed on but he was doing that work with linear harvesting. So that was the old
style strip harvest and using microscopic magnification to dissect the hair follicles
and then implant them in a way that would make the end result look natural. And it seems like,
well, why wasn't everybody doing that? Well, not every surgeon was using microscopes. Not every
surgeon was using tiny grafts. They were using either larger, what they called micro mini grafts,
let's say, or those punch grafts to create the density.
Two comments there. The first is, so they were still doing a linear graft, which means that these
patients were having hair taken out with a big scar, presumably in the back of their head.
So that's a comment. And then the question is, how in God's name do you take a strip of hair out
of the back and isolate it by follicle with or without a microscope? I'm just talking purely
from the standpoint of patients. How many years does that take?
No, no, no, it doesn't take years.
I mean, I'm being facetious, but I can't fathom-
No, I understand. So there's a lot of labor, right? So my training and my training happened in
the 1990s there. We took linear harvests on patients and we moved two to 3000 grafts in
a single day for those patients. And I did that early on in my practice as well from a linear
harvest. And the way that we did it was with labor. We had surgical technicians working
two, three, four, five at a time under backlights or microscope, stereoscopic magnification,
literally doing the bench work to process that tissue into rest.
But this is all done sterily.
It's done aseptically. So you can't sterilize the scalp. It's a
common knowledge. Good news, the scalp is very much immune to severe infection. It's just,
we're built that way much like the face.
So you said two to 3000 you could harvest in its grafts. And would that be like one strip that
would be what, how many centimeters long and how wide?
So the single strip could be, depending on the size of the case, could be 10 to 20 centimeters
long and a centimeter wide. So it's going to go from ear to ear, essentially around the back
of your scalp. And unfortunately for many of those patients, they ended up with some wide scars.
Even with techniques like I helped pioneer back with the linear harvesting,
trichophytic techniques where we would actually overlap the closures to get hair to grow through
the scar. There's still a scar and a scar has not as much hair. It's a little bit smooth. Sometimes
it has a different type of color than regular skin. So even with short haircuts,
hairs growing through the scar can still be a scar that can be disfiguring. And so I'm sure
you remember in the field of general surgery, there was a paradigm shift from open gallbladders
to laparoscopic. So that was happening in the mid 1990s. So I was very much attuned to changes
in surgical technique and surgical paradigms. And when FUE, follicular unit extraction,
started to become kind of a chatter on the internet, there were some guys in Australia
doing it and a few people here around the US, I wanted to really try to do that procedure and
perfect it. And so that led me down the road to adopt FUE, follicular unit extraction at a very,
very early stage of the game. So I just, so follicular unit extraction is the use of a very,
very tiny punch. Let's call it about a millimeter. In the early days, we use disposable punches
that were sharp that were used for punch biopsies, but these were very, very small items, smaller than
the tip of a ballpoint pen typically, to harvest the individual follicular units. So those are the
groups of one, two, or three hairs each out of the scalp. So the graft comes out of the scalp,
basically ready and without a scalpel and without stitches. Now in the early days, it was very
difficult. I designed the first manual hand turned instrument available to physicians to be able to
do this procedure. It was called the Bauman Mindex. And we were doing these procedures in a very,
very slow way. They weren't very efficient. They weren't very accurate. But what we learned
through many, many years of time on tissue, applying this kind of technique, eventually we
got to a point where it became a viable procedure. And is the harvest scar such that it doesn't even
require a closure or do you still need a stitch? No, no, it's less than a millimeter. It closes up
50% in 24 hours and the skin is totally clean within another day or two. Really the only thing
that you would see on a shaved scalp is if you had, think of the head of hair like a five o'clock
shadow is that you would see a little bit less shadow in those areas. There's no visible linear
scar. So now you could move a lot of hair and not leave someone with a disfiguring scar in the back
of their scalp. It gives them much more flexibility in hair styling. Is it safe to say today that
nobody is still doing large scars? Because even if I open up the magazines on the airplanes,
I feel like once it's in the airplane magazine, it's no longer inside baseball. They have the
picture of the guy standing there. You're looking at two guys from a head behind and there's the
scar and there's the no scar. Is it safe to say no one is having that type of a harvest any longer?
No, it's actually not true at all. Many of the large national clinics that you see on late night
infomercials still do linear harvesting. And many of my colleagues here in the US still prefer to do
a linear harvest than FUE. So I want you to play skeptic, devil's advocate for a moment. Why are
they still doing it? What are they saying is better about that approach than the approach you just
described of single follicular extraction? Well, you know, probably some surgeons that are kind
of stubborn. Yeah, but I would like to think that in something where aesthetics play such a
role, it seems like kind of a no brainer. There must be some other explanation other than like,
put it this way, if I'm a patient and I'm going to see somebody who's about to do a huge linear
scar on my scalp and I say to that person, why are you still doing it this way when the pictures
in the airplane magazine say I should not have a scar? They're going to say, oh, well, we get a lot
more hair this way. It's a lot more efficient. I don't have to buy any expensive equipment to do
this. I don't have to learn any new skills. It seems like it's much less efficient because,
well, I guess it depends how you define efficiency. You have more hands involved,
but presumably it can take less time. Is that what they mean by more efficient?
It definitely would take less time. If you're doing a 3000, 4000 graft procedure in your office
with a strip and you have enough staff, that could be much quicker than an FUE procedure for sure.
So if you had a patient and you were, I don't know if you'd do this, but if you were going to
dedicate the entire day to that patient, like it was a one, quote unquote, a big case of the day,
how many follicular units can you harvest and implant?
So we've done very, very large cases all in a single day, but today we would really prefer to
do anything over 2000 grafts in two consecutive days. We find it a lot more comfortable for the
patient. It's a lot more comfortable in the office for the staff and our harvest rates and our harvest
quality is much, much more improved than trying to do a marathon, you know, into the evening type
of session. So most of our patients, if they're going to do a large maximum, as much as possible
procedure, they're going to get, let's call it around 3500 to 4000 grafts over two days.
And that's with a wide shave all the way around, provided that they have the hair to do it.
You know, and there are exceptions. I mean, we've done 5000 grafts on some guys and,
you know, sometimes we try to get 3000 and we just can't even do it.
What is the greatest number of grafts you've implanted on a patient?
And I'll ask it two ways. One, harvesting only from their head and two, harvesting from other
sites on the body, which I'd never even heard of until you mentioned this a couple, maybe six
months ago, we were talking about this and you mentioned that in one of these patients,
you'd actually harvested something from his beard.
Oh yeah. We actually do quite a bit of beard harvesting these days. Many of our patients have
old style scar tissue from either procedures that I did back in the early days, you know,
in the early 2000s when we were still doing half of our work with the linear harvest technique,
you know, and I'm not afraid to correct those cases and to, you know, update those cases into
the latest and greatest possible situation that they could have. So top numbers. Well, you know,
my dad comes to mind, he had almost 8000 grafts. He was totally bald before we started. Most guys
were totally bald at the top, meaning that they only have the hair around the sides and the back.
Most of them will need somewhere around six to 9000 grafts to kind of fill up the zones.
And do you have, if someone is that bald, do they have enough donor site on the remainder hair?
Most of the time, if they've never been harvested, they do. But if they've had some less efficient
harvesting techniques, then we may have to go to other places, as you say, alternative sources of
donor, like the beard or the body hair to satisfy that. And I've never really thought about it,
but my beard hair, actually it seems about the same thickness as my hair, but I don't know,
is beard hair thicker than hair? Yes, usually it is, but everybody's different. So some people
have thicker beard hair than their scalp. Some people have thinner beard hair than their scalp.
Some people have curlier, coarser hair on their beard. It seems to be most common. So we're not
going to put your beard at the frontal hairline typically. It's going to be used as filler.
It's filler in the back. Yeah. And it works really well.
And body hair seems less, much less thick and robust than hair hair. I mean, scalp hair,
right? Again, everybody's different. I mean, if you are a person with very, very thin,
fine hair on your scalp, you may find that the other body hair is a better thicker force or
caliber. But the problem is, and this is just a general idea, that as you get farther away from
the scalp, the follicles spend less time in the growing phase. So again, we're going back to this
antigen, categin, telogenation. Sure, sure. The body hair doesn't really grow. I mean, it's...
So it spends less time in antigen, but it also, out of, let's say 10 follicles from the body,
the chest, maybe only five of them are growing at any given time. So it's kind of like hiring
part-time workers in your factory. You've hired 10 people, but only five of them are showing up a
day. That's not so good. So the beard is pretty good there for a male.
The beard is really good for that. It kind of solves a lot of problems.
Beard is good to fill in the scar too sometimes. Yeah, that makes sense. Now for women, is this...
Yeah, the beard's not going to work. Yeah, no. This strikes me as a much easier problem in women
because you have generally far less volume to cover and far greater ability to cover up donor
sites, right? So women pose different problems than the men. If you want to do a large session
on a man, you can say to most guys, hey, can we give you a pretty short haircut? And they'll be
like, yeah, okay, no problem. I may not love that haircut, but I'll do it. For women, that's not
really going to work. So if you need to move a lot of hair for a female patient, it needs to be done
in steps and stages. So there's a couple of ways to approach the donor area in women that would be
like shaving a tiny little stripe, so a little horizontal area where we're going to take the
individual follicles from, right? Because we're not going to cut a strip. We're going to take the
individual follicles that way. Or we may trim a couple of hairs here, let's say one out of every
10 or 20 hairs, and then go after those hair follicles the next day. So there's no shaving
whatsoever. Nice way to handle that. But you know, you'd be surprised how many women have receding
hair lines, like their temples really with female pattern hair loss really go back as they age,
55, 65 years old, they can start to lose that feminine shape to the hairline, you can really
start to move backwards. And that's the most common area that we transplant in women is the
temples, a part of the hairline. A lot of women want to move their hairline. They're not happy
with the size and the shape of their forehead. They want a hairline lowering procedure that
doesn't involve cutting with a scalpel or stitches or a prolonged recovery or risk of
invasive surgery. And it's very easy to do transplantation, to fix a high hairline and
to bring the hairline down into what DaVinci would call the golden ratio, which is one third,
one third, one third. So what are the biggest risks of this procedure besides the obvious risks
that we talk about in every surgery, bleeding, infection, et cetera, or is there anything that
is unique to this surgical procedure as far as a risk? Sure. Well, bleeding, infection, extremely
rare, thank goodness. Even though we're making thousands of little tiny sites in the scalp,
not only the harvesting and implantation part, bleeding is not an issue. I mean,
just like if you cut yourself shaving or you got a paper cut, you know, in 20, 30 seconds you stop.
Infection, your worst infection typically with a hair transplant might be a pimple,
to be honest. And maybe most people have one or two and we call it, you know, could be around
the time when the hair start to kick in like an ingrown hair, you kind of have to pop it like a
pimple, release the hair that may be caught at the level of the scalp. And it's pretty rare, maybe like,
you know, one out of every 20 or 30 patients that has more than, you know, a half a dozen pimples or
something where it needs something more significant in terms of wound care to kind of release those
hair follicles. Maybe they have curly hair or something like that. But I would say the main
concern for hair is not the physical attributes of the procedure itself because we can recreate
something with artistic bent, you know, we apply an artistic approach to the shape of the hairline,
the angle, the orientation and position of the hairs, the variation in terms of hair density
to make it look normally natural, not a wall of hair, straight density across the hairline,
the shape that builds into the sides, the temples, the temporal point on the side of the scalp,
the angle and orientation that's required for recreating a crown area. But really the risk
comes to that you're simply not happy with the result. And so, again, it all comes down to the
consultation process. What exactly are you expecting out of this procedure? And have we gone over
exactly what we believe we can achieve? Because if I tell you you're going to be a 10 out of 10,
and the reality is that it's going to always be a five out of 10, then I've promised you the wrong
thing, and you will be forever unhappy with that. So we have to be very, very clear about what's
possible and what's not. I can't put back a full head of dense hair for you, but I can make you
look like you have a full head of hair. You know, I go back to my dad, for example, total, total
baldness for two decades, wore a hairpiece and all that. The transplants that he has, if you look at
him today, even 15 years later after his procedures, it looks like he has a full head of hair,
but it's an illusion. It looks like he's got full coverage. You see the frame of his face,
you see that Da Vinci golden ratio. He looks 20 years younger than when he had his procedure,
but he never will have that density that he had as a teenager until we can figure out how to
clone these babies. That makes a lot of sense. And I guess that as your practice continues to grow,
one of the greatest things that each patient is providing as a gift to a subsequent patient is a
before and after photo that gives you a bigger and bigger database to show patients more closely,
I suspect, what they can expect based on where they are because you've got just a greater basis
from which you can say, look, I've got 27 patients who look almost identical to what you looked like.
Here's the range of outcomes. And if you're not comfortable with that range, you're not going to
be a great candidate. Correct. So after 8,000 surgeries, I can tell you with very, very good
confidence what's possible and what's not and what it will take to get there. And if the patient is
all in and he's going to protect the existing hair, we know that that's going to add a lot of
great benefit to the end result. If he's lackadaisical and he's losing other hair while we're
transplanting this area, other areas are being lost, that's going to be a much tougher battle.
So it's very much a team approach. And my patients become very much drivers of the bus,
so to speak, because in order to get the best results, there has to be a good amount of buy-in
and partnership with what we do and what we recommend. I can tell you what kind of therapies
and treatments and such that are going to keep your hair growing strong, but you have to do that
work. When you take a hair off the side of the head or the back of the head in an area as a donor
hair, a hair that was never going to fall out and you put that hair back on the top, is it susceptible
to its nature or its nurture? In other words, is it now susceptible to the DHT forces that took out
the hair that it's replacing or does it bring with it its genetic pattern from its donor site?
So the whole basis of the field of hair transplant surgery is based on the concept of donor dominance.
So that would mean, and again it's the theory, right, of donor dominance, meaning that the hair
follicles from the sides and the back of the scalp, which are virtually immune to the effects of DHT,
most guys with a total baldness problem never ever lose that hair, that it will grow, live and grow
forever in its new location. There are, I would say, very small numbers of scientific reports that
kind of put a dent into that. So in these few and far between cases, we believe that there is some
recipient area control. And the way that I would explain that to patients is if, remember we said
how long the follicles stay in the growth phase has a lot to do with where those follicles come
from. Well, one of our more prominent researchers and colleagues in the field took a hair follicle
from one place on his body and put it into another place and then move that follicle someplace else
and track those lengths of time that it spent in the growing phase. It tracked the antigen, the
growth phase. And so what you would expect initially is that wherever you took it from,
like let's say the chest, it grew for an inch and that's it. You put it in the back of your arm,
it should grow, or back of your hand, it should grow for an inch. Well, it didn't, it grew
differently in those different locations. So there is some local effect. So what we do say,
and especially true for women, where sometimes they can have a more diffuse hair loss problem,
right? Because it's maybe not necessarily all androgen dependent, that we say that those hairs
are relatively permanent. Has anyone ever done the experiment where you take a hair and implant it
in an area that has zero hair, like the palm or? Of course. Yes. In fact, I did that for someone.
Have you ever heard of Nalts from YouTube? No. So Nalts from YouTube is a prankster. I'm sure
he wouldn't be upset with me sharing with you and your listeners that he had some hair follicles
implanted into the palm of his hand during his last hair transplant procedure. And it grew fine.
Wow. So that is, from a, just from a pure biology standpoint, that is really amazing.
No, it's not because listen, the hair follicle is an organ. It's a self-determining organ. If you
have a scar, which doesn't make any hair on its own, you can cut that scar. It's going to bleed,
right? You throw a hair follicle in there, it will survive. It will grow. It will thrive.
It will demand more blood flow. But there must be something very unique about
parts of our body that don't grow any hair that, I don't know, I guess, I mean, look,
I don't think about this obviously very much, but it would just, it just strikes me as counter
intuitive. If this were an exam and you asked me that question, I would guess that if you implanted
the most robust hair into an area that otherwise would never grow hair,
it wouldn't have the fertile enough soil to promote it.
No, anywhere that you have a blood flow, it will grow because all it needs is energy. It needs the
oxygen. It needs the nutrients, the hair follicle. If you have a non-healing wound on the side of
your leg, a diabetic ulcer, you can implant follicles into that area. And those follicles
are so metabolically active that they will actually secrete the growth factors, demand
more blood flow and vascular neogenesis will occur and wound healing will be accelerated
and enhanced by placing hair follicles into that non-healing wound.
That's incredible.
The hair follicle cell population, the population of cells within the hair follicle are among the
most highest metabolically active cell populations in your body. It's one of the reasons why
chemotherapy knocks them out as well as the lining of your gut and bone marrow, right?
I mean, if your gut, your bone, your hair, those are some of the most highly metabolic
and metabolically active cell populations that we have. And so they continue to work and grind
away to grow on your head, a full head of hair, right? 150,000 hair follicles will produce
somewhere around 1500 feet of hair a day.
That's interesting. Did you say how many hairs on the head?
So you're born with about 100 to 150,000.
And it's amazing that you said you could take someone who is completely bald and through very
strategic placement using only 10,000 hairs say.
No, I said 10,000 grafts.
A graft could be two to three hairs.
Correct.
Got it. Okay.
Because, you know, again, we're not going to recapitulate a teenager hairline,
age appropriate matters, right? So the recession of the hairline, that's going to look normal and
natural. That's where some of the nuances, right? And the discussion between our patients who are
maybe in their twenties who want to look like they did in their teenage years versus patients who
may be a little bit more mature in their thirties or forties. So the idea is to design
something that looks normal and natural as they go through the process.
Well, Alan, this is super interesting. I suspect that there are going to be a lot of people who
listen to this who are going to potentially revisit assumptions that they've had on this
entire topic. I'm actually surprised at how often, you know, a patient asks me a question about this.
And obviously I just don't know much. I mean, all I've learned over the years is to find
people like you who I can send them to. But I think what surprised me the most in this
discussion is how far this field has come in what seems like a decade and a half, basically.
Yeah. I mean, it's incredible. This is the most fast moving field. I mean, it's incredible how
quickly things have changed in hair transplantation from, you know, whether it be linear harvesting
to follicular unit extraction to the use of cellular therapy, you know, PRP and other things
like low level laser therapy and compound of medications to attack the hair follicle. And
from all sides and all different ways and all different modalities to help our patients really
grow better hair and look great and feel great. I mean, that's what it's all about, right? It comes
down to the emotion. When you look in the mirror and you see that hairline growing back in, you
know, patient after patient, they say, this is amazing. This is a miracle. This is like, I never
thought I would see my hairline again. I never thought I'd cover that bald spot except with a
hat. I mean, that's the exciting thing that keeps me going every day. Well, Alan, thank you very
much. I appreciate the input and I hope that anyone listening to this who's had some questions
about this has got some of those answered. Great. Well, great to be here with you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There,
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read,
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social,
you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually
Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory
disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the givings of
medical advice. And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this podcast is
not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and
should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Lastly,
and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures,
the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.