Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Jeremy Shapp, one of the
preeminent journalists at ESPN and a wonderful guy. We spend a lot of time in this episode talking
about sports, obviously. Jeremy has done a lot of amazing work and he's written the book,
Cinderella Man, which is an incredible story of James J. Braddock, who many of you probably have
not heard of, but I think by the end of this episode, you'll understand why the story is so
beautiful. We also talk a lot about his most recent project, which is directing a 30 for 30 special
called 42 to 1, which is the story of the Buster Douglas upset of Mike Tyson. We get into a lot of
things that go beyond sports or at least are associated with sports, such as why these things
matter to us, what they teach us about life, and the challenges that he faced following in his
father's enormous footsteps and ultimately coping with his father's early death as a result of a
medical error. This episode could have gone on for a really long time, but we kind of had a time limit
on it and we had to draw it to a close earlier than either one of us would have liked. But with
that said, I think you'll really enjoy my conversation with Jeremy Shapp. Hey Jeremy, thanks for coming,
man. It's my pleasure, Peter. Thank you for having me. First trip on the second subway, huh? I guess
it's been a couple of years now. I mean, they've been building it since 1929, but it was nice to,
you know, I went out of my way to get a chance to see the 72nd street station. It was pretty
impressive. Not having been in New York that long, I don't appreciate the morass of like nonsense. Oh,
you know, by the year 2400, it should extend a little bit farther downtown, I would expect.
Apparently it's going all the way to Tribeca. Yeah, and then there's the LIRR, you know,
extension to Grand Central and, you know, the city is always improving just sometimes very slowly.
So there's so many things I want to talk about on the sports front, but I also realize that maybe
not everybody wants to hear all of this stuff, but I want to start with something in boxing,
because you and I have something in common, which is we are both completely obsessed with the history
of boxing. And we were talking about over dinner a few months ago. I don't think I know anything
that has happened in boxing from about the year 1996 forward. If you asked me to rattle off one
champion in one division that year probably coincides with the beginning of some new
professional endeavor or, you know, once you start building a family and your career and all that,
it's harder to be as obsessive about these things. And boxing itself has, let's face it,
lost a lot of its luster over the last several decades. I'm certainly not as up on the sport as
I was when I was covering it for ESPN on a regular basis. I was a ringside reporter for some time.
I wrote a book about boxing history, but that didn't have anything to do with the contemporary
sport. My assignment for about 10 years was being like the Mike Tyson reporter from 1995,
when he got out of prison until 2005, when he retired, that constituted a lot of the work
that I did. His last fight was against Kevin McBride. Kevin McBride, the Clonus Colossus.
Unforgettable, Clonus Colossus in Washington, DC. And I guess I sort of am exaggerating a little
bit. I still followed it enough. I mean, I would watch-
If you remember Kevin McBride.
Yeah. The fact that I can remember the Kevin McBride fight tells you I was still somewhat
paying attention, but I had an almost ridiculous obsession going back to about Jack Johnson.
Okay.
So from Johnson to Dempsey to Lewis to Marciano to Ali-
All heavyweights.
Yeah. And of course, you know, Robinson Armstrong, like, it's hard to put in words how much I
obsessed over that stuff. Like I knew every detail of every one of their fights at one point.
That goes way beyond me. I mean, I had-
But you wrote about Braddock, which I'd love to just-
Yeah. I mean, I immersed myself in the 30s. And the book that I wrote about Braddock and Bear,
it really was also kind of a primer on the first 50 years of the heavyweight division as well,
because those stories for me, like you, are just so fascinating. These guys were such big stars,
and so many of them were outsized personalities. And there was nothing else in sports that even
approached the significance of the heavyweight championship of the world. That was it. I mean,
you know, the middleweight champion of the world- Remember, there were only eight divisions and-
And one champion per division.
One champion per division, and there's something mythic about it. And it always fascinated me. And
I grew up in the 1970s. I was born in 1969. I grew up in the 1970s, obviously, in the sports
business. There was a lot of interesting stuff going on, epic stuff going on in the heavyweight
division. My father was very much Dick Shappe, very much a part of that. And I remember, you know,
being six, seven years old, I still have it, this encyclopedia boxing champions just sitting there,
memorizing it. Whether it was about Stanley Ketchill, the great middleweight, or it was about
the great heavyweights from the guys you named Dempsey and Johnson and Sullivan, there was
something that always attracted me to those stories as well.
So you chose to dive into a really interesting story that is, I think, honestly, without your
work would be a footnote, right? So most people wouldn't even know who James J. Braddock is,
were it not for the movie Cinderella Man starring Russell Crowe, which of course was based entirely
on your book. Well, it pains me to disabuse you of that misimpression, but I feel obligated to do so.
The movie was actually in the works before the book. Oh, I didn't know that. And I just assumed
that many people I wish the movie was in the works before the book. Yes, I'm taking all that
back. Take all of it back. Russell Crowe would have made everybody know. There had not been a
book written about since ever really a Big Mac's bear book and not since the 30s that anyone
written a book about Braddock. And I decided to make it kind of a dual biography as they are on
this collision course towards this heavyweight showdown in 1935. And so let's give people a
little bit of a sense of that because for me, I've always, like I looked at all of those
heavyweights to me, the entire lineage from Sullivan to Johnson to Lewis, et cetera. I mean,
every one of those guys seemed like a god. They didn't seem like they were mortal. They just,
there was nothing about them that seemed normal. Bear was like, first of all, like probably the
most good looking guy I've ever seen in my life. Very handsome guy. It's hard to imagine a more
handsome, beautiful, stunning human being. And his career gets off to kind of a weird start
when he kills this guy with Frankie Campbell. He kills Frankie Campbell in the ring. And it has
been about 15 years since I wrote the book. But if I recall correctly, Frankie died in a fight.
A couple of days later. Yeah. A couple of days later, it was in San Francisco. Frank, it was 1930
and Bear was from the Bay Area. I think Frankie was from the Bay Area as well. He happened to be
the older brother of Dolph Camilli, who would end up being an excellent first baseman in the major
leagues, the MVP of the National League in I think 1941 with the Brooklyn Dodgers. And there's
an inquest. I mean, there is a criminal investigation because of the way in which Campbell
was battered in the ring and then died. Yeah. Of course, all of the stuff I know about these
things are from watching old documentaries and reading about it. But I read that Bear was never
the same since after that fight. First of all, apparently he was just devastated by the fact that
Campbell died. And I mean, I remember reading something that his son wrote many years later
that said, look, my dad was he was a showman. I mean, he was not in this to hurt people. He
sort of took that as his job. But to have this guy die at your hands was he was never quite the same.
By all accounts, it really did shake him. And it affected the way that he approached life. It
affected the way that he approached his opponents in the ring. A few years later, he would be blamed
for the death of another heavyweight Ernie Schaff. Yeah. Although that one's a bit
controversial because I believe there was an autopsy done that suggested he actually had
meningitis and he hadn't recovered from sort of a chronic meningitis at the time that he actually
died because he died in the ring at the hands of another fighter whose name I'm blanking on.
That's right. You know, and it's been a while. I think it was Carneira.
Oh, you're right. It was primo carneira. You're right. It was primo carneira. It was at Madison
Square Garden. Although carneira ends up administering the blows in the fight in which
Schaff dies. But it was a very gentle blow. It was almost a jab that killed him. People said
it was the beating he took at the hands of bear that had made it possible for that. So all of this
is to basically say when Max bear finally beats primo carneira, which he does in ridiculous
fashion, I think there was 10 knockdowns. It's a laughable, laughable fight. Yeah. Bear looks
invincible and he'd already beaten Schmeling, correct? He'd already beaten Schmeling. Yeah.
And there was no way that he was going to give Schmeling a rematch given what was going on
politically. Again, it's been a while Peter, but my recollection is nobody was interested in giving
Max Schmeling a rematch against bear just because he wasn't really, he was considered washed up,
finished. I mean, when he beats Joe Louis in 1936, he's considered washed up and finished. He wasn't
even part of the discussion. Yeah. So they decided to take a tune up fight basically with this guy who
can't possibly win, right? Well, what happens? Jim Braddock has been out of the fight game.
He's hurt. He had been a light heavyweight contender in the late 1920s. He'd lost his one
shot to Tommy Lachran, who was a great light heavyweight. And at that point, Braddock's
entire personal situation really falls apart and his professional situation, not his personal,
really his professional situation. He breaks his hand. He can't fight anymore. He can't make any
money. The depression hits. He is working on the docks across the Hudson River from Manhattan.
He's desperate. He goes on relief, which at that time, in Braddock's mind, in the minds of a lot
of people, that was a kind of humiliation, taking government assistance, especially a guy like Braddock,
who had been so successful. He'd fought for the light heavyweight championship, which was a big,
big deal in 1929 in a way that it's not now. And everybody thinks he's through. He's finished.
He's done. Totally kaput. But the interesting thing is by doing the work on the docks, because
he doesn't have the money for bus fare or cab fare to get from his home to the docks, he's walking
every day 20 miles ridiculous. He's working as a stevedore, you know, hauling giant bales and stuff
like that, even with a broken hand, he builds up this strength, especially in his left hand, he
never had a left hand before the right hand is broken. So he's building strength. All of these
things, it sounds like some kind of fairy tale or something may prepare him in a way he hadn't been
prepared to seize the moment he gets the shot against an up and comer named John Griffin, John
Corn Griffin on the undercar of the Bear Carnera fight. And he was not expected to beat Griffin.
He was just an opponent. He was the guy who was going to be a stepping stone for Corn Griffin on
his way to fighting Max Bear. But Braddock is a different Braddock and he delivers against Corn
Griffin, stunning the promoters, people who had, you know, these high hopes for for Corn Griffin,
whose name is still in boxing circles, kind of stands for guy who couldn't get it done stepping
stone. It's almost like a Wally pip thing. And almost exactly a year later, I think 364 days
later, he beats, he beats a couple of more impressive fighters on the way sets himself
up for a showdown with Max Bear for the heavyweight title, which nobody gave him a shot. I believe it
was eight or nine to one huge underdog, eight, nine, 10 to one underdog, depending on who you ask,
which at that time was, I think the most lopsided odds ever in a heavyweight championship fight,
of course, we're gonna come to one that's a little more lopsided in a minute.
And Braddock is this guy who's fighting for his family. He's got three little kids. He's got the
wife. They're living in poverty. They're living in poverty when this rise starts. After he wins one
of the fights on the way that year, you know, he goes back, he shows up at the relief office. I
mean, it, it almost sounds like it has to be apocryphal, but everybody said it really happened.
He shows up at the relief office and returns, returns the money, $35 or whatever that he'd
taken on government relief. And he becomes the people's hero. But nobody thought he had a chance
against Max bear who looked utter. Yeah, I mean, Max bear looked like an executioner and he was
physically bigger than him. Oh, and he's a specimen. We just saw Deontay Wilder fight for
the heavyweight championship not long ago at 211 pounds, you know, it ends up being a draw with,
with Tyson Fury. And he's six foot seven Deontay Wilder, I think six, seven, six, six.
Max bear is six two and he weighs more and he is caught. Oh, he's you look at the pictures of him.
He does not have enough. He is he is ripped in a way that athletes were not ripped like that in
that he's 250 pounds. He weighs more than Deontay Wilder without being tubby. And Jim Braddock's,
you know, a former light heavyweight who somehow gets all the way up to like 192, 193, something
like that for the fight. It's not a good fight. It's a pretty boring fight and Max bears clowning
his way through it. He doesn't seem to be taking it seriously. It's his first title defense. For
some reason he seemed well, there are a lot of reasons why he was ambivalent about the sport.
We talked about Frankie Campbell and Ernie Schaff, but he doesn't show up in Braddock. Braddock
wins pretty easily. Yeah. And you know, it is a beautiful story because again, maybe it's my
recollections not there, but I remember reading that leading up to the fight Braddock said,
I'm not losing this fight. Like there is no way like he was fighting for his life, his honor,
his family. He was fighting for something much more beyond him. And you don't get to see that
often. No, it literally was. I mean, you don't often have in a heavyweight championship fight a
guy who is that where the the scent of desperation is so recently in his nostrils. You know, I mean,
if you're fighting for the heavyweight championship of the world, you're probably doing pretty
okay for a while at that point. You've been making money on other fights. You've been getting bigger
and stronger. You've been accustomed to success and only success. And Braddock was a guy who had
been broken. I mean, broken. And there was no chance he was ever going to challenge for anything
like the heavyweight championship again. I mean, impossible. And this would be everything to him.
And he inspired so many people. There were so many people pulling for him,
but nobody really thought that he had a chance against Max Baer who was five years younger.
By every metric was superior man. He should have won the fight.
And then of course, I think it was by that point Schmeling had upset Lewis, which was,
you know, 1936. That's right, 1936. Yeah. And I think at that point Baer did have a chance.
I mean, you could have argued he should have fought Schmeling, but by that point, the war
was really starting to ramp up in Europe. And again, maybe this isn't true. Maybe this is just
revisionist history, but he had a choice to fight Lewis versus Schmeling. And the logical choice
would have been Schmeling, right? Because he had beat Lewis, but the sort of more American choice
was you're going to fight- What about Braddock's choice, right?
Yeah, sorry, Braddock's choice. That's right. So he fights Lewis. And I mean, we all know how
the story ends, which is Lewis wins. And that goes on to create the most dominant heavyweight
in the history of the sport, 12 years champion, 25 final defenses. But the fight was more
compelling than people expected. I mean, Braddock put up a better fight.
Well, as I recall, he knocks down Joe Lewis in the first round.
Yeah.
You know, that's really, I mean, he would fight one more fight after Lewis.
Which he won and then retired.
Which he won and retired. But the thing about Jim Braddock, what I think he embodies
is this idea whether or not you buy into it, that there is something noble about that sport,
and about the commitment required, and about the dedication, and about its code,
whatever that code, you know, the code of courage, personal courage, of total commitment,
of believing there's something honorable about fighting until you've got nothing left.
None of that stuff mattered to Max Baer. That's the contrast to Max Baer thought this was
show business. And it was a way for him to make a buck. And I think after he killed Frankie
Campbell, and had a hand in the death of Ernie Schaff, it was kind of like, I'd like to make some
money. I'd like to be in movies. He was in movies. He was starring in Hollywood movies while he was
champion before he was champion getting good notices. And of course, moved out to Hollywood
later. And Braddock really felt, you know what, I'm going down like a Roman centurion on my back.
If he's taken my title, Joe Lewis, he's gonna damn near almost take my life.
He's got and that's exactly it. And you know, there's the story in the corner after
Lewis almost rips off his head, and he's battered and bloodied. And he's his corner wants to throw
in the towel. And he tells Joe Gould, who's his manager, his best friend, the guy who's been
there for everything with him, he says, if you throw in the towel, never taught you again.
And I think he meant it. Now today, we'd say that's just silly. You know, Jim,
that's Joe Lewis, that's 23 year old Joe Lewis, get out of the ring. But then it meant something.
And you're new, you're so right about Joe Lewis. I mean, it does break my heart a little bit today
when you see people talking about this sport without an understanding of what came before,
like what did it mean to be Joe Lewis, let's not even talk about the political and social side of
it, which to me is just as beautiful as what he could do athletically. But when you go back and
look at the film of him, including his rematch with smelling, which to me is one of the most
remarkable fights ever, he breaks his vertebrae, he breaks one of the bones in his back in the
first round in this revenge fight, everything he went on to do, you know, bringing it back to Max
Bear. I remember reading that after so Lewis fought Bear two years later. So now Lewis is
champion Bear is not and Lewis beats him badly, but Bear finishes on a knee. So you can, there's
a very famous image in boxing where Max Bear is on his knee clearly looking like he could get up
and gets counted out. Yeah. I mean, what I remember though is that Bear did not want to go
into the ring. I think he had a hand injury. He did not have been in the fight. That's absolutely
right. And so at the press conference after one of the reporters says to bear, Maxie, it looked
like you could have beat the count and he looks at him and he says something to the effect of he,
you know, Bear always had a great way of saying stuff, including his last words before he died.
But he said something to the effect of if I'm going to get executed, you're going to have to
pay a lot more than $35 to see it or whatever the ticket price was. That's exactly right. Which
is kind of the summation of everything he felt about the sport. Yeah. And he died young, which
broke my heart too. I mean, he died at 50, right? He had a heart attack. And the famous line, you
know, yeah, you know, these things sound too good to be true. We're so nerdy to be talking about this.
So you got to be skeptical, but you know, he's staying in a hotel in Hollywood, I think, and
he calls down. Yeah. He's having chest pain. He's having chest pain. Oh no, there's two lines.
One line is we'll send the house doctor. And he says, I don't need a house doctor. I need a person
doctor. That's right. Dummy. Right. And then they send somebody up and then, you know, this is
actually bringing it back to sort of my world of heart disease. I mean, you didn't have any tools
to help somebody having a heart attack back then, the way we do today. So once someone's going down
that path, they're gone. And by the time they did get the medical folks up to the hotel, he had a
second heart attack and his last words apparently were, Oh, here I go, or something to that effect.
This is it. I'm here. I go. Yeah. He was, he was a great, he was a fascinating figure. He was a
colorful character. He loses the title fight and then he fights Lewis and he didn't have any
interest in the fight game anymore. Is it a coincidence that you've written the New York
Times bestselling book that describes the entire story of what we just described. And then you go
on to make, you know, one of my favorite ESPN 30 for 30s, which is 42 to one, the parallels between
Buster Douglas and James J. Braddock are comical, right? You couldn't make it up. Right.
They're the two greatest underdogs in heavyweight championship history. Who also rose for a moment.
Yeah. I mean, that's right. Yeah. You know, they're the two biggest underdogs, but they were bigger
underdogs than all those guys who lost the fights. You know, they're underdogs who win the fights,
who sees the moment. And I've always loved the Buster Douglas story to me. You know, as I said,
I was born in 1969. I'm 49. I've seen everything you could see in sports. A lot of it I've seen in
person, you know, other stuff I've watched on TV and the night of that fight, it was nighttime here
in the US. It was the night of the slam dunk contest in the NBA. I remember this like it was
yesterday. It was that night and it was afternoon, early afternoon in Tokyo. And I found out the
result that night I couldn't find anywhere that had regular HBO to watch it. I wanted to watch it.
I tried to locate regular HBO. I happened to be in Hanover, New Hampshire that night.
And I couldn't find it. But somebody told me later in the night, did you hear what happened? Just like
millions of people around the world. Did you hear what happened? Did you hear what happened? No,
can't be can't possibly be could not have possibly occurred. And then my mother sent me a VHS. She
had recorded it off HBO and watching it even a few days later in my apartment in college.
It was still so thrilling, so exciting that it's such a great fight. It really is. It's such an
incredible fight. And for Buster Douglas to rise the occasion as he did, again, when the stakes were
so high cannot have been higher. 22 days after the death of his mother, when nobody thought he had a
chance, when Mike Tyson looked utterly invincible, there's nothing else quite like it. I obviously
watched it as soon as it came out. And I think I'm going to watch it again with you tonight at
the screening. But I had not seen the fight in about 15 years. Right. So I watched it probably a
million times at the time, but I'd forgotten a lot of it and I'd forgotten the ninth round. Oh,
I'd for I'd completely blanked on that round. You don't see those kinds of rounds in heavyweight
fighting. No, you put that in the category of round 10 of Riddick Bowe versus of Andrew Holyfield
in a round 10. You put that in a round of Hagler Hearn's round one, which was, by the way, that's
what got me into boxing. That was some Hagler Hearn's round one, April 1985 was when I decided
I wanted to be the middleweight champion of the world. That was, luckily I chose another path.
No, the Douglas fight was unbelievable. And I don't know if you ever heard it, you know,
blank on his name. Teddy Atlas was on Joe Rogan, I don't know, a while ago. And Teddy Atlas made
a really interesting point. He said, you know, Tyson's never won a fight in his life because
every fight he won, you know, won technically, the opponent was beat before they got in the ring.
Every fight he lost is because the guy came in and wasn't afraid. And Douglas was in many ways,
the most impressive of those because he was the first one to beat him. And then of course,
Holyfield would go on to do it twice and then Lewis and then ultimately McBride. I think those
were Tyson's five losses, correct? Yeah, it was Williams McBride, Chudaholy Field and
Lewis McBride, Chudaholy Field and Buster. Yeah. But the Douglas one is a different level.
It's a different level because it's the first and because he gave us not only the blueprint,
but because it was Mike Tyson at 23, not Mike Tyson after prison, not Mike Tyson at 37.
It was the Mike Tyson who had annihilated Michael Spinks and humiliated Larry Holmes.
And remember his previous fight to Douglas, wasn't it Frank Bruno who he had obliterated?
The fight right before it was, I think it was Frank, I'm getting mixed up now, there's
Carl Williams. Oh, you're right. No, no, you're right. It was Carl Williams in July of 89 was the
previous one. And before that was Frank Bruno. Right, right. And before that was Spinks.
Right. He was 37 and 0, 34 knockouts. Tony Tucker had taken him the distance,
but it wasn't a close fight at all. And then Bone Crusher Smith had taken him the distance.
That's right. And basically clinching the whole way there. He'd gone the distance twice before
Quick Tillis took him the distance. Three of them. Yeah, yeah, it was three of them, right.
And so it was a sense maybe some big guys could give him some trouble, you know, if they approached,
but those guys weren't in those fights. Those fights were not close fights. There was no one
who had stood up to him. And who had matched him punch for punch. And Buster Douglas did more than
that. The thing about the Buster Douglas story, why I really wanted for this to be given this
kind of treatment is because I've known Buster for a long time, I did stories about the 20th
anniversary of the fight, the 25th anniversary of the fight. And this moment for me as a young person
was just so it was such a transcendent sports moment, I said, and people don't get it. They
don't want to give Buster credit. They want to say it was a one hit wonder, he got lucky with a punch
or that he wasn't, he didn't deserve to even be in the same ring with Mike Tyson.
But everything people thought they knew about Buster Douglas was really wrong. Buster Douglas,
of course, you know, dominates that fight. I mean, it is an epic performance. He doesn't get lucky.
It's not a Sim Rockman in South Africa, that's right. Lennox Lewis. It's not one punch. It is a
butt kicking. It's an ass kicking by round three. Yeah. Like if you go back and watch that fight,
knowing the outcome, which of course now we would all do, you're not blinded by the way you are the
first time you saw it live, which is you're in denial. You're in denial. And by the way,
Or you just think something's going to happen. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Didn't two of the three judges
have Tyson ahead at the time of the knockout? I think that's right. Which is like those people
should be removed in a sport. And my co-director went to Japan and interviewed one of them and he's
just like, yeah, that's what it looked like to me. But that speaks to the aura of Tyson,
that you could have had Tyson winning one goddamn round besides. Or the Oradon King. Yeah. Yeah.
So, but you're right. It's a total ass kicking. Tyson's eye is swelling shut by the third round.
Even the eighth round where he knocks Douglas down, I mean, Douglas still dominated that round.
Yeah. And then the ninth round, he almost takes Tyson's head off his shoulders. That sequence in
the corner, you know, and that's the thing we didn't know. It also speaks to how tough Tyson was.
We didn't know Mike Tyson had a chin. We had no idea until that fight. Nobody had ever
challenged him. And I mean, the beating that he took, I think the people who thought Buster
were going to win and there were about four of them thought that he would win because he would
be able to keep his distance, use his jab. And Tyson wouldn't know what to do after four or five
rounds, that he would just kind of get frustrated and DQ himself or just fall apart physically from
the exhaustion. And instead, Mike Tyson, I mean, he's in there for 40 minutes taking an epic
beating, an epic beating from a bigger, stronger, more athletic man. I mean, you know, you could
say everything and look, Mike Tyson was a phenomenon. What Mike Tyson did from 1985 up until that moment
in Tokyo, it's pretty impressive. And it's pretty special. It doesn't look as special now because we
know the next chapter of the story. But of course, at that time, you know, for Buster Douglas to,
you know, Buster Douglas is a bigger guy. He is a stronger guy. Maybe stronger is not the right
word. He was a more focused guy. And he was a better athlete. And he used all of his advantages
and he marshaled all of his talents. And that's what's so fascinating about the story to me
is that here's a guy who had been considered an underachiever at best and a quitter at worst.
And by the way, I got to tell you, you guys made a great point of that. And the thing,
I guess I have a different view. He was beating Tucker Handley, right? And then he basically fails
to answer a few punches and the ref stops it. I'm not sure I call that quitting. I mean, I'm not sure
I do either. I just, I think that was always a very unfair label. It's totally, totally unfair.
A guy, look, boxing is a cruel sport. This is another reason why I want to tell this story.
Boxing, unlike other sports, right? Here's a guy, Buster Douglas, who at that point,
when he gets into the ring with Mike Tyson, right? You know, he fought for the heavyweight title.
He fought big, tough guys. He'd beaten Greg Page, who would be a heavyweight champion. He'd beaten
Oliver McCall, who was going to be a heavyweight champion. And yet people thought of him not as
just a guy who's not Mike Tyson's peer, but as a bump, you know, but only in boxing, right?
No, there's that quote that you guys have in the movie where what did Don King say about him?
He's a dog.
He's a dog. I mean, he's a quitter and he's a dog. Like Don King, if anybody would know a dog.
I mean, it is something, but that's the way I think the average sports fan and even boxing
fans talk about boxers. I've said this before, like if you're the 15th best left-handed pitcher
in the national league, you're getting a contract for like 110, 120 million dollars. Maybe, maybe
that's a slight exaggeration. Eighty five, ninety million dollars guaranteed. And you're an
all-star and people want your autograph and people say, oh, he's so effective and he can do this.
If you're the third best middleweight in the world, but you're not the best, nobody knows your name.
And it's like, oh, he lost that fight. He's a bump. You know, you hear that all the time. And
Buster Douglas, the reputation fairly or unfairly had been established in that fight against Tony
Tucker when he's winning. He's five rounds away. I think it was a 15 rounder still at that time.
You're right. That would have been the last of the 15 rounders.
I think it was 87. I think that I think it was still a 15 rounder.
It was May of 87. So, yeah.
I mean, Mills Lane did the right thing. It was time to stop that fight because Buster is standing
there. He just wasn't returning them. Yeah.
Six or seven, massive. I mean, Tony Tucker was a good fighter. Tony Tucker is a big guy.
He's pummeling Buster and Buster's not doing anything. So the fight had to end, but to call
him a quitter, you get in the ring and take some of those punches from Tony Tucker.
Yeah. The other thing I remember at the time was when Douglas' mother died two weeks before the
fight. And I remember that getting like small news. Remember, this fight wasn't getting that
much news because this was, people are already talking about the Holyfield fight that was supposed
to happen in June, I think. It was already a contract.
So, and I remember thinking, oh man, they're going to have to postpone the fight and he's
never going to get his shot. And I remember just feeling kind of sorry for Douglas. Like,
I at least want him to get paid. You know what I mean? Like, at this point, it's like,
at least you deserve a couple million bucks because you've been through all of this stuff.
There's only 1.2, but that's 2 million today. So, yeah.
Yeah. There were people who thought, I mean, you saw in the film, Bruce Trampler, the Hall of Fame
promoter and matchmaker who knew Buster from the time he was a little kid because he was his father's
father. He said, I thought he should pull out. I didn't see how he could possibly have enough
focus after his mother's death to get in the ring. That's how his brother kind of thought.
Buster said, no, let's go. Let's do this.
And there's something you did that was really beautiful in the film,
which was after one of Buster's fights, he's, I don't remember which fight it was, but he's
standing on the left. His mom is in the middle and the dad is on the right.
Right.
The interview, I forget who it was. It wasn't.
It's Al Bernstein.
It's right. It was a young Al Bernstein.
Big Al Bernstein.
I barely recognize him, right?
So Al Bernstein says to his mom, something to the effect of, are you proud of your son?
Al, that's not because you look old. That's not why Peter said that.
It's just you were wearing a strange suit.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. And your hair was a bit darker.
And he says to the mom, are you proud of your boy? And you initially, his mom didn't want him to
go down this path because she knew he was just a gentler soul than her husband, who was like a hard
ass. And then you see in this moment how proud she is of him and you see his face. It was this
beautiful look on Douglas's face as he looks at his mom saying how proud she is of him. And I
think at that point, someone basically makes the comment might have been in the narration that
he was just always closer to his mom. Like he was really his mom's child.
It's Bruce talking and he says, you know, that he favored his mother. I think those are the exact
words. His disposition was more like his mother, little pearls. He was not the stone cold killer
that his father, Bill Douglas, was in the ring. And that's the contrast to, of course, you know,
Bill Douglas was not a world champion. Bill Douglas was not Mike Tyson. He was a guy who
many people thought deserved title shots and didn't get them because he could do so much damage and
upset the apple cart. But his approach was Tyson like, and he fought with the same style and the
same commitment and the same determination to not just win, but to destroy. And that wasn't Buster.
On a little segue that I want to come back to the boxers who have fought with that ethos,
Sonny Liston, Jack Dempsey, George Foreman, Mike Tyson. There was a really interesting article in
Sports Illustrated and I believe it was March of 88. So it was even before Tyson fought Spinks.
If I recall, Larry Bird was on the cover. So it was a very nondescript article. And I wish I could
find it because I, you know, I used to have every Sports Illustrated ever. Wow. And my mom, like 15
years ago, called me, you know where this story is going, don't you? It's just going to break your
heart. I had the first, I had the Eddie Matthews on the cover one. I mean, I had every newspaper
clipping you could ever have on this stuff. And it was boxes upon boxes upon boxes. And my mom calls
me like 15 years ago and she's like, look, Peter, do you want to come and get these things? And I
don't know. I just was like, no, you can pitch them. And like, it's like top three shames of my
life. But nevertheless, there was this. Can't blame her. She asked my mom. It's my fault, not yours.
So at least I could have had them digitally archived or something. Something. So it's this,
again, March 7th, 1988 throwaway article of Sports Illustrated just before the Tony Tubbs fight,
if I recall, because remember he fought Tubbs in Tokyo in like March. First event to the Tokyo
Dome. That's right. March 21st, 88 or something like that. You're really good. Two round knockout.
Tony Tubbs looked like he looked like nothing. The article makes an interesting point. And the
point was this. Now remember, Mike Tyson is three years into the reign of terror and he looks
utterly invincible. And the author says, you know what? The flames that burn this bright burn out
really quick. And the author went back and said, look at Dempsey. This is how bright that light
shone. And then it was gone. And look at Liston and look at Fraser and look at Forman. And they're
like, if you put Tyson in that bucket, this is not a guy who's going to have a long career. He is
going to implode. And I remember reading that as a 13 year old going for 12 year old, whatever the
hell I was thinking, this guy's an idiot. He doesn't know what he's talking about. Tyson's going
to be the champion till he's 40. Like it again, which of course, Mike didn't even think he'd be
alive till he was 30. You were going out on a limb. So you just sort of think like, how much does
history repeat itself? Whereas when you look at the guys like Lewis and Ali, the ones that have
had the really, really long careers, you know, there's something different about it. There's
just something different about their ethos. They're a different type of person. They're not killers.
And it's not to say like they're gentlemen versus killers, but it's just
they're artists in a way that I think some of the most destructive and feared fighters were not.
Yeah, well, there's no doubt about that. Because if you fall in love with your right hand, and the
knockout in particular, you're going to get lazy, and you're going to get one dimensional, and you're
going to get exposed eventually. And there are enough good fighters out there who can box who
bring other skills to bear. And if you've got some kind of deficiency, they're going to locate it,
they're going to find it, they're going to wear you down. It is one of those interesting things,
though, those guys, those destroyers, you know, the Dempsey's and the Liston's and, and the
Tyson's and you know, as well as I do there, there are similarities and there are a lot of differences
also when we talk about guys like that. But if you are being hailed as the destroyer as the guy who
can do everything and can get it done with one punch, you're not going to be listening the same
way to your trainer, to Kevin Rooney or Teddy Atlas or Aaron Stowell, the way if you've had to
box, you've had some challenges. I mean, the interesting thing about I've been talking about
this a lot the last couple of months. And the thing about Tyson, right, is that he's the heavyweight
champion, he's considered invincible, he has this aura about him that no one has had since Dempsey.
So I was going to ask you about that. Because I just, it's hard to extract that from the literature.
Do you believe that Tyson's aura was greater than that of Foreman's and Liston's at the respective
times? Yeah, I mean, I guess I'd have to go back and look, I mean, after Foreman does what he does
to Joe Frazier and all that, but I think so because, you know, there's just more of it. And at that
point, he'd taken on all comers. He there was nobody and there was more of it. The fashion which he did
it to so many different guys, I think it was bigger. I think it was more impressive with Tyson at that
time. And it was also his own way of speaking about things, his story where he came from the
kid from reform school. Anyway, I mean, you know, there's similarities to with Liston. But I think
it's not a parallel really with Lewis. Because most people would tell you, and I'm gonna assume
you're one of them that Joe Lewis is the greatest heavyweight champion of all time. I was gonna ask
you what your thought was. It's certainly between Lewis and Ali. Right. So let's say it's Joe Lewis,
but Joe Lewis, before he becomes champion, as we earlier discussed, has already lost a fight.
Yeah, he was knocked out.
Knocked out, humiliated against an older guy that everybody thought was over the hill. So when he
becomes champion, he doesn't have that aura that Tyson has. He builds a different kind of aura.
And he builds a different kind of championship record with that blemish from the Schmeling fight
already behind him. Now, if he doesn't have that moment with Schmeling, right? Maybe it's a
different story. The fact that he had that moment, that more than a moment of adversity, he had that
huge setback to his career. It was a year before he would fight again, wasn't it? Before he would
get the Braddock fight. And it was no sure thing that Braddock would fight him. I mean, remember,
at this point, it's been more than 20. It's been 22 years since an African American has been allowed
to fight for the heavyweight championship. And there was no guarantee that in 1937, that the
boxing establishments would permit it or the public would demand it. It looked like it was heading that
way until he lost to Schmeling. And then it was like, well, we don't have to give this guy a shot.
Anyone who has an excuse. Yeah, exactly.
Right. But Braddock gives him a shot. And it's part of a business deal where he gets a percentage of
Lewis's earnings for 10 years on a great business deal. You wonder, you know, ethically about the
deal. But anyway, I don't remember exactly the point I was making. But Lewis is different. Dempsey,
I think, is similar. Dempsey, you know, he was a destroyer. And there was this cloak of menace.
Did your dad ever meet Dempsey? Because Dempsey didn't, I mean, he lived around for a long time.
He lived until 1983. He had a restaurant here.
He lived for a very long time, Jack Dempsey. And apparently, I mean, I'm not sure about the very
last years, but up until his mid 70s. I mean, I know that he was all there. And it's remarkable.
This isn't a guy who just had all of those knockdown drag out professional fights. I mean,
he fought hundreds of fights as basically a semi pro in mining camps in Colorado and
the toughest possible atmosphere you can imagine. I mean, a lot of it was barefisted and no holds
barred. And I mean, I can't imagine the kinds of now he was great. So I don't know how much punishment
he was taking. But when you're a young guy coming up there, you're getting hit. Oh, but to look at
the Dempsey fights are some of the most amazing things you can remember, though, when he becomes
champion, right. I mean, he goes three years from 1923 to 1926 without defending his title.
He is such a big celebrity. He's making so much money just off the championship and its significance
that he doesn't have to get into the ring. Finally, you know, he gets in the ring in 1926,
and he loses to Gene Tunney in Sesquicentennial Stadium in Philadelphia. And then they got the
rematch a year later, which is still arguably the biggest sports event in the history of the world.
Dempsey, Tunney to its Soldier Field. I'd probably make a case it's the biggest sports event in its
moment of all time. And he loses again. This one's a long count and all that. But it's funny, the
two biggest sports events of all time in my book are Ali Frazier one, March 8 1971, and Dempsey
Tunney to 1927 and Soldier Field. And the guys that we always talk about are the guys who lost
those fights, Ali and Dempsey, not the guys who won them, Tunney and Frazier. There's a beautiful
picture I once saw of Ali that morning walking in Central Park in the snow. And it's sort of
amazing. I mean, that's part of, I think what makes New York such an interesting place is the history.
And I think the whole Atlantic City in the eighties and Las Vegas, it's sort of taken away a little
bit from how remarkable it is to fight in Madison Square Garden and what that would have meant,
like how anticipated that fight was. And of course, when Tyson fought Spinks in 88 in Atlantic City,
most people who knew enough about the sport said, look, this is the most anticipated fight in the
heavyweight division since 1971. I mean, this is a really big deal. And of course, at the time,
that was only 16 years earlier, which seems kind of amazing to me, given what an eternity 16 years
is when you are 16 years old. When you're young, yeah. It's like, oh my God, that was the dark ages.
Yeah, whatever it was. So one question on the 42 to one, 30 for 30, did you guys even try to
interview Tyson? Yeah, so it's interesting because some people felt dissatisfied that we didn't have
today's stuff from Mike, we made a decision, I went to talk to Mike, Mike declined to take part
in the process. I had interviewed him in 2017, though, and asked him a lot of questions about
the fight. And we hadn't used that, I think anywhere. At one point, we had a cut of film
where we had a lot of it. And we had a few bites from it. And we made an artistic decision,
essentially at that point, that we wanted to see Mike only in context from the time of the fight,
who he was then, because seeing him now with the tattoo, and the way that he's changed, you know,
he's, he can be very quiet and low energy. It's such a stark contrast to what we're showing you
of him then, that it's almost jarring. And everybody knows the Mike Tyson story. I've done
no wisdom or Mike Tyson stories than me, literally, you know, on TV anyway, interviewed
more on TV than I have, I would think long form stories about him all that. I just felt this is
Buster's story. People know the Mike story people hear from Mike all the time, we still hear from
Mike all the time. The more you put Mike in it from today, I see your point you detract, you
detract a bit. Yeah. And what did Mike talk about in 2017 when you interviewed him about that fight
specifically? Because I've never really heard him talk much about that fight. There's so much about
him in Holyfield, and the men's that's been made and all those other things. But what is recollection
of that? Probably the best fight we had from that interview is something like where he said, look,
was Buster Douglas a better fighter that morning, that afternoon? Yes. Does that mean that he's a
better fighter than me? No. That's a fair point. He's certainly entitled to make that point. But
in terms of like, what happened? He said, I was living my life too fast. I was doing crazy stuff.
I was this, I was that, you know, it was in people say, well, that's making excuses. It's like, well,
I asked him what happened. I mean, whether it's an excuse or not. I mean, that's the truth,
I think, in his mind, I think he feels if he had approached that fight,
with full commitment, he would have wanted. But of course, he's going to think that and
that does not diminish what Buster Douglas did. Because I mean, if we're gonna, if we're gonna
say, well, it doesn't count, then then you know, nothing counts. Did the Soviet team really
approach the American kids in the Olympics the way they would have approached the Czechs or
something like that? No. Or the Canadian All-Star team or the, you know, NHL All-Star team? No. But
if you're gonna say, well, then it doesn't count, then nothing counts. It's just silly. No, in the
end, everything counts. That was a great line, by the way, with the bookie in Vegas. I love that part,
by the way, of him actually talking about the bats. And, you know, he was like, look, people say
that the miracle on ice was the biggest upset in sport. It's not even within a country mile that
that was the biggest upset in sport. Is there ever been Vegas odds bigger than 42 to one overcome?
In a heavyweight championship fight? No. In any sport? Oh, I think so. You know, a lot of people
say, well, Leicester City is a bigger upset because they were 5,000 won or something to
win the Premier League. Oh, yeah, of course. How could I forget that? That's a pretty amazing example.
Yeah, but to me, that's totally different. There wasn't a single game that season. I mean,
I don't know what I'd have to go back and look. Yeah, I bet there wasn't a single game that was
more than four to one or five to one. You know what I mean? And a season long thing.
That's a very good point. Yeah. Yeah. You know, in every year, there's somebody who wins a
conference or who wins a professional league or a championship who was, I think the St. Louis Rams
were 300 to one. That's right. So, I mean, look, even the New England Patriots, the first year they
won the Super Bowl. But all of that stuff is based on teams that because we don't know how those
teams are constituted. Buster Douglas was Buster Douglas. He was the guy who had had six fights
since Tony Tucker. People still thought he was 42 to one. Leicester City, the St. Louis Rams,
whatever you want to say, nobody knew who that team was. That wasn't the team that you had seen
the previous season. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, it's in the single event that's still kind of unusual odds.
Well, it was great. You know, the other thing that was nice to see was, for me at least,
because I hadn't seen much of Buster Douglas in many years, because I remember in 95 when he was
almost dead. I mean, five years after that fight, he's in a diabetic coma, 380 pounds. Bigger than
that. Yeah, really. I mean, yeah, it was kind of nice to see him. I like Buster very much. I've
spent a lot of time with Buster over the years. You know, I'm always cautious about saying this,
he's this or he's that when by the standards of my profession, I've spent a lot of time with him,
you know, three days here, two days here, a dinner here, a dinner there. Is he somebody that I've
spent like a work colleague where you spend years around them? I don't know, but I like Buster.
I think he's a good guy. He's a good person. He has not been a self promoter, which I think
has hurt him financially over the years. I think his feelings have been hurt because people for
so long have tried to diminish this victory. And there's so many avid Mike Tyson fans
who always want to make excuses for him, who always want to discredit Buster, for whatever
reason it is, I felt like he had not been fully appreciated for the magnitude of this.
What do you think went wrong after Tyson? Why do you think he didn't show up in shape for Holyfield?
Because on paper, he should have given Holyfield a hell of a fight. I think Douglas was a better
fighter than Riddick Bowe. I mean, you could certainly make that case. I mean, Riddick had
some great moments, most of them against Evander Holyfield, but he was Buster was a very skilled
boxer and he was a very good athlete and he was schooled in the sport. And when he was fully
dedicated and committed, which we saw only on a few occasions, he was very tough to beat.
And I don't think anybody I don't give his Jag Dempsey or Gene Tunney or John L. Sullivan himself
would have beaten him in Tokyo that day. I really don't think so. But after he defeats Tyson,
everything is just so chaotic. It's the typical story we hear, you know, too much, too fast,
too many people pulling at him. He's in court with Don King. He's in court over the long count
in the eighth round. All of this, as we would say, mishegas is, you know, driving him crazy. He's
getting rid of the people in his camp who had made it possible for him to achieve these great heights.
He's got a new team in there and he signs at the time for $24 million to fight Holyfield,
the largest person in the history of sports. Nobody had ever gotten a check like that in the history
of sports, which is like $48 million now. And even after the taxes and paying out Don King and
paying off his team, he still got like $9 million in cash, like $18 million today, something like
that. And I think his motivation was gone. And I think the reality of his mother's death sunk in
when she died, he had the fight to focus on. And now he's got this complicated, weird relationship
at times with his father, who's now like going to Don King's party when I think Buster is still
suing Don King. I mean, there's all kinds of crazy stuff going on. He doesn't, I think Buster would
be the first to admit he doesn't show up for that fight. Physically, mentally, motivationally,
didn't care. There's something about boxing that, I guess this is part of what attracted me to it
as a participant and then eventually always just as a fan. And maybe I have a slightly different
insight into it because I've done it, but the ring is a really lonely place. It's hard to put
in words what the fear is like when you get in the ring. And again, maybe it's just that that was
just who I was. And maybe there are some people who get in the ring and they're not afraid. But
even Tyson, I remember once said, anybody who gets in a boxing ring and who is not scared,
senseless is lying or crazy. Yeah. My thought was that-
Now I don't think he was scared by the time he got in the ring against Buster.
I don't think Mike was. But you have to have a relationship with fear.
Even if you feel like you're going to win, I think anytime I stepped into a ring, I felt like
I was going to win. There are no words to describe that anxiety. There's nothing I've ever experienced
since. No professional thing I've ever done that has put that much adrenaline into my body
that borders on the point of being like you're on the verge of it being unproductive.
And the audience can sense that. For me, I've seen a lot of great things in person.
By the time they fight in 2002, Lennox and Mike are both over the hill. They're 36 years old,
37 years old, something like that. And yet people have called it the last great fight,
the last big fight. I was covering that fight. I wasn't far from-
Did you see that beating being that bad?
That's what I thought. I really did think so. And I was working with a lot of people who thought
I was crazy, who thought that Mike was going to win. I think Mike was the favorite in a lot of
people's lives. Oh my God. I thought he was going to lose, no question. But I didn't expect
to see him beat up that badly. I'd seen Mike fight a lot over the previous seven years. I'd
seen Lennox fight more. And yeah, I didn't see how he would beat Lennox. Lennox Lewis,
top 10 heavyweights of all time? Off the top of my head, without going back and looking at
those two losses to McCall and Rockman, which they count. Yeah, I guess he's probably somewhere
right around there, right around the 10, 11, 12, something like that.
So asked another way, from Muhammad Ali until today, who are the three best? Larry Holmes,
let's give you Larry Holmes, right? He's got to be in there.
Okay. Yeah, Larry Holmes has got to be in there. Lennox has got to be in there.
Put Klitschko in there?
I think, yeah, the question is which one or both. I mean, two pretty impressive guys
who did impressive things. After Lennox fights, Vitaly in 2003, and Vitaly performs well,
but he doesn't win the fight and he gets a cut and you know, all that. After that, I kind of
stopped paying as much attention to the heavyweights and they, you know, they took the belts
off to Germany and we never really saw much of those fights. And there were a lot of guys that
were fighting who were kind of unknown entities. So I'm a little reluctant to talk too much about
the careers of either Klitschko brother. I don't know quite how to measure them, but before that.
But there was a sea change, right? I mean, I think there was an introduction of athleticism
to the heavyweight division that I don't think you saw before. And I think that the prototype
of the Lewis, the Riddick Bow, the Razor Roddocks, the Klitschkos, I mean, there's just a different
level of athleticism size and they are so big. So they are so freaking big.
Which is why it was so amazing to me to see a guy like Deontay Wilder, who is still undefeated
at this point after the Fury fight. And you know, maybe he's the guy who fights Joshua. Maybe it's
Fury, who knows whatever it is. There's a guy who's 212 fighting 212 pounds, who's arguably
the best heavyweight in the world, arguably, because we saw these guys getting 240, 250,
and they're gigantic. They're mountains. They're primo carnera size, these guys.
But with skill, right? I mean, carnera was just a clown.
Just size. So you don't think you're ever gonna go backwards from that? They were very tough guys,
Klitschko brothers. I could sit here and talk about boxing forever because it's not often I get to
talk to somebody who sort of thinks about it the way I do. But there are a few other things I want
to talk about. And sort of one of them is your most famous interview, right? With Bobby Knight.
So you don't have to say anything good or bad about him, but having never met him,
he just strikes me as just a deplorable human being. I don't know what it is about him. Maybe
truthfully, maybe there's a part of myself I see, like, you know, I have a really bad temper. And
I look at him and I think, God, I hope I've never done one one hundredth of what that guy has done.
I hope I've never hurt anybody the way he's hurt somebody. Did you see the 30 for 30? I did. And
it only solidified in my mind how much I despise him. Yeah, my friend Robert Abbott. Oh, it's one
of the saddest ones I've ever seen. It is so goddamn sad to me how many people's lives have
been destroyed by him. Here's the thing. I knew Bob Knight. I mean, again, you know, I say,
know somebody, you know how well I, my father was a friend of Bob Knight's. I had spent time with
Bob Knight before that interview. I was one of those people who appreciated his talents. And he
had this quote unquote genius, quote unquote genius and his sense of history, his sense of loyalty.
Look, there are good qualities there. There are other people who can, you know, talk, you can
watch the film, talk about the dark side of Bob Knight. The interview was a challenge.
How many days after he was fired was the interview? I want to say it was 72 hours later. It might have
been 48. It was, I can't remember exactly. Why did he give you that interview? Well,
I think he gave me that interview because he thought he could steamroll me and he'd known me.
And so what year was this 2000 2000. So your dad was still alive. My dad was still alive. What did
your dad tell you going into that interview? You know, I spoke to a lot of people the night before
the interview and the day of the interview because it's one of those, those situations. And I was
young. I just turned 31. And this is the biggest thing that's going on, not just in sports, but in
America period, at this moment in time, it really was. And I knew I had to get it right. I knew the
stakes were high for me. And so I spoke to a lot of people and I'm trying to remember what my dad
told me. I really don't remember what his advice was about the questions or this or that. I spoke
to a lot of people who told me, you know, it was important, of course, to ask him the tough questions
and not back down. And I think that's what I did. And that's, that's what people said at the time.
They said, you know, chaps stood up tonight. He didn't let the bully bully him. I asked the
right questions. I got to the important points. And I think perhaps most important, because there
was a moment of peak when I think he revealed himself in a way that he wouldn't often in live
television interview, that that really kind of said who he was more than anything else.
And so people still remember that interview. It was kind of what do you think is the most
memorable exchange of that interview? Well, that's indisputable because people remember it very well.
We're having a discussion. We're having a talk about the zero tolerance policy, which is ultimately
what led to his termination, ultimately what led to his termination. And he's explained telling me
how he doesn't know what zero tolerance meant and nobody ever defined it for him. And he was put in
a lose lose situation, whatever the exact words were. And he says in the real victim here is Pat,
his son who was one of the assistant coaches, the real victim here is Pat because Pat is going to
lose his job. And I feel it's my obligation at this point to point out and say, Bob, but
Pat wouldn't be losing his job if you had behaved yourself, if you had done what you were told to do.
And that's when he got angry, very angry. And he looked at me and he said, he glared at me. He said,
be careful here. You've got a long way to go until you're as good as your dad. And I said,
I appreciate that and moved on. But that's the exchange that everybody remembers. And my friend,
Willie Weinbaum, producer, I work with a lot. He's one of the guys I talked to before the interview,
great journalist, great interviewer. And he said, just remember, he's probably going to invoke your
dad at some point or compare you unfavorably, use that as a weapon in his arsenal. And I don't
really remember if it registered or didn't register, but I remember Willie did say that. And of course,
that's what people remember. But at the time, for me, it was like a kind of a career defining moment
all of a sudden, it was like, welcome to the big leagues. So what is it like then with a father
who's a legend? And it's not like you decided to become a dentist or an anesthesiologist. You
decided to do what your dad did. And that means subject yourself to constantly being compared to
him and living in his shadow. What did your mom say about that? You know, maybe I'm just getting
old. I don't remember. I don't remember us ever having really a conversation about it. Not only
not with my mother, but not really with my father. I mean, I grew up, especially when I was very young
before my parents divorced, like at his side, I mean, going to sports events with him going to the
I remember, on the weekends, you know, what I did was I went to the office with my father in the
morning while he prepared sports stories and sports reports on NBC back then. And I hung around the
office and I read sports books. It was almost like my entire life had been an apprenticeship
in the business. So and you weren't worried about the shadow. Maybe I should have been.
I ever gave it a second thought. I know that sounds ridiculous. No, no, it doesn't. Actually,
it's it's it's remarkable. I mean, I don't do anything that my dad does. My dad, you know,
he runs quarries. So I couldn't be further from what my dad does. But yet, in many ways,
I do compare myself to his work ethic. Right. I mean, like even a few weeks ago, I was sort of
complaining to my therapist. I was like, God, you know, I don't think I can work as hard as my dad.
And it's deep down. It makes me feel a little bit ashamed that, you know, my father's never been in
a bad mood. He's like the most upbeat, positive, optimistic immigrant that ever lived. Tomorrow is
always going to be a better day. And he can. Where did he come from? From Egypt. And he can will his
way into the world. Like what he wants to happen will happen. And, you know, as a kid, I never once
saw my dad even in bed. You know, he was coming home after I was asleep and he'd be up and gone
in the morning. Like he never slept in on a Saturday or anything like that. So you just had
this view of like, this is like a Superman. And of course, me, you know, I'm different. I can be
lazy at times and I can get into, you know, a fun. But you're still a very productive person. You're
just measuring yourself against an impossible standard. Right. But don't we all do that? I mean,
Oh, I do it. Compare ourselves to. That's what I'm saying is at least for me, I can keep the distance
between what we've done professionally. So, so I really can only compare myself to my father in
terms of work ethic, sacrifice, and just general disposition. But now you have all of those things
to compare yourself to. Plus, you know, being on the son of one of the most legendary sportscasters
of all time. Well, I think I'm just going to go lie down on the couch. Tell me, tell me how you're
really sure. You're right. I got to say that it really is a testament, I guess, to my naivete or
just stupidity that I got into this business without really thinking about that. And I just
knew that I wanted to be in the media. I wanted to work in TV. I wanted to be a writer. I wanted to
work. I wasn't sure if I wanted initially to be in sports or news. I started out working in news at
a local TV station here in New York and transitioned into sports. But I'd been in sports. So
that was kind of the tension wasn't was I got to be in the media, it was like, what exactly am I
going to do? For me, that was the question. And of course, when I made the decision to do sports,
and not to do news, not to do something else, then of course, you know, I was walking right into my
father's field. And I grew up around a guy who I really think was the best at what he did. He was
a great writer. He was a great journalist. He was he was a great TV storyteller. And I figured,
well, if he could do it, I could do it. That's amazing. You know, I do remember reading an
interview very recent, actually, maybe it was maybe maybe was a year ago, but someone once asked
you about, you know, lessons you learned from your father. And I would I remember you saying, I'm
going to have to paraphrase it, the gist of it was what it means to be fair as a reporter, what
fair journalism means, which means you do have to ask hard questions. And you do have to probe in
areas that are uncomfortable. But you've got to have a bit of empathy, you have to be able to put
yourself in the shoes of the person you're speaking with. And I don't know, I feel like that doesn't
exist all that much in journalism anymore, does it? I mean, maybe it doesn't. I'm just not aware
of it. And we see so many exceptions. But anyway, the way you described it, I thought was very
beautiful. And you really attributed it all to your father. Yeah. And I think he did operate in
that manner. It wasn't just idle talk. It was what informed his, his body of work. And I worked
in a business where there are people who are all about access. And they never asked the tough
questions. And then I work, you know, with people to who work with or there are people in the
business, I don't really, I can't think of any colleagues who are like this, but you see it
happen. It's like, they're tough for the sake of being tough. Yeah, yeah, exactly. They're
antagonistic just to be antagonistic. And I think I've built a reputation 30 years of the business
of being the guy who does ask the tough questions and doesn't shy away and is willing to sacrifice
relationships for the truth. And that's important. But fairness is the underpinning of everything,
right? You know, it's not just about being fair to the subject is about being fair to the audience.
It's about being fair to the story and fair to the truth. And it seems like it's a pretty simple
principle, really, to, I think it's not like I'm a Scotty Reston here. Or, you know, I mean, you know,
I work in the world of sports or the toy department, but it's a pretty simple principle. But I can't
say that it's always applied. We were talking about this a while ago, but it's sort of hard to
believe your father died in 2001 because it feels a lot more recent to me. And maybe that's just a
sign that we're all getting a little older. Time starts to travel faster because 2001 on paper is
a long time ago. But it's interesting because I believe his last broadcast was the Sunday after
9 11. And he actually talked about the insignificance of sport in the context of what had happened,
what, five days earlier. He would go on to have an elective hip operation a couple weeks later.
And one complication slash medical error after another. And ultimately he died. You're young,
you're 30 at the time. 32. 32. How hard was that? Oh, it was dead on two levels. Right. I mean,
I'm asking it sounds like an idiotic question, right? It's not, it's not hard to lose. But
it's one thing to lose somebody when they're old enough that you just expect to lose them. It's
another thing when someone goes into the hospital to have a procedure done and mistakes get made
and they don't come out of the hospital. It was devastating. I was extremely close with my father
and we had been, you know, for a long time at that point, there had been a period, you know,
in my teens and my parents divorced where the relationship had frayed. I mean, it felt like a
million years at the point when it was happening, but it's probably 18 months or something like that.
And then, you know, I went off to college and then I went into the business and we were doing
radio shows. I mean, we probably spoke once or twice a day and saw each other frequently.
They lived in the same place and connected by the business work for the same company. I mean,
you know, so there's the personal anguish seeing your father go through something like this and
he's in a coma most of the time, you know, you can't communicate with him. There's nothing when
he goes under, they put him in, you know, an induced coma to let him heal. You never get a
chance to say goodbye. And 13 weeks in ICU, you know what that takes out of family and the guilt,
like, are you there every day? Are you not there? I mean, all of that stuff. And then for it to also
be playing out, you know, as a public story as well, people would happen to ditch out what's going on,
how sick is he? Is he going to recover? You know, that doesn't make it any easier. And this is all
against the backdrop of this national calamity, which had taken place a few miles south of the
hospital in which he was in the intensive care unit. So there is that surreal grief stricken
moment as well in the history of the city in that country. So it all feels like a bad dream,
everything that was going on in the fall of 2001 for me, you know, and then, you know, there were
moments also, it's all it's made even more painful by the moments where you think they're telling you,
oh, he's made a turn for the better he's gonna be I mean, literally, I think, within two or three
days before he died, it seemed like he had suddenly recovered. And they were making plans
to take him out of the coma and slowly wake him up again. And you know, but you got to remember,
you know, I remember having a talk with one of the doctors like, you got to understand your father's
going to be he's recovering, but he's not going to be the same guy, he's gonna have to go to
rehab facility for a while, you know, strength back and this and that, but he's gonna be back,
and then all of a sudden, it was like, and I don't even you know, honestly, I don't remember what
happened in those two or three days after that. I mean, I remember what happened. I remember being
there when he died, but I don't remember how it went from so hopeful and optimistic to over very
quickly. So it was very hard on several levels. Was there anything about that collective experience,
meaning the loss of your father, which is, I mean, literally superimposed on 911 that made you
revisit your connection to sports? Did you ever go through the phase of, oh my god, I'm devoting my
life to a game versus no, wait a minute, sports is an amazing substrate for metaphor for life. Like,
how did you go through that process? I mean, I remember very vividly having a discussion.
I don't know if he remembers, but having a discussion with Keith Olbermann during the
baseball playoffs that year. And we were so this is a few weeks after 911 with my father in a
coma in the hospital. And we weren't talking about that we were talking about 911 and Keith,
with that time was still working in sports, I think at Fox Sports at that time. He's a very
smart guy, friend of mine, smart guy. He was telling me like, we can't be in sports anymore.
Everything is over. Everything we've known has changed everything. Nothing will ever be the same.
The country's going to be under constant attack. I mean, the result, you know, he's saying, you know,
get out of sports now, because nobody's going to care about sports anymore. And I remember not
being able really even in that moment process where you're saying but it certainly made sense.
It's it's how we felt at the time, as a country, like everything was discombobulated. We didn't
know where we stood anymore, in some regards. But for me personally, I remember having that
discussion. But I don't remember that being a moment where I say and myself,
I want to get out of sports, I want to do something different. I had had those discussions
a few years before that people at ABC News about maybe transition. I remember I wanted to go.
I had a meeting up there, one point where I said, you know, I don't want to work in sports anymore.
I want to transition. I want to go cover the war on the Balkans or something like that. And like,
no, we don't want you to get killed over there. Something like that. And I wasn't qualified. But
no, I don't remember reassessing my relationship with sports in that moment, except I did have an
immediate reaction to the whole idea that sports was going to make everything better. And if the
Yankees won the World Series, which they went ended up losing that it was this, that it would be this
incredible moment of catharsis or something like that. I thought it would be a few minutes of
catharsis. What do you think today many years later, right? We're already we're back in the
swing of things. What do you think is the most important thing that following sports as a
spectator, as a fan does for us? Because in many ways, what people like you do is you provide a
narrative that gives us who don't know as much a nuanced understanding. Again, just even to me,
like you probably won't find a bigger ESPN 30 for 30 fan than me. Like there might be two I haven't
seen. But I love that type of deep exploration. The story behind the story behind the story.
What do you think that does for people outside of the obvious, which is teaches you about a
sporting event? Well, I think that there's a greater appreciation now for sports is something
more than the toys or the toy department when we cover it that, you know, it's not just tribal.
It brings us all together. Right. I mean, I travel all over the country, I travel internationally a
lot, you can have discussions with sports with people anywhere. And it's, you know, in a lot of
ways, it's gotten harder to have discussions about other things, as we know, and, and sports can be
divisive as well. So there is the sense that it is this lingua franca, right? Some guy I don't know,
I'm sitting next to on a plane, we could have a four hour discussion. Right. Because you can't,
you don't want to talk about religion or politics. And yeah, there are too many things you
can't talk about anymore. There's that and we just like talking about sports too. We like sports.
And sometimes we overlook like the physicality of it, how much watching just the remarkable
way that athletes use their bodies and their minds, we sometimes lose appreciation for that.
There's so many things about sports that can be edifying. And also for me, I've used sports as
a platform to tell stories about other things going on in the world that transcend sports about
societal issues about cultural issues about crises of sexual abuse, homophobia, whatever they
are. I mean, a lot of the stories that I've done over the years, sports is a starting point, it's a
hook. And then it's about something bigger. And sports does that in a way, right, that other things
don't because so much of us are interested in sports, you know, there's a reason why
Jackie Robinson breaking the color line in 1947 is one of the most important moments in the annals
of the civil rights struggle. Why that's a watershed moment. There's a reason why Muhammad Ali
refusing induction is a watershed moment, whether you agree or disagree with him. Sports touches us
in a different way and it touches society in a different way. In Title IX, which wasn't just
about sports, we see mostly through the prism of sports when we talk about equality for women. And
the way in my father's lifetime that the emergence of the African American athlete was, I think,
the big story. You know, in a lot of ways, the last 40 years, the emergence of the female athlete,
the empowerment of the female athlete has been the big story. And sports is usually, I'm not going to
say always, but seems usually to be in the vanguard, you know, when society is going, you see
it first happening in sports. Now, in some ways, sports is old fashioned and resistant to change.
And there are plenty of examples of that as well. I mean, we could talk about golf clubs and that
kind of stuff. But sports has sparked change, and it's drawn our attention to issues. And I did a
story about Al Campanis on the 30th, I guess it was the 25th anniversary of the time of, you know,
his infamous Nightline interview where he said blacks lack the necessities to be coaches and
general managers. And I interviewed Ted Koppel and Ted Koppel told me I mean, Ted Koppel, the greatest
television newsman, I would argue of the last 50 years, the guy, you know, he said, the one
episode of Nightline, the one edition of Nightline, he gets asked about the most is the Al Campanis
episode, where he was so great in that moment. And he was so fair, but persistent and tough. And,
you know, but my point is that that moment, it sparked a discussion about a lot more than
coaches in the NFL or whatever. Yeah. So, Jeremy, you've reported on a ton of stories in sports.
And again, I'm a fan of many of them. But has there ever been one that you've done where in
retrospect you look back and you feel you made a mistake? Yeah, you know, I'm not sure if I would
characterize it as a mistake. And it's complicated. But I was the guy covering the home run chase in
1998 for ESPN with Mark McGuire. Wow. You know, so I was there, I saw, I think 20 of the 70 home runs
he hit in person. And I dipped in a couple times early in the season to do stuff when he was on
a great pace, I think, but I really picked it up in September, I think, when he had that crazy
September. So does that mean you interacted with Maris's family as well? I never interacted with
Roger Maris's family. No, but I was there when he broke the record when he hit 62. I mean, I was
there, I think, for every home run from 52 to 70. Wow. And there had been the story that summer
about the Andro and the locker, which now seems like, I don't know, if it was a red herring that
he was planting or, you know, the right way to put whatever it was. But looking back now, of course,
20 years later, or even five years afterwards, I wish I had approached that story with more
skepticism. Do you think you were just so caught up in the moment? Like you couldn't believe this
was happening? You know, it was funny, because of course, it wasn't as if it wasn't out there in the
ether. You know, people were talking about steroids, people had talked about them with him
going back, you know, years before. But the subject was kind of taboo. The Andro story
seemed to put everything to rest like, oh, he's not doing steroids that are
Yeah, it's Anderson Dion, which at the time was a supplement that was basically legal. Right. And
question became, well, maybe it is legal, but he shouldn't be using it. And the guy was prying it.
And I certainly didn't say vouch for him and say he's clean or anything like that.
But in the absence of evidence that he was cheating, we just kind of bought the story.
And I wish I'd been more skeptical because I don't know what I could have expressed at the time. And
I'm not letting myself off the hook. It was the entire national media. There was nobody expressing
any skepticism. Everybody was celebrating this. Everybody was so excited about the home run chase
and Sammy and Mark and all that. I was around Sammy too. But not the way that I was around Mark,
I was covering Mark every day for like a month plus. I wish I'd been more skeptical. Now,
because everything I saw was fake, was all fake. It doesn't mean anything anymore. You know, I saved
the newspaper. When Mark hit 62. I'm like, wow, I saw something really historic in the whole country
was I mean, you would have thought that you know, he'd landed on the moon. So I wish I had approached
that with more skepticism later when I covered cycling and I covered the Tour de France and I
covered Lance Armstrong's last two Tour de France victories. And then I covered his comeback as well.
I did ask the questions as I recall, you know, I asked them, Lance, you know, how does anybody
do this without being on EPO or where I mean, I asked the questions. But again, after he denies it,
there was great reporting. There was some great reporting being done by David Walsh at the London
Times. He got sued. The London Times lost a million pounds, I believe. I'm sure they've got back more in
space. Right. Yeah, going after him. So I asked the questions, but it was kind of like everybody
else asking the questions, but not digging deep enough to get to the truth, which was that Lance
was cheating too. In some ways, it's a bit sad. I've always had a soft spot in my heart for Roger
Maris because he's sort of a footnote to this story. But in some ways you could make the case,
he's still the home run King. And in that sense, that to me is where, and I'm probably biased,
but I find the cycling quote unquote scandal to be less upsetting because it really was a uniform
playing field. It was everybody doing it. I mean, you couldn't be a GC contender between 91 and
2010 without being on- The protocols were too good, were too effect. Yeah. Whereas we do tend to forget
what Mickey Mantle did and what, I mean, Mickey Mantle, he's in a different league because he's
so loved, but Maris sort of gets forgotten in a way. And when you think of that season,
when he hit 61 and how hated he was trying to do it and chase down Babe Ruth's record, like,
I don't know, I just have this softest spot in my heart for this guy. Oh, you know, and then that
phony stuff with McGuire and Sosa paying tribute to Maris' family at the time, I mean, that now we
look at and it's upsetting. This was Roger Maris' legacy, that record, the 61. And it was stolen
from him. And I think that's a fair way to characterize it. Look, a lot of guys were doing
it. Now, the counter argument, which again, I think the counter argument's a reasonable one is,
hey, the pitches were also doing it and the pitches were harder to hit off. And does that
normalize it? Does that equalize it? Well, the evidence, of course, is that it didn't normalize
it enough because the offense is what exploded. And it's not just, it's the magnitude. You're
the doctor, you understand this stuff, just because they're both using it doesn't mean that
it's as beneficial to the pitchers as it is to the hitters. And we saw that.
Well, that's interesting because when you think of it that way, and I can see why in hindsight,
you know, and I've actually had this discussion with Lance, which was, I actually believed Lance
was clean until, and this might make me sound like a dope.
Alpe d'Huez?
Nope. Because this is something you can do the math and justify on a Watts per kilo.
You could say, look, given what he did in 93 as a world champion in Oslo,
like the stuff that he would say back then, I was a world champion, you know, before.
But even doing the numbers, like you look at the Watts per kilo then and the Watts per kilo in
the Klein, when it became clear to me that he absolutely had to be doing this was when,
when Tyler Hamilton came out. Because Tyler Hamilton was the first guy that came out that
I thought was truly believable. I don't know. I don't know Tyler. I've never met him,
but he just struck me as so credible. And when Tyler basically spilled his beans,
and that's when you realized how ubiquitous it was. Because prior to Tyler, like you could make
the case, man, not everybody's doing it. But when Tyler came out and said, Oh, no, no, no,
we're all doing this.
Well, also the stuff with the Andraeus, it was frankly, I remember thinking at the time,
well, why would they be lying? I mean, they, the position as I remember it was they were
compelled to testify, to tell what happened in that hospital room. They didn't volunteer,
they weren't selling books, they weren't doing anything like that. They were asked under oath,
what happened? What was the conversation? Because Lance was getting sued. And they said, you know,
he had done steroids. And so it was easier for me to dismiss that because I always thought Betsy had
a little bit of a different agenda. I thought deep down Betsy was more pissed that Frankie had done
these drugs behind her back. I always thought there was something going on there.
Right. I just didn't see why they would lie under oath.
I always thought Betsy kind of wanted to be in the limelight more. But to me, Tyler was the
most credible cyclist to come forward.
And everybody who was covering it, and I was there for three summers, if you'd ask them,
your life's at stake, what's the right answer here? You know, the lady or the tire, like,
yeah, yeah, yeah.
You would have said, he's doing it.
Yeah.
They're all doing it. He's doing it. But we didn't have the proof.
I mean, Wada couldn't bust them. The cycling federation couldn't bust them. The French
couldn't bust them. The Spanish couldn't bust them. They had a very sophisticated,
I mean, in some ways, very sophisticated, almost clownishly, also brazen in some ways. You know,
they were so good at concealing it. And they were so aggressive about going after
anybody who questioned them. But we all thought.
And I will say this, though, Jeremy, it is it really chaps my ass that those seven years
have no champion. And yet you look in the years before and the years after, and there's a champion.
I mean, to me, that is ridiculous. And I, this will be, there's a lot that's ridiculous.
This will be the single most unpopular thing I'll ever say, I'm sure. I absolutely believe
Lance Armstrong deserves his yellow jerseys back. Because if you're going to take his away,
you better take away Pantanese, you better take away Ulrich, and you better take away
Bjorn Reese and probably Miguel Indran. And you know what I mean?
They did take away some of those, didn't they? Am I wrong?
None.
None. It is ridiculous.
That doesn't make any sense.
It's a little bit awkward.
You're right. That doesn't make any sense.
It's totally crazy.
Well.
And they certainly took away Floyd's.
Yes, but then they gave it to the guy right behind me. I mean, it's so ridiculous.
Yeah. So, well, anyway, no, that's, I can, I can see how now with the benefits of hindsight and
you feel foolish for having been swept up into it. We all do, right? I mean, we feel like.
Yeah. And at the same time as like, well, you ask the question, you get your kind of
same response from Lance, you know, why would I do that? Why would I put that in my body?
And everybody was so swept up in the story, the redemption story, the comeback story,
the survivor story. It was tough.
I think it's interesting today to look at cycling because to be honest with you,
I'm too far away from the sport and the numbers and they're still very concealed in what they do.
But I still think there's something going on. I just don't know what it is.
Me neither.
What's the most interesting story you think that's out there that isn't being told yet in sports?
Whew. There's so many stories that I think we don't pay attention to. I mean, there are big
issue stories. Obviously the head trauma stories, the biggest, I think the biggest story the last
20 years in sports. That's a story that's still obviously in the news all the time. That is being
covered. Are you surprised that hasn't had a bigger impact? I mean, or maybe it hasn't. I just,
I'm not aware of the metrics, but. I would say it's had a big impact. I mean,
youth participation, tackle football in certain parts of the country, plummeting.
And if that happens, it's a time question until college football starts to decline. And if college
football declines, then what does the NFL look like in 20 years?
That's the million dollar question, right? Like, does football have an existential problem?
Does it find a way to change the nature of what it's been for so long in a way that will alleviate
concerns about the long-term effects of head trauma? Does it become more regionalized where
we see it in certain parts of the country where people say this is part of what we do,
this part of our culture, and we reject the narrative that it's going to destroy the brains
of those who play? We don't know. We don't know. I mean, of course, what we do know is that
everything changes when you're in the moment. It seems like nothing will change. The NFL will
always be number one. Football will always be the most popular sport. You know, that's probably
how it felt to fans of baseball 60 years ago.
Or to fans of boxing in the 1930s.
Or fans of boxing in the 1930s. Or fans of harness racing in the first decade of the 20th century.
But what we do know is everything changes. Is head trauma going to be what changes
the way we consume football? Or is it only going to change the way that we participate in football?
Does the decline in participation necessarily lead to a decline in fan interest and viewership?
The other thing I have learned is not only does nothing stay number one and everything changes,
but no one can see the future. I mean, nobody is good at seeing the future with anything. Those
who can, many just get lucky and they don't do it a lot. Or they'd be in Vegas. Or now New Jersey.
I'd love to know what you think is the story that's not being told yet. Because I,
I mean, I think about it a little bit from my lens. And one of the things that I find interesting
is why drugs will always exist in some sports and why some sports seem relatively free of drugs.
Because I think drugs would help any athlete in any sport. I mean, I can't think of a sport in which
a drug, a performance enhancing drug, won't make a difference. And yet there are some sports that
are relatively clean. Like swimming. If you look at the United States and Australia, the two most
dominant countries, and there are certainly countries that have had lots of cheating. But
I do believe, and I don't think history will prove me wrong, but it could. I don't think that
Australia and the United States have a doping program in swimming. And yet they're the two
most dominant countries. But yet if you look at other Olympic sports, I mean, I am convinced the
track and field is always going to be full of growth hormone because it's undetectable.
That's the story I was going to say is the biggest story once you brought up drugs is that
human growth hormone is undetectable. So when we talk about guys who are clean,
we talk about female athletes who are clean, we really don't know what we're talking about.
Yeah, because HGH is effective. It does work. It makes a huge difference. And they say their
tests that detected, but they really don't. Right? You can test for its byproducts, but it's not like
testosterone. If a person takes exogenous testosterone, you can look for pair molecules,
you can look for epi testosterone. And if that's not rising at the levels of testosterone, you know,
they're taking it exogenously. And you can look at other hormones that get suppressed
when you take testosterone. So if you're taking testosterone exogenously from outside the body,
the pituitary hormones that tell the body to make it, luteinizing hormone, follicle-cementing
hormone, they go down. Yeah, there's lots of ways, but no, I think human growth hormone,
I don't have a lot of experience with it even clinically to know how effective it is, but
I think it's used pretty rampantly. My intuition is that that is certainly in most sports
got to be the drug of choice right now. And I think from my standpoint, the interest is,
do we have any sense of what the long-term harm is, which I don't pretend to know.
Yeah, I don't either, obviously. Well, we've got to get to this thing tonight, don't we?
We do. We do. We have to get there. We have to, we've got about a mile and a quarter to cover.
So, and it's rush hour in New York. We're going to walk there faster than we're going to go.
Last question, what is your favorite 30 for 30 that you weren't involved in making?
Wow, if I'm not involved. Give me three, without even ranking them if you want. Just give me a few
of your 30 for 30s that you love. It's an answer I think a lot of people give. I thought the Escabars,
the two Escabars, was great. I thought that was a great show. It was so heartbreaking. Yeah.
I was at that game at the Rose Bowl. You were? I was at that game at the Rose Bowl. I was 94.
94. I remember that vividly. Do you buy that if Pablo Escobar was still alive, Escobar would
not have been killed? It's been about nine years since that came out. I don't remember
my feelings. I don't even remember. Was that the conclusion that was drawn basically?
I don't even remember if that was the conclusion drawn from the 30 for 30 or if it was just my
conclusion post hoc. And maybe it was like rejuvenated when I watched Narcos a few years ago
and I got all reminded of everything in Escobar's life and the weird sense of loyalty that he had.
He was this evil guy with a good streak in him. I don't know. I wondered.
Yeah. I thought that was really powerful and well done. I thought The Night Show was really,
really well done as well. That's a very recent one. There have been so many. Last year alone,
there was the two Bills thing. Oh, the two Bills was pretty darn good. That's interesting. Yeah.
Those guys. One of the ones that I loved watching even when it came out, because it came out,
so Bo Jackson when I was a kid, that was my prime of-
I couldn't say that when I was in that one. That's right.
I'm disqualified for watching that one. When I go back and watch that, and my wife
and I were talking about this because we watched it for a third time a year ago maybe, we had that
moment of, are you freaking kidding me? I almost forgot how athletic that guy was.
You could make the case he's the greatest athlete ever.
Well, my father said he was. My father voted for him as the greatest athlete of the 20th century
in the sports century polling. I think he had a great case. It's interesting though.
Recently, I was with somebody who had played- I was interviewing Matt Millen,
who was waiting for a new heart. Just got a heart on Christmas Eve. He's doing well.
At this point, I'm going to see him again next week. Matt was telling me the teammate in Oakley,
he said, the funny thing is, and he had teammates who said this, Bo was obviously an incredible
track athlete, incredible football player, incredible baseball player, but he couldn't
dribble basketball. Interesting.
This was with Matt, I couldn't catch the football. Because he was a pretty good defensive player in
the outfield. He was not a good pass catcher. He didn't know the right technique to catch a
football as a running back coming out of the backfield. It was all hands. He didn't know how
to use his body to catch a ball. I think he said, there were guys, they try to teach me, and I say,
so it's an interesting dichotomy, because he's this incredible athlete with incredible hand-eye
coordination, incredible strength, incredible speed. Could have won the Olympic decathlon,
honestly, if he dedicated himself to that. But there are also these kind of lines.
Little gaps. When we talk about him, of course, then I also think about, you know what story
hasn't been done yet? Because it's been done, but it hasn't been closed. I'm kind of waiting for
Barry Bonds to just acknowledge the steroid use. I feel like, aren't we past the point where this
matters? Can't we just have an open and honest discussion about it and close the chapter?
Well, Sammy Sosa would tell you, no, I did something with Sammy this year. He certainly
wasn't prepared to go that far. I think from Barry's perspective, what does he have to gain?
And Barry's always had, how do I put this, a complicated relationship with the media.
Yeah, I think that's funny and loud.
And I don't think he cares. I don't think he has any interest in creating closure for us.
I'm going to create a lot of enemies by saying this, but I wish that Barry Bonds could just
acknowledge what he did and get into the Hall of Fame and be done with it. And we could acknowledge
that that was the era that we were in. A lot of people would find that a very controversial view,
but.
Oh, I don't think it's necessarily going to work either because Mark McGuire has admitted it and
he's not in the Hall of Fame.
Yeah, no, truthfully.
Yeah, they're different.
But Barry, you could make a much better case for Barry Bonds and Mark McGuire, right?
You could. You know, it's an interesting thing though, right? Like I've thought about this a lot,
probably way too much over the years, the Hall of Fame and steroids and all that. And I've heard
the argument many times, Roger Clemens and Barry Bonds are different because they were Hall of Fame
players before they started taking steroids. Although, of course, we don't know when they
started taking steroids. And this is based on the assumption that they did take steroids. And
it's hard to state that as just a fact. It's more complicated than that. But let's assume they did
take steroids and they should be in the Hall of Fame because they were these kinds of once in
a lifetime, once in a generation players before I said, okay, I get that. But they're being kept
out because they desecrated the record book in the minds of the voters by cheating. They broke
faith with the history of the game and the record book and all that they made a mockery of these
hallowed numbers, which means so much in baseball, not other sports. And nobody says, well, Joe Jackson,
I guess a few people, Joe Jackson's not in the Hall of Fame, nobody would dispute the fact that
he was a Hall of Fame player before the 1919 World Series. You know, it's like, well, he should be in
the Hall of Fame because up until the point that he participated in the fix or did not do anything
to stand in its way, he was a Hall of Fame player. Yeah, 356 career hitter. He's one of the greatest
hitters of all time. Babe Ruth, I think, called him the greatest hitter of all time. He'd been
around long enough. He's got the career numbers and all that. But you don't make the argument,
well, okay, but let's put him in the Hall of Fame because of what he did. It's what you did at that
moment that disqualifies you. Yeah, these are such tough questions. And for the sake of time,
I'm not going to take us down the path of cycling, which is another sport where I think
you can't do grand tours without drugs. And we've had a period, there was a 20 year period from,
call it 91 to 2011, 2010, I would say, when the drug use was simply comical. And what do we do
with those years? But anyway, all that said, Jeremy, this has been, I think it will be the
shortest podcast I've ever done, but that's only because we have this time constraint.
We're going to have to do it again then. I'm in.
We'll do around two. But no, this has been super interesting. And I just think that
I have a complicated relationship with sports. Sometimes I feel guilty for caring. Sometimes I
feel like, why do I care so much about this? Why am I not caring more about something else that
quote unquote matters more? But in the end, I think why I care about sports is they are basically the
substrate for some of the greatest metaphors we have in life. And I think when I think about why
do I want my kids to play sports? It's not because I think any one of them will ever be
a professional athlete. It's because of what they learn about themselves in this quest.
There's no doubt about that. And the other thing is, I mean, sometimes I think most people
are over this, but kind of the snobbish way of it, you know, sports is one thing, but the fine arts
are something else or, you know, ballet or opera or theater are on some plane that's above sports.
Look, I'll say this. There is nothing else. I mean, I'm a Giants fan. I was at the Super Bowl,
Super Bowl 25 when they won that game against the Bills and last second when Scott Norwood
missed that kick. That kind of joy you felt. That's another amazing. That might have been.
That was good. The four falls of Buffalo is. There's nothing else. I am a fan of the theater.
I'm a fan of the arts. I'm a fan of music. You don't go to a concert or you don't go to a
Broadway show or anything like that. And the end of it go completely nuts the way that,
say, for instance, it's Super Bowl 25. I was going nuts or all those hundreds of thousands of other
fans are going. I was at the World Cup final in 98 in Paris. I've been a three World Cup final games.
I was only one. The one in France 98 where the home team won. France wins its first World Cup
at home in that stadium in San Denis with 100,000 people. There's nothing else that gives us that
kind of moment. And that's universal. I mean, that's around the whole world. So there's
something special about sports that we've got to acknowledge. I think your point about it being
the lingua franca is actually I'd never thought of it that way, but I think you're right. It may be
the greatest lingua franca of them all. Or as I said it incorrectly lingua franca.
Maybe I'm saying it incorrectly. You're right. I think you're right.
Well, Jeremy, this is awesome. And thank you so much for your time. And let's go watch 42 to one.
For me, it's only the 45th time. It'll only be my second. You might still appreciate.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read,
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc. On social, you can find
me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. But usually Twitter is the best
way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials
linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not intended to be
a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard
or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the
assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most
importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures,
the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.