Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and their feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time, and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Chris Masterjohn. I've known
Chris for probably about six or seven years. He's an incredibly bright guy and we've been going back
and forth over the past several months just trying to figure out a date when we could get together.
And I knew this was going to be an exciting episode. I also want to preface this by saying
this may rank among one of the more technical episodes that we've done. And that's probably
saying a lot given our podcast. So this is definitely one where the show notes are going
to be helpful. So Chris earned his PhD about 10 years ago in nutrition science. And after a brief
stint as an academic, he has largely devoted himself to creating just a vast wealth of information
for people to help them understand so many aspects of nutrition. I have learned so much from Chris
over the years. And I must say I probably learned more on this podcast than I learn on many of the
podcasts that I host. Although I do like to learn something on every podcast and think that I do.
What do we talk about? Well, we talk about a ton of stuff. We kick this episode off by going deep
on choline. Choline deficiency is something that as Chris explains predisposes us to a whole bunch
of bad stuff, not the least of which is non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, which if you've
heard me rant on this before, you realize is an enormous epidemic and is in fact on pace to become
the leading cause of liver transplant in the United States. Of course, that leads us into a
lengthy discussion of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease and also a detailed discussion about the
different types of fats and how they may predispose us to different types of illnesses. We also get
into a topic that I get asked about all the time and I have purposely not gone into this in detail
because I've known that I want to have Chris on and I want to discuss this with Chris. And those
are the enzymes MTHFR and COMT. I get asked tons of questions about these and many of you ask
questions about methylation. They're great questions and I think it's safe to say virtually
every question you have on the topic of MTHFR methylation will be addressed here. We save the
best for last. And again, many of you have asked this question, Peter, what is your view on
nicotinamide riboside or NMN or NAD, Sirtuin activators, all of these things. Now we talked
about this stuff in pretty good detail with David Sinclair on one of the previous episodes. We go a
little deeper here and in particular that's because since the episode with David Sinclair,
there has been a little bit more research that's been published and we go really deep on some of
those papers. So I would say that by the time you're done with this episode, you will have
as much information as one could say is available on the use of supplemental products that contain
NR or NMN. So obviously the two of these that are most commercially known are Elysium's basis or
Chromadex's true nyogen. Again, I want to just say this episode is a little more technical than most
of our episodes. And again, I acknowledge the irony of that statement. That means it's really
technical. The show notes will be helpful. There may be parts of this that are more interesting
to you than others, although personally I found every minute of this to be like drinking from a
fire hose and truly learning this stuff. You can certainly find out more about Chris and his work
on his site, which is chrismasterjohnphd.com and that's basically spelt as you would expect it to
be. John is J-O-H-N. Chris is very active on social media, loves to interact with people.
So if you haven't heard about Chris prior to this episode, I suspect you'll become a fan of his
going forward. So I hope you'll enjoy my interview with Chris Masterjohn.
Hey Chris, thanks for trekking in, man. Thanks for having me, Peter. It's good to be here.
Yeah. So you said you've moved. You're no longer in Brooklyn, right? I moved to Astoria. So pretty
close by. Yeah. It was probably a quicker trek here from Astoria than Brooklyn, I think. Yeah.
It just has less cache, right? Like Brooklyn is so cool. Well, yeah, maybe I would have wanted to
spend more time in Brooklyn, but like, no, just geographically Astoria is more on the edge. Yeah,
it's a heck of a lot easier. Closer to the river. Yeah, yeah. And where'd you grow up?
So I was born in Queens actually. I kind of came full circle back, but when I was 10 months old,
my family moved to Massachusetts. So I grew up in a small town that almost no one has ever heard of
that wasn't big enough to have its own high school. And-
Impressive. So not Framingham? No, no, about an hour and a half west of Framingham.
And no accent? Yeah. You can do it on demand? No, just too far away from Boston.
Got it. And what did you study in college? I know you're, we'll talk about your PhD
because it's so interesting, but what did you study in college?
In my undergrad, I studied history. Okay. I focused on completely irrelevant things to
medicine and nutrition, like medieval church history and early American revolutionary history.
I originally wanted to be a social studies teacher. And so in my vision, I was majoring in
whatever was the most efficient way to get an undergrad that would be relevant to being a
social studies teacher. I just had such profound experiences with health in my last year or two
that I, by the time that I was in my last year, I completely changed my mind, decided I wanted to
go to medical school, but I had to finish my degree. And then in order to go to medical school,
which I didn't wind up doing, but in order to go to medical school, I had to take years worth of
undergrad science classes to get the basic prereqs. And while I was doing that, a combination of
my colleagues, my teachers, me falling in love with biochemistry and molecular biology and all
the little invisible things that we couldn't see. And also me starting to come up with my own
scientific hypotheses that I knew no one would ever research them unless I did all of that just
kind of combined to make me decide to go into research instead of medicine. So I think
what I really wanted to do is take my own experiences and pay them forward in some way.
And I think the best way that I can do that is by using the creative part of my brain to really
immerse myself in the research and come up with new ideas. Yeah. And it's funny, I think I've said
this before, maybe on the podcast, but if I haven't, I know I've said it elsewhere. I always
think the worst thing you can do is do an undergrad what you're necessarily going to
do in graduate school. So if you're going to go to medical school, I've never really understood
the logic of studying premed. I mean, I understand the logic, but I think if you can stomach it,
it's better to do something completely different. And then, and similarly, when you're doing your
PhD, I mean, sometimes you don't have a choice. If you want to do your PhD in aerospace engineering,
you have to do something that approximates engineering as an undergrad. But yeah,
your story is pretty interesting in that regard. And I suspect you're in some ways better off for
having done something totally different. If nothing else, it gave you, I suspect kind of a
fresh enthusiasm for what you were studying in graduate school. Yeah, I think for sure. And I
also think to some degree, I actually bring my history mind with me. So I think one of the things
that we often neglect in science is we get so caught up in the latest research that we forget
to study the foundations of where things came from. And so my instinct is always to say, well,
where did this idea come from? What was the origin of this? And that inevitably leads to finding a
fresh way to look at something because you realize that the path that led you there, that there were
details that got left behind because no one knew what to do with those details at that time. But
then 70 years later, oh, now that little detail that we forgot actually makes sense now. And you
can start to just get a fresher perspective than you would have if you only look at what's been
done over the last 10 or 20 years. When I was thinking about us sitting down together,
I was having a hard time figuring out where I wanted to start because I also I realized we run
the risk of once we start on a topic, it's possible we will never get out of said topic.
But there really are several distinct things I want to get into with you. So I actually did
something I don't often do, which is I made a bunch of notes and these notes are going to
kind of keep me honest because they're going to at least remind me of major themes. I've used
different fonts and highlighted things I do. I've really nerded out on this.
Why don't we start with something that you and I have spoken about probably six, seven years ago,
which is Colleen. And I think the context in which it came up was when a paper came out of Cleveland
Clinic, I believe it was Stan Hazen's paper that looked at TMAO and it got a ton of attention. And
the thesis was this TMAO thing is the arch enemy of your arteries and you're going to get atherosclerosis.
And diets that are high in Colleen are predisposing to this. And I remember you, me,
Stefangayne, Chris Kresser, we were talking a lot about this because certainly at the time
something didn't make sense to me. So we first encountered each other, right? Yeah, I don't know
if it was the first time, but it was certainly early on. Yeah, the first real email discussion.
That's right. Yeah, we had this huge email thread and I couldn't wrap my mind around
how could this be true if the epidemiology, which I'm not a fan of epidemiology, but in the
contrapositive, it can be quite helpful, which is every epidemiologic assessment of people who
consume high amounts of fish would suggest the exact opposite. And yet this paper would suggest
that there's nothing you could do worse than eating fish outside of Colleen laced sports drinks. So
let's go back in time to that whole thing. So let's start with what is Colleen? Colleen,
you could look at it from a health perspective or a chemical perspective. Yeah, let's start
chemically. Let's just say, yeah. So Colleen is a methyl donor. Colleen is an essential part of
acetylcholine, which is a neurotransmitter. And Colleen is an essential part of phosphatidylcholine,
which is a phospholipid that is in our cell membranes. And I'm just going to, because I know
just half of our listeners will know exactly what you just said and half of them won't. But because
we're going to come back to these terms so often, what's methyl? What is a methyl group? So I think
the easiest and simplest way to think of a methyl group is to come back and look at the fact that
we are biological organisms. All biological organisms are made of hydrocarbons. And if you
look at any molecule in our body, it's mostly a string of carbons. And if you want to synthesize
one of those molecules or you want to change one of those molecules, you're going to have to put
together carbons or take them apart. And you can either put together carbons in two carbon units
called acetyl groups, or you can put together carbons in one carbon units. And that one carbon
unit is a methyl group. And if you just think about it very simply, if you had a molecule with
an odd number of carbons, you'd have to put a methyl group in there sometime because two plus
two plus two plus two never makes an odd number. Or you might have a molecule that has something
else in it like a nitrogen and it's got three carbons attached to it. Well, the only way you
can do that is methylate that nitrogen three times. Right. So we use the term methylation
as a verb to say, to put on a methyl group, right? And we'll talk about that so much. And in fact,
the methylation is also called the one carbon metabolism. So a methyl group and a one carbon
is identical. Okay. So we've got this idea of choline plays an important role in regulating
how that whole methylation thing works. Choline is relatively abundant in certain things that we eat,
right? Yeah. If you look at the diet, you see enormous amounts of choline and liver and egg yolks.
And then you see moderate amounts of choline and many other foods. Most of those foods that are
pretty good sources of choline, but not awesome sources of choline are meats, nuts, and low
carbohydrate, low calorie vegetables, especially cruciferous vegetables. And in fact, we did not
know for the longest time that choline was an essential nutrient in humans. And still,
they started feeding people on total parenteral nutrition and they weren't putting choline in.
I'll explain to folks what that is. So total parenteral nutrition or TPN is something that
is completely given intravenously, but into large central veins. And it's for people who
have such severe pathology in their gut that nothing that you trickle into their gut could
ever give them nutrition. And so you're feeding them through these large veins. And I guess where
you're going to go with this is when you're feeding someone with total parenteral nutrition,
you have 100% control over what they're consuming. And I know where the story is going. It's so
interesting. It can really expose deficiencies that we take for granted. The same thing is true
of omega-3 fatty acids or a number of nutrients that we just assumed no one needed until we fed
them on TPN without that thing. And then all of a sudden something really, really bad happened.
So what happened with the choline deficient TPN folks?
Those folks developed fatty liver.
Which is very counterintuitive, right? In the sense that they probably weren't being
mainlined a lot of fat, right?
Right. But it turns out that because choline is an essential part of the phospholipid phosphatidylcholine,
and because that phospholipid is not just in our cell membranes, but it's also in the membranes of
the lipoproteins that carry fat out of the liver, then if you don't have enough choline,
you can't make the VLDL particle to get triglycerides out of the liver. And we think a lot about
we want triglycerides out of the blood, but we want triglycerides out of the liver too.
First and foremost.
Right.
Yeah.
So if choline is not there, you get fatty liver. That's not surprising in hindsight if you just
look at the animal research, because you go back almost a century and they had basically
done the same thing to animals. So when they started purifying animal diets,
it was almost the same story. They didn't realize these things were necessary.
A bunch of problems happened. They realized the nutrients that were necessary.
And going back to the beginning of the 20th century, what we have is rodents developing
fatty liver on the diets until they were able to either put choline in or reduce the sugar content.
But in those animal experiments, what ultimately was shown was that it doesn't really matter what
the cause of the fatty liver is, as long as you have enough choline in the diet or you have some
precursor to make choline, whether it's sugar, alcohol, fat, as long as you have enough choline
in the diet, you can clear those triglycerides out of the liver.
So that's interesting. And it's something I actually wanted to explore with you because
you know, I'm in the midst of writing this book, which I'm so sick of talking about the
fact that I'm in the middle of writing this book. I can't wait to just be done with the thing.
But one of the chapters is on kind of this spectrum of naphyl D,
NASH, insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes. So in doing that, you know, I went back and had to
look a lot more at the history of who was the first person to describe it. What was that index
patient who first had naphyl D? And it's this sort of funny story of this character who was drinking
something to the tune of like 20 bottles of Coca-Cola a day. You know, he's just mainlining coke.
This is back in the 50s. So you alluded to this a second ago, which is, you know, sucrose plays an
important role in this. Ethanol plays an important role in this. So the question is, if I understood
you correctly, is it safe to say that you take a person, let's just make it clinical, take a person
who has non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. And we'll talk a little bit more about that in a second.
But with enough choline, you don't have to necessarily restrict any of the substrates
that are predisposing to more fat accumulating in the liver than exiting the liver.
That's what I would believe based on all of the animal experiments that were done.
It baffles me that we don't have human studies addressing exactly that. I mean,
we have human studies that if you put people on a, if you take what the average person is eating
right now, and then you put them in a controlled lab environment and you take the choline out of
their diet, nine out of 10 of them will develop fatty liver disease. And by the way, does it
progress from fatty liver to the NASH variant where you actually start to see the inflammation,
or is that not necessarily a place that they progress to? Is it just the accumulation of fat?
In those days, you're looking at short term development of statosis and which is just the
simple fat accumulation. Based on how I understand the physiology of fatty liver disease,
what you would expect is that putting a bunch of fat in the liver is kind of like building the
kindling for a fire. So you build the fire and you don't light it. Then that person at some point,
they might not ever light that fire. But all it takes after all that kindling, what is put into
place is some hit of inflammation or oxidative stress that suddenly lights that up on fire.
And in the literature, that's called the two hit hypothesis of fatty liver. So what you presume is
not that statosis necessarily leads to statohepatitis, but that you can't develop statohepatitis
without statosis, right? So it just puts you now into this new category where there's a fairly
high probability that that will happen. But the point I want to make with these acute studies is
we know that the average person walking around that out there who doesn't have fatty liver,
they don't have fatty liver because of the choline in their diet, not because they're consuming
a paucity of the things that are uniquely fattening to the liver. The two most obvious being
fructose, ethanol, or highly abundant polyunsaturated fatty acids, things like that.
Well, it's both. But what I'm saying is in these studies that were done, I believe this was Steven
Ziesl's group, who's one of the main choline guys. They just took people randomly eating
whatever they were eating and they didn't have any fat in their liver. And then they put them on
this experimental diet where they took the choline out of what they were already eating. So they
probably were eating some sugar. They were probably drinking some alcohol. I don't know
exactly how much. But the point is if you're out there walking around without fatty liver,
and you can see this in the TPN too, like those people at some point in their history didn't have
fatty liver. They went on the TPN, they got fatty liver, but you don't have to put them on TPN. You
can just put them on a low choline diet. And if you look at all the animal experiments, what they
show is you can cause fatty liver with sucrose, you can cause fatty liver with alcohol, you can
cause fatty liver with fat. And no matter how you cause it, you just put in choline or you put in
things that can be precursors to choline and any of them at a high enough ratio with the other
things that are producing the fat in the liver, we'll get rid of the fatty liver.
So if we know in humans that you get fatty liver when you take the choline down,
and we know in animals that you get rid of fatty liver, if you put the choline up,
then I would think that if you took the humans with the fatty liver and you put the choline up,
you'd get rid of it. But for some reason, that hasn't been tested the way you'd think it would be.
Do you have a sense of how much choline is required in that situation? So if you took a patient who
unequivocally had fatty liver disease by say MRI, so we take the gold standard and we could
actually measure, you know, 20% of their liver was now made up of fat. And they were on, let's
say they were not on an especially restrictive diet. So they weren't someone who was avoiding
eggs or anything like that. But presumably, they weren't having enough. How much choline
would you guess you'd have to put in the diet? And would you be able to achieve that through
eating more foods rich in choline? Or would you actually need to supplement it?
I can only give you a wild guess. And my wild guess would be about 1200 milligrams of choline.
And you could get that by eating food, but it would be very difficult.
So how many milligrams of choline in an egg?
130.
You don't know how many eggs I eat.
How many eggs do you eat?
No. Well, I have chickens.
I had four this morning.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I could easily eat six eggs a day.
You can do it, but it's hard and you'd have to design the diet to do that, right?
I'm basing that on a couple things. One is there are human studies where it has been shown that
some people require 1200 milligrams of choline a day. And those studies are not looking at liver
fat. They're looking at other markers. But people who have a genetic predisposition to need what we
know is the highest choline requirement that a human can have is about 1200 milligrams.
The other way I base that is that it's been shown with labeling studies that in, if you take a
random sample of people with NASH, which is the stahedohepatitis, they have inflammation too.
If you take those people and you look at their triglyceride export, it's reduced by 75%. So if
it's 25% of normal, then I look at that and I say, well, you probably want to quadruple the ability
to export triglycerides from the liver. And it's my guess that although the adequate intake,
which is the replacement for an RDA when you don't have enough evidence for choline is higher,
I think the average choline intake is probably somewhere around 300 milligrams.
What's the RDA for choline?
It depends on men and women. I might be wrong on this, but I think it's around 500,
but it's a little bit higher for men. It's a little bit lower for women. I don't remember
the exact numbers. The funny thing with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease is it's hard to
know the rate at which it is increasing because like many things, it was so likely underdiagnosed.
In the book, I'm actually writing about sort of the first patient I saw that likely had it.
And it was during a case when I was a resident and we were operating on this guy and prior to
surgery, I had done all the usual things and tried to figure out how much alcohol he drank,
which you do with every patient because you need to understand what their requirement for
benzodiazepines is going to be and if they're going to have withdrawal in the perioperative period.
And this patient claimed he didn't drink any alcohol and I believed him. And then we got in
there and operated and his liver looked like a fat and duck liver. And I remember thinking,
I can't believe this guy lied to me. But after the fact that I went back to him and I said,
look, I'm not here to judge you. You got to tell me how much you drink. And he's like,
doc, I don't drink anything. And I sort of forgot about the whole thing until 10 years
later when I realized, oh my God, that was naffoldy. What year was that? 2001.
So in 1980, the Mayo Clinic published a paper in which they coined the term
Nash, which came before naffoldy. And they coined it because of that. If you read their paper,
their rationale is we have doctors that are seeing fatty liver. They assume that fatty
liver happens because of alcohol. The patients are telling them they don't drink alcohol and
they're saying, you're lying to me. And the best thing that can come from that is an argument.
And there could be worse. Part of it was that it facilitated the growth of a whole body of research.
But the other part of it was it allowed doctors to have a way of thinking and talking about the
person who says that they don't drink alcohol and yet they have fatty liver.
Right. They have a liver that for all intents and purposes looks grossly just like that of
someone who is about to kill themselves through a lot of alcohol. Now, Ron Bucetil, who certainly
one of the preeminent liver transplant surgeons in the world said, and this is probably about
four years ago, in the year 2000, something like 1% of liver transplants were being done for
naffoldy predispose. Nobody needs a liver transplant if they have naffoldy. But if you
get naffoldy, Nash and cirrhosis, you do need a transplant. And that amounted to 1%.
And in I think about 2013, 2014, he predicted that naffoldy, Nash, cirrhosis was going to be the
leading cause of liver transplant by the year 2030 in the United States as a result of two things.
One, the sort of undeniable increase we were seeing in naffoldy and of course, the success of treatment
for both hep B and hep C. So it's both those things coming down and the other one going up.
So my question to you, which I apologize for how long winded it is,
even if we are over diagnosing it today or seeing it more than it was there before,
it seems hard to deny that naffoldy is more prevalent now than 20 or 30 years ago.
Would you agree with that? Yeah, I think even though you can't track the prevalence over time,
you can assume that the prevalence has increased over time matched to obesity because that's the
overwhelmingly predisposing risk factor. So do you believe that it is more driven by
a fat accumulation in the liver problem or choline being less prevalent in our diets and
therefore more of a clearance problem? It's hard to make an either or question about it because
it comes down to fat in versus fat out and choline is such an overwhelming factor in the fat out part
of the equation. But I think the reason that it's increasing over time, if you had the data,
I really doubt that you could show that there's been a linear decrease in choline intake over
those years. And I think you probably could show that there was a fairly linear increase
in naffoldy over those years that tracked with obesity. And I think you can look at it like
what's the percentage of people with obesity who have fatty liver or what's the percentage of
people with fatty liver who have obesity. And I might have these numbers backwards, but I think
it's 67% of people who have obesity have fatty liver and 76% of people who have fatty liver have
obesity, something like that. And I think the overwhelming reason for that, and I don't think
it's the only reason, but I think the overwhelming reason for that is that the more obese you are,
the more likely you are to have visceral adiposity and the visceral fat pad directly
empties into the portal vein. And so is a huge factor in fat in compared to the subcutaneous
fat pad. And I think that that's probably a huge factor and why, again, not the only factor, but I
think that's probably a huge factor and why the metabolic health of someone who has relatively
more visceral fat is so much worse than the person who has relatively more subcutaneous fat is
because you're basically pounding the liver fat all the time. You don't even have to eat anything.
You're always engaging in the policies. You're always freeing some free fatty acids. And if
you have this gigantic tube going right into the liver, just feeding fatty acids in all the time,
then I think that's the major thing. Now, one of the challenges of studying NAFLD is,
and I can say this with some experience because I used to be involved in an organization that was
funding research in this, is removing the biggest confounder of the reduction of NAFLD, which is
weight loss. So the biggest challenge is, so let's say your hypothesis, and I think fructose is
overwhelmingly on a molecule for molecule basis, probably one of the greatest drivers of NAFLD,
when you take fructose out of the diet, very often a person is going to lose weight,
either through some reduction, you know, spontaneous reduction in intake or some other thing.
So it's hard to then say, well, with fructose elimination, you're ridding yourself of NAFLD,
you're dramatically reducing it. And how much of that was due to the fructose reduction? And how
much of that was due to the weight loss? Are you aware of any data that have done a great job at
trying to disentangle those two? And it doesn't necessarily have to be fructose, but it could be
an input issue. So ethanol, PUFA, fructose, an output issue, choline, or the way you describe
it is sort of this in between visceral thing, which is visceral fat tends to decrease when
adiposity decreases. So it's almost like there's a third variable. And it is challenging in humans
to figure out how to isolate each of those. I don't think you can do it in humans. Well,
I think you could do it in humans. I don't think anyone will do it in humans. And I don't think
that there's any data out there that do do it in humans. And I don't think anyone will ever bother
to try to figure that out. Because what that would require would be putting people in a metabolic
ward and feeding them precisely controlled diets. And I think this is a huge point that you're
making that applies so much broader than this discussion. Because whenever people make one
change in their diet, and that changes to the foods in their diet, they're actually changing
like 30 or 40 things in their diet. And they have a hype, their driving idea of what they're doing
is only one tiny part of what they're doing. And so if you look at, say, taking the fructose out
of the diet, well, you know, what's the fructose in most cases, it's a bunch of junk food, what did
they eat instead? Well, either they ate nothing instead, or they ate something different than
that, which was probably better. So the average person who takes fructose out or who takes carbs
out, even if you just go on a low carb diet, well, your ideas that you reduced your carbs,
but actually, you probably increased your protein, you probably increased your choline,
you probably increased your riboflavin, you probably increased a button, you probably increased
your zinc, you probably increased a bunch of different things. And I think that the only way
to make sense out of the human data is to take all of the animal data that does have precise
controls on it and say, you know, not assume that the animal data always matches the human data.
But if you can take all the animal data and you can say, wow, everything that is in the human data
makes perfect sense. According to what the theory we get out of the animal data is, then that's what
you do. So when we're talking about fructose, when I was in graduate school, I fed rats a 60%
fructose diet. And I was hoping that they would get fatty liver. And I was hoping that I would
actually what I was really- Wait, 60% fructose or sucrose?
Fructose. How can they even digest that? I mean, how do they not just get such severe dumping
syndrome with so much fructose? They might have had a little bit less
digestion because they were a little bit leaner. I was going to say, I mean-
But that's not the point. The point is there are studies out there showing a 60%
fructose diet causes fatty liver. And did you see it in yours?
No. Because you had lots of choline, do you assume? Well, I wasn't trying to have lots of
choline, but in my department, we never fed rats, wear mice on casein diets, which is what almost
every rodent study out there is. Casein being the dominant protein that you would see.
Yeah. But every rodent diet is based on casein almost. I didn't even know why we did this. It
was just tradition in our lab and in our whole department that we never used casein. And later,
I talked to my department head about it and he said, well, I've seen studies showing that
casein is inflammatory in rats and it causes copper deficiency, so we just prefer to avoid it.
So then I look into the amino acid composition of my diet versus the casein diets that everyone
else is using. And it's something like six times more methionine, which is a choline precursor
that has been shown in animals to obliterate fatty liver, something like six times more
methionine in my diet. So all of a sudden, my negative finding makes perfect sense with
everything else that I'm looking at. And part of the reason that I have a unique perspective on
this goes back to what we were talking about at the beginning about getting a historical perspective.
I was writing a review on fatty liver with my doctoral advisor and I was obsessive about
needing to know the origins of the methionine choline deficient mouse model. So I went all the
way back to the turn of the century. And what they found originally was you could produce fatty
liver in rodents if you fed them an 80% sucrose diet. If the nutrients came from whole foods that
they were using before, like yeast and cod liver oil and things like that. Then when they started
producing chemically defined diets, all of a sudden 50% sucrose was causing fatty liver.
And so then they said, oh, we need to reduce the sucrose. So they reduced it further.
But then people who took those same high sucrose diets at that time showed that you could add
choline, you could add methionine, which is a choline precursor, you could just up the protein.
If you just up the protein, which has methionine, which is a choline precursor, right? If you provide
any of those precursors, it just gets rid of the fatty liver. So I take those things and I look at
the human data and I say, well, that person reduced the fructose in their diet. I believe that's a
contributor because fructose compared to starch is more lipogenic. And in fact, one of the animal
models that you use for fatty liver is called the methionine choline deficient mouse model. Well,
it's not just deficient in methionine choline. Yeah, they have to give them sucrose. It's also
got a bunch of sugar in it and it's got a bunch of corn oil in it. And they have shown that you can
reduce the fatty liver if you replace the sugar with starch. So when I look at the human data,
I'm going to say I do believe that reducing the fructose is going to reduce the amount of fat that
the liver is producing from sugar. But I also believe that if you did that and you replaced it
with protein, then that was part of the results. Or if you replaced it with vegetables or you
replaced it with egg yolks, those were part of the results. Right. And to your point, it's very
difficult. So when you look at the study that just came out in JAMA two weeks ago, which actually
was the one that way at the beginning I was involved in the funding of, but I had no
involvement in the study whatsoever. I had to read about it like everybody else when it came
out of JAMA, but this is the one that Miriam Voss Emery was the first author on. This is the study
that took 40 Hispanic boys with biopsy proven NASH and for eight weeks put them on a virtually zero
fructose diet with no instruction to reduce carbohydrate. In fact, the idea was replace
fructose with glucose to your point, right? Glucose is not going to produce fatty liver in almost any
quantity. They saw a 50% reduction on MRI in liver fat. But if you want to be technically
rigorous, they lost three pounds on average. Now, I don't know that the three pounds matters that
much, but I think your broader point is they almost assuredly cleaned up the quality of their
diet in ways that's difficult to measure, even just looking at the macros, because I think it's
easy to report the macros in a study like that. Well, carbohydrate content was unchanged. Protein
went down a little, fat went up a little or vice versa, but at the micronutrient level or at the
amino acid level, I just don't think that stuff's being tracked. It would be interesting. Again, I
don't know, and it might even be worth you contacting Miriam Voss who I've met twice and she seems
very collaborative and interesting, and it might be worth understanding what other data they would
have with respect to the nutrient, because I'd be curious to dig further into this point.
Yeah, and if they have food data, if they were collecting, what are they eating for foods?
Well, the food was provided. Oh, I'm sure they could go back. If they have what the foods were,
I'm sure they could go back and- Yeah, this was a very well-controlled study in that the food
was provided not just to the children, but to their entire families. The idea was make it so
easy for the child to be compliant for the eight weeks that they were on this diet, that the entire
family is going to get fed the same food. Yeah, so they have to know what they were providing in
order to estimate the macros, so they must be able to estimate the micros. That would be interesting.
Yeah, I'd like to see that because I remember when I read it, I was really hoping that the
results would come out independent, like that there would be no change in weight, that the kids could
maintain their body weight, and then you could ask the question, could this nutritional intervention
alternafoldy independent of adiposity? Okay, so now let's go back to where we started, right?
So you've made this great case for choline and its importance, and I've always found the TPN stuff
to be one of the most compelling reasons because you just don't often get in life a chance to
create a truly deficient model in humans. So now let's talk about this thing called TMAO. What is
it and how did it rear its head into this discussion? And all of a sudden, choline became
public enemy number one. Before these studies came out from the Cleveland Clinic, TMAO was mostly
known in being found naturally in fish and in being produced in the gut in very rare cases where
there were people with genetic disorders. And I don't even remember off the top of my head what
those genetic disorders were, but they were feeding them absolutely massive amounts of choline.
And so it was known before that that in those cases of enormous choline loading,
some of that choline would be converted to trimethylamine by gut bacteria, and that that
trimethylamine. And actually, the interest was largely in the trimethylamine because the
trimethylamine is the more smelly compound. So this would produce fish odor syndrome,
these people are smelling like fish. So that was what was known about it at that point.
But then in 2011, I think was the first paper, the Cleveland Clinic came out with
experiments, I think in first in mouse, but also in humans showing different things. So in mice
that were genetically engineered to have defects in their lipoprotein metabolism,
they showed that TMAO was directly atherogenic. And in humans, they showed that there were two
different papers, the first one looked at choline and the second one looked at meat. But what they
were showing was that TMAO levels in humans correlate with heart disease risk. And when humans
eat either choline or carnitine, they will metabolize both of those to trimethylamine
in the gut and the liver will convert it to TMAO. And so the argument is the TMAO in those humans
will cause heart disease the way that it causes heart disease in the genetically engineered mice.
And if I recall, there were basically three ways that they were suggesting you could get
too much of it. One was too much fish. If you eat fish, you're getting the TMAO directly.
I don't think they mentioned fish.
Maybe I'm confusing it with a different paper, but I thought one argument was too much fish is too
much TMAO, too much carnitine, which is found in sports drinks is going to be converted and too
much choline. So basically any of those three that were too many were problematic. Now maybe
this was stretched across a couple of different papers.
So my recollection is that I brought the fish up because my argument was it's really easy to
just look at this stuff and repeat what we already believed about eggs and red meat being
bad for you. And if you isolate it to that, it kind of makes a clean story, but it makes a really
bad story if you bring fish into the equation because fish have so much TMAO that you're
probably literally getting hundreds of times more TMAO exposure when you eat fish than when you eat
those foods. So my point was always, how can you not bring fish into the discussion?
And yeah, so now it's coming back to me. You wrote a piece on this that I think we'll be
sure to link to. I think the reason I had seen this fish issue separately was I was actually
at an advisory meeting for a company that had asked me and a dozen other people a question,
which was, should we be using TMAO as a new biomarker for cardiovascular disease? And so
it was part of this two-day meeting where we're sort of in this room looking at all of the data
that somehow this someone else, and I don't remember who it was, came up with the idea of,
well, wait a minute. I mean, we got to take a step back here. I mean, if fish has more TMAO than you
could ever get from all of the red meat and eggs in the world, it converting to TMAO, it just seems
to fail on first principles. Yeah. And there were later papers that happened after those first two,
where there was some observational data showing that people who eat more fish have more TMAO in
their blood. I still get asked about this, I don't know, twice a year a patient will bring in
a copy of that paper. I think it was in Nature or Nature Communications or something like that and
say, oh my God, Peter, like, what do you think about this TMAO thing? And it's just always one
of those things where I kind of eye roll and I just sort of send them a link to what you wrote
or what Chris Cresser and say, go and read this and then come back to me and let's discuss why I
am not particularly impressed by this thesis. On a scale of one to 10, I wouldn't say that
my opinion that TMAO has negative properties in humans is zero. I think it's maybe one or two or
something like that. And I'm willing to see what they come up with there. But on a scale of one to
10, my view of the overall story that eating eggs and meat are bad for you because they alter the
microbiome in a way that makes you take the choline and the carnitine in those foods and convert it
into TMAO and make you as a red meat and egg eater uniquely vulnerable to heart disease.
I'm very close to zero on the probability of that story being true. I'm totally open to seeing new
studies on the ability of TMAO and plasma to be a biomarker and the potential for maybe eventually
altering the gut microbiome in a way that generates more TMAO. And actually I incorporate
this on a practical level in some cases. So when I'm looking at choline supplements,
I overwhelmingly prefer that someone would get phosphatidylcholine, which is the overwhelming
form of choline that's found in food, for two reasons. One is it's the overwhelming form of
choline found in food. And the second is that it's the form of choline that's least likely to
generate TMAO in the gut, almost exclusively driven because its absorption is better.
Do you dose it milligram for milligram? In other words, if you believe that 1200 milligrams of
choline is necessary. No. And actually that's very confusing on supplements because most
supplements of phosphatidylcholine tell you the amount of phosphatidylcholine in them and they
don't know how much choline is. No, you do. You can estimate that it's about 15%. Just by molar
weight. It's about 50%. Yeah. I mean, it's probably an imperfect number because probably
most of the time the fatty acids are different in each molecule, right? So it's just an average,
but it's close enough, right? But directionally then you would want like
nine or 10 grams to hit your 12. It's only practical if you're taking tablespoons of
less than, but you can get food so you could eat eggs, right? Yeah. So eating eggs and eating
foods is the best way to get choline in my opinion. But if I were to take someone in a particular
situation where for some reason they had one or two dietary restrictions in this way that made
them not be able to get choline and you, but they needed choline for these other reasons and you
had to supplement, I would do it with less than for those reasons. And one of the reasons is that I
don't know whether the increased TMAO that's generated when you take choline by tartrate
is problematic. Bob, the show notes guy, he sent me a paper that was just recently published where
they fed people 500 milligrams of choline by tartrate over the course of two months. And they
did an in vitro assay on their blood and showed that it was more sensitive to clotting. So it's
the level of that evidence isn't super strong, but it's an indication that maybe having that
level of TMAO in your blood is bad. But you cannot get that level of TMAO in your blood
by eating four eggs, which supplies the same amount of choline. How do I know?
Because Steven Ziesl's group did a study looking at plasma TMAO response to eggs. And if you eat
enough eggs, you get a plasma TMAO response, but it's three or four times lower than when you eat
the same amount of choline as choline by tartrate. And it's only anecdotal, but at the time that I
was involved in this discussion around developing an assay for TMAO, it was during that three,
three and a half year window when I was on a really strict ketogenic diet. And I was so, I mean,
relatively speaking, hyper caloric, because I was also really active at the time, I needed about
4,000 calories a day. Now, 4,000 calories a day on a ketogenic diet means you are really
having to limit your protein and carbohydrate. So I was about 2% to 3% carbohydrate and about 8% to
10% protein and the rest was fat. So it was on a, you know, what we would now call a four to one
ketogenic diet. Although I didn't at the time think of it that way. My point is, one of the ways that
I would, I had to make eggs is I couldn't just take 12 eggs and make scrambled eggs. That was too much
protein. So I could only eat, you know, I'd have like maybe four whites, eight yolks, and then I'd
have to fluff it with heavy cream. So the point is I was main lining this stuff. And when the lab
was sort of kicking around the idea of developing the assay, I said I had already done some work
with them where we had done like nine blood draws on nine consecutive days under various conditions
and they already had the serum. I said, well, let's look at the TMAO levels in there. That should be a
pretty good positive control. And interestingly, I had virtually none.
Hmm. Yeah. Well, in that study that I mentioned, looking at the plasma TMAO response to eggs,
there was enormous variability. And some people didn't really get, I think everyone got some
response to six eggs, but there was a lot of variation on the four egg mark. So half the
subjects didn't get any response at all until they ate four eggs. But some of the people got a very
significant response to the four eggs, which is what you'd expect based on what the Cleveland
Clinic Group is arguing, which is that the gut microbiome is a big determinant.
Well, and that was sort of my conclusion, which is, again, it was a very deep look into one
individual, me, and that's irrelevant because any one individual is irrelevant. But the thinking was,
I gotta be honest with you, I still don't know what gut health means. Like the concept is so,
you know, it's so difficult for me to, in amorphous to describe, but my intuition was
something in my gut was really preventing this from becoming problematic. I didn't know what
it was. I didn't know if it could be replicated, but the story seemed a lot deeper than it was
being presented. Yeah. I think one important point is that it's not about how many eggs you eat in a
day. It's about how many eggs you eat at a sitting. So the only reason eggs generate TMAO is because
there's some poorly characterized absorption cap to phosphatidylcholine. And even though it's
better absorbed than the other choline that's sold on the market, there's some cap to how much
choline you can absorb and no one really knows where it is. Where is it absorbed? Which transporter?
Is it an enterocyte transporter off the top of my head? I don't know, but it's gotta, yeah,
it's gotta be in the small intestine. Does it come as a single phospholipid or is it
esterified in some way? I mean, how does it actually come in from food? You mean how it's
absorbed or how you eat it? So if you're eating a food that's high in phosphatidylcholine,
does it actually show up like the analogous free fatty acid or does it show up more as the
analogous triglyceride where you get, say two or three of these bound to a glycerol
bound to other fatty acids? Do these things actually show up as free phosphatidyl molecules?
So I believe that most of the phosphatidylcholine in most of the foods is going to be as phosphatidylcholine
that are in cell membranes. I see, okay, no, you've answered that question. Okay, so that's what I
was wondering if it came in a more whole state or if it ever actually showed up like, so first of all,
does it come in through a chylomicron? I assume so. I haven't looked at the absorption pathway for a
while, so I might not be remembering the details here, but my guess is that you're going to have
partial hydrolysis of some of the fatty acids and then the phosphatidylcholine is mostly going to
wind up making its way into the mixed micelles and it's going to become probably part of the
membrane of a chylomicron would be my guess. Right, but coming in the lumen of the gut,
and I get, probably not even that relevant at this moment, why? I guess I'm just trying to
figure out what the, if the bottleneck is at the enterocyte transporter and that's why you're
limited in how many of these things you can get into the enterocyte, which then on the backside go
into the chylomicron. Right, that makes sense. I mean, back when I was trying to figure this out,
I asked Steven Ziesel about this, who if anyone knows about choline absorption or anything else
about choline, it's him, and he wrote back and was like, I really don't know. I assume that there's
some absorption cap in the small intestine. I have no idea what it is. Interesting. So the
choline story is interesting and I think if you look at it overly simplistically, you could say,
well, it's a good guy and a bad guy, but it seems to be more of a good guy than a bad guy, huh?
Yeah, I think so. I mean, certainly from the perspective of fatty liver, that's clear.
Yeah, now we don't see, I'm assuming, although I've never looked at this, in people who you would
expect to have huge choline deficiencies, which would be someone who's eating a very strict vegan
diet, right? So by definition, they're not eating any liver, they're not eating any eggs. They could
certainly be eating lots of nuts. Nuts and cruciferous vegetables they could be eating.
Now, but let's assume they're on like the college vegan diet, right? Which is like, you know,
they're eating as much crap as possible that has no animal matter in it. Is there data that would
suggest we would see a higher incidence of fatty liver in that population? I have no idea if that
data is out there. My guess is you probably wouldn't because probably those vegans aren't
too fat, but I don't know. And this comes back to your point, which is there's just something
about adiposity if it's accompanied by visceral fat that is really stoking the fire. Yeah, I mean,
if you take out all the fat in parts of the equation, then there's just the choline is not
going to matter that much. It's just that it becomes the bottleneck to getting fat out when
you have a buildup of fat in. So what do you think are the role of different fatty acids in this
problem? And I guess we'll just define it for the listener, right? So we sort of loosely
characterize fatty acids as either saturated, monounsaturated or polyunsaturated. We can further
divide the polyunsaturated into a number of constituents. I always think it's important
that people sort of demystify this stuff and we're so quick to demonize one versus the other. But it's,
as you said at the outset, it's really just a bunch of really fun biochemistry. A saturated
fatty acid is specified by the number of hydrocarbons. The number of carbons it has,
that's the chain. So a C8 versus a C12 would have eight versus 12 carbons. But being saturated just
means there are no double bonds. Every carbon is fully saturated with a hydrogen. And then of course,
you can finish the explanation for what a mono and polyunsaturated is. Right, a monounsaturated fat
has one double bond, a polyunsaturated fat has two or more double bonds. That introduces a couple
things. So one thing is that whenever you introduce a double bond, you create a kink in
the molecule. So saturated fats are really, you can imagine them as it just being straight and
linear and you can pack them together very well. So saturated fats tend to be solid.
Less saturated fats, fats that are higher in monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fat tend to
be more liquid. So olive oil is more liquid than butter because it's mostly monounsaturated fat.
If you take olive oil and you put it in the refrigerator and you take corn oil or sunflower
oil and put it in the refrigerator, eventually the olive oil is going to harden and the sunflower
wouldn't. And that's because the sunflower oil is more polyunsaturated and that has even more
resistance to packing together. The other thing is that in a fatty acid with two or more double
bonds, so polyunsaturated fat, the carbon that's between two of those double bonds is very unstable
and it is uniquely vulnerable to being damaged. And we call that damage lipid peroxidation.
So that fatty acid is not harmful in and of itself. And in fact, there are polyunsaturated fatty
acids that are absolutely essential for us. You alluded to these earlier, we'll come back to them,
which is the omega three. Right? Well, I know omega six, there are omega three and omega six,
both polyunsaturated, they're both essential to human physiology. But it's also the case that the
more of these that you have in your cell membranes, the more of a liability it becomes
because if you have oxidative stress, if you have inflammation, then all of a sudden those
fats are more vulnerable to damage. And it's very, very tricky when you're talking about fatty liver,
because there was a human study that was about two weeks long that was published when I was in
graduate school. So maybe 2010 or 2009, this was, they showed that over the course of a couple
weeks, polyunsaturated fats compared to saturated fats lead to less liver fat. And it was very,
they used MRS. So it was, you know, highly reliable data that they had. And if you just take that at
face value, you say, well, there's one study that looked at it in humans, there's a couple
observational studies overall, PUFAs are what you want to eat for fatty liver. There's a problem
with that, which is that if you have fatty liver and it's mostly PUFAs, you are way more vulnerable
to progressing from staetosis to staetohepititis because you have more oxidative targets. Right.
Yeah. So if you look at the animal data, it depends on the model. Generally, you get more staetosis
with longer chain length and more saturation, and you get less staetosis, the shorter chain length
or with less saturation. But if you have the staetosis, you have a dramatic increase
in the risk of progressing to staetohepititis. However, in the alcoholic model, there are
studies showing that you get less staetosis with saturated fats and with polyunsaturated fats.
I think the reason for this is that oxidative stress does not just cause you to go from
naphyl-D to NASH. It also can cause staetosis because you get oxidative destruction of the
ABOB particle. And so it's not just choline that allows you to export triglycerides from the liver.
You also need sufficient antioxidant protection in the liver because if you damage that particle
before it ever exports to triglycerides, then you prevent it from doing so. I think the way you
reconcile these different animal models is you say, well, in the alcoholic model, there's so much
oxidative stress already that's provided by the alcohol because the alcohol isn't just a way to
get fat in the liver. The alcohol's metabolism generates oxidative stress. So you're taking
a liver that doesn't yet have fat accumulation, you're putting a bunch of fat into it, and you're
adding on top of that an oxidative flame. So you actually wind up causing staetosis by causing
oxidative damage to the ABOB particle so that they can't leave the liver in that model.
So PUFA's, I think, are very complicated to think about because in the short term,
in someone who doesn't have a lot of stuff going on in their liver, they're probably going to be
better if you look at a two-week study. And we have the data in humans showing that. But I think
in the long term, if you're talking about the progression from staetosis to NASH, they're a
clear disadvantage. And I think if you're not talking about the healthy person who's got nothing
wrong with them, then they're, who knows? It's like 50-50. But in this two-week study you're
talking about, presumably the subjects were fed disproportionately high amounts of PUFA versus SFA.
Yeah. Do you recall the magnitudes that they had to be fed to produce this phenotype?
I don't recall the magnitudes, but they weren't ridiculously out of proportion. They weren't
super physiologic. No, no, no. They were basically the typical amount of fat that someone would eat,
but they controlled the fat intake. So maybe people would prefer to mix the types of fats that are
in their diet. But in that case, it was atypical. But they weren't feeding them 80 or 90% fat diets.
You know, it's interesting. You mentioned the APO-B issue. APO-B is used, obviously, in two ways in
the liver. The first way we've talked about, which is VLDL export, which is our main way to
get triglycerides out. But also we make de novo LDL in the liver. And so in those patients, do we
see a reduction in LDL as well? I don't remember. That's interesting. I feel like I want to start
paying a little closer attention to this. I certainly haven't- I can't even remember if
they measured that. I just haven't clinically seen that, because I do see NAFLD all the time
in the practice. Usually you suspect it with an elevated ALT disproportionate to AST, and then
an ultrasound will confirm the diagnosis. Very rarely do you need an MRI and certainly never a
biopsy. But I haven't seen the association with an alteration in VLDL, which we can estimate. And
obviously we can measure triglycerides in LDL. It's also confounded, by the way, by different
ethnicities. So when you look at African American patients, even with type 2 diabetes,
will still have very low VLDL and triglycerides. A Hispanic patient with diabetes will generally
have a high triglyceride and a high VLDL. And actually they're far more susceptible to NAFLD
than African American. And Caucasian is in the middle. Are you familiar with any of the data on
some of those differences as it pertains to the lipidology of these folks?
I just haven't paid attention to it. No, I'm not. I'm not. And can we
rewind a minute? What have you observed with VLDL? You said you haven't observed the association
between blood levels of VLDL and- And NAFLD. Yeah.
What would you expect to see that you didn't? I would have expected, based on what we're saying,
to see a reduction in VLDL. The more NAFLD they have, the less VLDL based on this idea.
Well, I think the problem with that is that- I mean, I have an explanation for why that might
not exist. And here's the explanation. In an ideal world, that might make sense. But there's
another thing that's going on. If you have NAFLD, you are very likely insulin resistant.
If you are insulin resistant, you are upregulating APOC3. If you are upregulating APOC3, your VLDL
are going to stick around a hell of a lot longer than if you do not. And that's why we see these
pathologic remnant VLDL particles that become atherogenic. So when you or I, presuming we're
both insulin sensitive, our VLDL really don't pose much of an atherogenic risk because they stick
around for such a short period of time. So we don't have many of them. They don't stick around long.
Our APOC3 is quite downregulated. But if APOC3 is upregulated and it's hard to measure this,
although Sam Tamekis is working on an assay to do so, you have VLDL now start to act like LDL.
They stick around long enough. They have a high enough residence time in the plasma that they
become atherogenic. And so I do wonder if maybe why I don't- not that this is scientific, but the
reason even my Gestalt is not to see that is maybe the less VLDL that's being exported in that
patient because of the reasons you've described is offset by a longer residence time due to more
APOC3. Right. And wouldn't you also expect that from lower rate of uptake of triglycerides from
peripheral tissues? Yeah, that's a great point. You have a lower peripheral disposal of triglycerides.
So the whole thing could be confe- In other words, it's a great point you raise actually. We should
take a macro step back. This is a problem of flux and people struggle to understand flux because
you can't understand flux with a snapshot. No. You have to have the goddamn video, right? I mean,
that's the analogy. You can't- You take a picture of something, you don't know the flux. What's in,
what's out, where it's being disposed of. I love this point. And one of the analogies that I like
to use is although you can't use the picture, how much information you have in a snapshot can have
a huge effect on your ability to know what's going on. Now, imagine that you have a picture of a car
accident. Well, if you zoom in to the tire, you might not- And you look at that, you don't know
what happened. You might not have any idea what happened. The more you zoom out and the more
different angles that you have, at some point, you can start to build a story of what probably
happened based on that snapshot. But if you're looking at one element in the snapshot, you can
never even so much as build a story about what probably happened. And I think that, yeah, the
idea that mistaking a concentration for flux is one of the overwhelming interpretive problems in
science and in popular science in both. Yeah, one of my biggest pet peeves. So every quarter,
when I do one of these seven day fasts, I get a lot of blood work done on myself throughout the
process. And I get a real kick out of it because by the time you're five, six, seven days into water
only, you start to look like there are things that if looked at in isolation look horrible.
For example, your free fatty acids get into the diabetic range. So if you show that to somebody,
they think, oh my God, you're you're diabetic. And you're like, really? My insulin is unmeasurable.
My glucose is 60 milligrams per deciliter. Yes, my FFA is two millimolar, but my BHB is, you know,
seven or five millimolar. Isn't it possible that what you're seeing is an incredible turnover of
lipolysis? And so, yeah, there's a lot of free fatty acid there, but it's in motion. It's in
transit versus what I think is probably happening in the person with high FFA who's got diabetes,
which is a much more stagnant form of elevated FFA. And so that's a muscle that's full of fat
that's going nowhere versus the fasted person where that fat is being turned over very quickly.
And would you rather drink water out of a stream or out of a sitting pool with mosquitoes all over
it? Exactly. So no, it's a good point. And I like your point, which is, look, the picture can be
helpful, but it has to be taken from a distance, right? So if you just look at one tread of the
tire in a photo, you're probably going to have no clue what caused the accident. If you look at a
huge picture, you could at least see where the skid marks are of both vehicles. Ultimately, there's
no substitute for having a video of the accident. And those turn out to be the hardest things to do
biochemically is to generate tests that can actually show you the movement. Well, biochemically,
what you do know, though, is that we've mapped out elsewhere biochemical pathways. If you know
all the possible sequences and you can measure all the metabolites, you can often reconstruct
what a video would have shown with fairly good precision. I think it's just that we're only on
the horizon of being able to do things like that. But even still, if you measure 20 things in
someone's blood, you can have a much better idea of what's going on, what probably happened,
than if you measure one thing in that blood. I should say 20 things in the pathway, right?
Yeah. And what you can get by measuring serially, even a few serial measurements can be quite
helpful. I mean, even just looking at something as, you know, simple, I hate to say that, but as
simple as an oral glucose tolerance test, you look at somebody's fasting glucose and fasting insulin,
you have some idea of what's going on, especially in extremes, right? So a person who's fasting
glucose is 70 milligrams per deciliter and their fasting insulin is one, the probability that
they're going to have post-prandial hyperinsulinemia is low, but it's not zero. Similarly, you look at
somebody who's fasting glucose is 130 and their fasting insulin is 30, the likelihood that there's
not a train wreck there is also virtually nil. But if you're willing to sample 30, 60, 90, and 120
minutes after a glucose challenge, you can develop a very interesting kinetic pathway using just two
or three measurements. You know, I often get asked, where will machine learning wreak the most havoc
in medicine? And my intuition is most likely radiology is the most obvious place for machine
learning to, I mean, wreak havoc is the wrong word, but displace human, you know, ability. I've often
thought the ICU would be the second most valuable place just based on the reams of data that are
coming out. But I've never thought of this particular question, right, which is something as
seemingly straightforward as looking at a bunch of biochemical metabolites and precursors and
intermediaries. There may be a very interesting opportunity here from machine learning to also
start to differentiate, but you know, this question of flux. I'm always asking myself that question
when I look at a blood test, which is this is a static test. Can I infer the movement, the
velocity or the derivative, the time derivative of this molecule or that molecule? So maybe that is
an interesting place for machine learning to start to play a role, because I do suspect it will do a
better job than me. Yeah. And what we do have taking it back to the fatty liver, what we do have
is not you'll never see this in your day to day clinical life. But what we do have is studies
where we look at labeled tracers. And that's what shows that in a random sample of Nash people,
you have a 75% decrease in able B secretion. It doesn't matter what the ape will be in the blood
test. You'd like to know why it's higher, but you know that it's not because it's coming out of
the liver at a higher rate. It's a great point, right? It can be longer residence time at the
VLDL, the LDL, the, yeah, that's such a great point. Okay. So speaking of tracers, which just
prompted me to think of another thing I wanted to talk with you about, let's talk about the most
sought after, discussed, asked about supplement on the market today, which are NAD precursors.
I know, I know you've got some feelings on this. I have pretty, I have pretty strong feelings on
this topic too. I'm trying to think how we can frame this. So let's take a step back. Well,
let's let me do this for the listener who is contemplating whether or not they should turn
the podcast off now or not. Cause you barely hung on to the biochemistry of Colleen and fatty liver
disease. Most people have heard of NR nicotinamide riboside, NAD as the sort of fountain of youth.
And if you've listened to other podcasts I've done specifically when I spoke with David Sinclair,
we talked a lot about sirtuins and the necessity of NAD as a substrate to sirtuins.
What many of you have also probably heard of is there were a couple of companies out there that
are making a very popular supplement. One of them is called Elysium. They make a supplement called
Basis. The other was called Chromadex. They make a supplement. I think it's called True Nyogen.
If I am I right on that? Yeah. I believe that Basis takes nicotinamide riboside,
combines it with terra stilbene, which is a sirtuin activator and that is their product.
And my recollection is that the True Nyogen folks are just giving nicotinamide riboside. I don't
know if they have a sirtuin activator in there, but I could be wrong and it's probably not relevant
unless you know the answer. All right. So the thinking goes as follows. We have this little
thing in our cells called mitochondria and they have all these little complexes and these complexes
are basically used to generate reducing agents that move electrons to one side of a double
membrane and it builds up a gradient and then that gradient allows us to make a bunch of ATP
and that whole process is called oxidative phosphorylation. The first of these complexes
turns NAD into NADH and, pardon me, NADH to NAD. So as the ratio, as we age, it has been postulated
and maybe even observed, I don't know if it's been truly observed inside the mitochondria,
maybe it has, that the ratio of NAD to NADH goes down. And if that's happening, then you have
presumably less NAD with NAD being an important substrate for sirtuins, which do many things,
but primarily repair DNA damage. It would seem that we would want more NAD.
Okay. You also have NAD depletion because the sirtuins and the PARPs, which is the other class
of enzymes that are using NAD for the purpose of protecting DNA and telomeres and all the things
that are postulated to be important to aging and longevity, they consume the NAD. They're consuming
the NAD. That's right. Yeah, absolutely. Which I think are two totally different things.
Correct. And there's another great example of it's hard to know why NAD levels might be low. Is it
low because of high consumption and high demand, or is it low because of low production?
Well, so if you're looking at the ratio of NAD to NADH, then I think that being in the
overfed state is the thing that's the problem. If you're talking about NAD amount levels dropping,
then you're looking at consumption by the PARPs and sirtuins that are consuming it for the purpose
of repairing damage. Yeah. So in an ideal world, if you could wave a magic wand,
you would presumably want more NAD inside your mitochondria. Tell us why that magic wand
doesn't exist. Why can't you just eat NAD in other words? I wouldn't say it doesn't exist,
but it's questionable how powerful of a wand this is. So there's niacin in our, these are all forms
collectively, we call all this stuff niacin in the diet. It's vitamin B3. And in the foods that we
primarily get niacin in the form of nicotinic acid from plant foods, we primarily get it in
the form of nicotinamide from animal foods. Like if we eat a steak, a lot of the niacin that's in
the steak is going to be in the form of NAD or NADPH that is in those cells. But all of that has
to be digested. And what we're absorbing in the intestines is either nicotinic acid or nicotinamide.
My guess is if you take a nicotinamide riboside supplement, you are absorbing the NR intact.
And if you take a nicotinamide mononucleotide supplement, NMN, you are probably digesting that
down to NR or nicotinamide and absorbing them, but we are definitely not absorbing NADH or NAD
in the intestines. So when we're eating food, once we go into the enterocyte, we have
nicotinic acid primarily being converted over to nicotinamide and the intestinal cell tries to turn
that into NAD, but whatever the intestinal cell doesn't turn into NAD itself, it passes on to the
liver. So you're going through the portal vein. Now you have maybe some nicotinic acid left,
depending on how much you ate, you have some nicotinamide in there. In theory, if you took a
nicotinamide riboside supplement, you got some nicotinamide riboside in there. Then it goes into
the liver and the liver is the main site that's really metabolizing all these forms for the entire
body. And what the liver is going to do is it's going to try to convert as much of those forms
into NAD as possible, not even just for itself, but because it's going to hold a reserve of NAD
for the rest of the body. And then almost everything that comes out of the liver into
the circulation is nicotinamide. So the overwhelming thing that gets niacin out of
the liver to any other tissue is nicotinamide. That's the transport form. And then those tissues
will convert that into NAD. So what we definitely don't see is we don't see NAD and NADH being
transported in the blood. There's some there, but it's not a physiological transport way to get
something from one place to another. If you take a nicotinamide riboside supplement, you will get
some nicotinamide riboside in the blood. Animal experiments suggest that there are trace amounts
of that that will get into certain cells like muscle cells and be converted into NAD, but there
are a physiologically meaningless amount of the NAD that wound up in that muscle cell from taking
that supplement. Overwhelmingly, if you're talking about a tissue other than the liver,
what's happening is that supplement gets converted into nicotinamide, reaches the other
tissues as nicotinamide, and increases tissue NAD by that tissue taking the nicotinamide and making
the NAD. But the first pass effect is pretty significant, right? So let's talk about-
First pass, the effect is basically complete. We'll come back to NMN in a moment, but let's
just talk about NR. NR becomes NMN, becomes NAD, I believe in the cycle. If you take it,
NR, yeah. Yeah. So if you take NR, which is the two most popular supplements on the market
with respect to this particular pathway, the liver is basically to your point taking all of that NR
and making NAD, correct? Yes. So do we have a sense of how much NAD actually makes its way into even
the cytoplasm of a cell that is non-hepatic in that situation? NAD that came from where? That is
derived ultimately from the NR that you ingested. From the liver? Yes. Oh, we know exactly what
happens. The liver turns that into nicotinamide and secretes it for the rest of the cells. How much?
Like a meaningful amount of- As a portion? Yeah. Well, or just-
Well, I don't know off the top of my head the amount, but what I can tell you is that
for all intents and purposes, all of the NAD that is in any of your cells that are not the liver,
well, actually I should say maybe 5% the kidney synthesized from protein. But aside from that 5%
in the kidney, pretty much every molecule of NAD is ultimately derived from circulating nicotinamide
that the liver put out. So in other words, it's not the case that NR needs to be brought into a cell
to be turned into NAD. It's that nicotinamide gets into a cell to be turned into NAD.
It's not even needs to, it's Ken, right? Because NAD, to my knowledge, does not go from plasma
into cell, but it's hard to know if- It does, it does. It just might be that you don't have enough
in the plasma to justify the- Well, you do if you're injecting it. Oh, so this is interesting.
Okay, I want to come back. I'm going to park that because I want to let you finish,
but I'm going to come back to that. So nicotinamide is the physiological circulating form of niacin
that all cells will use to make nicotinamide. I mean, excuse me, that all cells will not use to
make NAD. Minor exceptions are about five, we can make some niacin from tryptophan and about 95% of
that happens in the liver, 5% happens in the kidney. So there is some tiny bit of this that
the kidney is making its own, but overwhelmingly with that tiny exception, a tissue is getting
NAD because it took nicotinamide out of the blood that the liver made from its store of NAD.
Now let me expose my ignorance in biochemistry and my forgetfulness.
Nicotinamide is charged or not? I know NAD is, but-
No, nicotinamide is not charged.
Okay, so nicotinamide makes its way into a cell through an active or passive transporter?
Active transport, I believe. I would need to check that.
That's okay. We'll figure all that out. Once nicotinamide is in the cell,
how does it combine with adenosine, et cetera, to become NAD?
It goes through two steps that are ATP dependent. It gets converted to nicotinamide mononucleotide
and then it gets converted into NAD. A portion of the NMN, nicotinamide mononucleotide,
a portion of that becomes NR and then comes back to NMN. And I don't know exactly why,
but I think it's like a pressure release valve. So if you're trying to hold on to the nicotinamide
and get it to NAD more than the rate at which you can make the NAD, you might convert some to NR
to kind of hold on to it. Got it. And then it comes back and-
Wait, to NR or to NMN?
No, to NR. To NR, okay.
So you have nicotinamide, you go up to NMN, you go up to NAD. You can go from NMN over to NR,
but you have to go back over from NR to NMN to get to NAD.
Yep, and I think of it as a cycle.
Way easier to look at this in a picture.
Yeah, yeah. The picture that I have in my mind is NAD going to NAM to NMN as a cycle
with NR being a pop off of NMN.
Okay, yeah. So what you're talking about is in the case of NAD consuming enzymes like
sirtuins and PARPs that are using NAD for DNA repair and all those things we were talking
about before, what they do when they consume the NAD is they release nicotinamide.
So imagine you're a muscle cell. You took originally, to get every molecule of NAD you
have. Originally, you took some nicotinamide in from the blood, but then you did things with it.
Some of those things were what you were talking about with oxidative phosphorylation.
You don't consume NAD in that process. You just cycle it back and forth. You use it over and over
and over and over and over again. But some of the things that you did were with the sirtuins and
PARPs that are engaging in protection. And those enzymes will consume the NAD to generate nicotinamide.
The big problem here is that nicotinamide is an inhibitor of all those enzymes through
negative feedback loop. So you have to have to have to have to have to do something with the
nicotinamide very fast, or you need to methylate it, bring it back to the earlier discussion and
pee it out. So nicotinamide is circulating as the circulating form in the blood, but intracellularly,
you don't let it hang out there. You do something with it. So you take in the nicotinamide and you
either make NAD or you get rid of it. Yeah, actually, I didn't even realize one could have
free nicotinamide inside a cell, which I guess you're basically saying that that's, but only
momentarily. Momentarily, yeah. But it doesn't hang out there in that form. No, it doesn't.
Okay, so now let's go back to the question that I'm still trying to wrap my mind around,
which is if I give you a gram of nicotinamide riboside, you're saying none of that NR is
basically going to leave the liver instead, just nicotinamide is leaving the liver.
It is found in the blood. So there's clearly, there is some nicotinamide riboside in the blood
and we don't have the data in humans, but we do have the data in mice.
Isn't this what Joshua Benowitz did in that trace you're saying over the summer?
That's exactly what I'm referring to. So in his paper, what he showed was that there is a little
bit of nicotinamide riboside that gets into the blood, that there's a little bit that gets into
some of the cells, not others. So for example, it can't cross the brain at all. It's fairly
decent at getting into muscle if it's there. There's not a lot there, but what is there can
get into the muscle and there is a little bit that gets turned into NAD. But the nice thing about his
study was he was the way that he designed the tracers was they could see.
Yeah, you want to be able to separate the nicotinamide from the nicotinamide riboside,
right? Well, they could see even at the level of detail as like what was the history of this
molecule before it became NAD. So they could differentiate inside the muscle cell, they could
differentiate the pool of NAD that the muscle made from nicotinamide riboside. They could,
from the pool that it made from nicotinamide, even from the pool that it went through the cycle
and then back, right? So they had extremely fine detail. And what they showed was that there's a
little bit of nicotinamide riboside that makes it into the muscle intact. It pulled up the graph to
try to see the amount and they have to blow up that part of the bar graph to show you what that
tiny trace looks like. It's basically practically meaningless. Now, what they also showed in their
papers and also in the same group published one in 2016, what they also showed was that you do
increase NAD in the muscle a lot when you supplement with the nicotinamide riboside.
But it all comes from nicotinamide that the liver had made and circulated in the blood.
Let's just make the math easy. You take one mole of NR orally. We've already acknowledged that the
amount of NR that escapes the blood is so small you need a magnifying glass to see it. So it's
a pico mole or something. How many moles of nicotinamide make their way into the cell?
Again, I'm sort of directionally speaking. But order of magnitude, is it more of it or
like the majority of it does? Or how much loss is there outside of the first pass effect?
Is there an inefficiency? What are you calling loss? Are you calling increasing hepatic NAD loss?
Or are you calling alcohol loss, anything that prevents the actual nicotinamide from making it
into the cell? I don't know off the top of my head what those numbers would be. But I can come back.
I'll come back to the human data that the chromidex people have published on that point.
But what I can say about the physiology is that there's a lot that doesn't get into any particular
cell that isn't actually lost. And I think this is a really important point because in the
Rabinowitz group in 2016, they had another paper where they actually, when you're listening to this,
I mean, what's your thought right now? Would NR be more effective than nicotinamide eating it?
That's a good question. My intuition would have been NMN would have been the best precursor if
you could get it around the liver. So as a thought experiment like SL, sublingual or intravenous NMN
would have been my intuition is the best way to increase intracellular NAD.
If you didn't have that choice, if nicotinamide is the circulating form that's getting into the muscle,
would you think that NR is just generating nicotinamide that gets into the muscle?
Yeah, I think based on what you're saying, I would now say nicotinamide per se would be a better
substrate. Right, but it's not. And in the two, that's what I would think too. I love how you
walked me down that path. Well, no, because as I'm saying this, it sounds like why on earth,
why would you take anything other than nicotinamide? It's just going to make nicotinamide anyway.
And I think this gets back to your waste point too. In the 2016 paper that the Rabinowitz group
put out, they showed that, and this was a minor portion of their studies. They didn't have anywhere
near as much data as they had on the NR, but they showed that they got a much less NAD response in
the muscle with oral nicotinamide than they did with NR. Even though they also showed with very
elegant tracers that it all got there as nicotinamide. Let me make sure I understood what you said.
You give oral nicotinamide and you are now asking the question, how much of it goes to the liver,
how much of it leaves the liver, also is nicotinamide and makes it to the muscle.
They didn't have all that data on the oral nicotinamide.
Okay, so they skipped that step, but they're going from-
They're asking the question, in the muscle, our goal is to increase NAD in the muscle.
Yep.
Is it more effective to give oral NR or is it more effective to give oral nicotinamide?
And a minute ago, I would have said oral nicotinamide would make more sense.
But they showed that-
You're saying the opposite.
They showed the opposite, yeah. Here's the rationale that, now this is kind of my synthesis-
Did the 2018 paper shed light on that now? Because now they had a tracer.
They had tracers in the 2016 paper too.
But they couldn't see how much tyrosine in the liver was being-
Yeah, there was much more kinetic flux data in the 2018 paper. That clarified,
if you had them on to talk about it, I'm sure you'd get better responses about the details.
And by the way, I've tried to get Josh on a hundred times and Josh and I are friends
because we went to medical school together and I just can't get him to hop on a train
and come up here. So Josh, if you're listening to this, please just come up so we can talk about this.
Yeah, I'll just say what I learned about this paper. Because I read the paper, I took notes,
I synthesized them, I did my own podcast about this. So I think I have a pretty decent
understanding of that paper, but I'm sure there's details that I forgot. So what I learned from that
paper is a bunch of things. For example, I know now that the average NAD molecule turns over
every eight hours you consume an NAD molecule in most tissues, but it's every two hours in the
liver, things like that. I know that the spleen and the small intestine consume 40 times more
NAD than the muscle and the fat does. So there's a bunch of data in that paper, but there's not
infinite data about the proportion that went in in each compartment everywhere.
Back to the point about why is it more effective to take the NR? And this is what I think is going
on when I think is the most sensible rationale that makes sense of this. So in the liver,
you imagine that the NR, the nicotinamide, nicotinic acid, whatever it was you ate gets
into the liver. Think about that cycle that we talked about before. So we go from nicotinamide
and we go up to NMN, we go up to NAD. If we consume the NAD with sirtuins and PARPs,
we come back to nicotinamide. And having that nicotinamide around is a liability because it's
going to inhibit all the repair enzymes. So we either want to make NAD out of it or we want to
get rid of it. If you eat oral nicotinamide and you absorb oral nicotinamide into the liver
and the liver gets it, that oral nicotinamide is immediately a liability before it ever becomes NAD
because it can inhibit all those enzymes, the sirtuins and the PARPs. So the liver has a bifurcation
of what can it do with this? It can methylate it to get rid of it and pee it into the urine
or it can make NAD. If you take NR, then you go into NMN, you have to make NAD before you ever
generate nicotinamide and expose it to the detoxification process. What I believe is happening,
and I think this is backed up by the animal data, is nicotinamide riboside is a superior way to
increase hepatic NAD because when it gets to the liver, it can't be immediately detoxified.
It's not immediately a threat to the sirtuins and PARPs and it can only make NAD before it
does anything else. And again, this is a flux thing, right? It's not like the liver says,
okay, cells, tell me what our balance of NAD and NMN is on Friday. And on Saturday, I'll make a
decision about how much to empty into the urine. This is an immediate thing that's happening right
now. The liver says, oh, got two choices. I either detoxify this or I do something useful with it.
And so if you're presenting it with that thing that's a threat and it has to make that decision,
it can only make so much NAD at once at one time, then you're going to have much more waste
in the detoxification pathway than if you put the thing in that has to make NAD. That is not a threat
when it makes NAD. And that has to actually generate NAD to ever be exposed to the detoxification
pathway. So you have to appreciate the central role of the liver in controlling the flux
throughout the entire body. The liver's not just making NAD for itself. It's making NAD because it
carries all of the reserves for the rest of the body as NAD. So the liver doesn't just have NAD
that's immediately being used in respiration and is immediately being used in sirtuins and PARPs.
It has a reserve pool of NAD that it holds on to for the specific purpose of a slow release of
nicotinamide to the rest of the tissues that they will take up. And then they will have the immediate
decision to either detoxify it or make NAD. But if the liver can hold on safely to the NAD
and have a better ability to release nicotinamide on an as needed basis and a continuous basis
at a rate that the other tissues can take up and do something useful with, then because you got a
superior way of increasing hepatic NAD, you got a better continuous flux that was optimized of
nicotinamide to reach the other tissues so they can make NAD. Yeah. So in that sense, it's actually
sort of parallels glucose, right? In the sense that we have to maintain about five grams of glucose
in our bloodstream at all times. So if you have 10 grams of glucose in your bloodstream, you have
diabetes, you've got huge problems, you're going to go blind and get your toes cut off. But not if
you have a hundred grams in your liver. Exactly. But five grams is perfect. And if, by the way,
if you have two grams, you die. You know, it's just, it's an amazing problem where the liver
is constantly titrating. So you're basically drawing a parallel that says it's probably doing
the same thing holding onto NAD. So in this analogy, NAD is to glycogen what glucose is to
nicotinamide. Yeah. Is that a fair analogy? It's a fair analogy, except there's a probably much
larger percentage of the hepatic NAD pool that's actually being proportionally they're different.
But yeah, in principle, I think that's a good analogy. So let's see if we can go deeper on
that analogy. There are a lot of people out there who, in fact, I have a friend who came to me a year
ago and he said, I've got the greatest idea. I'm going to open up an IV NAD clinic and we're going
to do NAD and ketamine. So we'll give you ketamine to get rid of your depression and NAD to make you
live longer. And I said, well, I'm interested in the ketamine because I do think that's a super
interesting molecule for recalcitrant depression. At least a year ago, I said, my understanding is
giving intravenous NAD is not going to increase intracellular or certainly mitochondrial NAD. And
I don't know that that makes sense. Though I've got many friends who have done IV NAD and they all say
the same thing. It's the worst feeling in the world. Oh, I know why it's the worst feeling in the world.
Say why? We need to come back and say, what is the role of free NAD that's found extracellularly?
I can guess what the role is. What I can tell you is that one of the things it does
is it activates granulocytes to cause vasodilation and a massively ramped up inflammatory response.
So not unlike niacin. No, it's very different from niacin. So niacin has a very similar response,
doesn't it, at very high levels? Well, yeah, but biochemically, what's happening is totally
different. Oh, it is. Okay. Yeah. So why is niacin causing a flush? It's not the same as NAD's flush.
So nicotinic acid is specifically nicotinic acid activates the nicotinic acid receptor.
And that is present on a bunch of immune cells that are responsible for the flushing response,
not necessarily granulocytes. Yeah. So NAD is acting on it's a different receptor. And,
you know, I don't know, maybe it's maybe it's more, it might be more similar than I was leading on.
It's a different receptor, but maybe the results are some I've never injected.
I've never had the flushing response and I've never injected NAD. It probably is fair to say
that they're similar in their results and that there are some similarities biochemically,
but it's not the same biochemical mechanism. So if you do inject this NAD, what is it now you've
bypassed the liver and it's sitting there in the plasma. What's clearly happening based on the
anecdotal reports of the immediate response to that is that they're, that they are causing an
inflammatory response. What is not clear is the kinetics of where that NAD is going. Right. But
there's, there is definitely papers that I was able to find showing that there are a variety
of mammalian cell types that do have the ability to take that NAD into the cells.
But I look at this from the perspective of what is the normal physiology? I don't, I don't really
want to know what can happen. First. I want to know what's supposed to happen. Then I'll build
a theory about what I should do based on that. Right. For people who are not injecting it,
how does NAD get out of this cell in the first place? Well, the details aren't worked out,
but it appears to be that NAD, extracellular NAD is from dead cells, from dying cells,
and maybe from cells that are undergoing some sort of stress response and are
secreting it to some degree to reflect their energy status. You mean as a signal?
As a signal. Interesting. Oh, yeah. I think it's very clear. You think it can be a signaling
molecule as well? I think it's very clear that there, if there is any role for extracellular
NAD, it is as a signaling molecule. And I think it's almost certain that there is a role for
extracellular NAD as a signaling molecule because there are fairly decently characterized enzymes
that consume NAD that are found extracellularly. There's a whole class of extracellular NAD
consuming enzymes. So if NAD is not ever supposed to be outside of the cell, why would it be there?
And it's like, well, what do those enzymes do? They break it down to use it as a signaling
molecule. So it has to be the case that extracellular NAD is primarily a signaling
function. And so it's definitely not a normal way of transporting NAD from tissue to tissue.
What the signal means, I think will probably be debated if enough people care for a long time to
come. So I have no idea exactly how to simplify and state what it means, but it's very clear that
it's a signaling molecule. So when I look at NAD injection, I'm like, my idea is I'm going to
transport this thing. And that's definitely not the way you transport that thing. And my body's
idea is that that's a signal that means something about what's happening that is definitely not
happening when I. Right, because you're amplifying potentially a signal that's negative.
Yeah. And maybe that has good consequences because maybe it's some kind of rescue signal.
Maybe a stressed cell puts NAD out and says, come help me or come get rid of me because I suck.
Yeah, but if that's the case, gosh, when you took a motherload of NAD in the plasma,
what are you supposed to go after every cell? I mean, how would you even differentiate where
that signal, where that alarm is coming from? Well, that's why I would never do that. But I think
if I'm trying to if I'm trying to explain why are people experiencing reporting benefits from it,
either it's placebo or it's doing something. And if it's not just placebo, my guess is that it's
probably it's probably having some signaling effect that is by virtue of luck, doing something
that the person is reporting is beneficial. But I'm not going to do that because I have no idea
exactly what that signal means. So what's your take then, you know, kind of going back to where
we were a moment ago, which is doing what seems to be much more commonly done, which is taking
oral NR or oral NMN. Okay, so oral NMN, I would bet money that it's not absorbed intact. And that's
because NMN has a charged phosphate group on it. And generally charged phosphates cannot cross
cells. And so they're hydrolyzed. And even if it were to be true that there were transporters in
the intestines that could take NMN up intact, it probably still would not be absorbed intact
because the phosphatase is in the small intestine that cleave the phosphates off of everything that
all the molecules in the food you eat do so nonspecifically to all of the molecules in the
food you eat. So for example, riboflavin, when you consume riboflavin 5-phosphate, I'm quite
certain that none of it is absorbed intact. Were that because there were a specific riboflavin 5-phosphate
phosphatase that just cleaved that phosphate, then I would say, well, I don't know about niacin,
I need to look for the phosphatase. But that's not the case. What is the case is that in a normally
functioning small intestine, you have this overabundance of nonspecific phosphatases that just
cleave the phosphates off of everything that you're eating. And that's because even though there
might be some exceptions to the rule, perhaps the overwhelming rule is that it's really difficult to
carry charged phosphates across the intestines, across cell membranes in general. So I doubt that
the NMN gets in there intact. And I think that if anything, maybe it gets cleaved to NR and the NR
does. I believe the NR gets intact because that's what the Rubinowitz group's paper showed, that it
was getting into the liver as NR. And because it makes sense, because NR doesn't have a charged
phosphate on it. Okay, so we can simplify it and say, let's just limit our discussion to NR.
And let's just say now we're taking super physiologic doses of NR, which would be what's
prescribed in these supplements, sort of 500 to 1000 milligrams daily. Using our glycogen,
somewhat oversimplified analogy, we're now increasing our hepatic reservoir of nicotinamide
that we can slow drip out when it's demanded, because that's going to be the better way to do it.
Right. So there's promise based on the animal experiments, although there are in the human
trials that they've done, they haven't showed any benefit of doing this at all. Now, what you
mentioned Brenner, I mean, you didn't mention him by name, but you mentioned chromodex. Tell me a
little bit about their work. I've looked at a couple of their human studies and they've done
a couple of studies where they've characterized the metabolites that are produced when you take
oral NR. And they've done a couple of studies where they tried to look for some benefits and
didn't really find any. So there's no benefits on glucose metabolism. There's no benefits on lipid
metabolism. Now, were they doing these as kinetic studies or were they actually trying to look for
phenotypic improvement? In the first study, they just took one person and they extensively
characterized all the metabolites that were produced in three different compartments. But
then there were two, and I don't know if this is comprehensive, but in the studies that I looked at,
there were two other studies where they were measuring in different populations, they were
measuring things that you would relate to health like glucose and triglycerides. And you're saying
those things did not improve. Yeah. In fact, there's in one of the papers, I believe it was
the triglycerides went up a little bit and the potassium, the serum potassium went down a little
bit. I mean, nothing that was that you wouldn't conclude anything from it, but it didn't look like
it was doing anything good. Now I want to make a couple caveats here because these have been
pretty short studies and my suspicion is. Furthermore, they're not even measuring what
we really care about, right? I also don't think they're measuring like what you would
necessarily expect to see, which I think is harder to measure. So if you think about it,
think about the Rabinowitz paper, which showed that the turnover of NAD is, and this is in mice,
but it's all we have right now. The turnover of NAD in the small intestine is 40 times what it is
in muscle. Explain that to me. I mean, that is so counterintuitive. Think about it from the
opposite perspective. So we're thinking about life extension or health span extension with
super physiological doses of NR. Think about the opposite case of pellagra, which is nice and
deficiency. Where do you see that? You see the, if you're an optimist, you say the three Ds of
dermatitis, diarrhea, and dementia. If you're a pessimist, you say the four Ds and you include
death. And in the brain, what's going on is NAD is actually generating molecules that are directly
involved in immediate neurotransmitter production. So I think that's why you see brain effects in
pellagra, but overwhelmingly, if you exclude the brain, the two tissues where you are seeing the
most dramatic effect are the two tissues that are outside of the body. Okay. So it's interesting. I
was going to say, is it because they're outside the body or is it because of the rapid turnover?
I think part of the rapid turnover is because they're outside the body. I mean, think about,
think about the quality control inside your body compared to outside your body. And like,
think about once we cross the intestinal barrier, ideally we have incredible control over what
passes that barrier, but we have no control with what it encounters. Think about what goes into
the toilet. Like would we want that inside our body in the number two, right? So I think part
of the reason that NAD is so, and I'm guessing in their paper, if they had characterized it in the
skin, that it would be high, but they didn't. So what do we know about what causes pellagra? Well,
when you're out in the sun, you're always experiencing DNA damage from that sunlight.
You're always repairing it. So in the skin, you have this very incredibly high NAD turnover in
the skin, because even things that you normally think are benign, like just going outdoors is
actually causing damage that, that you are repairing always. And so when you have the skin
having a very high need to constantly repair itself, and then you take away its ability to
do that, then suddenly you see this manifestation in the skin in the gut. What's happening is,
I think part of it is that it's so energy intensive to maintain the cell turnover in the
gut. But it's also the case that just like the skin, the gut is exposed to so many insults
of just total lack of quality control over the things that come inside it.
And my suspicion is that where you would be likely to see benefits of increasing tissue NAD
over the short timeframe is going to be in those tissues with the highest turnover.
Like you're going to look at skin quality and small intestinal health, both of which are
very hard to wrap my mind around how you would design the ideal study compared to measuring
glucose and insulin and triglycerides and lipoproteins, right? Like you know exactly what
you would measure for metabolic syndrome. I would have to sit down and really think about how I'm
going to measure someone's skin quality or their small intestinal health. Over the long term,
what you would expect is increased genomic stability, decreased accumulation of DNA damage,
and increased telomere length, none of which have been measured.
But also why, I mean, I could certainly think of ways that those things could not be preserved,
even in the absence of gut and skin dysfunction. In other words, you could still see epigenetic
damage in the presence of perfect gut and skin barrier, right? You're just saying you expect to
see less of it if you created a better barrier. You were saying that over the long haul, you would
expect to see less epigenetic change. Oh, okay. Let me clarify. The point that I'm trying to make
is that if you're talking about a 12 week or 16 week time period, I don't think you're going
to see any results unless you're looking for specific things.
You're saying based on the non-external benefits. In other words, to understand what it's doing
inside all of the other cells in the body, you're going to need a much longer time period.
Exactly.
Okay, I got it.
Exactly. And so we basically don't have much data because we have these several week-long studies
in humans. And if we're going to look at things going on inside the body besides those tissues
with super high turnover, I think we're going to have to look at longer studies that have more
relevant endpoints.
So let's talk about it from the standpoint of harm.
Okay, yeah.
Because the other way we can think about this is if you're cost-insensitive, what's the downside in
spending 100 bucks a month, which is about what you're going to spend to take the party dose of
these compounds?
So I think the potential risk is that you're sapping your methyl group supply.
And the reason is that, like we said before, part of this cycle is when you do generate
nicotinamide, you face the possibility that you have to methylate it and you have to pee out
the methylated metabolite. And then the question is, well, if you're taking 1000 milligrams or
2000 milligrams of NR a day, which for the sake of putting some numbers on it, the RDA for niacin
is around 15 milligrams. So we're talking a hundred times.
You are losing a lot of methyl groups. And we know this in humans because the two papers that I found
where they did measure methylated metabolites of the nicotinamide riboside. And what you see is that
in urine and in blood cells, you see incredible increase in the methylated metabolites of
nicotinamide.
But wait, so wouldn't a quick and dirty test be homocysteine should go up, for example,
in a patient taking NR if they're losing methyl donors?
No, I don't think so. I don't think that would be the most sensitive thing. And I think we will
eventually see a paper showing that that's not true because I've heard Brenner on a podcast say
that he measured homocysteine and he measured acidenazylmethionine levels in the blood and
showed that it doesn't have any effect. So I didn't see that paper.
Publish it up and I think it will come out.
You're saying that you're always able to methylate folate even like we just prioritize the
methylation of folate high enough that even if we're losing methylation capacity to NR,
we're still going to preserve it at the folate level.
So yeah, I don't know if we might need to back up and talk about the methylation cycle to make this
clear, but you tell me. So the most sensitive thing that changes when you have a change in
the methyl group supply is your creatine synthesis.
Interesting. So I want to come back to that. If we jump to methylation, can we remember to come
back to finish this? Because we do need to talk about MTHFR and COMT and all of our other friends.
If we're going to do that, I think it would be much easier to talk about the methylation of NR
and what you would want to measure in a study to test that. I think it would be way easier to do that.
Once we've done that.
All right. So now we're going to hopefully I'm going to write this down. We're going to come
back to this. Let's talk about that five letter acronym that pretty much everybody's heard of by
now, but nobody really knows what the heck it is. What is an MTHFR gene and what is an MTHFR mutation
and should anyone care?
All right. So as we had said before, a methyl group is a one carbon unit and the methylation
cycle uses the amino acid methionine to donate that one carbon to dozens of different things.
So what we do there is we activate methionine to S-adenosyl methionine using ATP.
And S-adenosyl methionine is the universal methyl donor. So no matter what we're talking
about synthesizing, what we're talking about regulating, it is always S-adenosyl methionine
that donates that one carbon, that methyl group, it becomes through two steps. It becomes
homocysteine, which is the inevitable byproduct of using it. And once we have homocysteine,
we have two choices. We can either get rid of the homocysteine if we have an abundance of methyl
groups, or if we don't have enough methyl groups, we will recycle the homocysteine back to methionine.
There's two ways to do that. One is that folate, which is vitamin B9 can take a methyl group from
amino acid metabolism and can pass it on to B12. B12 passes it on to homocysteine.
Homocysteine regenerates methionine. Or choline can be oxidized to beta-ene, which can be
then the methyl donor to recycle homocysteine to methionine. Those two pathways are equivalent.
In the average person, they're probably 50-50, but it's going to depend on their dietary intake.
To your question about MTHFR, the MTHFR enzyme is one of the enzymes that is involved in constructing
the methyl group that came from amino acid metabolism that went on to the folate molecule.
That's how folate passed the methyl group on to B12 and then on to homocysteine to recycle
methionine. There's a lot of people going around saying, I have MTHFR. Well, we all have MTHFR.
I have ATP.
Exactly. It's not just misleading because we all have MTHFR. It's also misleading because
if you look at the two common polymorphisms, which are gene variants in the MTHFR gene,
they are so spread out in the population that what you actually see is a gradient of MTHFR
activity that's fairly even spread across the population. You could basically divide the
population into quintiles of MTHFR activity and you'd see it wouldn't be exactly 2020, 2020,
2020, but it would be fairly close to that. If you have limited ability to use folate for
methylation, there are several things that happen. The first is that you use up more choline
and you do that because you suck at using folate and you have no problem using choline.
So you basically say, I'm not that good at using this pathway. I'm going to use the alternative.
And that nutritionally, that makes the choline requirement go up. At the very beginning of this
podcast, I said that I'd seen some studies where some people need 1200 milligrams of choline.
That's the people with the worst MTHFR activity. What happens is there were two different
populations that were studied and exactly what happened to their choline metabolism was different
in each population, but the commonality was- And the worst function is, remind me, it's
ACCC, which or TTCC, which SNPs would be the quote unquote worst? The worst case for MTHFR is the C677T
homozygous. Homozygous A or- Homozygous for T instead of C.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So it's the TT and then on the A1298C, it's like the-
Yeah, for the A1298C, that one is less significant than the C677T, but you can have both of them.
So in the best case, you have neither of them. That's like 10% or 15% of the population. But the
next step up to have a little hit is to have- You're basically a CA or a CT and you're
functionally pretty close to normal. I like the way you describe it actually, which is
think of it in quintiles. Yeah. And I would even say it's less than quintiles because to your point,
in my experience, I only see maybe 10% of people that are wild type in both. That's pretty freaking
rare. I mean, I would be surprised if it's 10%. No, that's exactly what it is. I would be surprised
if it's 10%. No, it's not exactly quintiles, but it depends what population you look at too.
It's going to vary, but basically there's a little bit in each category and there's not a category
that even has a large minority of the people. That's right. It's not even like ApoE where you
can say, well, the two twos are basically unheard of and the three threes, the wild type. There's
no one that's unheard of. Yeah, yeah. It's almost like I don't really know what the wild type really
is. Yeah. I think it's misleading to call it even wild type and to say you have the mutation.
It's really like there's a spectrum that's even more convincing than gender, right? In this case,
it's like a very even literal, even spread. No one could make a case for binaryism in MTHFR.
So let's for the sake of being overly simplistic, which is not necessarily a good thing,
but to illustrate this point, let's compare the best methylators to the worst methylators,
meaning let's take the top and bottom quintiles of MTHFR function to now illustrate the point
you were making a moment ago before I interrupted you. Right. That's really where we have most of
our data from. So if you compare the best, and I don't even want to call them the best methylators.
Because they're not bad methylators. They're pretty good because they're using up their
choline to do it. So if you compare the people with the best methyl folate status compared to
the people with the worst methyl folate status, the people who have bad methyl folate status
are the people who are doubling up the amount of choline that they're blowing through for the cycle.
Now, that said, Chris, it's hard to deny. I mean, I'm getting to the point where one of my favorite
games to play, because I just love to play games with myself when I'm reviewing a patient's labs.
I like to predict a homocysteine based on an MTHFR. And there's an undeniable correlation,
which is not to say I can always predict it. But when I look at your MTHFR status,
the lower you are in your capacity to efficiently do so, the higher your homocysteine is,
all things equal. Now, wouldn't we expect that if they're truly as efficient at methylation,
even using choline, shouldn't they be able to compensate for that?
Okay, so right. I think I probably misspoke when I said they're just as good methylators,
because they're using choline. Yeah, it's a compensatory response. But the thing is,
what you see in the literature, at least, is that studies that can show a statistically significant
rise in homocysteine is generally limited to the people who are in the worst case scenario.
What's interesting that I think no one is talking about, and I didn't even realize this until
last week, is that if you subdivide those people by their riboflavin status,
all the people who have the MTHFR genotype that look bad, that have high homocysteine,
have bad riboflavin status. And the thing that lowers MTHFR activity with those polymorphisms
is that MTHFR is a riboflavin-dependent enzyme, which is vitamin B2, and it has a lower affinity
for the riboflavin as a cofactor. And so you need better riboflavin status to optimize your MTHFR.
This is so counterintuitive, because the thing that we find clinically that is the best hammer
is B6. Because you're not thinking about optimizing the MTHFR activity, you're thinking
about getting rid of the homocysteine. That's right. And do you think that's the wrong way
to think about it clinically? Yeah, I think it's the wrong way to think about it. I think it's too
simplistic. But if someone has high homocysteine, it goes away with B6 supplementation, that person
probably needed high B6. We should talk a little bit more about how this pathway is regulated.
I have a feeling this is going to be a set of show notes that's going to have
some really awesome diagrams. I actually sent Bob 30 slides on this. Awesome. Thank you.
Okay, so let's say that you eat a steak. There are some good things and bad things about that. One
thing is that you have a bunch of methionine in there, and you can use that methionine for
methylation. One of the negative aspects of that is that if you have this boatload of methionine
that comes in, you're going to generate a boatload of homocysteine. And you also don't have the
problem of needing to recycle that homocysteine because you got a boatload of methionine coming
in. In fact, it's probably dripping into the liver. And you can probably predict that if you
have a lot right now, you're going to have even more coming in 10 minutes from now and even more
coming in 10 minutes from now. So what do you do? You totally shut down MTHFR. You totally
shut down the enzyme that uses choline. So you're not recycling it anymore. And then you flip on
this other enzyme that's not usually active, that gets rid of the homocysteine by just breaking it
down. And then on top of that, you want to get rid of the extra methyl groups. And you turn on
this other enzyme that is going to use the amino acid glycine as a buffer. And then that glycine
is going to, if it can, hold on to the methyl group for later use. But if you methylate too
much of that glycine, you wind up peeing it out. So in this context, what the B6 is doing is it's
activating the enzyme that kicked on when you ate the steak that helped you break down the
homocysteine. So if a person has high homocysteine that goes down, the part of the point that I want
to make here is that they're not different parallel ways to do the same thing. Your MTHFR shuts down
in the fed state if you ate protein. The enzyme that uses B6-
And when you say protein, do you mean specifically methionine or do other amino acids-
Well, there's methionine in every protein. There's more methionine in eggs. There's more methionine
in meat compared to plant foods, but there's enough methionine that if you just eat a meal
that has a reasonable amount of protein, you're going in this direction.
So take the opposite situation, which is the amino acid that falls most quickly when you fast
is methionine. We don't preserve methionine the way, for example, we preserve branched
chain amino acids in a non-fed state. So three days into a fast, you should have very high MTHFR
activity. Yes. How this ties back to the patients with the B6 is that it's proof of concept that
the B6 worked that the problem you addressed was not MTHFR. That means that part of their high
homocysteine, it was a result of fed state homocysteine that should have been broken down
using the vitamin B6 that wasn't broken down because they didn't have enough B6.
The B6 is working because people need more B6. So this is actually very interesting, Chris. So
it's almost like we should define how much methyl folate and how much methyl B12 one needs,
even in the presence of MTHFR mutations that are quote unquote bad. And if they're still not
lowering homocysteine, flogging them with more of that is not the answer. You have to move to TMG
or B6 or something like that. So I think the typical supplement we would give a patient
would have 400 micrograms of methyl folate and maybe 800 micrograms of methyl B12.
Does that seem like even overkill, reasonable, more than sufficient? I think it's reasonable.
And if that's not fixing the problem, you've got to look elsewhere.
Well, you're not going to fix MTHFR with methyl folate.
No, no, that's right. If that's not fixing the homocysteine, you haven't identified what the
deficit is.
Yes. But we went down this direction because we were talking about is homocysteine a good indicator
of whether you're messing up your methylation. So I think homocysteine, yes, there's data saying
maybe the homocysteine is a problem in and of itself because it causes oxidative stress and
might contribute to cardiovascular disease. But it's also just a marker that things aren't
working right in that cycle. But it's not the only thing that goes wrong in that cycle.
You have other alterations. So for example, what I had said at the very beginning of this about
some people need 900 to 1200 milligrams of choline, that's because people with... And you're not going
to fix this by fixing homocysteine. People who have low MTHFR activity are doubling the amount
of choline that they blow through and they have problems that are a result of not having enough
choline that have nothing to do with homocysteine whatsoever that need to be fixed by putting more
choline into the system. So I'm not telling you that their homocysteine is going to go down when
you put the choline in, maybe it will. This choline is a methyl donor. But what I'm telling
you is that the data indicate that those people have a higher choline requirement. And the way
that you address that is by consuming enough choline. Is there then a relationship between
MTHFR and propensity to fatty liver disease given that a subset of patients are going to be burning
through choline quicker and therefore have less choline to do its job in the liver? I would expect
that that could be the case off the top of my head. I don't know if data on that. What I do...
Hopefully there's a graduate student listening to this who's going to pick... Because that'd be a
really interesting and elegant experiment that demonstrate that. What I do know there's data on
is showing that 900 to 1200 milligrams of choline will do two things. One, it will minimize
markers of oxidative DNA damage. And I'm not even sure what that mechanism is. And the second thing
that it does is it brings choline utilization markers back down to what you would find in someone
who didn't have the MTHFR polymorphism. And it comes back to everything that we said before
about the relative fluxes. So if someone's using up their choline more for that process,
I wouldn't necessarily expect them to have fatty liver, but I would expect them to have a higher
probability of developing it if you put the other conditions in. And again, just going back to what
you said earlier, you would generally recommend people supplement with phosphatidylcholine versus
choline. I would prefer food. And if you're going to do a supplement, I would prefer phosphatidylcholine
over a choline salt. So where does COMT fit into all of this? Because it's another enzyme,
it's involved in the catabolism of catecholamines. Talk a little bit about that. So part of moving
beyond homocysteine, one whole side of this equation is what are you methylating, right?
Because homocysteine is a byproduct of the methylation cycle. What you're methylating is
90% of it is to synthesize creatine and to synthesize phosphatidylcholine.
And then the other 10% is a gradient of a handful of things that are fairly sensitive to methyl groups
of probably and a lot of things that aren't. If you look at the next most sensitive thing to
creatine synthesis, it's dopamine. And COMT is the enzyme that methylates dopamine. Basically,
what it does is it modifies dopamine metabolism in a way where if you methylate more dopamine,
you are mentally more flexible. And if you methylate less dopamine, you are mentally more stable.
And if you're in the middle of that, it could just be a variation of your personality. But as you
start to get to the ends of that spectrum, you start to get into the possibility of psychiatric
disorders that could be a result of being in the extremes. But in the middle of that spectrum,
they talk about the worrier phenotype and the worrier phenotype. So the person who's the
worrier, W-A-R, is the person who has a higher rate of methylating dopamine, is more mentally
flexible. And that's the person that picks the battle, faces it, picks the battle, faces it,
defeats, and just moves from one thing to the next. The worrier gets stuck on things they're
worrying about. But you look at just like MTHFR activity, you look at COMT activity,
and it's a perfect spread. There aren't as many different types. It's basically like 50% of people
are in the middle, 25% are in one end, 25% are on the other end. Why is it spread like that?
Because there's a trade-off. And so I think the worrier, worrier phenotype is a bad way to talk
about it because actually the people with the so-called worriers, the so-called people who worry,
W-O, yeah, it's hard to pronounce that exactly right. So the people who have a low rate of
methylation, they're also better at doing a lot of things that require sustained focus. So better
at academics, there was a recent study that came out that showed that competitive swimmers who are
the low methylation phenotype get better results, they appear to do better competitively. And there
was another study in elderly people that found that if you do an exercise intervention, the people
with the low COMT phenotype are more likely to do more exercise because you told them to.
So these are people where things get stuck in their mind. And things getting stuck in your mind
is great if it's the right thing. So you are predisposed to worry more, because if you get
an anxiety-producing thought or depression-inducing thought in your mind, it gets stuck there more.
But also, if you're going to focus on work that needs to be done, if you're going to focus on
goals, you might be better at that because you've put the right thing in your mind and you had a
better ability to make it stick there. Is the other group, the warrior group,
more susceptible to addiction? Yeah, so if you look at the associations of the genotypes with
different psychiatric diseases, the ones that are most clearly related to impulsivity or getting
stuck on stuff are the ones that seem to be most consistently correlated. So obsessive-compulsive
disorder is associated with the low methylation phenotype, whereas substance abuse and ADHD are
associated with the high methylation phenotype. Then when you start looking at other psychiatric
disorders, you start to get into a lot of noisy data when you look at depression and anxiety and
panic disorder and things like that. But just taking the extremes, how strong are those hazard ratios?
Off the top of my head, I don't know. Directionally, are they meaningful? Are we
talking about hazard ratios of four and five or are we talking about like 1.17s?
I genuinely don't remember. I can put a meta-analysis of this in the show notes that I have.
Okay, that would be great. I mean, because this is one of those things that only once have I ever
been asked about this, and I didn't know the answer, of course, but one of my patients
asked me to go back and look through his genetic data to look at which SNPs he had for COMT
specifically because of this question. Oh, yeah, I don't think it has much diagnostic utility.
I find it interesting from creating a theoretical model of how this stuff works.
And I think part of the reason some of the data is so noisy about, let's say, things in the middle,
like depression and anxiety, which they do correlate. There are studies that show it one
way, but it's just very noisy data. I think part of the reason it's so noisy is that it's not really
about the genetics. You see really strong associations with genetics when you have a
monogenic disease. Of which there's like 73, right? I mean, there's virtually none.
It's not the norm, right? When you're talking about this, it's like, COMT is not a gene for
a mental state. Right. It's a gene that has a partial influence on the stickiness of your mind.
And the way that COMT methylates dopamine is with all the methyl donors. So nutrition is going to
play directly into that. And so your CMT genotype isn't even going to tell you the rate at which
you're methylating dopamine. It's going to tell you the rate at which you could methylate dopamine
given a certain supply of methyl donors. You've put a lot of time into this, Chris, and we'll
make sure we link to this, but you've basically done probably a better job than anyone I know of
at codifying the, if you have this mutation, this would be a great dietary strategy. It would take
us another 12 hours to go through all of them. Let's touch on three of them. You pick, but it
seems to me that the COMT MTHFR would be an interesting one to at least start with. Sure.
So MTHFR, I think what you want to do is, number one, you want to get between 900 and 1200 milligrams
of choline a day. That is the... And your preference, clearly. Fossil total choline. But get it from
your food. Get it from food. Like if you can eat enough eggs and... Yep. Okay. So there's that,
and that has the most data backing it out of everything else that I'm going to say. But
supplementation with creatine makes a lot of sense because 45% of your methyl demand is to synthesize
creatine. And just to put this in perspective for the listener, when people think creatine,
these days we think about creatine monohydrate versus creatine phosphate, which used to be the
supplement. Creatine monohydrate. Right. So creatine monohydrate is something that most people take for
exercise. They take about five grams a day. Back when I was in high school, we used to load it. We
would take 20 grams a day for five days, then five grams, and we'd cycle on and off. You're
probably not old enough to have been in that meat head phase. But the most recent literature I...
No, I did that. The tradition lived on. It's still on the label. Is it really? Yeah. Although the most
recent literature I've seen said just monohydrate, five grams a day is plenty. But again, for most
people, we think of that as creatine is a phosphate donor. And in certain types of exercise, i.e. the
most high intensity, so weight training, for example, that burst is really a phosphate donation
from creatine. It's not an ATP driven process. I actually wasn't really aware of the role of
choline in synthesizing creatine. It's a role of methylation in synthesizing creatine. And so
that whole cycle, whether you're taking the methyl groups from choline or you're taking the methyl
groups from folate, what you do when you synthesize creatine is you start with guanidine acetate,
which you make from the protein in your diet, and then you methylate it, and that makes creatine.
So literally, creatine is the only thing that is super sensitive to the methyl group supply.
So you ate that steak, you synthesized creatine. Five hours later, you're synthesizing nowhere near
as much creatine. And the whole system is designed. So creatine tracks much more closely to say
methionine than leucine. Yeah, because the rationale is that some things are so essential
to the body that you don't want them to ever change with the methyl group supply. So DNA
methylation for gene expression, you don't want to regulate thousands of genes, because you ate a
steak and you had a bunch of extra methyl groups, you want to control that for totally different
reasons. So that's designed to almost never change. Then there are other things that have to be fairly
acutely stable, like your dopamine and other neurotransmitters, you don't want that to go up
twice as much because you ate. But your creatine, you average person has 120 grams of creatine in
their body, and they lose two grams of creatine every day in the form of creatinine that they
pee out in their urine. And so the whole point of creatine synthesis is to keep the accounts balanced.
So if you synthesized no creatine for an entire day, your creatine in your body is going from 120
grams to 118 grams. It's like barely a dent. So creatine is the ideal thing to vary with the
methyl group supply because you can eat a steak, you can do all your creatine synthesis when you
had enough methyl groups, then five hours later you're in the fasted state and you don't synthesize
creatine anymore. It doesn't matter because it's not a neurotransmitter, it's not doing an acute
thing. You just have to make sure that in 60 days from now, your creatine isn't zero, it's still 120
grams in your body. What determines the phosphorylation status of creatine? About 120 grams,
how much of it has an inorganic phosphate? Oh, that's completely unrelated from the synthesis.
That's a matter of the energy state of the cell. So just like ATP gets used when you use energy,
creatine phosphate, so instead of kinastics- But do we have an enzyme? So the way that,
for example, AMPK is a great surrogate for ATP, ADP, AMP, it really gives you a sense of the
energetics. Do we have similar enzymes that give us a sense of CP versus C, creatine phosphate versus
creatine? I don't think there's an analogous enzyme, but there's a completely analogous energy
state. So when you're exercising, for example, your ATP levels go down, your AMP levels go up,
your creatine phosphate levels go down, your creatine levels go up. When you recover,
everything reverses. So this is most studied in muscle, but in an exercising muscle, if you do
weightlifting to failure, you're going to see the creatine phosphate go from about 100% down to about
40% at the point of failure, and then you rest for five minutes and you're going to see most of it
recovered. So by that logic, I mean, the reason athletes like to use creatine is for
increasing that maximal performance or the duration of short maximal performance, right?
It's not going to have an impact on your ability to run a marathon, but it certainly could have an
impact. I think it will have an impact on your ability to run a marathon. You do. Yeah. Interesting.
Because creatine does things in muscle that are independent of that. Independent of its phosphate
donation. Yeah. So the another thing that creatine does in muscle is that it hydrates the muscle
more. And so you literally have. That's for sure. Yeah. I mean, that's a given just based on the
amount of water that travels with it, right? That is a direct factor in strength in a way that has
nothing to do with the duration of the exercise. Yeah. So for the listener, they should know that
for anyone who's taken creatine knows this, you're going to put on about four or five pounds
and it looks sort of like muscle. I mean, it shows up in the right places, but a lot of it's just
water moving to the muscle, right? That's water that directly increases your muscular strength.
Interesting. So it's not just, you know, cause a lot of guys will say, well, that's great because
I look bigger, but the reality of it is actually functional and they're stronger. Yeah. You know,
you could get that amount of creatine if you just ate a few pounds of meat every day.
And apparently there's a diet going around these days where people are doing just that,
but I'm not willing to commit to it. The extent to which is important to kind of modify your diet
around MTHFR really depends on what problems are you facing and what goals do you have and to what
degree do you want to be anal about doing things that have theoretical payoff, right?
So I think that for someone who has either high homocysteine or they have psychiatric difficulties,
what you would expect from the low methylation state is for someone to be overly ruminating on
things. And so if you feel like that's a problem for you and you feel like what you would typically
do to be psychologically healthy is an uphill battle because of your physiology, it might be.
And so in that case, I think you would stick more to that protocol. So obviously,
taking creatine, increasing your choline amount is the most data-backed thing, but taking creatine
makes a lot of sense because if you cut your methyl demand in half, then it's probably going
to matter half as much that you're not that good at methylating, right? So you increase choline
because that's the alternative methyl donor. You put creatine into the system because that's
decreasing the demand. But there's another overlooked thing here, which is that methyl
folate is, I don't know if you want to go into the reasons why, but let me just state as a fact for
faith acceptance. Methyl folate is the thing that controls whether you pee out glycine as a methyl
buffer. If your methyl folate level is low, I'm closing my eyes because I'm now trying to figure
out how trimethyl glycine will fit into this because I have an anecdote to share with you.
Well, trimethyl glycine is beta-E, which is a thing that you make from choline.
Finish your story. I'm going to come back to this interesting anecdote because I'm looking forward
to you explaining to me why I observed this case, but keep going with this.
When your methyl folate level is low, your body thinks that you are in a state of methyl abundance
and that you need to methylate glycine and pee out the methyl groups on the glycine into the urine.
And so you probably need more glycine as well. No one's quantified it. No one's actually shown
that that's the case, but what we know is very, very data backed in terms of how does the system
work. And everything that we know about the system, how the system works says if you have
low methyl folate levels, you'll lose glycine in the urine as methylated metabolites. And so that
means that you do want to put methyl folate in there because you want to try to have some there
to stop that, but you probably need more glycine. And what we know is that we can synthesize glycine,
but the average person probably falls short of their ability to synthesize glycine by 10 to 60
grams a day in terms of optimizing collagen turnover in the skin and et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
We also know that there are studies showing that people get better sleep if they take three to six
grams of glycine before bed at night. People have better blood sugar if they take three to five
grams of glycine with a meal. So it's entirely reasonable that the average person could use
more glycine. And so I think it's entirely reasonable to say, maybe throw some bone broth
in here or throw some collagen in here or some gelatin or some glycine. Do you think it matters
whether you're getting it in bone marrow bone broth versus a supplement? It would be in the bone
broth. And I think the big differences are between getting collagen in versus getting glycine powder.
So for collagen and collagen is what you would get in bone broth. It's been shown to be better at
increasing collagen synthesis. Is that see, I've never understood why that's the case. I've always
kind of thought that that makes no sense because you eat a bunch of collagen. What basically emerges
from your gut is free amino acids. No, there's some collagen peptides or some dipeptides in there.
I mean, how robust are the data on that? I don't know how robust they are. I've actually told
patients on a couple of occasions that have insisted that they take their collagen that I
just don't think it's helping them. Well, I can believe that. For the benefit of replacing their
own collagen. I've always been like, I just don't see how that works. I mean, the other things
interesting more. Right. There's no good data showing that you will have less wrinkles if you
take collagen. I've never heard of any doubt on bone health. The other stuff's more interesting,
frankly. If you tell me that five grams of glycine in the form of collagen will produce better
glycemic control and better sleep. That's more interesting. I'm pretty sure all of the blood
sugar studies were done with glycine powder. I might be wrong about that. I know the sleep
studies were done with glycine powder. All I can think of off the top of my head for a study that
was done, and this wasn't even with collagen. It was with the gelatin, which I would assume would
be the same. Yeah. His last name is Barr. I forget his first name, but there was a study that showed
that before you exercise, if you take 15 grams of gelatin, but not five grams with a little vitamin
C, you will increase collagen synthesis in the tendons. And the rationale for the study, and
actually I didn't even look at this paper. I just listened to an interview that he did about it.
But the rationale was that in your muscle, your muscles met very metabolically active,
very good at taking things up when it wants to, but the connective tissues in your joints
are very dependent on you just pushing more blood supply there. And so when you exercise,
you have the amino acids coming in before you exercise. And then when you're exercising,
there's an increased blood flow that gets the collagen peptides into those tissues.
So part of my ideas here are speculation based on why this works. And so I'm using the reasoning
that we would expect those, like probably if you were measuring plasma glycine levels and those
people, you'd find lower levels of plasma glycine and you'd find higher levels of the
methylated metabolites of glycine. Probably if you looked in the urine, you'd find those things.
And so it makes logical sense to say that you may need more glycine and so you can put into your
diet in these ways, but ultimately this is like... What foods would be high enough in glycine if
someone was sort of opposed to... Skin and bones. Yeah. Including like chicken skin and things like
that. So bones are the highest and skin is intermediate. And bones, to your point,
it's not the marrow, it's the broth you make from the bone. Yeah, it's not the marrow,
it's the broth and it's dependent on the protein content. So if you're making it homemade, you
don't know exactly what the protein content is. I would use the metric of whether it's well gelled.
If you assume you can trust the label, there are several bone broth products on the market where
they say they have 10 grams per cup. And if they... And that's 10 grams of protein or 10 grams of
glycine. 10 grams of protein, which should be about three grams of glycine. Oh my God. So you
got to drink quite a bit of this stuff. Well, a cup is three grams of glycine. Yeah. But if you want
to... That's the bottom of your three to five. Yeah, you're going to drink that before bed every
night and it might help you sleep, right? In theory. Okay. So now that we've walked through
the methylation stuff, I still want to go back to this NR, N-N-N thing because this is what got us
down this path. Right. So in the studies done by Brenner, what we do know is that an enormous amount
of this NR is getting methylated as nicotinamide. I don't think it's possible to extract the data
from those papers and say exactly how much because they're in concentrations. And when they're in
urine, they're not in a 24 hour collection, they're in spot urine. I don't know exactly like what the
up and down flux is over time. But what I can say is that just as a rough calculation to get a sense
of how much impact you could have if the impact were maximal, for every thousand milligrams of
nicotinamide that you detoxify, you are in theory decreasing your synthesis of creatine by 500
milligrams. So you're synthesizing two grams of creatine in a day. So if you're taking 2000
milligrams of nicotinamide riboside, if all of it were detoxified, you'd be cutting your creatine
synthesis in half. But in theory, I mean, that means that you're going from 120 to 116 instead
of 118, right? In a day. You're talking about whole body creatine stores. I'm talking about synthesis.
You're talking about the cellular level too. First of all, no one's taking this for a day. They're
taking it every day if they're taking it, right? And you don't need your creatine to go to zero
before you have problems, right? Like the bodybuilders and the athletes are taking creatine
because they're hoping to maybe increase their body stores by about 30%. So just leveraging a
little bit marginal increase creatine makes big results in your strength. We should clarify that
although 90% of creatine is in your muscles and although the most famous reason to take creatine
is to support your exercise performance. It's also been shown that five grams of creatine a day
improves depression in women with major depressive disorder. And if you just look at the physiology
of creatine, for God's sake, you're using it to make your sperm swim and you're using it to pump
acid into your stomach. So creatine is important in all kinds of areas that you would not expect
to think about it in. So if one was going to take creatine, which I probably haven't taken since
NAMM, you wouldn't just take it during exercise. Like if you wouldn't just take it on the days
that you were lifting weights, which let's say you're doing that three or four times a week,
you would presumably want to take it daily. Take that five grams daily, correct?
Yeah. I mean, I think on the whole, although you could say that it might be better if you take it
after exercise with a carbohydrate bolus, it might be better if you split it up into two doses.
On the whole, if you just take it every day and you take five grams a day and you just always do
that, you're eventually going to get to the... Yeah, you'll hit that steady state. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah. It's something to take daily if you're doing that, but let's steer away from the person who
doesn't care at all about creatine supplementation. They're not even thinking of that. What I'm
thinking about is what would you want to do in an NR study to show that you're not impacting
methylation? So I expect that sometime rather soon, we're going to see a paper coming out
showing that it doesn't elevate homocysteine and showing that it doesn't affect the
acidenosyl methionine in plasma. And my position is not that this stuff is really dangerous.
That's not my position at all. However, I've been exposed to anecdotes of people who are taking this
who experienced things that were really seesawing in their energy levels and were really seesawing
in their mental and emotional states that are anecdotes that could be explained by a
thousand other things. But to me make it sound like, geez, this thing is really sapping the
methyl group supply. It's exactly what I would expect to happen in someone whose methyl group
supply is being set. And would that person be better off supplementing with choline or creatine
if they were going to pick? I would say take a lower dose of this stuff and match it with
a methyl donor. Yeah, in theory, you could do creatine. You'd have to test it, right? But my
recommendation, I actually put out the recommendation. I made a video about this. I said-
We'll link to it.
I said match at milligram for milligram with TMG, trimethylglycine.
Oh, that reminds me. I want to tell you about this anecdote. So we've got a patient who
you just couldn't get his homocysteine to budge. So on our lab scale below nine or less is what
would be normal. He's in the 13, 14, 15 region. On your standard dose of methyl folic, methyl B12,
nothing. Even doubling it, which always makes me a little uncomfortable, nothing. Adding 50
milligrams of B6 three times a week, which strikes me as overkill, nothing. Going to B6, 50 milligrams
daily, nothing. Add TMG, boom. Homocysteine falls by 50%. What was going on in this guy?
Okay. So the fact that you added B6 and it did nothing indicates one of two things. Either
that guy's enzyme for getting rid of the homocysteine didn't work that well, or more probably,
this was not a fed state homocysteine issue, right? So the way these things work is you're trying to
use MTHFR or choline to remethylate homocysteine when you're in the fasted state and you don't
have a lot of methionine coming in. You stop doing that entirely and you start trying to
break down the homocysteine, getting rid of it when you're in the fed state.
So we don't know the flux. We didn't have the video. We just had a bunch of snapshots of this
guy's homocysteine. My guess is that unlike the guy whose homocysteine went down with the B6,
this guy, he had a recycling issue. He did not have a problem of disposing of the homocysteine
in the fed state. He had a problem of recycling in the fasted state. He just couldn't do it.
And he couldn't do it because his MTHFR just didn't work very well. And so only when you
added the trimethylglycine, which is the choline pathway. So when you use choline for methylation,
what you do is you convert it into trimethylglycine and that becomes the methyl donor that's the
alternative. I mean, it makes me wonder now if we just supplemented more choline, if we could
have got the same result. Yeah, I'm sure you could have gotten the same result. The only
possibility that would prevent that would be if he had a problem with the enzyme that oxidizes
choline to trimethylglycine. I like that it all comes back to choline. We have four chickens
at home and my kids named them. So they have the funniest names that two of them have pretty normal
names. There's Sarah is one of them and Bang Bang and Go Go. You can almost tell which of my kids
named them. I feel like Sarah would feel left out. Yeah, exactly. So little Bang Bang and Go Go and
Sarah. Now I'm embarrassed to admit on the spot, I forgot the name of the fourth chicken, but it's
a totally normal name that's not funny because my daughter named Sarah and the normal one on my
guy. But now I feel like even more indebted to these little guys. I mean, I've always loved
eggs. And of course, once you eat eggs that are like coming from the chickens that you're feeding,
the leftover vegetables on your table, like the yolks are so yellow, the eggs taste so good.
It's very interesting to see this connection between choline, creatine, methylation. I mean,
this is complicated stuff. And of course, the skeptic will take a step back and say,
well, Chris, what if you're just fixing a bunch of numbers? Like, yeah, you can make
homocysteine go down and yeah, you can do this and you can do that outside of the naffoldy,
which there's no disputing. If you fix naffoldy, you've improved a person's life.
Does it matter if homocysteine goes down? Does it matter if you're at six instead of 14 because
you've optimized these things? I don't think we're going to. Ginger, by the way, it's Sarah,
ginger, bang, bang, go, go, or our chick. Yeah, I would still feel left out of us. Yeah.
Yeah. No, it's okay. So to the skeptic, no, I don't think the argument is super, super strong
that by fixing a homocysteine, you're reducing cardiovascular risk. That's definitely not an
airtight argument. I look at homocysteine and I say, well, look, young, healthy people have
a homocysteine on average between seven and nine. That's probably the sweet spot. But yeah, I mean,
if I were looking at that from the perspective of what is the least stuff I can do, unless I am
very compelled by the data to do it, then I would throw out at least everything that I just said,
except the choline. And depending on how hard of a skeptic I am, I'd probably throw out the choline
too. And that's because this comes down to a philosophical question of what is the level of
evidence that you need to take an action. Versus the level of evidence to not take an action,
which people always forget that they have to ask that question just as well. Well, also versus the
level of evidence to state that you have a certain degree of certainty or confidence in something.
So the thing is, I think that we can be fairly, we will debate it, but I think we can be fairly
rational and within a fairly narrow window on what do we believe are the principles
that we need to secure to say we have a certain degree of confidence that something is true.
But we can never create that window for saying, what is the level of evidence that I need in order
to take an action, because that comes back to your subjective values. A lot of this is assumption as
well. Even if you're coming to the question of what is the probability that we should assess that
something is true. For me, I would take as a background assumption that things that have
a proven track record in human history over a long period of time should be assumed as a default.
Someone else may take the assumption that nothing is the default or that the status quo is the
default. So if you're basically saying that we have to have meta analysis of randomized,
of large randomized controlled trials on clinical endpoints in order to have something,
you are assuming that in the absence of that evidence, we will follow the status quo.
So even in the case of us debating how confident we are that something is true, we have reasons
like that to have a spectrum of agreement or disagreement. But when it comes down to,
should I take this supplement, that comes to like subjective value over what kind of risks
do you want to take? So look, there are some people that want to optimize their metabolism
to make their body run like a well-oiled machine the best way that they know how,
and they're willing to spend some money or design their diet around doing so. And I think most of
what I said mostly applies to those people. I think for people who are looking for hard
clinical endpoints, in fact, this is why there's Twitter wars over MTHFR sometimes, which is that
they're really... Oh, thank God I missed those. So yeah, so I've gotten into some tussles on the
internet with some people who looked at this from the perspective of, look, there's no hard clinical
endpoints for which MTHFR is diagnostic. There's no hard clinical endpoints for which people with
MTHFR for whom that population has some specific dietary or supplemental regimen that alters that
clinical endpoint. And I think that's true. Where I come from, if I were in that situation,
I would want to bring my homocysteine down to what by all probability appears to be the healthy level.
If I were that person, I would want to reason, well, I feel like my mind is too sticky and I
want to loosen it up a little bit. If I were that person, I would want to have good energy, and I
would want to use a rational assessment of why my energy might be low and what I can do to bring
it up to normal. And I'm probably never going to convince anyone that if I feel better, that
there's a hard testable clinical endpoint to that. Let's come back to the NR. I did a...
I was just about to say, the one thing I really want to ask you about is in all of this stuff,
whether it's the increased choline, the glycine, the creatine, I think I get the sense where you,
on your own personal spectrum of risk, fall on those. I haven't actually got a sense of where
you fall on the NR spectrum. Personally? Yeah. Oh, well, if it helps clarify, I took 75 micrograms
of it with breakfast and 75 micrograms with lunch. Micrograms? Miligrams, sorry. Which is still
pretty low. I mean, that's much lower than what's provided in those supplements. Right. I got 150
milligram capsules that I had broken half. Okay. So that's much less than what's being provided
in basis and true nitrogen, right? Yeah, I might go up. I'm just playing around with it. It's just
a tinkering thing. With or without a sirtuin activator? Yeah, it's the true nitrogen. There's
no terrestil being in it. I was studying it a lot, so I figured, let me take it and see what happens.
Which, by the way, to me, is one of the most tried and true interesting ways to do science is to...
You have to become a little bit of a self-experimenter on this stuff. Well, H. Pylori.
Yeah, everybody loves to point to that example. I will say this anecdotally, for the patients of
mine who do religiously take one of those two products, Basis or true nitrogen, the one thing
that seems to, across the board, improve, and it would be very difficult to attribute this
to placebo, is patients who have even an inkling of rosacea seem to have a monumental improvement.
And again, I don't know if that has to do with the skin. You know, we were talking about the skin
again, but... Is it sun sensitive? Rosacea often is, but I don't know if I can say across the board
if each of those patients has rosacea. No, I wouldn't say it's exclusively sun sensitive,
right? So some people, their rosacea gets amplified by certain things in their diet. I have some
patients, when they eat chocolate, it goes off the rails, or alcohol, or stress, or sleep deprivation.
So no, I would say there could be multiple different triggers for it. And I remember once
even looking it up and finding sort of an old esoteric paper about topical niacin, I believe,
I think it was in the form of niacin that could improve rosacea. I said before, I think that the
skin is one of the areas where I would expect to see fast results. And so it's this question of how
do you design, how do you pick the right people and design the right study to see an effect like that?
And so that's interesting. Maybe a rosacea endpoint in a clinical study would have good results to it.
Yeah, but what I'm basically taking away from you is IV NAD is not a great idea. Just on the
principles we've described, that does not seem to be the way you want to administer it. It's much
better to build up a hepatic reservoir of nicotinamide that's converted through the NR,
that you can then slow trickle into circulation as needed is probably a better bet.
Yeah, I mean, I would consider it fascinating to see studies of what is actually happening
physiologically when people inject it, but nothing about it. But outside of that granulocyte
response, which some people take that to mean it's doing great things like, look at how shitty
I feel this must be doing something right. I've always taken that to mean, I don't know. That's
why Mercury was so successful back in the day. Yeah, I mean, it makes no physiological sense,
but yeah, I mean, a study could prove me wrong, but there are no studies and it makes them
physiological sense. But I want to come back to one little point on the decision making thing.
So the nicotinamide riboside video that I made, it took an anecdote of someone who posted on my
Facebook on something else that I was doing and told like a four paragraph story about how she
started taking the true nitrogen and she felt great for a couple of weeks, but then she started
feeling the energy sapping off and then dropping. And then she felt like going through a mental
roller coaster. And I used this anecdote that obviously could have other explanations and
clearly has no clinical measurable endpoint. And I got people just came out of the woodwork.
Meaning pissed off. Yeah, troll it like in the YouTube comments.
YouTube comments should be never read. But no, but I think listen, this is I think this is
an interesting contrast anecdote. So here there are people often pointing out that there's no
hard data in that story who are saying all kinds of great things about the way they feel when they
take a lot of this stuff, not realizing the hour. So not. Yeah. So I think it's irony, but it's it
also comes back to the point where look, people are going to make a decision to take this or not.
And there is no clear data on what it does. And so you either take the position that you're going
to wait 10 or 20 years until we know something better or you take the position that you're going
to tinker. And if you're going to tinker, you're going to tinker a lot more successfully if you
have a working model of what's going on than if you don't. Yeah. I mean, I think it comes down to,
and it would be impossible for me to say I don't subscribe to that ethos because I mean, look,
I take Rapa Mison for heaven's sakes. And if you want to talk about a much bigger hammer, I mean,
Rapa would probably be the single most out there thing that I do. But my model is robust. Now,
I also think I have much more data to point to. So even though people could say, well,
oh my God, Rapa Mison is so scary. I get the point to what happens in the yeast, the flies,
the worms, the mice, the rats, the dogs, the kangaroos, the human. So I feel like I'm standing
on the shoulder of much more evidence, even though I'm interfering with a much more important
sensor. I'm actually going after the God sensor, like the single most important nutrient sensor
in our body. But at the same time, you know, you don't feel anything, right? So what's interesting
is if you're taking nicotinamide riboside for a way you feel, it's very confusing because I don't
see how one can disentangle the placebo effect. I mean, I have, I think this has become something
that has come to the public's consciousness much more. I mean, even the New York Times wrote a
piece on this several months ago, which is the power of the placebo effect. And I've even spoken
with PIs who have run studies using psychoactive agents and you'd think, how could you placebo your
way out of that? And yet they've told me that the placebo effect in terms of the post depression you
would get with certain psychoactives is actually greater in the placebo group than the treatment
group. So I just don't know that I trust myself to discriminate between something that works or
doesn't work based on how I feel. I'd almost prefer to experiment with compounds where I'm
just pointing to biochemistry and, you know, hopefully in time some biochemical proxies.
Of course, with rapamycin, we don't have a great biochemical proxy. We can't measure autophagy. We
can't count our senescent cells. You know, we can't look at inflammation within our muscles, things
that we believe would be improving. But I just don't like the idea of having to rely on how I
feel solely. I mean, look, if you feel like crap, that's a reason whether it's placebo or not,
that's reason to stop. Yeah. Or if you feel like crap and then you take something that makes you
feel great, that's placebo leverage it. Yeah. Although again, look, I mean, you could argue that
taking heroin will transiently make you feel pretty good too. And it's sort of a dumb example
because it's so over the top. But so Peter Thiel has this great question that he poses in,
if he posed it in the book, you know, Zero to One, or he certainly talked about this, which is,
what's the important truth that very few people would agree with you on? So something that you
think is definitively the case or probabilistically very likely to be certain that you would find very
few people to agree with you on. And this doesn't have to be just limited to what we talked about
today. This could be anything. Should it be limited to health and medicine? No. Okay. Then
I think that's easy. The thing that I believe strongly about that the largest number would
people would think I was crazy for would probably be that I'm twice the libertarian of your
libertarian uncle. I don't know. I think you'd find a lot of people that more and more now are
losing faith in big government and would probably come to your aid on that. Maybe not. I believe
there would be a few hundred. Yeah. You're that extreme in your libertarian views. All right. Well,
then it's appropriate. I've phrased this question through the lens of Peter. What about within the
world of biochemistry medicine, et cetera? So I think it's a very population specific thing. So
for me, I believe certain things in the alternative health sphere that I think I'm surrounded by
people that disagree with me on. And I spend a lot of time there that other people in the
conventional sphere might think I'm totally right for advice. For example. So as an example,
in the alternative health sphere, it is almost by the way, am I in the alternative health sphere
or not? I don't know where I live. Probably. Yeah. Wow. It's a, so I think alternative medicine,
it doesn't really have a clear definition. Like the NIH has an arm of alternative medicine,
but alternative medicine is basically the stuff that's not standard practice. And then when it
becomes standard practice, it's not alternative anymore. Okay. Fair enough. So by one definition,
you could kind of encompass everyone who's doing something progressive or on the edge or whatever.
I mean, to the extent we would disagree with that, I would probably just modify my
definition here. But so I find myself in the nutrition sphere, I find myself among many
people who would throw out the RDAs, for example. So I would say people in nutrition that they're
not RDAs, they're fairly progressive or they're fairly alternative or they're into supplementation
or whatever, probably think that the RDAs are trash science. And I think that the RDAs are
actually super good science. They're often outdated. They're often limited by the fact that
if you are a committee who's producing a report that someone else is going to simplify onto a
four inch square on the side of the boxes of the cereal, that everyone in the 300 million Americans
are going to just look at the number and make some assumptions about that. You have to be a lot more
careful about what you say. But I think that we really throw the baby out with the bathwater if
we don't look at what's been done by the people who are hardcore conventionals.
This is your history coming back to you, right? Your appreciation for the history of how these things
came about. Yeah. I mean, it's not just history. I mean, for right now, one of the first things
that I did when I started researching Niacin was I read the DRI report for Niacin, which was in 1998.
There's a lot that you could say to criticize it. But I think that wherever you are in controversy,
that you really have to know the core of what constitutes the conventional belief.
Just look at my Twitter feed over the last few days, I'm in an environment where
many people are convinced about the carbohydrate hypothesis of obesity. And in fact, one of the
interesting things about me is that I think I found myself very friendly with people in the
low carb community because of things that I think are crazy in the conventional community
that we agree on. So for example, I think the history of the dietary guidelines and the
demonization of saturated fat and cholesterol in the diet is completely wrong. And I've done a lot
on that to the point where I think probably both of us for the amount of eggs that we consume,
there is a very large number of colleagues of ours who might think that we're crazy.
And let's take the example of the carbohydrate hypothesis of obesity. So I went into graduate
school thinking that insulin was the cause of obesity and that you couldn't store fats in
adipose tissue unless you had glucose there available and kind of all these things. And I
also went in thinking that the chain of causality was from metabolic problems to obesity. I couldn't
figure out why on earth my professors seem to think that the causal chain was opposite
and that obesity was causing metabolic dysfunction. I think I've come to really believe that the
conventional view of obesity being a cause of metabolic dysfunction is true. And that puts me
square in the middle of conventional theory on a lot of metrics. And because of the environment
that I've put myself in with the people that I'm friends with and colleagues with, in that
particular environment, I think it's a truth that a lot of people find me crazy for.
Yeah, that's interesting. I mean, yeah, I've never really thought about where I said,
I mean, you know, so my view is that obesity is actually largely a compensatory response
for something metabolic. So that's the opposite view of you, I think, if I'm understanding you
correctly. But it's also hard to neatly fit these views into a box. I mean, because you're always
going to find a patient that's an exception to your rule, but that's a whole separate story.
There's a lot more I'd like to go into, but we have been at this for about three hours.
So we might just have to do around two at some point in the interim. What is the best place for
people to find you? I know you're pretty active on social media. How do you like to engage?
So my website is chrismasterjohnphd.com. Everything I do is posted there. I'm on Facebook,
Twitter, Instagram, and YouTube are the main places to find me. Twitter is a good place.
And your handle is?
Chris, at Chris Masterjohn on all of those.
Yeah.
But not Chris Masterjohn PhD. That's only your website.
Yeah, I would have made it chrismasterjohn.com. But when I decided to buy it, there was someone
who bought it years ago and was selling the domain name for like $50,000 or something. And I said,
I'll just add the PhD.
That's why mine has MD, by the way.
Yeah, yeah.
I didn't want to pay for the regular one. A lot of the stuff we've talked about, this will be
some pretty robust show notes because we've got to, there's so much stuff to link to. As you pointed
out, so many of these things are not as difficult to, I don't want to say easy, but they're not as
difficult to understand when you can see the diagrams.
Yeah, for sure.
You've done some really elegant videos on a number of these topics, which we'll link to.
And I just want to thank you for being here, man.
Yeah, thank you for having me. It was great.
How was that Topo Chico, by the way? That was your first.
It was great. It has a slight taste of beer to me.
Interesting.
I promise I didn't spike it, so I'm glad. Whenever I can give someone their first Topo Chico,
it is such a feeling of gratification. So I'm really glad.
Thank you so much.
All right, man.
You can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast. There,
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at peteratiamd.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame
once a week email, where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID peteratiamd,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical
condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such
conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For
all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about.