Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hey, everybody.
Welcome to this week's episode of The Drive.
I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads on this podcast
and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support.
If you're listening to this, you probably already know.
The two things I care most about professionally are how to live longer and how to live better.
I have a complete fascination and obsession with this topic.
I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is basically
all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives.
Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy.
And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to me.
The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming.
I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information
with you.
To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own.
In fact, we now have a full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and the feedback
has mirrored this.
So all of this raises a natural question.
How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this?
As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads.
But after a lot of contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons.
Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you can trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being
paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it.
Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself.
I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for.
So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically.
So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can
work over time, and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest.
If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and support us at whatever level
works for you.
In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free.
It's that simple.
It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will
get back more than you give.
So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes, including
other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each episode.
These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many
of our shows.
Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me Anything
episodes.
That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to hear these
podcasts when they come out.
Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about, I want my supporters to get the best
deals possible on the products that I love.
And as I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to
do is work with companies who make the products that I already love and would already talk
about for free and have them pass savings on to you.
Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will find
enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for
members to support us at a level that makes sense for you.
I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen to this.
If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us directly
by signing up for a monthly subscription.
Welcome to the kickoff of this Matthew Walker three-part series on sleep.
This is one of the topics we are asked about the most, and I think this will be a fan favorite.
This series of podcasts will be released over three weeks with this one being the first.
Now at the end of the series, we're going to take questions for a follow-up AMA with
Matthew.
Asking questions on the AMA forum and listening to the AMA podcast with Matthew, along with
all AMAs, will only be available to subscribers.
If you haven't signed up yet, you can do so now at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe.
My guest this week is Matthew Walker, professor of neuroscience and psychology at the University
of California, Berkeley, and the founder and director of the Center for Human Sleep Science.
Matthew earned his undergraduate degree and PhD in neurophysiology in London and subsequently
became a professor of psychiatry at Harvard Medical School before moving to Berkeley.
His research examines the impact of sleep on human brain function in healthy and diseased
populations.
To date, he has published over a hundred scientific studies.
He has received numerous funding awards from the National Science Foundation, National
Institutes of Health, and he's a fellow with the National Academy of Sciences.
He's the author of the international bestseller, Why We Sleep, which also happens to be the
favorite book of my not yet two-year-old son.
He holds many patents covering various consumer-based sleep recordings, sleep tracking, and sleep
simulation.
He's a sleep scientist at Google where he helps the scientific exploration of sleep
in health and disease.
He is also an enormous fan of Formula One and my hero, Ira Tonsena.
In the third part of this installment, we actually spend quite a bit of time discussing
this.
Here in the first part of this series, we discuss the relationship between sleep, dementia,
and Alzheimer's disease, the four pillars of sleep, sleep stages, measurements, and
the overall importance of sleep, the lack of sleep and dangers of drowsy driving, and
how the conversation of sleep has changed over the past several years.
Without further delay, here is the first installment of my three-part series with Professor Matthew
Walker.
Hey, Matt.
Thank you so much for making time to meet on a Sunday.
Absolute privilege and a delight to be with you, Peter.
What's with the weather in Berkeley?
Is it always this bad?
Now, when Peter says, is it always this bad, it's probably in the low 60s and there isn't
much blue sky.
It's dry and there's a very pleasant breeze and there is some wonderful blossom.
I know it's not San Diego.
Everything is utopian and people are singing Come By R at the end of the day and holding
hands, but it's a pretty good day when you consider it's still February.
Right, right.
I know.
It's like I live in these extremes.
In San Diego, the bar is like it has to be perfect.
Then in New York, you just sort of expect it to be sort of like I was there two days
ago and it stunk.
I mean, all three of those are best than the United Kingdom.
My home country where essentially you have nine months of really bad weather and then
three months of winter and then that's your year.
This day, February, like this low 60s, I'm a happy man.
I came from Canada where it's bad in a different way, but the first time I saw California was
my interview for med school and it was a February day and it was 76 degrees.
That was the first time it occurred to me that you didn't have to suffer.
I never realized.
I mean, I guess intellectually I understood that it could be warm in the winter, but it
never occurred to me that you could choose to do that.
So well, now speaking of this, so what brought you to the US?
It was science.
I did all of my education back in United Kingdom.
I actually started off at medical school.
So back in the UK at aged 18, you can actually go to medical school.
It's a five year program.
And after about two years, this wonderful professor came up and said, look, you're a
nice guy, but you're always asking questions and you're asking them.
I think genuinely you're not asking them to be an ass, but I think you're actually a scientist,
not a doctor, because at the time, you know, he was thinking doctors are interested in
answers.
Scientists are interested in questions.
I think you're a scientist, not a doctor.
So we didn't have MD PhD programs back at that time.
So then, you know, I thought about it for the summer, came back, switched to neuroscience.
So essentially brain science did that as an undergraduate, then went on to do my PhD
at the medical research council in London and then came to Harvard for my first faculty
position there.
And I was there for seven years as faculty in psychiatry at Harvard.
And the winters just got to me and, you know, the environment at times as well, academic
was perhaps more combative and competitive.
And I think that's one way to breed productivity in a department.
And I'm not shaking a finger at it, but by nature, I'm just a person who is much more
collaborative and collegial rather than combative and competitive.
So Berkeley fit my mentality better, came out here, weather was great.
California, it's an immense, the easy place to arrive and a very difficult place to leave.
And I think I probably won't.
I know that feeling.
I'm probably leaving California.
I'm going through the morning process of accepting the departure because you're right.
You'll be back.
It's a hard place to leave.
When did the switch sort of flip in terms of your passion for sleep?
I think back at medical school, I was always interested in states of consciousness.
I guess you would describe it as I was fascinated by anesthesia, was fascinated by even hypnosis.
I remember I actually went out to meet this hypnotist to try and understand not, you know,
the act and the show.
I wasn't interested in that.
I fundamentally wanted to understand what did he think happened within the brain to
produce this altered state of consciousness.
So I got really interested in how the brain can switch between sort of states, mental
states and then just fundamental awareness states.
That then naturally led me to just become fascinated by sleep.
I mean, there is no better demonstration of a gigantic shift in conscious state that happens
to almost every single living creature on this planet every 24 hours.
And back then, this was 20 years ago, we had this fundamental question.
Why do we sleep?
And what was staggering to me is that it took a third of our lives.
Every species that we've studied today does it sleeps.
It seems to have evolved with life itself on this planet.
Even more, we've understood the functions of the other main biological drives, eating,
drinking and procreating for tens, if not hundreds of years.
But the fourth main biological drive, the drive to sleep had continued to elude scientific
judgment.
How was that possible?
And back then, 20 years ago, if someone were to ask you, you know, why do we sleep?
The crass answer was we sleep to cure sleepiness.
And that's the fatuous equivalent of saying, well, we eat to cure hunger.
Well, that tells you nothing about the fundamental nutritional benefits of macro nutrition.
But that's where we were at with sleep.
So it was for me, this perfect collision of a fascination in an innate biological problem
and universal behavior conserved across evolution, together with the fact that we did it for
a third of our lives.
Plus the fact that science had not been able to crack this, this nut.
It was one of the last great remaining scientific mysteries.
I thought, well, you know, if you want to pick something that's going to sustain you
for the rest of your life and some of the most acerbic, brilliant minds in science had
tried to crack this nut and failed, including Francis Crick, wonderful scientist who discovered
the helical structure of DNA.
It's unlikely I'm going to do it in my lifetime, but at least it will sustain me as a scientist.
That's a problem.
And I could not let it go.
And so that was where the intellectual bite happened.
The data, the empirical scientific bite happened when I was doing my PhD.
I was studying brainwave patterns in people with dementia and I was trying to do differential
diagnosis very early on in the course of cognitive decline, seeing which type of dementia did
they have.
Was it frontal lobe dementia?
Was it Lewy body dementia?
Was it Alzheimer's dementia?
And I was failing miserably for two years.
I was getting nothing.
I used to go home.
I was living in this doctor's residence and I had this sort of in the middle of my room,
this little igloo of journals that used to sit in on a Sunday, just this kind of like
sort of sanctified circle of knowledge.
And I was reading one Sunday and I realized that the different pathologies in these different
dementias, some would hit the sleep centers and others would leave those sleep centers
completely untouched.
Even within forms of dementia that clinically presented very similarly.
That's right.
Yeah.
You could see certain brainstem nuclei, certain centers within the basic base of the brain.
Some of those were getting eroded by the dementia and those are sleep generating centers.
Whilst in other of those pathologies, those centers were spurred until very late in the
disorder.
So they probably weren't affecting my early patients.
So I realized I was measuring their brainwave activity at the wrong time.
I was measuring my patients whilst they were awake.
What I should have been doing is measuring them whilst they were asleep, got a small
grant, set up a sleep lab, learned how to do it, got some great results.
And then the question became, if the sleep is so disrupted, is it not just a symptom
of dementia?
Could sleep disruption actually be a biomarker of dementia?
Could it actually foretell when you were going to develop dementia and which type or
even more profound is sleep disruption an underlying cause of Alzheimer's disease?
And I think right now, based on the weight of the data that we have, and we and others
have got large research programs doing this work, the evidence I think is causal.
I think that sleep at this stage may be one of the most significant lifestyle factors,
at least that determines your risk ratio for Alzheimer's disease.
I feel the causal evidence for that now in humans and animals is strong enough to make
that statement.
And I don't make that statement lightly.
Yeah, that is profound because when you think about the other really big ones, vascular
disease and insulin resistance, they both feed into a very similar mechanism, which
is neuronal energy deprivation.
That's right.
So do you think that sleep disruption or poor sleep, and I want to come back to the semantics
around that because I don't actually think I'm well equipped to talk about this intelligently,
but do you think that that also disrupts some aspect of energy metabolism in the brain or
where in the sort of chain of events do you think that that impacts?
I think one of the places that it impacts is in oxidative stress.
I think it's safe to say that wakefulness is low level brain damage and we need sleep
to avert some of that low level brain damage.
Sleep is the price that we pay for wakefulness, essentially.
And something I mentioned in a book that I put out was, and I got a little.
Just a little book, just a little, just a little New York Times bestseller.
Which by the way, before we're done, I brought my copy because my youngest son, who's named
after our mutual favorite race car driver, loves moons.
It's all he thinks about, moons, moons, his pajamas, moons, everything.
And he loves your book except for the fact that on the inside there are no pictures of
moons.
So he'll sit there and he'll look at the cover and he'll go, moo, moo, moo.
And then he flips through it and he gets so frustrated that there's no moon pictures inside.
I will course correct that if there's a second edition and I will just try to place the words
underneath that it is for the benefit of Ierten.
But in the book, you know, I proposed that we didn't evolve sleep, that perhaps we've
got it the wrong way round.
Perhaps the default state of life on the planet was sleep and it was from sleep that wakefulness
emerged.
Wow.
Why could it not have been that way?
Now I don't have any good evidence to support my hypothesis.
I think it could be utter nonsense, but I think it's a tenable hypothesis.
It's just one that's difficult to test.
But to come back to your question about Alzheimer's, which I think is critical, I think the first
thing is that we see that with insufficient sleep, you get increases in oxidative stress.
Those oxidative stress processes lead to a whole cascade of kind of a finger flick domino
effect of things that lead to neuronal death.
One of the areas in the brain that is most sensitive to that is an area that we call
the hippocampus, which is a critical memory center.
It's probably one of the first structures to undergo damage in Alzheimer's disease.
It's part of the reason why the sort of the phenotype of Alzheimer's is forgetfulness
problems with memory.
I think perhaps the stronger evidence though, in terms of sleep and Alzheimer's disease
risk is a remarkable discovery that was made probably about five or six years ago now by
some folks at Rochester University in rats.
What they discovered is that the brain actually has a sewage system inside of it.
Now your body has one that you're all familiar with called the lymphatic system, but it turns
out the brain has one.
It's called the glymphatic system named after the cells in the brain that form this system
called the glial cells, also known by sort of from a Greek derivative meaning glue.
So they used to be just thought as the sort of the cell.
The sort of irrelevant stuff between the neurons.
Exactly.
It was like junk DNA.
And of course what we always learn is that mother nature is far too efficient to leave
inefficiency on the table like glue or junk.
And it turns out they form this sanitization system within the brain.
And what happens they discovered is that when you go into deep sleep at night, this
sewage system kicks into high gear and essentially those glial cells which surround the brain
cells themselves, the neurons proper, they shrink in size by up to 200%.
And then all of a sudden it leaves a vast amount of room for cerebrospinal fluid to
start perfusing the brain and washing out the metabolic detritus of wakefulness.
So it would be like New York City at night, all of the buildings shrunk down to 200%.
You know, they became miniaturized.
And then there was this big effluent flush that just happened across Manhattan to clear
out all the debris.
And it's essentially good night, sleep clean, that you get this power cleanse at night.
Why is this related to Alzheimer's?
Well, one of the critical ingredients that they found that the glymphatic system washed
away was a sticky toxic protein called beta amyloid.
Beta amyloid is probably one of the two core proteins that we know underlie your risk for
the development of Alzheimer's.
Ergo, if you're not getting your sleep at night, you're not getting that washing away
of the toxic Alzheimer's protein.
Every night then you are building up more amyloid within the brain.
If you keep doing that night after night, it's like compounding interest on a loan.
It's just escalating your Alzheimer's risk.
That's why we can then explain the associational evidence, which I don't like associational
evidence in epidemiological studies.
And I don't think you're a huge fan of it, perhaps either.
Just don't tell anybody at the Harvard School of Public Health.
Yeah.
Or maybe the NIH and I were applying for grants for epidemiological studies.
What we certainly see is that if you bucket people into the amount of sleep on average
that they've got across the lifespan and at the end of the sort of life or in late life
in their seventies and their eighties, we do a special type of PET scan to map the amount
of amyloid in their brain.
And then you just sort of look at those brain scans.
Anyone on the street would not need any statistics.
They would not need any training in brain science to see that one of these maps is different
to the other.
It's on Sesame Street.
And what is remarkable is people are getting seven hours of sleep or less compared to seven
hours of sleep or more.
There is marked differences in the amount of amyloid that's built up.
Now that's just associational evidence.
But then when you take it down to the level of animal studies where they selectively deprive
animals of either deep non-REM sleep or they fragment their sleep, you get an immediate
amyloid buildup.
Essentially within the brain, you start to have what looks like a sort of, you know,
an amyloid sort of genetic process that's happening.
That's rats.
So then we can all wave our hands if we want because we would like to beat our chests and
sort of, you know, say, I don't need my sleep.
And that's just rat stuff.
Well, the studies have now been done in humans where we will take a human being and for one
single night, we will take away the deep sleep.
And the way that you do that is that you just play these auditory tones at night.
So they never wake up.
So the total amount of sleep that they get is still eight hours, but I can just selectively
excise your deep sleep when that that sewage system should be kicking into gear.
And then the next day we do something that's really rather unpleasant.
We do a spinal cord puncture and we suck out some cerebrospinal fluid and we can measure
the amount of the two toxic proteins linked to Alzheimer's.
One is called beta amyloid that we've discussed.
The other is called tau protein.
And we see the next day after one night of sleep disruption, a significant increase in
circulating levels of amyloid and tau.
For me, that was kind of like the turning point where I finally felt comfortable going
on record and saying, at this point, folks, I really feel comfortable saying that your
sleep is a critical component of your prevention of Alzheimer's disease.
I really think the evidence is now in that direction and way in that direction.
It's not just epidemiological.
It's not just prospective longitudinal studies, which are better than cross-sectional sort
of epidemiological.
It's not just causal in rats.
It's experimentally causal in humans after one night of sleep.
Do you see variation there?
Because one of the things that I find difficult with understanding all diseases and Alzheimer's
would be sort of more so than even cardiovascular disease because we still have so much less
data is there must clearly be enough variation between people that it's very easy at the
heterogeneous level to miss things that you would see in an otherwise homogeneous population.
For example, when you look at the coinage of the term Alzheimer's disease, it's quite
likely that that was coined based on a patient who probably had a PSN1 or 2 mutation.
Such an early onset of the disease versus the disease we typically see.
I mean, today, those patients make up less than 1%.
It's almost a different disease from the one.
These are people that are presenting in their 50s and they're usually dead before they're
60, whereas 99% of the population are getting a sort of later onset disease.
Within that population, all of the variation with ApoE genotype, it almost makes you wonder
if there's different susceptibilities to this deprivation because everybody and their brother
can point to the exceptions to these rules.
The person who did everything right slept like a baby every night and ends up down this
one path.
Then of course, the person who does everything incorrect and seems to be completely fine,
or at least from the perspective of no obvious disease.
Their analogy is really interesting because I don't really find myself hugely in the
amyloid beta camp as the main causal driver.
I think it's more of a result, but it's interesting.
What you posit is if it's more about the clearance of that than the generation of that, that
would be a congruent view with this idea that there could be other things on the back end
that are driving this primarily.
Of course, I think with Alzheimer's disease, it strikes me as just so complicated because
of the genetic predisposition coupled with the multiple pathways that can seem to drive
comparable insults to an otherwise incredibly sensitive organ.
I hugely cleave to the idea that probably what we call Alzheimer's right now is going
to be sub-typed at some point in the future that we'll have.
Imagine it's like cancer, where in 30 years, hopefully the rate of growth has slowed, that
it's not a pandemic, but you might have five sub-types or something for that.
That's right.
I think we will see that.
Then we will start to pattern match what features it.
I think the fact that sleep already, let's just call Alzheimer's disease this strange
heterogeneous mix right now that we feel uncomfortable about in terms of pinning one exact pathological
ingredient as the causal trigger for that.
In fact, I actually probably think tau is, if you look at the data, probably stronger
in terms of predicting cognitive decline at least than amyloid is.
The fact that we've now found that insufficient sleep will also lead to tau aggregation too,
I think is concerning and worrying.
Let's accept that this Alzheimer's thing, this disease state is heterogeneous.
The fact that sleep, and we can find such a strong predictive sleep signal in terms
of that risk, despite it being such a diffuse gray matter ball itself of a disease, must
mean that the links between insufficient sleep and this heterogeneous thing are, I think,
probably quite strong.
Otherwise, the dirtiness of the equation would be such that those associations would be far
weaker rather than stronger.
The fact that they're already present leads me to believe that when we do eventually subtype
Alzheimer's disease, we will then find that there are subsets of sleep features that are
deterministic of those subsets of Alzheimer's.
For example, deep sleep will be predictive of one form of Alzheimer's.
Sleep fragmentation, which is more about sleep quality than it is about physiological quantity.
Sleep fragmentation will be predictive of something else, another subtype of Alzheimer's
disease.
Then I think basic- Duration could matter.
I think there probably are four pillars of sleep.
There is probably regularity.
How consistent is your sleep schedule?
Are you undergoing what we call social jet lag, which is where you're bouncing around,
you're going to sleep at 1 a.m., then 10 p.m., and all over the map?
There's regularity.
There is the continuity of your sleep.
Is it fragmented?
Are you waking up many more times, or is it just nice one long shot?
That's a second feature.
I think the third feature is quantity, how much sleep you're getting, and how much of
the different stages are you getting.
Then independent of how regular your sleep is, how continuous your sleep is, and the
amount, the quantity, the final is quality.
Quality has become big in the last five years in the sleep field.
In other words, what is the electrical signature of your sleep?
Just because you're getting eight hours of sleep doesn't mean that you're getting eight
hours of good electrical quality deep sleep.
I hope that we get the chance to speak about things like caffeine and alcohol, other substances
of abuse that can make you feel like you're sleeping eight hours.
Quantity just fine.
Quality poor.
Come back to your question.
I love the way that you think about that problem, and I agree with it very much that Alzheimer's
disease is probably going to be heterogeneous.
I think the pathology already points to that and its complexity.
The way that sleep plugs into that heterogeneous disorder that we call Alzheimer's is also
going to be heterogeneous in nature.
Different sleep features will be predictive of different aspects of the amyloid pathology
cascade.
We just submitted a paper, which I'm going to blow now in terms of media outlet, which
hasn't been accepted yet.
We just tried to ask the question across someone's lifespan, if you bucket them into 10-year
decades and you ask, what was the quantity and quality of their sleep from their thirties
and forties, forties and fifties, fifties and sixties, so on and so forth.
Then at the end of their life, you stick them in a brain scanner and you map how much amyloid
is in the brain and how much tau is in the brain, which is what we can do here at the
sleep center.
Then you essentially can, in a retrospective manner, say, was sleep at certain times of
life more critical in predicting how much amyloid you will have late in life?
In other words, are there certain decades during an adult's lifespan where sleep is
even more important for determining your...
How can you do that retrospectively?
Let's say you had this cohort of patients.
Maybe at best you could, through questionnaires, infer duration, but how would you be able
to infer anything about depth or quality?
Depth we can't do, but quality we can do.
We've got a set of standardized questionnaires that have been essentially validated against
gold standard, what we call polysomnography, which essentially is sleep laboratory grade
recording with electrodes.
What we find is that those questionnaires have good predictive validity relative to objective
gold standard measures.
It's a hop, skip and a jump, but you can say, look, these subjective questionnaires seem
to go pretty well hand in hand with sleep quantity and quality.
Let's take those questionnaires and then let's ask of those patients what they were
doing in terms of their sleep quantity and quality in those different bucket decades
of their life.
It has all of the problems that you can imagine.
This seems like a slightly better version of a food frequency questionnaire, which your
peers would be relying on to do the same question about nutrition.
It's reliant on an individual.
It's got problems with history because the further you go back, does that signal of accuracy
degrade?
How big are the hazard ratios?
Because I guess this is where one of those things where if sleep could account for 25%
of this disease, or if it increased the risk by say 25% would be a better way to say that,
it strikes me as unlikely that you could see that signal because that's not a big enough
signal with all the noise you've just described.
But if you were talking about a hazard ratio of six or seven, or it's so funny today, one
of my kids asked me about smoking.
Why do people smoke?
I couldn't resist going down the Bradford Hill pathway.
Unfortunately he's four and a half, but he got a probably about a 12 minute lecture on
epidemiology and the hazard ratio of small cell lung cancer and smoking.
But the punchline in my story to him, Peter Attia, ladies and gentlemen, Peter Attia.
I was trying to explain to him what it would mean to have a 14X increase in risk, which
was basically what was observed in the first physician study of smoking.
The point there is that is such a massive signal that, I mean, as you describe it, I
love whenever you can get these things, that statistics aren't necessary.
When you don't need the P value to figure it out, that's it.
So does your intuition, and again, I don't want you to scoop what's already in this paper,
so if you can't speak about it, no problem.
But do you have a sense of that magnitude and therefore if even a crude backwards looking
metric is directionally pointing you at something that you think, wow, this isn't a subtle change?
Yeah, I mean, we're up in the region of from 0.45 to 0.6.
So it's-
In risk reduction for those doing it correctly?
Correct, yeah.
So it's substantial, but what was interesting to me, which gave me more confidence, was
that the windows of sleep sensitivity were, now by the way, across the entire lifespan,
if you're getting less sleep at almost any point in the lifespan, the risk that you're
going to have higher amounts of these Alzheimer's disease proteins in your brain is greater.
That's what we find across the board.
What's interesting is that when it comes to those two different proteins, amyloid and
tau, there are different decades that are predictive.
So if it's just one global subjective bias in your questionnaire, that you shouldn't
see that result.
So there is a sensitivity and specificity to these two different proteins that to me
got me more excited that it transcended some of the limitations that are inherent in this
approach and also the fact that for amyloid, you get a very strong predictive signal, you
know, thirties to forties and then again, sort of sixties to seventies.
And for tau, it's actually somewhere in sort of the starts in the fifties to sixties and
then goes through until the eighties.
So what about childhood?
So we actually, we didn't go back in terms of child, just because at that point it's
really difficult to feel confident about that data.
You'd have to get parents who are not living at that stage.
But to me, I think the fact that you've got these strange kind of hotspots across life.
And you have a, you described a bimodal distribution for amyloid beta.
Yeah.
Which then lends me to believe that that result is difficult to explain by sort of
just general memory biases, which would be kind of more of a linear approach.
But I don't, I mean, I think the point is that, you know, the evidence that continues
to build in favor of this story, that insufficient sleep is a significant lifestyle factor in
your deterministic ratio odds of developing Alzheimer's disease is ever stronger now.
And the fact that unlike many of the other lifestyle factors, the mechanism underlying
it has now been demonstrated causally in humans and adults.
And it's been done so acutely within a 24 hour period of time.
That to me just knocked me sideways.
And the controls did not have, so if you controlled for everything except the perturbation, you
didn't see the amyloid or tau rise in the controls.
Yeah.
And it's interesting too, because one of the reasons I've been a little less excited
about amyloid, there's two reasons.
One is what can only be, I think, described as just the abject failure of the pharmacologic
approach to amyloid reduction.
At our last counting, oh, I don't want to be misquoted on this.
We'll include it in the show notes, what the actual number is, but it's basically one amyloid
antibody quasi success at disease stabilization to the tune of 2000 failures.
That's one thing.
The second is the autopsy studies of people who died without any clinical evidence of
Alzheimer's disease who still have amyloid, making me wonder if amyloid is necessary but
not sufficient.
And therefore, what if there's something else going on?
And of course, the third thing I would now add just based on thinking about it for two
seconds, so this might not be well thought out is in the next couple of hours, we're
going to talk about a whole bunch of other things that sleep does that are in and of
themselves completely devastating to your health that also would feed into that, for
example, the impact that negative sleep has on cardiovascular disease.
And it's become quite clear that if you're doing bad things to your heart, you're doing
bad things to your brain.
And of course, we're going to talk about glucose disposal, hyperinsulinemia and all of
those things, which also have a clear impact.
So I think this would only strengthen the case that sleep deprivation is bad for you
and bad for your brain.
It to me makes it harder to tease out potentially the mechanistic links, although there's no
reason, as you said, that it can't be multifaceted.
Yeah.
And I think there are certainly those conundrums where you see patients with non-trivial
amounts of amyloid in the brain, let's say, at post-mortem who are even only in the early
stages of MCI of what we call mild cognitive impairment.
They haven't transitioned yet.
I'm glad you remember to explain these things because I'm nodding away like, of course,
I know what MCI is.
But that aside, I think the idea that it's necessary, maybe not sufficient, but necessary
if you truly don't want necessary in your life.
And if you're getting insufficient sleep, you're placing a necessary there where it
doesn't necessarily have to be.
No, the analogy could be with lipoproteins.
You know, there's a.
Oh, that's a very.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, lipoproteins are absolutely necessary, but not sufficient for atherosclerosis.
And so some people say, well, there's no efficacy in reducing lipoproteins.
And I think part of it is it's diffuse, right?
You're only attacking one of the four constitutive elements.
Four things have to happen for you to get atherosclerosis, the lipoproteins being one.
So that's actually an interesting idea.
And it's a great argument for why would you want something that's necessary,
but not sufficient there?
Why would you decrease your odds?
Yeah.
I mean, you know, think about it like this.
If your goal, the two most feared diseases in developed nations right now,
I believe are cancer and Alzheimer's disease.
And I would say it's in the other order.
And yeah.
And I think Alzheimer's is, you know, top of the list that
do you want to de-risk the probability of Alzheimer's disease in your life?
If you truly don't want to invite right to, you know, this thing called Alzheimer's disease
and invite it in, in the mail coming at you, but you're getting, you know,
less than seven hours of sleep a night, you're not working in the direction that you wish.
You're going against Alzheimer's disease prevention and you're working well towards
Alzheimer's invitation.
People will often say, you know, how much sleep do you get?
And I'll say, like, I give myself a non-negotiable eight hour sleep opportunity.
And that's not because I'm trying to practice what I preach.
I don't want to be some poster child for sleep.
If you understood what I knew about sleep and all cause mortality, as well as most disease
processes, you would realize that I'm being nothing short of utterly selfish in my preservation of
an eight hour sleep opportunity.
I don't want to die young and I don't want sickness and disease in my life.
My family, for example, has got a very strong history of cardiovascular disease.
And we know that deep sleep is probably the best form of blood pressure medication
that you could ever wish for.
That would be an easier one to study.
I'm guessing we'll come to that later.
Yeah.
The ability to perturb deep sleep and then see the change in blood pressure.
I think the point is, I think, bash people over the head with this sufficiently, but
the link between a lack of sleep and Alzheimer's now, I think, is very strong.
What I find though positive about that is, with Alzheimer's disease, just as you mentioned,
when it comes to pharmacological approaches, we just don't have anything that looks robust right
now.
So medicine in many ways, and especially for Alzheimer's disease, has started to shift from
a model of late stage treatment to early stage prevention.
And I think I feel very comfortable saying that one of the best preventative actions that you can
take on the basis of the science right now is start to capitalize on your sleep at night.
So let's shift gears just a little bit and go back to the polysom.
Let's explain to people, because we're going to eventually have to talk about
tracking these things.
And I want to bring up some of the commercially available ways that people do that, which
I think by definition are still not accurate enough for people to compare them to their
polysom.
But if I came into your lab tonight and I was willing to go to sleep there and you would
hook me up to an EEG, what are the different patterns of brainwaves and how would you
morphologically describe them and then bucket them by these stages you've already sort of
touched on a little bit as deep REM, deep REM, deep non-REM, et cetera?
Yeah, so upon falling asleep, human beings and in fact all mammals will experience two different
stages of sleep.
One of them is called non-rapid eye movement sleep.
The other is rapid eye movement sleep.
Non-REM sleep has been further subdivided into four separate stages, which are unimaginatively
called stages one through four.
Thank God.
Yeah, I know.
I think that's all that the sleep deprived people who are experimenting could come up
with at that time.
So increasing in their depth of sleep.
So stages three and four of non-REM sleep are the really deep restorative stages of sleep.
Stages one and two are the lighter stages of sleep.
And then on the other hand, we have rapid eye movement sleep or REM sleep, which is named
not after the popular Michael Stipe pop band, but because of these bizarre horizontal shuttling
eye movements that occur during this stage of sleep, these rapid eye movements.
So you have these two different types of sleep and they will essentially, as you fall asleep
here in at the sleep center at Berkeley, they will go into essentially a battle for brain
domination throughout the night.
And that cerebral war between non-REM and REM is going to be won and lost every 90 minutes
and then replayed every 90 minutes to create what we call a standard cycling architecture of sleep,
or what we call a hypnogram of sleep.
And so what you will see is that upon falling asleep, you'll go into the light stages of
non-REM, stages one and two.
Before we do that, let's say before I fall asleep, when I'm just laying in the bed,
how would you describe my brainwaves under the wakeful condition?
So at that point, what we typically see is that when you close your eyes,
the back of the brain goes into what's called an alpha rhythm.
So when you're awake, your brain shows this remarkably frenetic, high frequency electrical
activity. In other words, your brain is going in terms of its brainwaves, it's going up and down
many, many times a second. And the amplitude is very small,
which kind of is paradoxically you think, if I'm awake, then my brain is active.
And so the size of those brainwaves should be big. It's not, it's actually very small.
And here's the reason. Different parts of your brain are doing different things at different
times. So those brainwaves sort of are all canceling each other out.
So the analogy would be, if I were to dangle a microphone above a sports stadium,
what I'm picking up is the signal from the crowd of a hundred thousand individual neurons that sit
underneath it. That's how an EEG electrode is. Now, before the game starts, that's wakefulness.
And at that point, the hundred thousand people in the stadium, the hundred thousand brain cells,
they're all speaking to each other at different moments in time.
So there's a lot of cancellation.
So there's a lot of cancellation. They're not all coordinated,
but it's very fast and frenetic. So I just get this signal that is very desynchronized and
it's not synchronous. So they're not summing their power together. So the size of that brainwave is
not very big, but that's why the frequency is so high. The frequency is high, meaning that you're
sort of going up and down maybe 50, 60 times per second. Now, as you start to fall asleep or actually
even before you start to fall asleep, as you're lying in bed awake, the back of the brain is the
first part of the brain that really starts to settle down. It goes into what we call alpha rhythm
when you close your eyes. And I assume that's just because the occipital cortex is in the back and
you've closed your eyes. Brilliant. So the back of the brain, visual brain, if you close your eyes,
that part of the brain essentially stops processing the outside world and it goes into its
sort of default state when it's awake of slow frequency, it drops down from maybe 50 times per
second down to about, let's say 10 cycles per second. But still relatively low amplitude.
But still relatively low amplitude. Then once you start to actually transition, when you make that
bridge from the world of wakefulness to sleep, as you sort of cross through that window from one of
those worlds to the next, something bizarre happens. And if anyone out there is lucky enough
to be listening to this and they have a bed partner, you can actually see this. Just look at
their eyelids as they're falling asleep. And what you'll see is that their eyeballs start to roll in
their sockets and they're called slow rolling eye movements. Now we don't know why the eyes roll in
the sockets like that, but it's the first sign that you're making the transition from the world
of wakefulness into sleep. We use it as almost an indicator of the transition into sleep. Now,
by the way, if your partner wakes up, sometimes people will wake up from that state and they see
you just looking over them in bed, staring at their eyelids. If you're in early in a relationship,
it's usually the end of the relationship. It's just a point of note. Please don't blame me.
Usually wait till you're married and then start to do that one. The divorce usually is harder to
come by. So then you start to go down into the light stages of non-rem sleep, stages one and two.
Then after about 20 or so minutes, you'll go down deep into stages three and four.
And in one and two, have we transitioned out of that alpha wave? I mean, where do we start to see
the thetas and theta already happening in stage one? In stage two, you actually go into theater
activity, which is now down from 50 cycles per second, maybe down to just sort of six or seven
cycles per second. And the amplitude's getting a bit bigger. It is getting a bit bigger. Yeah. And
then every now and again during stage two, the way that I know that you're in this lighter stage of
non-rem sleep stage two is that you'll get these synchronous bursts of electrical activity that we
call sleep spindles. That's the K spindle. And that's sort of where you get this, actually you get
a nice big slow wave, like almost like a single slow wave. And then you get this burst of a sleep
spindle. And we actually did this great project here at the sleep center where we did the
sonification of sleep and we, we extracted brainwaves from human beings. And then we sort of,
you know, smooth them a little bit with some sort of audio software and then you can play them back.
And it's beautiful because when you hear these sleep spindles, they are these short,
synchronous bursts of electrical activity that last for about a second and a half.
And they go up to about 10 or 15 cycles per second. So it's almost like that beautiful rolling
R in sort of in the Hindi language, you know, sort of like a cat pairing. So, so you get these big
slow waves and then you get this ripple of a spindle. And when you hear it on the speakers,
it's just sensational. You get this, you know, it's, and it's every time I hear it. I mean,
this is spine tingling stuff. When you realize this is going on right now,
physiologically in someone's brain. And then from there, you start to go down to the really deep
stages of non-rung sleep stages, three and four. And at that point, the brain goes into this
incredible synchronous mantra chant of these slow waves. So the brain waves slow down,
you go down to maybe just one or two cycles per second, very, very slow brainwave activity,
but the size of those waves crashing on the beach of the cortex, as it were, they are huge. And the
reason is this go back to the sports stadium analogy. Let's say that we're here at Berkeley
and we're playing Stanford arch rivals. Yeah. Which hopefully you're going to kick their butt.
Fingers crossed. Just make sure there's no band anywhere to be found.
It always does. It's a terrible to say, but at that point they're chanting in unison.
They're all chanting in unison. So it's louder, but they're now making the same sound together.
And you can actually hear what's being said. Exactly. So now in that single microphone,
you can hear Stanford sucks, Stanford sucks. So all of a sudden, all of, for reasons that we
are only now starting to understand, the brain coordinates hundreds of thousands of neurons,
unlike it does at any moment elsewhere in the 24 hour period, hundreds of thousands of brain
cells all decide to join hands, as it were, physiologically, metaphorically, and they all
fire together. And then they all go silent. They all fire together. And then they all go.
And what I find amazing about that, by the way, is how slow that frequency is. You're basically,
you could be, this could be only happening once a second, right? That's right. And that's why it got
a terrible rap for 20 or 30 years, because it actually looked not dissimilar to some aspects
of coma. That's how slow those brainwaves were. So sleep scientists were, you know, understandably
fooled into thinking that deep sleep was a time when the brain essentially was just doing nothing.
Now we realize the exact opposite is true because it's during that deep sleep that you get
essentially information transfer within the brain. It's a file transfer mechanism. And the way to
think about this is let's say it's like long wave radio. If you're in the city, you tune into FM,
which is shortwave radio. You can pick up a bunch of signals and the further you drive out into the
desert, let's say here in California, you just lose those channels. Cause the range from the tower
is so short that you just lose that range. But if you go onto sort of, you know, the long wave radio
stations, you can still pick up stations for hundreds of miles. Why? Because the carrier
frequency of those radio waves is much slower. And so the distance over which you can transfer
information is much further. Deep sleep is a brain state of long distance information transfer.
Is there morphologically a difference that you can see between stages three and four, which are
obviously both Delta waves, but how do you distinguish those two?
Technically, no. The way it's defined is that what proportion of a 30 second period of time,
and that's the way that we score sleep. I'll have you sleep for eight hours, then I'll chop up that
eight hours into 30 second bits of information. And for each 30 seconds, you'll get a sleep score
and then we add them all up. And what differentiates stage three of deep non-rem sleep from the very
deepest stage, which is stage four non-rem sleep is simply what proportion of that 30 seconds
is consumed by that deep slow brainwave activity. If it's sort of less than 50 percent, then it's
stage three. If it's more than 50 percent, stage four. So morphologically no, although if you really
look at it morphologically, on average, yes, the waves are typically larger in amplitude and slower
in frequency in stage four than they are in stage three. And do people always progress
monotonically through these or do sometimes people go one, two, four, three, REM, for example?
No, you will have to go through three to get to four. You have to go to three to get to four.
You have to go from two to get to three to get to four with the exception of probably, let's say,
two examples. One is pathological. If you suffer from narcolepsy, one of the things that typically
happens is that you go from being awake straight into REM sleep. So to sort of finish the 90 minute
cycle, and this will make sense, you go sort of stage one to stage two, stage two, three, three,
four. Then after about 70 minutes, you'll rise back up into stage two. And then finally you'll
pop up into REM sleep. And then you'll have a short REM sleep period. And then you'll go back
down again, down into non REM sleep, up into REM, down into non REM sleep, up into REM. And you do
that, as I said, every 90 minutes. However, what changes is the ratio of non REM to REM within that
90 minute period as you move across the night, such that in the first half of the night, the
majority of your 90 minute sleep cycles are comprised of lots of deep non REM sleep and very
little REM sleep. But as you push through to the second half of the night, now the seesaw balance
changes. And the majority of those sleep cycles are comprised much more of rapid eye movement sleep
and almost no deep sleep. And that's why it's always dangerous when people say, you know, I'm
one of those who survives on, you know, six, six and a half hours of sleep at night. I wake up,
you know, five, five 30 to get a jumpstart on the day. And you can ask, well, let's say you're
getting six hours of sleep. How much sleep are you losing? And they will say, well, according to your
definition of eight hours of sleep, well, I'm 25% off because I'm getting, I lose two hours at the
end of an eight hour night of sleep. So I'm sleeping 75%. I'm losing 25% yes and no, because
yes, you're disproportionate. Exactly. So yes, you're losing 25% of total sleep, but you could
be losing up to 70% of all of your REM sleep because it's the REM sleep rich phase that you
are short changing to get a jumpstart on the day. So you've got to be very careful when you try to
think of your sleep dynamics. But to come back to your point, sorry, yes, you always have to go
through that linear progression. Norel epilepsy is a standout case that you'll usually go from
wakefulness sometimes immediately into REM sleep. Very frightening. Most people don't experience,
you know, logical, rational waking consciousness, and then go immediately into irrational
hallucinogenic consciousness, which is what REM sleep is. It's very disturbing when you speak to
these patients. The other is if you are horrifically REM sleep deprived or chronically sleep deprived,
occasionally you can make the transition straight into REM sleep. We see this in people who are
abusing alcohol heavily, who are alcoholics, alcohol, and we'll come onto this blocks your REM sleep.
You can build up such a hunger for REM sleep that the brain says, well, tonight I'm going to
forego the non-REM sleep. I'm just going to go and feast on REM sleep straight away. There's
hysteresis in the system, maladaptively so. That's a bad sign when you get hysteresis like that,
that type of pressure. Does this explain, and maybe this is not even really correct, but you
could see that someone who's constitutively sleeping six hours a night would suffer perhaps fewer of
the memory consolidation issues because they're still getting much of their deeper sleep earlier
in the evening, presumably where that hippocampal consolidation takes place and the lack of REMs
manifestations are just harder to see. Is that partially explain any of that or is that even
accurate? It turns out that different types of memory rely on different stages of sleep at
different times of night. So what we found is that you need sleep after learning to essentially hit
the save button on your memories so that you don't forget. And for that, it's all about deep non-REM
sleep. So as long as you were getting, let's say, the first half of the night, the first five hours,
then it's likely that you may have been able to protect those memories. But here's the other
problem that stage two non-REM sleep, which actually happens most in the second half of the
night. In the second half of the night, you're having either REM sleep or stage two. And in fact,
if you look at those sleep spindles, they exponentially increase towards the end of the
night. So you get most of your sleep spindle rich sleep in the last two hours of the night. The
reason that's important is because you not only need sleep after learning to consolidate to save
those memories, you also need sleep before learning to get your brain ready in preparation
to actually lay down new memories. And there it's stage two non-REM sleep and these spindles.
So what we've discovered is that the more of those sleep spindles that you have,
the greater refreshment of your memory encoding ability to. So think about it like this.
Yeah. And this is a very beautiful experimental demonstration because you can surgically deprive
people of each of those. And I've seen other talks you've given, of course, and in your book,
you touch on this, where you could preferentially from an experimental standpoint, prevent somebody
from consolidating memory and you could similarly prevent them from forming new memory.
Even though we can keep the total amount of sleep consistent. So it's not a stressor,
it's not that wakefulness, it's you can selectively excise just like you said,
individual stages of sleep. What's the biggest detriment that persons face clinically with the
reduction of REM? I think right now, based on the weight of the evidence, it probably starts with
mental health. Anything from depression, anxiety through to disease, anxiety, depression, and then
suicidality. I think one of the most striking things that we've been seeing in our hands and
other people have demonstrated to them, this is probably the second other big area of work that we
do here at the sleep center is sleep and mental health. You know, sleep is emotional first aid,
bottom line period. And what you find is that in young teenagers, one of the strongest predictors
of firstly suicidal ideation, in other words, thoughts of taking their own life,
strongest predictors of suicide attempts, and tragically, a very strong predictor of suicide
completion is insufficient sleep and sleep fragmentation. And what we've been finding is
that it's REM sleep that seems to provide essentially a form of overnight therapy.
And it's REM sleep that resets or recalibrates the emotional networks in the brain. And there's a
series, there's a network of them that involves an area called the prefrontal cortex, and particularly
the middle part of the prefrontal cortex, which acts like a top down regulator of your emotions.
So there's deep emotional brain centers, centers like the amygdala, which is a centerpiece region
for the generation of strong, impulsive, aversive negative reactions. Anyone with a young boy knows
what the amygdala does. Right. Exactly. If they have a temper tantrum in the middle of, you know,
the supermarket, it's because firstly, their prefrontal cortex, you know, has just not developed
yet. And what little of it that there is, if they haven't slept well, is obliterated. That's actually
a really great example of one of the most obvious observations. Like we taught, you know, I mean, any
parent listening to this knows how emphatically you protect the nap. Correct. You know, and it's like-
For mental, for emotional, mental health. Yeah, just for behavioral health of the child. Correct.
And it's sort of like your day revolves around the nap. Like, can you go to Disneyland today? I don't
know. It depends if we get the nap schedule and, you know, yes or no. And what you're basically
providing is a technical explanation for something that is so empirically obvious, it's undeniable.
And it's not the opposite, right? So bear with me for a moment. When it comes to the broader mental
health stuff, you could easily construct an argument that says the arrow of causality is the
other way. The person who is anxious, it's the anxiety that's keeping them awake. Now, my guess
is in reality, these two feed off each other constantly. I think you're right. You might be
predisposed to anxiety that fosters lack of sleep. The lack of sleep amplifies and boom,
boom, boom, boom. It's a two way street, but is the traffic flowing more dominantly in one direction
than the other? And I think this is what your point you're going to make. But then the behavior of a
four year old is a perfect example of you only need to screw that up one night. You give a four
year old one bad night or miss one nap. I mean, it's very obvious how that translates into the
behavior. So that would point in the direction of the sleep can really be the driver of the
pathology if you want to use pathology to describe that, which of course is a strong term to describe,
you know, outbursts of four year olds. But just to make the point, right? That to me is one of the
most interesting, albeit somewhat glib examples. But I think it's so consistent, you know, and I
use that frequently where you often see a parent with a child and the child is crying and they
look at you and they say, well, they just didn't sleep well asleep. As if there's this universal
parental knowledge that bad sleep the night before equals bad mood and emotional reactivity the next
day. And what's striking is that if you look at the data somewhere between infancy and even now
childhood, not only do we abandon the notion that sleep is absolutely essential and non-negotiable,
but we start to stigmatize it with this label of laziness that you're slothful or that your child
is slothful for getting sufficient sleep. And the reason that upsets me, and I am, I'm getting a
little bit, I'm getting a little bit animated, which is off for a British man. But the, you know,
the reason I do is because firstly, you know, it took mother nature 3.6 million years to put this
eight hour thing called a night of sleep in place. And within the space of 70 years, if you look at
the data, we've lopped off almost 20 to 25% of that. You know, imagine coming along and saying,
you know, in the next hundred years, I think what I'm going to do is for the entirety of human
society, I'm going to reduce their oxygen saturation by about 20 to 25%. Do you think that's a good
idea? And the answer is no. No, it's such a great example. I'll pause for a moment just to tell a
funny story that you and I have talked about off mic, which is up until about 2012, I was in the
I'll sleep when I'm dead camp. And I know what led to that. It wasn't that there was a very deliberate
decision at the end of medical school when a good friend of mine with all the best intentions, who
was a year ahead of me. So he was now in at the end of his internship, as I was about to begin mine,
he said, and this is in the days when we didn't have the 80 hour work week requirement in residency.
So we averaged, I think about 114 hours a week in the hospital. So he said to me, look, Peter,
you're, you're signing up for, you know, whatever five, seven years of this thing.
If you spent every moment outside of the hospital sleeping, you would still be tired.
The only difference is you wouldn't have any fun. So make sure you live every moment that you're not
in the hospital to the fullest. And so for me, that basically meant if I wasn't in the hospital,
I was swimming, I was going out with my friends, I was trying to meet girls, like I was doing
anything, everything such that during that period of my life, I, I just know, because I was pretty
adamant about recording how much time, like I was very wed to this idea. There's 168 hours in a week.
If I'm spending, you know, 114 of them here, and I spend this many driving and I spend this many
getting groceries and I spend this many swimming and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. I think I, I was
about 28 hours a week of sleep. So it wasn't four every night because you'd have none and then six
and then three and then eight. Like you, you could binge sleep from time to time,
but it was pretty much 28 a week. I'll come back to some of the implications of that. But fast
forward a few years. I'm talking to a good friend of mine, Kirk Parsley, who's a physician who,
like you, is adamant about, you know, the importance of sleep. And we're having dinner
one night and he says, he's challenging me on this. And he says, so let me get this straight.
You've just decided that you're going to sleep half of what is evolutionarily programmed. And I said,
yeah, he goes, does it strike you as odd that evolution would have designed us to spend a third
of our life not mating, not watching out for predators, not hunting for food, but doing this
thing for some other purpose. Do you think that thing must have been important? And it was such
an obvious argument, but it really overnight changed the way I thought about this, which was
evolution went to great lengths to do this and superficially at great cost to us. Right. I mean,
you could argue, well, imagine you didn't need to sleep and you could spend 24 hours a day
foraging for food or a mate or some other thing, but it didn't. So it's sort of, it's sort of like
there's probably a reason we are not anaerobic to your point about reducing oxygen saturation by
25%. You know, if you were to think about that, you know, during sleep, just as you said, you're
not eating, you're not finding food, you're not finding a mate, you're not reproducing, you're
not caring for your young, you're vulnerable to predation on any one of those grounds,
but especially all of them put together as a collective. It's completely anti-evolutionary.
It sounds like the dumbest thing. And, you know, I often said, and it has been said before,
if sleep doesn't serve an absolutely vital set of functions, it's the biggest mistake
that the evolutionary process has ever made. And we now realize from this constellation of evidence
that mother nature did not make a spectacular blunder in putting this thing called an eight
hour sort of need of sleep in place. It is the greatest life support system that you could ever
wish for. It is a remarkable health insurance policy. And what's great is that it's largely
democratic. It's mostly free. And in terms of a prescription from a doctor, it's largely painless.
So I almost wanted to title a book, Consciousness is Overrated,
or just sometimes dot, dot, dot, consciousness is overrated. But when you really look at the
evidence in terms of risk derisking just about every disease that is killing us in the developed
world, it's very hard to look no further than sleep. And that's why I don't want to trivialize
diet and I don't want to trivialize movement and activity. But what I would say is that if you want
to put sleep up against either one of those two and kind of play the whole head to head game,
which I don't think we need to do here, I would simply say that sleep is the foundation on which
those two other things sit. It's not the third pillar of good health. I think it is the foundation.
That's a really interesting way to think about it, because I typically describe four pillars or five,
if you include all of the exogenous molecules that you could lump together. But another way to
think about it, which again, I don't think is necessarily the right way to think about it,
but sometimes it makes the point. If you deprive yourself of food, how long can you survive?
Well, we have one person up to 382 days. Even someone who's as lean as you could survive 30
days with no food. How long could you survive without water? Depends greatly on the temperature,
et cetera. But you could make the case that deprivation of sleep would result in the quickest
reduction of health, certainly more than not eating or not exercising for a period of time.
And those studies have been done in rats.
And actually we know some of this from humans who have been trying to... In fact,
didn't the Guinness Book of World Records, I can't remember if I read this in your work,
they've actually banned attempts at longest period of sleep deprivation.
So I mentioned this. Yeah.
Yeah. You might leave it in the book.
There was a time when you could still try and beat the world record of sleep deprivation.
And it got up to about sort of, I think the last true effort was about 24 days.
But I think it was debatable, that one. But based on the weight of the scientific data,
the relationship between sleep loss and mental health, sleep loss and cancer,
sleep loss, cardiovascular disease, sleep loss and metabolic syndrome, Guinness started to feel
very, very uncomfortable. And then when suicide came on the table, it pulled it. So in other words,
think about this, there was a gentleman, Felix Baumgardner, I think his name was,
who sponsored by Red Bull, went up in a capsule in a hot air balloon to the outer surface of our
planet. This was about four years ago.
Four years ago. This was remarkable.
He opened the door and then he jumped out and he fell back down to earth at over a thousand
kilometers an hour using his body alone. He broke the sound barrier and he successfully came down.
And now Guinness says for that, just fine. However, to sleep deprive yourself, no,
much more unsafe. We're not going to let it happen.
You are allowed just to put it in context.
You're allowed up to 12 jumps off Niagara Falls.
Basically.
But that's okay. But no, no, you're not going to, that's such a great point. I want to go back to
one other thing to close the loop on this. And again, the listener may say, boy, this is where
there's a lot of stuff going on here, but there really is. Like this is, I think you have to have
a lot, and I'm trying to think about all the questions I can ask that others would have.
If you took two individuals who are sleeping six hours a night, if you have one person who,
just for the argument's sake, is doing it from 9 PM to 3 AM, and another person is doing it
from midnight to 6 AM, would you expect, or even if it were, let's make it even more clear,
it's the same individual, but you do it over a period of weeks. You transition them from
9 to 3 versus midnight to 6. Would their sleep wave cycles look the same? Would they still be
truncating the same amount of REM at the tail end of that? Or would they start to do some forward
truncation?
So essentially what happens is that your brain has a different hunger or different appetite
for different types of sleep. So think of those different stages of sleep, like a finger buffet,
and at different times of the night, that buffet is going to be sort of consumed more heavily
in terms of the deep non-REM sleep phase, which would probably be the hours from 9 PM through
until about sort of 3 AM. That's really the window of preferential appetite for your brain
when it comes to deep non-REM sleep. That's when it will preferentially eat at that type of sleep.
But then from about 3 AM through until about midday, then the brain shifts in terms of its
pattern. If you let people just sleep it out, if you look at sort of extreme owls who, and we
should speak about chronotypes at some point, but people who like to go to bed very late and wake
up very late, essentially there, then the buffet is going to get hit hard in terms of REM sleep
devouring. So I make that point that your brain has different taste sensitivities to non-REM and REM
across the 24 hour clock face, because it means that if you're shortchanging your sleep by two
hours, but you're doing it by going to bed very early and waking up very early, then what's going
to happen is that you're probably going to be losing most of your REM sleep because most of your
REM sleep happens in the late morning hours and you're already awake by 3 or 4 AM in the morning.
And so you're not getting the chance to get into those REM sleep rich phases. And which of those
patients would develop more appetite for sleep the subsequent evening? The person who was deprived,
and you know why I'm asking, by the way, it's exactly what we were talking about earlier.
It's this jet lag question. If you know you've got that flight and you need to force yourself
to sleep at a time zone, that's not right. I'm just now thinking about, well, I always do the
nine to three. Would I be better off doing the, in other words, I'm depriving myself of REM. Would
I be better off just describing, just restricting myself? Well, you're depriving yourself of REM,
but you're also still depriving yourself of total sleep as well, you know, when it comes to the jet
like model. And you know, there are, there's some, I think that that's an interesting model. And I
think it does work that you can try to in the week before you start to fly, let's say you're going,
I'm going home to London, which essentially is eight hours ahead. So I need to now essentially
start to sort of, by the time I'm waking up, people in London have already been awake for
essentially eight hours. So I need to start to get myself on the schedule. So I start to wake up,
you know, 10 minutes earlier for about five days before. And, you know, so I'm only about an hour
shifted, but it helps. And then the morning of the flight, I'll wake up really early. And then I
won't make the mistake that everyone makes on those transatlantic flights, which is they sleep
in the second half of the flight. You shouldn't do that. You should sleep in the first half of the
flight, which is when most people in the UK are asleep. And by the middle of that flight,
most people in the UK, that's the time to wake up. And so you should be waking up that time
so that you build up enough of this sleepiness pressure by the time that you want to get to bed
once you've landed that evening in London. And this won't make too much sense right now. And I
think we'll, we'll speak probably a lot more about this when we speak about caffeine and a denecence
pressure. But that, but to come to your point, you're building up what's called sleep pressure.
The longer that you're awake, the more of that healthy sleepiness that builds up. But to come
back to the real question at hand, yes, just because you sleep, you know, five hours from one
point in the clock face, maybe earlier in the night to sort of early in the morning versus five hours
late in the morning until later in that day, the type of sleep that you get will not be the same.
You will be selectively shortchanging yourself of sleep, either of deep sleep or of REM sleep on
either side of that equation. This points out another interesting observation, which I do want
to spend some time talking about wearables because of course, you know, we're both wearing our
wearables at the moment. And I think we both acknowledge that, look, I mean, these things
are still not quite at the level of the polysom and maybe they never will be. I mean, that's a
very difficult thing to replicate from, you know, something on your wrist or your finger.
But it's so funny, this might explain an observation I always experience when I come
from New York back to California, which is I generally try to stay on California time,
even when I'm in New York, going to bed later, waking up later. And in California, I'm a very
early sleeper and an early riser. So even if I'm trying to keep it at eight hours and eight hours,
and I can do that very well in California, not as well in New York, my first night back, even my
first two nights back in California, I have much higher deep sleep. And that would explain it. It's
this phase shift that I'm capturing this, I mean, last night was because I came back from New York
last night, you know, went to bed at, I don't know, 8 30 p.m. and got up at five or yeah, probably
4 30 or five in the morning. So you had a huge deep sleep. Exactly. So you've dragged your eight
hour window. If you think about the sort of eight hour window and you slide it back on the clock
phase from midnight to 11 p.m. to 10 p.m. to in fact, nine p.m. You're dragging that eight hour
sleep phase back closer into the deeper sleep rich phase, the deep non-REM sleep that you want.
So what your sort of aura ring will be telling you is you got more deep sleep. And perhaps you
may actually see a little bit of a reduction in REM sleep. As you go to New York, you may see the
opposite. As you sleep later in the morning, you'll get more of that REM sleep. I generally do see that pattern,
which is I get, and it pisses me off too. I'm like, I didn't get as much deep sleep and I got
more REM sleep. And not that REM is bad, but I'm generally more upset by the dearth of deep. You
know, this is interesting. It's now really I really I really need to think about that because of course,
on some level, our body is responding to cues in the environment. It's not just responding to the
intellectual knowledge that, hey, in California, it's this time, it's time to go to bed. It's,
I mean, light is playing a role. Meal timing is playing a role. Huge meal. And yeah, I want to
definitely talk with you about this because this is to me, it's such an important topic. And then,
of course, the accumulation of a denis scene and of course, the melatonin. So by the way, I would just
say that, you know, I think REM sleep, some people, I have this kind of bimodal distribution of
questions. Some people will say, how do I maximize my REM sleep? And I say, why do you want to
maximize your REM sleep? And say, well, that's dream sleep. And that's the good stuff, right?
As if, you know, it's like saying, you know, how do I maximize the amount of yolk in my egg? You know,
do I get like the, can I go the ostrich egg, whatever it is? I don't know what the analogy is.
And the question is, Mother Nature has found this equilibrium. Don't mess with it. It's the
da Vinci code of sleep and stick to it. You're good to go. But also then other people will say,
you know, how do I get more deep sleep? Or, you know, I, you know, I could get upset by that lack
of deep sleep to come back onto REM sleep and how important it is. The studies have been done where
firstly they deprived. And by the way, these studies have never been done again since the
1980s. And they probably never will be because of the ethics regarding them, because they are just
so devastating that we probably won't be allowed. And rightly so, I think to do these studies
to animals ever again, but they essentially deprived animals of sleep until they died.
And what they found was that rats will firstly die as quickly, if not quicker, almost by about
20% from total sleep deprivation as they will from total food deprivation. So if you want to put
sleep in food. That's interesting that their gap is much narrower because for humans, the gap is
very, you'll die way earlier from sleep deprivation than food deprivation, unless you're, you know,
the leanest person on the planet. And there is a tragic disorder that I described a little bit in
the book. It's a very rigidly inherited disorder called fatal familial insomnia. And it's really
the only evidence short of the disgusting travesty that is total sleep deprivation used in
certain countries for interrogation tactics that we know of that has led to death.
But withstanding that this disorder, fatal familial insomnia says it in the name that
essentially human beings, how old do people typically survive? It usually takes about 18
to 24 months before they die. But the problem is this is not, they wake up one day and they are
no longer sleeping at all. It's a gradual thing. So it's kind of like it masquerades as just
typical insomnia first restless nights for the first two or three months. Then it gets worse.
Then you're only sleeping four hours. Then, you know, by month 12, you're already sleeping two
hours. How much of this is genetic versus environmental versus we don't know. It's
strongly heritable that we know. So it's within the Mendelian sort of, you know, pool of genetic
disorders and it's testable. We know the gene. Interestingly, it's what seems to be the single
gene. Yeah. And it's a prion protein gene abnormality, which is, if you don't know about
prion proteins, you may have heard of mad cow disease, which was rife in the United Kingdom.
That's another thing. That's another prion protein disorder. That's why you can't donate blood.
And it's also why, yeah, I'll probably forget half of what I've been saying and start repeating
myself because I've been vegetarian for about 12 years. But before I went that route, I think I
definitely was in the phase of eating beef when it was filled with these prions in the United Kingdom.
So my brain is probably Swiss cheese at this stage, but essentially this disorder,
fatal familiar insomnia, it gives us some degree of disease proof that insufficient sleep is fatal
for human beings. But we knew it in these rat studies because these rats would die as quickly
from food deprivation as they did from sleep deprivation. But the more striking thing was
then they did a second round of studies. They selectively deprived them of either just non-rapid
eye movement sleep or rapid eye movement sleep. And what they found is that the rats were dead
within about nine to 10 days with total sleep deprivation. They were dead within just about the
same period of time from REM sleep deprivation. Duration was kept constant or also reduced?
It was still reduced somewhat. But you could probably look at a control that had a same
duration without a selective deprivation. Correct. So it's called, yeah, and there is
a, what's called a yoked paradigm. It's a very clever technique where you can mimic the total
amount of sleep deprivation in one other animal, but the other animal is still getting the chance
to get REM sleep. So REM sleep selectively removed. The rats died basically almost as
quickly as they did from total sleep deprivation. And then non-REM sleep deprivation was deathly.
Ultimately, it just took longer. It took about 20 days. Total sleep deprivation. Let's just say for
argument's sake, you die in nine days. Sleep reduction, but selective REM deprivation. You
die in the same period of time. Basically sleep reduction, but deep deprivation. You live maybe
twice as long. Yeah. So everything deathly, everything fatal, just that one takes a little
bit longer to kill you than the other. And what I find either strange or exciting about that is
if you look from an evolutionary standpoint, those two types of sleep did not emerge at the same time.
We only have observed true rapid eye movement sleep in birds and mammals.
We don't see true rapid eye movement sleep in reptiles, amphibians, fish, or insects. Now,
birds and mammals evolved separately along the evolutionary path from amphibians, fish,
and reptiles. So what this means is that when we went from the transition from being reptilian to
either avian or mammalian, that's when REM sleep emerged because we see non-REM sleep in every
species. Even in insects, we can observe something that looks like non-REM sleep in reptiles, fish,
amphibians, birds, and mammals. Every one of them has non-REM sleep. Not every one of them has REM
sleep. Only birds and mammals have REM sleep. In other words, REM sleep is the new kid on the block
in the time course of evolution. REM sleep firstly emerged later in the course of evolution. And
secondly, what's kind of wonderful is it emerged twice independently, once in birds and once in
mammals. So you could argue that, well, if deep non-REM sleep, which is much more evolutionary
from an evolutionary perspective, it's in a much older form of sleep, wouldn't it be the much more
necessary fundamental one? And therefore, wouldn't you die sooner? No, it seems the opposite because
you'd say, well, for the same reason that the cockroach can survive the nuclear disaster,
the avian mammalian pathway is more evolved, neuronally, presumably, and therefore probably
requires something essential in REM that when it deprives you, it takes away your superpower,
which is a cortex. And I think that's exactly what it is, which is when you look at anything
that has essentially a complex nervous system, maybe that's where the pressure for this thing
called REM sleep emerged. Even though we know that non-REM sleep actually supports many essential
central nervous system functions like synaptic pruning and some great sort of neural function,
you know, the glymphatic system clearing up the 30-cal time function. It's sort of similar to your
oxygen analogy, which is when you go from being an anaerobe to a faculty of anaerobe to an a-robe,
who's going to be most sensitive to oxygen deprivation? Yeah, exactly. And so, you know,
it's always a dangerous scientific hypothesis where you can argue it both ways, but I always
found that interesting and it's uncommented, but I just wanted to note that for, you know, 20 minutes
ago in kind of in defense of REM sleep, that, you know, if we should all be worried about the amount
of deep sleep that we're getting, absolutely. But we also need to be worried about how much REM sleep
that we're getting, because from a pure mortality risk standpoint, REM sleep is arguably even more
important than non-REM sleep. And we'll come to this later, but my recollection of the literature is,
and I think you even alluded to this earlier, ethanol's biggest hit is going to be on REM,
isn't it? Hands down. This is where we come on to substances that are misunderstood and misused when
it comes to sleep. And now before we go there, Matt, look, for me, I don't need any more of a case
in the importance of sleep. And I think honestly, the Alzheimer's thing alone should be sufficient
for anyone to take this seriously, because certainly my patients, that's the single most
important thing to them. Now, there are some of them that are more high risk, you know, people
that have, you know, APOE4 genotype that's in the, you know, the direction that would increase risk
or family history, but I don't think I've met a patient yet who doesn't say on some level
preserving cognition as their single highest priority in life. That said, can you spend even
just a minute, a couple of minutes? It's the drive after all. We have all the time in the world,
making the case, the similar case in the presence of cardiovascular disease and cancer.
Yeah. And I want to touch on that point before we go on about this Alzheimer's disease risk. You know,
a lot of people out there may be having this sort of like sleep machismo moment where they have this
braggadocio attitude of getting insufficient sleep. And they say, look, I'm in my fifties and,
you know, I'm fit as a fiddle. And my cognition is razor sharp and I sleep five or six hours a
night. So we've got, you know, heads of state, for example, who are saying this, people who,
you know, have a huge impact on the public and they're saying these things. And it makes me sad
because you can look at two other heads of state who were very vociferous about their proclamation
of the uselessness of sleep, Margaret Thatcher and Ronald Reagan. Both of them were chess beaters
when it came to insufficient sleep. They were very proud of saying that they only got four or five
hours of sleep, that they were immune to the effects of insufficient sleep, that sleep was for
the week and that you can sleep when you're dead, which PS is mortally unwise advice based on the
evidence, the shorter your sleep, the shorter your life. That's what all of the studies tell us.
I don't think it's coincidental now looking back that both of them went on to develop Alzheimer's
disease. And it makes me so sad because I saw pictures of Margaret Thatcher in an enfeebled
state of dementia. And I'm just thinking, you know, if only when she was, you know, in her fifties
and had that bravado about sleep, if she could see herself in that bed, in that later state of
life in such a crippled mental cognitive functioning state, would you be so brave about it?
And I would hope that she wouldn't, that humility would come into place.
So that's the first thing about, I think, the insufficient sleep argument and people
rightly being frightened, having the daylights frightened out of them about preserved cognition,
you should have that regarding your sleep. The other one though, that frightens me too,
is the other way that a lack of sleep can get you is not chronically across the lifespan without
Alzheimer's disease, but acutely with car crashes. And I know that we'll come on to this at some
point too. But the only thing I would say is that I get many emails from people who've read the book.
And two months ago, I got an email from a gentleman, I won't name him, and he was in his late thirties.
And he described how three months before that, he had lost his wife and his 18 month, 18 month old
child in a car crash. And it later became apparent that the person who hit them had basically been
surviving on about five and a half hours of sleep for the two months prior that they'd had what's
called a microsleep. They actually lost control of their car at 60 miles an hour at a moderate drift
angle. You are essentially in the next lane within less than a second and you're in the ditch
after a second. And they went straight head on. And now he was going to have to raise his four-year
old son by himself without the wife that he loved, without the 18 month daughter that they'd invested
in. Because someone perhaps had heard from someone vocally in the public that surviving on five hours
of sleep was something that was okay to do. And to me, that just breaks my heart. I just don't
feel comfortable in having the responsibility like the head of a state of a country. And then
speaking about this thing, this kind of magic attitude of insufficient sleep, because that's
what it can lead to. It can lead to the travesty of the explosion of a nuclear family.
And my guess is, even though it's going to be very difficult to actually quantify this, I believe that
the story you just shared is an especially tragic, poignant example of something that probably occurs
much more than we were able to quantify. I sometimes say to patients, you know, the four
horsemen of death would be these big chronic diseases that kill us, but we can never forget
accidental death. And then when you look at accidental death, how do you quantify it? Well,
it turns out that three forms of accidental death form 80% of them. And the biggest among them is
motor vehicle. Right. And so the question is, what can you do to reduce that risk? So if you look at it,
some form of distraction, and I've included sleep deprivation in that, but now I almost feel like
they need to be separated out. Distraction, meaning you're puttin' with your phone, you're
checkin' ways, you're doing something you shouldn't be doing with your phone, sleep deprivation,
ethanol, failure to wear a seat belt, and reckless driving. I mean, that basically accounts for it.
It wouldn't surprise me if that sleep deprivation bucket is bigger than we think.
I mean, we've got some decent data on this. And firstly, what we know is, in the hour that we've
been talking already, numerous people have lost their life in a drowsy driving related accident
based on the statistics. We know that already. And the way that we can tell that is both from
speaking to the people who were involved in the accident, but you can also pick this apart from
the dynamics of the accident as well. And here's the problem. When you are under slept, we're not
talking about a night of total sleep deprivation. That's where you fall asleep at the wheel. And
that's the obvious one. The much less obvious one, but the much more common one is what we call
microsleeps. So when you are trying to survive on seven hours of sleep or six hours of sleep,
and it really just takes that little of a dose. By the way, I haven't forgotten our cardiovascular
question. I will come back to it. But what you essentially have are these small lapses,
we call them microsleeps, where the eyelid will partially close. And you can pick this up on a
camera. And they've done these studies systematically where you dose people from getting
nine hours of sleep to eight hours of sleep, seven, six, five, four, three, four, one week,
two weeks, three weeks. These studies have been essentially looked at, sliced and diced
parametrically. They're probably the best studies done within the field of sleep.
And so we know them very well, what your lapse rate is, what your microsleep rate is.
And what you find is that the eyelid partially closes. And at that point, you no longer react.
And the reason I'm bringing this point up is that drowsy driving accounts for more accidents on our
roads than either drugs or alcohol combined, combined. Now I'm not condoning drink driving
or driving inebriated under any circumstance. What I am saying, however, is that firstly,
drowsy driving is a huge part of this problem on our roads. And the reason that it's not just
problematic is because it's usually much more deathly. When you are drunk, you typically react,
but you react too late. So you do something, but it's not enough. And you crash when you have a
microsleep. Yeah, it's a project. You do nothing. That's why drowsy driving is more fatal than
drunk driving typically is because there is no application of brake. There is no application
of brake. There's no course correction of steering wheel angle. There is nothing. There is simply a
car with no one in control. And it's a two ton missile on the freeway at 65 miles an hour with
no one in charge. This is why I feel really uncomfortable about the idea of public proclamations
of insufficient sleep. And I get that. And there are people, sports stars, all sorts of people who
I respect hugely. And I have an immense amount of sympathy for where they're coming from,
because I think there's a lot of public pressure to be this outspoken. I'm going to be crushing it
on the sports field, and then I'm going to be back in the gym the next morning and sleep is for X,
Y and Z, who cares. But then you get someone in a car and you hear a story like that. And I can't
help but just have my heart broken. But I think, you know, Matt, your work has come along at a
really interesting point. I mean, I have to be honest with you. I remember when your book came out
and my initial thought was, does the world need another sleep book? Because there's 2000 of them
out there. And I think there's two things that are different. The first is your book is exceptional.
Actually, I'd say three things. Your book is exceptional. The third is your understanding
of the topic and your credibility is exceptional. And those aren't necessarily synonymous. You can
have really credible, thoughtful people who write a book, but the book itself isn't exceptional,
or it doesn't hit the tone. And some and conversely, you can have someone who puts
together a good book, but they themselves don't have the credibility. I think that so you can take
credit for the first two. I think the third is, is the little bit of luck, which is, I think we are
at a point in time where people are ready to hear this. In other words, if you, the exact same
professor wrote the exact same book 20 years ago, I'm not convinced it would have the same impact it
is having today. Now, I don't know, you probably have a better sense than me. I don't know exactly
what accounts for that difference today. Is it that today we are more interested in, you know,
the thin end of the wedge for this might have been our interest in performance. Maybe that is the
thing that first got people to think about this, which is, well, wait a minute, you know, if I want
to be better at X, Y and Z, whether it be my sport, my craft, my whatever, is sleep a tool I need to be
optimizing the way people have for many years realized, hey, what you eat and how you exercise
absolutely impacts your performance. So I'm not, I'm not sure what it is, but I, I have a feeling,
and I actually had this discussion with my daughter a couple of weeks ago, that we will look back at
the way we think about nighttime electronics, sleep deprivation and things like that. We will look back
at that in 20 years, hopefully sooner, the way you and I would look back at, you know, a smoking
mother being told by her doctor, smoke this brand versus that brand. Like we can't even fathom that
that was a discussion that took place as recently as about 1966 in the United States. And yet we're
kind of in the, our infancy in the dark from a clinical perspective, from sort of a public
health perspective and functioning on this. So firstly, I mean, so much great stuff to unpack there.
I think you're absolutely right. I think the success of the book is largely despite my,
my ability to, to write and convey ideas. I think what happened is that it was a perfect storm
where there has been- I gave you, I gave you two thirds of the credit. Thank you. And I, and I,
I don't know if I can take them. I feel so ashamed, but I think that the middle point is
the erosion of sleep time has hit an all time high. We are now sleeping less than we have ever done
in what seems to be the history of our species. Now we can't say that for sure, but what we
certainly can say is that back in the earliest record that we have of a systematic questionnaire,
which was in 1942 by Gallup, what they found was that the average American adult was sleeping 7.9
hours a night. Now that number is down to six hours and 31 minutes. That's the average
6,031 minutes. That must mean that- How linear has that decline been,
Matt? Has that been something- Nonlinear.
Yeah. It's accelerating, isn't it? It's accelerating. Yeah. So I think you've,
you've had this ballistic erosion of sleep time, this decimation of sleep throughout
industrialized nations. And it's not just America, by the way, Japan is even worse. It's down to
6,021 minutes. My home country, the United Kingdom, not much better, 6,049 minutes.
And these are averages. You've got to imagine that at least a third of the people are probably
trying to survive on five hours of sleep, certainly during the week they are.
It's that plus this incredible explosion of sleep science over the past 30 years.
And this perfect storm has led to a collision where society is sleeping less.
Disease and sickness has been escalating in a manner that, you know, we've almost never seen
before. And the knowledge of what sleep is doing, we know far more now, sleep is not just curing
sleepiness. Sleep is actually supporting, there is no physiological system in the body and there is
no operation of the brain that isn't wonderfully enhanced by sleep when you get it or demonstrably
impaired when you don't get enough. That knowledge and the causal knowledge of sleep in that, it's
not just associational. It is many of them are causal links with those disease states. I think
led to this ability to write this book at this time that felt as though it was somewhat unequivocal
that it was very difficult to argue with. You know, you can pick apart one study from another,
but when you build that blueprint manifesto, when you build the scientific cold, hard, rational,
emotion-free case for sleep, it's very difficult to argue with. And it just happened that we were
at that time in our human history with sleep and we were at that time in our scientific journey
regarding our understanding of sleep. I think that's why the book felt like it needed to be
written and needed to be written now. For what it's worth, you had many moons on the front and
back cover, so my little I.R. thing was delighted. He loves that. He's probably read literally from
cover to back cover. Back cover, nothing in between. Yeah, exactly. That's just fine. I ask people,
they please, you don't have to read the book, you just have to buy it. That's all I ask.
Okay, there's like literally a hundred more things I want to ask you about. So
can you make the case for why cardiovascular disease is worsened by or accelerated by
sleep deprivation? And then same question I'm going to ask you in a moment for cancer.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read,
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc. On social, you can find
me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is the best
way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer,
this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the
practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.