Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives.
Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast,
that became clear to me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming.
I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information
with you. To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a
full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and their feedback has mirrored this.
So all of this raises a natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support
this? As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of
contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most
important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something
when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason
selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time
advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about
something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads,
I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can work over time, and that is to create
a subscriber support model for my audience. This keeps my relationship with you both simple and
honest. If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and support us at whatever level works
for you. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that
simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get
back more than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show
notes, including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts
for each episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature
of many of our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular
Ask Me Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also
getting to hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited
about, I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said,
we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies
who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them
pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of
you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive
for members to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a
moment to listen to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please
consider supporting us directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest today is Professor
Robert Sapolsky. And many of you may recognize that name because Robert has written some incredible
books, probably the one that you would recognize the most is Why Zebras Don't Get Ulcers, A Guide
to Stress, Stress-related Diseases and Coping. But he's also the author of A Primates Memoir,
which grew out of work that he spent in his early years in Africa. And he spent nearly 30 years in
Africa, four months at a time, The Trouble with Testosterone and other Essays on the Biology of
the Human Predicament. And his most recent book, Behave, The Biology of Humans at Our Best and Worst.
This is a book that Robert spent nearly four years researching and writing. And the book is almost 800
pages long. This is a treatise on the topic of human biology and behavior. Robert is a professor
of biological sciences at Stanford, where he's been, I believe, since he completed his PhD and
his postdoc, which he did back on the East Coast. He spent a lot of time in Kenya right after
college. He went to Kenya, then Uganda, where he studied for the next 30 years, the behavior of
baboons and other primates. He is a MacArthur Fellow. In 1987, he was awarded the fellowship,
which many of you may recognize by its other name, the Genius Grant. He is very
modest and soft spoken about this and really doesn't like to be reminded of that. But Robert
is a really impressive guy. Today is actually the first time we really met in person. I had seen him
speak about a year and a half ago. And after the talk, you know, introduced myself and we spoke
very briefly. But I remember during his talk thinking to myself, this is the first time I'm
really being convinced at the true pathology of stress. I think I had certainly appreciated the
benefits of meditation before when it came to being less miserable. But I think it was really
Robert's work. And in particular, that presentation on that day that got me to really start to think
about the molecular and physiologic harm of hypercorticillemia. So we talk a great deal about
that in this discussion. But we also talk about things that go far outside of that we talk about
the role of depression, we talk about the impact of stress on the developing brain, and also in the
brain later in life, and even some of the areas where the relationship between stress and disease
is not as well understood. And that clearly came across in our discussion of cancer. Overall,
I found this discussion riveting, and I could have continued this discussion for many hours
longer. On a personal level, I was also, you know, really kind of touched by the way he spoke about
this sort of change in heart he had around the relentless ambition and pursuit and how over the
past few years, he's really reevaluated that. And that comes across at the end when we sort of get
into more of a philosophical discussion about what one would do different given what he knows today.
It was an honor to spend so much time with Robert today discussing this. And I appreciated the
confidence he had in basically sight unseen, sitting down with a stranger to have this
discussion. So I hope you'll enjoy this discussion with Robert half as much as I do.
Robert, thank you so much for making the time to meet with me today on a lovely,
rainy San Francisco afternoon. Sure. Glad to be indoors here. As I was saying earlier,
we had met once before really briefly, so briefly that you would not remember it. And of course,
only I would. Summer of 17, I believe you were giving a talk in Sun Valley and I was there.
And you gave a talk on stress. Now it was to a lay audience. So you didn't really get to go
into the depth. And I remember sitting in the audience thinking, Oh, you know, a lot of what
he's saying is really starting to make sense to me. And I can't wait to get a little deeper into
this stuff. Because truthfully, and I'm just going to open with sort of my mea culpa, you've always
heard people say stress kills. And I got to be honest with you. I always thought that was sort
of nonsense. I was like, come on, what do you mean stress kills? Stress is good. It builds resilience,
what is the mechanism by which stress, quote unquote, kills? But of course, once you start to
understand the endocrine system, and of course, training as a surgeon and not an endocrinologist,
I sort of missed out on that. You start to see it. And in that talk, you admittedly at a sort of
high level for the audience really walked through the danger of hypercordicillemia. And so in many
ways, I guess, you know, a year and a half ago was really when I became a fan of your work, and then
kind of said, you know what, there is something to this. So anyway, with that, I appreciate you taking
this time. Sure. And just to sort of back off a bit from that, I actually don't think stress kills
you outright very often. But it sure makes other things that kill you more effective at doing it.
Maybe it's semantic, but you're right. Stress can amplify and accelerate the diseases of aging.
You grew up in New York, right? If I recall, you grew up in Brooklyn or in?
Brooklyn.
I remember reading that after college, you actually went straight off to Kenya first, is that right?
Yeah.
What prompted that?
Well, I was one of those, I've sort of spent my career oscillating between being a lab neuroscientist,
studying the effects of cortisol on the brain, punchline to decades of work is,
you don't want to have a whole lot of it marinating inside your head.
But also for more than 30 years, I've alternated spending my summers studying a population of wild
baboons in a national park in East Africa. And it's the same animals I go back to each year.
These are animals like in dart and nest the ties, get blood, do whole workups on them.
And essentially asking among them, what does your social rank have to do with patterns of stress
related disease? What does your personality, what does your patterns of social affiliation?
So it's been sort of a counterbalance to the lab where, you know, we've been sticking artificial
genes into neurons and fairly reductive stuff like that. So I was actually about eight years old when
I decided I wanted to be a primatologist. So I was kind of planning on that for a long time and
lucked out. I spent all of college brown nosing the right person who shipped me off to a field
site right after graduation. And I wound up sort of inheriting that site. And those have been my
baboons ever since. Did you spend the whole time in Kenya? I remember reading that you also were in
Uganda and obviously they're, I think if my geography is correct, they're neighbors. So
that's a pretty easy switch. Where do the actual baboons, like what is their scope of their
residence? How broadly? Oh, they're spread actually all over Africa. They're one of the
most ubiquitous primates for a lot of the same reasons that we are, which is they'll eat anything.
They're carnivores, but they're also herbivores. They're omnivores. They scavenge dead stuff. They eat
insects. They'll eat most anything so they can fill a lot of niches. So they're scattered
everywhere. But my main work over the years has been this one troop in the Serengeti in
Southwest Kenya. You know, for about 25 years I camped under the same tree. So it's really,
has been a continuity with the same population of animals. What is their natural predator besides
man? Leopards, lions, hyenas. Nonetheless, if you were a male baboon, the most likely thing to kill
you violently is another male. Another male. Yeah, exactly. Sort of like humans. Yes, indeed. Did you
say it's every summer or every other summer? Well, it was initially for about 25 straight summers and
then parenthood and all those complications came in. So wound up being every other summer and then
our kids were old enough to go with us one summer. But unfortunately the fieldwork ended about eight
years ago. So why is that? My Kenyan field assistant of 30 years, we started together when
we were 20. He died of AIDS, political issues there, some game park issues that made it harder
and harder to sort of get research done and kind of that middle-aged realization that I could find
some new game park or new country or something and start all over. But it was kind of time to pack
it in instead. So after you did your PhD, which he did it in New York, right? Yeah, Rockefeller
University. Did you come straight out to Stanford for a postdoc or? Postdoc at the Salk Institute
down in San Diego, spent a couple of years there. If people are sort of familiar with the hypothalamic
hormone that runs the stress response or hormone CRH, CRF, corticotropin releasing hormone. I went
and post-talked with this guy, Wiley Vale, who had discovered it in like two years before. So
that was a pretty exciting time to be there. So spent a couple of years there.
Stanford hired me and I've been there for 31 years since. That's kind of amazing. I keep coming
back to people at Stanford that would have been there when I was there in medical school, but
if it wasn't in the medical school, like you just weren't paying as close attention. And I honestly
don't recall if you ever gave us a lecture in med school. Do you remember giving lectures in
med school 20 plus years ago? I did. Almost certainly the students were paying as little
attention as I was. So that's true. I was about to say it certainly seems like something we should
have been learning in medical school. And yet I feel ashamed to say, I don't know if I recall it.
It was not much of an emphasis and was sort of snuck in embarrassingly.
Like a lunchtime seminar or something. Yeah, exactly. So that. Thrive them with free food.
Yes. And even still only about five people would stay past the cookies.
That's a much bigger issue we can come to. So you wrote a book,
gosh, how many years ago was Why Zebras Don't Get Ulcer? Is that 20 years ago?
Let's see. First edition was 94. It's gone through three editions now. Most recent one was 2004. So
at some point I got to do another one. As we talk about that, and you've written a book more
recently that I want to talk about as well. Let's back up and explain something you touched on a
second ago, which is sort of the physiology of a stress response. So walk us through the
relationship between the hypothalamus, the pituitary and the adrenal glands.
So when we're under stress levels of 11D different hormones change in our body, most of them are
relatively minor players. The two workhorses overwhelmingly, first one famously adrenaline,
British term epinephrine, sort of North American term output from the sympathetic nervous system.
It's on the scene in your bloodstream within one, two seconds or so after all hell breaks loose.
And I just want to explain what sympathetic means to the listener. We've had this discussion before.
It's not to say it's a nervous system that is kind. It just means it's one of the two branches
of these so-called autonomic or immediate, not under your conscious control, right?
So the fight or flight. Exactly. And the other half being parasympathetic, sympathetic fight
or flight or hell breaking loose alarms going off parasympathetic, calm vegetative function.
So not only do you turn on the sympathetic during stress, you very emphatically turn off
the parasympathetic second main workhorse, which it's already been alluded to the steroid hormone
class of hormones called glucocorticoids, human version, cortisol, also known as hydrocortisone,
rat version, corticosterone, synthetic versions, prednisone, dexamethasone and such.
These come out of the adrenal glands. Your brain notes something stressful is happening within
two seconds. Your hypothalamus is secreting that CRH, which within about 10 seconds is getting your
pituitary to release a hormone called ACTH, which within about 30 seconds has gotten to your
adrenals and you are slowly starting the glucocorticoid component of your stress response.
And in lots of ways, the adrenaline, the sympathetic response, the glucocorticoid response,
they work on hand in hand, they synergize. You want a metaphor adrenaline in two seconds is
handing guns out of the gun locker to whatever is going to defend you. Leucocorticoids are
building the aircraft carriers that a year from now are going to be essential. It does some of the
slower components of the stress response, stretching out over minutes to hours.
Because I was just about to ask you, and I think your question basically answers it, was why would
we have evolved these two separate systems? One can only speculate on such things, but it's basically
that certainly norepinephrine, epinephrine, they stick around for such a short period of time. I
mean, we don't even measure these things clinically. I can't poke your arm and measure your
norepinephrine or epinephrine level. The best I can do is collect its metabolites in your urine
for evidence that it's been around. So I guess we have this hormone or pair of hormones that
are on the scene in seconds, gone in seconds and really deal with the, I guess from an evolutionary
perspective, when the tiger is there, this is what gets you to jump into the tree. Is it doing much
beyond that? And is there some evidence of chronic low levels of those hormones, which come out of a
totally different part of the adrenal gland? I mean, that's the other thing that's sort of interesting
is you have two separate pieces, the cortex, the medulla, that secrete these hormones separately.
And embryologically, they're two very different tissues. They start off separately. It could have
just as randomly wound up that your adrenaline comes from your big toe and glucorticoids from
your thumbs. Why they wound up being in the same organ is in fact, somewhat just I think serendipitous.
Probably because you're more likely to have your toes and fingers lopped off and we wouldn't want
to have an incidental adrenal ectomy happening. You're right. That's certainly why they didn't
wind up out there in the extremities. What about in lower species? Is one of these considered more
primitive? Is the epinephrine arm something that began earlier and the cortisol arm more recent?
Yep. Nonetheless, the cortisol arm is just ancient. When you get stressed and you're secreting
glucorticoids, it's basically the exact same class of molecules as if you were a fish or bird or
reptile. Nonetheless, it's a very ancient wiring and that's part of what winds up getting us in
trouble. It's a system that's been serving vertebrates, doing a lot of help for them for
an awful long time. It's been a very recent modification to instead secrete them in response
to thinking about taxes. This basic dichotomy between the very human domains where we activate
the stress response and the more typical domains of animals. If you and I were sitting here 10,000
years ago, I can think of lots of things that we would want an adrenaline response for. The
tiger jumps out of the thing, whatever. What are some of the things that would result in that
cortisol response? Because you described it as building the aircraft carrier. Well, gosh,
if the tiger's there, either I'm dead or I'm not, but I don't need a stress response a day from now
or the next day. What is it that cortisol was doing 10,000 years ago that was serving our
interests? I want to certainly talk about what it's not doing today. When you look at what it
does, it actually makes perfect sense as long as you're being stressed like a normal mammal,
running for your life, running after a meal where if you don't catch something,
you're going to be dead by tomorrow, a short term physical crisis. The first five seconds of doing
that, which epinephrine is critical for, that's great. If we're heading into a couple of minutes
of evading a predator, being vigilant, thinking there might be, if you were getting into the realm
of a couple of minutes worth of a stress response, cortisol related glucorticoid hormones are
absolutely essential. So the glucose that's coming rushing out of your liver,
pretty important in that situation. Exactly. So it takes you about one second to decide you're
going to use your thigh muscles and run like mad. You need energy for them. And the main thing
glucorticoids are doing in the metabolic realm is glucocorticoids. They're increasing glucose
levels in your bloodstream. They're going to storage sites throughout your body, your liver,
your muscle and breaking stuff. What they do is they go to the bank, they empty out your savings
accounts and turn it into cash, glucose in the bloodstream to hand to whichever muscles are going
to save your neck. What they also do makes perfect sense whether you were running for your life or
running for a meal, which is they increase cardiovascular tone. In epinephrine is doing
the first five seconds of it by 30 seconds in glucocorticoids, you're bolstering it as well.
And it's that same logic. You're running like crazy. You want to deliver that glucose to your
thigh muscles as quickly as possible. You increase your heart rate, you increase your breathing rate,
your blood pressure, you alter your vasculature. So you're preferentially shunting to the exercising
muscle. So that makes perfect sense. Also, it turns out some of the most interesting stuff
glucocorticoids do in those circumstances is basically run a triage program. They shut down
everything that's not essential, not essential to surviving the next five minutes of this massive
physical challenge. So digestion would be a measure. Exactly. You got better things to do
than digest breakfast when you're trying to avoid being somebody's lunch, and you're sure not going
to get any metabolic benefits of digestion during this five minutes. It's slow, expensive,
the energy you're getting, you're getting from your liver, you're getting from your fat cells.
It shuts down growth. Obvious logic there, you know, grow antlers tomorrow if you're still
around to a bother right now, shuts off reproduction. Same logic there. It shuts off
all the long-term building projects and just focuses your energies on what's immediately there.
And this makes perfect sense if you are running for your life, running after a meal, and all you
need to do is look at a couple of diseases where people don't turn on the endocrine stress response.
Addison's disease, Schi-Dryger's syndrome, whatever. These are not diseases where somebody
who now is more at risk for adult onset diabetes eight months from now. These are diseases where
somebody goes running after their commuter bus and they drop dead from hypoglycemic shock.
JFK had this. Didn't JFK have Addison's? He had Addison's and that greatly constrained
the famed pictures of all those Kennedys playing touch football out and, you know,
Martha's Vineyard or stuff were mostly for the benefit of the photographers.
How did he survive World War II? Because he had done some pretty heroic things in that war.
Although I've seen, it's hard to tell if it's snarky revisionism as to how much that was public
relations stuff afterward sort of orchestrated. But just to get through basic training even
strikes me as an accomplishment because most people, I guess, who don't have a medical background
wouldn't appreciate this, but the tan that seemed to be eternally on JFK is the result of the
Addison's disease because the hormone you alluded to earlier that is released by the pituitary,
ACTH, in someone who's not making cortisol is going to be very, very high. And ACTH stimulates
the pigment producing cells in the skin. And that's what would give someone with Addison's
disease darker skin. The fascinating thing with Kennedy is if it were this situation now,
presumably his doctors would be on the air somewhere 24 seven. There's remarkably little
known about when his onset was, what the course of it was, how severe it was. So it's not quite clear.
But what little is known is it had a hell of an impact on his functioning. You really do need a
hormone if you like glucorticoids, if you were going to be physically activated in a moment of
crisis. This is sort of the amazing thing with hormones like insulin and cortisol. I'm always
impressed by how tight the U shape is on those curves. Thyroid hormone would be another example,
certainly less so with something like testosterone. You have just a much wider range that you can
function in. And the benefit is largely monotonically increasing. Sometimes if my patients
will tolerate me going on and on about this, I love to draw the pictures of which of these hormones
can you, you know, but to me, cortisol probably, if you thought of it as a drug, it has the
narrowest therapeutic index to your point. Too much of it will kill you eventually and make you
miserable as hell on the way. And too little of it will kill you quite quickly.
And what's most interesting about it is, okay, so there's an optimal level among other ways of
translating that. That means we don't hate stress. We hate the wrong amount of stress. When it's the
right amount, we love it. We pay money to be stressed, to get on a roller coaster, to go to
a scary movie. When it's the right amount, when it's the optimal amount, we call it stimulation.
Okay, so exactly as you say, it's a narrow range. So that's a tough biological problem.
Understanding a hormonal system that's pretty damn essential and where an awful lot of the
time you're walking on a knife edge where either side is bad news, too much or too little. But when
it comes to glucorticoids and what counts as good stress and stimulation, there's the added factor
that there's incredible individual variation as to what counts as the optimal level in between.
And one person's like hair-raising Audubon Society walk one Saturday morning looking for birds,
while the other person goes and signs up to be a mercenary in Yemen because that's when they feel
alive and awake and all of that. Not only that it's a narrow range, but we differ so much as to
what each person's optimum is. Now I want to make sure I understand that point, Robert. And this is
probably overly simplistic, so feel free to correct this. One of it would be the external
scenario that is being perceived. And I can see definitely how two people can have vastly
different views on that. I mean, it's the reason someone can voluntarily go and be a Navy SEAL
and someone can say, I feel much better not doing that, right? There's clearly a different appetite
and or capacity for distress. Is that what you're referring to or are you also referring to
you and I could be sitting here and have different levels of physiologic benefit and harm at the same
level of cortisol? Both. I see. Absolutely. So I mean, the former, I think most people would
acknowledge the latter is pretty new, right? I mean, I shouldn't say pretty new. That's not intuitive
to me. Because there's centuries of endocrinology saying what's the most important thing about
hormones? How much of the stuff there is in your bloodstream? What the levels are? And if you and I
are sitting here with the same circulating levels of whatever centuries of dogma was, that will
translate into the same biological effects. And then I don't know, sort of endocrine revolution
of 70s, 80s or so. Turns out how loud someone is yelling at you counts what the hormone levels are,
how sensitively you can hear them. The levels of your receptors in target cells turn out to be
essential as well. And there's all sorts of endocrine domains where in fact, screwy receptor
levels are much more consequential and impactful than are screwy levels of the hormone itself.
And individual differences in levels of receptors, what version you have, how well it works, how
avidly it holds on to the hormone, what it is then coupled with afterward downstream inside
the cell. That whole world turns out to be as central to understanding individual differences
as are the levels of hormones themselves. And as sensitive to all those things ranging from genes
to prenatal environment to early development to psychological factors and so on. So yeah,
that's a huge piece of the story now. When I hear you say it like that, Robert, it seems pretty
obvious because we would talk about insulin in exactly that way. You could have two people with
the exact same level of insulin, completely different physiologic response because of insulin
sensitivity. When insulin hits its receptor, it leads to the phosphorylation of AKT and that's
what leads to the glute four transporter coming up to the surface. And different people with the same
insulin can do that totally differently and different people will have a different insulin
response to the same food, to the same meal. That's the reason we do glucose tolerance tests.
So you could basically say someone is cortisol sensitive and cortisol resistant to make the
analogy to insulin. At the end product end, absolutely. If you're an obsessive with cortisol
stuff in the eighties, there was briefly this deep puzzle in that it turned out New World monkeys,
monkeys in South America, marmosets, tamarins or whatever. When you compare them to traditional
old world monkeys, the Asian and the African ones, it turns out they have like an order of magnitude
higher glucocorticoid levels. Oh my God, that's crazy. What's that about? All sorts of theorizing
about how for some reason it's more stressful to be a new world primate than an old world,
which didn't make a whole lot of sense. And then there was this issue of these animals should have
been falling out of trees from their Cushing's disease. And finally somebody found an explanation.
Oh, somewhere back when there was a mutation in the gene for the glucocorticoid receptor
in New World primates and it has roughly one-tenth the sensitivity. So the system just
equilibrated out at a different set point, but that's such a great example of just natural
variation, not only in how loudly you speak hormone, but how effectively your cells listen to
hormone. Do you have a sense in the human population today? I mean a log-full difference
like you just described sounds extreme, but do you have a sense of what the variability is in
humans today? Is it a two-fold, three-fold delta on the receptor side? Gut feeling and reflecting
the fact that my world, the brain, you don't get to measure receptor levels anywhere near as easily
as in a white blood cell, well under an order of magnitude. We just acknowledged or you just pointed
out that when a zebra sees a lion, everything that happens as far as the fast and what I would call
the acute and the subacute stress response is perfectly evolutionarily sound and completely in
the best interest of that zebra. We could also come up with countless examples of 10,000 years ago
or even today when the same thing is true in humans. When did that transition occur in our species
to where you started to see either something in the civilization or a society that was unhealthy?
So today I could point to a thousand examples, social media, you name it. I mean it's an infinite
number. When did that start to crop up? What does your research suggest is the arrival of that?
I think it predated us being humans and instead is a feature of smart social mammals because you
see indices of stress-related stuff, baboons, that's what I've spent my whole career on,
and other non-human primates, cetaceans, elephants and such. Okay, so why study baboons if you're
trying to understand human stress? And it turns out they perfectly illustrate the point you just
brought up. If you're a baboon living in the Serengeti in East Africa, your life is pretty good.
It's a fantastic ecosystem. Baboons, they live in these big troops, 50 to 100 animals or so,
so they really don't have to worry about lions very often. The infant mortality rate is lower
than among the neighboring Maasai tribes people and probably most importantly, unless it's a once
a generation drought, if you're just a baboon going about your everyday business, it takes you
about three hours a day to get your day's calories and that has a critical implication, which is if
you only need to spend three hours of sunlight each day getting enough food to get by, you've got
nine hours of free time every day to devote to being miserable to some other baboon.
And that's the key thing. They are well off enough in our westernized sense
that they can sit around and generate psychological stress for each other. Overwhelmingly, if you're
a baboon in the Serengeti and you're miserable, it's because another baboon has worked very hard
to bring that state about. They're wonderful models for westernized disease in that very few
of us get hypertensive because, you know, tigers are chasing us. Instead, it's psychosocial stuff
that we invent and that we can wallow in for hours every day. And that's exactly what baboons
do. They're great models for westernized stress. Do we have evidence? I'm sure it exists, but
in the humans, I would just be willing to bet that if you and I were subjected to the same
external stressor, I would probably internalize it more than you. That's my guess. So if we were
both baboons and there was a third baboon tormenting us, is it safe to say that you could be the baboon
that would roll with it more than me? Individual differences like that, absolutely. My guess is
both of us would respond to it by saying, I'm just going to get a longer and longer CV and then
he's going to regret it someday pushing me around. They'll be sorry when they see how many degrees I
have. But yeah, individual differences. One of the things that I focused on, you know, I spent my
first 10 years deciding rank and status, social status, everything. If you're a baboon and you
got a choice in the matter, you want to be high ranking because on the average, you have lower
glucorticoid levels, your resting blood pressure is lower, all sorts of stuff works better.
But what took me some growing up out there to do was to realize that yeah, social rank is important.
Far more important is the contextual meaning of your rank. Is that the same as your perception
of your rank or is there there's more to it, right? Well, it's what the rank means in your particular
troop. You can be a low ranking guy in one of two different troops and one troop simply because of
its culture and that's a perfectly scientific word to use for another species these days.
In one troop, being low ranking could be a whole lot crappier than in another troop in terms of
how often somebody in a bad mood displays his aggression on you in terms of how often somebody
actually grooms you and off in terms of how often you get to finish a meal before somebody steals
it from you kind of thing. So the same exact rank means different things in different sort of
baboon cultures. So I'll take an extreme example. In a prison, there's a clear hierarchy starting
with the warden, the guards, the inmates and of course within the inmates there's a hierarchy.
Presumably I'm making this up but certainly the pedophiles would be at the bottom of that list and
a violent criminal would probably be at the top of that list. So within that hierarchy, there's
probably a manner in which you would be perceived as a function of that unique environment which is
so artificial in its own way but that wouldn't necessarily be the same outside.
Absolutely and one of the most interesting things about us, us humans, when we talk about
across all sorts of primates being low ranking in general is bad for your health or what about
humans, we don't have ranking in the same system that sort of other primates do in a strict linear
kind of way but the other thing about us is we belong to multiple hierarchies at once and we can
have very different ranks in them. So for example, family, work, sports team, hobby. Exactly. You've
got some guy who's the mail room clerk in this giant corporation and you could not possibly be
lower status but he's the captain of the company softball team this year and you better bet when
you ask him what's important in his life, nine to five Monday to Friday is just a stupid way to
pay the rent and what really matters is when the weekend comes around, you have somebody with a
horrible low status job who's the deacon of their church. We belong to multiple hierarchies and we
are very good psychologically at deciding that whichever hierarchy we're highest in, that's the
one we define ourselves by. Let's take another extreme example which is you take people who are
very successful in what they do, you know, whatever they're the most famous hedge fund manager or
an entrepreneur that started some great company, you would argue, well they seem to be pretty good
on the food chain but yet many of them would say or you could measure objectively their
hypercordicillemia is problematic. So it seems like there's even more than just that ranking,
right? Isn't there something else? Because they're at the top, if they were baboons,
they're the alpha but they're still grossly stressed out. In other words, thank God we're
more subtle than baboons but it turns out baboons were even more subtle than just rank.
They have personality and you can be a high ranking baboon and personality differences and
again this is as scientific a word as this culture. If you're a high ranking baboon and your worst
rival sneezing 100 yards away is seen as a major provocation, you're going to have much higher
glucorticoid levels than if you're a highest ranking baboon for whom that's no big deal.
And in fact often you may have higher glucorticoid cortisol levels than if you're number 10 or number
20 in the hierarchy. There's lots of psychological filter stuff and I spent a ton of time studying
that. Baboons differ as to how readily they see things as being provocative or not, threatening or
not. You're sitting there and again your worst rival shows up and takes a nap 100 yards away.
There can be two baboons of the same rank and one of them keeps doing exactly what he's doing
and the other one is interrupted from whatever nice social thing is happening. He's agitated and
he's vigilant. He's got to look at the guy and lunge towards him a couple of times before going
back. If your worst rival taking a nap is as disruptive as the guy threatening you in your
face, you average about twice the cortisol levels in your bloodstream after controlling for rank
as a guy who can tell the difference between the big thing and the little thing.
Maybe this is too deep a question and the answer isn't known but what is it that actually
transmits that information through the filter of your personality into the physiology that's very
well understood? So I understand the bookends, right? I understand how the visual cortex takes
the guy who's your enemy sleeping over there and transmits that to your cortex and then I understand
how the sympathetic chain kicks off the response. Is there a link in between those? The processing
link? Here's one of those filters. You take people and you're flashing up faces at them,
stick them in a brain scanner and you're looking at how jumpy their amygdala is. Their amygdala
central to fear, anxiety, aggression and such and what you see is tremendous individual differences
and you show somebody a face with kind of a neutral expression. Does this person look happy,
sad, angry, threatening, whatever and lots of variability and you look at the people who tend
to view neutral expressions as threatening. In other words, they see threats that most other people
don't. What does that correlate with? A bigger amygdala. Physically larger amygdala. A physically
larger amygdala. Amygdala with a higher metabolic rate and amygdala that is more
electrophysiologically reactive and stuff. Let's back up for a moment. I mean, tell people in case
they don't know where the amygdala sits, what part of the brain it evolved from and why it's sort of
referred to as this reptilian brain. I think everybody's heard of the amygdala, but I think
you could explain this in a more interesting and accurate way. Okay. Amygdala is like one of the
anchors of what's called the limbic system in the brain. Limbic system, it's the part of the brain
that's all about emotion. Not surprisingly, mammals have a whole lot more limbic development
than fish do. Fisher are not famous for their emotional lives. Limbic system is arousal,
fear, anger, lust, love, maternal, pair bonding, mother infant bonding, all of that. And it's a
whole series of structures. Not surprisingly, ancient in mammals. Not surprisingly, highly
complex interconnected. Not surprisingly, sitting underneath the cortex. The cortex that more
recently evolved part of the brain that does your taxes, all of that. Limbic system underneath there,
all this subterranean emotion stuff. An amygdala is one of the key limbic structures and it's involved
in fear. It's involved in anxiety. It's involved in aggression. You learn to be afraid of something
or somebody that didn't used to scare you. And your amygdala does the exact same sort of cellular
basis of learning that goes on in other parts of your brain. When you learn somebody's middle name
and actually remember it, your amygdala learns to be afraid of new things. And when you manage to
stop being afraid of something, when you stop being afraid of thems, because it turns out, oh,
they're actually more similar to you than you thought. It's your amygdala that becomes less
reactive to stimuli like that. So your amygdala is absolutely central to some of our worst human
moments. It's so interesting because it's sandwiched between, you can think of the human
brain as having sort of a very grossly three parts, right? This brainstem, this midbrain,
which the amygdala, you could argue is the mare. And then the cortex that you describe,
it's not an oversimplification, I think, to say that as the complexity of the organism evolved,
so too did that hierarchy, right? I mean, the brainstem basically handles everything we don't
have to think about ever, breathing and all of those autonomic and sympathetic parasympathetic
functions. And then you layer on this midbrain that does everything that you said, which is
still kind of happening beneath consciousness. And then of course, there's where most of us live in
our cortex where we're, or where we think we live, which is we're thinking these thoughts, but
it seems we're maybe not as aware of how influenced the cortex is by what lies beneath it.
Exactly. Which is incredibly important. If you think of this kind of ancient reptilian brainstem
part of the brain, what does it do? It keeps track. It makes you breathe every now and then
without having to think about a boring sort of stuff. Then on top is the emotional limbic system.
Then on top is that cerebral thinking cognitive cortex thing. It's very easy to come up with a
conceptualization that what's fancy about humans is, for example, you're a lizard. And the only
thing that's going to change the functioning of that ancient brainstem stuff is if you're bleeding,
if you're too hot, if you're too cold, just like boring physiological states. Once you layer a
mammalian emotional limbic system on top, suddenly you can do something no lizard or on earth can do.
You're sitting there and you're some wildebeest and some other scary wildebeest shows up and is
peeking on some tree in your territory and nothing regulatory has changed in your body,
but your heart starts beating faster. Aha! Your emotional brain can alter sort of the basic
regulatory stuff down in the basement. Now you go one step higher and you layer a cortex on top of
it and now you could do amazing stuff. You sit there and you think about the fact that your
heart's going to stop beating someday and you start breathing faster and your brainstem,
the more ancient stuff has altered as a result. And you've just done something not only that no
reptile can do, you've just done something that no warthog can do, which is think about something
that's scary or arousing or remember the time that you would and suddenly something changes down below
there. So there's this easy picture of sort of top-down complexity once you get to us and where
the cortex can regulate your emotional brain and that regulatory brain at the bottom, your emotional
limbic brain can regulate what's far more interesting or underappreciated is exactly
what you bring up, which is those lower levels can influence what's going on up above. One example of
this is like this classic great study in sort of physiological psychology, social psych. You take
people and I think in this study they would take male volunteers, heterosexual male volunteers,
and of course they were no doubt college freshmen taking psych 101. And they had these guys walk
across this really scary suspended bridge and the deal was that either halfway across the bridge
you were met by from the other side a researcher who happened to be an attractive female.
And she would ask the volunteer some questions, what do you think of this bridge or how is it
walking across this or whatever. The other half of the time you would not encounter this person
until you were safely out at the other end. Then they would ask you to evaluate the attractiveness
of the person. Same person. That same person. You're either seeing her in the middle of the bridge or
exactly saying, Hey, remember while you were doing that you there was this, you know,
do you want to rate her attractiveness? Was she friendly? Did she seem smart? And what you would
see is guys in the middle of the bridge with their hearts racing because they're terrified
would do some misinterpretation. Why is my heart beating so much faster than if I was standing
safely so they would rate her more attractively in the middle of the bridge. Exactly. And then
is the ceiling of detail is now you do the same experiment and you give the person a beta blocker
so that they don't have the accelerate and they don't rate the person as attractive.
Is it the same with the beta blocker? You would treat you.
You do nothing to their ratings of them as how smart they seem, how kind they seem, whatever.
It's just this. Okay. If my heart's racing, it must be because so that's a great example.
Boring reptilian regulatory stuff down there is helping influence what you think your emotions
are. That reminds me of that 1995 ish movie Speed with Keanu Reeves and I'm blanking our name.
That's right. Senator Bullock. Where at the end of that movie, there's some cheesy line about how
relationships that start under this much distress, you know, it's dangerous. But, but of course,
the other read on that now is yeah, if you're on a bus that's about to blow up,
like I think you're going to think the chair is attractive, right? Potentially.
Wow. I haven't thought of that movie in years. Thanks.
Sorry. You can go home and I'm sure Netflix will stream that for you.
Right. So I read something you wrote. I can't remember where it might have been in another
interview that, and I didn't know this, and this is a great example of why I just love doing this
podcast because there's never an exception to how much I'm learning. It's like drinking from
a fire hose. And you'd think I would have remembered this from medical school. The neuron
of a human and the neuron of some other organism, when you look at it at the single cell level,
can't really differentiate it. If I showed you two microscope slides and here's a human and here's a
fish. So what is it about? And this is maybe getting us a little off topic, but I also think
it feeds into this broader issue of like the stew and the alchemy of how this stuff is put
together. But if we all have the same neurons, what is it? Is it the number of our neurons? Like
what is it that enables us to have all of this additional torture? Yeah, it's incredibly
interesting because I mean, there's, there's three and a half people on earth who have spent their
entire careers being able to tell the difference between like a tree shrew neuron and a human
neuron and could recognize it in their sleep. But yeah, for the most part, we are not humans
because we have invented brain areas that you don't find in other mammals or because we've
invented neurotransmitters that you don't find in other vertebrates or types of neurons. There's a
couple of types of neurons that people used to think were specific to humans. And it turns out
you find them in elephants and whales also, and that's plenty interesting, but it's the same
enzymes. It's the same gene regulation. It's the same, you know, we're sharing 98% of our DNA with
a chimp or a bonobo. So you say where do humanists come from? I think it's exactly the issue you talk
about. We have the same signal transduction pathways and neurons as you see in a fruit fly.
And what's the key difference? Isn't that a bit humbling? Yes, it is. When we just think we're
that special. And it's the where you can take one of their genes or one of our genes and stick it in
the other one and it functions just fine. Or you could take it from a single cell organism,
some genes related to program cell death, you can do that. So what's the big difference for
every neuron that a fruit fly has? We have 100 million. And sort of the sound bite that I think
summarizes all of that is with enough quantity, you invent quality. And this is this whole world
of emergent properties of complex systems. You take one ant and you put it on a table and nothing
that it does makes a huge amount of sense. And you put 10 ants there and pretty much the same thing.
And you put on, I don't know, a thousand and maybe they start making a trail or something.
And you put 10,000 and they build a colony and they farm mushrooms and they take aphids as slaves
and they could keep the temperature in the colony plus or minus two degrees and they have
specialization of labor. And no ant has any more rules than he had when he was watering around
on the table by himself. And you put enough of them together and complex adaptive stuff emerges
out of the very simple rules that each of those components has for dealing with another component.
It almost defies entropy, doesn't it? Like why does that happen? It's amazing that it does that.
And that's what our brains are. We've got more ants that are coming together in our heads than
does a fruit fly. And you get more complex emergent stuff happening. It blows my mind. So let's go
back to some of this stuff. Maybe about a year ago I read something that really frightened me
because the implications were so significant. If a mother is under great stress, there was this
critical window in which her child could see something in her eyes that would communicate
that stress to her. Or maybe it wasn't in her eyes, might have been just through her entire face,
but it would imprint epigenetically into the child and alter many features about them as they would
age. For example, their propensity to be depressed. I remember reading this in a lay press thing,
so I don't even think it got into the description of epigenetics, but that was the only assumption
I could make was that this must be modulated through that mechanism. Do you see evidence of
this in animals? Absolutely. And it's one of the trendiest topics around being like
hooray, science finally recognizes childhood matters. What your childhood is like has a lot
to do with what sort of adult you're going to wind up being. What do you know? And like lots
of childhood adversity versus childhood security and very different trajectories. And what's been
the huge mechanistic challenge for the field is understanding. So what is it about being in a
scary neighborhood or an unstable home or having a parent read to you or what is it about this whole
world of developmental individual differences? What are the nuts and bolts changes that occurs
in a kid so that as an adult, they are now 30 fold more likely than the next person for this or that
to happen to them. And this whole trendy field of epigenetics, which is early experience doesn't
change your genes, doesn't change your DNA sequence with some like circus trick exceptions. You've
pretty much got your DNA sequence forever. What epigenetics is, is early experience changing the
regulation of your genes, how easily you turn certain genes on, how easily you turn others off
in different parts of your body, different parts of your brain and so on. And that's exactly the
sort of domain where you see the sort of stuff that you outlined. So that, for example, if you're
a fetal rat and you, that rat have made a terrible decision. You've picked the wrong room
to be developing in and you happen to be inside a mother who's highly stressed.
She's secreting a lot of rat glucocorticoids, which get into the circulation through the placenta
and to the fetal circulation into the kid's brain. And one of the things that it does is it causes an
epigenetic change in the amygdala. So is that rat going to be born with a larger amygdala or is the
phenotype more complicated than just size? It's size and a bunch of other things. As an adult,
it's going to have a bigger amygdala and it's going to be more excitable and it's going to be
more prone towards interpreting a neutral situation as a threatening one. That's virtually
the definition of rat anxiety disorder, seeing menace that other people don't. And you see much
the same evidence in humans by now. Early experience. Forget early experience. What kind
of kindergarten teacher you had. This is fetal early experience. And this is exactly a domain
where you get potentially the lifelong epigenetic effect. Okay. So that turns out to have a hell of
an implication. That's just the most exciting subfield around there by now. Okay. So you were
fetus and got exposed to lots of moms glucocorticoid levels. And as a result, as an adult, you've gotten
a large amygdala and you see threat all over the place that other rats don't. And among other things,
you secrete elevated levels of glucocorticoids because the world is full of menace that only
you were seeing. So you get pregnant and during your pregnancy, as a result, your fetus is exposed
to elevated glucocorticoid levels. And to be clear, it's not because you have altered the germline
genome. It's that you have changed the expression of the gene which has altered the phenotype. And
now that phenotype is being passed generation to generation through parallel expression.
Exactly. Something termed non genetic transmission of traits, non Mendelian. And people have now shown
some of those traits. You see that ripple. It gets smaller each generation, but it's there half a
dozen generations later. And the exact equivalent of some of these have been found in humans. In other
words, individual differences are arising not only from experience, but from the multi-generational
transmission of some of the consequences of experience, which is just mind boggling that
that can work that way. Let's go back a little bit to why this is problematic. So at the outset,
we alluded to this idea that it's a misnomer to say stress kills. I'd love to hear if you have
a particular definition of stress. I probably butcher this stuff, but I sort of think of stress
as the external thing. And I think about it as it's anything that is sort of emotionally or
physically either chronically or acutely distressing. I mean, that's sort of a dumb
definition because it contains the word stress, but I think people understand distress a little
more than they understand stress. But of course, it's your response to that physiologic response,
right? So we can quantify this stuff in terms of what hormones are happening in the body and how
the hormones are moving the body. It's your response to that that probably has a greater
impact on your health. So let's go through three things. Help me understand how hypercorticillemia
and or its accompanying features will impact the brain, especially, well, through any timeline you
want. I'm obviously interested in the aging brain, but I can't imagine this also doesn't
impact the developing brain. This is basically what I've spent my whole professional career
thinking about. And historically, the first place where people sort of realized something
scary was happening was a brain region called the hippocampus. Hippocampus is all about learning and
memory. You want to have a hippocampus. It's the main brain region that's damaged in Alzheimer's
disease, and it's vulnerable in lots of other ways. Turns out it's extremely sensitive to
glucorticoids translated more reductively. It's got extremely high levels of receptors for
glucorticoids by the standards of the rest of the brain. And what's the evolutionary basis for that?
Is that to have a feedback loop? There's two reasons. One is to have a feedback loop, but the
other is, okay, so the hippocampus remembers stuff for you. You don't remember everything.
You don't remember where you were on 9-10 as opposed to 9-11 kind of thing. Your memory
processes has to come with a filter saying, is this one important? So you're saying the cortisol
amplifies memory consolidation and that you use this to consolidate stressful memories as a way
of learning. Exactly. Along with epinephrine and norepinephrine indirectly, they have some of the
same effects. So cortisol crosses the blood-brain barrier with no difficulty? Exactly. I assume
epi and norepinephrine do the same? They have to work more indirectly, heavily through the
vagal nerve because they don't get them as readily, but some of it is also norepinephrine being
released within the brain during stress. So it has some of its own memory enhancing effects.
Again, a great example of evolution has got this awesome system set up, and it only gets out of
whack when the stimulus becomes too much. You do want that imprint, but you don't want that
happening full-time. Or stated another way, this is the reason why you don't get much out of a class
if you're semi-comatose and you had two hours of sleep last night. If you're like three-quarter,
your glucocorticoid levels are low, you're not consolidating stuff. If you are out of your mind
terrified because there's a lion sitting next to you, you're not going to absorb much either
inverse you optimal range, all of that. So it turns out the optimal amount of glucocorticoids,
something that is moderately stressful, in other words, something stimulating,
does great stuff to your hippocampus. It increases blood delivery there, glucose, oxygen, it makes the
synapses, the connections between neurons more excitable in the hippocampus, does great stuff,
a little bit of arousal, alertness is a good thing for learning and memory. Now instead,
transition to you are stressed 24-7 ever since you were like 10 years old kind of thing,
and you're in the range where glucocorticoids do exactly the opposite. They decrease oxygen and
glucose delivery to the hippocampus. They make neurons less excitable, they disconnect synapses,
they cause the processes and neurons to shrivel, they block the birth of new neurons there,
they make other insults more damaging to neurons in the hippocampus. What you have there,
that's the world in which if you were stressed out of your mind, memory doesn't work so hot.
And what we're increasingly realizing is if you're exposed to excessive glucorticoid levels like on
the scale of years to decades, you're going to make this part of the brain get older faster.
Which speaks to something that I know you're quite passionate about, which is
the differences in how socioeconomic status can affect generational changes in this manner.
Because you use the example of a 10-year-old. Well, I did my residency in Baltimore. Let me
tell you a 10-year-old in inner city Baltimore who's in the wrong house versus a 10-year-old
in Palo Alto who's in quote unquote the right house. And look, that's not to say that you could
have a 10-year-old in Baltimore that's got a great environment and 10-year-old in Palo Alto
that's dealing with a whole bunch of other different issues, which especially in the era
of social media. But all things considered, probabilistically that 10-year-old in Baltimore
is going to have a much harder time given what you just said.
Or I don't know stated the other way. I have a friend who's a cardiologist who splits his time
between a hospital in Oakland and a private practice in San Francisco. Some of the time what
he's doing is dealing with 80-year-olds who are considering getting a pacemaker because the ski
season is coming and they were wondering if they're going to be in shape and time for that.
And then back in Oakland, he's dealing with 50-year-old elderly men who are having heart disease.
Yeah. Socioeconomic disparities are, I won't get on my soapbox now. When you look at the source of
variability in health among humans on this planet, socioeconomic differences, differences in absolute
levels, differences in degrees of inequality within cultures and within communities and so on,
there's an enormous predictor of health. You want to look at the most medically impacted,
low ranking primates you could find on earth. Look at poor humans, because when humans invented
socioeconomic status and the capacity to be poor, they invented a way to subordinate the have-nots
like no chimp on earth could ever dream of doing. As you've alluded to, there's something else to it.
Recently I interviewed an amazing physician named Tom Kattena who practices in the Nuba Mountains in
the south of Sudan. So he's the only physician to take care of one million people who, as you know,
are being killed by their own government. Bashir is indiscriminately killing these people.
So my discussion with Tom was one of the most riveting discussions I've ever had with a human
being. It just happened to be in front of a microphone. But one of the things that just as
an afterthought we were discussing that surprised me is we were going through all of the different
things that people die of there. They don't have vaccines. You've got measles outbreaks that are
killing people left, right in the center and the trauma, like the shrapnel blowing people apart.
Not surprisingly, they're just not getting the same chronic diseases. And the cancers they get
are not the cancers we get and they're not getting heart disease and they're almost unheard of to get
type 2 diabetes. But what really surprised me is there was no suicide. And I found that as the
single most interesting thing I guess I learned from Tom, which was we would look at their life
and think that is an abysmal existence that I couldn't tolerate for one second. And yet I would
have to guess that their level of cortisol might be lower than ours, even though they're in a much
worse environment. So whether it's that sense of community that they have or the shared purpose,
there's something about it. So in other words, my point is even in the presence of such great
poverty, it seems that there's ways that this can be overcome, whether it's through there's no
comparison to anybody else, because another point he made was most of the folks there don't even
know they're in Africa. Like they don't necessarily know that Africa is the continent in which their
country resides. So is the bigger issue there you think that there's no disparity? So even though
that's complete poverty, there's no real perceived disparity, or do you think it's the sense of
community? Like what would you hypothesize explains that health, that mental health?
All the above. There's a whole world of people who study happiness, along with more traditional
public health people who study things like longevity. You look at the quarter poorest
places on earth, and indeed people there don't live very long and are miserable.
But once you get past sort of the subsistence level, there's not a great relationship between
the wealth of a country GDP per capita, anything, and levels of happiness or life expectancy.
And you look at the fact that the US has a shorter life expectancy than Cuba and Lebanon and
Costa Rica. And it's like the shame of this country kind of thing. Once you get past mere
subsistence level, income is not a great predictor of any of this stuff. And that's instead where you
get into worlds of social capital and social support. And when you look at the whole literature
and you look basically at every westernized country on earth, and it's now seen as they become
westernized, and what you see is the health socioeconomic gradient. The poorer you are,
the worse your health on the average. The more of a whole array of diseases you get, not all of
them, but a huge number, the more impactful they are. And when you look in the west, the United
States is the poster child for that. We've got the steepest curve in any country on earth.
In the westernized world, the least steep ones are you bet, of course, the Scandinavian countries
ever reliable, sort of utopias. And then you begin to unpack why this relationship occurs. And like
some incredibly smart people have spent their careers looking at it. The most obvious one is,
if you're not healthy, it's very hard to pull off being the CEO of a company. Poor health precedes
and gives rise to poor socioeconomic status. Okay, that's plausible. That turns out to explain a tiny
percent to the variability. And you could look at the status socioeconomic status of the home in
which a child is raised. And that's a predictor of their likelihood of diabetes half a century later.
So absolutely, the socioeconomic status comes first in explaining the vast percentage of the
variability. Okay, so next thing, maybe it's just that, well, everybody's kind of equally healthy.
It's just that the really poor people are very unhealthy. We have a step function. No, you start
with Jeff Bezos and Bill Gates and every step down there and statistically, the lower you go down,
every rung of the way, the poorer you are. The poor you are with respect to health. I'm sorry,
the poor your health. Yes, yes, thanks. So now you unpack that. And what's the most obvious
explanation? And this is what people call a neo materialist explanation, which is obvious to poor
you are. You don't have health care access. You don't have health insurance, you can't go to the
doctor as readily your care is more lousy. That's obviously that explains everything that explains
virtually none of the variability in the data. Because you see the gradient nonetheless in
countries with socialized medicine, universal health care, you see it for diseases where it
doesn't matter how often you get health care access, juvenile diabetes, so it shows an SES
gradient kind of thing. So it's not health care access. You then look cross culturally and you see
wildly different income levels and wildly different levels of health care access. And you see very
similar lifespans across these countries and very similar gradients. So what people spent like the
last 30 years doing is having this huge shift towards it's got so little to do with the material
aspects of wealth or poverty, it's got to do with the psychological aspects, it's got to do with the
stress. First key finding, somebody at UCSF named Nancy Adler, who's done wonderful research,
showing, okay, your socio economic status, your wealth, your objective measure of wealth,
is indeed a predictor of your health. Turns out, at least as good of a predictor is your
subjective socio economic status. On the level when you look at people around you, how are you
doing compared to other people? Where would you place yourself on this 10 step ladder in terms of
what's your absolute SES? What's your subjective one? And by asking it that way, you're asking the
person to consider the community that's most pertinent to them. Who's the comparison group?
My next door neighbors, Warren Buffett, in between whatever. When you think of other people, how are
you doing compared to them? And it turns out your subjective SES is at least as good of a predictor
of your health as is your objective. In other words, if you took someone's income, which is quite
objective, it would offer no more prediction than asking that person in the Nuba Mountains,
where do you rack up in this tribe? And it's sort of like, you know, sort of top two thirds.
Yeah, exactly. Or another way of stating that is you look in some bloated corporation,
and there's some guy who's the assistant manager of the mail room, and that's an incredibly
status-filled position for that guy. And there's some other guy who's number two in the company,
who was just passed over to be number one. And the only pertinent thing in his mind is not the
99,000 employees that he's higher ranking in, that there's still somebody ahead of me. And you can
see the same thing in baboons. In other words, it's not being poor, it's feeling poor. The next
critical piece in the story is work from this guy, Richard Wilkinson in the UK, who shows
what's the best, most like effective way to make somebody feel poor, independent of their absolute
levels of income, surround them by inequality, surround them by reminders of all the people who
are doing better than them. I mean, this is where social media, it's the amplifier to all amplifiers
of this, right? You can't go 10 minutes if you're on it without looking at somebody who's obviously
better looking, obviously smarter, obviously richer, obviously having more fun. I think this
has been pretty well documented, right? Lifestyle or the rich and famous, or you could be driving
down a freeway and somebody passes you, and I don't know what counts as a high status car these
days that cost a fortune, but they come speeding past you and you can feel crappy and diminished
and like a less successful human, and you never even saw that person's face. This is unheard of
in the history of humans or primates of being able to feel socially subordinated, and you don't even
interact with the person. Oh, there's people out there with, you know, at least if the next door
neighbor has more camels than you, that's a very like tangible, real thing in terms of like likelihood
of surviving that extract. Income inequality explains the mediating effect between objective
socioeconomic status, subjective socioeconomic status, and health outcome. What I'm hearing you
also say, though, that's a more subtle spin on this is it's not necessarily global income inequality,
it's local income inequality that is much bigger. But what technology has allowed us to do is explain
what counts as local. That's right. That's exactly right. It's expanded what local means. You can sit there and
watch, I don't know, Lifestyles or the Rich and Famous. And back when you would never have gotten
into like the Petty or Phyfton's Castle or whatever. And now you can see all the crap they have that
you're never going to get and feel less loved as a result. It's so interesting to hear you talk about
this. This is a topic that I think anybody listening to this is well aware of, especially if you're a
parent, because you also have to think about this through a developmental lens, which is
at least when you and I grew up, I didn't grow up with a lot, but you really had no idea what was
different, right? Like you simply, everybody was the same. I mean, everybody's parents bought used
cars instead of new cars and everybody had more or less the same sort of, you know, clothing that
wasn't exactly the best and whatever. So at least you could argue, well, were we at least spared some
of this difficulty during a critical window of development? And what happens now to a 10 year old
that's got a smartphone and is subjected to this? Because I remember that funny show Lifestyles or
the Rich and Famous, I can still sort of hear the goofy cheesy theme song. I think I even probably
watched it once or twice as a kid, but it's a lot easier when that's the one exposure you have to
extreme wealth or disparity and either you can watch it for one hour or not. But it's quite a
different thing if not to pick on the Kardashians. I'm just, but if you're inundated with, oh my god,
look at how awesome the Kardashians are and what they're doing and how great their life is and
multiply that by three log orders. Do we have any data that suggest that we are at a critical
juncture? Because I was having this discussion with a friend yesterday, which is, is there evidence
of any greater transition in technology in both a positive and negative way than this generation to
the last? Is this truly the greatest step forward? I would assume so, but the things we worry about,
people have been worrying about for centuries. Oh my, kids, they don't go outside, they don't play,
they don't have like meaningful relationships because they spend all their time talking on
the telephone. They spend all their time listening to their transistor radio. So maybe we're blowing
this up. Maybe this is just this generation's version. I mean, I guess the one difference is
when you're talking on the telephone, when you're listening to the transistor radio, I don't know if
it creates that global to local phenomenon quite as easily or as quickly or with less resistance
as we see. Maybe you're right. Maybe this has always been one generation's struggle with the last.
But what you get is an amplifier now, because if you're an insecure, socially isolated,
peri-adolescent kid who's vulnerable in all sorts of ways, and no matter what decade or century it
was, you're the last one picked for the game. You're the one who's least popular or whatever,
and that has all its corrosive effects. Now, if you really set your mind to it and you're that kid,
you could spend 24-7 just wallowing, toxically, in evidence of a gazillion other people who are
better looking than you and more popular and invited to parties. It amplifies further.
And the technology does absolutely that. What I think it does is it makes the vulnerable
more damaged than in the past. I think it's safe to say these amplifiers aren't going anywhere.
So rather than wallow in their harm, I guess the more relevant question is, what do we do?
If you're a parent today or not a parent today, and you're thinking about this through the lens
of yourself versus your kids, whatever, what are the steps that one can take to become less
susceptible to these forces that seem to drive this? Because I want to step back for a moment.
When I think about these areas that we've talked about before about the impact of nutrition and
sleep and exercise and stress or distress to make it more the term I use, when I think about
this personally, the one I most worry about is the last one. I think I've got a pretty good handle
on nutrition and it's in many ways easier to control. I feel like I'm more in control of what
I eat and when I make bad choices, I'm usually doing them consciously like I've decided I'm going
to eat this pizza versus I can't help myself I'm going to eat this pizza. Similarly with exercise,
and again I'm not saying this for anybody else, but this is just my personal thing.
And even with sleep, once you commit to it, which is not something I did until probably seven or
eight years ago that I sort of committed to, wow this really matters and to forego this thing,
bad idea, it's this last one that really drives me crazy, which of course doesn't help matters
because the fact that it drives you crazy makes it worse. But I'll give you an example,
as a general rule, outside of the immediate postprandial period of a high glucose meal,
far and away my highest blood glucose is always in the morning. Now I wear a 24-hour glucose meter,
so I'm kind of a weird guy. For almost four years I've been wearing a glucose monitor all the time.
So it measures my glucose 24-7 at one minute increments and out of say 365 days in the year,
I'm easily wearing it 330 days of the year. So I've got a lot of data and without a question,
when you look at a 24-hour period, if you stripped away the x-axis of time, I could easily identify
mourning for you without exception. I'll give you an example, this is not something I'd plan to do.
I had breakfast yesterday, yesterday being Sunday, really early because I woke up with my kids made
breakfast. I normally don't eat breakfast, but I did. So I had a breakfast 730 in the morning,
did a workout, had to catch a flight, didn't have time to eat after, had a very, very busy day,
didn't eat a single thing, got to the hotel around 1030 or 11, didn't want to eat, so didn't.
Got up this morning, it's been almost 24 hours since a meal and I looked at my glucose meter
and it was like said 110, 110 milligrams per deciliter. I was like, there's no way that's right.
Calibrated it, sure enough it was 110. Now there is no earthly reason I should have had a glucose
of 110 milligrams per deciliter, 24 hours after my last meal, which by the way was bacon and eggs.
It's not like I was eating pancakes, right? Well, I promise you if I could spot check my cortisol,
it was high. And here's the thing, before I went to bed, my glucose was quite low.
You know, my glucose was probably 80 when I went to bed and it slowly rose. And sure enough,
as my day wore on today, the glucose went lower, lower, lower, lower, lower,
it was about 78 before you walked in here. I'm not alone by the way, so I've seen this a lot
clinically with patients. Once you start putting these 24 hour glucose sensors on people, which
a lot of my patients are now doing, you get this insight into this horrible thing that's happening
when we think we're sleeping and nothing else is going on, but we're ruminating or God knows what else.
And fits perfectly with morning wakening is when you get your highest glucorticoid levels,
which is probably one of the main driving forces on the increased blood glucose. And when you think
about it from a circadian standpoint, what's the most challenging thing you have to do each day in
the absence of any major tumult? Get up, start functioning, all of that. It just seems like it's
disproportionate. Certainly the dawn effect has been well described. It's more amplified in people
with type two diabetes, which is another interesting point, right? Which is why is it that someone who
already has glucose dysregulation would have an even higher cortisol response in the morning?
And yet you'll see, you know, enormous fluctuations in glucose. I guess my point here is this seems
like a harder problem to fix. And certainly meditation is by far the best tool I have ever
found to even approximate getting this under control. But it's still hard because it's not
like you have a pill. If your blood pressure is high, well, I think it's probably best to fix it
in any way possible. But we also have really great drugs that fix high blood pressure that can at
least mask these things. We don't have a pill to fix hypercorticillemia. It's one of the most
complicated endocrine situations. And yet as you've described eloquently, it's also so innately
wired into us. And we have this miserable midbrain that's just killing us. First of all, I'd love to
hear your thoughts on meditation, but then also other things that given how much time you've spent
thinking about this problem, I'd love to know how you would suggest someone who doesn't have quite
the Zen mindset that I can tell you do. What should someone else be thinking? Right off the bat,
I'm delighted to see that I have a persona of a Zen person. I'm actually like one of the most
type-A stressed people you're ever going to run across. I've spent 40 years professionally
studying how bad the outcome is going to be of all of these bad lifestyle aspects without having
anything insightful to say about how to actually fix it or prevent it. And I certainly have learned
personally absolutely nothing from my lifetime of work. I'm like incredibly stressed. I'm mostly
good at telling you what's going to happen if you don't get stuff under control rather than how to
get things under control. When I look at the stress management literature, I don't do it very often
because I tend to get sort of agitated at that point, but broadly it works. It works as in you can
lower blood pressure, you can lower cholesterol levels, you can lower subjective sense of health,
objective measures as well with all sorts of interventions. What you see when you look at
the literature closely, first off is you can't do your stress management on the weekends kind of
thing. It needs to be a regular sort of thing. You can't do it while you're on hold on the phone for
30 seconds. You need to set time out for it. The benefits of aerobic exercise, I don't know what
the magic number is these days, but 20 or 30 minute blocks is a minimum to start getting the
cardiovascular benefits. So it's got to be something like you stop things to do.
So that's important. Let's double click on that. What you're basically saying is,
because I think you're understating how much you know about this topic. Obviously,
it's something you know a lot about as seriously as we would take nutrition. And if you think about
how many hours a week do you put into eating? I mean, even if you're shoveling food down your
throat, it still takes quite a bit of time. If you're going to exercise to the levels that have
demonstrated benefit, we're talking about hours a week, not minutes a week. If you're going to
make the difference between getting by on sleep versus getting restorative sleep, I'm not talking
about the absolute amount of sleep. I'm just talking about the delta between those two.
Think about how many hours that is. In fact, for the average American, that would work out to be
about an extra seven to eight hours a week of sleep. And what you're basically saying is,
if you want to combat this hypercordous selebia dude, guess what? It ain't a 20 minute a week
thing. And in some ways that taps into one of the 80-20 rules of sort of mental health professionals.
Okay, so you have this crazy stressful lifestyle and there's just a bazillion things you can't say
no to and you're just going 24-7. And if you've gotten to the point of saying, this is crazy,
this is not a quality life. I want to live a healthy, quality old age. Well, I got to get
this stuff under control. I'm going to start doing something stress managementy. And if you've gotten
to the point where in this lifestyle where there's a billion things you can't say no to each day,
you're saying no to them enough that nonetheless 20 minutes every single day you are doing this,
it almost doesn't matter what intervention you're doing. You're 80% of the way there already
if you're managing to do that. And that's very similar to this sort of amazing classic finding.
You get people who are clinically depressed and finally, finally, finally, they're going to do
something about it and merely making a first appointment. Even before you've seen the person,
people feel significantly better because you are finally saying, I matter enough to do something
about this or I'm activated enough or I'm optimistic enough to actually go. You're halfway
there at that point merely by doing something on a near daily basis. So just on that logic,
even though I don't know that this has been done, you would argue that 10 minutes of deliberate
mindful practice of meditation daily would probably be better than one hour once a week.
Absolutely. In part because if nothing else, if you do it daily seven times a week, you were sitting
in the aftermath of having done that versus only one time a week and an awful lot of what's most
interesting about physiology and its impact on mental health, things like that is what's happening
in the recovery period after something like that. In the same way, one awful hour long stressor a
week versus punctuated episodes of it throughout the week without question, the latter is worse
because you've now got umpteen different times that you have to recover from having turned on
the stress response. And that's where a lot of the damage occurs. I learned something about
myself that's going to sound so stupid because it's so obvious. Although I don't think it's true
for everybody, email is a huge stress to me. To be blunt, I hate it. That would be the kindest thing
I could say about email. I really a few months ago hit a true nadir in my response and I'm like
looking at these glucose levels going up and I'm looking at these morning glucose levels. So even
though my overall glucose levels still look great, I mean this trend was upsetting to me. I'm watching
my resting heart rate in the morning go up. Over the course of four months it had gone up like
six beats per minute and if anything I was in better shape exercising more regularly.
I made this observation one day which is how many times in a day do I stop to look at email,
even if it's just to check one or two? And the answer was like 50.
And every time I do it to your point, even if it's very brief, the after effect is not that brief. So
I could look at an email and see two stressful things but it might sit with me for 20 minutes.
So I tried this experiment which is I'm going to just check email twice a day,
two 30-minute blocks of email and I would say within two weeks I just really felt better.
It seems to me like we just have to figure out ways to figure out what those
triggers are for us individually. There's probably some people for whom email doesn't trigger them
at all. For me Twitter doesn't trigger anything because A, I have a very narrow window that I
pay attention to and it doesn't involve things that are aggravating like politics or religion
or whatever. It just sort of I'm only really following science. So anytime I look at Twitter
I'm actually learning something kind of new but I'm sure there are many people listening to this
who would say oh my god, if I spend an hour on Twitter my blood pressure could be through the
roof. So it's like everyone's got to kind of pick their thing. You said you're type A which obviously
you are. I mean you know what I didn't say at the outset when we started speaking but you've won
one of the most prestigious awards imaginable which is the MacArthur award and you won that
about 30 years ago, right? That's impressive. They don't give that award out lightly so that's the one
that's referred to as the Genius Award and I know you're probably like your skin is crawling when I
say that. My point being is you're an incredibly accomplished successful guy. It's not surprising
you would describe yourself as a type A. What have you learned about yourself over the past
30 years or even longer going back to your first days in Kenya about what those triggers are for
you and what you can do to lower your cortisol levels? Not surprisingly if you hang out with
people who are field biologists of any sort and again I've only been a part-time annual one over
the decades but nonetheless still think of myself as a field biologist. We're kind of a solitary
tribe. I mean during my peak periods of doing field work I'm spending three, four months a year alone
living in a tent where 12 hours a day I wouldn't say a word to another person. Temperamentally this
is kind of who I've been for a long time and there was always this ironic thing because I was sitting
there studying these baboons because I'm interested in primate social behavior and there's big sort
of epiphany I had in my work that okay your social rank as a baboon has something to do with your
health but much more importantly is your patterns of socialization and social networks and how often
do you groom and how often does somebody groom you and how often do you sit in contact with
another baboon or playing with an infant and then I finish the day's work and go back to my tent.
So there was something ironic that I was like studying the health benefits of sociality,
living alone in a tent, a large part of the year. Your wife is a scientist too isn't she? She was,
she kind of decided she was sick of it and she now directs a musical theater program which is
much more fulfilling for her but at one point my wife came along. Yeah yeah that's what I was going
to ask. And eventually family and you know kind of realizing oh I've missed out on an awful lot
of what are really like the wonderful worth living for moments in life out of the sociality stuff
and that is a refuge and a sanctuary from the world's madness and I could not have predicted
as a 20 year old who had been planning to be a field biologist for a dozen years at that point
I could not have predicted sort of how much of my equilibrium at this point turns out to be due to
interacting with the right two or three other primates like being in love with them and stuff.
That one was kind of a revelation for me. I am not the social being that I would have guessed I would
have been back when. Which is interesting because having this discussion with you today I can sense
much more of your introversion than the first time we met when you were giving an unbelievably
charismatic animated talk and I don't know how many of us were there maybe a hundred people and
which is so interesting right because you would I think anybody sitting in the audience would look
at this and say oh that's that's the life of the party but it's interesting that we can compartmentalize
and separate those things right I mean you couldn't get up there and you can do what you need to do
and you're at your happiest I'm guessing in the way you described it versus in the aftermath of
that talk when a hundred people run up to you to ask you four questions each. Not to get too
self-reflective or something but I'm a fairly introverted person who does better with scripts
and giving a lecture is a pretty structured script and having sort of an academic persona
or whatever is another version of it as well. What year did you become a full professor at Stanford?
It was 33 or something early 90s. I mean you live in San Francisco so you're not making that commute
every day I hope. Nope but I did for about a quarter century. Yeah that'll that'll hurt the
cortisol levels won't it? I used the commuter train caltrain here. So you could read and
I loved it I loved this was much of it was before cell phones. So you'd pick it up at fourth and king
and you'd just go yeah I used to make that ride all the I used to have a girlfriend that lived in
San Francisco and I loved that train ride and then you get off on your bike at fourth and king
and you could go anywhere in the city. Exactly I wrote half my book writing was on the train there.
It's pretty weird when you realize that like one of your valid social communities or the conductors
on caltrains or as you're watching them grow up on you and things like that but yeah no that was
I was a big fan of train commuting. So speaking about books let's talk about your more recent
book. It's about human behavior which you know I mean I can see based on this discussion now how
your interest would shift to that. What was the impetus for that research? Well title is behave
the biology of humans that are best and worst and sort of as we were talking about before I closed
my lab four years ago and stopped active research to sit for four years and write this book and it's
basically trying to make sense of the biology of what is for me the most puzzling thing about us
as a behaving species which is we are simultaneously the most miserably violent species on earth
and the most altruistic and cooperative and empathic and any given human is capable
depending on the setting of incredible gyrations as to whether they are being wonderful or awful
or in between or behaviors where whether that counts as good or bad is incredibly dependent
on what culture they happen to be doing it in. Just trying to make sense of the biology I mean
totally boring biology as to like how your brain makes you do something like pull a trigger like
which muscle groups have been told like that's that's like studying cockroach neurobiology.
What's totally interesting is the fact that we're a species we're sometimes pulling a trigger can be
one of the most awful things a human can do and sometimes it could be one of the most wondrous
ones if you're suicidally drawing fire from innocent people and you're sacrificing yourself
or in one setting you put your hand on somebody else's and that could be a moment of incredible
compassion or in another moment you do the exact same thing with your primate muscles and that's
the first step of betraying a loved one of just making sense of this contextual stuff about human
behavior which is hugely complicated and the song and dance that I go through in nearly 800
agonizing pages in the book is you're going to understand nothing about that if you've concluded
aha we now know this is the part of the brain that explains everything or this is the neurotransmitter
or the hormone or the gene or the child instead to make sense of human behavior you got to factor
in what your neurons did one second ago but you got to factor in the environmental triggers of that
30 seconds ago and you've got to factor in what your hormone levels were like this morning
and what neuroplasticity you've done over the last two seasons and what your adolescence was
like in your childhood and your fetal life and your genes and amazingly what sort of culture
were your ancestors inventing centuries ago because that influenced the way you were raised
within minutes of birth and what things you value and what things your amygdala does or doesn't
respond to and all the thing of that what sort of ecosystems produce different types of cultures and
then finally evolution and why we're in some ways like chimps and in some ways like bonobos
but we're not chimps we're not bonobos we've solved our own special evolutionary like you've
got to understand this stuff it's everything from one second before to a hundred million years before
and all these levels interact and it's complicated as hell. When people ask the question which I'm
sure you've heard this a hundred times and you hear people asking all the time are we innately
good or bad that question doesn't really permit the level of nuance you're describing the answer
is yes. Yes exactly and what's most startling about us is most of us have the capacity to do
something that we would be stunned and sickened that we were capable of doing it and most of us
are capable of in some circumstance of doing something that is so damn heroic and most of
us spending most of our time doing things that instead are ambiguous and multi-layered and full
of ulterior motives and what's really going on there and you look at the worst of us and the best
of us and there's not a whole lot of really reliable predictors beforehand. And how much of
this like you know you wrote a little bit about PMS so when I think about PMS I think about it
purely through the lens of the endocrine system right I think of it purely through the lens of
when a woman is in her luteal phase that progesterone level has to rise for the placenta
and then of course virtually every time it's a false alarm you don't need it you shed that
lining and that progesterone level comes crashing down and it's this crashing down a progesterone
that has always interested me why two women could experience the same we can measure progesterone
levels throughout the cycle and we could know that at day 22 two women could have the exact
same progesterone and on the first day of their menses they could have the same progesterone so
you know they had the same peak to valley and yet two women can experience that in two totally
different ways now I've thought about that through the lens of progesterone receptors and you know
the way we sort of talked about the cortisol stuff is there something else to that that you layer on
top of that that is even more subtle about those differences yeah tons of this sort of additional
insights here's one example that comes completely out of left field and this was actually my my
wife's thesis research on baboons so your female baboon and you're coming up on your period
and we could frame it as you just did here's two two females who are both about to have their
period and they have the same exact progesterone levels and as soon as they start menstruating
progesterone drops in the exact same way and one of them is a totally irritable awful like
jerk to all the other females around her for three days afterward and the other one is not
the other one withdraws and becomes socially isolated okay what's the difference it sure can't
be progesterone levels and it's probably not going to be progesterone receptor levels it's
one of them's high ranking she could afford to be a jerk to everybody else and get away with it
the other one's low ranking oh it's not just your hormone levels it's what sort of position in your
society you have even if you're a baboon or now you look at humans and depending on what sort of
culture you're in are you in an individualist culture or a collectivist one individualist
the united states poster child of individualist thinking collectivist 99 of the research has been
done on east asian cultures and how you somaticize your mood shifts and your physical shifts during
your period differs in collectivist versus individualist cultures how irritable you become
not because there's a difference in how much of negative affect you're feeling during the time
are you in a culture where it's culturally acceptable to bitch and moan to all your best
friends when you're not feeling well or are you in a culture where when you're feeling lousy what
you're supposed to do is reach out affiliatively and reify your like social values and how much of
that do you think is also genetic so for example i mean even though i'm not a gynecologist and
therefore don't see a lot of this i see enough to realize that women will often say my sister and my
mother either go through or went through the same feelings and of course as you described there are
so many different variants the stereotypical one is the you know the sort of the nasty phenotype
but actually the one that i think might be more prevalent is the sadder phenotype the more
emotionally distraught just emotionally labile but in a non-aggressive way that's probably the
phenotype i see more easier to cry or something like that so how much of that do you think is
heritable in the way that eye color or some other aspect of body habitus or even depression is quite
heritable versus the ecosystem you're in purely environmental well the answer is you really can't
choose one of the other blah blah but if you could only manipulate one which would be the first one
and i'm definitely of the school of genes get overrated in terms of their impact and you know
a gene affecting your eye color it's okay to use words like determine and it's probably not even
100 accurate but when you get to genetic influences on all the interesting stuff and behavior and our
internal lives and all of that yeah genes are important but overwhelmingly these are genes
that modify vulnerability vulnerability to certain types of environments okay so for example
you bring up depression and catastrophic pandemic of that and you know there's a whole shopping list
by now of genes that have been implicated and probably the single most important one it's called
the gene for the serotonin transporter serotonin ssris prozac although the serotonin was just like
we're right in the middle of what we understand about the neurochemistry of depression and it
turns out the serotonin transporter gene comes in a few different flavors a few different genetic
variants and a ton of basic research rats monkeys etc suggested that if you had one particular variant
you were more at risk for major depression okay so this classic work this guy a duke off shalom
kasbe who's sort of a god in the field goes out and he follows like 17 000 people from birth up
to age 25 or so he's got genetic information on them and he's able to ask this critical question
okay if you have the quote bad version of this gene by age 25 are you more likely to have the
history of clinical depression and what's the prevalence of the gene approximately depends on
the population in his population his was a mixed one but westernized western urine populations
i think it's got about a 20 percent incidence so the question then is of those 20 percent how many
go on to get depressed of the 80 percent how many go on to get depressed the answer is very likely
going to be it's not a one-to-one mapping it might be an increase in risk by some factor
and what they saw was overall there was no increase in risk having the bad variant however
if it was coupled with a lot of childhood stress you had about a 20-fold increase in the risk
so just to be clear on aggregate there was no difference the hazard ratio is one
for with gene versus without because of a ton of variability but if you wanted to amplify it take
that gene and expose it to childhood stress or trauma and you almost assure depression you get a
massive boost in predictability look at people without the scariant vulnerability variant and
look at the same severity of childhood stressors and loss and you got a moderate increase in
incidence of depression these folks massive order of magnitude multiples of that more increase there
what that tells you is this is a gene whose variants alter how readily you deal with
experiential kicks in the asses growing up and it turns out these different variants are regulated
in different ways by glucocorticoids aha so there's a stress angle all of that the same way
there's another gene to the people who are interested in the genetics of aggression
this gene monoamine oxidase and it comes in variants and it's and there's a class of drugs
that targets these yeah perceptors yeah again a ton of basic research had suggested oh there's a
scary variant of it which if you have it you are good at more being more predisposed towards
violence and in fact the same group working with the same population massive data set winds up
showing just having that variant doesn't get you a higher risk of antisocial violent behavior by
age 25 if and only if it was coupled with abuse childhood abuse growing up oh if you didn't have
the scary variant childhood abuse a little bit of increased risk have this variant with the abuse
and it was virtually the same figure as with the serotonin transporter gene huge boost in very
over and over the genes that are interesting when it comes to this stuff these are all genes about
vulnerability and potentialities and tendencies that are emerging only in certain environments
and not in others their factors are inseparable it makes me think of the apo-e genotype which is
linked to alzheimer's disease and there we see that there is a difference about 25 percent of
the population carries at least one copy of that gene and they represent about two-thirds of the
cases of alzheimer's disease it's not a deterministic gene but it does increase risk now of course you
could argue that maybe in a decade or more we will be able to say something very similar about apo-e
which is it's not remotely deterministic it only gets turned on when x y and z happen before
this period of time or in absolute and of course we don't know what those things are right now
at least in the examples you gave you could say well trauma or childhood you know some event in
childhood was was the trigger and if you're seeing a 20-fold difference it's pretty clear
that you found the trigger nonetheless there's still variability to explain after that but yeah
it's pathetically that counts as virtually state of the art for understanding the modifying factors
and it's it's going to be that way i mean anytime you do these like gewass massive fishing expeditions
and you come out with 300 genes are implicated in a trait that's as boring as height 300 genes
which you put together all of your knowledge of the variation of them in any given individual and
you have like four percent predictability of their height you know christ if you're talking about genes
for propensity towards feeling poignancy or genes for like anything that's interesting yeah
this is not a chance even if you just limit yourself to diseases you know of the 20 000
genes in our body you can really only point to about a hundred that are directly this mutation
means this disease and they're all pretty esoteric right it's all like inborn errors of metabolism
and certain things like that but when you start to talk about the complex diseases like alzheimer's
disease even as predictive as the apo-e4 is it's not even close to being enough to understand it
and and i think yeah it's funny when you talk about it through that lens you realize the importance
of environment which is you know the risk of stating the obvious you said something a while ago
that i made a note of because i wanted to come back to it you talked about the effective glucocorticoids
on the hippocampus and not only how harmful it was for memory consolidation but overall
cognitive impairment and listening to you talk about that was exactly the way matthew walker
at berkeley speaks about sleep deprivation and its impact on the hippocampus which then makes me
wonder i assume it's been well studied that you know when people are sleep deprived we see greater
elevations of cortisol do you have a sense of what the evolutionary basis of that is because
it seems counterintuitive you would think even evolution would want that to be in the opposite
direction i mean the only explanation i can come up with is if you're sleep deprived you're assuming
that there's a reason for it that's good and therefore you want that of course not with any
the fact that higher cortisol will then i think that's probably the best sort of piece of teleology
for that yeah if you're like a basic mammal which means either you are emphatically diurnal or
emphatically nocturnal and if instead you are wide awake eight hours into what should be the
twelve this does not happen by chance the odds are you have something stressful going on i think
that's the logic of it turns out the stress sleep sleep quality cortisol cluster of interactions
even more subtle incredibly cool study this was a science paper some years back
that okay so as we talked about the circadian peak of glucorticoids are around the time you wake up
what's interesting is about an hour before you wake up levels begin to rise telling you something
a subtle point which is a lot of glucorticoid actions are not for dealing with a stressor
that has already commenced but can be preparatory so the preparatory stressor is having to actually
get up and get out of bed and start functioning addressed in an hour before people wake spontaneously
glucorticoid levels are elevating now in the study what you do is you take a whole bunch of
volunteers who are sleeping and you see the preparatory rise all of that and you tell them
tonight we're doing something different i'm going to wake you up at four in the morning
and what you see is around three o'clock glucorticoid levels start rising okay now you do something even
more interesting you say okay tonight i'm not going to tell you when but i'm going to wake you
up at some point during the night and that's the end of your night's sleep and the person is about
90 minutes into their sleep stage and all of that and cortisol rises and stays high for the rest of
the night you get one sleep cycle and then the adrenal gland says that's it i'm on ready alert
yeah exactly so not only is it bad not to get enough sleep not only is it bad if the insufficient
sleep is fragmented but the worst is if it's fragmented unpredictably and that's like every
medical resident in history it's the first thought i had actually when you said that which was
every night of call you have this pager and you're in this call room and you just want so desperately
to sleep for an hour two hours three hours i remember as my residency went on the the degree
of sleep deprivation got greater and greater that the steps i had to take to ensure i wouldn't sleep
through a page got greater and greater and i'm not making this up i've nothing i've ever told
the story before it's so ridiculous i used to use this really heavy paper tape and tape the pager to
my head my forehead at full volume because you would get both the sound to your ear and then
you'd get the transmission you know through the bone but imagine laying in bed with tape wrapped
around your head holding a pager on your forehead in anticipation of what's coming not knowing when
it's coming it could be in five minutes or it could be in two hours you know you're going to wake up
yeah i'm i'm guessing that wasn't great sleep it's like wildly destructive and what do you know
it turns out if you have elevated glucorticoid levels while you're asleep you have less delta
sleep time which is the restorative stuff you make less adenosine stores in your brain during
so even if you manage to go to sleep if it's under the i could be asleep for two hours now
or 30 seconds the sleep quality is going to be horrible this interplay becomes more pronounced
what about cancer what role do you think stress plays in cancer and do you think it's mostly
mediated through the immune system i mean cortisol can be quite damaging yeah all right
hugely hugely controversial subject there is a common perception that stress can play a very
substantial role in the onset of cancer in coming out of remission and rates of tumor growth and such
sufficiently so that there's been all sorts of studies where you ask cancer patients what do
you think is the cause of your cancer and stress is invariably way up there the actual evidence for
a role of stress in causing cancer bringing it out of remission accelerating tumor growth
is very very minimal there's been a remarkably small number of good prospective studies of humans
that have really truly ruled out all the confounding factors when you look at the animal studies what
they typically involve is you experimentally induce a tumor you inject transformed cells you
give a carcinogen some such thing my lab back when did some of that work under those circumstances
you can accelerate the growth of a tumor but those are circumstances of cancer acquisition
that are virtually irrelevant to human cancer and the other question is can you do it without
perturbing other things so for example if you go ahead and stick the tumor into the mouse
and apply a stress to it it seems that that by definition will alter some other parameter
what it eats how much it sleeps the quality of its sleep so it becomes difficult to disentangle
cortisol i mean i guess the only thing i can think of is what does the experiment look like
where you take the mouse that experimentally has the tumor and you just start injecting more
glucocorticoid so in other words you don't actually increase the stress level you just
increase the readout state of stress you accelerate the tumor growth we did one study
showing that as soon as cells become transformed they up regulate the glute four glucose transporter
and that's the one that's further up regulated by glucocorticoids and target cells so you're just
shoveling energy over those cells yeah which preferentially consume glucose anyway just given
the number of them followed by the warburg effect so to me even though that's very mechanistic and
artificial that that strikes me as pretty reasonable evidence that cortisol can play a
role in cancer i mean i guess it's going to be much more difficult to disentangle that in the
real world yep and again these are types of cancers where this was virally induced transformation of
cells that are then transplanted very artificial systems that turn out not to be terribly applicable
to puma cancers and what you wind up seeing then okay yes glucocorticoids can be potently
immunosuppressive usually by the time you have a tumor growing that's long past the point where
it's an immunological problem it's now can you keep the tumor from growing a whole bunch of
capillaries that will feed it can you keep it from stealing all sorts of energy can you keep it from
turning off cell death programs it's no longer in the immune realm so it seems that there'd be
hard to make the case that acute bouts of stress can really have any impact because you know yes
sure you can acutely disrupt the immune system and maybe get sick right that you know i could
explain why you might get a cold under a period of great stress but not necessarily cancer
and what that means is that should be a massive massive take-home message for anyone who's
predisposed towards thinking ooh stress caused my cancer too bad i didn't have better priorities in
life now i know whose fault it is that sort of thing and it should certainly make you damn
cautious if there's some highly credentialed quack out there who is selling a stress management will
stop your tumor will make it disappear entirely and you watch your wallet at that point all that
being said there's been some wonderful work and a lot of this was pioneered by a stanford colleague
of mine david speagle who showed that things like supportive group therapy among cancer patients
enhances survival so what do you think is the mechanism of that okay this was when he first
published this in the late 80s this was front page news i remember this i mean i don't remember when
it was published but i remember learning about it in medical school massive finding and one is
immediately tempted to at least as a biology type like me to come up with a biological explanation
along the lines of what you proposed okay supportive group therapy you're less stressed
so you don't secrete as many glucorticoids and therefore you're not having those adverse effects
of it on your immune systems you're better able to fight the tumor you live longer trellis and lower
glucose levels and lower glucose and lower insulin and lower ig if you could you could come up with a
complete biological and in general those studies have shown that pathway does not occur speagle and
i did some of those studies things so what's actually going on something which if you're a
nuts and bolts reductive bio type person is terribly disappointing but is so interesting
and important people when they have supportive cancer therapy with other people going through
the same hell they become more compliant when they're medical regimes they're more likely to
go the extra round of chemo because everybody else is cheering them on saying i didn't want to do it
either and they're more likely to take the meds that make them nauseous as hell have you eaten
today me neither we're going to eat right after we're done with the group have you taken your meds
you're going to take them right now people become more compliant and that was very hard to demonstrate
because what cancer patient ever wants to admit to a researcher actually i skip about a third of my meds
because they make me feel so damn sick they're saving your life would it's in some ways a dark
dirty secret in cancer therapeutics how much people diverge from their optimal treatment regime
because the treatment regimes are sheer utter hell when you're surrounded by people who are
going through the same thing and understand you're more likely to be compliant i think that
winds up explaining an awful lot of that effect so when you look at cancer atherosclerosis and
neurodegenerative disease it seems to me that the direct lines of evidence for the damage of
hypercorticillemia and the accelerated stress response are probably most demonstrated in
cardiovascular disease and atherosclerosis vis-a-vis several mechanisms not the least of which is
hypertension both macro and microvasculature but also through endothelial disruption adhesion of
cells and sludging and yeah it's the best understood realm cancer is probably the weakest realm
i would expect that it's playing a role in dementia but again this probably gets to the
layer of susceptibility right there's probably in isolation maybe this wouldn't play a role but
in combination with other factors it would and it seems that for example we know that
cortisol inhibits melatonin secretion so even if you take two people who have the same amount of
blue light reduction which should therefore stimulate melatonin the one with hypercorticillemia
is going to and we actually measure this right we can measure overnight urinary cortisol and
overnight urinary melatonin you can see this association quite strongly well melatonin it's a
pro-neurogenic molecule so having less of that is less restorative to the brain even beyond its
important role which is sort of removing the brakes on being awake so what other lines of
evidence do you see beyond what you've already described at the developmental stage now later
in life basically everything we talked about with the hippocampus applies in the adult brain as well
and it's the first place we tend to see changes and it was the first area researched first evidence
for stress damaging the hippocampus and hippocampal dependent memory type stuff
late 70s i mean that was really the first domain and superb studies from a number of groups and
i had my two cents and that would return also showing you could accelerate aspects of hippocampal
aging with lots of stress lots of glucorticoids extensive neuron loss extensive memory problem
extensive reactive gileosis etc etc next big outpost that people began to appreciate
in adult brains was derivative of what we talked about before which was the amygdala i was just
about to say is there a direct correlation i guess between amygdala size and dementia
what you see instead is that the syndrome where it's most demonstrated is ptsd
you see expansion of the amygdala and you see atrophy of the hippocampus and glucocorticoids
probably play the driving role in both so in the amygdala like the hippocampal story is stress and
glucocorticoids screw it up neurons don't work as well networks don't work as well the overall size
decreases you had atrophy in the amygdala it's the exact opposite story neurons work better than
they should neurons become more excitable form denser networks the amygdala gets bigger what's
that about the problem with chronic stress is your memory goes down the tubes hippocampus isn't
working as well as usual the problem with chronic stress and the amygdala is it works better than
it's supposed to and this is the link between stress and anxiety disorders stress and fear
stress and all of that next sort of outpost that people started looking at was the dopamine system
in the brain and dopamine neurotransmitter most famously associated with reward pleasure
cocaine works on the dopamine system a much more accurate subtle picture of it is dopamine is
actually more about the anticipation of pleasure than it is about pleasure itself and about goal
directed behavior you're willing to do in anticipation of reward but then a whole literature
showing what distress and glucocorticoids do there they mess with the dopamine system it's
less clean of a story than amygdala or hippocampus but in ways that predispose towards the two big
psychiatric diseases of screwed up dopamine systems number one addiction more vulnerability
to addiction harder to get off of addictive substances number two depression depression is
a disease of on a certain level dopamine depletion it's a disease of inability to feel
pleasure and hedonia and that's the neurochemistry of the link between chronic stress and why that
increases the likelihood of the first three four episodes of major depression what for me is the
most exciting area is one where if i was starting over you know forget the hippocampus who cares
about like how many digits you could remember backwards or whatever the most interesting domain
is turning out to be what stress and glucocorticoids do to the frontal cortex judgment impulse control
executive function long-term planning strategizing and it turns out virtually every bad thing
cellularly that stress and glucocorticoids do in the hippocampus they're turning out to do in the
frontal cortex as well and what does that begin to explain this entire world of why it is during
moments of extreme emotional arousal especially aversive ones why we make terrible terrible
decisions that seem brilliant at the time and you spend the rest of your life regretting it because
impulse control your amygdala overpowers your frontal cortex at those times your amygdala has
a lot more talking to your motor systems than your frontal cortex does it's the reason why
judgments and impulse control become terrible when we're frazzled it's also looking like as
a side story with that it's one of the reasons why when we're very stressed it's hard for the
frontal cortex to do one of its harder jobs which is to take the view of the world from somebody
else's perspective empathy empathy exactly some research on animal models of empathy and this was
worked with this guy at McGill named Jeffrey Mogul and where I collaborated with him
showing in both rats and humans you're a lesson pathic towards strangers when they're in pain
and if you block glucocorticoid release you don't get that effect anymore
glucocorticoids the stressfulness of dealing with scary novel humans or scary novel mice
if you're a rodent glucocorticoids narrow your window as to who counts as an us and whose pain
registers and things of that sort so for me you know it's incredibly interesting if you're stressed
and suddenly your SAT scores plummet the fact that stress makes people crappier to each other
and less empathic and more parochial and more xenophobic and more impulsive with the worst of
our impulses that's the stuff that really interests me these days everything you just said
robert is almost a call to action in criminal justice reform and i've done a podcast on this
topic where you know i was very fortunate to go into a maximum security prison with a program
that is really there to do incredible rehabilitative work led by this woman named katherine hoke
it's a humbling experience there's a game that we played about halfway through the day called step
to the line this is a game that's used to basically identify the vast difference between those of us
who are volunteers like in other words the role of luck in our lives versus the gentleman who two
thirds of these men are never going to get out of prison one man had even spent more than half his
life in solitary confinement his total life so it starts with these questions of step to the line if
you grew up in a home that had two parents and you know of the volunteers you know 60 step to the
line of the inmates five step to the line right step to the line if you grew up in a home where
there were more than four books you can imagine the disparity step to the line if you saw someone
die with your own eyes before this age step i mean and it's it's a very emotional thing to go
through because as this game is unfolding you're just you're feeling more and more fortunate on
the one hand because you realize if not for the the grace of this luck and at the same time the
empathy you have for these men who have done the most heinous things grows and you start to realize
boy there's a fine line between those of us on the inside those of us on the outside
because everything you said really resonated when i was thinking about some of the stories the men
told us about the decisions that they made and there's this one part of the exercise that's
incredibly emotional where you're partnered with one one guy so it's it's one volunteer one inmate
and you were each telling the other person the greatest regret of your life the biggest
mistake you've made and hearing some of these stories it's not to justify anything that's been
done and it's not to say that there shouldn't be consequences for it but a lot of these things that
people have wound up in prison for are really impulsive horrible decisions as opposed to decades
of sinister planning it's one thing to look at what you know like hitler did it's hard to argue
that anything that he did that was bad was impulsive it's quite another thing when you look at someone
in a gang related incident where you know this guy gets shot and you're going to shoot this guy
back or this guy's about to shoot you and you shoot him i mean and yet that type of drug related
violence is disproportionately represented in certainly in the u.s penal system and then to
build on what you said it's not clear that the environment in there is reducing cortisol levels
to the level that would enable rehabilitation which is really the thesis of and a lot of people
i'm sure listening to this are thinking why would you feel empathy for these folks that are in there
and why should society care about them but the reality of it is if they're going to get out you
should care that says nothing of maybe the higher level that you should care which is the injustice
of it but even if you took a purely selfish view a non-trivial number of these men and women are
going to get out so wouldn't you rather they get out and function better and yet it's really
tragic to see this and i i know two people actually very well who spent a great deal of
time in prison one of whom i interviewed on this podcast his name is cori mccarthy and it really
strikes me as the exception and not the rule that people are able to emerge from that environment
and go on to be successful outside it's a system that is so so broken any study the last century
and a half's worth of neurobiology and genetics and child development and all of that
and the notion that we are free agents of our action is so destructively misplaced i'm sure
you're familiar with the work of sam harris sam has been one of the most interesting forces in
my life at getting me to really even question this notion of free will and once you realize that
free will may not even be yours it takes luck to a new level it's something i spent a lot of time
thinking about now what advice would you offer somebody who is interested in the neurobiology
of stress or behavior and who wants to be able to look back when they're your age and be as you
know maybe accomplished as the wrong word i don't want i know you you sort of bristle at that but
to have made as many contributions as you've made i mean what in retrospect was sort of the secret
to being able to pursue your bliss and be as successful as you've been and and look frankly to
be where you are and to still have the passion that you have for what you're doing which to me
is really the marker of success it's that you're sitting here saying there's this other problem and
i you know like i could spend you know the next 20 years just thinking about that how do you think
about how you've done that just damn luck every bit of neurosis every bit of affective instability
i've got every childhood trauma i've got tucked away i've titrated in just the right way that
i've turned it into more productivity and incredibly lucky in that regard in my capacity to
sublimate emotion into intellectual pursuit into really really really wanting to understand
something into i've just been very lucky on that regard i've gotten just the right levels of all
sorts of like tumult and that have synergized most productively in other words just huge amounts of
luck huge amounts of luck and at least now coming later in life an increasing capacity to more
carefully try to analyze what cost each type of ambition comes with hmm say more about that oh i
don't know this had much to do with my closing my lab four years ago a big booming lab with lots
of people and all sorts of labs around the world we were going to kick the asses of by getting the
answer to this or that and you know if if you're raised in the right sort of rarefied ambitious
world of biomedical research at age 25 you've got a list down to the floor of the diseases you're
going to vanquish and the the problems you're going to solve and all of that and you know
getting to that point in life where you're realizing it's not going to happen is that what
actually happened four years ago was it that much of a cerebral realization or was it combined with
other factors you know you've described obviously having this network of people around you who matter
the most and i mean was part of it just thinking i haven't spent enough time with them at the expense
of this or was it the this problem is enormous and when you know a thousand years from now whether
i worked this much harder or this much less it won't have altered the trajectory of x-ray like
i mean how much of it is all of these holy above family growing up real fast as they tend to do
realizing your best work was decades behind you realizing there's this book you want to write
where the only way you can do it is to just sit for really long stretches kenyon field work having
collapsed a few years before body feeling older limits to how many 80 hours of work a week you can
do all of them converging what i mean such a cliche question what advice would you give the
the 25 year old robert as he was just finishing that phd at rockefeller be less ambitious
well i think on that note which by the way i think is some of the greatest advice one could
ever get and receive and those of us who are still on the climbing ambition curve should do
everything to listen to it i want to i want to thank you so much for taking the time to sit down
with me and more importantly i think for just all of the work you've done and you're continuing to do
thank you so much no thanks for having me on this has been
fun is the wrong word but stimulating good glad we did this
you can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast
there you'll find the show notes readings and links related to this episode you can also find
my blog at peteratiamd.com maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively
non-lame once a week email where i'll update you on what i've been up to the most interesting
papers i've read and all things related to longevity science performance sleep etc on
social you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id peteratia md but usually
twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments now for the obligatory
disclaimer this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine nursing or other professional health care services including the givings of medical
advice and note no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the
materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk the content of this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnoses or treatment users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have
and should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions
lastly and perhaps most importantly i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures the companies i invest in and or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash
about