Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is my good friend, Dr. Ethan
Weiss. Ethan and I have known each other for a few years. We both sit on the advisory board of a
company called Virta Health, and we've always found ourselves sitting around the table at these
meetings or elsewhere, just having super nerdy discussions. And we just decided we got to at
least put some of these discussions on the podcast. So what follows is a really deep and for me
certainly interesting discussion about two topics that at the surface seem completely unrelated,
cardiovascular disease and the role of growth hormone and IGF in disease. Now, it won't be
clear from what I just said why one guy would be an expert on both of those things, but as the story
unfolds, you'll see that Ethan is quite a unique individual. By training, he's a cardiologist. He
specializes in preventative cardiology at UCSF, trained at Hopkins in both medical school and in
his residency and then completed his fellowship at UCSF where he has since remained. And his interests
are wide ranging from prevention in all aspects of it, which includes lipids and the management
of blood pressure and the endocrine system, et cetera. But what I found most interesting in this
discussion, in addition to just the master's class in understanding everything from acute coronary
syndrome to all of the complex nuances around stent placement, which is something that I think
anybody listening to this knows at least somebody who's had a stent placed and to sort of go through
all of that literature in detail and understand who are the ideal candidates versus who is not.
All of that, I don't want to say paled in comparison because I would minimize it, but
it was nothing compared to at least for me diving into what led him to pursue this field of
endocrinology and specifically what he found with respect to growth hormone and IGF. And this is
something I only knew about Ethan maybe six to nine months ago. It was really quite recent that
this came onto my radar about his level of expertise in this. And so we just spent a great
deal of time talking about this and you could almost think of this as two separate podcasts,
one that really deals with cardiovascular disease, specifically interventional radiology
and diagnostic techniques. We talk extensively about calcium scores and CT angiograms and things
like that that we get asked about all the time. And then there's basically a second podcast here,
which is a really interesting discussion around growth hormone, its effect on the liver,
the brain, et cetera. Finally, we touch really briefly at the end on a company that Ethan has
started quite recently called Keto or Key2, depending on how you pronounce it, which is a
breath analyzer for acetone. So again, nothing that novel there, but what is novel is the way
this device works and socially kind of provides feedback and allows you to get great feedback
when you're fasting or on a ketogenic diet or something like that. So I hope you enjoy this
podcast. This is one of those ones where the show notes are really going to be helpful, especially
for people who actually want to go back and look through all of the literature in all the clinical
trials we talk about and even just some of the diagrams, frankly, to even understand when we're
talking about EKG changes and things like that. Sometimes the diagrams help. So without further
delay, please welcome my guest, Dr. Ethan Weiss. Ethan, thanks so much for making time today.
Thank you, Peter. Thanks for coming over, Randy San Francisco. I can't believe this is the first
time I've been to your office, which I must say, anyone who knows me knows how much I love white
boards, but the glass white board is just next level stuff. We got a little bit of flack when we
picked these out. The architects, this is actually super fancy Italian glass and the architects sort
of convinced us you'll really appreciate it. And I love it. Actually, my kids love it too. They've
daked out their own territory on this. I actually like that the kids have their drawings adjacent
to the drawing of mTOR. Yeah. Perfect. I think you should always be able to mix those. The other
thing that I don't know, I guess it's because I've never been to your office that I don't know how
we have never discussed is our mutual appreciation for Wayne Gretzky. You have in front of me
a home Jersey circa 1986, Edmund Tenoylers signed by none other than the great one.
Yeah. Look, I grew up in Baltimore, which was not really a hotbed of hockey. I think they were the
skip Jack, my early hockey team, triple-a team, I guess. I don't know if they call him that in
hockey. Anyway, we had the skip Jacks and the Clippers and I never really was too into hockey.
I was a baseball fan and a football fan, but my dad had grown up in Chicago and really did like
hockey. And one year we were back there visiting my grandparents for Christmas. I think it was the
winter of 1979. He said, let's go to a Black Hawks game. So we went to the old Chicago stadium.
It was my first introduction to this game that, you know, I basically fell in love with
instantly. And at that time in the late seventies, early eighties, it was, you know, the birth of
these dynasties, I think first the Islanders and then they had been to the Oilers and
you couldn't be a sports fan, but you couldn't be a hockey fan and not appreciate Gretzky. So I
eventually developed into being like Washington capitalist fan, which was sheer torture until last
June, which was super fun. But in the process of being a fan, of course, I always remained true to
Gretzky. Anyway, a couple of years ago, my mom said, Hey, look, I'm coming to California. We're
going to go to LA. My uncle, my brother, my uncle is an oncologist down there. He's being honored by
the sarcoma foundation. I said, sure, it's an hour flood. I can hop on. I'll come down. I'll join
you. So we go to one of these LA galas and there's like a big series of tables with, with a bunch of
silent auction items. And I walked by this Jersey a couple of times and on the third or fourth time
I walked by the guy who was manning the table, stopped me and he said, Hey, you know, buddy,
I see you walked by that a few times. You have any interest in it? I said, yeah, I've got interest
in it, but there's, I can't, I can't afford that. And he said, no, listen, I'm pretty sure if you
bid the minimum, you'll get it. And the minimum, minimum bid was a hundred dollars. And I said,
you gotta be kidding me. Gretzky played here in LA and how can that's impossible? It's a signed
Jersey. It's beautiful. The frame alone is worth more than a hundred dollars. So he finally convinced
me to do it. I put down the bid and I walked out with this Jersey, which my wife instantly told me
she loved, but she loved it anywhere but our home. So I brought it here. And it's,
it's awesome as a conversation starter when people come visit. What I immediately loved about it was
when I was 10, so 1983. So just as the, it was kind of the year that the Oilers lost their first
Stanley cup to the Islanders who were winning their fourth. And I wanted that Jersey for my birthday.
And I got that Jersey. It took a lot because the Jersey cost $50. And I just asked my mom if I could
ask all the kids at my birthday for money instead of gifts. And I remember everyone showed up with
five to $10 and it added up to 50. And we went, I still remember it. Like it's really one of those
amazing early memories to go and be able to buy it. And I was really torn between the home and the
away Jersey. I went with the home Jersey, which is the one you have. And it was so big. Like I just
couldn't, you know, I just wanted to make sure I never grew out of it. And I probably wore it
for like every day for three years. The sad thing is I don't have it anymore. I, I, it really bums
me out that it somehow got lost because it would be such a cool thing to show my kids and have them
roll their eyes at one day. That one's amazing. So wait, you grew up in Toronto. Yeah. And you were
in a leather stand. I was. I mean, the Leafs were not Toronto, such a great hockey town that, you know,
going to games was, I mean, just the greatest highlight of my life. And I even got to see a
few oiler games, you know, always in the cheapest seats in the house. Maple Leaf Gardens had, you
know, sort of this color system. So the gray is up at the very top is where I usually sat. But back
then it was so unsophisticated that if the game was a blowout by the third period, you could sneak
down into the golds and you could, you know, be like right there. You know, I actually had dinner
with Mark Messier a few months ago, who I just met. And he's just the most amazing guy. And we,
I mean, I'm sure he's so tired of doing that, but we just rehashed all of the oiler glory days. And
you know, it's sort of hard to believe that you could have Gretzky Messier, Curry,
coffee, Kevin Lowe, Grant Fuhrer, all on the ice at one point in time. It was hard to believe before
I went to Edmonton, but I took my daughter four years ago now to go to the Women's World Cup. And
we went, we decided to go to Edmonton for some reason. I can't remember. It was just like the
best chance of seeing the American women's team play. So we spent three days in Edmonton in July
and we walked by the old whatever it was. I think they built a new one. In any case, I thought,
wow, it was pretty amazing that these guys would all be here. But then you see Edmonton and you
think, oh my God, like I cannot believe they kept them here as long as they did. It's really
remarkably, I don't want to be harsh about Edmonton. I mean, I'm sure there are great things
about it, but it's not glamorous. It's certainly not like LA.
Yeah. It's not like that was the New York Rangers.
No.
Yeah.
Or even Vancouver.
Or Toronto.
Or Montreal.
Yeah.
Yeah. We share something in common, which I guess is this Hopkins thing. You were a few years
ahead of me. So you did med school and residency there, didn't you?
I tell people I kind of grew up in the hospital. I wasn't born in Baltimore, but my dad moved.
So I was born in Ann Arbor, Michigan, where my dad had done his internship. And like a lot of
people at that time of his age, in an effort to avoid going to Vietnam, he picked up from
Ann Arbor and moved to Bethesda where he worked at the NIH for a few years. It's actually a pretty
funny side story, which is I didn't really understand what my dad was doing. I was young.
I was only two. And I found a bunch of marijuana cultivation books in his office when I was a kid.
And I said, dad, is there something I don't know about you? Because you don't strike me as the kind
of person who would be, he said, no, this is what I was working on in the lab. We were working on
marijuana. He was working in Julie Axelrod's lab. So we ended up living in Bethesda for a couple
of years. And eventually he finished and he went back to, he went to Baltimore where he finished
his residency and then did his fellowship and joined the faculty at Hopkins in cardiology.
And he had remains on the faculty there has been there, you know, been on the faculty for over,
over 40 years. So I grew up going to the hospital as a kid to visit my dad at work. And then
my very first summer job was to work in that hospital. So it was sort of a second home for
me. And then I went away to college and came back and I did medical school there
and stayed around for residency and then moved to San Francisco in 1998, 20, 21 years ago.
Did you always want to do medicine? No, never. Uh-uh. It was a combination of sort of, I think,
not really wanting to do exactly what my dad had done, but also not having the aptitude for it.
And I was a pretty bad, I was a very average student in high school, but particularly an
average or mediocre science student. And so I went off to college, I went to Vassar, which is a
liberal arts school and intended to study music. Actually, I really kind of was going to study
music and realized I didn't have the talent to do that either. And just sort of on a whim decided
to take a science course. And it was a, one of these sort of freak accidents that I happened to
be in a place where science was friendly and presented in a way that was appetizing to me.
And non-threatening. And I think if I'd gone to a place like Harvard, there's no way in the world
I'd be sitting here right now doing what I'm doing. So I really enjoyed science at that stage in life.
And eventually when I figured I wasn't going to be able to do music, I said, you know, maybe I can
go off and do medicine, but I'll do something very different. I had no intention of doing science. I
had less than the bare minimum science requirements for medical school. So when I got to Hopkins in
the fall of 1991, I was probably one of 10 non-hard science majors. And at that time, there were
as many biochemistry majors as there were biology majors. It was really unusual to have
us humanities people. And we were ranked in the class, you know, one to 120. And we all ended up
in the bottom. We were 110, 111 through 120 and struggled mightily with science, especially with
the first year. It was tough. It was a tough sledding for me. I can't imagine what Hopkins was
like then. So I'm obviously a few years behind you. And I got into Hopkins for medical school in 96
or 97. I would have matriculated in 97. I remember even at the time you'd now interviewed
at a bunch of schools. So you sort of saw the way it was here versus there. And I was like, wow,
this place is going to be rough sledding. I mean, it still had letter grades when most schools had
gone to pass fail or high pass pass fail. And you just got the sense like this place was,
if it didn't kill you, it would make you stronger. But there was a non-trivial chance it would kill
you. It was interesting because of course, you know, from the outside you have people come,
I was a student member on the admissions committee. And so you got to hear firsthand what people would
think. And there was this story that you probably heard, because this is probably around the same
time when I was doing it, that Hopkins was this like super intense pressure cooker and everybody
was a gunner and you'd never survive. And it was just a miserable place to be a student. It was
actually a beautiful place to be a student. And my fellow classmates were really supportive.
Everybody was just an incredibly strong achiever on their own. They didn't care how I did. They
just wanted to do the best for them. So it was really inspirational. I think after I got over
the shock of not being able to keep up, because really the disparity information was tremendous.
Right. I had had one semester of biology and I'm hanging out with guys who, you know, had been
working in a lab since they were seven and understood things that like I still today don't
understand. And I mean, it was guys like David Sabatini and Dave Brett and, you know, my high
school classmate, Andy Cameron, I mean, a bunch of people who were, you know, just so far ahead of me
and where, where I'd ever be. It was a fun place to be once I got over the idea, like, Hey, look,
I was used to being a pretty good student. And by definition, most of us probably came in here
because we were at or near the top of our class. And it ain't gonna happen that way now. Right.
There are 120 of us and not all 120 of us can get an A. And once I got over that and kind of
decided that I was okay with not having all A's unless I wanted to die, it was great.
I think I forgot that you were in the same class as David, which of course would put you in the
same class as Andy Cameron. And there's an obviously interesting story there is Andy
Cameron being the son of John Cameron, who was the chairman of surgery. And one of the main reasons
I ultimately did go to Hopkins for my residency, his father, of course, being a luminary in the
field. And of course, David Sapatini is no stranger to anybody listening to this. So yeah,
it was sort of like, I guess going to med school at Hopkins in that era was like playing for the
Yankees. In the end, I agree with you after I interviewed there and I made a point to stay an
extra two days, I came away way more bullish on the idea that it would, it could be a great
experience. And in the end, it really came down to, I wouldn't say a coin toss. I mean, I think in
the end Stanford won out for a number of reasons. I don't think it was as good a medical school as
Hopkins, at least not according to the rankings. Hopkins was the best, but I think just living in
California as a kid coming from Toronto seemed like a great opportunity. Well, and I did it the
opposite way. I mean, I knew I had to get out after having been there for seven years and having
grown up in that environment. And you know, my dad being there made things complicated. So I
knew I had to leave. And it's funny because when I got here, lifestyle is much more central to
people here in California. And I didn't appreciate that. And you know, of course now I do,
but I wouldn't trade that experience. It was an amazing experience and all those people. I mean,
I remember operating, I did as a medical student, I did GI gold. That was back when Cameron Yeo,
and when was Kurt Campbell, the other attending on at that time? No, he, I think he was a chief
resident. I'm pretty sure he was. Oh wow. Yeah. So why I spent a lot of time in the operating room
with Dr. Cameron and wow. I mean, what an entertaining human being and you know, master
surgeon. I don't know, were they still doing Sunday school when you were there? Oh yes. In fact,
Ted Schafer and I did an interview a while ago where we talked about our fondness for Sunday
school. It was one of the highlights of internship. It was incredible. As a student, you were
terrified because you knew they told you, you know, residents would tell you they're like,
you're going to go in there. You're going to present a case. You'll get through seven words,
maybe if you're lucky and he's going to cut you off and then he's going to start asking you
questions. So I mean, this is Sunday morning sitting around this huge boardroom table and
you're a little puny medical student in front of, you know, the entire surgical house staff and
a lot of them and the most famous surgeon in the United States. Yeah. But of course,
he had a wonderful way of not humiliating people. I mean, he was rough, but it was an amazing
experience. I, it was really one of my favorite things that I remember about being a medical
student back there. I have nothing but fond memories from my time there, despite the challenges.
Now, what was a medicine residency like in the nineties? It still must have been pretty freaking
rough, especially at Hopkins. So I was an intern in 1996. I think it was the first year they switched
from Q3 to Q4 call. And it had been not that long since they switched from Q2 to Q3, but there
were still a few rotations where you did every other night call. So as an intern in the medical
ICU and the CCU, we did every other night call. And that that's a, again, it's one of these things
that you look back on and you think, I don't know how I survived it, but in retrospect,
it was really fun. But I mean, just imagine what you're doing. You're going in, you start rounds
at whatever eight o'clock in the morning, you go all day. At that time you never left the unit. So
people would bring you food. There was a bathroom and a call room adjacent to the unit. You never
left the unit. And then you'd stay up all night, taking care of patients. You'd get to rounds the
next day, you'd finish by 11 o'clock. And we had this tradition of going out to have breakfast and
beer with the ICU nurses. And then you'd go home, you'd take a little nap, you wake up, you'd have
some dinner, you'd go back to sleep, you do the whole thing all over again. So for 30 straight
days, you basically did nothing but sleep or be in the hospital. But it was fun. It was an
incredible experience. I mean, there was still a lot of active HIV disease. And one of my favorite
inpatient rotations was doing what they used to call the OSA rate rotation, which is the inpatient
HIV ward. And I mean, you did that as a junior resident with two other junior residents and
there was no one else around. And it's basically ICU level care. I mean, these were some of the
sickest people in the world. This is pre-protease inhibitors. So sick, sick, sick people,
but amazing. I mean, I remember doing procedures on people who are still my dear friends,
fellow residents, really an amazing experience. So how did you pick cardiology?
Well, again, so the background is I'm a second generation cardiologist. So my intention was to
avoid it for a lot of reasons, but I also just wasn't really drawn to it. But actually, I did a
CCU rotation as a medical student. And I'll never forget, we had a series of people, patients come in
who were kind of in their late thirties, early forties who had myocardial infarction,
had a heart attack and had relatively absent any obvious risk factors. So our assessment of risk
factors for coronary disease hasn't changed a lot in the past 20, 25 years. But what I'm saying is
that they had normal lipids, normal blood pressure, nothing identifiable. And I thought, wow, this is
really kind of fascinating. So I worked the summer between first and second year, I worked in a lab,
I worked in a neurosciences lab, I was working on the genetics of trinucleotide repeat diseases,
and so it hadn't been proven yet. But there was a strong suspicion that some of these psychiatric
diseases like schizophrenia and bipolar depression were mediated by trinucleotide repeats. And it was
my first time in a lab and I loved it. So I knew I wanted to go back and do that. I ended up
basically asking a bunch of people, I said, you know, is anybody here doing work on the pathogenesis
of, it wasn't called ACS or key coronary syndrome back then, but the pathogenesis of unstable
angina or MI and young people without risk factors. So I got pointed to this guy who was a young,
at that time, assistant professor, Belgian guy, who went on later to be the dean of the medical
school at the University of Miami. And he had a illustrious academic career. His name is Pascal
Goldschmidt. And so I met with Pascal and I said, Pascal, I'd love to come spend a year working in
your lab. And he said, great. So that sort of was my next introduction to science. And it was really
that experience, which was phenomenal and career defining for me that drove my clinical interest
more than the other way around. So I kind of at that point had thought, well, this is kind of fun,
but maybe I'll do adult cardiology or maybe I'll do pediatric cardiology. And I'm not entirely
convinced that I know the answer yet, but ended up eventually deciding that I didn't like parents.
And so I went down the path of doing adult cardiology. I want to touch on all the stuff
you just brought up because you and I have had so many discussions about this over the past couple
of years. And I've always found you to be one of the most lucid people at describing these
distinctions and sort of synthesizing this. And for someone like me, who is not really on the
front lines of acute cardiology problems, it can be an overwhelming body of literature. So let's
just start with some of the semantics, acute coronary syndrome, unstable angina, stable
angina. How would you define all these terms for folks? And what's the framework in which
you anchor these things? This is what's amazing is if you go back in time, it was relatively recent
in history that there was a debate about the cause of most myocardial infarctions. 99% of
heart attacks in this country happened because of a ruptured atherosclerotic plaque. So,
and that's worth even pausing on for a moment because I don't even think that most people
realize that. I think most people think that a heart attack occurs when the pipe narrows,
narrows, narrows, narrows, and finally closes so that when you hear about so and so who has a
95% occlusion in the artery on the angiogram, my God, that's just 5% away from killing them.
And they sort of don't understand what I think you just said. So can you double click on that point?
Yeah. Well, this is what's so amazing is that if you go back not that far in the literature,
you'll find articles where people are having a debate about whether the, so they did autopsies
on people who presented with sudden cardiac death. Somebody would show up dead from a heart attack.
They do an autopsy. They'd open up the heart, open up the artery, and they'd find a clot there. And
there was a debate about whether that clot was primary or secondary. Was it there before or
after the person died? Was it the basis? And it really was the work of Michael Davies in the late
1970s and early 1980s that kind of demonstrated, proved the idea that this was actually causal.
And then early 1980s, I think it was, I can't remember the exact trial, they went in and
actually aspirated out clots and people who showed up in the emergency department with a heart attack.
And those people got better. So this was pre-angioplasty, but they were able to aspirate out
the clot using a suction catheter and people got better. And so that was the first demonstration
that this clot event was the primary cause of most heart attacks. So again, the pathologist leading
the discussion on how that happened and what you could see in anybody was you'd see a lot of these
plaques. And Davies described, I think, I can't remember which paper it was, I'll have to go back
and find it for you. But he described something that stuck with me, which was that if you look
at an autopsy, somebody who presents with a heart attack and dies, you'll find you can tell by
looking at the histology how many times the plaque is actually ruptured, much like you'd look at the
age of a tree. So you can see that there's plaque rupture and then there's healing. And actually
now other pathologists like Reno Verami and others have said that a lot of the progression
of coronary disease, so getting narrower and narrower is probably that event happening
sequentially. So plaque rupture, healing, and then as you do that, you're laying down more
fibrous tissue. So he could see how many times, and on average, these people in that first series
had had seven plaque ruptures in their culprit artery before they died.
At the same point in the artery or along different points?
In the same plaque. So in the same plaque. And so that told-
So basically a seven ringed tree. On the cover of Starry's pathology book, which is,
I've talked about this before, it's sort of one of the most important books I have to explain
atherosclerosis to patients. There's actually a picture on the cover that shows a very comparable
lesion to that, which is just these concentric rings where the final one, you have this big,
dark, bloody clot in there, which was obviously the fatal one.
That was what lit the fire for me scientifically back when I went to Pascal. I was struck with
this idea, well, gosh, if it, like, why didn't somebody die at the first one? Why don't they
die after the first one? Like if the reaction is, so just for listeners, the contents of that plaque,
what we're calling this atherosclerotic plaque, it's rich with lipids and inflammatory cells,
but the thing that causes the heart attack is none of that stuff. It's that the macrophages,
which are these white blood cells, carry around this protein called tissue factor,
which is then basically the instigator or the trigger for the clotting cascade.
What you're doing is exposing blood, flowing blood to tissue factor, which is basically a,
you know, a wound healing signal. So if you cut yourself, we have tissue factor underneath
the anathelium, which is that interlying of our blood vessel, and that's there to sense injury.
And when the blood sees tissue factor, the blood, there's a biochemical reaction that
we've been described for decades that ends up resulting in a blood clot.
It's sort of an epoxy, you know, those epoxies that come in two separate tubes,
taken alone, they're not sticky, but when the tube combines them, it becomes like rock solid
glue. So the macrophage exposes the tissue factor. Now the blood passing through becomes the other
tube of the epoxy and boom, you get this acute brick. I've been describing it as substrate and
trigger, but I think that's a much better, I like your description. So, and that was again, a debate
not that long ago about what, what the cause of these things was eventually within a 10 year
period. We learned so much because it was, I think 1988 that ISIS two was published and ISIS
two was the, this is off the top of my head, but I think it was a comparison of aspirin and
streptokinase versus aspirin alone in patients who presented with heart attack.
You know, it tell folks what streptokinase does.
Streptokinase is a, what's called a thrombolytic. So streptokinase is a natural substance that we
make or we make something similar that dissolves clots. So clotting is sort of this balance, this,
this battle between pro forces and anti-forces because if you think about it, if you're a
mammal and you have a circulatory system, you have to be able to sense injury so you can keep
your blood from flowing out of you. So the system has to be incredibly tuned and you as an engineer
will appreciate how you must be able to respond incredibly quickly, but it has to be specific.
So you can't get clots happening. We all know what happens.
That's such a great point to make, right? So let's go back and think about this with the lens of
evolution. You get a scratch across you as bad as that scratch or cut is, it still represents
a fraction of the surface area of your vascular system. So to your point, you have to have a
system in place that can identify the area that needs to be fixed. Hence the two check system
where I have to have the tissue factor, which allows for the local aggregation. And then very
quickly you have to respond. And yeah, if it was just a diffuse response, well, you'd kill the
organism by clotting everything within the circulatory system. Well, that's right. And we
really appreciated that through human genetics and then later mouse genetics. So if you knock out
any of the pro-coagulant coagulation factors, say, you know, any of the one, you know, factor two
prothrombin, you'll get a sick mouse, but the mouse will survive through development. So they will,
they will survive. And then what kills them is the process of being born. So they'll die right after
birth. If you knock out one of the anticoagulants and knock out, say protein C protein S, any of the
anticoagulant, the mouse won't make it through half of the embryonic, basically day seven or day eight,
they die. And then there's the whole other interesting layer, which we won't have time to
get into today, which is the role of the placenta and how placentas don't clot off. And there's just
unbelievable fascinating evolutionary biology that we can send to power. Unless someone has
help syndrome, that becomes this awful exception to that rule where you get these infarcted,
clotted placentas and then the fetus is usually underdeveloped. So... Well, I'm not an expert,
but I think that one of the most common causes of fetal loss of idiopathic fetal loss, so women
who end up losing multiple pregnancies again and again and again, is an undiagnosed hypercoagulable
state, I think, because basically the placenta ends up clotting off.
Yeah. You're saying in the case where you don't have an obvious aneuploidy that or a
chromosomal abnormality, you know? So is it easier to talk about where we were 10 years ago,
where we are today, or do you want to just define today? So you've talked about what
a myocardial infarction is.
Yeah, we got sidetracked. So...
Yeah, that's what I do here. I sidetracked.
That's all right. That's fun. So myocardial infarction was defined clinically as most things
were and not pathophysiologically until recently. It was defined by the constellation of things that
still, I think, make up most of the definition, which is chest pain changes in the electrocardiogram
and presence of biomarkers.
Let's explain what those three things are. So everybody understands what chest pain is.
You have these classic symptoms that people understand. Elephants sitting on chest,
radiating into left arm, nausea, that sort of stuff up into the neck. You mentioned the
changes in the electrocardiogram. We'll obviously link to photos of this sort of stuff, but it's
hard to do this because we're going to try to do it for the listener. But every time the heart beats,
there's a signature that can be measured electronically when you put leads on the
chest. And you have a little wave that symbolizes when the atrium is doing its contraction. That's
called the P wave. Then you have the big signal, which is this QRS spike, and that's this ventricular
contraction. And then you have another little wave called the T wave. And I can't even remember. Is
that the repolarization?
That's the repolarization.
Yeah.
Ventricular repolarization.
Ventricular repolarization. And then it goes again. So what are the signs on that that you
are looking at when you're in the ER and somebody comes in to help you decide if this person is
having a heart attack or maybe even has had one in the past?
Yeah. It's important that we cover this now because actually,
after it was agreed upon that a ruptured plaque led to a clot, the clot led to basically the
absence of any blood flow distal to that clot. So beyond the clot, so then any tissue beyond
that blockage would then be starved of oxygen. And after some period of time, a few minutes,
five minutes would die. And it wasn't that long ago that the treatment of MI, of heart attack,
was to put somebody in bed. And then there was the advent of beta blockers, a couple other blood
pressure medicines, which were basically pharmacological bed rest, and then aspirin,
and then streptokinase, which we talked about, which is basically a clot dissolving medicine.
That trial demonstrated that if you dissolve the clot pharmacologically, you could rescue people.
And then we got into actually going and doing these things with balloons and later with stents.
But the nomenclature at the time that I was a medical student was you defined myocardial infarction,
so MI, by the presence or absence of the Q wave. So you mentioned on the EKG,
there was this big deflection that happens early on, and that represents depolarization
of the ventricles. So the biggest largest mass in the heart is your left ventricle. So that's the
pumping chamber that pumps blood out to the body. And that has a very strong electrical signal.
And if in certain areas, regions on the EKG, so we do 12 leads and it creates a vector,
and we can basically recreate the heart in three dimensions. And so you're doing that by putting
these leads, these electrodes across the chest and on the arms and the legs. And if after somebody
had a heart attack, they developed a Q wave in certain leads that signaled to us clinicians
that they had what we at that time called a Q wave myocardial infarction. And what that meant was that
there was transmural or all the way through cell death. So the entire wall, there had been an actual
necrotic, basically what had become necrotic and died. Whereas there was another version of heart
attack at that time that we called non-Q wave heart attack. And those people presented with
the same clinical picture. So they had chest pain. They also had positive biomarkers. At that time,
we were measuring CK or cretin kinase. And that's an enzyme that's leaked out of the site is all of
a muscle cell when there's damage to it. And so people have heart attacks. There are a bunch of
these enzymes, myoglobin and others that go up. And that's one of the ways that we define heart
attacks. So people would come in, they'd have a positive biomarker that have chest pain,
but they didn't have this Q wave. And so they were called non-Q wave myocardial infarction.
So basically the diagnosis was based on the chest pain and the leaking of the enzymes. So I'll say
a little bit more about that, because we're going to come back to it. But basically when a muscle
dies, you can pick up signs of muscle death in the blood and CK being one of them. In fact,
if someone goes out and runs a marathon, it's not uncommon that the next day, if you draw their CK
level, it's very elevated. They've broken down muscle. My recollection, because it's been so long
since I've looked at CK, is they used to even look at a fraction called the MB fraction, which would
try to be more specific for cardiac muscle than say the muscles in your quads or something like
that. So if you had those two things, the pain and the enzyme findings you were having at MI,
the EKG was simply used to determine if it was Q wave completely through or non-Q wave. Is that
right? Mostly, I mean, the EKG is fundamental. I mean, it's really the first thing that gets done
when somebody shows up, they're actually doing them in the field now. And it does today define
how we treat people. It defined it as well back then, but things have changed significantly in the
past 20 years. And we can touch on that a little bit, but the EKG is a fundamental tool. We can't
get away without it. So that was the way it was described. And then there was this other thing
called unstable angina. And unstable angina was thought to be the same pathophysiology,
so ruptured plaque, but it was thought to be incomplete cessation of blood. So maybe the
clot didn't completely block the arteries. There was still a little bit of blood flow getting
through. So in that case, back then, and again, it's changed now, but back then, if you had chest
pain and the EKG changes, but you didn't have a prize in the biomarker, you were said to have
unstable angina. And that was differentiated from stable angina based on what? Yes. So stable
angina has been described forever, which is you walk and you get these symptoms that people
describe, and we can come back and talk about what people, we call it chest pain. That's a garbage
basket term that comprises a lot of different things ranging from exercise intolerance to
actually that feeling of Fred Sanford talking about him having the big one or an elephant sitting on
your chest. That is a clinical term of art, basically the way I think about it. So chest pain,
presence or absence of the biomarker and the EKG, and that would define the symptoms. Stable angina
was defined as you're exercising, you're increasing demand. So again, what we're talking about is an
imbalance between myocardial oxygen supply and demand. So what used to be called stable angina,
and still mostly called stable angina, was thought to be a demand issue. So there would be a lesion
that would narrow the artery and you'd only get chest pain when you increase demand. Sometimes
people call it demand ischemia. And so the idea was that if you have this blockage that's 75,
80% of the diameter of your artery, and you go out and you do something that causes you to increase
your demand. So you go walk up a flight of stairs or a hill here in San Francisco, you need to be
able to deliver more oxygen to the tissue and you can't do that. So the way the coronaries work
physiologically is that they augment blood flow by dilating. So it's a different physiology than
most other vascular beds. So it's part of the reason these drugs like adenosine work is that
they dilate the coronary. That's why people are told to take nitroglycerin if they're having chest
pain. That's right. But the problem is if you've got a fixed lesion there, that's full of a
calcified plaque with a bunch of different lipids and stuff in there, you can't really dilate.
You can dilate the proximal segment before the blockage or you can dilate the distal segment
after, but you can't really deliver more. And so you end up getting an increase in blood flow to
all the other segments. And then you get a little bit more of what probably a little bit of
coronary steel. So in other words, you're getting more blood is even being taken away.
And so that syndrome is considered to be stable. And so you're walking up a hill,
you get chest pain, shortness of breath, whatever the symptom is, you sit down and you rest and it
goes away. Or like you mentioned, you take a nitroglycerin and it goes away and that's stable.
That's actually the best explanation I've ever heard for it. Understanding the fact that I'm
not a cardiologist. And even when I was learning this stuff in medical school,
maybe I just wasn't paying close enough attention, but I think the way you just explained it is great.
It's not just that in the unstable case, you may have some actual plaque rupture.
It's this idea that in the stable case, it's the inability to dilate the target lesion and the
plausible steel of blood. So morphologically, it's a totally reversible process. Nothing has changed.
There hasn't been a new injury, but under a certain period of stress, you're able to
basically see this area that otherwise can't function fully.
So just to put this in a little bit of reference for you, so having coronary disease, which most
Western adults will have by the time they get to be 50, meaning if you looked by CT at me or you,
maybe not you, but I'll probably have a little bit of plaque. But it's very unlikely that plaque,
the amount of plaque is obstructing blood flow, either significantly arrest or with exertion.
Over time, if that plaque gets bigger, at some point, it'll start to become apparent to me
that when I'm walking, increasing my demand, that I'm not able to deliver oxygen. So I'll become
symptomatic. And that the point at which we say most people become symptomatic is when the
percent diameter stenosis or blockage is about 70%. Conveniently, it's also the point when stress
tests, whatever flavor you like, also begin to be able to detect coronary disease. So we have
focused, I think, a lot of energy on this 70% number because it's what we can measure clinically,
either through symptoms or through our testing. But there's nothing to suggest that there's a magic
in that number that would put somebody at a greater risk as opposed to somebody who had a 50%. In fact,
if you go back over time and again to the work of Michael Davies, I think, and I don't want to
misspeak here, but I think a lot of the fatal plaque rupture events that happened in this series
of people who came in and died happened in arteries that had only 30% or 40%.
I think that's actually correct. I mean, that's sort of one of the things I remember from that
literature that was very surprising, which was it was very difficult, a priority to predict which
one of these things was going to be the fatal one. You could have these 90% occlusions that
were highly symptomatic, but just incredibly stable and they were never going to rupture and
they were never going to be the things that killed you. And in fact, there's almost a paradox,
which is the more the stenosis increases, the more likely it tells you that the downstream
musculature has either found some other way to acquire it. So someone who's walking around with
a 95% stenosis is very likely to suffer death in the case of that plaque rupturing. Of course,
that's still a harbinger for what's going on elsewhere in the heart. So there are obviously,
very few people are walking around with a single point of this injury. It's telling you that
there's probably injury throughout the heart and that they could die from another one, but
that to me, which I want to come back to, right? Because I want to talk in depth about some of the
diagnostic tools that we have, especially to predict who's at risk, who's not at risk. And
this is becoming increasingly more important as we have to decide both on the risks and costs of
treatment as the treatments get more and more elaborate. And this ability to predict who's
going to have a fatal MI versus who's not, I'm not convinced we're that much better at it today
than 20 years ago, are we? I don't think so. I mean, I think we should definitely come back to that.
That's a fascinating discussion. We could spend eight hours talking about that.
Yeah. Let's go to where we are today. So we've talked about Q wave, non-Q wave. Talk to me about
what is the nomenclature today?
The nomenclature evolved over the past 15 or 20 years. And the reason it did was that it was
sort of the advent of interventional cardiology and what people realized was in the acute setting
of a heart attack. So I was talking about that Q wave before that appears days after a heart attack,
but in the acute setting of a heart attack, there was a defining feature that seemed to predict
whether there was a complete loss of blood flow. And that was something that we described as called
ST elevation. So you described beautifully the different waves. And so it's the QRS complex,
so the end of that big squiggly complex, the seg, there's then a line, a direct line, a flat line
that connects the end of the S wave to the beginning of the T wave. And that we call the
ST segment. And that is usually isoelectric with the rest of the EKG. In other words,
it's at the same level as the PR segment and everything else. What people realized was that
if that segment gets increased above a couple of millimeters and it does so in more than one lead,
that that signaled that there was a block, a complete blockage of an artery. And that then
evolved into this term that we use today still, which is called ST elevation, MI or STEMI. And that
is a medical emergency immediately signal, we need to open this artery. And that's work that was done
by Gene Ralwald and other people in the Timmy group. And he was done with a combination of
pharmacology, so striptokines, but then also TPA and other thrombolytic agents. And then
people realized you could actually go in there and open the artery manually with a balloon catheter.
So the standard of care in this country today is that if you show up with ST elevation and a
clinical picture that looks like MI, you end up going to a cath lab within an hour and you get
that artery opened up. What is the overlap between ST elevation and if you go back and
look at all the EKGs that define Q wave and non-Q wave, I'm guessing the non-Q waves rarely had ST
elevation and some of the Q waves, but not all of them did. Yeah, I think that's the right thing. So
the way to think about it is the Q wave and the ST elevation MI are probably the same. It's just
you're seeing a later manifestation of the Q wave. If somebody had showed up and if at that time they
did EKGs on everybody who walked into the emergency room with chest pain like they do now,
you probably would have seen the ST elevation. They probably just missed it. So they saw the Q
wave because that was what came later. The non-Q wave MI is probably now what we call non-ST elevation
MI and it's actually evolved to a different term, which is I don't love, which is called non-ST elevation
acute coronary syndrome. Which is just not as easy to say as non-STEM. No, so acute coronary syndrome,
I think the way I tell the teach the students is acute coronary syndrome is the entire collection.
It's everything and it includes STEMIs, non-STEMIs, everything. And it includes what we used to call
unstable angina. Unstable angina doesn't really exist anymore. So we now have ST elevation ACS or
ST elevation MI and we have non-ST elevation ACS. And that's very simply defined by the presence or
absence of ST elevation. It turns out that people who don't have ST elevation often have other ST
segment abnormalities. Most commonly their ST segments are actually depressed and that has to
do with changes in the repolarization. I'm not an electrophysiologist, but changes in the
repolarization that happen when the muscle is completely started with oxygen versus only
partially started. It's a super interesting thing that I've never understood. I probably should go
learn why that is. So clinically, if somebody shows up in the emergency room with ST elevation,
it triggers 911, activate the cath lab. This patient goes straight in, they get heparin,
they get aspirin, they get all the other things, clopidogrel. And just to be clear,
do we even check enzymes in those patients or we don't care?
No. So it's an immediate thing. And in fact, when this change happened during the time I was a
cardiology fellow. So when I was a cardiology fellow, if somebody showed up in the emergency
department with ST elevation, they'd call me and I'd come down there, I'd look at the EKG and then
I would make the decision to activate or not activate the cath lab. But since Gene Brownwell
coined this term, time is myocardium. Since we understand that the longer that the heart is
deprived of oxygen, the less chance it's going to actually recover. There's been a push to
speed things up. And so now there's-
So the ER can now make that call.
Yeah. It's actually often made in the field. So the ER makes the call and the page goes directly
to the interventional cardiology team and the cardiology fellow and the attending. So when
I'm on service, I often learn about, I'm the last one to hear about a patient of ours who's come in
with a STEMI.
You hear about it when they're in the cath lab or maybe on the way out.
Yeah. I hear about it when the student or the intern calls and says, what do you want this dose
of this to be? In the old days, wasn't that long ago, 15 years ago, this cardiology fellow had to
make that call.
How much time has that saved? If you think about where we are today versus 10 years ago,
is that a half an hour savings potentially?
Maybe. I mean, every hospital now in this country is measuring their, what's called door to balloon
time or door to open artery time. It's a quality metric. And like every quality metric, they're
a trade-offs, right? So there are more people taken to the cath lab who probably don't belong there.
There are some people taken there who are maybe, you know, DNR, DNI, or have metastatic cancer,
or there are other things that you don't have the time to have a nuanced conversation and you're
not having a conversation with an expert. So there is a trade-off, but the overall net net,
I think there's our society of people, citizens and cardiologists and other people and emergency
room doctors, all I think all agree that this is better than it used to be. The dilly-dallying
that would happen and delays are gone. So the most important thing is get somebody up there.
If it's a mistake, it's a mistake. It's not the end of the world. It's a little bit of radiation.
And since we're-
So which trial, was it courage that made this case? Which is the trial that told us
that what you just said was really the right way to do things, that opening the artery in the
STEMI patients is going to save lives?
I'd have to go back. It was probably one of the early Timmy trials. I don't remember which one.
I'd have to go back and look about which one. There were a series of trials down in the 1990s
comparing what used to be called primary angioplasty. So angioplasty is the Greek
way of saying opening an artery with a balloon.
Can you explain just, I mean, there's going to be a lot of people listening to this who
won't necessarily know exactly what we mean. So when a patient goes into a cath lab,
what actually happens?
So again, a little bit different today than it was in the old days, because in the old days,
almost everybody had basically a needle put into the femorhoidy. So the femorhoidy is a major
offshoot of the aortic, feeds your leg oxygen.
You go into the crease in the groin and you can, anybody can feel their pulse there.
So if you feel that that's your femoral artery, that's about the size of your,
you know, somewhere between your pinky and your middle finger. I mean, that's a monster artery
and you're putting a catheter in there.
There's a technique called the modified cell gender technique, which allows you to put a catheter
into that artery. So that catheter then allows you to have access to the artery.
At the tip of that catheter is a one-way valve. You put things in, but blood can't come back out.
So through the tip of that catheter, there's a little plastic one-way valve and you can thread
things in. You can thread in other plastic catheters. So in this case, you thread in a regular
coronary catheter, which I think is like two millimeters. You thread that in, you can then
under x-ray guidance with a wire to make it a little stiffer, guide it all the way up
around the arch of the aorta and back down.
We'll have a figure of this for sure. So people can see what that does.
Back down to the base of the heart where the coronary osteoar. So they're normal human beings.
There's a left coronary osteoam and a right coronary osteoam. And you can put that catheter
and engage it. And then that allows you to inject contrast dye, which under x-ray will allow you to
actually see the artery or see at least the inverse of what the artery looks like. And then
what people realized was you can deliver other things through these catheters too. You can deliver
another smaller catheter. And on the tip of that catheter, you could wrap a balloon and then
basically you could use a syringe to blow up that balloon. And that would basically crush open the
blockage or clot or combination of whatever else it is that's there and reestablish blood flow.
So it's just, it's a very mechanical process. I mean, when people, I don't think necessarily
people appreciate just how mechanical and in some ways crude this is at the, you know, you described
an incredibly complex chemical reaction that is taking place. And one of our solutions is chemical,
right? We can inject something that can break apart the epoxy, but also we can put a balloon in
and use that balloon to inflate open and try to crack it open. And as you'll mention in a
moment, I'm sure you can put in these metallic things that spring open called stents.
It's such a good point, Peter. I mean, it's really, it's as if you went to a stream and there were a
beaver dam there and you just take a bulldozer or you take a shovel and just shove all of it
downstream. And so, you know, one of the questions I've always asked is, well, why is this
therapy not more effective? And we'll get into where it's effective and not effective, but is
there potentially a downside to elaborating all of that crap downstream? And does that have an
effect on smaller blood vessels or smaller areas of muscle that end up getting occluded by all this
stuff that you elaborate downstream when you're blowing open this artery? And actually goes back
to the question of sort of when people were doing these trials to compare the efficacy of what's
called primary angioplasty versus thrombolytics, TPA or streptokinase, these chemical drugs.
So the mechanical versus the chemical.
That's right. The reason that those drugs are not more effective is not that they're not
great at dissolving blood clots, although they're not perfect at it, but that by doing so,
you're increasing the risk of dislodging a blood clot somewhere else that might be really important.
So let's just say you had an injury in your head and there was a blood clot somewhere in your
subdural area. And so if you go in and you blow in this TPA, you're basically dissolving all blood
clots and it's not precise. It's sort of an imprecise, just every blood clot. So if you have one
somewhere in your GI tract, you'll start bleeding out there. And so the consequences of doing that,
I think we're great. And that's part of the reason why primary angioplasty again became standard of
care in this country. Because while the epoxy process requires two things and therefore is
highly specific and be localized, the clot busting is not. You have to put that solution
into the circulation. And even though you apply it locally, every time that heart beats, it gets
dissipated. So every part of the body is going to see it. So there are certain circumstances
where people try to deliver TPA or cousins of TPA locally. Like I think even in stroke,
they're still injecting TPA and trying to keep it relatively local. But it's a very difficult
process because as you say, circulation is circulation, right? I mean, it doesn't take
that long for something that's this part of your circulation to get around your whole body and come
back again. So that's why I think, well, I should say when I was a cardiology fellow in 2001, 2002,
we were still doing using TPA as a way of treating people who showed up with a heart attack at San
Francisco General Hospital. That's not the case anymore. I think most almost all US hospitals now
it's primary angioplasty. And so after you mentioned these stents, these little metal scaffolds,
they developed back in the 1990s as a means of treating stable angina. So if somebody came in
and they were having stable angina, they said, God, you know, doc, I'm walking up the hill and I get
this burning in my chest and I sit down and it goes away and I can't now I'm just not able to
walk anywhere. So what can we do? Well, people realize that if you went in there, you blow up
the balloon, this angioplasty thing, but if you wrap a metal scaffold around, it's almost like a
slinky around the balloon, when you blow up the balloon, you leave that behind and that helps to
keep the artery from recoiling back down. And so that was more of a physical barrier to the artery
coming back down. So people found that if you just did the balloon, this is back in the 1990s,
again, and people with stable angina, a certain percentage of them, probably 40, 50, 60% of people
would show up with what was called restenosis. And restenosis just meant that the artery would
narrow back down again. Some of that was thought to be physical. Some of it was thought to be
secondary to the injury you caused when you blow up the balloon. So people thought, well, gosh,
if you could believe this metal scaffold behind, you can actually improve the likelihood that it's
not going to restenose. So stents completely cured the physical recoil problem, which I think,
again, I don't know the exact number, but it was some nonzero number, but they left behind this
other problem, which was the injury problem. And so what people realized was that in the act of
blowing up the stent, you created a lot of injury on the vessel wall. And so the body's reaction to
that was to create scar tissue. And so then you'd get what now was called instant restenosis or ISR,
instant restenosis, which was basically the formation of a bunch of fibrous scar tissue
inside the stent. So before the era of what are now called drug eluting stents, this is back in
the 1990s. If you did a stent on somebody, again, stable angina, you'd see that there was some
likelihood that they'd come back within three to six months with recurrent symptoms. And you'd do
a stress test. You'd see that there was looked like there was a ischemia. You'd come back in,
you angiogram, you'd look at the artery, and there was narrowing again within the stent.
And that was called instant restenosis. We went through this entire period of five or seven years
of trying to find ways to solve restenosis, including radiating the inside of the vessel wall.
So, but when I was a cardiologist, we'd have the radiation oncologist come into the cath lab with
us. And we would put these radioactive beads up like in one of these balloon catheters into
somebody's artery and basically try to almost kill the fibroblasts and other cells that were going to
make the scar tissue. And God knows what we were doing to each other and to the patients. But that
went away in the early 2000s with the advent of what are called drug eluding stents. And we can
talk about those, but you probably already talked about them a bunch.
Well, no, no, I was just going to make the point, right? Which is we've sure talked a lot about my
favorite drugs that end up in these drug eluding stents, but why don't you take a moment to explain
why a drug that inhibits mTOR would find its way onto the coating of a metal stent?
I can't remember the exact story. I think it involved a guy who used to be a Columbia
named Andy Marks. I think he actually figured this stuff out, but we'll have to go back and do
a deep dive on that. But basically these drugs, these rapamycin and other drugs, these mTOR
inhibitors were known to be, I think first before even they were modulators of the immune system,
they were known to be anti-proliferative drugs that people use to treat cancer. And so again,
what I described in a simple way that I think about it is that it's a proliferation problem.
So these cells that are making in response to an injury, a real injury, they're making
they're making scar tissue. And so somebody realized, gosh, if you apply this drug,
you can block that proliferative process. So you can block the smooth muscle cells and
fibroblasts and other cells that are making this scar tissue. And what they realized was that you
could paint the outside of a stent with this drug. And so it would basically be there locally and it
wouldn't cause any systemic toxicity or any other problems. And it would just act on the cells that
you wanted it to. So that mostly got rid of that problem that we used to call instant
rheostenosis. For the most part now, that problem is no longer.
And there was a bit of a hiccup in oh, oh, five, oh, six, oh, seven, when they drug
eluding stents were briefly taken off the market. And my recollection is you had Medtronic still
had a bare metal stent that was basically getting all the market share while Boston Scientific and
Abbott were sitting their time out waiting for these drug eluding stents to come back. And I
recall that they even at one point, even Boston Scientific and Abbott had the same stent,
identical, but branded under different names. I mean, it was such an interesting time in the
cardiology world. I don't remember all the details. I remember that a lot of these reps from these
companies were in the cath lab and there was a big battle to get market share in these different
stents. And there were other things besides which drugs were on the stents. There were issues
around deliverability and how stiff they were and how long, you know, all these other things.
And so it was a, you know, as a general cardiology fellow and somebody who was interested in basic
science, I wasn't paying attention to the nitty gritty of kind of what was going on in this war
for market share. But there definitely was a lot going on. The biggest problem with these drug
eluding stents was, so if you back up to the early 1990s, when stents first started getting
used in coronaries, one of the biggest problems that happened was that you'd put the stent in
there and then within a period of a few weeks, a non-trivial amount of people would come back with
effectively was a STEMI. The stent would clot off. That was happening and that was bad. So there were
series of trials where people tried aspirin. I believe they tried warfarin. They tried everything
and they actually couldn't. So aspirin and warfarin are both blood thinners through different
mechanisms. That's right. So aspirin acts on platelets, warfarin blocks that coagulation cascade,
you know, downstream tissue factor. But people couldn't use these stents for a while. And then
in 1996, and I know this because I as a medical student had the ridiculously good fortune of being
the first author on a paper that was published in the knowing the journal of medicine and that same
issue. So our paper was forgotten mostly except for me. But in that same issue, and I looked at
it the other day, was a trial that demonstrated that you could do stenting of coronary arteries
safely with the addition of this drug that's no longer used because it had toxicity called
tyclopidine, Ticlid. And so Ticlid was the first generation of these what we call thienopyridines.
Thienopyridines act to block at the time we didn't notice, but they block a receptor on the surface
of a platelet that's called the ADP receptor. And it basically renders the platelet a little bit less
sticky or less prone to be activated and become sticky. And what these guys demonstrated, which
was transformational for interventional cardiology is if you gave people this drug Ticlid at the time
they got their stent, the chance of the stent clotting off went to almost zero. And eventually
that drug had some toxicity and was replaced with the drug that's used in most cases still today
called clopidogrel, which is acting on the same receptor. It's the same biology.
And patients might know that drug by a different name.
Plavix, right.
So today when a patient gets their stent, they also get a year supply of plavix. How long do we
keep it on?
Yeah. So where I was going with that was that there was this thing called subacute stent
thrombosis. So thrombosis is the word for blood clotting. Subacute means within a few weeks.
So back in the day, if somebody stopped taking their plavix or didn't get their plavix, there
was a likelihood that they would get this condition called subacute stent thrombosis.
Again, for all intents and purposes, it's like a STEMI because it's a complete stoppage of blood
flow and it's critical and people can die.
Which is kind of ironic, right? You can show up with a stable problem
that's chronic and through the intervention end up having an acute fatal complication.
That's right.
I mean, the stakes are so high.
Huge. And people did and it was bad. And there were lots of questions about why and all that
was happening. That problem mostly got solved for them. Again, 95 plus percent of people,
there was some discussion about plavix resistance and other things, but mostly that problem got
solved with plavix and people realized if you take plavix for a month after a bare metal stent,
you're good to go. So then people fast forward and you were in the drug looting stent era and
we've solved the restenosis problem, but people are showing up now. They've taken their plavix
for a month, but now they're showing up at three months, six months, nine months with not subacute,
but whatever the after subacute is stent thrombosis, late stent thrombosis and having again,
the same life threatening STEMI like experience. And what people realized was in the process of
inhibiting these cells, these smooth muscle cells and other cells that make the scar tissue,
we're also inhibiting the endothelial cells. So one of the things that happens,
if you take a patient who has a stent and that patient say dies in a car accident, you look
under the microscope pathologically, you'll see that that stent is now covered with endothelial
cells after about three weeks and it's the endothelial cells that prevent the blood clotting.
So the stent struts themselves are probably pro thrombotic. So they probably trigger some
clotting. So what we realized was that your own body would basically wall out the stent.
Which is exactly what you want in a good way to reproduce the endothelium that is this beautiful,
you know, I try to explain to patients that, you know, atherosclerosis is complicated.
And the reason that there's no one single causal factor is you have to have this sort of perfect
storm of endothelial injury. And that can be anything from smoking cigarettes will do that
to high blood pressure will do that. You have to have a lipoprotein that can actually carry
cholesterol through that injury. So you have that injury, you can carry through that has to
get oxidized and create an immune response that then has to lead to the formation of this plaque,
which for reasons that aren't entirely clear, some rupture, some don't and kick off the epoxy
problem. So what you just described is the body will reproduce that beautiful endothelium around
the metal stent again. And if that's what happens, you end up in the good camp. And if instead of
that happening, you kick off this inflammatory cascade again, you can get into a very bad
situation very quickly. Basically, the way to think about it is that most people with a bare
metal stent will re endothelialize the inside of the stem within, you know, like three weeks,
four weeks. So the standard of care in 2002, 2003, but before drug-leading stents was take
plavix for one month and you're done. And people did great. And then drug-leading stents come along,
they solve this one problem, but they create a new problem. The problem was that in addition to
inhibiting the proliferation of these smooth muscle cells and fibroblasts.
You inhibit the endothelium.
Exactly. So people were coming back with this stent thrombosis problem now, you know, months later,
then it became unclear about what the correct amount of time to take your plavix or other drug
was after a stent. And I think now there's some great work being done by people. I think for the
most part with these newest generation drug-alluding stents that have the right mixture and cocktail
of drug on them, and they're really easy to deliver and cause less injury, it's six months.
If something's complicated, if the patient has diabetes or other risk factors,
then you may extend the time. But again, what you're doing is you're buying bleeding risk
by inhibiting this risk of stent thrombosis. Obviously stent thrombosis is the worst. You
don't want, you can't have that. So when I have a patient who leaves the hospital and they say,
what do I take? I say, listen, if you're going to an island and you can only bring one thing with
you for the first, you know, whatever it is, few months, all that matters is your plavix. You've
got to take it every day. Right. At this point, whether you remember to take your statin or your
blood pressure drug, those are important. But yeah, that's a great way to put it.
If the ship is sinking, the highest priority is the lifeboat. This is your lifeboat.
It didn't get communicated clearly enough, I think, for a while. So when people would
shop in the hospital with stent thrombosis, it was often because they hadn't been told
appropriately strongly enough that they had to take plavix.
So you've done a great job of explaining the unambiguous part of interventional cardiology,
which is the case where I think most people agree interventional cardiology through the stent has
provided a survival benefit. There are a whole bunch of other areas where that is quite gray.
You and I have had some really interesting discussions about that going through
some of the really important trials in the past decade that have tried to ask
a question. So let's begin with the case that you described a while ago, which is
patient comes to see you in clinic says, you know, Dr. Weiss, God, it's just,
every time I get on that treadmill, I just get a tightness in my chest. And the other day I was
walking up the street and it was really steep and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. So they've got
stable angina. Let's assume you decide it's worth doing an angiogram in that person you do. And you
see low and behold, there is a 60 or 70% occlusion smack in the middle of their left interior
descending artery that runs right down the front of their left ventricle. What should you do? Maybe
another way to say it is what would people have normally said and what have the data now suggested?
I mean, this is one of the most controversial areas, I think, and least well understood areas
of medicine. I'm not even going to say cardiology. So in the 1980s, that patient gets a prescription
for nitroglycerin and beta blocker. So beta blocker helped reduce the demand. So basically,
it's like putting a governor on a car or golf cart. So you can't rev the engine as high. So you're
going to be less likely to get symptoms. And nitroglycerin, as we described, helps relax the
blood vessels and maybe also decreases demand by decreasing blood pressure. So it's basically
a couple of not great tools in the 1980s. And then people would go to a point where they
couldn't walk anymore. And eventually they'd get bypassed because there was no other option for
what we now call revascularization. Eventually, when stents became viable in the mid 1990s,
people realized, well, gosh, that person, if you open that artery and put a stent in there,
you can give somebody a really durable response and they won't have to take any of these medicines.
And just to be clear, at this point in time, we only had one sort of plumbing solution that had
been demonstrated to impact survival. And that, if I'm correct, it was Lima to LAD Cabbage. So I'll
explain what that is. So everything as you can tell in cardiology is an acronym. So Lima stands
for left internal mammary artery. So when you open up the sternum, you have these arteries on the
inside of the sternum. And the left and right version of these turn out to be the most important
conduits that you can use to bypass because they're already attached on one end and they're
beautiful blood sources. And you used to attach it what we call distally, so past the lesion.
And by the way, if my memory is correct, it was only Lima to LAD. It wasn't Lima to CERC. It wasn't
Lima to right man. There was nothing else. They did sham surgeries, if I recall, to demonstrate
that. I don't know if they did sham surgeries back then, but you're absolutely right. It was only
Lima to LAD. It was only a subset, right? So I think it was, you had to have multivessel disease,
blephentricular dysfunction, diabetes. I mean, there were a subset of people,
as not everybody got a mortality benefit. I'd have to go back and look at the...
Maybe those weren't the shams, but I know there were some sham surgeries that involved sternotomies,
which when you think about that, I mean, imagine signing that consent form. Golly.
So in defense of the cardiology community in the mid-90s, it wasn't an unreasonable hypothesis
that, hey, if taking the Lima and attaching it to the LAD, effectively bypassing this thing works,
at least in a subset of patients, shouldn't we be able to rotor rooter this thing and open it up
and get the same benefit, right? Right. And I think the important thing to remember is to define the
benefit you're interested in. So we need to talk about the two things that matter. And when a patient
comes to see me in the office or you in the office, we often end up talking about two things. One is,
how do I feel? So presence or absence of symptoms. And the second is, is this going to impact how
long I live? Mortality. And those are the two variables we think about every day in cardiology
and as you mentioned, there was evidence that this one procedure or a subset of these procedures
could confer a mortality benefit. But most of the time when we're talking about revascularizing or
treating stable angina, we're talking about treating symptoms. That remains true today.
And people sometimes poo-poo that, but I think it's important, at least for me, I like to dispel
that because there's certainly, I find a heavy dose of people in the peanut gallery who think
if it doesn't impact all-cause mortality, it's never worth talking about. And I suspect these
people have never taken care of patients. Of course not. No. I mean, look, if you can't walk
up your stairs, you can't garden, you can't hike with your wife, you can't go skiing with your
children. I mean, there are a lot of things that were- You can't have sex. Yeah. Yeah. Yes. And all
that stuff I think is incredibly important and it shouldn't just because you're not conferring a
mortality benefit, all-cause mortality benefit, doesn't mean that there's not benefit. So I think
that the advent of the statin era was remarkable. It happened to coincide with the advent of the
statin era, right? So the first statin, lowest statin was approved in 1988, I believe. So
remember I had said that we were treating people with angina with basically beta blockers and
nitrates. And so then statins got added to the mix. They weren't initially added for treatment
of stable disease. They were there for, they were initially tested in people who were having
unstable disease, but it quickly became obvious that they were going to become an important
mainstay of treatment of people with stable coronary disease as well. So this idea that
even if there's an intervention that doesn't extend life by one day, if it improves the quality of
life, it should still be on the table. So walk us through a little bit of the trial architecture
and how it navigated how we ought to treat these patients with stable angina, or you can even
define it as the, if you want to do it through the ACS language, feel free as well. So let's back up
and just make sure we reemphasize, because I don't think this point cannot be emphasized too many
times. So if you show up in the hospital or in the emergency room or anywhere in the world with
this ST elevation, MI a STEMI, in other words, that ST segment is increased above baseline
and you're having a heart attack. Yeah. It's a do not pass. Go do not collect $200. You're
going straight to the Catholic. That's right. If you show up and you have a non STEMI, so chest
pain, let's say you have positive biomarker. So now modern day we use another biomarker called
troponin, which is just a component of the architecture that allows muscles to contract.
And there's an isoform of flavor of it that's specific to cardiac muscle. So if you show up
with some of that in your blood, it signals that your heart has suffered cell death muscles have.
And so that's part of the diagnosis. So you show up with chest pain, positive troponin,
and any KG change that is not ST elevation, anything other than ST elevation, it could be normal.
That puts you into a different category. And mostly in the United States, the management of
depending on a couple of factors, but most people are managed either what's called medically. So
with a bunch of medicines or they go down a path of interventional cardiology. So now let me ask you
a question, even we didn't distinguish this, but it's worth adding in the STEMI patient. You don't
care if they're hemodynamically stable or not. In other words, if their blood pressure is stable,
they're having chest pain, but they're not in extreme distress, they're still going to the
cath lab. In the non STEMI patient has chest pain, patient has the enzymes, EKG looks normal,
but presumably there are still cases where those patients are not hemodynamically stable.
So if you have what we would call complicated non STEMI, so hemodynamic instability, I mean,
your blood pressure is very low or you have heart failure, you fluid in your lungs,
something else that makes it complicated or you can't treat people can't make their chest pain go
away with medicines, something that makes it complicated or ongoing concerning KG changes,
or just you don't feel right. That patient also can go to the cath lab. It isn't an emergency
unless there's hemodynamic instability, but oftentimes people will go along the same timeline.
It won't may not be within 60 minutes, but it'll be quickly. Again, depending on how complicated,
if you have uncomplicated non STEMI, so the blood pressure is fine. You don't have any evidence of
congestive heart failure. There's nothing else that makes this look scary. Those patients can
be managed either non-invasively with medicines or invasively. And we can talk a little bit about
how that happens. There was a period of time, I think in this country where most of those people
went into the interventional arm where they went and got, and they went to the cath lab and they
would get a stand. And I think in the past few years there have been questions about the sort of
value of that. And there's debate about that, but just to be clear, there's one area of medicine
where there's no debate, which is there's a more clear mortality benefit by opening up the artery.
Again, if you're in Uganda and you don't have a cath lab, then TPA is the best you can do,
but opening the artery saves lives. In the non STEMI situation, if you're hemodynamically unstable,
again, same thing, opening the artery saves lives. If you're hemodynamically stable,
things start to become a little bit more gray and then stable angina, which is the last thing we'll
come back to, there's a huge amount of gray area. Again, about mortality, not symptoms.
So let's talk about Orbida. What did that trial look at? What question did it try to answer?
This trial was published in November of 2017, I believe. And it was done by a group in London
who I had never heard of before this trial came out. I guess Darryl Francis was the PI and I think
he was well known in the interventional cardiology community, but not to those of us who are not in
in that world. This trial shook the world. Actually, we should probably talk about courage
before we talk about it. Let's do that. Yeah, thank you. Let's go. Because I alluded to courage and
then we got off topic. Tell me about courage. So courage was published in 2007. And if anybody
asks me what courage stands for, I don't remember. I don't remember either. Yeah, but it's an
acronym that is put together to explain what the trial was about. And I also can't remember who the
PI was, but that study, so again, we're talking at this point back about stable angina. So people
who are not showing up in the hospital with new symptoms or new EEG changes, this is a totally
different animal. This is somebody who's been out living in their home and they have symptoms that
have been going on for some period of time. So courage was designed to ask the question and
answer the question of is there in addition to a symptom relief that you'd get from putting a
stent in an artery of somebody who's got a blocked artery and has stable angina? By the way,
I'm just going to interject. So I'm going to make a plug for one of my favorite apps, which is
incredibly dorky. It's called trials. I don't know if you've seen this app, but let me show it to you
and we'll make sure we link to it. So the, I'm sorry, the app is called journal club. It's either
free or very cheap. So if you go into journal club, you can search every single clinical trial
in the history of mankind. So I just went courage and it pulled it up and it's, it gives you just a
treatise on the topic, right? It gives you the bottom line and then it tells you what it stands
for. Okay. So major points. So it's called clinical outcomes utilizing revascularation and aggressive
drug evaluation, parentheses courage. And then it goes through and explains everything about it. So
if you're listening to this and you're a physician and you don't have this app, get it.
And truthfully, even if you just have a tincture of interest in clinical trials, this is a great app
to have. I must look at this like once every two or three days and you can screen and search by,
like sometimes if I'm just sitting around and I've got 20 minutes to kill and I'm kind of bored and
it's, you know, I'm in the, I'm on the runway and it's taken a while to take off. I'll just open it
up and search by subjects. Like I wonder what's going on in oncology in the last two months,
what new trials have come out. So anyway, journal club is awesome. Well, now you can read it and see
how close I am. So I'll try to be, I will be intentionally less detailed about what have I,
how I described these trials since everyone's going to be reading along. So anyway, this trial
was designed with one purpose. And the purpose of this was to compare maximum medical therapy to
stenting in patients with stable coronary disease. And the idea was, is there a benefit in terms of
reducing the risk of heart attack or some other heart outcome like death in patients when you
randomly assign them in a non-blinded manner to be treated with maximum medicines or stents.
Non-blinded meaning they did not do sham procedures in the people who randomized to no stent.
That's right. So obviously you as a patient or you as a doctor knows if you're going to go get a
stent or not. So you, you were told you've been assigned to this category, you're going to get
medical therapy and then they got medicines. And this is something I have to go back and look at,
but I believe the people randomized to the interventional arm also got aggressive medical
therapy. I don't think there were huge differences, but that may be one of the areas where the,
there was debate. But the net of this whole thing was that this trial was organized and run by
interventional cardiologists. And the purpose of it was to demonstrate that there's a benefit in
heart outcomes by stenting that this, we were going to prove finally that opening the arteries
did more than just relieve symptoms. And it was negative, completely negative. So there was no
difference between the two arms. I can't remember the details cause it's been over 10 years, but
there may have been, I remember that because like I said, I just saw that it was 2007. I was going
to guess 2006, but I kind of remember where I was when that study came out. And boy, that was like
a big hit in an industry where it was pretty much the wild West at that point in terms of the number
of stents people were getting. I mean, we used to joke about it kind of teasing these guys,
which is like, God, if somebody looks at you wrong in the parking lot, you're going to put a stent in
them. Well, it was. And this was the era again, where there were people, like there was this
hospital up North, I think it was like a tenant hospital where there was this guy who was stent,
you'd show up there with like too much farting or something. And then he'd do a calcium scan on you
and you'd see like a, you know, calcium score of 20. And he'd say, we got to take you to the cath lab.
And then he'd put stents in you. And there was really no way to argue against that.
Even in asymptomatic people, it was just a crazy time. So this, this definitely was a big result
in cardiology, particularly in interventional cardiology. It was not met without criticism,
as you can imagine. And I can't remember all the details, but there were definitely some
big questions raised. But the net of it was, Hey, look, the other way to look at this is that we've
been doing trials of stenting for a long time now. And no one outside of the STEMI situation has
demonstrated any benefit in hard outcomes that to date. So, you know, you could say the burden
of proof, the onus is on the interventional cardiology community to prove it. So they tried
and they failed. So I think that was a big practice changer. I think what that told you was, look,
again, back to what we were talking about earlier, this is a symptom management problem.
We're not doing this to extend life. Doesn't mean that it's not important. It doesn't mean
that you still don't use it as a tool, but it, maybe it shouldn't be the primary tool.
Maybe the primary tool should be, Hey, look, let's try and use these medicines,
which are really effective and we'll optimize them as best we can. And if that doesn't work,
then we'll go down the path of trying to open the artery. And so it really did change. I think the
way we managed people, again, mostly outpatients, mostly stable, legitimate patients.
So then what was the impetus for orbiter 10 years later?
Well, I would have to ask the Daryl and I hope someday you could ask him because he's a
phenomenally entertaining guy.
You got me on to him and his work and I follow him on Twitter now and I think he's in the UK and
I can't, I can't wait to hopefully meet him at some point.
He made this like tremendous appearance and splash on Twitter that year and a half ago and like
set the world on fire because he was fearless and obnoxious and just everything you'd love about him.
And, and I guess he pissed a lot of people off and somebody basically pulled his plug. So he's
been really quiet, if not completely absent from Twitter for the past, I want to say six months,
but anyway, he was the PI on this study orbiter and the impetus there was, okay, well, courage
kind of established that there's not going to be a benefit in terms of heart outcomes. So we're
really, we've sort of settled on this idea that stents are there and they're useful for treating
symptoms in patients who fail medical therapy, but orbiter was our stents actually even doing
what they're supposed to do in terms of reducing symptoms. So orbiter, you mentioned sham trials.
This was the first sham trial that I, interventional cardiology that I knew of.
So orbiter stands for objective randomized blinded investigation with optimal medical
therapy of angioplasty in stable angina. And one of the beauties of naming clinical trials
is you can use a sentence with as many words in it as you want, as long as you capitalize
the beginning of the words that you want in your acronym, you get it. So if you just heard me read
that and said, how the hell does that work out to orbiter? You only capitalize the objective
randomized blinded investigation therapy angioplasty. Yeah. Well, that app would have
been fun as a medical student because you used to get pimped on kind of what were the key trials
and stuff. So anyway, the key differentiator of this trial is blinded, which meant there were sham
procedures done. So what they did was they took people who had demonstrated documented angina
and lesions. So they all had catheterizations, whereas I think in courage, they were randomized
after a stress test. I don't think everybody had an angiogram before they got randomized. In this
case, they got randomized after the angiogram showing that they had a blockage.
They could not have three vessel disease or left main disease. I think there were a few
other exclusions, but these were people who could have one, two advanced disease
and they could be tight lesions. They could be 95, 98% lesions. Then they were randomly assigned
to get either optimized medical therapy or stent. And that was done blind to the patient
and blind to the, not the obviously the interventional cardiologist, but to the
treating referring physician. So if I sent you in to be randomized in this trial, you and I would
not know what you got because they would take you to the cat lab. They'd put a catheter in your leg.
They'd wind a catheter up into your corner or osteo and they would pretend to blow up a balloon
and you wouldn't know what you got. And it was a small trial, which was one of the major criticisms,
I think, because it was such a small trial and I'm not a trialist. So I don't get into the nitty
gritty on kind of what makes trials more or less robust. Well, I mean, from a size perspective,
the issue comes down to power. I think this is the biggest challenge of trial design.
People talk a lot about significance, which is what the P value tells you, but people don't talk
a lot about power, which is beta. And the idea here is you have to have some sense, a priority
of how much of a difference you will see to design your trial because you have to know how
many people to put in it. Because if the trial comes out and there is a significant difference,
a statistically significant difference, which is usually defined as a P value less than 0.05,
meaning there is a less than 5% chance that the difference you have observed is due to chance,
then power becomes irrelevant. It's just that power becomes so important when the opposite
happens, when you don't see a difference. And it's your ability to say, we don't see a difference
and we believe that a difference is not there versus we don't see a difference, but we didn't
have enough people to look at it. So for example, if I was going to design a trial with me and Ethan,
just as the two of us, it's quite likely that I would never find a statistically significant
distinction. But that doesn't mean that the metric I'm looking at doesn't exist. It's just with two
people in a trial, the probability that I'm going to find it is incredibly low unless the difference
is egregious. So I've always found this to be the biggest challenge of clinical trials,
is that you have to have some sense of your expected outcome to select beta to power the
study appropriately. And this was the obviously the core place that people argued because it was
a small trial and people said it's an underpowered study and there's, you couldn't see a difference.
Study was interesting because they, they both asked people sort of how do you feel in terms of your
angina? So how, every one of these patients had some frequency of anginal episodes. They'd get
chest pain if they walked or did something, but then they did some objective things too. So they
did stress testing. I believe they did like the obedience stress test. So basically they,
it's a way of looking to see objectively was there more or less ischemia and they also did
treadmill tests. So they looked at their exercise capacity and how long they could exercise before
they got symptoms. And I don't want to get misspeak and piss off all my interventional friends,
but for the most part, the thing was pretty negative. And I think there might've been a
slight difference in the treadmill time. There was something very slight, but for the most part,
it was a negative study. And so the result, which ended up splashed all over the New York
Times, the wall street journal and every other news organization you could think of the conclusion
that was sort of reported to the general public was stents. Not only did they not reduce your
risk of having a heart attack or dying, they don't even reduce your symptoms. And so it became a
sort of firestorm of conversation. And this was not long after former president George W. Bush
had a stent placed after what I don't believe was a STEMI. That's right. He had stable angina,
same thing. And this goes back to the old days of when people would do routine sort of
surveillance stress testing in people to look for these 70% blockages and then they'd go and
stent them. This was the way things operated until relatively recently. So what we learned
from that trial was, look, this may have been underpowered, but at the very least it tells
you again and again and again that medical therapy is really good. So modern medical optimized
therapy is great. And so the way I, what I took home from this trial and what I convey to my
patients today, along with the important caveat that what I convey to you today is very likely to
be a lot different from what I convey to you tomorrow. But I say what I can be today is that
while stents may or may not be useful in some circumstances at reducing your symptoms, if you
have bad symptoms, it's very unlikely that in stable angina they're going to do anything else.
But either way, it's our job to try to manage you as best we can with medicines before we go down
that path, because there are going to be consequences of putting a stent in you. And we've
all seen these patients who end up with 20 and 30 stent, you know, tons and tons of stents. And
again, taking a stent is not just an isolated experience. It means going on one of these
powerful blood thinning medicines like Plavix or a more powerful one. And it means a lot of other
things that we do and don't understand. So what I say is, look, our job, our obligation is to try as
best we can to use medicines to optimize you. If we fail at that, we're going to keep that stenting
procedure in our back pocket. If you come back to me in three months and you say either one of two
things, either these medicines are not working and I'm still having a lot of chest pain,
then we go down, then we can say, let's go look at opening the artery with a stent. Or if you say to
me, these medicines are making me feel miserable. Like I just, I don't like the way I feel. I want
to take fewer medicines. I also believe it's reasonable at that point to say, all right,
let's go see what we can do with a stent. So I have not stopped referring people
to interventional cardiology. In fact, I probably haven't changed dramatically how many people get
stent. Courage probably did change it a little bit, but for the most part, I'm sending the same
number of people. I'm sending the same people to the cath lab as I did before or whatever.
Yeah, it's probably just the composition of those patients is probably migrating constantly.
And that's, I think some people, you know, you said something sort of interesting that I think
for some people is frustrating to hear, which is what do you mean what you're telling me today
could be different tomorrow? But that's unfortunately the nature of science. I,
one of the things I like to say, and I wish I knew who said it first because I,
I feel like I'm plagiarizing it though. I don't actually recall is that all facts have a half
life. And in some ways that's the single most exciting thing about science. I mean,
it would be kind of boring if all of the natural universe and the, and its laws were known. And
this was just a game of memorizing all those facts. I mean, I just don't think science would
be nearly as interesting as the fact that we're constantly in the dark trying to refine our
knowledge. You can say that on a micro level and a macro level. I mean, I always tell people that
work with me in our, in my lab, in our lab that, you know, if you know the answer to the experiment
before you do them, we don't need to, we don't need to experiment. Just stop. We can write it up,
right? What are we going to learn? And the other thing is that the results of these experiments,
whether they're experiments in a lab, cells and tissues or animals, or whether they're clinical
experiments that are done on lots of human beings, there is some likelihood that that result is
quote unquote wrong. Even a P value of 0.05 means that there's a 95% chance that it didn't
happen by chance, but there's a 5% chance that it, that result did happen by chance. So there is
a constant refining of what is truth or what is as close as what we can call to truth. And so I
think we have to stay humble. I love it when I'm wrong. And there have been a few examples this
year where I've been wrong, brutally wrong. And it, it brings me joy. Like I, it's a great, I love
it when something defies my expectation. I don't know that I can say I enjoyed as much as you do,
but if I just look at constantly being challenged, I mean, you know, at the time of this recording,
there is just such a gauntlet being thrown down to challenge the dogma around utility of vitamin
D and sunscreen. That's something that I've been spending a lot of time reading about in the past
two months. And I have to tell you, I don't know that I would say I love the fact that I probably
know nothing about this now based on all of this new information that is emerging,
but it's certainly exciting. I mean, it is so great to say, wow, I get to go back and learn
this whole thing all over again. And you sort of have to hope that there hasn't been damage done
in a previous paradigm that's being turned over. You know, you brought up your labs,
so I want to talk about that, but I'm not ready to leave this topic yet because I want you to
give us a quick or reasonably quick primer on other things that tend to confuse patients, such as
calcium scores versus CT angiograms. And I even want to touch on heart flow in a minute because
that comes back to it. So I think the listeners know what a calcium score is in a CT angiogram is,
but so just give this the quickest sense of that because what I'm much more interested in is,
what do the results tell us? As a cardiologist practicing in 2019, I struggle with the question
of whether I'm going to help you or hurt you, that I feel this tremendous sense of uncertainty about
whether I should be as aggressive as I can picking up every rock and looking under everything
and trying to optimize to the best of my extent, my ability versus whether that may be the best
thing I can do is leave you alone. And you've probably seen examples too where, I mean,
I remember again as a cardiology fellow, maybe even as a resident where somebody would come in
from an outside hospital sick as shit, just absolutely on death's door. And all we did was
turn off everything and the patient got better because they were just overmanaged. And I think
I struggle a little bit with this sort of where I want to be in that spectrum and how aggressive I
should be in looking for say a cult coronary disease, which I think is a question you get
a lot and I get a lot. One of the major reasons somebody comes to see me as a preventive
cardiologist is they say, am I going to die of a heart attack? And what's my risk of dying from a
heart attack? Or my brother died of a heart attack at 44, what should I do? And I still don't have an
answer about how aggressive I should be in trying to understand it. But a lot of these tests we'll
talk about, I think feed into that. And I think ultimately what we're missing, and I hope we can
eventually refine it and make it better, is a good way to predict disease risk in these chronic
diseases, these common chronic diseases like cardiovascular disease, metabolic disease, that
we just don't now yet have the tools to be able to say, Peter, well, your risk is X, Y, or Z. And so
therefore we should do this or this or this in terms of prevention. Understanding that there's
going to be risk in each one of these things that we do and there may be risk in even part of the
process of getting from here to here, point A to point B. So I'm glad you brought that up because
it illustrates the challenge that frankly can't be explained or rationalized or described on Twitter,
not to pick on Twitter, but just to... So there's this idea which you've said, which is,
I don't know sometimes how aggressive to be or not to be. And what you're really saying is at the
individual level with you as my patient sitting in front of me, I don't know how aggressive to be or
not to be. You're not asking the question on average. And yet what tool are you given to guide
you? You are given a tool called a clinical trial, which is by its very nature all about averages.
And so therein lies the mismatch of what I've described as Medicine 2.0. When I say described,
meaning I'm writing about it in this book I'm working on that hopefully I'll have finished
by the time I'm alive or not alive. And the idea is it's not the poo poo clinical trials,
it's just to acknowledge that clinical trials give us great information on averages and the
larger and more robust the trial, generally the more heterogeneous the data. But you've asked
a question that comes down to judgment. You know what it means to be aggressive and you know what
it means to be conservative and you know what the corners of that box look like. What you're asking
is I could have two people in front of me that superficially look similar, but actually one of
them is probably going to have a better outcome if I behave aggressively and the other one might have
a better outcome if I behave conservatively. It's the challenge to figure out which one's which.
If you're a hammer and everything's a nail, even if you're acting as a hammer and nail in
accordance with clinical trials, I suspect you are still acting in a very blunt manner.
A hundred percent, but I'm also talking about these areas and I think prevention is a great
example that are sort of outside the boundary of what's been studied or is likely to be studied
in the context of a clinical trial. I mean there's not going to be a clinical trial to answer a lot
of the questions that I have about how to manage my patients. I feel the same way. I mean prevention
is not really amenable to this idea of medicine 2.0, which is clinical trial, average outcome,
short duration, simple intervention, easy to measure outcome. It's the economic thing. I mean
you're a company and you want to get your product to market whether that product is a stent or a
drug or whatever it is and the best way to do that economically is the shortest amount of time and so
you want to take the sickest people. So these trials, I mean I joke that like a prevention
trial, all kinds of trials that I want to do would take 50 or 60 years. How do you convince somebody
I'm about to be 50? I wouldn't want to start a trial that I'm not going to see the answer from,
the result from. So it's unsettling to me and again I think you just have to remain humble as
I've tried to and hope that your patients, your human patients have some patients that were going
to be wrong. Their litany of examples like LPLAA was something I didn't pay attention to until
the past few years. Coronary calcium scan, if somebody came to see me with a coronary calcium
scan 10 years ago, I would say I wish I didn't have this information but I never ordered one
before seven to eight years ago. So there are lots of examples of things that I didn't use to do that
I've now incorporated into my practice and I'm doing so without that like safety belt of evidence
basis that we're used to, right? There's not going to be a orbit like trial to help me decide whether
I should be aggressive with lipid lowering in a 35 year old. That's not going to happen with primary
prevention. So we have a mutual patient in whom that's exactly the type of question that's being
asked, right? Yeah. And there's a term and I know all these cute little terms and I never know who to
attribute them to but we talk about evidence-based medicine versus evidence-informed medicine. And to
me the latter just makes much more sense because these decisions that you have to make virtually
every day and I feel like I'm in the same situation, virtually nothing that I do can I
point to the orbiter or courage equivalent. I mean it just doesn't exist and certainly not if you
really wanted to scrutinize it, every single thing is a variation on a theme that stems from some
clinical trial. But if you really wanted to be a skeptic you would say nope that's not the exact
same patient and that's not the exact same situation and therefore you can talk yourself
out of doing anything. And I'm super fond of saying that being a preventive cardiologist is
no one should feel sorry for me. I have the best job in the world but it's difficult in that we
only know success by the absence of failure. So there's no one who's going to come to me tomorrow
and say gosh Ethan, thank you for the fact that I'm 46 that I did not have a heart attack again
this year. It just doesn't happen. That's a great way to explain it. Whereas the other way around
like I've had a few patients. But as an orthopedic surgeon for example, you break your leg,
you fix it. Or an interventional cardiologist, right? You show up in the cath lab with that
STEMI, you know what you did. The outcome is clear. The outcome is not that clear in prevention unless
there's failure. So those examples and I've had a few recently that I've been public about them
on Twitter that are treatment failures but maybe not personal failures. In fact, I don't think I
managed the patients incorrectly. But the fact is they had events while they were under my care.
Those live with you for a long time. So then the question is, I know you're a race card driver,
the question is, is your reaction to that to then have a tendency to want to oversteer?
So because I have these anecdotes, these very profound anecdotes of young people who've had
terrifyingly scary outcomes and I was not as aggressive as I could have been but probably
still following the sort of guidelines, is that going to guide me as a physician to be more
aggressive in the future? And again, we're not going to have clinical trial data to help us here.
This is all art and judgment. The subtitle of my book, I'm hoping if the publisher lets me,
is going to be called The Science and Art of Longevity. There's a title to it, but that's
the subtitle and I'm insistent upon that order because normally you say it in the reverse,
the art and science of whatever. But it's the science and art. You're informed by science,
but in the end, this still comes down to an art.
Well, it's the art of the science too, as you said. It is sort of how do you put this and then
there's the whole other layer, which is how do you communicate it with your patients and how do you
include them as a partner in making these decisions? I mean, that's where things get
really interesting. And there are other physicians because typically these are not just discussions
between two people. So what's a CAC, what's a CTA and how do you use them?
The way I break this down is there's anatomy, so anatomic tests and their physiologic tests. So
physiologic tests, it'd be like a stress test, a treadmill test. So you get up on the treadmill,
you walk and then you have one of a few different ways to kind of determine in addition to whether
you have symptoms, determine whether there's ischemia, meaning there's a difference in the supply and
demand of oxygen. So you can use an EKG or you can use an ECHO or you can use what's called nuclear,
which is basically a radio labeled potassium analog that lights up living cells. So that's one
way, that's the physiology. And that's been the standard of care in this field for 40 years.
In the past 20 years or so, people have started to explore whether there's a role for anatomy. So
one anatomic test is an angiogram. So you can take somebody to the cath lab and you can
put a catheter up there and inject some dye into the artery and you can see if it looks like there
are blockages. That's not something that you would apply broadly to a population. You wouldn't use
that as a screening test. And patients often ask me, in fact, sometimes people will come in the
office and they'll say, I should have an angiogram. No symptoms, just I want to have an angiogram. I
want to know that I don't have any. Right. Just to preventative, get a baseline. Yes. Which is very
much like I want to make sure I don't have colon cancer or breast cancer. And the same things that
come up as being difficult and controversial in any screening, whether it's prostate cancer
screening, breast cancer screening, any of these screening areas are going to be super controversial
here. But I think the community agrees mostly that screening angiography is not appropriate. But
the question is, are there other things that could be appropriate in the right people?
And in general, the population of people that we're talking about are people in this intermediate
risk category. So if you're low risk, for the most part, there's not going to be much benefit to
adding one of these tests. We're talking about asymptomatic people here. So if you're symptomatic,
you fall into a different category altogether. So asymptomatic people, and if you're high risk,
you probably fall into a different category as well. And what I tell people is that the results
of these anatomic tests that we might do are really about answering one question, which is
how aggressive should we be with our medical therapy? And what they are, they are triggers
for basically saying yes or no to statins or yes or no to statins and PCS-canine inhibitors.
Basically, it's a way of gauging how aggressive we want to be. So again, low risk, you're probably
not going to use a statin anyway, except in sort of unusual circumstances. Say somebody has like a
very early and extreme family history or something else is funny, but if somebody falls into a low
risk category, they probably get left alone. So it's these intermediate risk people. So
there was a doctor, I believe he was from Houston named Agustin, and he came up with this idea so
people could see on chest x-rays back a hundred years that if somebody had a blocked artery,
that there was a likelihood that you could see the outline of the artery on the chest x-ray,
that's because calcium is radio opaque. So people realize that these arteries, again by autopsies
and other conventional imaging, that these arteries get calcified as they develop more plaque. And so
this radiologist in Houston figured out that there was a linear relationship between the amount of
plaque that you have and the degree of calcium that you have in your arteries. And so he developed a
quantitative measure and that's called the coronary artery calcium scan or SCORE. And that
is a low dose radiation screening test that basically just looks for this one thing,
which is calcium. And then it quantitatively tells you how much you have and it then gives you
on a percentile basis what you are, what you should be based on your age and sex.
So that's a calcium scan. It's worth pausing for a moment to make sure, because this is a discussion
I tend to have with patients a lot, which is what does it mean if it shows nothing, meaning your
score is zero? What does it mean if it shows anything that's not zero? And to explain this
to patients, I usually have to again pull out the pathology textbook and explain all of the things
that happen before you would see calcification. So when you look at the stages of lesions,
calcification is a very late process. You described it earlier as basically the repair
of damage. So if you have a calcium score of zero, does it mean you have perfect coronary
arteries? You can't conclude. Yeah, this is a really important point. And to me, there's been
a lot of work on sort of what people call the power of zero. So what does a calcium score of zero
mean? To me, it's all about the context. So in a 25 year old or my 15 year old daughter is going to
have a calcium score of zero. It's meaningless. It gives you absolutely no additional risk
stratification. Conversely, when a 90 year old shows up and has a calcium score of zero,
it's quite informative. Informative. And in fact, I have some patients in their 70s and 80s
who I've taken off of statins because they had a calcium score of zero. And in those patients,
their risk of having a heart attack is not zero, but it's low one percent. I mean, again, let's
remember that the biggest risk factor for having a heart attack is your age. So age supersedes
everything else that supersedes all the other known risk factors that we use every day. Your
lipids, your blood pressure, the presence or absence of diabetes. Although I will throw in my
rant here. Why is age the greatest risk factor? I don't know. It's a good question. I mean, I would
argue as Alan Snyderman has argued that it's an area under the curve issue. It's an exposure
question. So age is the greatest risk factor for a number of diseases in which it's not entirely
clear why, but I think in atherosclerosis, you would have to argue that this area under the curve
shows a monotonic progression in an individual just as we see progression of polyptych cancer
in the colon. So that's exactly why I think the older you are, the more interesting it is to have
a zero calcium score. It's Bayes theorem at its finest. You are acquiring more and more information
as somebody goes on. So, you know, when I see 35 year olds with zero calcium scores saying, see,
I'm totally fine. I say, I have no goddamn clue. How do you know that? But the contrast is that if
you see a 35 year old who does have calcium. That's exactly right. That's informative. So there you
have the way I describe it is it's a two by two and there's only two quadrants that are interesting
to me. Young people, meaning someone under say 45 or 50 who has calcification and old people,
and I'm sorry to use the term old, but older folks call it someone over 70 who has no calcification.
If you're in those categories, Bayes theorem is lighting up like ding, ding, ding, ding, ding,
ding, ding. If you're in the other two quadrants, I don't think I've learned anything mostly. So I
started again, I frame this as I started off thinking there was no value calcium scans.
I evolved to think, all right, well, there's going to be value in these two
quadrants you describe. I also think there's probably some value in the extremes in say,
I saw a patient recently who was in his fifties, early fifties who had a calcium score of 1300,
asymptomatic primary prevention. I have a 49 year old who just scored 4500.
So that, I mean, that to me is useful, right? So that takes us again, not going to ever be
supported by clinical trials, but that takes us from, okay, well now we all agree that you should
be on at least statin for primary prevention, but maybe we want to be even more aggressive,
right? And so that's when you start thinking, this is actually going to change what we do
or change at least in my head, the risk benefit ratio. Anecdotally, I want to tell you about that
patient because this is just getting off in the weeds a little bit. This is a patient who's
family history. If I shared it with you, you would say, oh, he's going to have an elevated LP little
A. Father had first MI at 42, dead by 49, brother had MI in forties, et cetera, et cetera. When you
hear these stories, you say, well, it's elevated LP little A for sure. You do an advanced blood
test on him, normal LP little A, and you want to know something else? Lip bits aren't even that
crazy. It's not like he's got FH. It's not like he's got an Apo B in the 99th percentile. Yeah,
he's probably in the 70th percentile, but it's like these are the patients that keep you up at
night. And it's like when I was talking to Richard Isaacson about Alzheimer's disease,
he's way more afraid of the patients with a ravaging family history of Alzheimer's disease
who have normal Apo E because there's clearly something going on and I don't even know what
it is. And that's sort of how we feel about these patients of which we have many where it's not even
like, you know, they're at the 70th or 80th percentile of risk by lipids and by other metrics,
but by story and now by calcium and other tests. I mean, they're at the 99th percentile. I had a
patient I talked about a lot on Twitter a couple of weeks ago who ended up in his early fifties,
they ended up having like a very, very tight proximal left main, like just the kind of thing
that you're the so-called widow maker. You look at this thing and you think there's no way in the
world this guy should have walked into my office and he did. And his first past lipids were all
completely normal. You know, his regular fasting lip. He had no obvious risk factors. And then
we got his LPA back and it was high and I was relieved and I was relieved because on the one
hand I knew I understood what was going on. On the other hand, we're still left with this.
Well, we still don't really have a direct therapy to offer.
But at least we've got a couple of indirect things till Sam Tameka says ASOs are around.
Did you look at his aortic valve yet? It's normal.
It is. Yeah.
That's so interesting. I would have guessed someone that young with such aggressive
athera would also have something abnormal in his aortic valve. Interesting. All right. So that's
the calcium score. I've always found it very difficult to interpret the data on this because
they tend to report it without clearly specifying the age cohort. So for example, everybody loves
to quote a study that would say a zero calcium score means your 10 year risk is 1.9% or something
to that effect. But you can't actually say that without knowing the age of the cohort
because a zero calcium score in a group of 30 year olds probably has a 10 year risk of less than 1%.
A zero calcium score in a cohort of 70 year olds would clearly be 5 to 10% still. So that's another
thing that I just find very sloppy. But I don't have these discussions too much in social media
because I find it so frustrating. But it's that you just don't have the time to explain that nuance
to folks. It's a great point. And I use the Mesa calculator because it's a nice, you know, it has
the traditional risk factors and then you can add in the calcium score if you have it.
So Mesa, multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis, one of the two largest cohorts we have
ever to study atherosclerosis along with Framingham. And then they'll give you the 10 year risk
plus or minus. So they'll say, well, this is what the 10 year risk would have been without the
calcium. And that's somewhat helpful. But again, it comes back to this being way more
art than science. I mean, this is at this point in primary prevention, this is still
very much art and not science and probably will be for our lifetime. So we'll have to get used to that.
So then CT angiograms basically said, look, we're going to do more or less what the angiogram did
in terms of providing anatomic detail because the calcium score doesn't really give you anatomic
detail of the artery. It's basically just showing you show me every place where there was a disaster
that's been repaired. The CTA says, well, now I'm going to actually show you both the negative and
positive image of the artery. So you'll see everything that's going on. But it's in many
ways even a better test than the angiogram because you get to see the wall and you can look for soft
plaque or other forms of injury to the artery that haven't yet reached the point of calcification.
Assuming somebody doesn't have a lot of calcium, if somebody has a lot of calcium, then you can't
really do it. And assuming that you can block the heart down, the scanners have gotten fast enough
now that the quality of the data we get back from these is spectacular. And we get this information
we never used to have unless you did Ivas. So I was as intrasculine ultrasound. So when you do an
angiogram, you don't get to see what's underneath the endothelium. You have to infer it. So now you
can see it. So you can see not just the plaque. So I'm fond, I have a strong family history of
melanoma and I'm told by my dermatology colleagues that nevi melanoma grows down before it grows up.
So what's happening underneath the surface you can't see. And then when it starts to grow,
you start to see on the surface. That's right. Luminal narrowing is a very, very late consequence
of atherosclerosis. So that's why I said if we did a CTA on us or an average 50 year old, you'd see
plaque. It may not narrow the lumen more than a couple percent if at all. It may just look like
a normal variation and sort of lumpy bumpiness. But you'll see plaque and that plaque grows down
before it grows up. There's a ton of information. The question of course is what is the value of
that information and how does it change our management? That's odd. To me it just adds color
to the discussion we already had. It adds great benefit on the negative and on the positive
depending on the age. But you take that patient with a zero calcium score whose CT angiogram
is pristine. Their arteries are enormously patent and there's not a shred of evidence of soft plaque.
It's still not a guarantee. I mean we know that right. Even IVUS could miss plaque or vulnerability.
But it makes you feel a bit more comfortable that your level of aggression can be lower and the
converse then is true as well. So then what's the cost right? So other than the theoretical cost of
the radiation which is probably something. Yeah right now they're going so fast. These things are
at a really good scanner so that the top shelf scanners here are doing CT angiograms at about
two milli sieverts of radiation. So for the listener milli sieverts the unit in which we
measure radiation. The NRC limits people or suggests an upper limit of 50 milli sieverts for a year.
We want our patients to be below 20 milli sieverts for a year. Living at sea level exposes you to
maybe one milli sievert over the course of a year. Living in Denver probably exposes you to four or
five milli sieverts for a year. So that puts the two milli sieverts in context. The first generations
of these Ethan 20 milli sieverts just for a CT angiogram. What's a chest x-ray? Incredibly low.
It's less than one milli sievert. So we can sort of dismiss that. There's very little risk of the
contrast in most people. Obviously if you're older you have kidney disease something else that it
becomes a different issue. One of the greatest costs is the economic cost. It's rarely covered
and it's a, I don't remember exact cost, but it's not trivial. It's probably, you know, $2,000,
$2,500. So it's a quite expensive study relative to the CT, the calcium score, which I got to put
a plug in by the way. Your institution here needs to get its head out of its ass. I mean, jeez us.
I send patients to Stanford. Stanford. Stanford's doing CT angiograms for like a hundred bucks.
And you coconuts here are charging like thousands of dollars. Don't get me started. Well, I think
it'll change now with the new guidelines. I think the price has to come down, but it's such an
interesting. I have to send patients from San Francisco to drive down to Stanford. They're
pissed off, but I'm like, you know, I tell my patients, this is the one example of they're
actually being an efficient market in medicine, right? Because third party payers don't pay for
it up until recently. They haven't paid for it. You have to pay for it out of pocket. So these
guys realize the only way they're going to get it, no one's going to pay $3,000 to get it. It's the
same basic machine, same everything else. It's just that there there's a market. It's a fixed
cost is already sunk and there's no variable cost. It's just, yeah, it's comical. The question
then is sort of what is the risk of the CTA? And so from my perspective, the risk is with the right
patient, the right doctor is zero. The wrong patient, the wrong doctor, it could be high.
And so the example I use is I've got patients and I'm sure you have a lot too who are anxious and
they can't, even though they don't anticipate that they're going to be this way, they can't live with
this sort of thing growing inside of them. I'm sure you had patients when you were doing cancer
surgery who just basically said, get this tumor, the hell out of me. I don't want cancer anymore.
Get it out. And even though prostate cancer is a great example, right? There are lots of ways to
treat prostate cancer today. And some of them involve cutting the tumor out. Others that are
equally as effective probably are close don't, but some people mentally can't get their head around
living with cancer. And I think I have patients of mine who, when they get a CTA and they see
there's plaque there, they just can't sleep because they think this thing is going, I'm going to die
from a heart attack. And no matter what we say, no matter what I say, I can't dissuade them of that.
That to me is the one cause. So that's where I would sort of say, this is why I'm not going to,
that in the economic thing is sort of why I'm not going to widely do this in everybody.
But in certain people it's spectacular. So before we leave this, let's just talk about what heart
flow is, because that's something that's come on the scene and about the past. I want to say it's
about three years ago, maybe four years ago. It's a company here in the Bay area, correct? And
they're layering on an analysis to the CTN diagram. Can you explain a little bit about what that is
and where it came about? I'm going to try and keep it brief. Cause I got quoted in an article
over the summer about heart flow. And I think I said something like, I don't wake up in the middle
of the night dreaming about which patient I want to use heart flow in. So I don't want to be too
harsh on them. This is basically based on the idea that you can use physics to measure the
percent narrowing of an artery by measuring the velocity across the lesion. So as you, anyone who
puts their finger on the end of a garden hose knows that the velocity of the water that comes
out of the garden hose goes up as you narrow the opening of the garden hose. So the same thing is
true in an artery. If you have a narrowing, then the velocity across that is going to be faster.
And there will be a pressure gradient. So you can actually measure pressure using a catheter
with a pressure sensor on it. And you can measure pressure before and after the blockage. And you
can basically then infer how severe the blockage is. And that technique was first developed
invasively in people who were going into the cath lab. And there were patients where you'd
look at the artery and you'd think, yeah, we're looking at this in two dimensions and we can't
really see it doesn't, it's hard to see exactly how severe this is. So there were a couple of
these tools that were developed. One of them is this intravascular ultrasound, Ivas. And then
the other one was this FFR, which is a way of measuring pressure and basically inferring the
degree of blockage that way. So fractional flow reserve is the calculation of P2, which is the
pressure beyond the occlusion over P1. Right. And they do it before and after
administering a vasodilator. So they'll give a patient a vasodilator and they can measure
sort of maximal blood flow. And you can do that in a normal artery, in a normal artery, you'll see
it augment in a diseased artery, it doesn't, it'll go down. And there are two big trials that looked
at the use of invasive fractional flow reserve. One was called FAME, the other was called FAME2.
I'll spare everybody me looking up exactly what FAME stood for again. What did those studies show?
The take home, and again, there's controversy as with almost anything in cardiology, there's
controversy. But the take home was that if you had an FFR that was less than 0.8, so you use a
mathematical format to basically calculate. And if it was less than 0.8, if you then put a stint in
that artery, people did better. So it suggested that this could be a useful tool to help stratify
who should be getting stents and who shouldn't be getting stents. And I think a lot of our
interventional cardiology colleagues have been using it that way for the past few years.
Again, there are questions, I don't want to get into the controversy, but there are questions
about the technique and about how they did it. And there are some questions about the validity of it,
but it's mostly a useful tool and people do use it, but it's invasive. So you have to be having
an angiogram to do it. So somebody came up with this idea that you could do the same thing
using just a non-invasive CT scan. And you could basically measure the velocity and infer the
pressure using Ohm's law. So they did the same thing. They gave it to basically dilate or not.
And they can do this. And the oil's law. Sorry.
Boils. Yeah. Yeah. I don't know. You're the engineer. It's been a major.
So they did this and lo and behold, they were able to measure this thing non-invasively. You
don't have to have a catheterization. You can do it all through CT. And then heart flow basically
is selling the software as an add-on package to the CTA and they'll give you what's called a
CTFFR, which is their like calculated FFR. Is this changing your practice? Because I've,
you know, when it came out, I started doing it and then I realized, especially just based on
orbita, that wasn't really going to change my management. So I have not done a heart flow study
and probably over a year on anybody. That's the point. Whereas the anatomy of sort of whether
there's plaque there does help guide you about how aggressive to be with your medical therapy.
It's not clear to me that we're learning anything from adding the heart flow on. So I have never
ordered one. It doesn't mean that I won't order one in the future. I've done a lot of this where
I've said I've never ordered one. And then 10 years later I've ordered one. I've ordered a lot.
So I reserved the right to be wrong on this one. But my instinct is like you say,
we have the information from these two other big trials that tell us that this is probably not
going to be a huge game changer because what information is it adding and how are we going
to react to it? So their pitch from a business standpoint is that it saves unnecessary
catheterizations. That's a business discussion that I think I generally don't believe right now,
but that's their case. And if you're an individual patient, what value is it going to bring to you?
Or you as a doctor, what value does it bring to you? I can't think of a big value today,
unless you had somebody who you were going to send to the Catholic and you thought this would
help sort of make you feel comfortable about not doing it. Let's pivot for a second. Because
we're sitting here in your office. We've been nerding out for two hours on preventative
cardiology, but I'm looking at your very, very beautiful whiteboard. And not only do I have
tremendous whiteboard envy, but there's not a single thing on here that looks like it's about
cardiology. If I didn't know better, I would think I was in the lab of David Sabatini or one of my
other friends, you know, Luke Hantley. I mean, we've got insulin receptors, PI 3K. We've got
mTOR. You've even delineated between mTOR complex one, two pathways to autophagy, lots of growth
hormone, IGF pathways, pancreas, liver. Are we in your office? Whose office is this?
I came here to San Francisco 21 years ago to study in the lab. The person who became my mentor was
my boss until he left to go work in Novartis a couple of years ago, a year ago, two years ago,
Sean Coughlin. And I came here because I was interested in the biology of blood clotting.
And so when I left his lab and decided that I want to stay here in San Francisco, I had to find
something that I wanted to do that would be not what he was doing because that would be dumb.
And so at that time I got very interested in the biology of sex differences. And I don't want to
spend seven hours describing it, but it's a really interesting literature. And so I did a deep dive
on it and thought, gosh, there's a lot of reasons to think that there may be significant differences
in the way men and women behave clinically and biologically with regard to the clotting system.
And there may be reasons to expect why that would be right. We talked a little bit before about the
placenta and pregnancy. Men don't have to have this other thing living inside of them and therefore
could afford maybe to optimize more towards a sort of wound healing defense strategy, right?
Men, there's a difference in sort of the way you might, if you were to design a system, if you were
to create evolution there, you may be able to optimize it. This system for the two sexes
differently. That is the most interesting idea I've ever heard because one of the questions
I've always batted about in my mind is all things equal, why are women less susceptible to
cardiovascular disease? Or at least I wouldn't say it that way. Why do women experience a phase shift?
They get it later. And you look at blood pressure differences. Maybe women have lower blood pressure.
Another one is iron. Women have less iron for 30, 40 years of their life. They're basically
doing a blood donation every month. I never once considered what you just said, which as you say,
it actually makes a lot of sense. Men would in theory evolve to heal from a wound much quicker,
even at greater cost down the line because of their role in a hunter-gatherer society.
Whereas the woman must evolve to protect the offspring much more. And you could see how that
would be a lower immune response, a lower inflammatory response, a lower pro-thrombotic
response. That's it. I can't believe I didn't even know that. Well, if you want to get really crazy,
you can start to imagine, well, maybe women evolved to be the less sort of masculine of the
sexes. In other words, maybe they're the ones not going out and throwing spears and fighting
because they have to carry pregnancy. And so they're a little bit more susceptible to bleeding.
There's the added sort of complication of menstruation, all these other things. So
anyway, I thought, wow, this is a really interesting area. And the reason it was
particularly interesting was that in the work that we had done primarily in mouse genetic models,
it looked like there was a pretty significant difference in the rate of clotting between male
and female mice. So I thought, well, this would be a really fun thing to study. And of course,
I did exactly what you did, which was I immediately kind of latched onto what must be sex hormones
and did some early kind of pilot studies looking at the role of estrogen, estrogen receptor
different. And it didn't pan out. And so I did more reading about sex dimorphism in general.
And it turns out that mammals have this remarkable sexually dimorphic liver. So if you take the liver
out of a, of a mammal, human or mouse, there's a set of genes that are expressed dramatically
different, even up to a hundred fold different males and females. And a lot of these genes are
genes that regulate sex hormone, sex hormone binding or modification. Others are sexually
dimorphic for reasons we don't understand. But if you do a sort of array of gene expression,
whether you're using an old fashioned chipper or whether you're doing RNA-seq, you see this
tremendous signature difference between the genes that are turned on in the liver of females and
males. Well, where clotting factors made the liver. So I thought, well, this is what we're
going to do. And so I set off to like basically try and understand of how this happens. So what
regulates the dimorphism of liver gene expression in mammals, it turns out it's not sex hormones.
That's actually secondary. It turns out that it's a dimorphic pattern of growth hormone secretion. So
it was described back in the fifties and sixties that there was a factor from the pituitary called
feminizing factor, but it wasn't known what it was. If you just ground up the extract of the pituitary
and injected it into a male or female mouse, you could basically drive the expression of these
genes. And ultimately it was found in a beautiful paper. I think it was published in 1982 in cell
by Richard Palmer's group. It was found that that factor is growth hormone. And that if you-
Which by the way is the last one I would have predicted. Like I would have said, oh, it's
probably luteinizing hormone or follicle stimulating hormone. I wouldn't have guessed growth hormone.
No, it's growth hormone. So, you know, males have a more pulsatile pattern of growth hormone
secretion. So they have longer intervals between the pulses. Females are more continuous. And so
they have, they have very short- So the guys have these spikes that are less frequent and the women
are putting now area under the curve about the same. Mean is the same. So what's cool is you
can actually take an intact normal wild type male rodent and put a pump in and deliver continuous
growth hormone. And you can completely reverse the signature of their gene expression in the liver.
And you can do the opposite with a female mouse. Take a female mouse and it, because if you give
exogenous growth hormone, you basically suppress endogenous growth hormone secretion from the
pituitary. You can give a couple of injections. I think it's just one or two a day to a female
mouse and you masculinize the liver. We live in a world where a lot of people have decided it's a
good idea to prescribe growth hormone to reduce the effects of aging. I talked about this very
briefly with Nier Barzilai on our podcast. And I would say that Nier's view from that was that
there might be some benefit in men in certain circumstances and women less so. But is it safe
to say that if a man and a woman are both receiving the same dose and same dosing pattern
of exogenous growth hormone, you would evaporate that difference of gene expression in the liver?
Because you would have suppressed the pituitary secretion? Yes, you should. Have you done that
experiment? In people? No, in mice? Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. We did that experience. So I got into
this because I was interested in clotting and that makes sense as a cardiologist. I just,
we just spent two hours talking about why clotting is interesting to a cardiologist. So
starting off my lab as a junior assistant professor, I thought, well, this is what I'm
going to do. I'll understand the biological basis of sex differences of clotting, get into this
growth hormone pattern. And so we started to do that. And we, as a lot of people of my generation
do, science is a little bit of a game of you do whatever else does and see what comes out. And so
we started knocking out different components of the growth hormone signaling pathway in mouse.
And we got to this protein called Jack two, which is a kinase, which basically adds a phosphate
group to proteins. And it's important for other areas of medicine and science, but it's
obligate signal transducer of growth hormones. So downstream of the receptor growth hormone binds,
Jack two basically allows this signal to be transduced. Is there a different receptor
for growth hormone in the liver versus outside of the liver? No, GHR is the same everywhere.
There are different isoforms. I think there's a soluble one, which is basically a GH binding
protein, but the GHR is the same and that signal is transduced because growth hormone receptor
itself is a type one psychoreceptor. It doesn't have any intrinsic tyrosine kinase activity.
It has to partner with this other non-receptor tyrosine kinase Jack two to transduce the signal.
So we eventually knocked out Jack two in the liver and hepatocytes. And I'll never forget that I had
a technician working in the lab at the time. He actually, he was the only person working in the
lab at the time. It was just the two of us. And he came to me, he said, Ethan, there's something
wrong with these livers. I don't even need to genotype them. And I'll show you a picture,
but it turns out that the livers in the animals where we had selectively deleted Jack two in
hepatocytes were basically turned into adipose tissue. It was the most-
So you were creating NAFLD? Yes.
So just to make sure I understand what you're saying. If you knock out Jack two in a liver,
you prevent growth hormone from exerting its transduction in the liver because you need Jack
two as that second tyrosine kinase. So it's basically like taking away growth hormone from
the liver. That's right. And if you do that, you accumulate fat in the liver.
25 fold increase in-
25 fold. So it becomes clinically grotesque. I mean, you just basically create foie gras.
In fact, there was a moment in time where I thought, well, this would be a fun side business.
I'll just make foie gras because we can engineer it.
Quick question. Did the triglycerides go up or stay the same?
Zero.
Yes.
No, they were the same.
So in other words, you shut off export, it seems like significantly, right? There was no flux.
There's no outward. You were basically not getting any VLDL or triglyceride out of those livers.
Well, so we didn't know what we did at the beginning. We had no idea. In fact, I took
the liver to a pathologist because I said, I don't know what this is because I didn't know what it
was. And he said, Ethan, I'll look at another microscope for you, but I know what this is.
And I said, what's that? He said, it's NAFLD. I said, what's NAFLD? And he said,
it's non-alcoholic fatty liver. And I said, okay. And so then of course, I started with the very
basic, like, all right, well, what are the causes of NAFLD? It's an increase in synthesis,
so increase in DNL, the decrease in export, increase in uptake, or it's decrease in oxidation.
So we started to go through this whole list. And to make a very long story short, what we settled on
and published, we published a model that I think mostly we've validated to be true,
although there's a little bit of controversy about it. And it comes back to what you said.
So growth-errant signals and one of the products of growth-errant signaling in the hepatocyte and
other cells is this protein called IGF-1, insulin-like growth factor one. And 95% of circulating,
if not more of circulating IGF-1 in the plasma. So if you take blood of you or mate comes from
the liver, so it's liver derived. So if you knock out growth hormone signaling in hepatocytes,
you completely shut off and shut down circulating IGF-1. There's still local IGF-1 in cells and
tissues, but circulating IGF-1 goes to zero. And circulating IGF-1 is the plasma biosensor for
growth hormones. Growth hormones half-life is extremely short. So we evolved a system to
measure growth hormone levels, not by measuring growth hormone itself, but by measuring IGF-1.
So when IGF-1 levels fall, the hypothalamus pituitary sense that, and then they turn on
a growth hormone. That is so brilliant. Just as an engineer, I have to sort of reflect on that
for a moment. Every time I hear something like what you just said, I'm so glad that I was not
in charge of evolution. Because I would have screwed that one up. I would have said, make
the growth hormone sensor sense growth hormone. And of course you would get into a cyclic amplified
response because of how short it sticks around. But instead, luckily evolution was in charge and
not me, it said, no, no, no, no, dude, that's going to be way too fluctuating. Let's look at something
that's much more stable. That's a readout of growth hormone. Oh, hey, how about IGF? And have
that be the feedback loop. Goodness gracious. I love when nature is so smart. The fascinating thing
is that circulating IGF-1, I won't say it's all it does because it does a few other things,
but the vast majority of its role is as a plasma biosensor for growth hormone. So it regulates
growth hormone secretion. So what happens if you knock down IGF-1, you get this huge increase in
growth hormone secretion. You basically get acromegaly, but you get selective growth hormone
resistance in the hepatocyte. So you probably remember the growth hormone has been described
for a long time forever and ever to be pro-lipolytic. So it's actually one of two hormones. It's both
catabolic and anabolic, but it turns on, it's a way to mobilize fat from adipose tissue stores.
Testosterone being the other where you can be anabolic to muscle, catabolic to fat.
And thyroid hormone, I think is another one where you can be both.
Unlike insulin, for example, which would be anabolic to both or cortisol, which would be,
actually cortisol is the reverse. It's catabolic to muscle, anabolic to fat.
That's right. So in any case, if you give an animal growth hormone, if you have a patient
who has a tumor that secretes growth hormone, what disease called acromegaly or gigantism,
Andre the giant had gigantism. Those people have a decrease in lean body mass,
increase in muscle mass. That's basically because growth hormone mobilizes fat from
adipose tissue stores. So we reasoned that what was happening was that growth hormone was turning
on lipolysis and mobilizing all this fat and that that fat was getting taken up by the liver.
What was interesting was we did a relatively deep analysis of all the mouse models that have been
made involving the receptor, GHR downstream signaling components, including JAK2 and another
one called STAT5. And we looked at animals that have been engineered to be missing any of those
components in the whole animal versus just in the liver. And what was interesting was that the
animals where you knock out the pathway in the whole animal had a one to two fold increase in
lipid in their liver, very modest, if hardly noticeable. Whereas if you knock out the receptor
or this other molecule STAT5 or JAK2 selectively just in hepatocytes, you get this 20 to 25 fold
increase. And so that told us it's not just about having high growth hormone levels. It's about high
growth hormone levels and those growth hormone levels acting on the periphery. There must be
some other factor that is important here. And so we reasoned, we did what people do is we did a
gene expression array. We saw there's a molecule called CD36, which is also known as fatty acid
translocase. And we saw that it was increased by 20 fold in these animals where we knocked out JAK2
in the liver. And we thought, well, gosh, this could be facilitating uptake. And so we did a
series of following experiments after that where we knocked out CD36 just in hepatocytes and showed
that we could make that get better. So we put together this model where growth hormone basically
growth hormone secretion is disinhibited at the level of the hypothalamus pituitary. You get an
increase in activity in peripheral tissues. It's then mobilizing all this fat and then the fat is
being taken up sort of preferentially or augmented rate of uptake by the upregulation of this
molecule. Now, if you block JAK2 and block the expression of CD36, do you eliminate the fat
accumulation in the liver? Yeah, that's experiment we did. It wasn't a hundred percent, but we
basically brought it back down to almost, instead of it being a hundred grams per milligram of
tissue or something, it was like 20 where normal mouse would be 11 or 12. So it's near normalized.
We also then did an experiment where we said, well, what happens if we block this pathway,
the growth hormone signaling pathway in adipocytes, since we're presuming that this must be
a product of lipolysis? So what happens if we block this pathway in adipocytes?
So we went and made an animal where we knocked out JAK2 in adipocytes selectively. And then we
crossed the two together and asked what would happen basically, can you reduce the amount of
lipid in the liver by knocking out both at the same time? And we did. And that experiment we did
almost 10 years ago. And what was so fascinating about that experiment was we never intended to
get into any of the insulin glucose homostasis stuff at all. But when you're doing these
experiments, they're expensive. And so we did a bunch of things measured. I think we did an
insulin tolerance test for some reason on these mice. And we saw that the mice where we knocked
out JAK2 just in the adipocytes had the most profound insulin sensitivity. We actually killed
our mice because they died from hypoglycemia. We gave them the same amount of insulin that you gave
a normal mouse and they bottomed out and we couldn't rescue them. And they were super
insulin sensitive. And this was mostly glucose being disposed into the muscle?
No, it turns out. So we thought that was interesting. So we then went on to kind of
dig deeper on what was going on. Again, here we knocked out this pathway just in adipocytes.
And we saw that if you knock out the pathway in adipocytes. But I'm confused. So you knock out
the pathway in adipocytes, when they're hypoglycemic, you're putting that glucose
very easily into muscle or into liver. I mean, you'd have to put it into one of those two,
wouldn't you? Even if you wanted to then put it into fat into the fat cell.
Yeah. So, and what you're asking is a phenomenal question. And we had initially,
I think naively thought that this was an adipocyte autonomous effect that we thought must be the
adipocyte. But then there's not that much glucose that's actually disposed into the adipocyte on a
per mass basis. So we thought that doesn't make sense. So we ended up doing what you do,
which is to clamp the animals. And it turns out that the defect is almost entirely in turning off
EGP. So basically what we do is we completely turn off endogenous glucose production from the liver.
Which is really not an insulin sensitivity issue at all. It just masquerades as profound
insulin sensitivity, but you basically clamped the portal vein metaphorically and you kill an
organism in five minutes if you stop hepatic glucose output. How quickly did you see these
animals die? It was within 30 minutes. Oh my God. Yeah. It was really profound. And so this then
sent us off in this long, what's now been a 10 year journey to try and understand how growth
one regulates insulin sensitivity or insulin glucose homeostasis and how that happens through
the adipocyte. We won't get into all of it now, but it turned me onto the
kind of remarkable figure, one of these figures in history that I didn't know before I got into this,
that I'm surprised he, this guy, Bernardo Hussai, who was an Argentinian physician scientist who
won the Nobel prize. First Latin American to win the Nobel prize, right? I mean,
this guy was unbelievable. I'll send you a link. There was a period of time in the 1930s,
I think it was 1936, where he was the first or only author on 14 articles in the New England
Journal of Medicine over five weeks. At one point he had, it was the most unbelievably
productive period of time ever seen. And he ended up with the Nobel prize. He shared the
Nobel prize with the Corey's of the Corey cycle, which I didn't know until recently. I was reviewing
some of this stuff for our talk today. And I didn't realize that they had collaborated on
some stuff back in the 1930s, but he defined the diabetic nature of growth hormone. So he did these
experiments that I think were really cool and basically got left behind because no one really
paid attention to any of this stuff for a long time. But he defined that if you take an animal,
the first set of experiments he did was we took an animal and took the pituitary out and then gave
the animal insulin and saw that the animal he described it as they were more susceptible to
being to the toxic effects of insulin. So they bottom their blood sugar out. He then did the
opposite experiment where he took an animal, he loped out the pancreas and then saw that if he
got rid of the pituitary gland, that they were less susceptible to the hyperglycemia, that they
basically had improved diabetes. And those experiments continued on for 60 years.
So let me just make sure I understood. Take away growth hormone and you're going to become much
more theoretically or appear insulin sensitive, but in reality, much more hypoglycemic. Take away
growth hormone in the absence of the pancreas and you actually tolerate hyperglycemia better.
That's right. And in fact, there were people in the 60s, I believe, who were doing
hypophysectomies in people with very brittle type two diabetes.
So severing the link between the hypothalamus and the pituitary?
They were taking the pituitary out.
They were taking the pituitary right out. Wow.
And it was a very effective treatment, actually, except that it had significant
morbidity and mortality of the surgery. So at that time they had perfected the art of taking
the pituitary out.
But even when they did, you're saying even now that they'd have to replace all of the thyroid
and sex hormone and ACTH, the cortisol related stuff, it still turned out to be better off.
All things considered in how well it managed their diabetes.
The ultimate killer experiment happened in 1983 ish or so. And so they took patients with type
one diabetes who had an insulin pump. So they were getting a fixed dose of insulin and then
they gave them, I believe, one or two injections of growth hormone. And you could see the insulin
level go like this straight up. Basically, their insulin use within a day spikes and stays up
until they stop the GH injections and it comes back down. And in fact, three out of the seven
people in this one study got profoundly hypoglycemic when they stopped the growth hormone.
So it turns out that there's a drug that blocks the growth hormone receptor that's used as a
second line treatment for acromegaly. It's called somoverter, pygvissimont. It's an analog of
native wild type GH. It just has a few mutations in it that renders it basically as a dominant
negative. So it doesn't allow, basically shuts off the receptor. And it's used, again, clinically.
And if you look at the package insert, the black box warning is if you take any diabetes
drugs, let your doctor know because your risk of hypoglycemia is so high. So it actually reminds
me a lot of the sort of low carb ketogenic diet in the sense that it has that same effect. And in
that 1983 New England Journal paper, they actually talked about growth hormone secretion being as much
the cause of brittle type two diabetes as the effect. And for reasons that I don't understand,
people just forgot about it. And so we set out to kind of try and understand at least at the
beginning at a cellular level, how is this regulated? And we're trying to dig down. It turns
out that it all comes back to your favorite molecule, mTOR. And it looks like it converges
in this intersection between these two signaling pathways that evolved actually only, I mean,
growth hormone doesn't exist pre-TELIOS. So there's no growth hormone in flies or worms. It's only in
invertebrates and TELIOS. And it co-evolved basically from insulin, which is not that
surprising, right? IGF-1 is basically the target molecule of GH. It's not surprising that GH and
insulin would have evolved in a similar way, even though they look very different, they act very
different. So the way I think about it is that growth hormones kind of retained a lot of the
sort of metabolic effects of insulin. And insulin obviously has retained a lot of the growth
promoting effects that used to be with growth hormone when they were all one molecule. And so
the point is that I think that these two molecules act in concert and from our experiments, it looks
like that's happening in the adipocyte and that basically growth hormone is acting as a break
on insulin signaling and that that's controlling metabolism in the whole body at a distance. And
so that's what we've been working on. And again, we could probably talk about that for three hours,
but it's been keeping us busy. So let me kind of think through this a little bit,
because it's so interesting. Let's go back for a second to, you didn't mention IGF binding proteins,
but where do they fit into this? The IGF-BPs as they're called are also made by the liver, correct?
So IGF is mostly made by the liver, IGF-BP2, BP3 also made by the liver. These are interesting to
most people listening to this because if they pay attention to any of the sort of epidemiology
around longevity, there's so much controversy around this idea of IGF and its association with
mortality. And you have such conflicting information, that's what makes this so challenging, right? So
you have these people that have mutations in either the GHR or low GH secretion and or low IGF
due to a deficient GHR on the liver and they seem to live longer or at least get less cancer,
but then they also seem to get a bunch of other diseases that are kind of weird. But when you look
at all cause mortality, it seems to nadir at the 60th or 70th percentile for everything. But when
you do it by disease, certain diseases seem to get better with higher IGF like Alzheimer's disease.
And I believe cardiovascular disease, you would know this, but others get worse, like cancer starts
to go up. So how does all of that make sense in terms of what you're learning at this level?
Well, I'll say that the GHR meetings are fascinating because they're basically the room
aligns in these two camps. There's one side of the room that believes that GHR is the elixir that
will promote longevity. And there's the other side of the room that believes that too much GHR
signaling will negatively impact longevity. It's really interesting the way these two things. I
think for me, if you start with what we know from human genetics and animal genetics, it's incontrovertible
that excess GHR signaling, at least at the levels that you see with transgenic animals or
acromegaly is one of the most potent ways to die. I mean, people with acromegaly, untreated
acromegaly die in their thirties and twenties and they die of cardiovascular disease. So I think
that's gain of function. And again, the animal is the same thing. It's a great way to shorten
lifespan in any animal, whether it's a worm or a fly or increased signaling through this pathway
and you'll shorten lifespan. And then the flip sides, he mentioned the LaRone patients, those
patients don't have increased longevity per se, but they sure do have a decrease in their risk of
metabolic disease. It's a much decreased risk of developing type 2 diabetes,
despite an increase in body fat. So they have this body composition where they have a 50% body fat,
which you'd think would be dangerous. It turns out that they and the mice, so there's a mouse model
of LaRone syndrome and that's actually the longest lived mouse that's ever been engineered. There was
a prize that I don't know if it still exists, but it's called the Methuselah prize. And they used to
give out, it was $5 million to an investigator. You could engineer the longest living mouse that's
ever been made. And so this guy, Andre Barkie at Southern Illinois engineered the mouse that's
missing. Actually, he and John Copchick did it together, this experiment where they engineered
the mouse that's missing GHR and that mouse lived to be 1819 days, which is basically the equivalent
of like 207 human years. It's still to this day, the longest living mouse that's ever been made.
And that meant it was without GHR in the liver.
No, anywhere.
Anywhere.
And that means for its entire life.
The whole life. So these are short and fat mice and they live forever. But they have all the other
problems that you'd have if you're missing growth or congenitally. So they're short and they're
pretty fat. What's interesting is that that fat-
Are they cognitively the same?
The mice or the people?
The mice. Well, I guess both, but I was asking specifically about the mice.
I think they are. It's a great question. I don't know how much has been done on their
cognitive abilities late in life, but they clearly are very resistant to these diseases that kill
mice in labs. They're healthy by every stretch. They're extraordinarily insulin sensitive. I mean,
again, same thing that was described before we ever did these experiments. What we demonstrated
was that the insulin sensitivity is conferred by the absence of the signaling pathway in the
adipose tissue, which is acting at a distance, mostly on the liver.
So what do you think confers the protection to the La Ronze patients?
I don't know. That's one of the things I think about every day, but at a very simple level,
I think of it as an improvement in insulin sensitivity, a decrease in insulin and decrease
in IGF-1. I can't get better than that right now, but I think the circulating insulin levels
are nearly undetectable and mice in labs die of cancer. I think there's probably just less
insulin, less IGF-1, and they just don't get cancer.
Because this relationship between hyperinsulinemia and high glucose, you and I both are on an advisory
board of a company called Virta Health, and that's how we actually met a few years ago.
I remember in one of the meetings, we were discussing this idea that people need to
understand the difference between managing glucose and managing insulin. If you manage
glucose levels, if you keep glucose levels in the ideal range, by any means you control
microvascular disease. You're less likely to go blind and less likely to have kidney failure and
have an amputation. But if you do that with a strategy of high insulin, you trade it for
macrovascular disease, atherosclerosis, coronary artery disease throughout the body, obviously,
the coronary arteries and cerebral arteries, even the aorta, the large vessels, suggesting that even
high insulin by itself can be problematic. These patients are walking around with very low insulin,
which you could see would protect them at the macrovascular level. Because of this,
I still think of it as a paradox because I'm still struggling to wrap my head around their insulin
sensitivity, how they can be so insulin sensitive, but they also obviously have normal glucose levels,
so their microvascular stuff is okay. Then on top of that, you're saying if insulin and IGF are pro,
from a metabolic standpoint, pro-oncologic or pro tumor, you also get that benefit.
The one I've never understood is aren't these things important neurotrophically? I mean,
isn't IGF and GH important in the brain and how are they avoiding those consequences?
One of the foibles of doing what we do is that we look at what we look at and don't look at
anything else. So again, I set out to do these experiments originally because I was interested
in the clotting. It was only an accident that we noticed that the liver looked like fogra.
We've never looked at the brain and I don't know how much others have looked at the brain.
I'm not sure what happens in a mouse brain would guide us, but it's a great question. I think if
you're just asking about the things that I can measure, so metabolic disease, cardiovascular
disease, cancer, and lifespan, it seems like everything aligns towards too much GH being
bad and less GH being better, but I can't tell you about the neuro stuff. It could be the opposite
there. Why is it that if the patients with Laurent syndrome are less likely to die or they get to
phase shift and delay the onset of cardiovascular disease, neurodegenerative disease, and cancer,
they don't have a survival advantage? Well, the story that I, I mean, again,
you're talking about pockets of a few hundred people. I think the one that's gotten the most
attention is this one in Ecuador and there are 300 patients there. I think what's amazing is that
the 30 year follow up of that cohort of people, there was not one single case of cancer or diabetes
over 30 years and 300 people compared to like 15% in their age matched relatives. What I heard was
that they were depressed and had an increased risk of alcoholism because they were basically
ostracized for being fat dwarfs. I hate to be harsh, but I think that was the other thing.
Yeah. And I also heard there was a higher incidence of accidental death and other things,
which you could argue, well, you have to die of something. So if accidental death explains it,
that should still show a survival advantage. I think we're getting into the sort of trouble
of trying to- Yeah. Epidemiology just makes this very difficult. Especially in these small,
inbred communities, I think it just becomes almost impossible. So we talked about experiments,
we're never going to have answers to. We're never going to have a human longevity lifespan
study that you or I will see the results of. And we just have to understand that. So,
but in the meantime, we can talk about the other stuff. And I mean, the insulin thing to me is
interesting because I think there are some people out there in the Twitter sphere who are sort of
fall into the category of statin denialists. I think there's this narrative that's developed
out there that statins don't treat the underlying cause of cardiovascular disease, that the underlying
cause of cardiovascular disease is insulin. And while I'm firmly in the camp and will ever
expect to remain in the camp, that lipids are fundamental and probably the most important
driver of cardiovascular disease, of atherosclerotic disease and events, I do think there's good
evidence that insulin actually does play a role. And in fact, there were some studies that were
published over the years that showed that fasting insulin was an independent risk factor for
cardiovascular disease. And it makes sense. Don't we also see this borne out in the type
one literature that stratifies patients by insulin use? Yeah. I think James O'Keefe published a
paper on this about two years ago. Do you know James? No. Provincial cardiologist in Kansas,
mostly his work is an exercise and the role of too much exercise actually, but actually published
a paper in this a while ago. So yeah, super interesting. This is clearly top 10 questions
I get asked all the time is, should I be on growth hormone? My general answer is no,
mostly through the lens of, I'm not convinced by any data that growth hormone will promote
longevity, but on the flip side, I've also softened my tone. I used to just think on first
principles, it made no sense because of, if nothing else, the cancer risk. But of course,
the other thing that's odd is there's so many people taking growth hormone, especially athletes.
And if there is a negative consequence of it, it's probably not as big as I would have guessed
and, or it takes a lot longer to show up than I would have guessed because we just don't see the
trail of body bags that you would expect. I mean, that's the thing is you have Barry Bonds at 25 or
28 taking a bunch of growth hormone. What do you expect? So maybe his risk of having an MI
is increased twofold or threefold. Would that be enough to see, don't you think? Wouldn't a
twofold increase show up in a non-randomized cohort of athletes taking in a legal drug? I don't think
we have the data. I don't feel confident. What I've learned in this work is that these hormones are
regulated in ways that we can't even begin to understand. I mean, that it's so complicated. And
so I'm nervous to go in there and start perturbing it or replacing it if it's deficient. Because I
see all the different things that can happen and how complicated that can be. So I'm a little bit
more of a minimalist, I guess, when it comes to these kinds of interventions. But my answer to
my patients is every line of evidence I can see about GH at least is that if you're worried,
if you're optimizing for longevity, it's hard to tell a story that that's going to help you. Now,
if you're optimizing for, I want to feel better. I want to increase my lean muscle mass. I want to
decrease my fat mass. I want to look better. Go for it. If that's what you want. And so that's what
I tell people is if this is something that you're willing to understand that we have no evidence
that it's probably going to increase your lifespan, it may more likely even decrease it, but you like
how it makes you feel and look then, then sure. So I would agree with all of that. I think the
one area where I would love to see more investigation, and this is certainly amenable to a clinical trial,
is does increasing IGF in patients with either very high risk for or early cognitive impairment
improve outcomes? I think the literature makes a plausible case that that could be the case.
And that strikes me as a subset in patients, at least for me clinically, that I am most interested
in knowing the answer to that question. If we take our high risk dementia patients or worse yet,
patients who are already in the earliest stages of cognitive impairment and take the ones who are at
lower levels, the bottom quartile of IGF levels, will GH provide benefit? Yeah, it's a great trial.
What happens to your IGF-1 when you fast? Oh, it plummets. And the numbers are kind of irrelevant
because it's all a function of your scale. So when I was on a ketogenic diet for three years
with no fluctuation, my IGF level resided at the 40th or 50th percentile for my age. So the lab that
I use gives me not only my IGF level, but in five-year increments, it gives me the distribution of it.
So you can very accurately peg where you are. So for me, constantly being on a ketogenic diet,
put me at about the 40th to 50th percentile for IGF level, which is not really surprising when
you consider that a ketogenic diet minimizes insulin and also for most people actually keeps
protein lower than you would otherwise normally have it. So methionine plays such an important
role in this, of course. When I'm not on a ketogenic diet, which I'm not these days, except for in the
peri fasting period, my IGF probably lives closer to the 70th percentile. On our scale, that's about
200. When I do a fast, so I'll do a blood draw right before the fast, and then usually on day six
or day seven of a complete water only fast, that IGF will be in the 80s, 90s, which is more than two
standard deviations below the mean. What I find most interesting is how long it takes to rebound,
and it takes about six weeks to come back to normal. So, and have you ever, measuring
growth hormone is one of the hardest things to do because it's so- I've never measured it for that
reason. I just, I, yeah. I mean, it might be so high that you would be able to, to see something.
Let's talk about it because I'd love to figure out, the problem is I only fast in New York and
ever in San Francisco, but maybe I'll do a fast up here and swing by the lab and we'll do daily
blood draws or something. I guess we have to get an IRB these days. We can't do anything for fun,
but it's very interesting to see how much you can manipulate GH nutritionally.
Well, that's what, one of the things that we're really interested in understanding,
like in the future is understanding its role in this fasting feeding transition. It goes up in
fasting, but as you say, IGF-1 levels go down. So you get this selective GH resistance in the liver,
at least the question of is whether you're getting GH resistance in other tissues as well,
but why would you have this hormone go up and then lose its activity? It's kind of a funny thing,
right? And you see this in people with anorexia too. Yeah, I've never actually understood it as
well as I feel like I do now based on the way you've told this story of, that's a great way to
describe it, right? Selective GH resistance in the liver, IGF is plummeting, GH is skyrocketing.
Then the question, and we should know this and eventually we will, what is GH activity in adipocytes?
Is it actually maintained? And so are you basically trying to mobilize fat as a way of
avoiding starvation? Is it basically you're trying to direct GH to act only on the periphery and not
on the liver? By the way, if you believe that periodic fasting improves longevity, and I
certainly do, Valter Longo does, we might come at it from different ways. It also begs the question,
is the benefit conferred by the reduction in IGF or the transient rise in GH?
Yeah, or something completely different.
I never even really considered that the benefit could be conferred from the GH rise, although
that seems less likely given that it's hard to imagine you, I mean, who knows though? Maybe
there's something, I mean, if biology teaches us anything, it's to stop acting like we know what
we're talking about. Exactly, exactly. Ethan, I want to go back to something because I know
we've got to wrap up, you've got to get back to stuff. You talked about something at the
beginning that I didn't know, which was you went off to Vassar to get as far away from science as
you could, and yet you had an experience there that presented science in the right way. And I
would argue the world is actually a better place for you doing what you're doing now, which is not
to say that you being the drummer of a band wouldn't have been equally impactful, but maybe I'm biased.
This is an interesting topic to me because my biggest fear, certainly one of my biggest fears
in education is a retreat from science. What could a parent think about out there as they think about
their son or daughter? And I'm actually even more afraid of it in the case of girls where there's
this ridiculous, stupid, and I really think it is stupid and incorrect, that girls are just not
going to be as good at science or math. I think that most of that is actually a feed forward
mechanism that's built into an expectation. I mean, how do you think about this with your kids,
or how could I think about it with my kids or anybody else thinking about this? What can we do
to make science as exciting as it can possibly be? And if for no other reason, I even say this to
people, it's not because everyone has to become a scientist. It's an inability to understand science
makes you a victim for the rest of your life, whether you want to admit it or not. If you can't
at least have some understanding of science and think critically, you are going to be overrun
with propaganda and nonsense. And the consequence of that is enormous and we see it. I don't think
this fact is necessarily correct today, but it was at the time that I knew it and it won't be
directionally off. At the time of the statistic, there was what, 565 members in the House of
Representatives in the Senate. Five of them had degrees in science. So less than 1% of the
lawmakers of this country are trained scientifically. That just doesn't strike me as an appropriate
balance. So what happened at Vassar and how can we reproduce it? So those are two things that I
think about a lot. One is obviously we as a group of scientists need to do a better job of communicating
what we do in an interesting and exciting way to people without dumbing it down. And I think,
honestly, I'm not just saying this to shove sunshine up your ass, but I've had so many calls
from people, either people I do know or people I don't know who've said, I just heard this great
podcast. And I think what you're doing here is bold because you're not shying away from getting
into the depth. It may be that a lot of the conversation that we had around the science
was over the head of the average layperson who hasn't had science, but I still think it's valuable
and they're going to go off and get literate about something and they're finding it interesting. So I
think we as a community need to do that. And whether it's you or it's Ron Vale and iBiology
or other things, which if you haven't seen it, I highly recommend he's making these videos. In fact,
they did one with Dave Sabatini, a series on mTOR. Yeah, I saw that one. Yeah. And if we're going
to get more people interested in science, we got to make it more interesting. The second thing is
there's this trend and you know this because you've got kids of hyper specialization earlier and
earlier in life. I could afford to go to medical school and making the decision as a sophomore in
college. That's almost impossible to believe that that could happen today. I mean, it could happen.
You'd have to take time off. But what I find with our trainees is that people who don't
do things happen. One is people who get into science at a young age get burned out and don't
like it by the time they get to be a fellow or a resident or attending. And the second thing is the
people who don't get into science like me, the Ethan Weisses who go to Vassar in 2019 and not
1991 find it way too much of an obstacle to get in now. It's just too complicated and too many
barriers. So one of the things that I'm passionate about and I'm actually working on it, I can't
really talk about it now, but we're going to talk about it soon. We're working on some ways to help
MD only medical students and beyond get exposed to like real intensive two and three year
experiences in the lab. So the kind of thing that used to happen routinely where people would go and
work at NIH like you did or other things where they can get exposed to science in a meaningful
way, even if their career is not going to be as a PI running a lab, it will help increase the
scientific literacy, being able to speak both these languages. So that's something I'm super
passionate about. Because traditional medical school is actually not scientific training.
That means it's gone now. So, you know, I've heard this saying, I don't know who this one gets
attributed to, but the gist of it is that we've taken the science out of medical school and the
medicine out of graduate school, right? So our graduate students are craving more understanding
of physiology and medicine. Our medical students are not really missing what they're not getting,
but they're not learning science anymore. And so once that happens, then the likelihood that that
student who's not done a PhD, who's never worked in a lab is going to have the courage or the
ability to go work in a lab later on in life is close to zero. And the thing is what was great
about the way it happened for me was that I came to it without much preconceived notion in dogma.
So I came to it with just native curiosity and sort of like, how should things work? And look,
I wish my basis of scientific knowledge was greater than it is. I'm jealous of people,
like, you know, my MD, PhD friends from Hopkins, like Dave Sabatine, those guys, I'm totally jealous
of how deep their knowledge is. But I have a different perspective and I bring the clinical
work that I do and the things that I think about when I'm seeing patients that have thought about.
So it's a different way. We didn't get a chance to talk about it, but you've been
really, I mean, as though everything we've described your entire clinical career,
you're in amazing stuff you're doing in the lab isn't enough to keep you busy. And oh, by the way,
you also have a family. You decided like, I mean, I feel like you did it in a week because I remember
when you called me and told me about it. And then a week later you had a prototype. And then
two weeks later you had your next, you started a company last year. Yeah. So can you tell us a
little bit about that? Cause half my patients now are using this device. We could do an entire
podcast on this. And maybe I'll have a podcast and bring you on. Cause I do think there's some
of this stuff. Like when I first called you, I remember calling you, it was like a Saturday or
Sunday and you were generous to take the time to help me think about this. And we talked a lot about
the behavioral science, which and the behavioral economics, which is something we've talked about
a lot at our time on the Virta advisory board. And I think it's to me, it's the most interesting
part of this whole obesity story, right? Is that we're talking about a behavior at its core and
a change in behavior. And how do we at the absolute most basic level, how do we use technology to help
people change their behavior? And that's something that I've been thinking about for a long time.
And to make a really, really, really long story short, I got together with an amazing team of
people who'd been doing work in weight loss. And actually when I told them what I wanted to do,
they both told me to get lost. They said, they're never going to do a weight loss startup again.
They had started and sold a company to Weight Watchers and said, it's too hard. People say
they want to lose weight, but they actually don't. They don't have the tools to do it. So
short version of a long story. We, we thought, well, gosh, you know, one thing that is true,
I think about weight loss in general for people who struggle is that we're not giving them the
information they need to be able to make the change in behavior. The only information that
we give people is the information they get from stepping on their scale. That's an incredibly
lagging indicator. I mean, you could have entire gallon of ice cream tonight at 11 o'clock and
step on the scale tomorrow and you may not have any difference in your weight. So it's relatively
useless on a day to day level. And by the time you actually get information, it's not actionable.
I would add one more thing, which is the amount of movement in water alone makes it almost
impossible. For example, the average woman who is still experiencing a menstrual cycle
can easily fluctuate by eight pounds in a month. It's a four kilogram average fluctuation in
water weight. So can you imagine if a woman says, I want to lose 10 pounds in, and she's using her
scale, it's just impossible. And you know, you can build in, you know, moving averages and other
things, but again, you're not giving them the information they need to be able to make the
changes if they want to make a change. So what's interesting and unique about, so when I came to
the Virta Advisory Board, I'd never done keto before. And frankly, I kind of thought it was a
little bit weird. I don't know if you remember that first advisory board meeting we had at the
Mexican restaurant down there. And I still joke about this. In fact, I think I've joked about it
with Sami and Steve that I show up at this thing and like there's bowls of guacamole there with
spoons in them and like, you know, fajita dishes without wraps and like, there was no
carbohydrate to be found on the table. I thought this is like a cult. Like this is,
this is weird. And I never really had any curiosity about doing it. Then I tried it myself.
And I realized that the one unique fact about this diet that's different from all other diets that I
know of other than fasting for a week is it allows you to follow biomarker. And that if you use that
biomarker as a guide to help your own adherence, it can help reinforce some of these behaviors.
And maybe that would be sufficient. So we finally decided to try this thing. And one of the issues
as you know better than anybody testing your ketone level, whether it's through blood or breath or
urine has all kinds of issues and there's imperfection. But we figured if we could build
a good sensor, I'm not talking about like a lab level sensor, but a good sensor that people could
use, they could carry around that would be portable and accurate enough to help guide these
behavioral changes that we could use that as the basis of basically replacing a lot of the human
intervention that goes into programs like Virta. So Virta is successful at what they do in a
different population, the population of people not really primarily trying to lose weight,
but more trying to manage their diabetes. But that takes a lot of human capital. So could this
information help replace that and kind of make it more economically feasible? And so basically
through just a series of incredibly fortunate accidents and beyond hard work from this team,
we were able to get the sensor, swap out an alcohol sensor for an acetone specific sensor
and got this thing to market quickly. It didn't feel like a day, but it was fast. I mean, we
basically, I think you and I spoke in August. I feel like I had a prototype in October because
I'd managed my calendar through my fasts, which are always being a quarter. And then of course,
my December had the version I have now, which is great. And that's the one a number of my patients
have. I think it was November. And so yeah, we are doing this kind of slow. So tell people,
I don't even think we've mentioned the name of the company. So what's the name of the company?
It's called, well, it's spelled K-E-Y-T-O and most people pronounce it keto as you would pronounce
ketogenic diet, but we were sort of intentional in being vague about whether you could call it
key two if you wanted to, and that leaves it open to the idea that it could be more than just
ketogenic diet. And so the company is organized around one is giving people the information they
need through this sensor, which, you know, links up to an app to giving people information they need
to be able to succeed at whatever they're doing. So you know how to do keto. You've done Ted talks
on keto, but an average person hears about ketogenic diet and they're like, well, I don't know. I don't
know how to do that. So we give people the information they need to be able to do the diet.
And then at some point, and it won't be now, but at some point we're going to help people get to,
you know what to do. You're measuring how well you're doing it, but how do you actually enact,
how can you enable that? How can you get people the food? So I cook 90% of the meals. I've got my
lunch that I brought with me over there in a bag, but a lot of people don't have that luxury. And so
they'll go out here to this food court and want to get lunch. And so can we help deliver that food to
them at some point? So that's sort of the big picture of what we're doing. And it's been
incredibly fun. I mean, I've been at UCSF now, I've been in this office for almost 10 years.
And I do think I'm like one of the luckiest people in the world to be able to do the things I do,
both combining this clinical work, which is just a gift with this lab work, which is basically like
a game. It's like a glorified living, breathing video game that we get to try and solve puzzles
every day. And I get paid to do it. But this thing has been fun to do. And it happens at a different
pace. As you said, it's like a normal cycle for me in the lab is like five years. This thing
happened in three months. And so it's fun to kind of exercise different muscles and think about
business for the first time in my life. I mean, I haven't really thought about business before.
I actually enjoy it. I love thinking about the human psychology and the behavior. So it's been
kind of a fun adventure. We'll see how it goes. Awesome. And you've got one for me to take back
to one of my, I'm seeing one of my patients next week who I was with the other day and I was
talking about it with him, like I had already given him one. And he's like, well, what are you
talking about? And I was like, well, I'm going to see Ethan. So I'll get you one. You're someone
that I follow on Twitter because I always enjoy, I mean, you know, for me, Twitter is just a great
way to curate reading and stuff. And I love following your stuff. So where can people find
you? That's probably my biggest place that I spend time social media wise. And my Twitter handles
at Ethan J wise, I have to say I probably had a significant problem. And my wife would say that
I had a more than significant problem with the amount of time I spent on there. I'm not there as
much anymore just because I can't keep up that and my job and my family and this startup thing. So,
but I do try to respond. You know, somebody sends me a message. I'll try to respond.
Even if once a week there's a great study that you're highlighting, I find that super helpful.
Yeah, it's fun. Look, Twitter actually went down there and visited a friend of mine as the CFO at
the company, Ned Siegel. And he invited me to, he said, you're so active, like you're a power user
in science and medicine. You should come visit. And it was really sweet. He brought, he invited
me to come down and we toured through the facility. I'd never been there before, but I think they have
something going there that talk about increasing scientific literacy. It's, it's, and I know I've,
my own patients who follow me and they tell me they learn a lot. They learn a lot about medicine
and science. They learn a lot from you. You don't have to be a stranger to, unless you've been in the
Himalayas hunting Yeti for the past five years. You certainly realize that right now Twitter is
under attack and I feel bad every time Jack Dorsey has to go on a podcast. It's just basically to get
skewered. I understand why people are upset about the role of Twitter in politics and fake news and
stuff. And I think that's a super upsetting problem. Fortunately, in the world that we play in Twitter,
I still find it more positive than negative. In the end, I've got a bunch of people I follow
who basically curate some of the research I just wouldn't be able to keep up with. Because I'm,
you know, I'm really narrow in what I do, but I need to know what's going on in these
fields that are adjacent and that's a great way to do it. So Ethan, I can't think enough has been
awesome. And I suspect this won't be the last time we have to sit down and have a formal discussion.
And we'll obviously have many more informal ones. Awesome, Peter. Thank you so much for coming up.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read,
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social,
you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but
usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the
obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.