Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Kevin Sayer. Kevin is the
executive chairman of the board of directors and the president and CEO of Dexcom. During his
tenure with Dexcom, he's been instrumental in leading the development of new technology,
including the G5, G4, and of course now the G6. If you've followed me for some time, you probably
know how much I love my Dexcom glucose monitor. I consider it to be one of the two most important
devices that I wear and I wear it pretty much all the time. I would say 300 to 330 days a year I
am wearing my CGM. It's offered me great insight, not just into the obvious things like how does
eating food X impact my glucose, although I still continue to learn a lot through that lens, but also
the impact of exercise, sleep, and stress on mitigating those things or amplifying those things.
So for example, one of the things I've noticed much more recently is the role that cortisol in
the evening plays on my glucose. In this interview with Kevin, we talk about a bunch of things. We
talk about how we met and his path to becoming the CEO of Dexcom. We talk about how the CGM
technology works and what makes the G6 what I conceive to be is the best model yet. We talk
about the challenges of working in the US healthcare system after getting CGM insured.
We talk about developing an even smaller, more user-friendly, less costly product while maintaining
performance and accuracy. Kevin does a really good job of explaining his framework on what
are the constitutive elements that would drive a CGM device. You'll see where this performance
and accuracy become important. We talk about what's the next thing on horizon for patients
with type 1 diabetes, the accuracy of the G6, software improvements for people with type 2
diabetes, and the remarkable benefits of real-time feedback that drive behavioral change for anybody
using this. Talk a little bit about Dexcom versus the competitors. There's basically
three large companies that do this, Dexcom being one, Abbott being the other through the acquisition
of Libre and Medtronic. We talk about less invasive options that people have asked about a lot.
Talk about the cost, why you need a prescription, when there might be an OTC, that's over-the-counter
option. We talk about smartwatch integration, Bluetooth, exciting collaborations and partnerships,
and future places for CGM such as in the hospital. We talk about lessons learned through failures and
successes. Before we get to this, I want to read a disclaimer that Kevin's team has asked me to read
and that's of course because he's the CEO of a public-traded company. This presentation includes
forward-looking statements. All forward-looking statements included in this presentation are made
as of September 21st, 2018, that was the date of the interview, based on information currently
available to Dexcom and are subject to various risks and uncertainties and the actual results
could differ. Dexcom undertakes no obligation to update such statements. With that said,
and without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Kevin Sayer.
Kevin, how are you? I'm great. Thanks so much for making time. I don't often come into somebody's
office, take them away from their work and ask them to sit down and talk. You know, our discussions
have been so interesting over time. I was thrilled when you asked me to do this. I can't imagine
what journey will go on as we talk for the next while, but I'm really looking forward to it. So,
speaking of which, I think I've told the story a couple of times to some friends how we met,
but it's sort of funny to me because anyone who knows me knows I'm when I'm on an airplane,
I'm there to mostly just work and I don't really talk to people. Occasionally, if somebody talks
to me, I'll certainly be polite, but I'm really focused. And so of course, it was about three
years ago, you and I met on an airplane. The funny part to me is how it happened, which is
I'm taking a little break from work to look at one of my 12 favorite watch sites and you look
over. Do you remember what you said? Oh, I do. I took my headphones off. I said, are you sure you
want one of those? You know, and I'm the same as you, Peter. I get on a plane and my wife claims
I am the most unfriendly individual in the world because I sit down. I wait for that moment when
I can open up my computer. I'm hooked to wifi. I start working and I'm thrilled. Or I just take
a break from life and watch something on the screen. So we hadn't said a word and all of a sudden,
you open up to watches and I go, I've got to talk with this guy. We've got to look at these things
and make sure he picks the right one. It was a very fun meeting and then neither of us worked
the rest of the flight. Yeah. But the best part is we talked about watches for an hour.
And then we're about an hour outside of New York. And at some point we literally hadn't talked about
anything but watches, but I just sort of said, Oh, are you heading home or heading to work? And you
said, Oh, you're going to work. And then it was like, what do you do? And then this is the part I
don't think I told you. I had only heard about Dexcom two months earlier from a guy named Jake
Kushner. I don't know if you know Jake, but he's a pediatric endocrinologist. Yeah. And so I was
having dinner in Houston with Jake a couple of months earlier and he was showing me his data
on his kids with type one diabetes that are walking around with hemoglobin A1c's of 5.6.
And he's saying to me, it's a game changer. We're done with telling kids with T1D that 7.5 is normal.
The new normal is 5.6 and we're having no hypo events. And he goes, but we can't do it without
this thing called CGM. And I was like, tell me more. And he said, so we use this thing. I think
it was the G5 that they were using at the time. And I remember sort of thinking about it and going,
that sounds so interesting. That's on my list of things I need to learn more about. And then
I ask you what you do and this is what you guys, they couldn't have made it up. No. And this is
all we do here at Dexcom. And we do see remarkable results in type one diabetes with these kids and
with everybody who uses the technology. Well, I've been wearing one now for almost three years.
I think after that flight, you said, well, you got to come in one day and we'll shoot the breeze. And
within like a week I was wearing one and I've never stopped. Well, and I also use you as a critique.
Because if we give Peter technology, you're a very, very good critic and very objective versus
our diabetes patients who, while they love the technology, it's life saving for them. For you,
you kind of look at it from a different perspective. And I use observations like that all the time when
I talk to engineers. And as we design future products, I love different perspectives on things.
And one of the things in our culture that is very unique, we are very curious as an executive team
by nature and curious is the word that I would use. We love to learn, explore. We all wear these
things. We all wear the new ones. In fact, I'm supposed to get a prototype of a new one next
week that's going to communicate with some other devices. It's really fun. And it does allow for
learning. It keeps your mind going very quickly. We put Peter on our G6 technology right as it was
approved. Yeah. And well, actually, I mean, I was on that G5X a year ago, which was almost a G6 minus
the calibration issue. That's right. So now let's go back a little bit. What were you doing before
Dexcom? So if you go back in the history of my career, I started in diabetes in 1994. I met
an individual named Al Mann, who's one of the most remarkable entrepreneurs ever. And he had designed
the insulin pump that is now Medtronic Diabetes. And we had a glucose sensor there. That's where
I saw the first one. And I worked in diabetes there as the finance person and very much a
business person till we sold the company to Medtronic. I stayed on with Medtronic for a while.
And we launched the first continuous glucose monitor at Minimend and Medtronic back in those
days. And then I decided I didn't love big company. So I left and I found a couple of other jobs that
were interesting, but I didn't love them. And my job right before this company was culturally
fascinating. It was a Singapore headquartered Singapore public company. And I was head of the
US operation and the chief financial officer of the entire company, but we had operations in China,
Japan, and all over Europe. At the same time, I joined the Dexcom board. My dear friend and
associate from Minimed, Terry Gregg was the CEO here. And as we wrapped our other company down,
as it became obvious, we weren't going to be a US presence, the opportunity came to move to
San Diego and go to work at Dexcom. So I went home after our board meeting in December of 2010
and told my wife, I think we're leaving our dream house here in North LA. We're going to go,
I have another adventure. And we moved down here in June of 2011. And it's been just a tremendous
ride ever since. Now between the time you spent at Medtronic, where you were a finance guy,
but obviously as the listeners going to learn soon, you have pretty good technical chops on
this stuff. But you were working on CGM then and you probably just by osmosis absorbed a lot of it.
But between the, what sounds like the mid to late nineties and then your return here via Dexcom,
were you still in a CGM space? No, my position right after Medtronic was with a specialty laboratory
that ran esoteric lab tests and did that for a little while. And my company right before here,
the Singapore based company was a drug eluding stent business. And we had a proprietary drug
formulation and a proprietary polymer that was bi-absorbable. So when the drug eluding stent
was expanded into the vessel, both the drug and the polymer would absorb for better safety rates.
But getting a stent approved in the United States was too big of a deal for a company as small as ours.
Well, especially when Abbott, Medtronic, J&J and Boston Scientific, the four of them own the entire
market. The law of four. Medical device companies, you see technologies, you start with a couple,
they swell up to 10 or 11 and then you go back down to three or four.
I didn't even know this about you. So once we're done with this podcast, when we go grab coffee,
we'll talk about my previous life where I had to know everything about drug eluding stents.
Oh. I spent two months interviewing 150
interventional cardiologists around the country when I was at McKinsey trying to learn everything
about this for our client, which was obviously I can't say who, but it was one of those four.
And it was at the reintroduction because remember there was a period of time when they had to go
back to bare metal. Oh yeah.
And then they had to reintroduce. So fascinating topic. So basically you came back to this company
and what I assume you were bringing that was of most value was you understood medical devices,
you understand durable medical goods, you understood the law of healthcare. It wasn't
that you were the world's expert on CGM. No, I'd been on the board and I really
will never be the world's CGM technical expert. These guys here are spectacular. But what I did
bring, or at least I believe is very much that curious factor I talked about and a very open
and aggressive mind to grow our business. This company has gone through tremendous change.
I came in for a couple of reasons. Terry is exactly 10 years older than me and I was supposed
to succeed him at Medtronic and that one didn't work out the way we wanted to. And when I joined
the board, that was something we talked about early on. And I knew all these guys. I knew the
technology very well. I knew how bright they were and I just thought it would be a tremendous
opportunity. Let's take another step back just for folks to give them a basic because there's so many
questions I get asked about this. In fact, I went out to Twitter a week ago and said,
I was going to be sitting down with you and hey folks, if you have questions shoot them over. And
I was really amazed at how many people ask questions. And there are a lot of questions
that I could answer truthfully, but there are some that I can't. So I'm going to try to assimilate
the question. So I think the first question that I get asked a lot is how does this actually work?
In other words, why is it that even if you don't look at CGM, if you just talk about point of care
glucose, why is it that with one prick of blood, you can measure something like glucose,
but you can't measure a number of other things? What is it about measuring glucose that enables
that? Well, our technology is designed to measure glucose only. And the way our sensor works is
there's a small wire that's thinner literally than a human hair or as thin as a human hair
that's inserted subcutaneously into your tissue. That wire is very special metal alloys and it's
coated with a number of membranes. That wire and those membranes then generate an electrochemical
signal that goes up into a transmitter that sits on top of the sensor. You've worn it,
you know what it looks like. And inside that transmitters an algorithm that converts that
electrochemical signal to a glucose value. So that is the only thing that we have done
with this technology. There probably are other analytes we could take and develop enzymatic
layers that would sense that type of chemistry. In fact, you and I have talked about some of the
things that might be meaningful and useful over time, but we've grown so quickly, we just, we
haven't addressed those. But I think the key is it's an enzymatic reaction. And I think that's
the point I try to make to folks is if there's an antibody that can be linked to it, if there's an
enzymatic reaction that can be done without multiple washes, that's the kind of stuff you
can measure in point of care. Whereas many things that are complex, you can't, you know,
you can't measure, you know, the number of lipoproteins or something like that, because that
requires NMR. It's a very separate test. You can't even measure insulin. You're either going to do
it through a radio immune assay or you're going to do it through multiple washes, something called
an ELISA based assay where you have to rinse and repeat and stuff like that. So out of the gate,
there are some things that can be measured in a drop of blood, which again is different from what
you guys are doing. And, you know, glucose is one of them, electrolytes, lactate, beta-hydroxybutyrate,
which you and I have talked about a lot. So, I mean, I guess let's go back and so how deep is that
that little filament that sits inside the patient? It goes in at an angle now it sits in probably a
half inch under the skin. The insertion technology of the sensor goes in with a needle and needle
comes out. There is so many engineering hours into the insertion of that sensor. And one of the first
things you notice about the Gen 6 product, it's an automated insertion. The needle is in your skin
as the engineers tell me, less time than it takes a hummingbird to flap its wings a couple of times.
So it's in and out very quickly. So a patient doesn't feel it. And then the sensor rest in the
subcutaneous tissue and you really don't feel that sensor at all. I think I've commented to you
probably the very first time I tried this, which was on the prototype that with the G5, of course,
you are the one is the patient who is responsible for the velocity with which that needle goes in.
And if you're a human being, which we all are, I think we're just hardwired to do it a little
slower than we'd like because it's so, you know, it's a little uncomfortable. Look, it wasn't the
most uncomfortable thing in the world, but it's, if you're doing it, it's scary. Yeah. Yeah. It is
not an appealing thing. You look at that, our old device, which was very functional, but you look at
it and it truly looks like, I don't know if I want it. And we've had patients send emails saying,
I've stared at this thing for six weeks and I don't dare put it in my body. We're not having
that reaction with the new one. Yeah. And I had that reaction with a number of my patients,
because as you know, a lot of the patients in my practice, though, they don't have type one or type
two diabetes, like me, they understand the value of even people with, you know, quote unquote,
normal glucose levels being able to track this. But occasionally folks would freak out and they'd
say, you know, we'd go through the, all the process of getting them a three month supply and they,
you know, they've already paid for it. Cause of course their insurance isn't going to cover it.
They don't have diabetes, but then that needle just sort of scares them away. Of course,
the other thing that we speculate, or maybe it's not a speculation, maybe it's just a given is
the lack of trauma that's involved with the G6 insertion seems to make for a much more
accurate device, which the G5 itself was remarkably accurate, but I don't know if it's
anecdotal, but in my hands, at least the way I track it, the G6 seems to be so accurate. It's
almost hard to believe. There's so many elements that go into the performance of a sensor. I
believe the insertion process does make it more accurate, but that G6 sensor has new membrane
technology versus the old one. There's also a new algorithm. In fact, one of the things that has
made our company successful during this G6 project in the middle of it, our algorithm engineers came
and they said, we have a better way to do this, but it's going to delay the project if we do it.
We looked around the room and said, but if it's going to be that much better, let's delay it and
put it in. And so we did, and we made that decision. That algorithm has helped tremendously
with the accuracy. So all those things together, the easier insertion, the new membrane technology,
the new algorithm, I think even the fact that it's flatter on the body and doesn't pull as
much is helpful as well. I think on three occasions over two plus years, my kids kicked
out my G5, including once on the very first day I put it in, which really bummed me out when I
picked up my son and he obviously just not playing around and he horse and he kicked me and the thing
came out. Whereas the G6, yeah, it's a lower form factor. And obviously this is only going to
continue as the evolution of these things goes. So you talked about a couple of other things that
could be measured besides glucose. Are there any that you think are commercially viable? There's
lots that could be interesting, but do you think there's anything else that's commercially viable?
We don't know yet, but we have so many markets to take our technology to now that we need to
capitalize on this opportunity and take care of the people that we serve and open the other markets
where glucose can just be a wonderful tool that we really haven't done that much of yet.
So approximately how many patients in the United States have type 1 diabetes or what percentage
population? How do you think about it? About a million and anything you read in the literature
says anywhere from 1.3 to 2 million in the United States, common numbers 1.5. And there are another
1.5 million people with type 2 diabetes who intensively use insulin. So they are really in
need of a continuous glucose sensor to manage their health. Now, going back to those folks with type
1 diabetes, what percentage of them use one of the commercially available continuous glucose monitors?
Most would estimate somewhere between 20 and 30 percent right now. And again, these percentages
have grown rapidly over the past couple of years as we've gotten better and as other products have
come to the market. So you and your competitors, and I guess your main competitor is Abbott?
Abbott and Metronic. The three of you collectively aren't even remotely close to
saturating the most obvious market for this product, which is type 1 diabetes. That's right.
Again, hard to speak speculatively about what others think, but I assume everybody's also
looking at that second group you just mentioned, which is another market, which is the insulin
using patients with type 2 diabetes. Yeah, in fact, when Medicare and CMS gave us approval in
January of 2017, they approved the use of CGM for intensive insulin using type 2 patients.
And that was a step that we really needed. One of the barriers, and it's not really a barrier,
but it's very interesting as you grow a business and one of the fascinating things about our journey
here, it makes such common sense. Everybody thinks, well, everybody should just have this.
And the insurance companies were very well insured and very well covered,
but it's not always easy to get. I was in a state not too long ago, for example,
where a patient had to document a certain number of events where their blood sugars went below 50
before they can get an X-Com, even if they have type 1 diabetes.
Which is very dangerous for a type 1 diabetic. Very dangerous for anybody.
Yes. And yet, because of fear for spending money on devices and treatments that aren't useful,
payers are hesitant sometimes. Not all of them. We get very, very good coverage, but it is cyclical.
You know, a payer will cover us very well for a two-year period and they'll look and, man,
we've added so many people to this technology. What are we doing? Let's slow it down. So they'll
slow it down through criteria. We have a full-on sales team that does nothing but call on those
who reimburse for the product and we try and make it as easy as we can. There are trade-offs for
price and access and we try and negotiate those things on a regular basis. I believe over time,
at least 80% of the people with type 1, and I've said this in public forums, 80% of the type 1
intensive population should be using continuous glucose monitoring.
Has there been an economic analysis done, ideally, independently, but it might be done, obviously,
by one of the companies or more, that does the equivalent of what we would think of as an NNT
for a drug trial. So for the listener, an NNT is a number needed to treat. This is an analysis
that's not done economically. This is more of a life-saving. So how many patients do you need to
treat with a certain drug to save a life? But you can also start to do these things economically.
And is there a question of how many patients need to be on a CGM before you either save a life
through a hypoglycemic event or maybe a different analysis would be the cost of the CGM versus the
cost of the complications from mismanagement? So has any of that been done? We have done some
economic models and studies in that area. What we find is the major cost that CGM prevents is exactly
what you talked about in the acute setting. They prevent hospitalizations. So you end up with a
specific set of patients who are what are often called hypoglycemia unaware, who aren't aware when
their blood sugars go low. The CGM gives them alerts and alarms. And our system also alerts
and alarms others who give care to those patients to whereby they can be taken care of. That share
feature is really one of the most remarkable things we've done here. You could be in Singapore,
and your wife could be here. If you had type 1 diabetes and your blood sugars went low, your wife
would know. And she could call the hotel and wake you up. And we hear stories like that all the time.
Does Medtronic's product or does Abbott's product do that? I believe Medtronic's new product does.
I believe they do have some sharing capabilities, but I know we pioneered it. We're the ones who
got it through the FDA, and it took a lot of effort. So that sharing capability is really good
for hypoglycemia unaware. That category, one hospitalization, I've seen numbers ranging from
10 to 30,000 dollars for that one hospitalization, but not everybody's hospitalized. We certainly
save on the long-term complications of diabetes, and that has been measured historically. And you
know, I've talked about this with A1c, which neither of us believe is the perfect measure.
But in our studies, we see at least a half a point drop over the course of a 12-month period compared
to multiple finger sticks. A full point drop for the patients, if you just look at them
independently on continuous glucose monitoring use for a six-month period, that is sustained.
That drop in A1c leads to reduced costs in the healthcare system, and there are very,
you know, well-known economic models to build that out. But here's where the rubber meets the road.
A 25-year-old probably isn't generating all those complications yet, and a 25-year-old is with an
insurance plan for two years before they move to their next job, and they're on another insurance
plan for two years. So we have to do a better job as a company documenting these economic benefits.
We run more studies to see how, you know, how much quality of life's improved, to see what we can
prevent. We are currently building outcome-type-based models to whereby we can, look, we can go into an
insurance company or a parent, say, look, here's what we think we can save you if we can put
everybody on CGM. But we're creating a new industry here. It's a completely new business.
Every day is a challenge like that, and every day there's more thoughts and more things to address
along those lines. The Medicare one is the most interesting. I spoke at a conference on a January
Wednesday where I told a group of our investors we would not have Medicare approval for 18 months.
And we got it Thursday.
That makes you look not terribly well informed.
That is correct. And the way it was approved, our device talks to a phone or a dedicated
Dexcom receiver. The way it was approved for the Medicare patients is they couldn't use the phone
app. Yet our Medicare patients are the ones most likely, other than children, to need to share the
data with somebody else. It took us, I want to say 18 months, we finally got the phone use
approved for the Medicare patients. When you're creating an industry like that, there are all
sorts of hurdles that you run into that you don't contemplate. You just kind of have to react.
I mean, I think that's one of the challenges that folks face in this industry in general,
which is the policy piece of it is hard because you don't exactly know from a long-term planning
standpoint exactly what changes are going to come about. The challenge that you raised, I think is,
I'm glad you brought it up because I think it's one of the most misunderstood issues in the US
healthcare system. I grew up in Canada and I'm actually not incredibly that impressed with the
Canadian healthcare system. I know that's going to make me a lot of enemies out there, but I don't
think it's like a panacea. I don't think necessarily Canada is doing it right either. But there's one
thing that I think a single payer system, at least one thing a single payer system brings over a
system that we have in the United States, which is the incentive is aligned between the payer,
the patient, the provider over a long-term. It's easier to align incentives because one way or the
other, that payer is going to pay. It's pay now or pay later. Yeah, that's right. Which by the way,
we were talking about children before we went on the mic and you had great piece of advice,
which I'm going to ask of you to share with others, but my brother's advice, which is
my brother has five kids. His piece of advice is pay now or pay later. Pay now or pay later.
You can either discipline your kid when they're five or you're going to discipline them when
they're older. But this thing with healthcare is if you have that 25 year old and the difference
between them having a hemoglobin A1C of 8% versus 6%, in the next year, it's nothing. It doesn't
matter. But in 20 years, it matters beyond words. That's right. And if you as the payer are on the
hook for that one way or the other, the economic model becomes so much more straightforward because
you don't have the portability of healthcare. That's right. Again, I'm not close enough to this
to know if a single payer system is even something that's viable in the US. It strikes me as
politically very unviable, but who knows? That said, it's not what you're dealing with now. So
you have a harder challenge to make the case economically, I suppose. No, we do. But again,
we're covered by 99, literally 99% of all reimbursement authorities where our coverage
is a little spotty still is in the Medicaid programs, we've got several states. But it's still,
there's a lot of documentation required. We're covered where it gets difficult as the documentation
the patients have to provide or the physicians have to provide and consistency of copays and
things of that nature. We're also classified as durable medical equipment. So our patients have
a copay and a deductible, which leads to a very seasonal business for us because in the fourth
quarter, most of our patients are maxed out on their deductible and copays and they want to buy
everything they possibly can. It's like Christmas. It's like Christmas. So from October to the end of
December here, it is all hands on deck. That's interesting. What percentage of your patients,
I'm guessing it's very small, but do what me and my patients do, which is it's a cash pay business.
There's no dealing with insurance. It's directly from, you know, a physician writes the prescription
and the patient comes straight to Dexcom. Not very many. Again, like you do, we have cash pay
patients and everybody in your system uses prescription is important for the regulatory
folks that I point that out. Not as many as we used to. We used to have a lot of Medicare patients
who paid cash. I see. But once Medicare covered, we actually had to refuse the Medicare cash patients
because if we took cash Medicare, while Medicare covered a device, we were in trouble. And it took
them seven or eight months to figure out how we could ship and process this new product code. So
we had upset patients for somewhere between six and eight months before we could start serving
them properly. The people who don't live in the United States that are listening to this are
scratching their heads, thinking what is going on over there? It is a, we have a really complicated
healthcare system. Yeah, we do. But look, there are some things that I think it does well. And I
think, you know, one of the things that does well is it seems to set up an economic engine that
allows for an innovation that I think is hard to do outside of the United States. Oh, I'd agree
with that. And I don't think it's a small accident that the disproportionate share of the innovations
come out of the US. So, you know, kind of going back to some of the technical stuff,
you have a partnership, you have a collaboration with Verily. We do. So tell people what is Verily,
how does that have, what does that have to do with Google? And how did that collaboration come about?
And how does it work? Well, the way it came about was interesting. Back in 2015, there was a
healthcare group within the walls of Google before Alphabet came around. And they analyzed
technologies where they felt they could develop technology that would make an impact on future
products. And they also analyzed disease states where they felt they could use Google's or Google
Healthcare's analytic capabilities to develop better care models. Google has made a couple of
attempts at healthcare. And they came down and met with us and said, Look, we've looked at your
product, we've looked at what you do, we have a lot of electronics expertise, we have expertise
in data analytics, and a bunch of other areas we would like to partner with you. Aislinn told us
they were going to talk to other glucose sensor companies as well. We looked at that and said,
You know what, this Google is a big company, and they do a lot of things. And we looked at their
concepts and their thoughts. And they looked at the problems different than we do. They looked more
at miniaturization and size and convenience, and the things that consumers look at. Because we as
a company, again, serving our, our population of people with type one diabetes are in a bay, we
tell you this, our core principle has been performance and accuracy, we will performance and
accuracy, we always want to build the best, we were the first to be connected. But as far as really
getting the thing tiny, or something that somebody without diabetes can wear, that had not been a
focus here. And you know, that they can wear for fitness. So when they came down and presented this
this to us, we decided that as an electronics and design partner that we would like to work with them.
So after several months of negotiations, we not several months, a couple of months, we
signed up a deal more co developing future products for Dexcom. Those products will be Dexcom
sensors, those membranes and those algorithms that we've developed to make our sensor accurate,
and perform very well will come from our core technology that we've always developed.
The electronic side and some of the communication and the Bluetooth and those other things
have been driven by the Verily engineers, that's where they have great areas of expertise.
The overall package and mechanical part of the system we've done together. We've talked about
this Peter, we focus on performance, patient convenience and usability and then taking cost
out of it. We kept all three of those in mind as we did that. Yeah, it seems to me and I like your
framework, right? So let me see if I remember what you said, it's going to be performance.
Performance first.
How accurate is this thing? End of the day, that's the single most important thing. If it doesn't
perform, who cares what else it does? Then the patient experience, how big is it? How easy is it
to use? How often do you have to change it? Do you have to separate the sensor from the transmit?
What does the software look like?
And then cost.
It seems to me, having been fiddling around with this thing for a while, that the step between
G5 and G6, you're now on the asymptotic part of the performance curve. There's not a lot of
performance gain at this point, is there?
There is some performance to gain. Boy, we spend a lot of time studying this and talking about this.
As far as just bringing the overall accuracy percentage down, there's not a whole lot to gain.
Where there is to gain on the performance side is bringing that curve of performance. You have a
bell curve of performance for every sensor, pushing that bell curve in to whereby every
experience is the same. Most of them are the same now, and we believe it's very consistent,
but that consistency and reliability enables us to do two things. Number one, it enables us to
do very sophisticated things with people who want to control their insulin dosage with our sensor
whether through an artificial pancreas system or on their own using our data.
But the other thing it enables to do, if that performs the same all the time, it will enable
us to go out to broader markets because people won't question or challenge the data. They will
see it and go, okay, this is right. This one works. And we call it internally eliminating
the outliers. And I know every company does this with what they build. And so performance-wise,
that's where we're headed there. And those are the things that we look at and in our meetings
all the time. I don't even know if I told you the story. It's kind of funny, about a year and a
half ago, a mutual friend, so it's a friend that I introduced to you, but I won't call him out. I'll
keep his identity private. He introduced me to Andy Conrad at Verily, but it was through some
completely unrelated, there was a different reason for us to meet. So I'm up there and I didn't,
at the time, I just, I either didn't know that you guys had worked with Verily or I just hadn't put
too many together. So I'm sitting in his office and I see these mock-ups of things that look like
next-gen CGM's. And I said, Andy, what are those? And he goes, oh yeah, we work with this company
called Dexcom. And of course I lifted up my shirt and showed him my, as at the time it was a G5.
And oh my God, I mean, it was, I felt like Dorothy, this was like Oz. I couldn't believe
what the future could hold. So going back then from a technical standpoint,
because you alluded to what the future could hold, right now you are measuring glucose in
subcutaneous fluid. Correct? Yes, that's correct. Not in blood. So people need to understand that.
So even a relatively lean individual has enough subcutaneous tissue that the risk of using this
thing, it's like, is it an issue in kids? Because I've seen some really tiny little kids with type 1
diabetes. Sometimes it is and parents learn how to make sure they insert it and that the needle
doesn't go into the muscle tissue. There will be an occasional instance where a sensor may go too far
in the tissue. But by and large, no, it's very successful. There's a meeting in Florida every
year, a group called Children with Diabetes, and look at all the kids who wear this. It's not an
issue for children. They do extremely well with it. You know, and I think I'm, I don't know if I
ever told you this story, but I was at a swim meet, it was my daughter's swim meet. I had just finished
my swim workout at the same pool. So I'm in my bathing suit finishing my workout as the kids are
about to start the meet. And this kid comes over to me and his eyes light up like saucers because
he sees that I have a sensor on and he's got a sensor on and he is tiny. He is the littlest
kid I've ever seen. And he was like, do you have type 1 diabetes? And I said, no. Why? And he looked,
I didn't even realize what he was looking at. And I said, he said, because you're wearing the same
thing I'm wearing. And I said, Oh, hey, little buddy, let me tell you, I volunteered to wear
this thing. That's how cool it is to wear. Oh, that's great. Yeah. He loved it. He loved that
there was some adult who was wearing this who didn't quote unquote have to wear it. But I was
like, yeah, we're the coolest guys here. I assure you. One of the most humbling things about this job
is when I go out to a diabetes function and meet the children or the adult patients, whoever who
has had this device save their life or change their life the way that it has. They want their
picture taken with me. I said, how about we just take care? No, we want you. Nobody wants needs
their picture with me. No, they want to take a picture. They are so gracious. They are so,
I know that they're so indebted to our company and it's really why we come to work every day.
What keeps us going. We had my favorite meeting ever. An 11 year old young man comes in. We sit
down and people come to San Diego on vacation and they come to Dexcom. So we got Lego land,
SeaWorld, Dexcom. And parents will bring their kids in and whichever the executive team is here,
we'll take them on a tour of the factory and then we'll sit in a conference room with them because
that is the best market research in the world to sit and talk to somebody who uses this each and
every day. This 11 year old young man said, I have some questions. I said, okay. He pulls like a legal
pad out of his notebook, out of his backpack and he has 40 questions. He wanted to know the chemical
composition of the membrane. 11. We just looked at him and go, no, we're not going to tell you all
those things. But he had thoughtfully written out all these questions and then had several
suggestions for us. It's just amazing. And your story, it happens all the time. Yeah, it's really
special. And I do have a friend with type 1 diabetes and she did say something to me that I've
thought a lot about since. She said, Peter, you have the luxury of if you don't want to wear that
sensor for a couple of weeks, you don't have to wear that sensor. She goes, I don't have that
luxury. And again, she wasn't saying that to be critical of how much I loved using it. She was just
saying, understand that my relationship with this CGM is different from yours. This is my lifeline.
For you, this is just a gain in your health, but it's not necessary for you to function. And I was
sort of humbled by that a little bit. And I realized, I can understand why someone who's got
type 1 diabetes has sort of a different relationship with this on both extremes.
On both extremes. It is love a lot of time. It's sometimes hate.
And the hate I think is the, I have to do this. I have to have this thing on me.
I had two close friends in residency who had type 1 diabetes. And this was back in the Wild West.
I mean, it was, I couldn't believe how archaic it was and how hard it was for them to manage
their diabetes. Because in a surgical residency, it's very difficult to predict when you're going
to eat. Oh yeah.
And therefore it's very difficult to predict when you're going to use insulin and which insulin
you're going to use. And I remember one of my friends who's now a cardiac surgeon in Minnesota,
there would be times when he always had to have a thing of orange juice and candies in the OR next
to his pager. And he would hopefully get to the point where he could say to a nurse while he's
operating, Hey, I need some orange juice quickly. And she would bring over the orange juice and
tuck the straw behind the mask and let him sip some orange juice or stick a candy in his mouth
or something like that. If he was, you know, this was an operation that was supposed to be done in
three hours and now it's five hours, that kind of thing. We take for granted in many ways,
like what this disease meant before banting. Oh, I don't know how people did it. Well,
they did it. They managed and then people have lived long, healthy lives. But this tool is so
much better than what we had before. And the things that can come in the future,
we made an acquisition a couple of weeks ago. The next thing on the horizon for type one diabetes,
let me take a step back is to develop algorithms to go with the sensor because right now we tell
you your glucose value. We tell you your trend. We tell you how fast you're going up or going down.
We will give you alerts and alarms based on what's going on. But we don't tell you what to do.
And algorithms have been developed for automated insulin delivery that will automatically do
things for you. One product that we're partnered with is tandem's new insulin pump. And it shuts
off when your glucose goes too low and then turns back on based on sensor signals. And the early
read on that product from consumers has been wonderful from patients. But these algorithms
are getting more and more sophisticated. Explain for the listener where that product sits. How
does it actually work? So there's an insulin pump that is on your body. It's about the size of a
good old fashioned pager that used to carry around in your hand. And there's an insulin
cartridge inside that pump contains software that regulates the delivery of insulin with that,
through that insulin cartridge to a small infusion set that is usually placed on your abdomen. A
little Teflon cannula goes under your skin and the sensor resides another place on your body.
And the sensor signal is read by that pump, which then takes all the information about insulin that
it knows how much has been delivered, your glucose value, and will determine, at least for this system,
if your blood sugars go too low, it turns off insulin delivery for some period of time,
then turns it back on when it sees the trend that you're coming back up.
Algorithms over time will do more than that. They can regulate your insulin delivery all throughout
the day, whether you're high or you're low, and detect things like meals. I mean, this is very
futuristic, but there are algorithms that will detect, okay, it's very apparent that Kevin just
ate, let's put some insulin in here and see how it goes. There are algorithms, again, to take care
of you more during the nighttime, because during the nighttime while you sleep, you're not eating
and you're not exercising. So there's not as many variables involved. So we acquired one of these
algorithms two or three weeks ago, just because it's an asset we felt we needed to have and develop.
Not everybody uses an insulin pump, not everyone will have access to that technology, it's not
inexpensive either. We think a lot of people will, but we also think we can take these algorithms and
apply them to people who use multiple daily injections as well to develop decision support.
You know, I always tell the engineers, I want the staples button, I want the easy button.
I want to take a shot and I want to hit something and say how much insulin do I take?
Or I want at 10 o'clock, I want to hit a button that says I'm about to go to bed.
What do you predict is going to happen? Those types of things are an engineer's dream,
which is what again, why it's so fun to work here. We have chemical engineers, software engineers,
electrical engineers, mechanical engineers, packaging it, any engineer you could think of.
Well, the algorithm guys, and along with the wonderful asset we acquired, are going to look
at developing those type of decision support tools to help make this easier for patients to
make good decisions. Now the question becomes how much benefit does that add to their care?
If they only go from 8A1C to 7.8, it's probably not worth it and nobody's going to pay for that.
But we think we can build a very strong outcome case over time.
But even if you went from 8 to 8 but reduced bad outcomes, like hypos.
Yeah, and reduced hypos. Yeah, that oftentimes happens. Your A1C may stay the same,
but your time hypoglycemic may go away.
That's the thing I was impressed with. Jake's data went way back even before you and I met,
which was they dropped hemoglobin A1C, I want to say like 2% on average,
but they reduced the hypos too.
Oh yeah.
And that's the part that like I remember in medical school, the standard teaching was,
you don't care about the hypers are fine. Yes, you can go too hyper, but the thing that you have to
ward against is the hypo and you'll accept a higher A1C to do it. And I think the tide is
changing. I think people are understanding that because of how long a person is going to live
with type 1 diabetes, the microvascular complications are real. And as you probably
know, there are data that actually suggest, and I saw this through Jake's work that
better glycemic control in kids when they're young, these are not randomized. So there's
an obvious confounder here, but it can predict better intellectual performance in school and
stuff like that. Now again, the obvious confounder there is maybe the kids that have better glycemic
control have better glycemic control because of some other variable that's impacting their
performance later on, socioeconomic status or the education of parents or the attention of parents.
So there's lots of other things there. I don't follow this literature closely. So it's possible
that there's actually been a randomization that would allow for determining that. But
the other thing, we talk a lot about average blood glucose and instantaneous blood glucose,
but another variable that I find very informative is the standard deviation. So every
day I look at my report, I always do the seven day report. I want to see a seven day report every
day. And that's showing me my average blood glucose for the last seven days and my standard deviation.
And then every month or so I want to see my 90 day trailing report. And you brought up hemoglobin
A1C earlier. I'm one of those people for whom hemoglobin A1C is categorically useless because
I have beta thalassemia minor. So my red blood cells are very small. They stick around for very
long periods of time. My hemoglobin A1C on a blood test generally varies between 5.6 and 6.0.
Basically I'm pre-diabetic on a test. But using CGM for the last few years and calibrating it,
because even the G6 I still calibrate every day just to... We left that option in. By the way,
that is a very elegant option. That's basically when I took my libre and threw it out the door.
Because I used to use the two in parallel and I just gave up on the libre because you couldn't
force the calibration and it was so inaccurate and you couldn't get real time. I mean, there was just
too many problems with it to even discuss here. But using these forced calibrations, I realize
this thing's plus or minus 3%. There are many days, Kevin, when it is the exact same number.
And I think to myself, this can't be happening. The meter says I'm 88 and I poke my finger and
it says I'm 88. And I'm like, how is that impossible? We call that the unicorn. Yeah.
But I get a lot of unicorns today before I came here. I did a calibration and I don't know,
the device said 89 and I was 88 or something. I mean, it was staggering. It's an interesting
dynamic because you are very focused on accuracy. I would say the biggest benefit of G6 to our users
has been the accuracy without the calibrations. We had somebody in yesterday who's been on a
product for a very long time, one of our Dexcom warriors. And I asked him how it was going and he
held his hands out to me and he goes, my fingers have not felt like this for 15 years. And that's
how long I've had diabetes. Well, that's another interesting point you bring up, which is when I
do my fasts, I'm calibrating twice a day. I'm checking ketones two or three times a day,
just 14 days of that kind of checking. My fingers are all blue and they hurt like crazy. And that's
another realization for me, which is think of all those kids that that is their life.
That's right. It sounds like how big a deal is that? It's really painful. In fact, you start to
lose sensation. One day I was upset about some clinical results I saw because we were calibrating
the sensor with a meter and it became apparent that the meter was off. So I got my car, I drove
to the drugstore, I bought three meters and I stuck my finger 60 times in a day, 20 times with
each of the three meters and I made my own little spreadsheet, recorded all the meters, recorded the
CGM reading to see what had happened. Because in the old days, when you had to calibrate this device
twice a day, a bad fingerstick would set it off for a while. Now we have since revised the algorithm
to identify a fingerstick that we just think is inaccurate and we'll wait a while and ask for
another one if somebody enters them. But it was very discouraging because we'd submitted a clinical
trial to the FDA based on a meter from a large company that we were told was fabulous and it
turned out to be high all the time. And that drives our accuracy level off. Do you have a point of view
about which of the commercially available drugstore meters do you find the most accurate?
I wouldn't offer that up. I have idea. I think most of them are okay. I would tell you my experience
of meters is also about the consistency. So oftentimes when I'm wearing our sensor and go
to check the accuracy, now I don't enter the calibrations like you. I like to see what the
patient is experiencing, but I'll stick my finger twice in a row and get like some meters I'll get
a big difference. Others I don't get very much. And do you do two sticks or same blood? I vary it.
Okay. So here's a little tip that I've learned and maybe you've already heard this from patients, but
by washing your hands before you do it, then using the alcohol, you can get some false elevations if
you have any food on your hands. So if you have just a little, you know, again, like a crumb on
your hand can actually raise the glucose. So, and I remember my friend in residency, again, I'm glad
I'm not identifying if I don't want to call him out. I mean, he wouldn't even wash his hands before
he'd be poking his finger. Cause he was just like, you know, on the go all the time. Yeah, on the go.
It's like, I don't have alcohol pads. I'm just going to poke my finger and you know, but you know,
those little things do, I think add up to a little bit of benefit for what it's worth. I guess I can
say what I like the most for glucose. I like the one touch ultra. Okay. I've switched to that. I
used to use an Abbott meter or a different meter by, I think it was by Abbott. And I don't know,
I found the one touch ultra to be pretty darn good. And I've done the same sort of experience.
The thing you've done where I've gone multiple sticks, multiple fingers, blah, blah, blah, blah,
going back to finish the A1C thing, my 90 day trailing average glucose under these very tight
conditions shows an imputed A1C of 4.5 to 5.1, depending on how tight my nutrition is. So in
other words, my hemoglobin A1C is a full percent higher. Oh yeah. And that's actually posed real
difficulties for me when applying for life insurance. Cause they say you're a pre-diabetic.
And I say, I'm not a pre-diabetic. And they say, yeah, but your hemoglobin A1C is 5.8 or whatever
it is. And I've had many interesting discussions with the actuaries as I explain the limitations
of hemoglobin A1C. But if I could be health czar for a day and wave a magic wand, I would love to
have something that meets all of your criteria, right? So it does the performance. It's got the
patient, it costs very little, but I really think that if everybody had a CGM on every minute of
every day in some completely fantasy based way where it doesn't hurt, it doesn't cost anything,
but they had that data. It just drives such a behavioral change. And I think that that's why
the use of CGM, even without a deliberate intervention, superimposed improves outcomes.
Because it is really hard to not pay attention to how activities in your life, mostly food,
but not just food, stress. It's amazing what stress can do to your glucose level. I think
one of the first insights I remember coming and talking to your team about a couple of years ago
was how high nighttime cortisol levels were raising my glucose levels at night.
I'd go to bed with a glucose of 90, three hours after eating dinner, and I'd wake up with a glucose
of 105. And once I started measuring nighttime cortisol levels by collecting urine overnight,
I could correlate this amount of cortisol produced at night to how much that glucose
level would rise in the morning. And today I'll tell patients that fasting glucose
is not nearly as helpful as people think it is inside of a reasonably physiologic range. So
someone who has a fasting glucose of 130, that's a different situation. There's something going on
there. But I have patients that get very upset if their fasting glucose is 100 instead of being 90.
And I say, it's very difficult to understand what's going on there. That can very easily be
explained by cortisol or hepatic glucose output for some other reason that's not a function of
insulin resistance. So that's why I just think that these tools are so valuable. And like even
yesterday, I was on a late flight coming back from, I was in Chicago, and I just hadn't eaten much.
My flight was delayed. That's the other thing. So I went into the little store near the gate,
and they don't sell anything but crap. That is, absolutely.
Yeah. And I've already learned, there are certain snacks that I love, and they're kind of my comfort
food when my flights are delayed. I feel like I deserve a treat because I'm stuck in the airport.
And I bought one. I bought my treat. My treat is trail mix. I love me some trail mix.
Trail mix will spike you as fast as anything you can eat.
Yep. So I get on the plane, and I buy the big trail mix because I don't do anything in moderation.
So it's got, it's full of M&Ms and raisins and peanuts and little whatever. And I get on the
plane, and I'm looking at the bag, and I'm looking at my glucose, and my glucose level's great.
And I just decide I'm not eating it. So I didn't eat it.
Oh my goodness.
And I promise you, if I didn't have that CGM, I would have eaten it. But I just didn't feel like
looking at that glucose, because I know I've done it in the past. I eat that whole bag of trail mix.
My blood glucose will be 130, easily.
Oh, then that shows what good shape you're in, because that'll get me up to 150 or 160.
It'll get me higher. The worst glucose experience I've ever had was in an airport.
And I had been with investors all day long, and I had not, my glucose hadn't spiked at all,
because when I sit in those meetings all day, I don't eat very much.
And I'm in the airport, and I'm in Boston, and I say, you know what? I'm going to try something here.
The yogurt-covered raisins, in the little thing where you turn the wheel like the bubblegum machine,
got myself a cup of yogurt-covered raisins. I think there's some chocolate raisins in it too,
and ate the whole little cup of them. And I'm telling you, that was my only ever
above-200-glucose spike in my life, and it only took 30 minutes. It just,
right up as fast as possible. And it came down very quickly as well.
Yeah, and then it overshoots. It probably came down to 60.
And then it overshot, and I was, yeah, it overshot down in the low 70s,
because I put so much glucose into my body, that's how my pancreas reacted.
But all of our bodies behave differently. We've talked a lot about type 1 diabetes today, and
one of our visions going forward is to get into other conditions. And you're certainly a pioneer
in this, and really one of our first. We started doing work in type 2 diabetes.
So again, let's paint a picture. We've talked about kids with type 1,
adults with type 1 who have to deal with insulin their entire lives, or they die.
And the device is a love-hate relationship, because it always reminds them.
Now let's look at somebody with type 2 diabetes. They're my age, 60 years old.
May have had type 2 diabetes for five years. All they do is they go to the doctor, they get
some pills, they get a meter, they go home, and nobody tells them what's going on, and they say,
you need to eat less and exercise more, and take your pills, and after five, ten years of this,
all of a sudden your A1C's at 11, and what do you do?
So we start adding more drugs, and you can turn on the television anytime you want to,
and you can see more type 2 diabetes drug advertisements, probably than any other
pharmaceutical product, because these drugs are expensive, and there is a big population
here to be addressed. So we start prescribing other compounds, hoping the A1C will come down,
and it might come down a little bit, it might not, and if it doesn't come down enough,
we prescribe another compound, and another compound, and another compound,
and some point in time that patient gets the dreaded information, they've got to go on insulin.
But type 2 diabetes, I'm not a neuroscientific as you, but it's almost not diabetes. It's almost a
completely different disorder with all the insulin resistance, and all the other things
that go on in your body. Yeah, the biggest disservice that I think has been done to this field,
and this is hyperbolic, I mean there have been many disservices, it's the fact that we refer to
them both as diabetes. Now I understand why historically that's the case, but you're
absolutely right. Type 1 diabetes and type 2 diabetes are so different, and I try to be
disciplined about always referring to them that way, and not just saying diabetes, because it
really does a disservice to them. What you point out is very important, Kevin, which is
that the real problem in type 2 diabetes is that we have fixated so much on just the glucose and
not worrying about how we get there. That's right. So when you use a class of drugs that increases
endogenous insulin production, and or when you use more insulin, what you reduce is the glucose,
and what you reduce are the microvascular complications, you do not save lives.
They're still getting cancer, they're still getting heart disease, they're still getting
Alzheimer's disease at a much higher rate. The challenge in type 2 diabetes is the combination
of the hyperglycemia with the hyperinsulinemia. So the therapies that save lives in type 2 diabetes
would be things like metformin, where you're actually fixing the glucose side of the equation,
and not just adding more insulin to the system. The SGLT2 inhibitors, these are the things that
are getting the glucose out of the system, which actually brings me to a question based on something
you said earlier. Is there any way it is algorithmically possible to estimate, let's say,
the average insulin that a non-diabetic would make over the course of the day based on glucose,
if you had some data points? So if I came to you, Kevin, and said, look, let me go and get under test
conditions, certain levels of glucose and insulin that are associated, we develop a kinetics model
for it, and then by tracking my continuous glucose data over time, could we ever try to estimate what
my insulin levels are in between? We have some studies that are very preliminary, and I really
can't talk too much about it, but we do believe that it's possible to measure how quickly insulin
reacts and how much by the slope of the glucose curves, but not at our five-minute measurement
intervals. So we're looking at other ways to record data, to develop algorithms to do that,
but it's very preliminary right now. I think over time, and this gets back into another thing that
Dexcom will do over time, we have an open architecture platform as well. So we've developed
APIs to whereby we will provide data to other software platforms if they can analyze glucose
values better than we can. One Drop, there are a number of them. They haven't produced a lot for
us commercially, but we've made the decision that this is the type of company we want to be,
because we just can't do everything. I think over time, that might be something that we'll look at,
but it also might be something somebody might be able to look at better than us.
Your raisins one, by the way, is so funny because I've had a number of those experiences.
Similar to that one where I was shocked was grapes.
Oh, grapes are awful for glucose values, yes.
I had not eaten anything in about 18 hours.
You had grapes, but the glucose ants are on.
I had grapes, and I was so pissed off. I thought the thing was broken. I was ready to rip it off my
body. It was not.
It was like, there is no way my glucose is this high after. I haven't had a grape since. That was
about six months ago. Oh, that's funny.
I was on an airplane about a month ago, and they had a snack tray, and it was some cheese,
a strawberry, and some grapes. It had five grapes, and I was actually really hungry. I ate
everything, but I didn't eat the five grapes. I'm sure the five grapes wouldn't have done anything,
but I'm boycotting grapes. I am done with that, what I call quasi fruit.
Well, I have not eaten many yogurt-covered raisins since that episode in Boston either,
so there you go.
See, that's my point. I think CGM has the potential to change the way people eat more than
any other technology I have ever laid eyes on. I'm heavily biased. I've stated my bias many times.
I'm a very big proponent of CGM, but I also believe in real-time feedback. I think it's
very difficult to curb a person's behavior when the feedback loop is so long, and the weight on
the scale, the blood test that you get at your doctor every six months, those things are valuable.
They help, but nothing trumps the 30 minutes after I eat the chocolate-covered raisins.
A, I see what it looks like, and now I can correlate that feeling of, I feel like crap
an hour later because my glucose has gone from 200 to 60. That's a crappy feeling. That's not
physiologically reasonable, and now people see why. So over time, where this gets very interesting is
that core technology platform I talked about where we make products to perform well,
that patients will use, and that costs less, never goes away. But there's a software element to what
we do that we can change dramatically given the experience we want a patient to have
or that a patient needs. And again, I'll give you the perfect example. Our type 1 patients,
the alerts and the alarms at nighttime while they sleep, are absolutely critical.
But somebody with type 2 diabetes who's taking these compounds, that may not be as critical for
them, but what would be critical is an analysis at the end of the day where we complement somebody
on, gee, you kept your glucose within range extremely well, or insights as we look back,
what did you eat for dinner today? Or integrating the CGM data into a food database to whereby
you take pictures of what you eat over time, and when you go back, you look at that food and say,
wow, I ate those scrambled eggs this morning and my glucose values didn't go up. Maybe scrambled
eggs for breakfast is a good thing for me, and then you take a picture of pancakes. And the next
time you sit down to eat, if you take a picture of those pancakes, you get reminded, you know,
you had pancakes a month ago, and that may not have been the outcome that you're looking for.
And I think this is the kind of stuff neutrino is working on, and I agree with you. That stuff is so
powerful. I feel like, you know, people assume I know a lot about food because of, you know,
sort of the work I've done and the things I've talked about and written about. And,
but the reality of it is I'm still humbled by how much I don't know, because it's not just what you
eat, but it's the physiologic state you are in when you eat it. It's very different. What happens if
you eat a bowl of pasta after you've exercised, you know, 30 minutes after a hard workout versus,
you know, eating it after having not exercised. It's a very different glycemic response.
Stress. We've talked about this and it can't be understated. How much higher my glucose levels
are when my sleep is crappy? Oh, or the correlation between high glucose levels and crappy sleep.
Because if you go to bed with high glucose levels after eating a very high carb dinner,
I've seen a direct correlation between my sleep and my glucose values. Yeah. Personally. Anyway,
I can't make this case enough. Now we talked about there are a couple other companies out there that
are doing this. Is there any publicly available information that compares the performance and
fidelity of the Abbott product or the Medtronic product to your current product? We all have
accuracy tables in our user guides, but they're biased towards the way the companies want to
project themselves. We have studies that we've published comparing ours to the other products.
We maintain our performance all the time. Yeah. It's not subtle in my hands. I mean,
I've been pretty vocal about it. It's not a subtle difference. And it isn't. We perform
extremely well across all the range of glucose in the low and in the high range. I won't speak as
much to the other guys. Our patients know. Our patients know what a Dexcom is versus the others,
and we can live with that one. Do you think that you will be able to maintain performance as the
sensor gets smaller and smaller? So in other words, is there a day when there's going to be a one
millimeter sensor? So something that really doesn't even get into the interstitium, but is still sort
of in the dermis itself that can perform this well, or is there just a technical limit to being
able to do this without accessing interstitial fluid? For us today, we've only gone down to the
interstitial fluid. We have looked at technologies that would go down more shallow. We have within
our R&D group, an advanced technology group who looks at nothing but things like that. Our second
verily product, one of our goals is to have a shorter sensor and to make it smaller, but there
are complications of a shorter sensor. What did the membrane layers look like so you can get an
extended wear on a 14-day sensor? How's the electrochemical reaction on a 14, you know,
on a longer life sensor if it's shorter versus the one that we have now? So we go through a lot of
trial and error as we look at these things to determine what is the best combination
of all of these features. I think we'll have a shorter one. Right now, we're very comfortable
with the interstitial fluid. If the pain of insertion is effectively eliminated, which it is,
once it's in there, I don't actually know the difference between it being in me versus on the
yeah on the skin. And I've played with other sensors out there that there are some that are,
you know, as short as 400 microns. There's some very short ones. And we evaluate those technologies.
We look at them. One of the beautiful things of being a public company having resources is if we
saw one that we thought was remarkable, we'd talk to them and see if there's something we can do to
further it along. But right now we're comfortable with what we're doing and what we have.
Now another question I get asked a lot is why can't this be done optically? Why can't this be done
the way a pulse oximeter, where you put it on your finger. So for someone listening to this who
doesn't know what that is, but if you've ever had surgery or anything like that, when you're
under anesthesia, there's a little device they usually put on your finger or on your earlobe.
And using light, it's actually measuring or estimating the saturation of oxygen. And can't
we just do that to measure glucose? Are there limitations to this that are just too great?
It has been tried on numerous occasions to do that. Several technologies have tried non-invasive
sensors. In fact, the first glucose sensor that I saw somebody wear, other than one we developed at
many men and Medtronic was one called the Glucowatch, which actually was a watch that sat on your wrist
and would take fluid out of your skin through reverse anaphoresis and measure it that way.
Wow.
It would leave a red mark on the outside of your arm and it was hard. We've seen a lot of
non-invasive glucose sensors and people call our sensor invasive because there's a needle
that goes in your body and comes out in a sensor that remains. So oftentimes people say,
we're going to develop something that is non-invasive. If it's two inches by three inches
and sits on the outside of your body, you can say, yeah, it was non-invasive. Well,
how do you find invasive? To me invasive is does it invade your lifestyle and does it produce the
result that you're looking for? A lot of people have worked on that type of thing. They've worked
on just measuring on the skin. There's one company that has one that measures in your tears that you
put inside your eye that I've seen. Are these accurate? Not accurate enough and none of them
have been to market yet, but only time will tell. People will continue to look, but they're not
solving the fundamental problem. I'll go back to those three things we build our product around
and I'll add a fourth. If it's accurate, if you solve the accuracy problem, if you make it more
convenient and solve the convenient problem, if you lower the cost, and finally, if you can produce
a healthcare outcome, you have something that's meaningful. Well, not having the little wire in
your skin while one can try and paint a horse story around that, it's not really that invasive
to your body. So anything that comes has to solve one of those problems better than the
technologies that are on the market. And if somebody can do that with an infrared sensor,
optical sensor, then we've had a wonderful technological step and we'll all figure out
where we move from there. We just haven't seen anything yet that's accurate enough,
performs well enough. Yeah, I suspect it's going to depend heavily on how much this stuff matters
and meaning how much accuracy matters. Obviously for me and for my patients, that's the highest
priority in what you give up right now is cost. I think of the four metrics you just identified,
the place where this is by far the biggest barrier is the economic barrier. It's the economics,
I would agree. So on that thread, anyone listening to this who says, gosh, I got to have a CGM,
they have to go get a prescription from their doctor and very likely they're going to pay out
of pocket for it. Unless they have diabetes. Yeah. They have diabetes. Including type two?
Depends. A few payers cover type two, not many, but a few.
Do you have the liberty of saying which payers? Do you know which payers cover type two?
Not at the top of the head. Because it's going to depend by region as well.
It's very regional and most of the type two patients are patients who use intensive insulin,
such as the CMS Medicare patients. And this gets into our pair negotiations. Sometimes we sit and
we discuss, we want to make this easier for everyone to get. We want to cover type twos.
We want to cover type ones. We want all these things. And they go back to their economic models
and say, well, we can't do all those things, but we can give you this and we can give you this for
the type ones. And it is very much a business negotiation. And then based on your insurance
plan, typically our patients pay 20% of the cost, standard copay for durable medical equipment.
And depending upon the timing of the year, if you buy the first of the year and
their copayments and their deductibles have not been met, it's more expensive for them.
And is the cash cost fixed across the country or is that a regional?
We have cash prices here that are pretty much national.
You can say what the cash cost is.
I'll be honest with you, I don't even know what they are.
I should know this. My office does all the buying. The sensors come in boxes of threes, right?
Three centuries.
And we typically buy them nine at a time. So that's about a three month supply
because it's 10 days per cent. So that's 90 days. You know what? I used to do the math on what are
you paying per day? I'd amortize the whole thing over a per day cost. Does nine bucks a day sound
about right?
That's about right as to what somebody pays on the outside.
Yeah, I think that's what we pay. Nine or 10 bucks a day.
Between nine and $11 a day, we say on our earnings calls, for example, our average price per sensor
is X. We used to be only seven day sensors. So our average price is always between 70 and $75
that we have recognized in our revenue. Our 10 day sensor, we have different models as we've
gotten that reimbursed. That cost per day has to come down.
What do you think, or have you guys done an internal analysis that says, look,
at this point, this is a product where if we have 1% of the population has type 2 diabetes,
you've obviously built a very successful company where your customer base is 1% of the US population
or less. You've got a type 2 diabetes population that I think would benefit from this as much as
the type 1 population would, even though, as you've pointed out eloquently, different diseases,
basically. So that takes you to 10% of the population. Then you've got the pre-diabetic
population. Another 10.
Exactly. But then you've got like sort of half the people are kind of, I hate the term wellness,
but these are people that we're trying to optimize health for and they don't have a disease, but it's
not just that we're trying to prevent them from getting diabetes, but we're trying to figure out
if you can actually make them live longer through better glycemic control. What do you think or
what's your intuition about what does that need to cost per day to make that group say, look, out
of pocket, I'm going to pay for this because there's no way an insurance company is going to pay for
healthy people wearing these things.
We drive those discussions all the time. It's interesting. I had a discussion with a payer
once and I said, look, we want this to go to everybody that uses insulin intensively.
Tell me what the price is. Just tell me what to make it. Give me a number.
And the response I got was how low would you go? So I don't know what a person would pay out of
pocket because all we do is speculate on these kinds of things. Is it $25 for a two week sensor?
Is it $50 for a two week sensor? A lot would depend upon the information and the things that
you learn from it. There's a whole regulatory process we'll have to go through to get a health
and wellness product. For example, our device is a prescription device. Now we've been very clear
in our discussions, your patients who use this in its non-diabetic state, they have a prescription
from you and you pay cash for that. And we write them a new prescription every three months. And
they get it. To make this a non-prescription product, there's a lot of steps we'd have to go
through at the FDA. And one of the things that we look at with respect to our human factors and
our software design, if it were non-prescription, what would that software experience have to look
like? So let's explain to the listener why that's the case. So right now, everything we've talked
about, as you said, is still a medical device. It is a class two medical device. A physician
writes a prescription. And I'm only just talking about the cash patients. So this is not about
insurance anymore. Physician writes prescription, patient gets it filled, and they're all in cost,
is about nine bucks a day to wear this thing. And they are seeing the exact same data using the
exact same device with the exact same algorithms that a patient would type one diabetes. And the
exact same app. Yeah, the exact same software. Everything is the same. I am using everything
that someone with type one diabetes is using. So explain, Kevin, why if tomorrow a little elf
jumped out of your desk and said, voila, we can make this thing for a dollar. And just say that
the dollar was the price where like at a dollar a day, you could penetrate this new market.
That the FDA doesn't say, great, go ahead, go start selling it. Like there's a
fundamental issue. What is that issue? We have to go through clinical trials,
particularly if we're labeled for use for people with diabetes, to demonstrate the accuracy and
consistency of the product across all glucose ranges. The FDA and Ocander has been very
progressive with Dexcom. I mean, we're the first company ever to go directly to the phone. We're
the first company to share data. We're the first company ever to have a sensor perform at the
accuracy levels that we have. Most every first with the FDA in our industry has come to us
partnering with them. Most recently, they created a new category for continuous glucose
monitoring. And this is the intensive diabetes world called ICGM versus CGM, where they set
accuracy standards, where the products have to demonstrate on a statistical basis, they perform,
and you have to have a certain number of values in a study in a low range, in the high range,
in a certain number of points to statistically prove that that product is capable of doing the
things that we want it to do. In our intensive world, that's dosing insulin, either through a
manual calculation or thinking by a patient. But also with this ICGM category, which stands for
interconnected, we can connect to other devices. And they've made an easier path for other devices
to connect to our product. So for example, if you have an insulin pump in an algorithm,
and would like to run that algorithm, a glucose sensor, your regulatory path with Dexcom
is just to show you get the signal, you don't have to do a study to show the Dexcom is accurate,
we're done, it's interconnected. And Tandem's recent approval is along those lines. But if
you're displaying a glucose value, and that is a real time glucose value, and that is where we've
been at our discussions with the FDA, that's a class two medical device. And as of today,
that requires a prescription. At some point in time, again, as we look to the future, and as you
and I have talked, I'd like a device we could sell over the counter, or we could sell through
nutrition programs that a patient couldn't use to dose insulin, but what would be the real time
feedback you'd give somebody? Explain why that's necessary. That's what you just said is the
important point, which is if you want to sell this over the counter, the FDA is going to say,
it cannot be used by someone to dose insulin for today. For today, and maybe that will change over
time, but for now, those are the rules. And those are the rules that we play by. And that's very
important for people to understand, because that's one of the questions I get asked the most, which is,
why can't this thing just be over the counter now? I'm willing to pay the full price. Why do I have to?
Because not every patient has a physician who understands the benefit of this. And I know,
just from what I see on social media, a lot of people go to their doctor and say,
hey, you know, Dr. So-and-so, please write me the prescription. And he or she says,
what the hell for? Get out of here. Yeah, what are you talking about? Yeah. And so now that patient,
who's actually says, look, I'm willing to make an enormous investment in this because it's my health
and I believe that this is going to matter. Well, they can't do it. So what I'm hearing you say is,
there's one regulatory path that says maybe down the road, the FDA says, you know what?
This will no longer be something that requires a prescription. If the patient's willing to pay for
it, the patient can have it. I can't speak for them, but they have been so progressive with us
so far. What we would literally have to present again, is a case as to how somebody would never
harm themselves. And remember, there's a needle involved in inserting our product as well. There
may be standards and rules around needles, things like that. So I can't speculate how we get there.
But I think over time, that's something we would like to take on. But again, it would not be a
device used for diabetes treatment, it would be a device used for other things. We'll have to
figure out what that looks like. We don't know yet. And what you were alluding to a moment ago
was the other option for making this OTC is not to take the same device and just deal with the
FDA changing a rule, but it's to create a device that would fit into the current sort of regulatory
environment, which says the device would basically have to be dumbed down. You'd basically have to
strip functionality out of the device, right? Strip functionality and the user experience,
yeah. Not necessarily accuracy, not performance, but strip down the information that's presented
to the individual. So the ways that that can be done is one, you could make it such that they
don't get real time information. Because if you don't have real time information, if you see the
perfectly accurate identical data a day later, doesn't help you dose insulin. Another way is,
as you said, you just show ranges. Colors, the circles on your Apple Watch. I don't wear one
of those things, but I know you don't. You and I both like to wear our regular watches. I do wear
Apple, the Apple Watch frequently just to see what the user experience is. Okay. So what are the
circles? What are the circles? It's for training. You track your, how many times you stand up,
how many steps you take a day. They have some very simple measures. It's right there. It's pretty easy
to see and very easy to use. This is a totally unrelated question. Does the Apple Watch have a
little app or plugin that allows you to put the face of really cool watches on it so that you,
like if you really want to have a paddock, you could have like a little paddock Apple Watch.
Because that would be easy to do. You just need a picture of the paddock and you could have it like
looking like a, you know, your pick your favorite GMT, you know, or whatever. See Peter, we start
talking and it gets back to watches and other businesses we'd like to go start and do. I don't,
I don't know that that exists, but that would be fun. Who, why haven't Apple is your listening to this?
Maybe somebody has. Yeah, someone's got to develop the plugin that allows you to have
any watch you want as your Apple Watch. Apple Watch has cost what, a few hundred bucks? Yeah.
But you could put the face of a million dollar watch on it if you want. Well, and what we have
found within our company and with our patient base, there's a very high number of Apple Watch users
because our device goes from the phone and then the phone there's a watch app. Also, I didn't even,
because I don't use the thing I've never noticed. Yeah, there is a watch app and then we are
developing a direct to watch transmitter communication protocol. What that would do
for a patient, again, the new Apple watches have cellular capability as well, as will some of the
Android watches and some of the new Fitbit products. But with that direct cell capability,
that watch then can become a patient's receiver and the data could still be shared. You wouldn't
have to have it go to your phone. And again, we're thinking about those criteria talked to you about
earlier, as far as convenience, it's a lot easier for some of our people to pull their sleeve up and
look at their glucose than to get their phone out during an important meeting or to even take their
phone to bed, make it where they're watched to bed. Well, that's another new thing I like about the
G6 a lot. We didn't talk about this. With the G5, I had to keep my phone in my room to see all my
nighttime data. The G6 seems to store the data so that if I keep my phone in the office, it backloads
my file. There is some backloading if you do lose connectivity. The transmission range of our product,
I believe it's labeled for 20 feet. And if we've learned one thing about going to the phone,
Bluetooth is not an exact size. And I think we've all experienced that where some headphones connect
really well, other headphones do not. Sometimes you get your car, it works. Sometimes it doesn't,
it is very hard to explain. But is that why you went with Bluetooth as opposed to near field
communication? We went with Bluetooth because we didn't want our patients to have to put the phone
close to the device. We wanted the continuous feed. I think there is a place for near field
and it's quite possible we'd have both chips in a future one. But for now, we're very BLE oriented
and it works pretty well. Are there any, and again, I want to be sensitive to what you can
and can't talk about publicly. Are there any other partnerships or collaborations that you're able to
speak about that are maybe interesting to consumers, especially in this sort of non-diabetes,
non-type one, non-type two market for the people like me who are thinking about this for quote unquote
wellness. Well, nothing real concrete. I will tell you that Apple has been a wonderful partner for us
in getting the device to the iPhone and getting our apps working on Apple watch. In fact, at the
developer conference one year, we got a VIP invitation. Our head of R&D couldn't go. So I
went and Peter and I addressed differently. I'm total business person and Peter's Peter. And so
I show up at the Apple developer conference in my sport code in my shoes. And of course,
the guys next to me are in shorts and they're way younger than me. And they're looking at me like,
who's this? Who's this? Nobody dresses like this here. And I'm sitting there feeling pretty
uncomfortable. And they came out and talked about Apple watch. And lo and behold, Apple's got
Dexcom watch on the screen. Wow. Up there. And I, I elbowed the kid next to me. I said,
you see that? He said, yeah, I said, I run that company. I thought I was pretty, pretty special
for the day. Our partnership with Verily includes work with a company that they have called on Duo
that is developing treatment for type two diabetes and developing apps that combine everything
they've learned about diabetes with a lot of Google technology. And they're in pilot phases
with various payers on the type two side. We're also doing a lot of work with United Healthcare.
On type two diabetes. And I think in the future with them, we're also going to develop some
prediabetes models as we take this gen six technology out. You know, we talked about going
to the consumer. Peter, you wouldn't have taken G5 to a consumer anywhere. It's too hard.
Yeah. I had a hard time getting patients to do the G5.
G6 is, it's not all the way there, but it's close. There are things we can do to make a little bit
easier like pairing the device with the transmitter and some of the other things that have been
inherent within our system. But it's close. As we get this thing closer to consumers,
I think you'll see us try more things, more in different things. A couple of other applications
where we'd love to take our continuous glucose monitoring technology where it's not.
I've had numerous physicians ping me on LinkedIn saying, why aren't you in the hospital?
Why aren't you in the hospital?
That's a good question. Why aren't you in the ICU of all places, right?
We tried many years ago. We had a joint venture with Edwards Life Sciences. And then the FDA was
extremely strict on accuracy and performance. And by the time we built what we built, it just,
it didn't work out. Our technology has come so far and we've learned so much through projects
like that in the past that we will make a run with G6 in that type of market to help patients.
Think about it. You connect the Bluetooth to the nurses station. I was in one medical center
where patients in the ICU are tested every 30 minutes, 48 finger sticks in a 24 hour period.
Not uncommon. Intensive insulin therapy, of course, has had its ups and downs,
resurgence in the literature, in the critical care literature. But basically there was a paper
that came out in 2001 or 2002 in the New England Journal of Medicine that really changed the face
of how glucose and insulin levels were managed or glucose levels were managed using intensive
insulin therapy in the ICU. That has been questioned. Obviously there have been subsequent
trials that have suggested that, you know, maybe the benefits on the glucose side come at the cost
or the insulin side, et cetera. But you're absolutely right. Now that reminds me of something
though, which is acetaminophen. Tylenol has an effect on the performance, at least of the G5.
Not G6.
Oh, it doesn't have the effect anymore.
That does not affect G6. We ran a very, very, very large study and put a lot of acetaminophen
into patients to whereby we have no contraindication for acetaminophen anymore.
So that's interesting, but the G5 would over or under?
It would go high.
It would overestimate.
It would go up a little bit.
Yeah. So one of the challenges I suspect in the ICU patient is all of the drugs that they're on,
also the third space like crazy. So their interstitium looks totally different from a
normal person's interstitium. It's almost like there's a whole new calibration, right?
We're going to have to go run some studies. But that being said,
I'll go back to what you said your friend told you, you can pay me now or pay me later.
If we can get this in the right configuration in the hospital on most every patient,
at least every patient over 50 that comes in, forget whether or not I have diabetes,
that hyperglycemia effect on healing we know is a very difficult thing.
If we can get it on everybody and make this affordable and fit within the normal workflow
of the hospital, that's a tremendous market for us. Another place we haven't been or been labeled,
and you're going to be a little bit, probably chastise me after this. We've never been labeled
for gestational diabetes. We had this discussion once.
I didn't realize you weren't actually labeled, but I have a patient whose fiance is pregnant,
and she had a device in and it turned out she had an old device. So she had the device and then
never used it with one pregnancy, then used it with another and it wasn't working.
We did some troubleshooting and to make a long story short, she said,
I called Dexcom, but they said it's not approved for gestational use. I remember saying,
what would be the difference? I'm very proud of my people for saying the right thing.
We haven't run a study in gestational diabetes. We'll have to run a study there to get that label.
One of my daughters-in-law contracted gestational diabetes while pregnant with twins.
So her OBGYN wrote a script and we procured a Dexcom for her.
He just looked at it and said, this is remarkable. We should all be on this.
This gets back to A1C and other measures. As we look at evolving this Gen 6 technology,
one of the things that we look at is this product that's a diagnostic as well.
Right now, you drink that real sugary drink, go way high, you go way low. It's kind of awful.
What about a blinded sensor on somebody for a week?
Infinitely better.
And then develop the algorithms to see what we can predict with respect to gestational diabetes.
Those are the type of studies that we want to run in the future and the way we'd like to go about
that market. And there's others as well. Again, I'll go back to your health and wellness one.
Combining this with some of the nutrition apps out there, the Weight Watchers app,
combining. If that had glucose data and you ate your points per day and you ate your 32 points
today, but your glucose values were still high, maybe we take you down to 26 and vice versa.
You can see how that can integrate with it wonderfully and integrate without
showing a glucose value that you can dose insulin off of.
I just think in the end, it's a much better metric for health. And I think health matters
more than weight. Weight is correlated with health, but the correlation is not exceptional.
It's reasonable, but it's so far from great. And my prediction would be when those trials are done,
your standard deviation of blood glucose over a three month period is going to tell you infinitely
more than whatever the fluctuations were in your weight. And it's frankly going to help you
identify probably the type of weight that matters more. Obviously there's been a big
discussion about the difference between subcutaneous fat and visceral fat. You could have two people
that weigh exactly the same and you could even have two people that have a similar mass of fat.
But where that fat resides probably tells us much more about their metabolic health. So I don't know.
Like I said, if I could be czar of whatever for a day, I just don't see why I wouldn't want someone
to have this information continuously in real time, every minute of every day under any physiologic
circumstance, because what you learn, and not just someone who's got type two diabetes or type one
diabetes or gestational diabetes, it's going to alter your baby. It comes back to the airport
stories when we're in these environments that are at our worst. And you learn other really
interesting things. I mean, you get a sense of how much even exercise can transiently raise your
blood glucose, but what the benefits are after the fact, which is your ability to dispose of glucose
goes up significantly. Yeah, I get about a 30 point spike in a workout, but for the rest of the day,
my average glucose is about 10 points lower. Yeah, it's so amazing to think that such a simple
biomarker is glucose, something we take for granted on every chemistry test we do on patients. You
know, no one goes to their doctor and doesn't get their glucose measured, but what the utility of
that is when you can measure it every five minutes. Kevin, this has been super interesting. I want to
be respectful of your time. I know we don't have all day here and you have to get back to work. One
of the stories you just told that I love so much that I didn't know was the going to the pharmacy,
getting three of these things and poking yourself 60 times. To me, that's like, you know, Dexcom is
a pretty big public company. Your market cap's like what, 12 billion? 12 billion dollars. Yeah.
And, but yet you're still kind of a startup company. Oh, that's a startup CEO move.
It really is. And I've had to learn to be less startup as we've grown. We've all grown with the
company. But that culture, and again, one of the things that I manage as CEO here,
is we've had to bring in skills and supplement our management team from that startup mentality
to the mid-size company mentality to whereby we have more structure and systems of a large company.
So we're trying to mix all of those things together. We just had our employee survey and
it's interesting. I read every comment. It's almost 200 pages of comments. I read everything,
all the employees write, the good ones, the bad ones, and the funny ones. I will not quote the
funny ones, but there, there, there's some pretty hilarious things people say. The most contradicting
comments are we all need to go back to being a startup versus we need more structure to be bigger.
And both are true. Both are true. The, the nimbleness of a startup in an industry where you're
creating everything is absolutely essential. You've got to remain nimble. You've got to be
willing to fail. You've got to be willing to start over. You got to be willing to do what's right.
Conversely, that big company structure where you have systems and, and balances and checks to make
sure you're doing the right thing and you start watching dollars more is a different culture.
So we're mixing those two together. We're kind of like a mixed family here.
We will have added more than 1500 employees in the last two years.
Wow. I didn't realize you were that big.
I was employee three, about 300 in 2011. I think we have 2500 full-time employees and
several hundred attempts. We do a lot of our manufacturing work, attempt to hire and bring
them in and grow and, and shrink with volume. They were the temporary workforce, but no,
we have that many people.
Can I add one more question for your internal survey that I think will produce awesome,
interesting results. Every month have a, or every quarter or whatever frequency makes sense,
have a tell us your best surprise glucose spike story. Because I mean, honestly, this,
the grapes, the stupid chocolate covered M&Ms, whatever, I mean, I think, I mean, there's going
to be the obvious ones. Like I ate a bag of Swedish fish. Look what happened to my blood sugar.
But there's these surprise ones either in the velocity of glucose escape or the peak. Because
I'm guessing most of your employees are wearing these things, right?
No, no, no, no, no, there's too many of us.
There's actually impact production.
There's too many of us now. But you know, if we run an internal study under IRB protocol and
everything, we will recruit volunteers within the company. We have several people at Type 1
diabetes that work here because they can lend us a perspective for our patients that we don't have
on our own. So that's important to us as well. A lot of it, where I'm in a lot of the things that
we learn are through those in-house studies and through that in-house wear process.
You said something a second ago about failing quickly. You have five kids, right?
I have five sons.
And just before we were getting ready to start, we were talking about our kids. And you asked me
if I wanted some advice on being a parent to which I couldn't say no, of course I did. Do you
remember the advice you gave me?
I do. And I was recounting a story of how things have changed. There's a big gap. My oldest is 15
years older than my youngest. And there's an eight year gap between number four and number
five. But what I told you is we can't be afraid to let our kids fail. I know I'm going to sound
horribly mean, but everybody getting a ribbon and everybody getting a trophy. I once told a coach to
cut my son so he would learn something. If he wasn't going to play him, go ahead and do that.
We learn in life as much from our failures as we do our successes. Sometimes we learn more
and sometimes they motivate us to be great and motivate us to do great things.
But we oftentimes as parents shelter our kids so much from that, what appears to be traumatic.
And I'd given that advice to somebody who didn't have any children. And he came in my office,
he goes, give me one bit of advice. And I said, all right, I'll give it to you. Because we just
try and manage and regulate everything so much all the time. And look, I will tell you with number
five, I did a lot more of that than I did with number one. Number one would tell you that I was
very tough on him, but I let him carve his own way. And it's a good thing to let him learn.
Last question, Kevin, is there a failure that you point to in your professional life,
leading up to where you are today that has taught you more than the others about what you're doing
now? Boy, that is a great question. I wouldn't tell you one in particular, at a corporate level,
I'm going to go big picture. I was at one company where I knew exactly what to do. And
it was really the only course of action that would have made that company successful.
And I presented it to my board and they said no. And I then rolled up my sleeves and worked
hard for several months and several months and several months. And I still got the answer, no.
And I finally left after beating my head up against the wall. And that taught me a lot of
lessons. Number one, to be better prepared and how I give my message. And I attribute
fires like that to me. I don't blame the others. To be better prepared on how I deliver my message,
to be more thoughtful. But if the situation isn't going to work out and what I ended up doing,
and my wife would tell you this, my commute was five miles at the time. It's the most miserable
I've ever been in my entire life. She would look at me and say, what on earth are you doing? I'm
going to fix this. I'm going to get this. And I couldn't win. So I left and that's the one time
where it felt like I didn't get done what we could have got completed. But I didn't see all
the signs on the wall. So I've looked at ways I can be better from that. When I see something
strategic like that, I do more homework. We have the people around us do more homework. We're more
thoughtful. So that's one of them. We've all had numerous little failures. Sometimes, again,
our failures are our biggest blessings. I would say the failure that's been my biggest blessing
are all the jobs I didn't take. Because you get opportunities and you get mesmerized with an
opportunity. I mean, you can go do this. And countless times in my life, those didn't work out.
And then lo and behold, an opportunity comes along and it's, wow, I'm so glad that didn't work out.
And then you learn so much from that. Now, and I would say the other thing that's important as far
as success, you're only as good as those people that are around you. And it becomes clear and
clear to me the longer I work. This team we have here at Dexcom, they are committed, they work hard.
We are all engaged in our business each and every day. I never go to a meeting with another company
where their people are as engaged in what they do as ours.
Well, that's an interesting point to end on because I do think that Dexcom, obviously,
I'm very biased. I've been very, very vocal about my bias to Dexcom over the other
two Abbott and Medtronic. But I think you guys have an advantage that on the one hand is a
disadvantage. Let's be honest, diversification. Those companies have a million products to fall
back on. CGM is but one of a hundred things they do. But that disadvantage is actually your biggest
advantage, which is everybody shows up to, and I feel like I know half the staff here. I'm here so
often shooting the breeze with you. There's something to be said for, what's the expression?
You burn your ships, right? That's right. Yeah, you guys have burned your ships. You're all in on CGM.
We are. Well, Kevin, I want to thank you very much for your time, for your insights and for your
friendship. It's been amazing to think that we met on that airplane almost three, four years ago.
And to this day, we managed to do a good job of not talking watches this whole thing. Once we turn
the recording off, I want to talk to you about the one I'm wearing right now, which I think you're
going to love. It is beautiful. Yeah, thank you. I wore it today because I knew I was going to see you.
Okay. This is what watch idiots do. We do like show and tell. Does your wife make fun of you as well?
Oh, it's ridiculous. Now I've learned a good trick, which is you start giving your wife nice watches,
and she now understands and appreciates like why a Daytona is a nice watch and what Paul Newman
meant and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, and all these other things. So now she's a little bit more
tolerant of my nonsense. All right. All right, Kevin, have a great afternoon. Thank you, Peter.
Thanks so much for your time. We'll see you. You can find all of this information and more
at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There you'll find the show notes, readings,
and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest
thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week email, where I'll update
you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read, and all things related to
longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram,
and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to
share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for
general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine,
nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials
linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not intended to be
a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not
disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should
seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.