Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia. The drive
is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking, along
with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession
with this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information
is basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their
lives. Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the
podcast, that became clear to me. The sheer volume of material published in this space
is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing
this information with you. To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own.
In fact, we now have a full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and their
feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural question. How will we continue
to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know, the tried and true way
to do this is to sell ads, but after a lot of contemplation, that model just doesn't
feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know
I'm being paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling
ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time
advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about
something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically. So instead of selling
ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can work over time, and
that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience. This keeps my relationship
with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and
support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above
and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my goal to ensure that no
matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more than you give.
So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes, including
other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each episode.
These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many
of our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular
Ask Me Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and
also getting to hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm
really excited about, I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products
that I love. And as I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd
like to do is work with companies who make the products that I already love and would
already talk about for free and have them pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast
will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will find enough value in one,
the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members to support us
at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider
supporting us directly by signing up for a monthly subscription.
I guess this week is Dr. Jason Fung. Jason is a nephrologist in Toronto, Canada. Many
of you listening to this podcast probably already are at least familiar with him just
if for another reason through social media or other channels. He's quite a vocal critic
of the conventional approach to treating type two diabetes. And he also has, in my experience,
at least one of the most significant clinical practices that utilizes fasting as a treatment
for metabolic disease. Known Jason relatively informally for quite a while, but I've gotten
to know him better in the past year and was really looking forward to doing this interview
because I certainly get asked a lot of questions that I think Jason would have great insight
into. He's the author of several books, including The Obesity Code, The Diabetes Code, The Complete
Guide to Fasting, and The Longevity Solution. He's the co-founder of the Intensive Dietary
Management Program. Jason graduated from the University of Toronto and completed his residency
at UCLA. In this episode, we talk about a lot. We actually kick it off with a discussion
I didn't plan to get into, but I thought it was really interesting and I hope you do as
well about evidence-based medicine and the difference between taking two scientific disciplines,
one of medicine biology, the other of physics and comparing and contrasting some of the differences.
I sort of make an argument around theoretical versus experimentalist and things like that.
I'm going to talk a little bit about nephrology. What took Jason into that field and why is
being a nephrologist, a doctor who specializes in kidney disease, why does that give him
a quite unique insight into kind of the early indications of metabolic disease? Then we
get into the meat of this thing, which honestly, I think this is one of the most interesting
discussions I've ever had on insulin resistance. You'll listen to this podcast. You've heard
me talk about that a lot. I think Jason's take on this quite frankly is probably the
smartest thing I've heard. Now, that doesn't mean that I necessarily agree with everything
and that doesn't mean that there aren't holes in these arguments, but his explanation for
why a concept of insulin resistance, which is very difficult to explain when you try
to parse it out into tissue specific effects of insulin, he has a much better explanation
for this that clinically makes more sense and ultimately results in a much more logical
treatment plan.
Once we go through this discussion of what people call insulin resistance and come away
with this idea of hyperinsulinemia, for which by the way, he has a great example using a
suitcase that I'd never heard before, but I took the liberty of bolting onto it as much
as possible. By the end of this, you might be sick of hearing about suitcases. We talk
a little bit about NAFLD and then we close the discussion. If there's sort of a final
part of this, it's getting into the clinical stuff, the use of dietary restriction, including
ketogenic diets, carbohydrate restriction, but most of what we talk about pertains to
fasting. I think that that's where a lot of people are going to be kind of interested.
Jason has a very different approach to fasting than I do in my practice. I think that probably
stems from the fact that I'm not treating patients who are nearly as sick as Jason.
In that sense, he has to be a little bit more extreme out of the gate and to listen to some
of the clinical wisdom that he brings to this is even for me quite informative. I hope
you enjoy this discussion with Jason half as much as I did.
There are so many things I want to talk about with you. I would say that you are among the
three people, top three certainly, that on social people are always saying, when are
you going to interview Jason? When are you going to interview Jason? Of course, we had
planned to do this in December in person. That's when I had my whole dental calamity
that required tooth extraction after secondary tooth extraction. I never made it up. Anyway,
I'm glad we could do this and I appreciate everyone's patience with this. I guess the
broader point is I think people are so interested in speaking because of all the work you've
done around fasting, insulin resistance, and just overall, you're a clinician on the front
lines. It's one thing to pontificate on Twitter. It's quite another thing when you actually
have to show up in clinic and see hundreds of patients as you do.
Thanks. I think that's one of the things that I think distinguishes me from some of
the other people that are out there is that the stuff's got to work. Otherwise, it just
ain't worth it. You can talk all you want about this and that, but if it doesn't change
management, then it doesn't interest me particularly because that's where I come from. I think
this is where a lot of people get sort of, they see these academics and they say, okay,
well, they know everything about this. It's like, well, they might know everything, but
if it doesn't work on the front lines, it's not worth anything. I think this is an attitude
I see in physics, which is, I know you really look up to Richard Feynman as do I, but I
actually love the whole story of Einstein and Niels Bohr and all that because physics
to me is sort of like, I love that because the way they do science is so much better
than we do in medicine. That is to say for in this specific instance, for example, if
you have all these theories, they're great, but if they don't agree with experimental
evidence, it ain't worth anything. They say this in physics, but they don't say this in
medicine where it's like, okay, you think that eating lots of carbs is really good for
you. You have this hypothesis that eating less fat and tons and tons of refined carbs
is good for you. That's a great theory. It all makes sense. The same thing with calories.
It sounds like if you just cut calories, it makes sense, but if your theory doesn't work,
then it's not a good theory. This is what they say in physics, which they don't say
in medicine. In medicine, it always boggles my mind how these bad theories go round and
round and round because they make sense, but nobody's actually put them to the test or
nobody's pointing out these things. It's the same with insulin resistance. I think actually,
to me, the most important topic is insulin resistance because, again, that's what I deal
with as a nephrologist. I see a lot of type 2 diabetes. That, to me, is completely misunderstood,
and the way we think about insulin resistance is totally wrong, and that's why we have the
mess that we have, I think. Well, we're going to get to that for certain.
I'd definitely like to build on what you've said. Yeah, there's a beautiful demonstration
of what you described. It's a video from either Caltech or Cornell, I can't recall.
It was either right before he had left Cornell or after he had arrived at Caltech, where
Feynman is at a blackboard, and he is explaining the scientific method in about as elegant
a way as you can, which is to basically say what you did, which is this is the scientific
method. You make a guess. You design an experiment to test the consequences of that guess. You
do the experiment, and if the output of that experiment aligns with your guess, the hypothesis
turns out to be likely correct or more likely to be correct, and if it doesn't, you go back
to the drawing board. The simplicity with which one of the most brilliant physicists
of the 20th century explains that is not lost on anyone who watches it. I would agree with
you completely. I've gotten into trouble by saying this before, but I guess on your podcast
you can sort of say what you want. I'm generally suspect of people who have very, very strong
points of view on things in biology or medicine who no longer interact with patients. It doesn't
mean that they're wrong, but I'm generally suspect because of that, because the other
thing is biology is harder than physics. The reality of it is just a lot messier, and sometimes
people ask me, do you think you'll always see patients? The answer is yes, I think so,
and I hope so, because they are kind of a humbling tool. Every time I think I've really
got it figured out, I'll always meet a patient who proves me wrong, and they're obviously
right and I'm wrong.
I think the other part about physics, which I love, is that the way they think about it
is that there's a theory, like Newton has a theory, for example, and it explains a lot.
There's a great theory and everything, but then there's these anomalies, and the anomalies
are what drives science forward because you have to come up with a better theory that
explains the anomalies. If you come up with a better theory, they make these wild predictions,
and if these wild predictions are true, you know this new theory can sort of supplant
it, so the way Niels Bohr and the Qantas supplanted Einstein, even though he was brilliant.
The point is that that doesn't happen in medicine. In medicine, we have this super laborious
process of evidence-based medicine, where instead of saying, hey, here's a theory that
makes more sense because it explains everything, what they do is they say every single point,
they go, where's the evidence? Where's the evidence? Where's the evidence? That's why
nothing ever moves forward. I do the same thing in nephrology that I did 20 years ago
when I was doing my training. It's like, what was the last advance we had? It's like
so from so long a word. Most of the advances in medicine, for example, come from aspirin.
It counts for like 50% of the progress we've made. It's sort of ridiculous, whereas physics
sort of moves at light speed because they don't demand this sort of evidence-based.
I always say that evidence-based medicine is good if you know how to apply it, because
the whole point of evidence-based medicine is that it's not a search for truth, it's
a search for consensus. It may or may not be true, but if you have a crazy theory and
then you send it out to five people and they say, well, it's crazy, it gets killed. If
you have a theory, hey, the Earth goes around the sun, not the sun goes around the Earth.
You send it to a consensus of peers, they say, no, no, no, no. Clearly the sun revolves
around the Earth, that would never have made it through. The evidence-based medicine is
not everything. You have to understand where to apply it. This is where I think we've gotten
into so much trouble is that every sort of advance moves glacially because we sort of
demand that things have to have evidence. Something like fasting, for example, which
I always get into trouble a lot too. I get into tons of trouble for calories, everybody
tax me for all kinds of stuff, but fasting five years ago was the dumbest thing you could
do. I'm like, why? It doesn't make any sense that it should be so bad. I thought about
it and I went through it and then I just brought it immediately to patients. Just treated hundreds
and hundreds and hundreds of patients and the results, amazing. Of course, if you don't
eat, you're going to lose weight. If you don't eat, your diabetes is going to get better.
It worked and that was the point. You got to get to that point where it's like, and
then everybody says to me, oh, where's the evidence? I'm like, why do I need evidence?
People are getting better. I'm not a researcher. You can come up with the research, but just
try it on people. Look at it. All these people were saying, oh, there's no evidence. There's
no evidence. Clearly it's bad. That's where everything just sort of bogs down. You get
all these people who sort of demand that every sort of little step has to be based
on consensus. The consensus moves so slowly that you can't move. You can't move like Einstein
moved. You can't make those sort of intuitive leaps forward. That always bothers me a lot.
Well, it's sort of a problem. There is a distinction, right? In physics, I think broadly speaking,
and again, physicists will sort of bristle at the simplicity with which I'm saying this,
but you can generally divide the field into the experimentalists and the theorists. That's
what I think allows the step function changes and understanding. Einstein's advances were
theoretical. The experimental evidence to support these things came after, but yes,
many times the big steps forward come on the basis of theoretical propositions. We don't
really have that in medicine and biology. We don't have experimentalists and theorists.
I've thought a lot about this actually, and I didn't intend to go down that rabbit hole,
but there's a whole separate podcast, by the way, on this topic of how could you change
biological research to take some of the advantages that we see in the physical sciences where you
can create a symbiosis between the theorists and the experimentalists. The last thing I'll say on
this point, by the way, that I agree with you is the real challenge of exclusively relying on
evidence-based medicine is that framework is very good for certain problems. It's actually quite
good for problems that are rather acute, for which the interventions to address them are rather simple,
and for which you will get an answer quickly. So in many ways, the pillar of evidence-based
medicine is infectious disease. If you think about how much we have learned through evidence-based
medicine with respect to the treatment of HIV and frankly, most infections, it's remarkable. I mean,
we've really got that dialed in. But again, if you take a step back and look at those criteria,
well, infections are quite acute typically, very easy and binary to measure progression. The
interventions are simple. Take this medication, don't take this medication. That's much more
complicated than, well, I want you to exercise a certain way for this period of time or I want
you to eat a certain diet for a certain period of time. And then the resolution can be to whatever
metric it is, whether it be T cell count or amelioration of the clinical infection. That
occurs really quickly. So you're right. I mean, I think evidence-informed medicine is probably a
better way to think about it. But yeah, someone like you is, you know, you're really on the forefront
of using your best ethical judgment to say, look, I'm going to bring something to a patient population.
The other thing I want to add, by the way, while I'm on my soapbox that you helped me stand up on
to is people are very quick to say, well, you don't have the evidence to support fasting for a patient
with type 2 diabetes. And you can say, okay, that's true. So there is a risk that if this patient with
type 2 diabetes goes on a fasting protocol, something bad could happen. But what people in
medicine I find are very, I wouldn't even say quick to forget, I don't even think it registers,
is what's the risk of not doing something? The risk of doing something is usually more in our
forefront. It's that risk of not doing something that people often forget. And if the risk of not
doing something is stay the course, slowly, slowly increase the amount of insulin this patient
requires, slowly, slowly watch the micro and macroscopic vascular disease progress. Well,
that risk's actually, that's a pretty bad risk. Well, that's absolutely true. And it's like,
this is the point that I always made to patients is like, if you keep on doing what it is that most
doctors do, including myself, right? I used to just give people tons and tons of insulin. I know
what is going to happen. And everybody acknowledges that you'll just get worse over time. And it was
just sort of accepted as like, there's the risk of not doing anything, right? But if you suddenly
change, you know, bring an intervention like fasting or low carbohydrate diets, ketogenic diets,
or whatever, there's a risk of doing it. Sure, we don't know what the risks are. But you know,
the risk of not doing something, and that's the virtual certainty that you're going to in 10 years,
go on dialysis or something like that, right? And that's not an insignificant risk. It's actually
a huge risk compared to doing fasting, which has been done for thousands of years. And I always say
like, look, like the problem with evidence based medicine and consensus and stuff, look at look at
what happened with the low carb guidelines. So as you know, a couple days ago, the American Diabetes
Association came out with sort of new guidelines, and they said, Hey, low carbohydrates pretty
reasonable. It has the most evidence behind it. It's like five years ago, they're persecuting
dieticians for giving low carb advice, right? It's like, you know, our human body hasn't changed in
the five years that it took for you to realize that, right? And that's where you're doing patients
a real disservice by having these sort of expert opinions, guidelines, right, where people can't
decide for themselves. Like as a dietician, you can't decide for yourself that you want to be low
carb because five years ago, they would have run you out and persecuted you, right? Taking away
your license. And today, like as of sort of two days ago, you're actually falling completely within
American Diabetes Association guidelines, right? So it's like, this is a big problem.
The flip side, I guess that's progress. And we'll take it right. You know, I've said this before.
It's sort of one of my little tongue in cheek comments. But you know, all facts have a half
life and some of those half lives can be quite short. But it is interesting to see this because
it's been about 10 years that I've been paying attention to this. And these things typically do
occur on five year cycles, both through the ADA, the AHA, and then in the United States, obviously,
the USDA also, I guess, in fact, gosh, it's hard to believe we're coming up to 2020. This time next
year, we'll be dealing with a new set of dietary guidelines, which I don't want to think about.
So let's change gears for a moment. You're a nephrologist. So for people listening,
that means you specialized after doing your training in internal medicine, you then
subspecialized to double down on one particular organ, a beautiful organ called the kidney,
which give us a little bit of a sense of like, what is it about the kidney that is
so special because it is a pretty special organ.
You know, in internal medicine, everybody sort of divides themselves into types, right? So in medical
school, it's interesting because you have the jocks who go into orthopedics, right? And then you
have the really sort of touchy feely people and they go into family medicine and pediatrics and
internal medicine generally attracts a lot of people who sort of like to think about things.
And then within internal medicine, you have the sort of subdivision into the different types.
And generally, when at least when where I was going to school at the University of Toronto,
the nephrologists were always the ones who like to think about things because that's all we could do.
We can do it couldn't do a lot about it. Like, you know, you stick people on dialysis and so on,
but they like to think about problems like puzzles, like electrolyte problems and stuff.
So you have this low sodiums and low potassiums and what's happening in the kidneys because the
kidneys do a lot in terms of homeostasis. They keep track of, you know, they keep the sodium in
check and you keep the proper amount of water and salt and potassium and calcium in the body.
So it's fairly complex, but it's a specialty where people like to think as opposed to like GI,
which was towards the sort of action oriented people who like to scope and, you know,
snare things out and stuff. So that was really what attracted me to nephrology really was that
that's sort of my personality is I like to think about stuff. I like to work out puzzles. I'm
addicted to Sudoku. It's just something I love to do. And it's just the way I am. So that's sort of
why I chose nephrology and I wound up doing it at UCLA. I do enjoy it. And when I say there's not
a lot we can do, what I mean is that up to a certain point, kidney disease, you can treat them,
but there's really like two treatments, right? There's prednisone and then dialysis. And the
last time we had a drug that actually slowed down progression of kidney disease was like the ACE
inhibitors in the eighties, right? It's been a long time since things changed. And just now we
have the SGLT2 for diabetic kidney disease. Before that, it's like nothing. So there wasn't a lot to
do, but there's a lot to think about. So that's sort of what I liked about it. And the kidney,
I mean, every organ is unique in its own way. But one of the things that I recall being sort of
blown away by in medical school was how smart the kidney was. You don't think of it as a
particularly intelligent organ. You think of it as well as just a filter. But there was a very
clever design in evolution, which said rather than the kidney learning what is bad and figuring out
a way to always get rid of things that are bad, it was the opposite. It was learn what is good.
And when you throw everything out during the first pass of filtration, just learn to pull back the
good because the probability that the good things are going to change is low. The probability that
you'll see new bad things is high. And so I remember the nephrologist sort of standing there
saying, look, it would be tempting to think that the kidney would operate like it's going into your
sock drawer to pull out just the right sock, but it doesn't. It pulls out all of the socks and puts
back the right ones. And that always sort of stuck with me. One is a pretty interesting
statement of just how important it is to have that system working. And the second thing is
how small the organ is. And yet what a high fraction of our circulating blood volume passes
through it. And as you build on that, which gets to some of the stuff we're going to talk about today,
why the kidney is such an early warning indicator of disease either through high blood pressure or
high glucose. I mean, is it safe to say that some would argue that the eyes are generally the first
place you can see evidence of that disease of either high blood pressure, high glucose, but the
kidneys would probably come in pretty close as well, wouldn't they? Oh, yeah, absolutely. So the thing
about the kidney is that they get like 20 percent of the entire circulation of the body. So it's a
huge amount of blood that goes through. And then the amount that comes out through the glomerulus,
which is the sort of functional unit of the kidney is huge. So basically they take everything out and
then sort of put it back in. So that's why they can fine tune it so well. But there's a huge amount
of fluid that goes through the kidneys sort of all the time, even though a trickle comes out as urine,
like it's filtering like 10 times more than that. So you might have a liter of urine a day,
but you're filtering way more than that every single minute truthfully. So it's an incredible
system. And the reason that the eyes and the kidneys are such early warning indicators is that
the eyes is the best because you can actually directly visualize. It's the only place you can
directly visualize the blood vessel. But the glomerulus, which is, you know, you have about a
million of these glomeruli in the body, but they're basically a big bag of blood vessels.
So if you're going to have diseases of the blood vessel, which turns out to be where these metabolic
diseases impact each other. So the heart disease and kidney disease, that comes later on.
But there's so many blood vessels in the kidney that it gives you this sort of early warning.
So the first thing you generally see in terms of diabetes or high blood pressure, you start to see
this protein that appears in the urine. So you can measure it, something called the albumin
to creatinine ratio, and you can actually see it. So when you start to get increased urinary albumin
excretion, what you know is that there is damage to the vascular system, just because the vascular
treat is like so, so big there, and you can directly measure it. So if you were to go to your liver,
for example, there's nothing you can measure, right? So it's got a big vascular, so the lungs
have a big vascular system, but you can't measure anything. Whereas the urine, you can actually
directly measure it, and the eyes, you can directly see it. So that's why they come out so early. So
increased urine albumin excretion, actually a very, very strong correlation to heart disease, not
because having a bit of urine is so bad, but it tells you that there's something bad going on in
the blood vessels of the kidney, which tells you that something bad is going on in the blood vessels
of the body. So that's why looking directly into the eyes is useful and measuring the urine is very
useful. Yeah, and because my skills for looking into patients' eyes are not good enough that I
can reliably do that, I have in the past three years really started to pay much closer attention
to cystatin C creatinine along with microalbumin for exactly this reason, because it sort of
occurred to me in a momentary insight that if my interest is in longevity, which means trying to
figure out a way to get people to outlive what their expected time course is, well, one of the
most important organs that gets neglected is the kidney. And if you are in your 40s, but you
already have a glomerular filtration rate at 80% of what would be predicted, you have to fast
forward a little bit and say, well, what's that going to look like when you're 80? The net
implication to me has been a much greater focus on blood pressure, even sort of stage one, so
slightly elevated blood pressure that I think many physicians until recently probably just weren't
thinking of as a significant enough problem. But once you do start looking at that microalbumin
and that cystatin C, as a non-nephrologist, we get a little bit of a window of insight
into your world. And there are a lot of people walking around, I mean, a staggering amount of
people walking around who on the surface, just based on their creatinine, look pretty normal,
but a slightly deeper look says, no, actually, they're not normal, they are compromised. And it
won't be clinically relevant for 30 or 40 years, but that's going to be relevant. The thing is that
there are no symptoms. So I see people all the time with diseases like IgA nephritis, which is
the most common sort of primary kidney disease in the world. And they will not know it. And they
will have lost sort of like 95% of their kidney function by the time I see them just because they
never knew they had a problem because they never checked it. It's very silent in that way. You
just don't know you have a problem unless you start looking for these things. And that's why
it's important to sort of keep an eye on the urine. And it's so easy too, right? It's non-invasive.
Anybody can do it. Well, let's talk about this thing called insulin resistance because there's
two broad, broad topics I want to explore with you today. And I can see no better way to approach
them than in this order. Let's start with the problem statement, and then let's start to talk
about the treatment. So I will confess at the outset, Jason, that as it's been nine or 10 years
that I've thought about this problem, I still have a hard time explaining to somebody, certainly if
I only have the duration of an elevator ride, what insulin resistance is, because I get tempted to
get into, well, it means this thing in this type of tissue, but this thing in this type of tissue,
blah, blah, blah. So let's not hold you to the standard if you've only got an elevator ride to
explain it, but how would you explain it both to maybe a layperson, but then even at the level of
nuance that we could sort of have a rigorous discussion about it? This is really what I think
is the sort of most important problem in medicine, which is the metabolic syndrome and insulin
resistance. And the whole way that we sort of think about it, I think is completely wrong.
I'll kind of step back and say, let's start with what we think is insulin resistance and taking
this physics approach, what's wrong with it? What parts of it don't fit the sort of experimental
evidence, if you will. So when we talk about insulin resistance and sort of, I'll just step
back a bit and say, okay, what do we think about insulin resistance the way I was taught about
insulin resistance, which I'll tell you I think is completely wrong. And probably you were taught
the same thing, right? So the way we think about insulin resistance is we think about it only in
terms of the glucose, right? So insulin is a hormone. And when insulin goes up, it allows glucose
from the blood to go into the cells. So we know that we know that for receptors go, it goes into
the cell membrane glucose codes in, and now the cell can use it. So the reason we call it insulin
resistance is because we know that there are normal levels of insulin, as opposed to type one,
where there are low levels of it's that there's normal levels of insulin, but the glucose is not
going into the cell for some reason. And when you measure the blood glucose, for example,
it's very high and there's insulin around. So if insulin is around, why can't the glucose
go into the cell? And this is why we say, Hey, if there's insulin, then the cell must be resistant
to the insulin. This is insulin resistance. This is the sort of lock and key paradigm that we talk
about. So insulin is a hormone. It acts on the insulin receptor, which is on the cell surface.
And the insulin receptor is like a gate. So there's a door, there's a lock, insulin is like
the key. So it opens the door and therefore the glucose can go from the blood into the cell. The
cell has energy to use. So we can measure insulin. We can also look at insulin receptors. You can
sequence it and you can tell there's actually nothing wrong with them. So insulin receptors
are completely normal. Insulin is completely normal. So what you say is that, well, there must
be something that's gumming up the system. So like a piece of gum that's sort of stuck in that lock,
it's gumming up the things you have a normal key, you have a normal lock, but when you put the key
in the lock, it doesn't really work. And then therefore the glucose can't get into the cell.
And the cell is now facing a internal starvation and the internal starvation is why we give insulin
to move the glucose into the cell. And that's our current thinking, or at least what I was taught,
and what most people still think about insulin resistance, but it's almost completely incorrect.
And there's no possible way it can be correct because there's a central paradox of insulin
resistance, which is that insulin has actually many, many different functions, only one of which is
letting glucose into the cell. So for example, we know in the liver that insulin is responsible for
de novo lipogenesis. That is, if you have a lot of carbohydrates, glucose, it will build it into
glycogen and that is working fine. If there's too much glucose after the glycogen is full,
it's going to turn it into triglycerides or fat, and that is working fine. So de novo lipogenesis
is working fine. Let's take a state of type two diabetes, which is we acknowledge is a high
insulin resistance. How can it be that you have a liver cell which can't let in the glucose,
so it's resistant to the insulin, yet the other effect of insulin, which is de novo lipogenesis,
is not only working fine, it's actually going overtime, right? You can measure de novo lipogenesis
and type two diabetes. It's super, super high. And what about the mitogenic effects of insulin?
So insulin is a growth factor. You can measure it, for example, with large for gestational age babies.
And you say that a woman is insulin resistant, yet insulin is actually doing what it's supposed to do.
It's actually stimulating a lot of growth. So there again, insulin is super sensitive,
or say testosterone. We know insulin has effect on testosterone and PCOS. And there it's working,
again, not just normally, like super high. So in the liver, you have this sort of central paradox
where you say in the same tissue to the same levels of insulin, you have both resistance
and super sensitivity. That's not really possible. It's the same cell, same thing,
but people call it selective insulin resistance. So that's sort of the central paradox of insulin
resistance. And it doesn't really make any sense that this can be the way.
And Jason, I would just add an even simpler observation to that, which I've always struggled
with, which is a very common phenotype of insulin resistance is adiposity, obesity, meaning obesity,
which of course means the accumulation of fat in a fat cell. So a fat cell is getting bigger.
Well, for a fat cell to get larger, it needs to incorporate triglyceride. To incorporate
triglyceride requires insulin. And to keep insulin in the fat cell requires insulin to
prevent lipolysis. And so on the one hand, you say, well, this patient is insulin resistant.
We'll talk about which cells, you know, maybe the muscle is insulin resistant,
but at the very least, looking at the fat cell, it appears to be quite well insensitive to insulin,
right? Exactly. And it's the same thing with de novo lipogenesis. And that this is why I say,
we know that de novo lipogenesis in this state of insulin resistance is taking sort of glucose
and turning it into fat. And then the liver sort of exports this fat as VLDL and triglycerides.
Well, the thing is that if you have internal starvation of this liver cell, that is the
glucose cannot get into this liver cell. How on earth is this liver going to package glucose
and turn it into fat? Because we know that is happening. But where's this glucose? Like it's
taking glucose making it into fat. But you're telling me if that with this paradigm, that no
glucose is getting in, you're facing internal starvation. I mean, it's like making a brick wall
with no bricks. It's just impossible. But yet this is the paradigm that we we face this internal
starvation paradigm. And you look at the the person like you look at a type one untreated type
one diabetic where there actually is no insulin. And they're like a stick. So if you've ever seen
some pictures, these type one diabetics could not gain fat no matter how much they ate. Then they
you know, they peed out all their glucose, then they died. That's not what it looks like in type
two diabetes in insulin resistance, because type two diabetes is a disease of too much insulin
resistance. So there's no way that is possibly true. So what you have to come up with is a different
sort of a new paradigm of thinking about what insulin resistance actually is. And this is one
of the things that you know, why I say physics always appeals to me, because that's where you
can come up with a new theory, which explains all these sort of paradoxes much better. And that is
that it's not a sort of underfill problem. It's an overflow problem, because there's two possible
ways. So we say they're insulin resistant, because the glucose does not go into the cell. That's the
whole reason we say it's insulin resistance, locking key paradigm, the gate is closed. But there's
actually two reasons why that glucose might not go into the cell, because either the door is closed,
or it's already too full. That is, if you have a cell that is already bursting to the seams with
glucose, that glucose from the blood simply can't get in. So this is a totally different paradigm
than this sort of internal starvation paradigm, because it's an overflow paradigm. But it solves
the problem of the central paradox. That is, why is this liver cell making so much new fat from
glucose? Because it's jammed full of fat. The glucose from the outside cannot go in. But the
liver cell is so busy trying to make new fat, de novo lipogenesis, that is just shoving it out
the door. But there's too much going in. So the problem is not insulin resistance, per se. The
problem is hyperinsulinemia. That is, in the first place, it was all this insulin that put all this
glucose into the cell. But you're putting so much into the cell that it's too full. I use an analogy,
like suppose you have a suitcase, and you're putting your shirts in your suitcase, which is
fine. And your wife says here, put these shirts in, you put it in, that's fine. And then at some point,
your wife says here, put these two shirts into your suitcase, but you don't put them in.
Well, why don't you put those two t shirts, last two t shirts into your suitcase, either the
suitcase doesn't open, or it's just full. There's two possibilities. And they're completely different.
Or to extend on that analogy, you could say, well, you're just not listening to your wife.
What you're basically saying is, look, the conventional view here is, when your wife said,
put these two shirts in your suitcase, the last two times, you just decided, I don't want to,
you know, I don't want to do that. But what if there's another approach? What if you're
fully well and willing to put those last two t shirts in the suitcase, but when you open up
the suitcase, there is simply no more room, the output looks the same, excess shirts outside of
the suitcase, right? But the reason could be entirely different. Exactly. But the implications
are huge. Because the thing is that if it's just the fact that you're not listening to your wife,
and you're not putting the t shirts in, then the solution is for somebody to grab those two t
shirts and just shove them in. Right? And that's what we did with type two diabetes, because we
said the glucose can't get into the cell, what we need to do is give you exogenous insulin,
sometimes huge doses of exogenous insulin, so that we can shove the glucose, ram it down the throats
of the cell, that's for some reason not listening to us, right? But if it's an overflow paradigm,
the implication is completely different. Because the solution is to get rid of the some of the stuff
that's in your suitcase, right? So if you bring it back to insulin resistance or hyperinsulinemia,
then the solution to trying to get rid of this so called insulin resistance is not giving more
insulin, because that was the problem in the first place, putting those shirts in the suitcase,
that was the problem in the first place. So putting more in is not the solution. The solution
is to get rid of it. So the solution is to empty that cell of glucose. That's the whole solution,
which is a totally different paradigm than what we've been taught, right? Because we use sulfonylureas,
we use insulin based on just trying to shove more glucose into this already filled cell.
And it solves the problem, it explains the paradox of, I'll tell you the whole thing,
it actually goes much further. But it solves the problem of the central paradox of why
it's making testosterone, why the insulin effect that the so high, right? Why do you get PCOS? Why
do you get the mitogenic effects of insulin, the growth effects of insulin, because you know that
insulin is a growth factor, it has huge implications for cancer, for example. So breast
cancer, colon cancer, very insulin sensitive, much higher rates in type 2 diabetes and obesity.
So you're getting the cancer causing effects of the insulin, but yet you're saying people are
insulin resistance, the fat, and the whole thing. It solves the problem of why you're having continued
de novo lipogenesis, even in the face of this so-called resistance, because you actually have
too much. It's not just a theoretical thing. It actually has huge implications for the treatment,
because your treatment now has to be getting rid of the sugar, getting the insulin down.
So let's pause for a moment and talk about the treatment. So I want to just sort of synthesize
this for the listener, because what you're suggesting is quite radical. Let's be honest,
right? The conventional view is going back to your analogy, which I love, by the way,
is that after your wife asking you enough times to put more t-shirts in, you stop doing it. And the
consensus view is you just stop doing it for some reason. You're not sensitive enough to her
request. You're being an insensitive guy. Look, that's an easy thing to understand. You're just
an insensitive guy. Well, the current approach is your wife walks over and opens the suitcase and
gets a few of her friends and your friends to help jam those t-shirts in there, because if you had
enough people and you could put enough weight on the t-shirts, you could probably sneak a few more
in, right? In other words, if you had more insulin or another analogy would be she yells louder is
probably a better analogy, right? So if her polite request is insulin, then raising her voice is more
insulin, then yelling and screaming. And then by the end, she's going to like take your favorite
football and throw it at your head. And at that point, you're mainlining insulin into the patient.
Let's talk a little bit about some of the other drugs, because most of the approaches to type 2
diabetes pharmacologically are not actually aimed at reducing glucose. Metformin is one of the very
few drugs you mentioned the SGLT2 inhibitors, which I want to come back to. So we'll carve out
the ones that actually lower glucose, but most of them are trying to amplify the noise. So walk us
through the classes of those drugs. So we have the sulfonylureas, which stimulate insulin, and
there's insulin, which stimulates insulin and the DPP4s, for example, which are also similar in terms
of the increased insulin. This is more than incretins, but they increase insulin, basically.
So the classic response of the older class of medication, so I'm going to leave. So metformin,
I'm going to leave aside because that's actually a totally different thing. SGLT2s is the sort of
newest class, but the old ones are all about increasing insulin. So that's your wife screaming
louder at you to shove more shirts in. And this is the thing. So if you do that, so say you give
somebody a sulfonylurea and you start shoving more, you know, your wife starts yelling at you.
So you start shoving more t-shirts. And at first you can do it. But as you keep doing that,
the problem just keeps getting worse and worse because at first it's a little full, then it's
a lot too full. And then what happens? Well, even if she's yelling at you really loud,
you still can't put any more. And because you've now you're just way over the limit. So this is
what happened in the body because look, if we look at the way we treat a type 2 diabetes sort of 20
years ago, it was to give sulfonylureas, then insulin, then more insulin, then more insulin,
you're just shoving more shirts into that suitcase. And the cell is getting more and more glucose,
and it's getting more and more full. As it gets more and more full, the insulin resistance gets
worse and worse. So what do you do? You keep going up, you keep going up. And guess what? That's
exactly what happened. But if you think about it, if you have a patient who 10 years ago was on
one drug, and now they're on huge doses of insulin, that diabetes never got better. The sugars might
have gotten better, right? But the actual disease itself of type 2 diabetes never got better. It
only got worse. And that's the reason we say it's chronic and progressive because the treatment
was completely incorrect. We did the wrong thing. We kept putting more shirts in when we should have
been taking shirts out. We kept putting more glucose into the liver, which is what insulin does,
right? Instead of taking all that glucose out of the liver. It was the wrong thing. That's why
people got worse. That's why we could never show any benefit to type glucose control in type 2
diabetes. That's why the Accord, the Advance, the VADT, and all those trials failed because
they're working on this incorrect paradigm of insulin resistance. This is the lock and key
paradigm. So now we have a drug class, which is something completely different. So this is the
SGLT2. Before you go to that, Jason, I'll just add another point to this because I know I discussed
this with Jake Kushner several months ago, but it's important to revisit this in case
folks have either forgotten that or didn't listen to it. I want to emphasize what you just said a
second ago, because you said it sort of like, yeah, we all know this, but it's such an important point.
Right. When diabetes trials are using glycemia as their endpoint, meaning how low can you get
the hemoglobin A1C? How quote unquote tightly can you control the glucose? They do seem to have some
benefits. Anything that is macrovascular does seem to get a little bit better. So where glucose
at high levels causes problems, those things seem to get a little bit better. But where glucose at
modest levels in the presence of high insulin, sorry, at the micro, I said macro, I meant
microvascular, but the opposite is not true. So by taking someone's average glucose from 200 down
to 150, that would be considered a huge win in a diabetes trial if you took their glucose from 200
down to 150. And that benefit might show up in their kidneys. But if you had to double the amount
of insulin you gave them to do that, it turns out at the macrovascular level, for example, heart and
brain, they don't get any better. In fact, they might get worse. I remember the first time I sort
of saw that about three years ago, it was a big aha moment, which is, why aren't they getting
better? And that's sort of when I began to think about hyperinsulinemia itself. I mean, maybe it
was longer than that, but not that long ago, right? It was like hyperinsulinemia itself is problematic
if you normalize for glycemic levels. Yeah, because this is the thing that is not the blood glucose
per se, it's the whole body glucose. Because if you think about this overflow paradigm now,
if you take the glucose that's in the blood and simply shove it into the liver, have you done
anything good for this patient? The answer is no, because you're just covering up the problem. So
you take insulin and your sugars are amazing, right? They're normal, but you shoved all this sugar
into your liver. What happens when you stop taking the insulin? All the sugar comes rushing back out
of your liver and your sugar goes high. So you actually have to keep taking it to keep it bottled
up. All you've done is you've covered up the problem. You never made it better because it's
like taking garbage and throwing it under your sink. You can pretend that your kitchen is nice
and clean, but it's going to start to smell. And that's the problem. It's the whole body glucose,
moving the glucose from one compartment of the body, which is the blood, to another compartment,
which is the liver. So you move the glucose from where you could see it into somewhere where you
couldn't see it. That doesn't do your body any good. And that was the real lesson of the accord
advance VADT. That was 2008. Those were actually the trials that started me down this whole thinking
that what we're doing is actually completely incorrect. Because if you remember for 2008,
I've been doing this for like 18 years or 17 years. And that was what we always thought,
right? You get the blood glucose low enough or normalize it, you're going to see huge benefits.
But we didn't, we didn't see any benefits at all. And that was a huge paradigm shift because these
all came in 2008. And yet, nobody wanted to propose a new theory of what is insulin resistance and how
we're treating it and why are we so wrong? We just kept doing what we kept doing. We just said, well,
maybe it's the hypoglycemia. It's like, come on, that's stupid. They weren't getting a lot of
hypoglycemia. But what they had to understand at that point, which nobody ever did, was that this
paradigm of lock and key internal starvation is completely the wrong way to think about it.
Therefore, you're using the wrong treatments, you're using treatments that are actually going to make
it worse, not better. And when you actually get rid of the glucose, so this is gets me back to
SGLT2s. So the SGLT2s are a new class of drug. And what they do is they actually make you pee out
the sugar. So it blocks the receptor on the kidneys, where you're actually absorbing the glucose, and
you actually pee out the sugar. So you get side effects, you get tons of side effects, you get like
urine infections and yeast infections, and for some reason, you get ketoacidosis too. But the point is
that if you look at the trials, they're actually quite consistent, you actually get a huge,
huge protective effect from the SGLT2s. That is, for the first time in like decades, we have a drug
that actually protects against kidney disease. So reduce the risk of kidney disease by about 25%,
and reduce the risk of heart disease, which we've never seen before in any class of
anti-diabetic drug. Because what we're doing now is we're actually getting rid of the garbage,
we're getting rid of the glucose, we're emptying out that suitcase. So the amount of lowering of
blood sugar was super unimpressive in all of these trials. So there's like five or six trials now.
Every single one of these trials shows end organ protection with almost no benefit to your blood
sugar. Like A1c would drop like 0.3 or 0.4, like nothing, it was terrible for the blood sugar,
but the end points were incredible. Why? Because you're actually getting rid of the actual problem.
You're emptying out the body of this glucose, which is what was making them sick in the first place,
as opposed to simply moving it around. And that I think is the explanation as to why SGLT2s are so,
so effective for organ protection, which we never saw before. Because now you're actually treating
the underlying problem of too much whole body glucose, as opposed to too much glucose in the
blood. You know, it's a totally different dynamic. Like if your whole body has too much sodium versus
just the blood has too much sodium, it's a totally different problem, right? If your whole body has
too much sodium, you get edema. If your just your blood has too much sodium, you have hypernatremia,
totally separate problems. Same thing here. If your blood glucose is high and your whole body
glucose is high, totally separate problems. Now we're actually addressing the underlying reason.
Let's consider, we're going to go to this in detail so we don't have to go deep now on it, but
just listening to the way you're describing it, it seems that another way to provide benefit,
which clinically seems to work quite well, is exercise. Because the more one would exercise,
the more one would increase a different reservoir outside of the liver, which is actually a larger
reservoir, and one that can't put its glucose back into circulation, which is the muscle.
So as I listened to you describe this, it's not inconsistent with this clinical observation,
which is you take a person with type 2 diabetes who is not exercising at all, who is sedentary,
and even if you make no change to their nutrition, exercising them quite vigorously for an hour a day
is actually going to have a benefit independent of anything else. Now the idea here would be how
many of these things can you combine them? Now, so what is the magnitude of that benefit?
There is a benefit for sure. I mean, all the studies we've done on exercise are beneficial,
but it's much less efficient than attacking the diet, just because the liver is really the key to
type 2 diabetes, the fatty liver and all that sort of thing, and you really can't exercise your liver.
You can burn off a lot of this glucose with exercise, but compared to the amount that you
put in on a daily basis, it's a lot more work than to simply not eat, for example. So in terms of
efficiency, it's just less efficient, but clearly there is a benefit to exercise, and it's the same
thing. You're really just trying to empty out all this glucose from the system. The other thing is
that what always strikes me as sort of funny is that it's not really just about the diabetes.
It actually affects more than that because it actually goes into the entire metabolic syndrome,
because if you think about it, metabolic syndrome is a constellation of five things. If you take the
ATP definition, it's the increased blood glucose, which we've talked about, but also abdominal
obesity, high triglycerides, low HDL, and high blood pressure. And if you think about it,
hyperinsulinemia plays a role in the same thing, because what happens, of course, is that if you
have this overflow paradigm, this liver is now busy exporting out tons and tons of the fat,
right? It's got too much glucose because of too much insulin. So it's too much glucose,
too much insulin. So therefore the liver is jam-packed, and it wants to get rid of all this
extra fat. So it's actually putting out tons of triglycerides. So that's why you get hyper
triglyceridemia. And then, of course, as triglycerides go up, we know that HDL goes down. So HDL goes
down. As you're exporting out all of this fat, this fat goes into all kinds of places where it's
not supposed to go, into the pancreas, into the omenital fat, and you get this abdominal obesity,
not because of dietary fat, because remember, dietary fat doesn't go into the liver. It goes
into the chylomicrons, which goes into the blood vessels, which is taken out by the adipocytes,
right? It never goes into the liver. It's the fact that the liver is pouring out all this new fat
that gets taken up in all the organs around it. So you get fatty pancreas, for example, which I
wanted to talk about in a second. But that's abdominal obesity. And we know that insulin has
an effect on blood pressure, because insulin causes reabsorption of sodium at the site of
the proximal tubule. So now, hyperinsulinemia, too much insulin, is really what is behind
abdominal obesity, high blood glucose, high blood pressure, low HDL, and hypertriglyceridemia.
That's the metabolic syndrome. The whole syndrome is not a syndrome of insulin resistance.
It's a syndrome of hyperinsulinemia. And that's a way better way to think about it,
because if the problem is hyperinsulinemia, then the solution is completely obvious. Insulin's
high. How are we going to lower it? It's no different than, hey, if your thyroid is too high,
you want to lower it. If your thyroid is too low, you want to give some. Well, that's not so hard
to understand. But think about type 2 diabetes for a second. Type 2 diabetes, we know that insulin
levels are high. So why did we think it would get better? By giving more insulin. We totally
misunderstand the problem. Yeah, I had a mentor who trained as an endocrinologist, but now focuses
exclusively on type 2 diabetes and obesity. He said the exact same thing, which is we have to,
he doesn't like the term insulin resistance for the same reason you don't, which is he says it's not
consistent with the way we think about endocrinology. In endocrinology, we think about
hyper and hypo fill in the blank. And yeah, he uses example thyroid. And he's like, look,
if you have too little thyroid hormone, we give you more. If you hypothyroid, we give you more. And
type 1 diabetes is that analogy. If you have too much thyroid hormone, we don't give you more of it.
We treat you in a way that reduces the effect of it. And sometimes that means taking out part of
the thyroid and all these other things. It's funny, I think part of the reason I think people
struggle with this is the endocrine system is easier to replace than to shut down. Hyper
cortisol is another great example. When you have patients whose cortisol levels are unmeasurable,
an extreme example of that would be someone in an Addisonian crisis. We're pretty good at giving
more cortisol. But when you have people with hypercorticillemia, which unfortunately comes
hand in hand with hyperinsulinemia, there's no pill to lower hypercorticillemia. Exactly. And
this is the same problem we had. That is type 1 diabetes, which is too little insulin. Hey,
it was great. Just give more insulin. But when you had type 2 diabetes, which is too much insulin,
there's no drug like SGLD2 for a little bit. But before that, there's no drug. So then we just gave
the same thing. It's so ridiculous, just like giving a hyperthyroid patient, hey, give them
some L-thyroxine. It's like, that's going to make it worse. But we did the same thing. And we watched
these people get worse. We gave them insulin and what happened? They all gained like 30 pounds.
Every single study showed that. The DCCT showed that. They just gained weight and they became
hyperinsulinemia. We have type ones who actually became hyperinsulinemia. You start out taking 20
units, 15 units a day when you're a kid. And then by the time you're 45, you're taking like 60 units
a day. Why? You developed insulin resistance. And yet you had no insulin in your body in the first
place 20 years ago, right? Because we thought that giving more insulin was good, but we didn't realize
that, hey, too much insulin is just as bad as too little insulin or worse in this case. And the
funny part about it is that we actually know a lot about biochemically how this sort of overflow
paradigm works. So if you look at the glycolytic cycle and the TCA cycle, for example, you have
glucose, which undergoes glycolysis to pyruvate. And pyruvate goes through pyruvate oxidation
into acetyl CoA, which undergoes the citric acid cycle, which gives you citrate and gives you ATP,
which again, we know feeds back and blocks glycolysis. Like, okay, well, that's you have
glucose. It goes into the cell, goes undergoes citric acid cycle. You get lots of ATP, you get
lots of citric acid, feeds back, blocks glycolysis, which means that glucose can't go in. It's like,
okay, we worked out the whole biochemistry of how this is overflow paradigm is supposed to work.
We actually teach it to like high school students that, hey, if you're feeding in way too much of
this stuff into the TCA cycle, there's a feedback. There's a negative feedback loop. And almost every
biochemical reaction does this, right? In biology, if you start stimulating stuff, you actually have
something that's going to block it. TCA cycles, no different. ATP is going to block glycolysis,
which is going to block that glucose. So you don't overload the system. That's what's happening.
Glucose can't go in anymore. This is such an important point because then you can say, okay,
hyperinsulinemia, which is actually too much glucose, too much insulin is going to feed back
and not let the glucose into the cell, which is why the glucose stays outside and you have the
so-called insulin resistance. But the key is to empty out the cell of glucose. How are you going
to do that? Well, low carbohydrate diets, intermittent fast. There's no more potent way
to lower insulin than to fast. I mean, we're going to come to this in a moment, but I get such a kick
out of watching people argue back and forth about whether carbohydrate restriction versus fat
restriction is better at lowering insulin. My experience is that carbohydrate restriction does
a better job than fat restriction, but I feel like sitting on the sidelines saying, hey guys,
there's another tool over here you've both sort of forgotten that's like infinitely more potent.
Eat nothing and watch what happens to insulin levels. And this is what we did. We just said,
okay, don't eat anything. You got to clear out this glucose. You got too much glucose in your
cell. Clear it out. The easiest way to do that is eat nothing. Then you're going to force your body
to start using some of this fuel, right? And the first place is going to pull it out of is this
fatty liver. Oh, by the way, the fatty liver. So of course is driven by this de novo lipogenesis,
which is why again, we see this huge correlation between fatty liver, which is a huge problem,
by the way, it's actually causing a ton of cirrhosis these days and type two diabetes, because
it's actually part of the same problem. But exactly, you're, you're, you're completely ignoring
your most effective tool, which is intermittent fasting. As soon as we did that, we saw tons of
people just reverse their type two diabetes, which gets me to my next point, which is the type
two diabetes. And everybody forgets that this is actually a two step process, right? You don't
develop type two diabetes just with insulin resistance. It's actually is two things you need.
One is insulin resistance or hyperinsulinemia, which is a much better name. And then two,
you need beta cell failure, because what happens is, and this is where the old paradigm was
completely wrong again. So we said, okay, well, you have insulin resistance, your body responds
by increasing the amount of insulin. So we know that that happens. So you get hyperinsulinemia.
And then eventually, the pancreas is just so tired of making all this insulin that it atrophies,
and it fails. And that's beta cell failure. That's when you actually see the blood glucose go way up.
And this whole process takes like 10 years or so. So the rising insulin resistance is met with
hyperinsulinemia, which keeps the blood glucose normal. And it keeps it normal for a long time
at the expense of hyperinsulinemia. And this is precisely what Kraft said, you can figure it out
much earlier if you look at insulin levels, as opposed to blood glucose levels. But the point is
that now you have to hypothesize that there's two completely separate things going on. One is
insulin resistance, and two is beta cell failure. And they're totally separate. And again, it doesn't
make any sense. There's too many experimental points that don't line up. One, we know that if
you're going to say type two diabetics, their beta cells have failed. Well, we know that's not true,
because virtually all type two diabetics are reversible. If you do bariatric surgery,
if you look at the studies, like 80%, 90% of those type two diabetics, they actually get off all their
meds, they actually reverse their type two diabetes. So if you said that the beta cell just failed,
then you're wrong. Because even the most severe type two diabetics reverse, we have three year
old, so the youngest person in the world to get type two diabetes was three years old, you're going
to hypothesize that this three year old pancreas has failed, has atrophied, like that's clearly
wrong. And the other thing is that you have to say if these two things go hand in hand,
why is it that you only see beta cell failure in this case of insulin resistance,
and never anywhere else? Like, how does that even work? Like they go together, one goes with the
other all the time and exclusively with each other. So this is the point that you'd have to
say that there's two separate things going on. But if you think about the sort of overflow paradigm,
again, explains this paradox very easily. Because what happens is that, and this is where, you know,
if you look at a lot of the work on the twin cycles hypothesis fits in, is that you're filling up your
liver with all this glucose, hyperinsulinemia, you got too much glucose in your liver, your liver
starts making fat and pumping it out. Then one of the organs that it accumulates in is the
pancreas. So now you've got fatty pancreas. And that is the problem is that your pancreas is not
failed. Your pancreas is just clogged with fat. And you can measure these in an MRI and whatever,
and you can see that all these people who have type two diabetes actually have big fatty pancreases
as well. And as you simply get them to fast, so the counterpoint study, which was done by Royce
Taylor and so on, they showed that the type two diabetes was reversible because you simply unclog
the fat. But now the fatty liver is responsible for the insulin resistance or hyperinsulinemia.
And the fatty pancreas is responsible for the beta failure. So they're both manifestations of the same
thing. They're both manifestations of hyperinsulinemia. And that explains why it's not two defects of type
two diabetes. It's actually a single defect and why it's a reversible problem. So again, this
hypothesis fits the anomalies so much better than everything else. And if you look at fructose,
for example, it's like, why is fructose so bad? And it's like, well, it doesn't have any
glycemic effect. It really doesn't have that much of an insulin effect, but causes a lot of this
fatty liver. All that fructose goes into the liver, gets turned into fat through pneumocytoplagrogenesis.
And now that's all part of the same pathogenesis, the fatty liver, the hyperinsulinemia. So it
explains everything about how this disease of type two diabetes, more than just hyperinsulinemia
or insulin resistance, it explains how that all kind of comes about. It sort of fits a lot better.
And this is what I mean. That's why I like the physics model, which is like, okay, we have a
theory now, which now fits the facts so much better than the old lock and key model. And
therefore you have to adopt it and say, what are the treatments that come out of this that are going
to be more effective? There are actually two separate things I want to ask about. The first one is,
do you see a way that naphyl D is causal towards hyperinsulinemia and separately where hyperinsulinemia
is causal to naphyl D? The literature is really not clear on this. And you could just say, well,
let's just dismiss the literature out of hand. But clinically, these things are so tightly wound.
And I've never really done the clinical experiment to tackle one without the other. So it's a very
common presentation is hyperinsulinemia that you describe. And I also am a big fan of Joseph Kraft.
And actually I would credit it to Najit Orbeh, who was one of my mentors, the endocrinologist I
referred to who really got me to think of it as hyperinsulinemia as the endocrine condition.
And his view was, look, the oral glucose tolerance test with frequent sampling is our best tool,
because long before glucose levels get out of whack, you're going to see inappropriate amounts
of hyperinsulinemia early on. But nevertheless, the common presentation is patient has hyperinsulinemia
with or without normal glucose levels. Their hemoglobin A1c is often completely normal.
Their ALT is high, much higher than we would like it to see, though not so high that people would get
alarmed by it. And if you really felt like doing it and you were resource unconstrained, you could
get an ultrasound of the liver and you would almost assuredly see the accumulation of fat.
Well, with that patient, we take a treatment plan that addresses both. The NAFLD resolved, the LFTs
within a very short period of time normalize, and so too does the hyperinsulinemia. And so I've
never tried to disentangle if the high level of insulin is really pushing the fat accumulation
in the liver or the other way around. Although, of course, you could argue that there's different
scenarios, right? If you put somebody on a very high fructose diet that wasn't necessarily
overly abundant in glucose, it might actually be that the NAFLD drives the hyperinsulinemia
versus a diet that is too high in carbohydrates for the individual such that it's the hyperinsulinemia
that ultimately leads to what? Help me think through the arrow of causation in the other
direction. Well, I think it does both, right? So you have those studies by Havel from 2009 where
he took people and gave them a lot of fructose, right? So the experiment was great. They took
people, two groups of people. One they gave sort of Kool-Aid that was sweetened with glucose and
one that they gave Kool-Aid sweetened with fructose. And then they actually looked for insulin
resistance and so on. And what they found was that when you gave a lot of fructose, people got type
two diabetes. You could measure the oral glucose tolerance test and they actually became diabetic.
So what you see is that the fructose, which is metabolized in the liver, is causing this fat
accumulation specifically in the liver. And that is going to cause a hyperinsulinemia, right? Because
the liver is full of all this excess fat. Now you're trying to shove all this glucose into this
fatty liver cell and the liver is like, no, I can't take anymore. So I'm going to be
resistant to this. So as it gets resistant, the blood glucose goes up and the body starts to
have to make more insulin to sort of get rid of this other situation, which is, hey,
there's too much glucose in the body. So I think the arrow of causation goes both ways, which means
it's sort of a vicious cycle. Each is making the other worse. So you have to take care of the
problem. So when you take care of one, you sort of take care of both. And I always say that what's
interesting is to look at this way of thinking. And then if you think about it, if you take it
sort of one step further, what you see is that the obesity, the insulin resistance and the type
two diabetes, which is the fatty pancreas as well, is they're actually not detrimental. They're
actually protective. They're actually mechanisms of protection against the problem. So for example,
let's take obesity. So I say, okay, so let's think about this one step at a time. Suppose you have
houses on a street and insulin every day, you take a little bit of sugar, so a bit of glucose,
and insulin comes by and knocks on the door and gives you a little bit of glucose. And you say,
thank you, and you use it for energy and everything's great. Now, all of a sudden, you start taking a
lot of glucose. So insulin comes by and instead of giving you a little cup of glucose, it gives you
a big barrel of glucose. And it's sort of like too much, right? But you take it because you're
supposed to. But eventually, your house fills up with all this glucose. So after a while, the glucose
keeps coming in and insulin keeps giving you a big barrel full that you can't use every single
day. And now your house is full. So what are you going to do? Well, you're going to stop taking that
glucose. So that's insulin resistance. So that's not actually, that's protective. It's protecting
itself from the effect of too much glucose. That's what the fatty liver is doing. It's protecting
itself from too much glucose. It says, hey, hey, hey, I can't take any more of this. So what happens,
of course, is the insulin is like, oh, I got to get rid of this glucose, right? I can't have it
hanging around. I'm going to lose my job. So it gets more insulin and starts battering down the
door and just shoving in all this glucose. Not that glucose is bad, but there's just too much of it.
So it just keeps shoveling in it. So then you're overcoming that protective response. The obesity,
which is the filling up of your house, was actually trying to protect yourself against this
excessive insulin resistance. And we see actually evidence of that in the lipodistrophes.
So I don't know if you saw that paper a few years ago about lipodistrophes. So you had these people
that actually had no fat and you think, okay, if they're so thin, if they're so skinny, they must
have no insulin resistance. They had the worst insulin resistance you've ever seen, like off
the charts. They wrote about it in the New York time. Yeah. This is the thing that sort of explains
that paradigm, which is if you are truly insulin resistant and you at least buy the argument that
that's a global term, meaning one cell is insulin resistant, they all are. Well then, yes, you should
be the leanest individual on the face of the earth because your adipose tissue does not have the
ability to integrate or assimilate the signal that says, one, bring triglyceride in and two,
halt the process of lipolysis. The problem is not insulin resistance per se, it's actually
hyperinsulinemia. So what your body is doing is taking all this fat and sort of storing it away.
So it doesn't cause a problem, right? So these people with the lipodistrophy, they couldn't store
the fat. So what happened is that the fat stored up in their liver and they had the highest insulin
resistance you've ever measured because it's really a protective mechanism. The fat is trying to suck
away all this glucose so that it doesn't cause a problem. This is why obesity itself is actually a
protective mechanism against hyperinsulinemia, against too much sugar. So the ultimate problem
is too much glucose and too much insulin. So then the next step is, okay, so now insulin sort of is
way too much. The insulin's got all his cousins out, you know, battering down your door, throwing in
all this stuff and you can't take it anymore. So then what do you do? Well, you start to take some
of these barrels and you try and give it to like your friends and your family and so on, right? So
this is what the liver does, right? It's got way too much fat sitting around. So it takes this fat
and shovels it out the door as VLDL and it goes into the other organs. So it goes into the pancreas,
it goes into the liver, it goes into your omentum. That's how you get the obesity,
the abdominal obesity that you see. So now you've got obesity as a protective mechanism
and insulin resistance itself is a protective mechanism because the cell is trying to protect
itself from too much insulin, too much sugar. The last part is that you're throwing out all this
glucose into your pancreas, all this fat into your pancreas. Your pancreas stops,
it makes a lot of insulin, makes a lot of insulin, makes a lot of insulin up onto a certain point.
Now it's all clogged up and it can't make the insulin. So what happens? Well, you start to
pee out all this sugar, right? You get the polyuria, polydipsia, glycosuria. Your body
is actually trying to protect itself by peeing out all this sugar. So it's like you have to look
at it the other way. We think of all these responses, obesity, insulin resistance, and
the beta cell failure as pathologic. They're actually protective. It's a totally different
thing. Your body is actually trying to protect yourself against the root cause of the problem,
which is too much insulin, too much glucose. So when you enhance that glycosuria with SGLT2s,
guess what? You actually have a protective, like a hugely protective effect because that's the
protective mechanism against the root cause. When you actually give people more insulin,
you actually keep all that inside, then what happens? Again, we, and clinically you see this,
clinically the patients know it because you give them insulin, their blood sugars are better,
but then they gain weight. And as they gain weight, their diabetes gets worse. So you give
them more insulin and as you give them more insulin, they gain more weight. Do you think that
adiposity per se, all things equal, is also driving the hyperinsulinemia? And if so,
what is the mechanism? Or do you believe that the adiposity is a bystander of it? Because this is
also an enormously difficult problem to tease out in clinical trials because virtually any
clinical trial that demonstrates an improvement in quote insulin resistance or more accurately
a reduction in hyperinsulinemia is without exception to my knowledge accompanied by weight
loss and a reduction in adiposity. And this too then drives a causal question, which is,
is the adiposity driving the hyperinsulinemia? So let's for a moment, pos it that hyperinsulinemia
is the way we will refer to this. And we won't talk about insulin resistance because that term
has really lost meaning in this context, that the adiposity is driving the insulin resistance
or the insulin resistance is driving the adiposity. I think it's more likely that the
hyperinsulinemia is driving the obesity rather than the other way around. I mean,
it's always hard to tease out, but you can look at, to me, it's always like, let's take
sort of an experiment and see. So there is a great experiment a few years ago where they
took people who were type 2 diabetic, and this is in the 90s, and they gave them a lot of insulin.
So from time zero to six months, they went from zero units of insulin to like a hundred units of
insulin, the blood sugars were great. And what happened? Well, they gained like 20 pounds. And
if you look at the number of calories that they were eating per day, it actually dropped by about
two, 300 calories per day. So what you see is that the only difference, because this was a randomized
sort of trial, the only difference was the hyperinsulinemia. That's what we changed.
When we changed experimentally, the amount of insulin people were getting because we're giving
it to them, they gained weight. So to me, that is clearly a causal relationship. We see this all
the time, right? You prescribe insulin, people gain weight. You give sulfonylureas, which increase
insulin, people gain weight, right? You give them SGLT2s, which make insulin drop, then you lose
weight. And type 1 diabetics know it too, like they lose weight. So the arrow of causality is very
easy to establish going from hyperinsulinemia to obesity. And forgetting all the mechanism,
all I'm saying is that when you give insulin, people gain weight. Every single time you give
insulin or raise it by sulfonylureas, or when you lower insulin with type 1 diabetes, they lose
weight. And it doesn't forget about what you eat or whatever. Like people always say, oh, let's put
equal calories in the liquid. All I'm changing is the insulin. Then obesity goes up or down,
depending on what happens to the insulin. It's much harder to establish that causality the other way
around, right? You can, and they've done this with liposuction. So if you take a situation where
you remove 20 pounds of fat, what happens? And the answer is nothing. Right. Now that study,
if you're referring to the one that Sam Klein published in the New England Journal of Medicine,
I love that because it's a great example. Of course, the pushback is yes, but that was only
subcutaneous fat that was removed. We don't do liposuction on visceral fat. You know, on some
level, I think this is a great theoretical question. It might not matter. In other words,
it doesn't change the clinical decision. It's an important question as we think mechanistically
about what's happening, but it doesn't change what you do with a patient, which in the final analysis
matters more than anything. But yes, until we can really do liposuction on visceral fat,
which I personally think would just pose too much risk to justify, it's going to be very difficult
to tease out the other direction. But what about the role of inflammation? Because the other thing
that seems to go hand in hand with hyperinsulinemia in patients is they also tend to be quite
inflamed. And we can measure this non-specifically with things like C-reactive protein, fibrinogen,
interleukins. We can even see cardiac specific forms of inflammation. So for me, this is just
a very non-scientific clinical observation, but I'm curious as to whether you've seen it.
Yeah. In terms of inflammation, again, I look at it from an experimental standpoint. So if I think
inflammation causes obesity, for example, then what happens when you decrease inflammation? Because
we have anti-inflammatory medications. What happens to obesity? Well, you can give NSAIDs,
and people don't lose weight. You can give prednisone, which is probably our most powerful
anti-inflammatory. People don't lose weight. If you give all these antibodies, this antibody,
that end, there's all kinds of inflammatory IL-2 and TNF. And you have all these things,
other than if they get super nauseated, they lose weight. But if they don't get super nauseated,
then they don't really lose weight. So to me, that whole story, there might be a kernel of truth in
that. But to me, it doesn't really make a lot of sense. Like if you get a really bad infection,
some kind of inflammatory state, so inflammation goes way up, rheumatoid arthritis, do you gain a
lot of weight? It's like, yeah, I don't really see it. As opposed to the consistency where you give
insulin, people gain weight. You take away insulin, people lose weight. To me, that's a consistent
causal relationship. Whereas inflammation, it's much less. I don't deny that there's a lot of
important inflammatory mediators and stuff, but it's just not so simple that you can say
more inflammation causes weight gain, less inflammation causes weight loss. Therefore,
treat everybody with Advil or something like that. Yeah, where I was going to go was actually
slightly more nuanced, which is again, getting a little bit ahead of where we're going to go,
because I want to start talking about some treatment ideas. But you take a hyperinsulinemic
patient with no inflammation. In my limited experience, they tend to respond quite well to
carbohydrate restriction and exercise. When I take patients who have significant hyperinsulinemia,
but it's also coupled with inflammation, I don't find that they are as impacted by what I just said.
And I find that those are the patients that initially got me to start exploring significant
periods of fasting, either significant 500 calories a day for five days, that type of fasting, or
water only for three days, five days, that sort of thing. And again, not a very scientific
organization or observation rather, these are small and clinical things that I see.
But I wonder if A, you've seen that and B, if it suggests that inflammation can have a negative
synergy with hyperinsulinemia. I think that there probably is something to that because there is,
I mean, for sure other hormones are involved. Like we know for sure there are other hormones
involved. So look at cortisol, for example, inflammation is difficult because there's so
many different mediators, right? You can have TNF, you can have IL-2, you can have all kinds of
inflammatory mediators, endotoxin and stuff. But there are for sure other hormones that
make it really are very important, like cortisol. So you give cortisol, people gain weight, right?
It's not as much as with insulin, but you give prednisone and we've all done it. You give
prednisone, you gain weight. When you take away the prednisone, like they finish their course of
prednisone, that weight kind of goes back down. So we know that cortisol, for example, has a huge
impact on body fatness. For example, we know the studies from sleep. If you get good sleep,
you're more likely to be a good weight. If you are sleep deprived, for example,
it's a stressful situation where cortisol is going to go up, then you're more likely to gain weight.
So that's not an insulin thing, it's a cortisol thing. And we know for sure that sex hormones
have to play a role somewhere in there as well, because there are women who develop gestational
diabetes and their insulin, their diets, they don't change. The difference is they got pregnant,
right? And that's a difference in sex hormones. And somehow that impacts, and I actually don't
know how this works, but somehow it does impact the response of, I'm not sure they're hyperinsulinemic
either. I think there must be something completely different about that entire thing, but it's not as
common. So I don't think about it as much. Or girls and boys at puberty, for example, the difference
of girls and boys is testosterone versus estrogen for the most part. It's not an insulin difference,
yet girls who go through puberty have way more fat than boys who get more muscle. So we know
that there are other hormones that clearly impact. So it's not just about insulin, but it's about
cortisol, it's about sex hormones. And I think inflammation probably comes in there somewhere,
but what to do about it? And it's a lot messier. Inflammation is a lot messier than thinking about
cortisol, for example, right? Where you can measure levels and you can think about up or down,
you know, cortisol, for example, you have the too much, which is Cushing's disease, and what's the
sort of hallmark? Well, obesity, and then you can get too little, too little cortisol is Addison's
disease. And what's the hallmark? Weight loss, right? So again, very, very clear. It's easy to
measure inflammation. It's just so hard. It's just too many moving parts for me.
I think this whole thing is too hard for me, but let's talk a little bit also about the role of
hyperinsulinemia specifically on the vascular system. What is it about hyperinsulinemia
and the endothelium or the capillaries that seems to wreak havoc beyond what tends to
accompany late stages of it, which is hyperglycemia, which of course has significant damage mechanically
on the microvascular system. But what about, like for example, why would hyperinsulinemia
exacerbate coronary artery disease, absent abnormal glucose levels, or even once corrected
for lipid levels, which I, you know, that observation exists, right? You can take patients
that have the same lipid levels, the same glucose levels, but the hyperinsulinemic patient is going
to have worse cardiovascular disease. Why is that? For that specifically, I don't know. I think that
there's a lot more work because a lot of people still don't think about it as a disease of
hyperinsulinemia. But I think of it generally in terms of two things. So I think about two things,
like cardiovascular disease a lot and cancer, because those are actually the two top killers
of Americans is CVE disease and cancer. And they're both to me diseases of too much growth.
That is, everybody thinks growth is good, but growth in adults is generally bad. Like you don't
want to grow. Once you reach adult size, your liver doesn't grow, your kidney doesn't grow,
you shouldn't be growing. And if you are growing, it's generally bad. So if you gain weight,
you're obesity gain fat, that's a disease of too much growth. If you have a big fat liver,
that's too much growth. If you have all this excess protein in your brain that's blocking
your signals, and that's Alzheimer's disease, that's bad. And it's the same thing, cancer,
disease of excessive growth. In the blood vessels, we know that there's excessive growth, right? It's
not a matter. And this whole idea of fat or cholesterol clogging your arteries like a pipe,
it's super like even when I was in medical school, we knew that was not the case.
We know it's a response to injury. That's why you get it at bifurcation points, for example,
and you get smooth muscle proliferation. And then the foam cells which go in and it's not clear
whether the foam cells and all that is a response to the injury. But it's because of that whole
cascade, the atherogenic cascade, it's a response to injury, but you get excess proliferation of
certain things including smooth muscle cells and so on. But to me, it's just the disease of too
much growth that's eventually building and collapsed and closing off that artery. And this
is where diseases of too much growth is linked very tightly to insulin, because insulin is a
growth factor. I mean, this is one of the things that is super exciting in cancer, I'll tell you,
like the whole PI3K thing, because it directly links insulin, which we all think about in terms
of metabolism, to growth. Every single time that you have a nutrient sensor like insulin like mTOR
like AMPK, it's the same insulin, the pathway that it goes through, which goes through PI3K and then
MAPK and AKT, is it influences growth, increases growth. And that to me is one of the big problems
with insulin all the time, is that you're telling your body to grow all the time when it really
shouldn't be growing all the time. So you actually have to decrease growth if the problem is too
much growth, you want less growth. And one of the things that you want to influence is insulin and
mTOR. mTOR, I know you talk a lot about mTOR, it's the same, exactly the same. It's a nutrient
sensor at heart, it's very sensitive to dietary protein. And what it does is if there's a lot of
protein, you turn on all these cell proliferation signals, when you have very little protein, what
happens? It's ophagy. It's like, oh, okay, so you have to realize that metabolism and growth are
exactly the same thing and it has even more implication for cancer, which is a disease of
too much growth. So being obese, for example, it doesn't give you cancer, but it certainly
increases your risk of breast and colon cancer by a whole lot. There are 13 cancers that are listed
as obesity related. And we know that there's a very strong relationship between type 2 diabetes,
even without the obesity, but because they're hyperinsulinemic, there's a very strong relationship
between type 2 diabetes and breast cancer, for example. So to me, those are all diseases of
excessive growth. And therefore, you have to start looking at growth pathways, which actually are the
exact same as metabolic pathways, which is insulin, mTOR, AMPK, which is important, of course, for
metformin. And then all of a sudden you see, hey, all of these times that you can decrease nutrient
sensors, that is, decrease mTOR, decrease insulin, increase AMPK, you're getting good effects for
longevity. This is fascinating. Yeah, yeah. And it's so funny you say this, Jason. So this past
week I was in Boston and I was meeting with a number of folks. And one of the folks I was meeting
with wrote a paper, a very interesting paper in 2006. I was not aware of it at the time.
He wrote a theoretical paper. So it was a paper that got rejected by virtually every journal out
there. But in 2006, he proposed theoretically that rapamycin would be a great longevity drug.
Now, today we'd say, well, that's obvious, but it's important to note that the first trial
demonstrating the immense power of rapamycin to promote longevity was not published until 2009,
three years after this paper was written. And what he said was, based on all of the evidence
he had examined to date of the use of rapamycin, even in patients with transplant, it's anti-proliferative
properties alone speak to this. And it's so funny to hear you say what you just said, because he said
the exact same thing. He said, think about it, Peter, every chronic disease is some amount of
hyperproliferation, hypergrowth. And you have a drug here that in the most elegant way, in the least
toxic way, in the most specific way, targets one of the most important regulators of growth.
His prediction was this is going to be the most important longevity drug there is. And
I would agree with that. In 2019, I think that there is no more promising agent than rapamycin
for longevity. But again, it comes back to this growth thing. And to put another bow on what you
said, it was certainly lost on me in medical school, how anabolic insulin is. In fact, I remember
learning many years later that bodybuilders used insulin. And I remember thinking,
oh, that's odd. I wonder why. And of course, after speaking to some bodybuilders,
you know, I got to learn, well, look, testosterone is anabolic, but insulin is even more anabolic.
Now, you can't go overboard. And this is where these hormones are very sophisticated, because
testosterone is very anabolic to muscle, which insulin is as well. But testosterone is catabolic
to fat, whereas insulin is anabolic to fat and anabolic to muscle. Cortisol, just to bring it
full circle, is the worst of both worlds. Hypercortoselemia is catabolic to muscle,
while anabolic to fat. I usually end up drawing this picture for patients on the whiteboard,
showing estrogen, testosterone, cortisol, insulin, and then, you know, you draw a muscle cell,
a fat cell. And it very quickly starts to paint the picture that says, this whole thing is just
endocrinology. I mean, all of this comes down to how can you manipulate these hormones to the
desired outcome, nutrition being one tool, but exercise, the use of hormones themselves,
of course, in cases where there's deficiencies being another way to do it. So it's a very
interesting way to sort of frame this as the things that we care most about avoiding,
if you really look closely involve some measure of hyperproliferation and growth.
Yeah, because that's the chronic diseases today, because there's been a huge shift in the diseases
that we treat. So if you go back 50 years, 100 years, you're talking about treatment of infectious
diseases, right? Hepatitis virus and pneumonia and diarrhea and all this sort of stuff.
And we did great. We developed all these great drugs, antibiotics, antivirals, like,
like really, really good stuff. And they haven't been as big a problem. Now we have a problem with
resistance, of course, which is actually the same thing. Interestingly enough, I think there's a huge
parallel between antibiotic resistance and insulin resistance. And in that they're the same thing.
Antibiotic resistance is not caused by some phantom things caused by using too much antibiotic.
Insulin resistance is the same thing. It's caused by too much insulin. So you have almost the same
thing where antibiotic resistance is caused by too much antibiotics. And we try and treat it by using
even more antibiotics, right, to overcome that resistance, which is the dumbest thing you can do.
In insulin, we have insulin resistance, we treat it with more insulin, which is what caused in the
first place. And then things get worse. And we don't understand why. So you know that treating
antibiotic resistance is about using less same with insulin, you got to use less. But anyway,
we shifted from using from treating these diseases, which are infectious diseases to
these chronic diseases, but we never changed our paradigm of medicine, which is the paradigm was
you come into me as a doctor, I give you a pill and antibiotic and you get better.
Then people came in with these diseases like diabetes and obesity and the related diseases
of hyperproliferation, or I call them diseases of too much growth, cardiovascular disease and cancer,
and all this other stuff, too. Like it's all about fibrosis, right, which in the end is just
about you revving the system too hard. But it's basically hyperproliferation. And then we said,
let me give you a pill. It's like, that's totally the wrong thing. Because you don't have that pill
to decrease proliferation. Rapamycin might be one, but rapamycin to me is limited because you've got
not one problem. You don't have one nutrient sensor, you have three nutrient sensors, you have
insulin, you have mTOR, and you have AMPK. It's a very sophisticated system. Look, insulin responds
to dietary carbohydrates and dietary proteins. mTOR responds mostly to dietary protein. AMPK
is actually like a, you know, measures the ATP, the AMP ATP ratio. So it actually doesn't care
what you eat, it just cares about the cellular energy availability. So they're all three measuring
different sort of things. And they all work on different timescales. So insulin goes up and down
within minutes, it's gone within hours. mTOR is sort of up and down between 18 and 30 hours. And
AMPK is sort of days to weeks. So you have such a sophisticated system because you have three
nutrient sensors that are giving you different information based on your diet and also based on
your time scale. So your body actually gets such incredible information just by integrating which
one is up and which one is down. But rapamycin only affects the one. Whereas some things like
intermittent fasting is going to decrease your insulin, it's going to decrease your mTOR and
increase your AMPK, which is all three things that you need to do in order to sort of decrease
proliferation. Because you know that all three of them, insulin feeds into mTOR and AMPK also feeds
in, they're all part of that same thing. You're affecting three different parts of that pathway
as opposed to one. And that is going to give you the best bang for your buck. And it's free and
you can do it anytime you want. And it's like, oh, hey, they told people this 2000 years ago, right,
when all the religion said, oh, you should fast and you should do this and you should do that,
which is to me, this sort of just incredible that it all comes sort of back to what we knew
2000 years ago, which is that, hey, fasting every so often has incredible benefits because you're
going to be able to affect those diseases of excessive growth. Let's pivot to this now. Let's
talk about fasting. You and I are certainly two folks that are no strangers to this. Anyone who's
been cared for by you or anyone who's been cared for by me pretty much is used to the same drum beat,
which is, I mean, I don't actually, I'd like to hear about how you do it in our practice.
You know, generally for the first year, we don't push too hard on the fasting thread,
but boy, by the end of that first year and into their second year with us,
we're really having a hard discussion about this in some cases for patients that are resistant. Now,
I have this sort of framework that I think about for fasting, which is you start out on this sort
of crappy standard American diet. And how do you escape that gravitational pull of that horrible
thing? I'll be sensitive and call it the standard crappy diet, the Canadian crappy diet or whatever
as well. They're comparable. To me, the two easiest ways to help patients escape the gravitational
pull of pure garbage is time restricted feeding and or some measure of dietary restriction. So
the way that I explain that is time restricted feeding says ostensibly you don't restrict what
a person eats. You just restrict when they eat and nor do you restrict how much for that matter,
but you just put a feeding window on and you say, look for 16 or 18 hours a day, you'll consume
nothing and you will eat ad libitum in the remainder of that period of time. And you contrast
that with dietary restriction, which we've already alluded to carbohydrate restriction as a form of
dietary restriction. And it can come with and without caloric restriction, but the simplest
way to execute it would be to say, look, no restriction on when you eat, no restriction
on how much you eat. You just can't eat these foods. And that's sort of where the majority of
the diet wars live is, are you a vegetarian? Are you vegan? Are you on a low fat diet, a
Mediterranean diet, a paleo diet, a low carb diet, a ketogenic diet? They're all forms of dietary
restriction. And to my knowledge, I'm not aware of one of them that is not significantly better than
just being on the standard American diet. So that speaks probably less to their individual efficacy
and more to the abject misery, metabolically, that is being exerted on people. Before we get
into fasting, let's get everybody really dialed in on those two things, time restricted feeding,
plus or minus dietary restriction. How do you visit those two things before we get into fasting?
I focus a lot more on the fasting. So I've always said, yeah, it comes down to the when you eat and
what you eat. And this was the thing that I sort of pointed out years ago, like three,
four years ago, which the everybody focuses so hard on the what to eat. And nobody talks like
ever about the when to eat. That is, there is a sort of consensus. It was never intentional
that we should eat all the time, right? You should eat six or eight times a day, you should grace
throughout the day. And you know, there's all sorts of reasons that were made up to suggest why we
should be eating six times a day. But there was never any science, right? So, you know, if you ever
look back and say, Hey, where did we get this idea that we should eat six or eight times a day,
it's like from nowhere, somebody made it up, it stuck. And that was about it, right? It didn't,
there was no studies, there was no randomized control trials, there's nothing. Somebody just
thought it was a great idea. And a few years ago, I said the same thing, which is that, hey,
we're sort of missing half of the problem. Because if it's two problems, when to eat and what to eat,
and you're nobody's talking about when to eat, then you're not going to succeed, no matter what
you do. And that this is why there's this sort of diet wars. I wasn't that interested in getting
into that. I was like, more, hey, let's look at this whole other problem. So what we do generally
is start with that, because it's a lot easier to change the frequency, as opposed to what it is
they're actually eating. And this just comes from experience. So the first thing I did when I started
really focusing in on diet was try and change people's diet. But I did it from a clinical
standpoint, that is, I'm not seeing one person sort of for an hour every week, I have a clinical
practice, which means you get like 10 minutes, like every three months. So it has to be something
that is sort of easy to understand, and super effective, as opposed to sort of counting
carbohydrates or something, which takes a long time to explain to somebody and then explain
why eating fat's not that bad for you and so on. I needed something that was sort of much more
efficient in that way. And that's why we started using fasting quite a lot, because it's something
that people sort of understood. You can explain it within the 10 minutes, and then you can follow
up with them and see if they're eating and they know sort of what it means to be fasting, as opposed
to some of these people who really didn't have any idea what a low carb diet really meant. And that
was the issue. Tell the story again. I remember last year you were telling me a funny story about,
and I don't remember what the ethnicity was, and the point was not to poke fun at one ethnicity or
other. It was just like within this culture to say don't eat carbs meant, oh, okay, well, I won't eat
bread or pasta, but I'm still going to eat lots of noodles and lots of this and lots of that. And
they came back in and you said, how is the carbohydrate restriction going? And they said,
oh, it's fantastic, Dr. Fung. I'm doing so well. Great. What are you eating? And it was like all
carbs. It was just different carbs. And that was, I remember you describing that being sort of an aha
moment of culturally, it can be very difficult to get people to restrict carbohydrates.
Yeah, because it's their traditional food. So I get half a lot of Asians, so both East Asians and
South Asians. And of course the diet is based on rice and rice noodles. And for the South Asians,
it's rice again. So there's a lot of cultural difficulty, which is why it was very difficult
to sort of push too hard on it. You can if you make enough of an effort. And I think that message
anyway is getting across that eating all these carbs are not great for you. These refined carbs.
But the point was that you have to still come up with something. And this is where the practical
experience sort of comes in. Like you can't just say, okay, well, I'm just going to stick with carb
restriction, right? I'm going to put these Chinese and Filipino and South Asian Sri Lankan people on
no rice, no noodles, ketogenic diet. They might say yes, but they actually won't do anything to
you know, to follow it because it's just so difficult, right? Their culture is like that.
They've been eating this way for 70 years, and it's very hard for them to change. And their family
eats like this. So it's like, what are you going to do as opposed to fasting, which to me was a much
simpler idea that was already embedded in every culture. So you talk to Muslims about and they're
all like, ah, I know what you're talking about. And you talk to Catholics and you talk to, you know,
Jewish people like they will go, ah, this is a Greek Orthodox or whatever. And they're all like,
ah, and the Buddhists were like, ah, so it was way easier just from a practical standpoint. That was
where I started using it. And then I saw like these crazy, like crazy good, like results. It was like
insane. So we wrote a case report that was published in BMJ case reports. It was three patients who
had like sort of 20 to 25 years of type two diabetes and like five years of insulin on big,
big doses of insulin. We told them about low carb diets, but you know, we don't spend a lot of time,
but we put on 24 hours of fasting three times a week, which is like a one meal a day, right?
Nothing too strenuous or anything. We got off all their insulin like between five and 18 days. It
was ridiculous how quickly they responded. And years later, we still have people who are like
non diabetic. They went from 20 years of diabetes to non-diabetic and have maintained it for the
last six years. It was ridiculous how good like, I just couldn't believe the results that we're
getting. And that's when we were like, okay, let's tell people and let's start writing about it and
all this sort of stuff. And it took ages to get that. It took like two, three years to get that
case series published. You alluded to bariatric surgery earlier. And about five years ago,
I was involved in an effort to do a clinical trial to try to tease apart the observation you
alluded to, which was that when you take a patient with type two diabetes, who undergoes bariatric
surgery at the time, I believe this was true primarily for the Roux-en-Y gastric bypass.
So for the listener, that's a surgical procedure where the part of the bowel that comes out of the
stomach, which is called the jejunum is the first part after the duodenum. You cut a piece and then
reattach it as a piece of a Y and then bring it up such that you are basically bypassing not just
significant parts of the volume of the stomach as a reservoir, but also the initial part of the
duodenum and the jejunum. The observation was the following. You do this operation on a patient
within about 10 days. They haven't lost a meaningful amount of weight, but all of a sudden
they don't need insulin anymore. And very quickly, their diabetes resolves. In fact,
I believe we are still at a point, although this may be changing, where the only treatment that is
viewed by an insurance company to actually reverse type two diabetes is bariatric surgery.
So the question we were trying to ask was how would you design a clinical trial to parse out
how much of that is due to the change in the internal architecture? Is there something
problematic about the duodenum of that patient? How much of that is due to the change in the
nutrition of the patient? Because a patient who undergoes a gastric bypass has to make significant
changes in their nutrition. And how much of that is due to the perioperative period of caloric
restriction? So what's your take on those patients, which again, pretty profound results.
Again, not that profound. I think when you consider them in the context of what we now talk
about with what fasting can do, but what's your take on that? My take is that the fasting does
everything. So you can actually get, I think exactly the same results if you simply didn't
feed them for 14 days or something like that. Because the thing is that when we do this for
people, when you put people on a seven or 14 day fast, we see this, we don't do it a lot because
generally they're older. So we want to be a little bit more sort of regimented. And there's also
these cases of latent onset type one and so on. But you actually see exactly the same thing where
the diabetes complete results. And the thing about it is that you can understand it perfectly
by understanding this sort of overflow paradigm. Because what you're doing, of course, is dropping
insulin levels very low. And then you're forcing the body after the first 24 hours, glycogen runs
out. So now you're going into a period where your body is going to have to metabolize fat for energy.
So the first place it's going to start pulling it out of is going to be the internal organs,
because it's right there. The liver is going to be the first place that it's going to start pulling
the fat out of. And if you look at Royce Taylor's data, what you see is that the liver fat starts
to go down right away. The insulin resistance starts to go down right away because that's the
problem, right? It's this big fatty liver, which you can't shove any more glucose in. That's what
insulin resistance is. As this big fatty liver goes down, just like emptying your suitcase,
the insulin resistance starts to melt away. And slower, because he showed this incredible data,
which looked at pancreatic function with ultra low diet. It wasn't fasting, but it is an ultra low
calorie diet. You can start to see that the pancreatic fat starts to go down because the
body's not pumping out. Your liver's not pumping out fat and dumping it in your pancreas. And as
you get rid of that pancreatic fat, you're unclogging the pancreas and you're producing enough insulin
that you don't get the hyperglycemia anymore. Your glucose isn't that high because now you're
at a stage where insulin production is going to go up because they measured that in Royce Taylor's
Counterpoint Study, the one from UK. And you can see that the first phase insulin response starts
to go up. It takes a few weeks, but that's exactly what you see clinically. That is, before you lose
the weight, which is all a lot of sort of subcutaneous fat, you're getting rid of the visceral fat,
the fat around the organs, which is the heart of the matter. The insulin resistance is fatty liver,
the beta cell failure is fatty pancreas. You're getting rid of that first. And that's why that
diabetes goes away so quickly before you see significant weight loss. So the whole pathophysiology
makes sense to me. And to me, I call it medical bariatrics. Fasting is what I call medical
bariatrics. You get all the benefits of bariatric surgery without doing any surgery because you can
get almost everything the same. Like obviously, it's a lot more, you know, you have to do it.
The compliance with bariatric surgery is easier than the compliance with fasting. I guess for me,
I don't know, I still entertain the notion that there may be more than one way to skin this cat,
and that I think bariatric surgery is probably a great example of putting three things in place.
I've actually seen data that look at making no change to a patient other than altering the
morphology of the duodenum, and that improves type 2 diabetes, which again, if you bypass the duodenum,
you would bypass what that problem is there. So because, you know, the thing with the bariatric
surgery patients is they're not fasting for that long, right? They're going to have fasted for
12 to 18 hours before surgery. And nowadays, those patients are dripping in liquids that are
caloric, even the day of or the day after surgery. So they might have a 24 hour fast,
but there's no question that their caloric intake is lower during that first three or four days.
But remember that you've got the malabsorption too, right? So the Roux-en-Y is both restrictive
and malabsorptive, right? That is not only do you restrict how much they can eat, the amount they
eat doesn't all get absorbed. And that's why I get dumping syndrome and so on. I agree with you.
That's a good point. It's hard to do it based on just how much they're eating. I mean,
technically, we don't know how much they're absorbing. I like your term, right? Which is,
look, let's just refer to this as medical bariatrics, and it's super potent.
When you have purely restrictive things like the lap band, it's like, boy, those things didn't
work at all, right? We thought they'd be great lap bands, purely restrictive, easy to put in,
and so on. And it's like, yeah, you look at the numbers of people and they're just dropping.
My friend who is a surgeon says, yeah, he used to put in lots of lap bands. He says, now,
the most common procedure I do is removal of lap bands because everybody wants to get rid of them
because the pure restriction didn't work because they're dripping in. They're drinking sodas and
they're drinking milkshakes and stuff, and they're not getting the malabsorptive part, which is that
rue on Y, and therefore that was the problem. But I agree with you. I'm not against bariatric
surgery. I just think that as a sort of solution for everybody, it's a much more difficult problem
because there's a lot of expenses. There's a lot of expertise as opposed to the sort of easy thing,
which is, hey, everybody can do fasting. It's just a matter of spreading knowledge and making
it easy, right? It's not that people can't fast. It's that people tell them they shouldn't fast,
right? Like if you go and look at Ramadan or something like that, right? People can fast.
If it's the norm or Lent or the orthodox, if you look at what the norm is, people can follow that.
It's just that the norm is so far off. We tell our kids, oh, hey, you got to have a snack. You got to
have a, you know, you have kids, right? It's like after school, it's a snack. Like you get a,
you know, the other day I got a thing home saying, oh, your son is going on a trip,
but don't worry. We're going to give him lots of snacks. I'm like, oh, like, why,
why did you need to do that? Right? Or, you know, you send your kids to play soccer,
which I do, right? I did net they don't anymore. And it's like, somehow, everybody thinks that
between the halves of soccer, the parents were taking turns bringing snacks. It's like,
you don't need to give them juice and cookies in between halves of soccer. Just let them play the
game. The game is fun, right? But it's, it's this culture where it says you must eat all the time.
This skipping breakfast is perfect example. Oh, as soon as you get up, you got to start putting
muffins in your mouth. Otherwise you're going to die, right? You're going to die of heart attack.
Like what the hell? Did you see the publication a couple of weeks ago that suggested that
people who skipped breakfast had a higher cardiac mortality? Yeah, that's what I was referring to.
It's like, Oh my God, what's your explanation for that study? I'm sure you've been asked about it a
dozen times. Because these nutritional epidemiology studies are so dangerous, right? It's because
those people, if you tell everybody that you have to eat breakfast, then you're going to select a
group of people who don't listen to you, right? And they're going to be unhealthier. They're
unhealthier in a lot of ways you can't measure. You can measure smoking, you can measure this,
but there's so many things that you can't measure that are going to influence why those people who
skip breakfast are more likely to have heart attacks. That association may exist, but it's
not causal. And that's, that's the thing, right? It's a correlation, not a causation. And it's a
very dangerous assumption to say that, Hey, you can eat breakfast and now prevent heart attacks,
because that's what gets out into the press. Put a muffin in your mouth as soon as you wake up and
you'll have less heart disease. That's not what the study shows, but that's the implication that
always comes out in the press. My issue with these studies, some of yours, I suppose, is that
there's a non-healthy user bias to a lot of these. So the, one of the more obvious examples of the
studies that suggest that diet sodas are, you know, worse for you than sodas. But of course,
it misses a very obvious or clear thing that, you know, might be missing, which is who are the
patients who are going to disproportionately consume diet sodas. You know, certainly a subset
of them might be people who are more health conscious and say, well, if I want a soda,
I'd rather it be diet than not. But it's more often that people who are being told, look,
you can't have a regular soda. And so therefore you're selecting for less healthy patients.
That is my interpretation of that study. Now, while we're on that topic,
do you think there are clinical benefits from a 16-8, just to use that example,
time restricted feeding pattern? So if you, if you said to a patient who came in to see you,
I want you to only eat between noon and 8 p.m., nothing outside of that,
but you don't make any other change. Do you see them get better?
We do. So I think that you would do better if you fix what they eat inside that eight hours too.
But if you take their diet and just squish it into eight hours, I think that, like we see people
get better. Like we see people change a lot because as I said, we did sort of one meal a day
where we squish it even further. And those people basically, they didn't even change their diet that
much. We talked to them about it, but we didn't focus a lot on it. And if you actually probably
were to ask them, my guess is their diet didn't change a huge amount. But just by squishing the
time that you're eating, you're sort of forcing people away. And I think part of the issue is that
in the old days, like in the seventies, what you had was a fairly lengthy fasting period anyway.
That's why you have the term breakfast, right? So you eat dinner at 6 p.m. and you eat breakfast at
8 a.m. It's 14 hours of fasting as your baseline, right? And that's every day without even thinking
about it. Now it's kind of spread, right? Sachin Panda has done all these studies about how long
people actually eat. And it's like, you know, constantly the minute they wake up to the
mini gutter bed, it's almost 15 hours a day that people are eating. I think that's gotten so bad
that when you squish it back to a normal sort of 16, eight sort of thing, because 14 hours and 16
hours, like 14 hours was sort of baseline in the seventies and 16 is just a little bit. But because
it's gotten so bad when you squish it back into that, we do see a lot of people who benefit just
from that one intervention alone. And, you know, to me, it's always about practicalities. That is,
is it easier? So if you have people, for example, say two strategies, one is counting carbs,
which I think can work versus counting the number of hours that you don't eat. It's like, it's so
much easier to tell people between 12 and eight, as you're eating window, everything else don't eat,
versus look at everything that you eat in the day, try and calculate how many carbs it is,
and add it up so that you have some arbitrary less than, right? Less than 120, less than 50,
less than 20. It's so difficult, whether you're counting calories or whether you're counting
carbohydrates or doing macros, right? It's just so difficult to do. It's so much easier to say
things like only eat between this hour and this hour, and don't eat anything that came in a box
kind of thing, right? Those, to me, that's practical, useful advice, as opposed to say,
let's get your carbs from 55% to 40%. It's like, it's so difficult. It's just, and I'm not saying
that it can't work. I think it can work. I just think it's so hard to implement when you're
seeing patients sort of every few minutes, right? Like, how are you going to do that from a practical
standpoint, right? It's not feasible. I completely agree. I mean, I think there is no simpler
instruction than when to eat and when not to eat. And yeah, I think, you know, combining these things
can often be incredibly potent. I don't know. I've seen mixed results on 16.8, truthfully.
I've seen some patients who have really significant improvement. I've seen other patients
experience no improvement whatsoever. We typically will push that window tighter, 18.6, 22.2. Again,
the tighter you push it, the more benefits you see, but I've really seen no substitute for
what I call intermittent fasting. We use that terminology very distinctly. We reserve the term
time restricted feeding for up to 24 hours of restriction, but we use the term intermittent
fasting to describe what I think that term means, which is you intermittently, periodically, i.e.,
fast. And fasting can be a complete reduction of calories or it can be a hypocaloric fast. So you
can consume somewhere between 20 and 40 percent of your normal caloric requirement for a period of
time. Typically, look at three to seven days and you repeat that cycle. What type of protocols do
you use for intermittent fasting with your patients? We use all of them. So because we're
predominantly clinical, we'll individualize. So the things we take into account is one,
how severe is it? So severe type 2 diabetic on a huge amount of insulin. We're going to give a
more stringent schedule than somebody who's just sort of pre-diabetic and wants to sort of prevent
it from getting into diabetes. So the other thing is how old they are and how willing they are to do
it. So we see a lot of people who are in their 80s. We have people in the 80s doing like, you know,
we had a lady who was like, I think she did 61 days, right? And she's not young, right? And we
have people in the 80s, nothing. Yeah, that's what she said. Although sometimes when you actually go
into it, sometimes they have little things here and there. But she said she did 61. We have lots
of people who do long fast like that and they don't have any problems. We monitor them very
closely though, but generally we don't do that. There's no point taking that much risk a lot of
times. She actually just felt good on it. So that's why she did it. But we don't usually push it long
like that, but we will if we need to. But it depends on how quickly. So it's how severe is it,
how old the patient is and how urgent it is because we have people who have a ton of disease,
right? And we're like, if you don't get this diabetes fixed, like right now, you're going to
be in a world of trouble. So we had this guy, he was actually in his 40s. He had a non-healing
diabetic foot ulcer for like a year followed by a plastic surgeon. So he actually came into the
hospital and I saw him because I was seeing him for his diabetic foot infection, gave him antibiotics.
I said, you know, your problem is not your foot. Your problem is your diabetes, right? Because
you know, the reason you have this foot ulcer is because of diabetes. You don't get foot ulcers
if you're not diabetic, right? Unless you have severe PVD or something, right? But the point is
that if it's diabetes was just causing your foot ulcer, you got to get rid of your diabetes. So I
talked to his dad because this guy was like in his 40s and the dad was Greek Orthodox. So his dad was
like, oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Let's do this. So we put them on and we put them on fairly strict
restriction. We started from, I think on a week of fasting and then 36 hours, three times a week.
And that ulcer healed like within three weeks. It was like ridiculous how quick that thing
just healed up. You led with a single week of fasting before cycling 36 hours weekly, or did
you lead with the 36 hours? No, I started with the seven days and then we did like 36 hours because
it was severe. Honestly, he was going to get his foot chopped off at some point.
You're definitely more aggressive than I am because you're seeing much sicker patients.
I never lead off with water only fasting for patients. Usually what we do is we go,
we push the windows of time restriction, which as I said a moment ago, I'm not convinced there's
huge benefit in time restriction. I think there's some benefit. I think the biggest benefit of time
restricted feeding is the psychological one. It's breaking the cycle you just described
earlier, which is people think intravenous access to food is essential for life. If they
go more than two hours without a meal, the sky is going to fall. And so in many ways,
time restricted feeding is just a way to prove to them that that is total nonsense.
I actually think that the long fasts do exactly the same thing.
Well, yes, yes, yes, but you can't lead. I mean, at least for me, I haven't tried leading off with
that. Talk me through that particular patient. So first of all, let's grant it that he now has
agreed to try this. This is a patient who is not entering a fast the way I would enter a fast,
which is I usually spend a week in ketosis before the fast, which means I'm showing up in a fast
with a ketone level of somewhere between 0.5 and one millimolar of beta hydroxybutyrate.
I sail generally pretty easily into these fasts, not all the time.
This is a guy who's got a respiratory quotient of one. He is a completely
obligate glycogen consumer. He's probably not oxidized a fatty acid since Guns and Roses were
popular. This is a guy who's going to be in for a world of hurt when you strip food away from him,
because within a few hours he's going to sense his liver will sense glycogen levels are low.
It's time to eat. So how are you getting him through that?
There's no easy way. We just tell him this is going to suck for a week because you're not going
to feel that great. You're going to be hungry and all this sort of stuff. It was the urgency.
I'll tell you that people actually can do it. Quite a lot of people have. We've done it on a
number of people. Most of the people, as long as you warn them ahead of time that it's going to
be tough, they get through it. But the thing is, the psychological, if you've done a week,
you know that 24 hours is like nothing and you get into ketosis so fast because that's the fastest
way to get into ketosis. It's just too fast. There's no faster way you can do it than that.
So it's not easy, but there's reasons why. That's why I say it's important that everything is
individualized because I'd never do this to somebody who's like 40 and has an A1c of like 6.0.
It's like, why put yourself through that? Do it gradually. You have no time restrictions.
This is a guy who's actually coming into the hospital with diabetic foot ulcers that were
getting close to osteomyelitis. It's a much different situation than not. I'm trying to
make sure that somebody doesn't wind up getting a bad infection and somebody wind up chopping
his foot off, which is why I was super aggressive in that case. I've heard stories of other people
who have put patients on starting 10-day fast and so on. So they don't all do well. They don't all
get through it, but it's an option. That's all I'll say. I hate to be prescriptive like,
oh, you have to do this. You have to do this. This is what seeing patients does to you.
I find that the people who are super dogmatic are the people who never see patients.
Yeah, I can't agree with you more.
Yeah, because patients always prove you're wrong. You think your stuff works. Well,
like 40% of your patients it doesn't work in. So then I'm never like, oh, you have to do this.
You have to do this because it's like, yeah, I know it doesn't work. Like carb restriction,
like some people it really does work well. And some people it really doesn't work that well.
And the study show the same thing, right? Chris Gardner's study. If you look at the splay between
low fat and low carbs, some people do great on a low fat diet and some people do terribly on a
low fat diet. It's the same diet. Same with the low carb. In general, the low carb people do better.
But when you look at the individual differences, and that's why people get on,
get on Twitter and they start talking about, Oh, it's all about this, or it's all this, all this.
Then it's like, I know you don't treat people because if you actually treated people,
you'd never say stuff like that. You'd never get on somebody about taking the opposite position
because you've been proven wrong. So many like every day I'm proven wrong, like something doesn't
work. And that's why I'm always like, let's do this. See if it works. If it doesn't work, we're
going to adjust it. And then if it works better, then we're going to keep doing that and we'll
adjust it. Right. And that's, that's where the kind of art of medicine comes in. So you can start,
but to me, I always tell people like there's two options when you do fasting. You, it's like going
into a pool you can wait in or you can cannonball and both are acceptable. One's a big shock to the
system, but it works. And the other is not as big a shock and it still works for this particular
patient. You know, that was one of the few few times because most of the time it's not that urgent
that I did recommend, Oh, you just got to do this. And his father was on board and he was on board
and we monitored him super closely. We actually started him in hospital because he happened to
be in the hospital anyway. So I put him on clear fluids, right? And then just told him, don't take
anything with sugar, just, just water. And, and, and he did very, very well. And I've done it to
a few other people with diabetic foot ulcers as well, because I consider that one of the,
the more difficult, like that's, that's something that you really have to take care of. And I always
think diabetic foot ulcers to me is fascinating because it's like, if you think about this
overflow paradigm, it's like, why do diabetics get these infections that nobody else gets? Why do you
get mucomycosis? Why do you get osteomyelitis? Why do you get diabetic foot ulcers? You don't get like
foot ulcers from ischemic cardiomyopathy foot ulcer, right? You don't get that ischemic cardiomyopathy
or mycosis. It's like, it's because what you're doing is you're putting all this sugar into the
body. Then when the blood glucose goes up, you give them insulin to really jam that sugar into
the body, right? And the body takes it and your liver gets all this sugar and starts sending it
all over the place. Pretty soon, your whole body is so full of sugar that everything just starts
rotting. And that's why you get the kidney disease. That's why I get the eye disease. And that's why
the bugs just love it because there's so much sugar and nutrients everywhere. So they get in
your foot and they never go away. Those foot ulcers never heal. You get these weird infections that
you never see anywhere else. You get the, you know, the rashes, the anacanthosis and all that.
It's just, you've got way too much sugar. It's all about the whole body sugar and not just the blood
sugar. That's the real shift in thinking in paradigm that to me makes a lot of sense. And as
soon as we're able to empty out all that sort of sugar, and I always use the analogy of a sugar
bowl, we're just filling up the sugar bowl, you got to empty that sugar bowl and then the sugar
won't spill out. And that's why it works. And the fast thing is the same thing. So we'll individualize
it. So based on all those sort of factors, like including what they want to do, right? You got to
talk to people and say, what are you willing to do? Right? And a lot of people aren't willing to
do a long fast, but a lot of people are actually, it's striking. What percentage of your patients
are willing to do a water only fast for at least a period of three days? Right off the bat, because
we offer this as a treatment to everybody. We don't say, okay, well, if you've never heard of it,
we'll still recommend it. And like 50% right off the bat won't do it. Any fasting at all, right?
They're so like ingrained. And I had this discussion yesterday with a fellow. I told him, oh, he needs
to fast. He was, he was developing, you know, pro-nuria and he was going into renal failure. And
I said, really, you need to fast. And he says, my endocrinologist says, I can't fast. No way.
So it's like, okay, that's it right there. So 50% of people won't fast for any period of time
at all. Like not even like five hours, right? So it's changing. I think views on fasting are
changing, but you can see like, you know, did you read that whole thing with Jack Dorsey? He gets on
CNBC or whatever. And everybody goes like crazy that, oh, he doesn't eat for 24 hours.
It's like, what's the big deal? Like, why do you think we carry body fat? Right? And it's like,
look, he's looking good. He feels good. What's the big deal? Why are you getting on him? Right?
But the idea is so ingrained that we have to eat, have to eat, have to eat, even to lose weight,
we have to eat that they won't do it. So if you take away the 50% who won't do it right off the bat,
then you have people who will do it for short periods of time. And probably only about 20% might
agree to like a longer fast mostly. And it's not the physical side that actually gets them. It's
always the psychological side. The physical stuff is super easy to deal with. It's the psychological
part. That's really hard. That is, when you're looking at somebody who's eating and you're
trying to fast, it's like really hard, right? And yeah, you can do it once in a while. But if you do
it sort of breakfast, lunch, dinner, breakfast, lunch, that's the hard part. And that's where
we focus a lot of our attention working on the psychological how to set your environment up for
success and coming up with different strategies for success and creating a supportive community
that's going to help your success. That's the hard part. Because think about religions like Ramadan,
how do they all fast? Because people say, Oh, I could never fast. It's like, but you know,
that literally hundreds of millions of Muslims fast, it's like it's because the environment
is supportive. If all your friends are doing it and all your family, it's not fun, but it's not
that difficult to actually do it. And that's the difference. And now we're recommending it for
people who have no community. And that's what we're trying to create community of people who are
accepting. And also, that's part of the point of bringing it into the mainstream. I wrote a couple
of books about this, of course. And that's the point. If I wrote a couple of articles that I sent
to JAMA or something to get peer reviewed, first of all, the peer review would kill it. And then
second of all, you'd get no traction whatsoever. And then you're not doing anybody any good, because
by making it sort of more out there, you make it more acceptable for people to talk about it and
to accept it as a viable treatment. So let's go through some of the stuff. So that, let's say that
40-year-old patient, first of all, appreciates the severity of what you've shared with him and his dad,
which is, look, it's one thing to have diabetes, which you do, but you're actually in quite a late
stage of this. If you're, I mean, I don't remember the literature on this, but from my days in surgical
training, the five-year mortality once you have an amputation with type 2 diabetes is staggering. So
I don't remember what it was, but it was so high that the point was once you're getting a toe
amputated or a foot amputated or something like that, the probability you're going to be alive in
five years is incredibly low. So I could be wrong on this, but I feel like the five-year mortality
was something like 70%. So if you're in your 40s and you're already getting a diabetic ulcer that's
not healing, there's a non-zero chance. There's actually a significant chance you're not going to
make it to your 50th birthday. So he says, I'm in, you mentioned something that I think can't be
overstated, which is you have to be in a supportive environment. So if a patient tries to fast and
they are surrounded by people, both their friends and family, and also their other medical practitioners
who are telling them this is a horrible idea, well, that's a recipe for failure. So now let's
posit that we've also got the support of the medical team and the friends and family. What are
some of the other tricks and trades? I mean, one of the things that I hear a lot about is, Peter,
my sleep is really hard when I'm fasting. How do you address that? Yeah, that's a tough one because
they all can't sleep. There's not that much to do. We tell them one to expect it. So it's one of the
things is that if they know about it ahead of time, then they're much more accepting. So we say, look,
you may have a lot of trouble going to sleep because people get so people don't understand,
but the whole sympathetic nervous system and everything that's revved up, right, nor adrenaline,
all that stuff gets revved up. And a lot of people actually can't sleep. And we say, well,
you know what, if you find that, then, you know, stay up, do some work and so on. And don't worry
about it, right? This is a temporary situation. It's not going to last forever. We just want to
make sure that everything gets better. And that patient, I don't think he had any sleep trouble,
but we did warn him. So one of the things we do is we warn him ahead of time of all the potential
problems. So it's like the book, what to expect when expecting, right? So it's not like it makes
the symptoms any better, but it makes dealing with it a lot better. So we tell him, Hey, look,
you can have headaches. Those will go away. You can have cramps. This is what to do. You can have
diarrhea. This is what to do. You can have constipation. This is what to do. Sleep is,
you know, you can expect this and you need to watch this in terms of your blood sugars and,
and so on. And this is what to do with your medications. And that patient, we actually,
I think his last A1C that we saw was like 5.9, which here is actually classified as non-diabetic,
not even pre-diabetic. So we took him from a couple of medications and a non-healing diabetic
ulcer to non-diabetic, like within a couple of months. Yeah. It took a little bit longer than,
than somebody else. And everybody responds differently. And even a couple of years later,
he's like non-diabetic, right? So it's like, that was the whole point we missed,
you know, in medicine, it's so difficult because we're so ingrained into these patterns of thinking.
That is you have obesity, which causes type two diabetes, which causes a foot ulcer. So we get the
plastic surgeon to, to bribe the ulcer. It's like, that's the least important part. You need to get
rid of the diabetes and get rid of the obesity. And then he will actually get better. So warning
people ahead of time is one thing that we do and it doesn't make the problem any better, but it makes
them deal with it. One, they, they trust you because they go, Oh, Hey, I got a headache for
three days. And then it went away. So they, they know, you know what you're doing. And that gives
them confidence. And then just having that support. So he had his, his father of course, who was going
yes, yes, yes, you need to do this. And that was, that came from his religion. So it was a good set
up for that. Many times we'll actually get the opposite, which is what you're saying is that
I'll get that patient. I'll say, this is what you need to do. The family says, Oh man, that's crazy.
And the family doctor says, Oh man, that's crazy. And the endocrinologist says, you must never do
this. Then nothing changes, right? They have this and so on. My tip on this one, Jason is that in
anticipation of that sympathetic outflow, we recommend that patients take phosphatidylserine
with the fast in the evening. And that sort of calms down the adrenal glands. And then even just
an oral over the counter GABA, unfortunately it's becoming harder to get centrally penetrating GABA
over the counter, but even just peripheral GABA will, will sort of take down some of that
sympathetic tone. So that coupled with some other sort of sleep supplements actually not only tends
to help people sleep, but a number of people note that you can have some of the best sleep imaginable
with those lower levels of glucose, higher levels of ketones. Now, what about electrolytes? How do
you manage the electrolytes in particular sodium and magnesium during these longer fasts?
There's nothing specifically we do actually. So we monitor it very closely of course. Magnesium is
the one, so everybody worries about sodium and you can get some people who do get a bit sodium
depleted, but if you're otherwise healthy, your kidneys should never get to that state because
there are people from the intersalt study, there are people that actually barely eat any salt at
all and still survive fine. So your body should be able to reabsorb all the sodium it needs.
Magnesium is a bit more difficult because a lot of type 2 diabetics are depleted of magnesium to
start. So we'll often recommend magnesium supplements and that's where a lot of the
cramps and so on kick in. Some people do get a little dizzy and so on. So that's when we use
the bone broth, which is technically not a fast, but it's got calories and amino acids and stuff.
But that's where we'll use bone broth for example, where you can put a decent amount of salt in
and take it and still feel well. We monitor the electrolytes more just because we want to make
sure that nobody's getting into trouble. But I'll tell you that the number of times that I've
actually had to intervene or tell somebody to stop a fast because of electrolytes is like zero,
I think. I don't think I've ever had a case where the blood work came back and said,
oh my god, they have to stop. There are some other things like if they get diarrhea, for example,
it can be fairly significant, then that might play a role. But when they get those, we tell them stop.
We're always super cautious because we monitor them very closely. These are relatively sick
patients, right? So they generally have a lot of medical issues, but we monitor them very closely
and we give them very careful instructions that, hey, if you don't feel well, you need to stop
right away. Don't even tell me. Stop it. And then tell me, right? Because the point is that you can,
let's figure out what's going on. Then if it's a solvable problem, then we can do it starting
tomorrow or we can do a totally different regimen, shorter, fast, more frequently. We're not stuck to
this one thing or we can do ketogenic diets or we can do something else, right? There's all kinds
of things that we can do without doing a long fast. And some people actually hate the long fast and
some people actually love the long fast. So we always say, don't get so rigid in your thinking
that you have to push through. The one thing we tell people more than, don't just push through
because that's when you're going to get yourself into trouble. There's always tomorrow to start
another fast if we figure out what's going on with this. Don't you find it's helpful to explain what
you're pushing through? I mean, for example, even if I fast for seven days, there is no day during
that seven when I am not at least at one point quite hungry. Oh yeah, the hunger for sure. We
always say you can be hungry, but make sure you're not like lethargic or something. I think it's
important for patients to understand even seasoned fasters still get hungry. But what I find
interesting in my wife who doesn't fast but is sort of interested in why I do it, she can't
believe it, right? She can't believe that I'll work long hard days and exercise and do all that stuff
while fasting. And she's like, aren't you just starving? And I said truthfully, yes, every single
day I feel quite hungry at some point in the day, but it's never more hungry than on a regular day
if I'm getting really hungry. Being hungry on the seventh day of a fast is not a more profound
hunger. It's the anticipation of that that becomes problematic, which really speaks to the Shakespeare
quote about nothing is either good or bad, but thinking simply makes it so. The anticipation
of that hunger seems to be a bigger problem. Maybe for your patients, it's less of a concern
because the highest priority is the amelioration of the diabetes. But do you spend much time
thinking about how they can minimize muscle mass loss with the obvious loss of protein intake? Or
do you just say, look, it's so intermittent that we do this fasting that we're going to take whatever
we have to take in the most catabolic sense and then deal with it on the back end? Or do you do
anything specifically with respect to exercise? Nothing specifically, because again, I'm treating
different population. Like I'm not treating bodybuilders, right? I'm treating 65 year old women.
For them, it's like they don't even know how much muscle mass they have. And honestly, I'm not even
sure. Like there is some protein loss and I'm not sure that's a bad thing. I mean, I think that
most people actually don't get a lot of muscle loss. Like you can get protein loss, which is
connective tissue and skin. And this is one of the things that people always rag on me about,
but it's, this is clinical medicine, right? So I've treated thousands of people with fasting and
some have lost a lot of weight, like hundreds of pounds. And I've, I've documented a few case
studies in my blog and stuff. And one of the things that's very unusual about fasting for
weight loss as opposed to weight loss for other things is that we don't see the skin problems
because skin is protein. Like it's not fat, right? Skin connective tissue, it's protein.
And you do go, when you do the intermittent fasting, you do go through that period where
you have gluconeogenesis and you're breaking down protein. That's the whole point of autophagy,
for example, is breaking down protein. It's not fat. And I'm not sure that it's bad thing.
So we actually get much less. I've never referred a patient for skin removal surgery. And some people
have lost like 150 pounds for like years, right? And they actually don't notice the problem. A couple
of my colleagues who I work with and they, they've noticed the same thing that you don't have as many
of the problems that you do with regular sort of weight loss, which is chronic calorie restriction,
where you get these big flaps of skin that you have to go in surgically and take out. The question
is why doesn't your body get rid of them? Because it's superfluous. Your body shouldn't be keeping
it around. Your body should be getting rid of it. And it doesn't because you never went through
this period where you're undergoing gluconeogenesis, where you actually are breaking down protein.
So do you get more muscle loss? There's been a couple of studies on alternate daily fasting,
which really haven't shown increased muscle loss or lean loss. I think that the protein loss is
often confused and called muscle loss. To me, it makes no sense. Like your body has a system. And
I'm not talking the situation where you have 4% body fat, right? I'm talking about a situation
where you have 30% or more body fat. It makes no sense that the body should store food energy
as glycogen and body fat. But the minute you need to use it, you start burning muscle.
Do we think our bodies are really just that stupid that they're going to do that? It's like
storing firewood for the winter. And then as soon as you need to use it, you chop up your sofa and
throw it in the fire. Like who would do that? But we think that our bodies are just that stupid.
Like I don't think their bodies are that stupid. I think that there's a period which is fairly
limited during the fasting where you have gluconeogenesis. Then you can see fat oxidation goes
way up. And Kevin Hall, I think did some of these studies on what happens. And
Cahill of course did all those studies on what happens during actual starvation. You got to
remember that he was no wimp. These are like 60 days of fasting, not like 16 hours. It was huge.
And these people were not even overweight. There are some studies that you just think,
wow, how did they get away with that? It was before the days of the IRB.
I know. There is a great study. I don't know if you've seen this. There's two studies where they
took people who were not even overweight. They fasted them for 60 days and gave them a big slug
of insulin. It's like, why? It's like just to see what would happen.
Well, no, no. I mean, that study was to actually see if the ketones were protective in the presence
of hypoglycemia. They injected those patients with insulin, took their glucose down to below
one millimolar. These people were walking around with it. Yeah, they did totally fine,
provided they had enough BHB. That's incredible. Yeah, it's incredible. But you'd never get that
study done today. You'd get thrown out, like you'd get laughed at right by the IRB. You're going to
drop people's glucose to less than one. Are you serious? Everybody now thinks if you don't eat for
24 hours, you can get seizures, right? But the point is that, yes, it was for the ketones and
stuff. But it's a great study, stuff that you just couldn't do these days. But the amount of protein,
so when you look at all the Cahill studies and all the classic studies of fasting,
that's a relatively limited period that you're actually burning. You've got the gluconeogenesis
in your burning protein, which I actually think is a beneficial thing in the right situation where
you have somebody with obesity and so on. And if you look at studies like Natal did a bunch of
these studies and he tried to estimate how much excess protein somebody who is overweight has,
it's like 20 to 50% more protein than a regular person. There's more skin, there's more muscle,
there's more connective tissue, there's blood vessels, there's all kinds of extra protein that
goes along with being overweight. And that all needs to go if you're going to do it. So I'm not
actually worried. So again, I've treated a few thousands of patients with type 2 diabetes.
Remember, I'm not talking about the guy who has 4% body fat and is a body builder and can
tell how much muscle he has based on how much he can live. I'm talking about the 65-year-old
person with a lot of body fat and generally excess protein. In that case, the question is,
how many patients have I had to stop because I was worried about muscle loss? That would be
like zero in six years. And because I use it in a therapeutic manner, that is, I'm not treating one
person a week sort of thing. It's like every person who comes in every 10 minutes, I'll say,
this is what you need to do. This is what you need to do. So it's just part of my clinical practice.
So it's like hundreds of patients a year and over six years, it's like thousands of patients,
like zero people had to stop because I was worried about muscle loss. So it's like, okay,
tell me how that is going to be a big concern to me. And this is where, again, it's like
people who don't fast and people rag on me all the time about this. It's like, oh,
what about this? What about this? I'm like, okay, how many thousands of patients have you done this
for? Try it on several thousand patients and then come back to me and tell me if muscle loss is the
most important thing for this 65-year-old 300-pound man on 150 units of insulin.
It's a totally different situation. Last question, because I know you've got to get back to clinic.
We've taken you away from it. Do you think there's a role for this type of fasting in people who
are actually healthy but looking to get benefit that goes beyond getting rid of a disease they
don't have? In other words, if you take a person who's not hyperinsulinemic, i.e. insulin sensitive
by these definitions, though, we made a pretty good case that everybody's insulin sensitive
without a lepidistrophy, but you take a non-obese, non-diabetic, non-naphal, the insulin sensitive,
non-hyperinsulinemic individual who's asking the question, will periodic fasts reduce my odds of
chronic disease down the line? How do you feel about that? Absolutely, yes, because look,
the point of fasting is to lower insulin levels. If you fast and you're healthy and you're not
hyperinsulinemic, well, if you do periodic fasting, it doesn't have to be a long time or
even that frequent. If you look at the 70s, a typical person who is eating three meals a day,
14 hours of fasting every day, and then once a year maybe on Yom Kippur or during Lent or
during Ramadan, he'll have a little bit longer fast. But there are times he's eating a lot too,
Christmas and all this sort of time. That's just the balance. It's all about balance.
This is the whole point is that you have to balance periods where you have going to take
a lot of food like Christmas. You're eating, you're eating, you're eating, you're eating.
Now you want to balance that with Lent where you're just not going to eat a lot because that's what
they told you to do. This is what's going to happen is that you're going to drop your insulin
levels periodically, which will prevent you. It's going to clear out all that sugar every once in a
while and then prevent you from getting diseases of hyperinsulinemia. So if you drop your insulin
every so often, you're going to prevent yourself or lower your chance of getting diseases of
hyperinsulinemia, which are heart disease, stroke, cancer, Alzheimer's disease, type 2 diabetes,
obesity. Well, that's the major risk of our current population. So you want to lower your risk of
getting those? Great. Like you're not going to lower your risk of getting pneumonia. Like you're
going to lower your risk of these diseases of hyperinsulinemia. So for a healthy person,
yes, I think fasting is very beneficial, but you don't have to do five days of fasting every month
or something like that, right? You could do a little bit longer fasting once in a while and maybe
not do some bedtime snacks and stuff. But you don't buy the argument then that, for example,
of Altralongo's FMD, which is a type of intermittent fast. I know you know what it is, but a listener
might not. So this is one of literally 100 different ways you could fast, but he would
suggest that based on a certain set of macronutrients, you're consuming about 1,000 calories,
followed by 750 calories for four days. And that gives you a five-day cycle. And he talks about
doing that quarterly and would argue that there are actual longevity benefits, even in the non-diabetic
or non-metabolically ill person. Again, I think for some people, that sounds really extreme.
Personally, I don't think it's that extreme. In your patients, that doesn't seem extreme.
It's actually fairly routine for a lot of people that we talk to. But again,
it's a different patient population. For healthy people, I think that the data is just not there.
So prevention of Alzheimer's, prevention of cancer, treatment of autoimmune diseases, for example,
of Altralongo's talking about sometimes. I don't think that there's enough data to say yes or no.
Could it work? Absolutely, it could work. I actually think that there's a good reason to
think that these things will work to prevent a lot of those diseases. Not necessarily. So of course,
to me, all the diseases of excessive growth and hyperinsulinemia, to me, clearly are going to
reduce your risk. But now you're talking about other diseases like autoimmune diseases. And I
think that there's good reason to think why they might work. But is there data to show it? Not
really. Yeah, this gets back to the first point of will we ever have evidence-based guidelines
to support this? I think it's impossible, not improbable. And therefore, we are stuck thinking
about this through mechanistic lenses. Yeah, but see, the thing is that, again,
people have it all wrong because people say, okay, so say they're talking about a five-day fast once
a quarter or something like that. Whether you do fasting mimicking or regular fasting,
let's say somebody says you should do five days of fasting once a quarter or once a year.
Okay, so the evidence-based medicine people are always way off because they say there is no
evidence to suggest that five days of fasting once a year is beneficial. They're right, but they're
completely wrong from a clinical perspective. Because there's also no evidence that five days
of fasting a year and a person who's normal weight and otherwise healthy is harmful to you. So now
you have to say, what is the risk of doing that five days of fasting? So five days, so in a year,
you will eat three meals a day. One year, you'll eat a thousand meals. For five days,
you're going to make 15 meals out of a thousand. That's it. That's the extent of what you're doing.
What is the risk of that? I'll tell you it's just about zero. Like, yeah, you're going to be hungry
and stuff. But if you're otherwise healthy, the risk is very, very, very low. And then you say,
what is the benefit? Well, there's not really any great evidence of benefit either, but because
your risk is so low, your risk to reward ratio is pretty reasonable. Why wouldn't you do it? That's
the question because the risk is so low. Maybe there's no benefit. Maybe there is a benefit.
I can't tell you, right? And it's the same for all drugs. You know that there's a certain number
needed to treat. So a number needed to treat a 50 means that 49 out of 50 people simply do not
benefit from that drug that you gave them. And it's going to be the same for fasting. There's
going to be one person who benefits and 50 people who don't benefit. But the risk to reward, because
when you give a drug, the risk starts getting so high that the risk, the reward ratios, they don't
make sense. But for something like fasting, missing 15 meals out of a thousand. Yeah, it can make sense.
And that's why, you know, all these sort of EBM zealots are all like, oh, there's no evidence.
There's no evidence. It's like you don't need evidence. It's assessing the risk and the reward
and what clinically makes sense. To me, if I had, for example, some kind of autoimmune disease,
so let's take this disease, rheumatoid arthritis, that there's no evidence that
fasting is going to do anything for. And Dr. Longo says, well, you know, you can reset your
immune system if you do seven days of fasting. What would I do? I would absolutely do it,
as opposed to taking a bunch of toxic drugs like prednisone. Like you've seen what prednisone does
to people. Why wouldn't I do seven days of fasting? The risk of that is zero. Say I don't get any
benefit from that. Then I don't have to do it ever again. But what happens if things get a lot better?
I've just treated my own disease. The reward can be so high, but you don't have to guess at it.
You can just do it. Speaking of risk, there's some, in my opinion, kind of weak epidemiology
suggesting that skipping breakfast will increase your risk of gallstones. How often are you seeing
that in your practice? A lot of people have gallstones. So I don't see an increased risk,
but on the other hand, it's going to be tough because the problem is that people who follow
a low fat diet, of course, their gallbladder, you don't need bile, right? You need bile to emulsify
the fat. So therefore your gallbladder just sits around with all this stuff and you get sludge and
so on. So I think the low fat diet can certainly predispose you to stones. Then you start eating a
higher fat diet and then it's squeezing out and you're getting stones. I don't see it clinically
as a problem. I think what caused a lot of the problems was probably the lower fat diet because
you're simply not getting the flow, the enterorhepatic flow. Like the bile is supposed to come out.
It's not supposed to sit there, but when you get rid of all the fat, it just sits there.
That's just the balance. Our body makes it, sticks it in the gallbladder so that when you eat fat,
you can squirt a little bit of it out. Now we think we're so much smarter than our body,
which has survived for millions of years, that we're going to eat zero fat and just have all this
stuff, the sludge just sit in the gallbladder because you never took it out.
Like how does that make sense? To me, it makes no sense.
Well, on that note, we are at exactly the time when I know you need to get back to clinic.
So I want to thank you greatly for your insights, both at the, what I would say are hugely paradigm
challenging level, especially as it pertains to insulin resistance and hyperinsulinemia.
And then also at the boots on the ground clinical level, I know that very few people have the
experience treating patients with fasting protocols for type 2 diabetes. And I think
you're doing fantastic work. So I want to thank you very much for that.
Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up
for my subjectively non-lame once a week email, where I'll update you on what I've been up to,
the most interesting papers I've read and all things related to longevity,
science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions
and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes
only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient
relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the
user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare
professionals for any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts
of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise,
please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.