Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives.
Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast,
that became clear to me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming.
I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information
with you. To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a
full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and their feedback has mirrored this.
So all of this raises a natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support
this? As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of
contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most
important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something
when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason
selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time
advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about
something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads,
I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can work over time, and that is to create
a subscriber support model for my audience. This keeps my relationship with you both simple and
honest. If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and support us at whatever level works
for you. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that
simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get
back more than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show
notes, including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts
for each episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature
of many of our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular
Ask Me Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also
getting to hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited
about, I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said,
we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies
who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them
pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of
you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive
for members to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a
moment to listen to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please
consider supporting us directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Dr.
Rick Doblin. Rick is the founder and the executive director of the Multidisciplinary Association for
Psychedelic Studies, better known as MAPS. Now, if you listen to the podcast that I did with Tim
Ferris, that name may sound familiar. We spoke quite a bit about Rick, well more so about MAPS
and really the work that they've been doing to legalize specifically MDMA, but other molecules
as well for medical use. Rick is, he's a force of nature and there's just no other way I can
describe this interview, how much I learned about a guy that I already sort of knew in terms of his
background, his passion, what motivated him. He's really a unique individual and at the very end of
the interview, I even sort of comment to that effect that there's just not that many people that can
really bend the arc of history the way I believe Rick is doing that. We spent about the first hour
and 20 minutes or so putting some background together, both Rick's background where his drive
for this came from and also the background of how these molecules, and we talked mostly about
LSD as an example, but how these molecules were synthesized, basically made broadly available and
utilized quite liberally and then ultimately how they were scheduled with the drug act of the early
70s. At that point in the podcast, we then turn our attention specifically to MDMA because what
I really wanted to focus on here was MDMA for several reasons. One, as I think I stayed in the
podcast, whether right or wrong, my personal opinion is MDMA is the single most important
synthetic molecule ever created by our species. Also, it's the closest one to being de-scheduled,
meaning taken from being an illegal drug that is a Schedule I to something that will have a medical
application and you'll see through this discussion how long it has taken to do that and what the
implications of that are. Of course, more importantly, you'll probably appreciate why we
would think that that's an important thing to do. When it comes to MDMA, we talk about a lot. We
talk about how it was created back in 1912, how it was rediscovered and resynthesized, where its
use, where it found its use, and how the parallel use of ecstasy as the party version of this drug
in some ways kind of, well not in some ways, I mean in many ways really hurt the clinical
application of MDMA, which was really where it started, how it was of course scheduled and made
illegal in 1985, which is relatively late compared to all of the other psychedelics. You can see that
through this discussion that MDMA is sort of not your typical psychedelic. Then how a year later,
Rick created maps and did everything from going off to the Harvard Kennedy School to get a PhD
to help him understand the regulatory morass he was going to have to navigate his way through
and right to where we are today, which is truly being on the cusp of legalizing this incredibly
powerful molecule that is going to help, in my opinion, literally millions of people.
So I'll just give you one example of something that we dive into pretty deep that I think people
are going to find very interesting, which is the toxicity of MDMA. So there are lots of rumors about
the toxicity of this drug and of course every drug has toxicity. So the point here isn't that it
doesn't have it, but the point is what is the toxicity and is it really what we were led to
believe with everything from depression, Parkinsonian syndromes, neuronal destruction, versus what's
actually happening. So a very nuanced discussion on that and I think we end with a message of hope,
which is one, there are going to be many people I think who listen to this who are going to wonder
what can they do to receive this therapy and we're going to talk about what those clinical trials
look like, what the enrollment looks like, and perhaps more importantly what a compassionate
use license would look like such that if there are patients who are in need of this therapy
prior to its approval, what are the legal paths to do that? I have to state something very important
that I feel strongly about. Of course, the Drug Enforcement Agency considers MDMA to be a schedule
one drug. That means it is illegal. That means according to the DEA, at least at the time of
that scheduling in 1985, they do not believe there to be a medical use and that they believe
that it has the high potential for abuse. Now, I think you'll see from this discussion, neither
Rick nor I agree with that at all, but we do have to respect the letter of the law. So there's
nothing in this podcast that I want to be construed as encouraging you and or endorsing the use of
illicit MDMA. I think there are more than sufficient legal channels by which people could pursue
compassionate exemption for the appropriate treatment of PTSD, which is at this point in time
where we believe MDMA is most valuable. So with that said, sit back and please enjoy
my interview and discussion with Dr. Rick Doblin. Before we begin this podcast, I want to point out
something that we did here a little different from what we've done in previous podcasts.
Rick and I sat down for a very lengthy conversation. And in the beginning, we spent a lot of time going
really deep into his background. Now, while I think this conversation is really interesting,
I also realize that the entire conversation is long and many of you may be tuning in
for more of what we talk about at the end, specifically as it pertains to MDMA. So what
we did is we took roughly the first hour and 15 minutes of this interview and put it at the end.
So what you're about to hear is where we pick up the conversation, again, roughly an hour 15 into
it, where we start to talk about maps and Rick's work on MDMA, which I think is what the majority
of you are probably wanting to hear about. Then at the end of that podcast, we will roll directly
into the initial conversation on Rick's background, which the diehards like me will find just as
interesting as this is a different sort of format than we typically do. Hopefully it makes sense and
you'll enjoy the interview, but it's our belief that this will create slightly better flow for
what you're about to hear. Rick, thanks so much for opening your home today. Oh, it's a pleasure
to have you here. Every once in a while, I get ready to sort of interview somebody and I think
to myself, this is highly applicable. This is incredibly broad. This topic we're discussing
is so important. And I don't know, as I was coming over here, I was talking to my wife
and she said, I can't believe I'm not there to listen to you guys have this discussion,
to which I said, you've never once listened to me record a single podcast. Why are you so interested
in this? And she's like, I don't know. I just, you've spoken about Rick so much and you've spoken
about MDMA so much that I just don't want to miss it. And I said, well, don't worry. It's going to
be recorded. You're going to be able to hear it with everybody else. But this is a discussion
I've wanted to have for such a long time. Now, in many ways, there's probably few people,
if any, that have done more to sort of right the wrongs of that era and that we're now 33 years
into an organization that you started that organization. You started in 1986 called MAPS.
Tell me what MAPS stands for and what you set out to do. So MAPS is multidisciplinary association
for psychedelic studies. I knew at the time that I wanted to have the word psychedelic in the title
of the nonprofit. So just to go back a little bit further. So in 1972, when I was at New College and
having difficulties with my psychedelic experiences, I went to the guidance counselor
at college and I asked for help. And I said, I'm having powerful, important experiences,
but I'm not able to fully integrate them. And I was just so fortunate. The guidance counselor gave
me a copy of a book, Realms of the Human Unconscious by Stan Groff about his work with LSD
before it was even published, manuscript copy. And it was reading that book that really helped me
see that here is science, here is spirituality, but viewed through a scientific lens. And it had
the reality check of therapy. It's focused on how do you help these people suffering from different
conditions grow. And so I felt that this was now everything together for me, science, mysticism,
spirituality, the sense of unity and therapy reality checks. So in 72 is when I decided to
become a psychedelic therapist. And I wrote a letter to Stan Groff and he ended up writing me
back. And I took a workshop with him in the summer of 72. And I did everything that I could
to try to elevate and expand my consciousness, including I have the delusion that the more I,
psychedelics I took, the faster I would evolve, which I underestimated the whole integration
process. So I basically then took 10 years to integrate. I dropped out of college. I didn't see
Stan anymore. I spent 10 years trying to get prepared to make psychedelics the forefront.
So I was in the construction business and build houses and build various things and got grounded
in this 10 year period. And every once in a while would take LSD and work on my fear. And so I went
back to college in 1982 at new college, the same college I had dropped out of. I'd built houses for
a couple of the professors. I figured out how I could sort of frame what I was doing as studying
transpersonal psychology and psychedelic psychotherapy. And so the very first semester
that I went back to school, Stan Groff was giving a workshop, a month long workshop at Esalen called
the Mystical Quest. And where's Esalen? Esalen is in Big Sur. It's about three and a half hours
south of San Francisco. It's on, perched on the cliffs overlooking the ocean. There's hot springs
that come up there. There's baths. It's sort of the cradle of the human potential movement.
You were just there. I was just there for a week long program on psychedelics where the entire
property, which fits around 120 people, it's sort of a commune, you could say, where they grow their
own food. Their job is to provide housing and workshops for people. They've been involved
since the 60s started by Dick Price and Michael Murphy. Fritz Pearls from Gasol Therapy lived
there. Ida Rolf from Rolfing. Stan Groff was there for about almost 15 years as scholar in residence.
All sorts of people have taught there and still going. And so this particular workshop that I
was just at had the largest waiting list in the entire history of Esalen since the 60s. They had
over a thousand people try to get into this program for 120 people. But I went there in September of
82 as the beginning of my going back to school. My first semester was going to be about creating a
curriculum to become a psychedelic therapist. And so during this month long at Esalen with Stan and
Kristina Groff, his wife, this woman named Debbie Harlow came by. She wasn't in the workshop,
but she came by to Esalen and she started talking about this new drug called Adam, which was MDMA.
And that it was used in therapy. It had been used in underground therapy circles since the middle 70s.
It was itself legal at the time, but it was kept quiet because this was again during the drug war
period. And that if it were made public, chances are it would be criminalized. And when we learned
about it in 82, when Debbie started talking about it, she also shared that it had escaped these
therapeutic circles and was being sold as the drug ecstasy. So it was clear that it was doomed.
It just wasn't clear when. And my initial impression of it was that I underestimated it.
You underestimated the drug or the backlash that would come against it?
The drug.
Okay.
Yeah. So she said it helps you feel love. It helps you feel connected. It helps you be a better
listener and helps you talk to people, speak from your heart. And I felt that I'm in love. I feel
love. I feel like I can talk. I saw a group of people doing it and they were just sitting
around in a circle talking to each other. And I thought, how profound can that be? When you take
250 micrograms of LSD, you can't talk. You go into this nonverbal place. That's what's really
profound. You go beyond your ego.
At that time, Rick, was the language that we now use to describe that distinction known,
was it understood that for example, psilocybin was an entheogen while MDMA was an empathogen?
Did we even understand what that meant in 82?
In 82, not quite then. So entheogen, I don't actually use that word because that's the God
within to generate a spiritual experience. I think that that word was created by Jonathan
Ott and others to try to create a counter to the word hallucinogen. So hallucinogen is
pejorative, negative. It's a delusion. It's negatively loaded. Enthiogen is sort of
positively loaded. It's going to be spiritual. Psychedelic is mind manifesting. It's neutral.
And it describes what it actually does. So I've chosen to try to reclaim the word psychedelic.
The empathogen is a really good word for MDMA, that it produces empathy. Others, Dave Nichols,
that was Ralph Metzner's word, empathogen. Dave Nichols proposed entactogen to mean to touch
within. And what was going on there, so that was really created, those empathogen, entactogen,
those words were created once we needed in our legal case to try to protect the use of MDMA.
It was to try to say that it wasn't like a traditional psychedelic. So I think in 82,
when I was first learning about MDMA, when I was foolish enough to underestimate it,
but smart enough to buy some, that it was clear that MDMA was not like a classic psychedelic.
There's no dissociation. There's no hallucination. You remember it as though you're completely awake.
It is really in a class of its own in that way, isn't it?
Yeah. Yeah. It's very good. And so that was the attempt to try to, the entheogen
word was just to try to balance out hallucinogen, but empathogen and tactogen was part of our legal
case to try to say this was a different class of drugs and you couldn't criminalize it the way
these others had criminalized it. That in the end failed. And psychedelic is a broader word,
mind manifesting. So I think that MDMA is a psychedelic, but it's not a classic psychedelic.
So once I learned about it and actually underestimated it, but bought some and
tried some and was then just profoundly impacted by how subtle it was and how
incredible of a drug it was. Do you remember the first time you took it?
Oh yeah. Oh yeah. I remembered it really well. I was with the girlfriend and we took it together.
And at one point we said this love we're expressing and experiencing is, it's really us. It's not a
drug delusion. It's liberating us to express what we really feel. I felt like the profundity and the
depth of connection was genuine and also something that we could learn from. I think one of the
things that makes this so helpful therapeutically in this drug is that because you're not dissolving
your ego, it's easier to integrate what happened. It's not that far away from normal consciousness.
It's a subtle shift with a reduction in fear and the amygdala in different areas.
It's just profound therapeutic. And so once I tried it, I thought that this was an incredible
opportunity because there was going to be a backlash, but it was still legal. And I had
learned about LSD, really the value of it in 71 and 72 after the backlash, which was 1970 and the
Controlled Substances Act and criminalization of all the psychedelics and the effort to squash
psychedelic research all over the world. So I felt I missed my moment.
You knew you had a small window, but you didn't know how big it was going to be.
Yeah. So I started a different nonprofit in 1984 before maps. What had happened actually,
and again, it's great that you're wearing the doors shirt because Laura Huxley was key to
my whole life. So in 1983, after I had learned about MDMA, I read this book by Robert Mueller,
who was the Assistant Secretary General of the UN. He was from France, a French resistance fighter.
He was the mystic of the UN. He'd been there for 40 years. The book was New Genesis,
Shaping a Global Spirituality. And so this book was about how the UN is for conflicts between
nations, but actually a lot of these conflicts are religious conflicts and how he felt we needed a
global spirituality that would enliven every particular religion. It's not like a one-world
religion, like one-world language, but it was the sense that religions are like languages. They're
all different ways of expressing something similar, a similar reality. And that if we move beyond my
religion as the one right religion, and if you don't follow it, you're an infidel or you're all
these religious wars that we've had over the centuries, this idea that there was this sort of,
we're all from the same planet. We all have more in common than separate. That's what Robert Mueller
wrote about this global spirituality and as the key to human survival. So I wrote him a letter
as a college undergraduate. And I said, I agree with what you say, but you don't say anything
about psychedelics. I told him about the Good Friday experiment. I mentioned MDMA as a tool
that could be used. And he wrote me back and introduced me to various people who were mystics
to share MDMA with them and see what they had to say. So this letter though, that I wrote to Robert
Mueller was Debbie Harlow Sott, who had introduced me to MDMA. She showed it to a friend of hers who
showed it to Laura Huxley. And so Laura thought, wow, I'm trying to do important political work,
outreach work. So I got invited to meetings that were taking place at Esalen organized by Dick
Price and others to try to figure out how to protect MDMA and how to bring this MDMA had sort
of revitalized the psychedelic underground because now there was a new tool that was tremendously
effective and it was legal. But there was a parallel sort of social drug that was coming out
as well. So when was ecstasy becoming the sort of parallel path for MDMA to become mainstream? Was
that about the same time? Yeah, that was about the same time. So Michael Klieg was one of the people
that had gotten MDMA under the name Adam in these sort of therapeutic contexts in private homes,
not all done by therapists and patients, but personal growth, private homes out of public
settings. Michael had been involved with being a cocaine dealer. Others, he knew other cocaine
dealers and he thought this was a tremendous drug and more people should know about it. And so he
created ecstasy. He created this ecstasy and started marketing it in public ways. And that was going
to attract the attention of the government, particularly at the Stark Club in Dallas was
where it became a real party drug. You could buy it over the counter 800 numbers. Michael had quite
a large operation. And was it at the time ecstasy pure MDMA or was it typically included with other
impurities or additional stimulants? It was pure MDMA. It was great quality and people had incredible
experiences and started sharing it more and more and more and more people wanted to do it. And so
it was used a lot. It was sort of the beginnings of the rave movement, the dance movement. It was
used in these more public settings. And so that was a concern to those of us that were interested
in trying to protect the therapeutic use that this public use was going to doom it. And we
actually contacted Michael and others. He approached us at different conferences. And so we got to know
who the underground manufacturers were. And basically I said that they owed a debt of gratitude
to the people that created MDMA and they should help us protect it. And so they did make some
donations for us to help in our legal efforts. And just to give listeners the background, right? I
mean, MDMA, again, like LSD, completely synthesized manmade originally synthesized in 1912, I believe.
Yeah. Somewhat forgotten about, correct? Yeah. So MDMA was invented by Merck Pharmaceutical in 1912.
They were actually looking to evade a competitor's patent on getting to a different drug. And so they
had a whole different synthetic route and they patented every step along the way, MDMA being one
of them, but they weren't looking for MDMA. It was just an intermediary towards the other ultimate
goal. Yeah. And then they did nothing with it. World War I came along. It's a German pharmaceutical
company and they actually didn't test it in animals until 1927. And at that point in time,
they found nothing of interest and abandoned it. It's funny to me, by the way, to imagine animals
on MDMA. That's such an interesting concept. Like would it do anything to an animal? Do they?
Well, it does actually. And so some researchers at Johns Hopkins have done studies with octopuses
with MDMA. So as it turns out, octopuses- You can make them less ornery? Yes, you can. They're
solitary creatures unless it's mating season. And so they've got this experimental contraption.
This is a digression, but it's worthwhile. They've got this experiment. So they put an octopus in the
center chamber and then they have two chambers off of each side. One has an inanimate object in it,
in a kind of a birdcage so that it doesn't move in a larger area. And the other has an octopus in
this sort of birdcage, so it doesn't move either. So under normal circumstances, the octopus will
spend way more time with the inanimate object than with the other octopus. They don't really like
being with other octopuses. We supplied the MDMA for this experiment, we meaning maps. So we ended
up that they figured out how to dose the proper amount of MDMA in the water. So they soak the
octopus in a bath of MDMA infused water for 10 minutes. And then they put the octopus back in
this experimental contraption. And lo and behold, now they spend way more time with the other
octopus. And humans and octopuses diverged 250 million years ago. And so the big question that
the experimenters had is first off, would octopuses react to MDMA at all? And then secondly,
even if they did, would it have any kind of similar effect as it does in humans? And it turns out that
it does. Suggesting that whatever MDMA is doing is in a primitive enough part of our brain,
meaning it was still there before the bifurcation of us. Yes, yeah, yeah. Suggesting it's not in the
cortex. Yes, and also that it's something that we're not only in the cortex. Exactly, not exclusively
in the cortex. And also that the FDA has told us that if we manage to prove safety and efficacy in
adults, they want us to do work in adolescence with PTSD. And if that works, they want us to go
down to seven to 11 year olds. So it suggests to me that working with the octopus that young children
who've been traumatized may still benefit from MDMA even if they don't have a lot of verbal
facilities. And so MDMA has also been given the same group at Hopkins just published a paper in
Nature, which we can reference to. We'll go to all these things, yeah. Yeah, they just published a
paper in Nature that was in mice. And what they showed is that MDMA releases oxytocin,
which causes neurogenesis, the birth of new neurons and new neural connections in pro-social
areas of the brain. And they speculated that that's what's underlying the increase in the
therapeutic alliance between patient and therapist that MDMA catalyzes this oxytocin release, hormones
of love and bonding and nurturing nursing mothers and when you're in love. But when Merck came back
to it, there's like this period where it was sort of forgotten about until Sasha came along and
started synthesizing. Sort of. So what happened then, so invented in 1912, 1927 Merck does studies
in animals and then gives it up. The next time that we know about it was in 1953 when the US Army
Chemical Warfare Service tested eight different drugs for toxicity in animals. This was classified,
it didn't come out until the early 70s. So very few people knew about it, but MDMA was one of those
drugs. And so what they did is they tested a series of eight drugs with mescaline on one side
and methamphetamine on the other and MDMA more in the middle. So I think that's a good way to
understand MDMA is that it has the energy properties of methamphetamine. That's why people can take it
and stay up all night and dance. It makes you alert, but it doesn't make you jittery like
methamphetamine. You can take it and be alert, but be perfectly still. You can use it in meditation
and many people have actually. Is it technically considered a stimulant? I mean, it is an amphetamine
chemically. Well, it has stimulant properties for sure, but it's also similar to mescaline,
but it doesn't have the ego dissolving sort of visual classic psychedelic properties that mescaline
has. So MDMA is kind of between mescaline and methamphetamine, but different from each end of
the spectrum. So that research was done in animals. There's no evidence that they did anything in
humans and that wasn't declassified till the early seventies. So then what happened though is that a
drug called MDA, methylenedioxymhetamine, was developed independently and it became quite
popular during the sixties and it was called the miracle drug of America. It's a little bit like
an MDMA LSD combination and a lot of people really used it during the sixties. It was a pretty
incredible experience and also kind of a different contrast to LSD, a softer version of LSD.
And so once all the drugs were criminalized in 1970 in this backlash in the controlled
substances act, then chemists like Sasha and others were looking to modify drugs that were
illegal to develop new versions that would be legal and might have therapeutic properties. So
it was because of the popularity of MDA that people started looking at that kind of molecule
and then MDMA was actually rediscovered without people knowing that it had been invented by Merck
or that the army chemical warfare service had used it. And then it became used. So Sasha Shulgin
actually was told by a graduate student of his that he should check into that particular molecule.
And then he took it and the way Sasha worked was incredible that he and his wife Anne,
he would invent these new drugs. He was looking for drugs for consciousness change. He had been
working for Dow and had invented a biodegradable insecticide and Dow had given him his own lab
and said, you could do whatever you wanted to do. But what he wanted to do was investigate psychedelics.
And he'd had his first experience was with mescaline and he had a very spiritual experience
with mescaline. After a while, it was clear that he wasn't going to be producing anything that
Dow wanted to market. And so he left and started on his own and taught chemistry, but really became
the premier American psychedelic chemist. And so he resynthesized MDMA and his process was he would
take things himself. He and Anne would take them. They had a group of 12 people that they would,
and these were the same 12 people that they would test all these new drugs. And he felt that
individuals are so different from each other. If you have 12 people and you all take the same drug,
you'll get a range of experiences and that gives you a good sense of what this drug might be.
And those drugs that this group of 12 thought might have therapeutic potential, then he worked
with a fellow named Leo Zeph, who was a clinical psychologist, PhD, who had, when the crackdown
came, decided to continue using psychedelics. And so Leo was sort of the leader of the underground
psychedelic psychotherapy movement. The first book that MAPS ever published was called The
Secret Chief. And then a few years after that, we were able to publish The Secret Chief Revealed,
once his family was comfortable with us talking about Leo. Leo was going to retire, but once he
did MDMA, he realized that this had incredible therapeutic potential. So he didn't retire and
Leo is the one that trained lots and lots of therapists and psychiatrists. And he really built
up the therapeutic use of MDMA. And so from the middle 70s to the middle 80s, half a million doses,
much of it made at MIT secretly. Chemists at MIT were making MDMA for this underground
therapy community. And it was out of that then that it leaked and Michael Klee turned it into ecstasy.
Is it your belief, Rick, that had ecstasy never made it to the public party scene,
that MDMA could have potentially evaded censorship that came with its criminalization as a schedule
one? Is it possible this could have just at that moment in history been integrated into
medically accepted psychotherapy? I don't think so. No, I think that there was the backlash against
the classic psychedelic. So the summer of 84, so I started going to these meetings at Esalen
in 83, 84 and 85. And we were planning how to protect MDMA. The summer of 84 is when I started
Earth Metabolic Design Lab. So that was the nonprofit that actually had been started by
Buckminster Fuller. And a friend of mine had a branch of it in Sarasota, Florida for alternative
energy. My friend hadn't used it. And so I was able to take over the nonprofit and interpret the
alternative energy to include mental energy as well. And so that was the nonprofit that we used
to try to organize to protect MDMA once the eventual backlash happened. So when the DEA
first moved to criminalize MDMA in the summer of 84, Sasha had had connections with an attorney,
Rick Cotton, with a big DC law firm. Andy Weill had gone to Harvard as an undergraduate with
Rick Cotton and now. So Rick was monitoring the DEA. And so once the DEA moved to criminalize
MDMA, he let Sasha know so that we had 30 days to go to Washington. And so I went to Washington on
like day 28 and filed for a lawsuit to try to DEA administrative law judge hearing. So if there
hadn't been the crackdown at that point, that was still an era when all psychedelic research was
banned. That didn't change till 1992 when the FDA had an advisory committee meeting and decided that
they would open the door to psychedelic research. That was where in 1990, a new group of people at
the FDA took over regulating schedule on drugs and they decided to put science before politics.
Let's pause for a moment and explain what are the criteria for schedule drugs. So you have
four schedules within the DEA. I'll let you explain what schedule one is and we'll work our way.
So schedule one is for drugs that have a high potential for abuse, no accepted safety under
medical supervision and no currently accepted medical use. That basically says this is incredibly
harmful, addictive, etc. And there is no benefit to using it medically. And so heroin is a schedule
one drug. Conversely, cocaine is not the listener might say, wait, how could cocaine, which of those
two does cocaine not satisfy? Well, it clearly satisfies the first one. It's highly addictive
and harmful, but it turns out it does have one very important medically valid use, which is
it's a remarkable local anesthetic in very vascular areas. And so cocaine is used quite carefully in
nasal surgery. If you're having a nose procedure done by an ENT surgeon, there's a reasonable
chance they use cocaine. So MDMA lands itself as a schedule one drug, meaning it's on the same
level as heroin or methamphetamine. Well, methamphetamine also has a medical use. Oh,
that's right. That's right. Yeah. So marijuana is a schedule one drug. So the way in which it's been
interpreted, high potential for abuse, they emphasize the word potential. So it doesn't
have to have a lot of people using it. It just has to have a high potential for abuse. And the
way they defined abuse is non-medical use. It's a very loose definition. It can encompass anything
because it doesn't have to actually have harm. It just has the high potential for abuse. So a grape,
technically, could be a schedule one agent. Well, what's the potential for abuse of a grape? I mean,
well, if you ate enough, you could get diabetes. Yeah, that'd be a bit strange. I don't think
grapes are likely to be scheduled, but I see your point. Yeah. I mean, it's so ridiculous is my point.
Yeah. No accepted safety under medical supervision just means that it's not a prescription drug.
The definition becomes a bit of a tautology. Yeah. And no currently accepted medical use.
I think where people misinterpret what schedule one means is that it doesn't mean that the
government has determined that there is no medical use. There's no currently accepted medical use.
And currently accepted has been interpreted as FDA approval. It's not that you have a whole bunch
of doctors that say, this looks like it's got incredible potential. They've made it so to get
out of schedule one, you have to have FDA approval. So schedule two is high potential for abuse, but it
has currently accepted safety under medical supervision and it's got a currently accepted
medical use. So opiates fit into this category, fentanyl, oxycodone, Oxycontin, cocaine, as we
discussed. Yeah, methamphetamine for attention deficit disorder. Schedule three is for drugs that
have less than high potential for abuse. Schedule two drugs, whenever there's a prescription,
one copy goes to the DEA. So there's a lot of special controls for schedule two drugs,
even though they're medically available. You can't write a prescription that's automatically renewed
for a schedule two drug. Every new prescription has to be written explicitly by your doctor. You
can't renew this every three months for the next couple of years. So, and it goes down there from
schedule three to schedule four to schedule five, where you get over the counter drugs, but they're
still controlled in certain ways, but minimally. So what we're anticipating and what we're trying
to do is move MDMA and also psilocybin is schedule one drug. LSD is schedule one drug. Mescaline is
a schedule one drug. All these psychedelics are schedule one drugs. Ketamine has been used as a
dissociative anesthetic by anesthesiologists and it's a prescription medicine. It was just approved
as ketamine, an isomer of ketamine was just approved for depression. And it's considered among
the most important, if not the most important new development in the treatment of mental illness in
the last several decades, because it's being used for depression and it's effective relatively
immediately rather than the current anti-depressives that sometimes take weeks and weeks of daily
dosing. So this schedule system, what eventually I think should happen is that the psychedelics
should be de-scheduled completely. I think that there's a fundamental human right that people
have to explore their consciousness, particularly when you think about it as spiritual experiences,
that we should have this fundamental human right. I believe we should have a system of licensed
legalization. Is there a precedent for the DEA taking something that is on schedule one and
moving it to schedule two? Yeah, the oral THC pill, Maranil, which was used in 85-86 for nausea
control for cancer chemotherapy was switched from schedule one to schedule two. GHB was in schedule
one, but it's now actually in schedule three. Yeah, and last year there was like 1.4 billion in sales.
So Xyrem, it's for narcolepsy. It's to help people sleep at night so that they don't fall
asleep during the day. Isn't Xyrem actually a chemical cousin of GHB and not actual GHB?
I'm not sure about that. I thought it was actual GHB. It's close enough that I can understand why,
but GHB of course being, what was its street name again? Well, that's what's called the date rape
drug. The date rape drug, yeah. Did it have another name? I'm not sure. It's the date rape
drug because you can put it in water and then it makes people sleepy, particularly when mixed with
alcohol. And so it does have a bit of a taste, but you put it in alcohol or something, it's hard
to taste it. So there is a precedent of moving drugs off of schedule one into other schedules.
Usually, initially it goes schedule two and then depending on how it goes, it could go down further.
So all of this is to get back around to this idea that the DEA moved to criminalize MDMA in
84, this nonprofit that I'd started with Debbie Harlow and Elise Agar to protect it. We got a
hearing and we eventually triumphed. So the DEA administrative law judge said that it should be
schedule three, but while the hearing was going on, that was in 1986. So while the hearing was
still going on in 1985, we were winning in the court. The DEA administrative law judge doesn't
work for the DEA. The administrative law judges are employed and paid separately, and then they're
inserted into the different agencies to administer disputes between people and the agencies and they
make recommendations to the head of the agency about what they should do. So they don't make
binding decisions. They are there as a quasi neutral arbitrator of dispute. Yeah, exactly.
If you don't like the decision that's been made by the head of the administrator of the agency,
then you can sue them in the appeals court. So that's what we did. So in 85 though, we're winning
in the court, which is dismaying to the DEA. The DEA didn't even anticipate that we would file
because they didn't know about therapeutic use of MDMA. So they just thought they're criminalizing
ecstasy. They're criminalizing a party drug, and in the final hour, you guys show up and say,
wait, please, this has really important therapeutic benefit, which by the way, Rick, we should circle
back and really talk through that. And now all of a sudden, quote unquote, their judge, although it's
not really their judge, agrees with you guys and says, this should be a schedule three agent. Yeah.
But before the judge issued his ruling, it was clear that we showed up with doctors, with
psychiatrists from Harvard Medical School from all over with testimony. We did a secret study,
actually, as the safety of MDMA. So we had data to present to them. We had all these things that
we kept a secret because we didn't want it to be criminalized before the DEA moved. So also,
we were winning in the court of public opinion. So Robert Miller, who had mentioned, was the
assistant secretary of general, the UN had referred me to various mystics to whom I had sent MDMA.
So in the very first article, it was early 1985 in Newsweek, the first large media article about
MDMA, Brother David Steinlerass spoke on behalf of MDMA and said that a monk spends his whole life
trying to cultivate the mental attitude that you can get from taking MDMA. There was this paper in
the Washington Post that Rabbi Zalman Schachter, who had also experimented with MDMA that I'd send
him, he compared MDMA to the Sabbath. So the idea of this as a party drug used by hedonistic kids,
just recklessly risking their brains. That narrative, which is what the DEA wanted to share,
was contradicted by this narrative of rabbis and monks and therapists and psychiatrists talking
about the value of MDMA. So we're winning in the court of public opinion, winning in the court,
and the DEA freaked out and declared MDMA illegal on an emergency basis in the middle of 1985,
while the hearings were still going on. And that was actually heartbreaking because we had thought
that the hearing might actually save it. So DEA criminalizes it on an emergency basis. Later,
it turned out that the DEA committed a crime in the sense that they didn't have the authority
to emergency schedule. I was just going to ask you both, do they have the authority? And secondly,
was there a precedent for that? Well, no, there was not a precedent for that. What had happened
is that Congress had given the attorney general the power to emergency schedule drugs. The attorney
general, not the DEA. Yeah, all the attorney general would have needed to do was to subdelegate
the power. They would have just had to file a piece of paper in the federal register saying
that the attorney general subdelegates down to the administrative of the DEA. But that had not
been done. Had not been done. Who was the AG at the time? I don't actually remember. Presumably,
the AG at the time was very sympathetic to the DEA. Oh, completely. Because this was, as you pointed
out, I mean, this was one of Reagan's signature policy pieces. Very much, the escalation of the
drug war. And so you could argue that the DEA, though technically in violation of the reg,
probably could have done it if they'd waited, gone through the proper channel. They probably
could have received authority from the AG to do this. The bigger question is why? Why were they
so afraid at that moment? Well, because here was a drug that was being used by a lot of people,
but it wasn't causing problems. Let's dig into this for a little bit. So I think there are going
to be many people listening to this who are up until this point in the podcast are thinking,
what the hell are these two guys talking about? You're sitting here glorifying drugs. And so let's
talk very specifically about ecstasy. I think back to when I was in college, I had never touched
this drug and certainly a lot of kids were using it. And the conventional wisdom was this drug
gives you hyperthermia. So you run this risk of overheating. You run this risk of getting long term
really depressed because you deplete serotonin levels. I mean, there was certainly a lot of
seemingly legitimate fear around this. What was actually happening? Well, MDMA can cause
hyperthermia. There are cases of people that have taken MDMA. Usually there are people that have
danced in hot environments and got overheated, didn't have enough fluid replacement. And so some
people have died from hyperthermia. And is it actually the MDMA that's precipitating the
hyperthermia or is it just that anybody who could dance that long and that heat could get
hyperthermia and the MDMA just sort of blunted their other ability to self-regulate? Well,
people generally don't die from hyperthermia from dancing all night. So the MDMA contributes. It's a
contributing factor. So the MDMA in therapeutic settings doesn't cause hyperthermia. So there's
something about MDMA combining with lots of movement and dehydration that creates this trifecta.
Yeah. What also was happening is that in a lot of these environments where people were doing
MDMA, these bars, people weren't buying alcohol. Alcohol kind of blunts the MDMA experience. People
weren't buying alcohol. And so what the bars would be doing would be shutting off the water in the
bathrooms and making people buy water. And so that's why sometimes people wouldn't drink. Now,
also occasionally people drink too much water. They dilute their blood, they get hyponitremia.
And so what we use in therapy is fruit juices or things with electrolytes. So for those people
that are looking for harm reduction tips, it's better to drink stuff with electrolytes and water
if you're doing MDMA. So you drink as much as you want, you're not going to dilute your blood and
get hyponitremia. It's very, very rare that people will have these side effects. MDMA doesn't cause
the same kind of dissolution of ego that the classic psychedelics do. So generally people
don't have difficult experiences. However, there are people that have had traumas in the past or
issues that are emotional issues, even without traumas. Because MDMA reduces activity in the
amygdala, it reduces your fear response to difficult emotions. A lot of times when people
do take MDMA, difficult things come to their awareness. And I've witnessed this in therapeutic
settings where the tears of past events just come out in a way that you could never imagine
this happening otherwise. Yeah. I mean, profound in ways that therapy, sometimes people are too
scared to let it out, but MDMA helps them to do that. And so people can have difficult experiences.
One of the stories I told during my TED talk, which we'll link to when it's out, was about a
woman who I worked with in 1984 who had PTSD. And she had taken MDMA, not in a therapeutic setting,
and this violent sexual assault that had happened to her years before came to the surface and
intensified her suicidal feelings. And she actually checked herself into a mental institution to
protect herself from committing suicide after having taken MDMA. And when she got out with the
same old drugs that had been given to her before, she was even more suicidal. And so a friend of
hers, I didn't know her at the time, contacted me about her. And so I started talking to her and
agreed to work with her. And under the influence of MDMA and then also an MDMA-LST combination,
she was able to overcome her PTSD. So in 1984 is when I learned about directly working with someone
and seeing that MDMA could be helpful for PTSD. Was that to your knowledge, Rick, the first time?
I mean, first of all, were you guys referring to the term PTSD? Was that a term that was
widely understood in 1984? No. There was a lot of people that had- I mean, clearly we'd seen it. I
mean, all these poor guys coming back from Vietnam when you were in college beyond traumatized, but
that term was not commonly used. I'm not sure the actual history of the term PTSD. I think it was
used somewhat, but people weren't as aware of how much trauma impacts so many, many different people.
So at that moment in 1984, really what you knew was this is a woman who'd been traumatized, for
lack of a better word. And you saw the potential in this agent to, while on its own, do something
potentially dangerous in a controlled setting. You actually felt what, that she could relive this
experience and do so safely and process it? Talk me through what you were really doing in 1984 to
understand that. Okay. So this woman's name is Marcella. So other people before this, so I had been
working with various people with MDMA before, both taking it myself and also sometimes with people
that had different issues and sometimes people just looking to communicate to others. I had spoken to
a soldier who had been shot in the back and he told me under the influence of MDMA that he was
able to relax in certain ways so that the pain in his back went away to a large degree, that sort
of combination of the impact of the bullets, but also the fear connected to all of that. This was
a key turning point in my life. So I had been back to Esalen for a month long workshop in the spring
of 1984. And this was again with Stan and Christina Groff and it was called the spiritual
emergence network. So there's a bunch of people that break down for different reasons and different
ways where people break down their path in life is not working for them. And often it gets pathologized
and people get tranquilized or they get hospitalized or different things. But what Stan Groff and
others were saying is that this can be a spiritual emergence. It can be seen as a spiritual crisis
that we're resisting. So it comes in dramatic ways, but the process of what's trying to emerge is
healthy. The process is not. So I had studied how to help people who were struggling to integrate
different either spiritual experiences or psychological experiences that were coming back
as part of my effort to become a psychedelic therapist. And I was only home for about less
than a week when I got a call from this friend of mine who I actually had sold the MDMA to
when it was still legal. And he said that he and Marcella had done this together in a
kind of a romantic situation and that her past trauma had emerged. He wasn't aware of that
and that she was now suicidal and that whatever had been tried by traditional psychiatry,
including the psychiatrist, the mental institution that not worked for her, she was suicidal even
worse. So I felt like I'm not qualified. This is a terrifying situation, somebody being suicidal,
but I didn't think that she had any other options. She tried her best in traditional psychiatry.
And I felt this is what I'm trying to do, learn how to be a therapist to work with this. And I
felt somewhat responsible for having sold them the MDMA. And so I agreed to talk to her, talk to her
on MDA or just talk to her on the phone. So during the discussion, she explained what had happened.
And I was saying that you'd taken this MDMA in a situation where you weren't really anticipating
that this would emerge or that you would process this and that it made you destabilized and now
you're suicidal. However, if we were to do this in a therapeutic setting where you're not trying to
be with someone where you're able to focus on this, the properties of MDMA may help you integrate it,
may help you fully experience it, look at it, come to peace with it. And I said that if she
were willing to promise not to commit suicide while we were working together, I would be willing
to try to work with her. Even though I said I'm not a fully trained therapist, this is something
that I have been training to become. I just went through this month long training. And so I'd be
willing to work with you and I would get a group of my friends, particularly female friends to come
and create a safe space around you. And you could come to my house and work and we would work with
you to try to help you integrate it. And so she agreed to do that. And so we created this context,
the first MDMA experience that she had turned out to be like a tour of the traumatic experiences of
her life. This violent rape and assault where she was almost left for dead was not the only trauma
that she had. There was a series of those other traumas that she had kidnapped when she was young,
different things. And she'd grown up in Columbia, South America. So we got a tour of all those
various traumas in her life. And it was progress. A lot of tears, a lot of processing. She didn't
feel as hopeless, but it didn't feel like it had sort of solved her problem. So I thought let's
switch to LSD for the next experience. And she agreed to do that. Just to say that the first use
of a psychedelic for treating PTSD was done by a Dutch psychiatrist, Dr. Jan Bastians. And he had
done this in the fifties, sixties, seventies, and he did LSD for what he called concentration camp
syndrome. So it was for people that were in the concentration camps traumatized by that. And that
he had found that LSD would bring a lot of the memories back to the surface and then they could
try to process them. But LSD doesn't really reduce the fear. There's an Israeli Holocaust writer,
Kat Setnik, which was his concentration camp number. And then his number who wrote a book called
Shaviti, a vision, which is tremendous because he went to get LSD therapy with Dr. Bastians. And
this is a book about his therapy. And it was very difficult. And a bunch of my Israeli relatives
knew him and said that it helped him, but he was still tormented a lot. So in any case,
with Marcello, he decided to switch to LSD. And so during the LSD experience, a lot of these
memories again resurfaced. What amount of time was separated between them? Two weeks. So it's
really important to integrate the experience before you're ready to do it again. So during
the LSD experience, what happened was that she started having this vision of a double sun. She
was on a foreign planet and there was a double sun and she was baking to death. And it was just
terrifying to her. And she was stuck. She couldn't process it. It was just overwhelming fear. And so
I suggested that she take half a dose of MDMA. Full dose is like 125 milligrams. So about 62 and
half. And I thought the MDMA would soften the LSD and might help her process it. And it turned out
that's what happened. And so once she took the MDMA, it condensed from this symbolic foreign thing
to actually her life where after she was raped and beaten and thrown out of the car and left
under the sun sort of way out to die. So it condensed the MDMA helped it turn into this
experience that had actually happened to her. And then she was starting to able to share that this
person had been a date rape situation. And there was times where she was seeing me as the rapist.
My feet were turning into his feet. Then they turned back to my feet, different kind of things.
And so you still had females there as well. Not at this one time, but around her and before
and after, but at this point it was just her and I. So I felt like I could take these projections
onto me because that wasn't really me. And so she was able to sort of clarify that she was seeing
the world through her own distrust or what had happened in the past. She wasn't sure what she
could trust through her own filters. And then when she could sort of feel more safe that it was me
and not the rapist. At one point I asked her when I realized it was date rape, I said, what did you
like about this guy? And she immediately vomited. And then she started sharing that he had liked
animals. And so what she was able to do, and one of the things that was making her suicidal was
that she felt that she could never find love again, because she could never trust herself.
Yeah, I was just about to say there's probably a piece of self-hatred, which is
at some level she made a decision to at least be with this guy in some capacity socially, right?
Or maybe they had a meal together or something. And it's like her judgment failed her is probably
part of this pain. Yeah, very much so. Yeah. It meant she could never trust herself. So how could
she find love? Because it could always turn into something like another date rape. But the fact
that she could go back and say, he liked animals. Okay, so now I could know that somebody else who
likes animals doesn't mean that I should automatically trust them. She was recovering her ability to be
discerning. You know, that's a really interesting story, Rick, because it illustrates something I
don't think I've ever thought of until you said it, which is that a woman who's been raped in that
situation has maybe an additional level of trauma that the equally tragic woman who gets yanked into
the alleyway by some stranger doesn't have, which is this sense of this loss of self-trust and maybe
even this sort of self-loathing of how could I have possibly let myself get into this situation.
Yeah, I think that's what made Marcella so suicidal is that knowing that she led herself into this
in a way, or she had made some fundamental misjudgment causing her to question everything
that she would then do in the future. And so I think once she was able to sort of say, yes,
he liked animals, but that's not a reason to automatically trust people, she was starting to
regain her discernment and regain her ability to feel hope that maybe she could go out and find love.
Were you afraid during this situation? I mean, I can't imagine what it would be like to
be flying by the seat of my pants in a situation like that. You're dealing with an incredibly
fragile woman who is broken and on the verge of something awful. And by your own admission,
you're not qualified to be doing this yet, but at the same time, there's no alternative it would
seem, which puts you in a tough situation. I mean, how frightened were you? Once she agreed not to
commit suicide, that reduced my fear a lot. And then I did see progress from the first MDMA
experience and she did too. So that made it less scary. And also I've had my own terrifying
blockages with LSD where I reached places where I wasn't able to really make any further progress,
wasn't able to integrate it. So it was scary, but once I could see that the MDMA was taking
an effect, once it moved from something that she was just overwhelmed and then that she was able
to process it, then my fear went down. And then when I saw her throw up and it's almost like she
was purging. Yeah, very much. It was like this. I think what did you like about him? The fact that
she immediately threw up, that was a clue that that was kind of part of the thing that was keeping
her. So this happened in 84. This happened in 84 and that was the breakthrough. I mean,
she didn't have any more sessions. We just did two sessions and then she felt able to also,
this person had told her that if she ever talked about what happened, he'd kill her. And so even
though this was years before, the fact that she hadn't been able to talk about it was prisoner in
her own mind. And so being able to talk about it and see that even though he was a continent away,
the fear was still implanted in her, but that she could overcome that. She could start talking
about it was also freeing for her. So a year later, you watch this molecule that you believe
has incredible potential. You watch it get scheduled as one and you realize it's only
going to be more difficult for patients like this woman to experience what she experienced. And at
that moment in time, because one of the things that so impressive about the work you've done at
maps is the, well, one, it's just been relentless. It's hard to, as someone myself who has dabbled in
the sort of nonprofit slash policy world only to immediately realize like this is not for me,
it's the fortitude with which you can do it. But also it's sort of the clarity of purpose. Now,
I want to make sure we talk about certain concepts like the breakthrough therapy designation,
which is such an important piece of this story. But before we get to that, I guess what I want
to ask you is in 1985, 1986, how much of what would transpire over the next 30 years was clear
to you? In other words, how much of this strategy of we find an indication for which it is crystal
clear that this is valuable, the best indication would be one for which there is no other therapy.
Hence this notion of breakthrough therapy. Did you think that that was going to be PTSD? I mean,
what were you thinking about? You hadn't even started at grad school. Yeah, that I was still
an undergraduate. Yeah. Because your PhD is basically geared towards getting you ready to
fight this fight. Yeah. I think when I look back on my life, it was really at this period when I
was 18 in 1972, when I felt like I might be going to jail for being a draft position. I just felt
like the contribution I could make to the world that this support from my family, this multi
generational process that permitted me to look at deeper threats that I was terrified of the world
and terrified of what happens and terrified of our own human potential for murder and genocide. And
I felt that I had this rare gift from my family, this freedom to choose what I thought would be
the most strategic thing I could imagine, which was helping people to realize that we are more
in common than separate and that we're all part of one big family and that you shouldn't dehumanize
and kill that that decision at age 18, now that I've recently in November turned 65, it's always
made sense. So I feel incredibly lucky and fortunate that something that I stumbled on at age
18 still at this other period of my life still makes sense. And it has made sense continually.
And I've also thought that if not, but for an accident of birth, I could have been born earlier,
I could have been in the concentration camps, or I could have been sent off to Vietnam or
incinerated in nuclear warfare, that I always felt that whatever the struggles were that I was having
were nothing compared to what a lot of struggles that other people had to go through. And that
this dream that I had of a Holocaust survivor telling me to be a psychedelic therapist,
that that's where the motivation came from, that I had this rare opportunity to try to work on
long term threats that didn't have to directly lead to a job that didn't exist. So when I was 18,
I thought I would be an underground psychedelic therapist. The first day in the office of
President Carter, he pardoned all the draft resistors. So that started me starting to think
that I could have an above ground career. But it's a far away from being pardoned as a
draft resistor to the legalization of psychedelics. Are you saying that that was just
your first clue that the ice was melting a little bit? I identified myself as a counterculture drug
using criminal. So at age 18, that was my self identity counterculture drug using criminal,
a little bit of the criminal part was taken away. And then I thought I could sort of rejoin society
in a certain way. But I was still criminal from using psychedelics. Going to college was now in
82, starting was now psychedelics were forefront, but they were always what I had been planning to
in this 10 year period that I was building houses and preparing for doing this. And then the
transition of being politically involved with a nonprofit in 84, and then starting maps in 86,
that also changed my attitude, the fact that there was a nonprofit that this friend had started
John Lambie connected with Buckminster Fuller, the arithmetic metabolic design lab, I started
realizing that that was part of the system, this nonprofit and that the system permits you to fight
the system. So I was sort of outgrowing this idea of myself as counterculture and seeing that you
could work within and that there are opportunities for reform from inside. And then the work with
Marcella in 1984, and seeing her continually get better over time as the demonization of MDMA
increased. And as all of this NIDA, National Institute on Drug Abuse funded research,
started talking about MDMA neurotoxicity and all the concerns about hypothermia and hyponitremia,
just the demonization of MDMA, the blocking of all MDMA research, the whole part of that,
the big transition for me, once MDMA was criminalized by the DEA on an emergency basis,
the judge in 86 said that it should be schedule three, the DEA rejected those recommendations,
and then we sued in the appeals court and we won twice in the appeals court. Both at the time,
the appeals court tends to tell agencies what you did is wrong, they don't normally say you
should do this, they just say what you do is wrong, go back and rethink it. Do they have
authority to do anything other than just make a formal position on what was done? Yeah, so for
example in school integration, sometimes courts will take over school systems, courts can actually
compel, the appeals courts can compel. But this is unbelievable, I mean you have the DEA judge
says make it schedule three, and then you have two subsequent appeals saying that basically what
the judge said they agreed with or what the DEA did was incorrect. Yes, that's what they said,
so the rationale for the DEA to reject the recommendation, the first rationale was that
the DEA said they didn't have the authority to reschedule, only the FDA did. The Controlled
Substances Act of 1970 clearly says either the Attorney General or the HHS Secretary either could
reschedule to make the drug into a medicine. And the FDA sits under which branch? HHS. HHS,
yeah. Which is where, yeah okay, and the DEA sits under what? The Attorney General. The AG,
and you're saying the Controlled Substance Act made it clear either had the power to reschedule.
So the DEA basically said, it's sort of ironic, they had the power to schedule but not reschedule,
is what they're basically claiming. Yeah, so the DEA lawyers as I've learned over the decades,
they don't really care if their arguments are flawed because they delay. So delay is the same
as victory to them. So if they put out a ruling that's wrong, it can take you years to go through
the appeals court. And so justice delayed is justice denied. So they don't care about their
arguments, they just want to delay. So the first argument they made was that they didn't have the
authority. So the appeals court said yes, you do. Then they came up with an eight-part standard
that they said you have to meet these standards in order for us to reschedule. To whom? The DEA
lawyers would then put a new ruling in the Federal Register justifying why they rejected the
administrative law judge's recommendation. And so their new rationale was, okay, here's our
eight-part standard. So then we appealed on that because that was essentially the same as FDA. And
if the Congress had wanted the FDA to be the only agency to reschedule, that would have been one
thing. But the fact that they gave the DEA the authority to do it, the DEA couldn't say it's
exactly the same thing as the FDA. Why didn't you at this point go to the FDA, which because the
problem with the DEA at this point is the cognitive dissonance is overwhelming. You're asking someone
who's done something to openly acknowledge what they've done was incorrect. So why not go to a new
body? Well, we were also going to the FDA, but the FDA was rejecting all the protocols. So this was
a period of time when the backlash against psychedelic research was so strong that the FDA
was rejecting every single protocol. And so we were trying to go to the FDA, but they weren't
responsive either. And so then the courts rejected this eight-part standard as being too equivalent
to FDA. And then the DEA came up with a five-part standard, which the court accepted, which is still
essentially the FDA. You still need phase three studies. And so basically the DEA gave away their
authority to reschedule to the FDA because they didn't want to reschedule. They wanted to schedule,
but not reschedule. Is that pretty much how it stands today? Yeah, the DEA is. But what's happened
a few years ago is that Congress passed a law. It was always the case that if FDA says a drug is a
medicine, the DEA must reschedule, but they didn't have a time limit. So now they have 90 days that
they have to reschedule. So we had MDMA criminalized in 85, kept that way in 86, I start maps. And then
I thought that I would go and get a clinical psych PhD. So I graduated college in 87 with my Good
Friday follow-up as my senior thesis. And because New College didn't have any grades, I knew that to
get into graduate school, I had to really study well on the GREs. So I did great on the GREs. I had
incredible recommendations from this professor that had been head of the PhD program in psychology and
social change at Harvard, who had retired in Sarasota and who was my special teacher every
semester. I had one class with him on psychedel. So in any case, I tried to get into clinical psych
PhD programs, and nobody would let me in because I told them I want to do MDMA research. And I was
saying, we can't do it now, but I don't want to spend five years getting a PhD. And then I'm about
to do my dissertation. And then you tell me you won't let me do it. So I want to tell you what I
want to do now. And if we get there and the system won't let me do it, I'll do something else. It's
very hard to get into clinical psych PhD programs. But I came very close a couple of times in programs
that had psychotherapy outcome research as their specialties. And so I wasn't in the end able to get
in. And so I was confused because since 1972 till now it was 1988, that I had been on this track for
clinical psych PhD, learn how to do psychotherapy outcome research with psychedelics. So I went home
after the last rejection, I said I'm going to figure out what I need to do with my life. And so
I decided to smoke marijuana and think about it. And marijuana gives me a way to think about things
from a different perspective. I'll be trapped in a box. And so I had this realization that I want
too much too soon, that I want to do the science, but the politics is in the way. And so I'm leaping
over the culture isn't ready. I want too much too soon. And so I thought, okay, if I want to do the
science, but the politics in the way, maybe I have to study the politics. And I remembered reading an
interview in Harper's Magazine with several people talking about drug policy. And one of them was a
professor at Harvard at the Kennedy School of Government, Mark Kliman. And they talked about our
lawsuit against the DEA. I wasn't even aware of public policy schools or the Kennedy School
of Government. But I remember that he had mentioned our lawsuit. So I called him up and I said,
I want to study the politics. I can't do the research I want to do. I can't do the education
I want. So would you be my mentor? And he said, if you can get into the Kennedy School, I would be
glad to be your mentor. And so I applied and I managed to get in sort of the token left wing
hippie of the year, Kennedy School. And so that also started changing who I thought I was.
And now I'm even more becoming part of the system rather than becoming part of the counterculture.
Now I'm at the Kennedy School of Government, Harvard, and people are planning careers in the
federal government. And so what they had was there was a program called the Presidential
Management Internship. It's now the Presidential Management Fellowship. And so it's for people that
want careers in the federal government. It's a competitive situation. Federal employees watch
you as you do group exercises. There's all sorts of essays and things. And so I managed to,
it was at the same time that the Native American church was having a Supreme Court case about
whether the peyote would be protected by religious freedom. So that was my essay. I was able to write
an essay about a Supreme Court case, but it happened to be about psychedelics. And so I managed to get
a Presidential Management Internship. And then I tried to get a job at the FDA. I figured I want
to work at the FDA. And coincidentally, in 1990, is when I got my master's and when I was applying
for this job at the FDA, the group that regulated psychedelics switched in 1990 to a new group. So
the group that had blocked research basically for two decades was now out of the picture and a new
group took over. And my application ended up with this new group. It was called the Pilot Drug
Evaluation Staff. They were there in response to the AIDS epidemic where the FDA had been criticized
for being too slow to approve drugs. This was a group that was going to review new ways to
approve drugs in faster. And so they were looking around to the FDA, to other parts of the FDA, which
groups had drugs that they didn't care about that they could take over. So they'd have real life
examples. And the Schedule 1 drugs had been blocked by Paul Lieber, was this guy in charge of the
division that took care of Schedule 1 drugs. And so he gave them up to this Pilot Drug Evaluation
Staff. My application ended up with them. And we went through about a six month process of review,
whether I would be able to get this FDA job, including interviews with the number two guy,
Carl Peck, who was in charge of all drug research at FDA. And the FDA decided that they would hire
me. It was great. I was really excited. I was willing to give up doing drugs. I was willing
to wear a suit and die and do all this stuff to go work into the FDA for a couple of years,
learn how they work, and then come back and run maps and try to make MDMA into medicine.
But at the last minute, right before I got hired, the DEA told the FDA that they would refuse to
work with me because I'd sued them before. And this is the branch of the FDA that works with
scheduled drugs that deals with the DEA. So the FDA said that I couldn't be hired,
but they would work with me informally. It's hard to be listening to this story and have a lot of
empathy for the DEA. I'm trying to sort of put my DEA hat on and sort of say, look, these are good
people. They're doing their job. They believe that they're doing the right thing, but they really
come across as a petty bunch of, I don't know what the right word is, but just sort of intellectually
not particularly curious, not especially thoughtful. I mean, to say we're not going
to work with this guy just strikes me as a bit petty. Oh, extremely. Yeah. And then shunning
responsibility, deciding, well, we're going to schedule something, but we don't want to de-schedule
it. But my guess is if anybody's able to muster up some empathy for the DEA at the same time,
it's also you. Nothing about you resonates this disdain for them. It's more of a,
gosh, I wish I could help them see what I see and what I've seen and the potential benefit of this.
Yeah. And what has really changed is I have started having some sympathy for the police
and how difficult their job is. And so actually we have a senior retired DEA official who is now
acting as a consultant for us. The reason is because his son went into the military and has
PTSD and uses cannabis for his PTSD. So that changed the father's mind. And actually October
of last year, 2018, this fella, Tony Colson, Bormour from the DEA arranged for us to give a talk at
the international association of chiefs of police. So it's a convention that was all over the world.
It was 10,000 police chiefs and police officers. And so we actually had a veteran, one of our
therapists, me and our DEA consultant speak. And what's so exciting for me, what happened there
is that it was such a politically ripe environment for president Trump that two days before we were
supposed to speak, he decided he would speak there and they scheduled his talk at the same
time as ours. And almost everybody went to his talk, but 30 people came to our talk,
including a psychologist who works for the police, a police officer who helps other police with
psychological issues. And he said that at the end of our talk, he wanted to go through our training
and he has. And so next week I'm meeting with, he's actually from the Boston area. So I'm meeting
with his police chiefs about having police with trauma volunteer for our study. That was a big
step for me is trying to have sympathy for the police. And what's also ironic is that my sister,
an oldest of four, I have two brothers and a sister, both brothers have done MDMA, but my sister
will never do a drug. She's very conservative in that way. Her son, her oldest son, Nathaniel,
my nephew is now a police officer in Washington DC. So I have a police officer in the family.
So all these us and them kind of barriers are dissolving. And in December of 2017,
we had a meeting with the police with the DEA headquarters. And it was to talk about what's
called expanded access, which is compassionate use of MDMA. And all sorts of people are going to
want to do that. And they're also going to need these DEA schedule and licenses. So we had a
meeting with the DEA to talk about that with our consultant again, to prepare them for all these
licenses. And they said that they would do that. One thing happened that was so personally
meaningful is that you can't go to DEA without an escort. When they take you into the building,
they don't want you to see somebody's desk or whatever. So we had an escort. So we're in this
elevator with the escort and we're going up to the fourth floor to where our meeting is. And for
whatever reason, it's only our team and this escort and the door opens on the second floor,
the elevator door, nobody got in, nobody got out. We didn't press number two, but for whatever
reason, the door opens on the second floor closes and then we go up to our meeting. And our
DEA consultant whispers to me that the second floor is where the courtroom is. So I was
previously in that building in 2005 suing the DEA, not on MDMA, but on another lawsuit for
marijuana, trying to get a license to grow marijuana. So it felt like the door opened on
the past conflict that we had with the DEA and then closed. We noticed it, but nobody else noticed
it. And then we went up to have a cooperative meeting about how we could work together with
the DEA. And the one part of the meeting that went flat, everything was really good. They're
willing to give all these licenses. I just said to them, if any of you have DEA officials or
officers that you know that have trauma that are in cities where we have studies, they can volunteer
for our project. And nobody smiled, nobody offered, but I just wanted them to know that this is for
them too, that I did have that level of compassion for them. And I knew it would be awkward for me to
say it, but I felt like I had to say that, that this is for them too. And now I understand more
and more about how police are traumatized. So this notion of, I don't know how to explain it,
there's a really nice video you guys made. It's a maps video. It's like maybe 10 minutes long.
It can't be that old because Sasha died how many years ago? Oh, quite a few. Like 2014 maybe? Yeah,
I'm not sure exactly what year. It was that year because at the end of the video, it notes that
he died about four months after the filming. Like I said, it's maybe 10 minutes long, but there were
many survivors in it talking about their experiences with MDMA. And it's very moving. Do you know the
video I'm talking about? We'll find this one and we'll link to it. But it's worth someone who either
doesn't have experience with PTSD, trauma, MDMA, to maybe pause for a moment and watch that and
get a sense of what it is that you saw in 1984 that kind of created an eternal flame inside of you
that said, look, until every person who has experienced trauma or is suffering from PTSD,
at least has the opportunity to experience this type of therapy, I'm not really going to stop.
That's sort of what I sense in how you talk about this. Yeah, yeah, that's true. I mean,
even if I'd never discovered MDMA, I would have tried to legitimize LSD in the classic psychedelics.
But seeing that there was a softer, gentler way of working with MDMA, I feel that it's very rare
that people who work on social justice movements live to see the change that they're working for
because a lot of these things are multi-generational. If you think about civil rights or end of slavery,
yes, of course. Yeah, I think that through an accident of history, I was born just at the right
time so that there was this backlash that I was able to see for psychedelics. The classic
psychedelics done this backlash against MDMA, but now I might actually live to see the medicalization
of psychedelics. And that would be an arc of a life contained. It'd be incredible. When did you
guys receive the breakthrough therapy designation? Started maps in 86. So from 86 to 92, we had five
different protocols all rejected by the FDA. And again, just for the listener to understand
what we're talking about, you are proposing to the FDA clinical trials that would necessitate
the FDA to create an exemption for the use of a Schedule I drug. It's a big deal. Yes, and DEA
would also have to approve it as well, and institutional review boards or ethics committees.
And then in California, that's the only state that actually has an additional review body
for scheduled drugs. So it is a lot of regulatory affairs, and I did learn a lot about it in the
Kennedy School, how to work through it. So in 92, the group at the FDA that regulated psychedelics
switched, and that group decided to put psychedelics on a track for science. So from 92, we got
permission for the Phase I safety study, the first dose response Phase I safety study. That took us
till about 96. Wow, I just want to pause for a second. That's 10 years of your life, and you
spent six of them just getting rejected, being told you're not even allowed to play the game,
get off the field. Then you spend four years demonstrating what you pretty much know is
already true, which is at a given range of doses, there's no toxicity to this drug. But of course,
that is a hoop you must jump through, understandably. Yeah, we had to do that. And then the doctor that
I was working with, Charlie Grove. Sorry, one other technical question. At any point in here,
did you have to file an IND? All the protocols that were rejected were INDs. Yeah. Maybe explain
to folks what that is and why that matters. IND stands for investigational new drug. It's
the formal application to do research with a drug to try to make it into a medicine. Before that,
actually in 1985, even before maps, I funded through this first nonprofit, animal studies,
28 day animal toxicity studies in the dog and the rat. So that was a requirement to do phase one or
phase two research. You have to have certain animal toxicity studies. So I did that already.
We had our MDMA manufactured by Dave Nichols at Purdue University in 1985. We're still using some
of that today. 34 years later, incredible stable molecule. We've had new MDMA made for phase three
and for commercial uses if we succeed. But it took till around 96 to get the safety study done.
And then Charlie Grove, the psychiatrist that we were working with, we were proposing a study on
cancer patients with anxiety. I knew about PTSD, but there was such a concern about
neurotoxicity, which was vastly exaggerated. Yeah. The other thing that people talked about a
lot was Parkinsonian like symptoms. My recollection is a lot of that research,
quote unquote research has been quite debunked. Is that the case? 100% debunked. Because it turns
out that the only claims that Parkinson's were again from George Riccardi and Una McCann,
these researchers that were at Johns Hopkins funded by NIDA. And they claimed, well, from the
middle 80s to near the end of the 90s, they were focused on MDMA supposedly hurting the serotonin
system and causing functional consequences of a serious nature so that nobody should even ever
get MDMA even once. It was so serious. One dose, functional brain damage, stay away from it
completely. Shouldn't even be researched. I was taught that in medical school in 97,
taking pharmacology. It was this is a drug that can permanently alter your serotonin receptors.
Yeah, totally not true. But we started challenging that. So actually,
George Riccardi was my first Alliance was so I recognize that in the 60s, there was an
exaggeration of the risks by the prohibitionists and a denial of research and a denial of the
benefits, but the advocates like Leary were exaggerating the benefits and.
Both sides were doing the same thing. So I felt that maps had to be the expert on the benefits
and on the risks that we had to be reliable. People had to rely on our risk estimates.
And so once I started working with maps in 86, my first Alliance for six years basically was with
George Riccardi, the expert funded by NIDA to look at the risks of MDMA. And so I funded his
first monkeys to move from rats to monkeys. So this is a real team of rivals. Oh, yeah.
You are funding the person who is being sponsored by your opponent and basically suggesting things
that you believe are untrue. Now, presumably you don't believe that there's any fraud in this.
It comes to that. So with George Riccardi. So first off was I thought, OK, we're scientists.
We want to find out what's really going on. I am very interested in what's really going on. What
are the risks? I'm taking the drugs. I should know myself. Everybody should know. And we got as far
as we could with the animals and in the primates, we found out what was called the no effect level
for neurotoxicity. No as in N.O. Yeah. So it's N.O.E.L. no L. So no effect level. So it turns out
that five milligrams per kilogram in a primate given every two weeks for four months. So eight
exposures every two weeks and at five milligrams per kilogram. There was some nerve terminal
degeneration in the primate at two and a half milligrams per kilogram. There was no nerve
terminal degeneration. So again, I should say that there may be changes, but changes are not
necessarily bad. I mean, our brains are constantly changing. And in fact, when you have therapy with
MDMA, you have a reduction overall before and after in activity in the amygdala. So certain things are
definitely changing, which can be good. What were the changes that occurred phenotypically at the
five milligram per kilogram? Well, there's never a cell death. It's just nerve terminals degenerate.
Did that manifest itself in any cognitive deficit or behavioral deficit? No. The claim was that the
only functional consequence that could be identified in ecstasy users were neurocognitive
consequences supposedly memory. However, we've since done studies. A member of MAPS contacted me
to say that methodologically all these studies that were done in ecstasy users were
methodologically confounded because these users had done all sorts of other drugs. So how do you
say what's from MDMA? And also, there's no pre and post. It's only retrospective compared to
supposedly controlled groups. So this guy said, I have the solution that there's a group of people
that have done only MDMA and you need to study them. And so we're right here right now, just about
a mile from McLean hospital, which is more psychiatric research, part of Harvard Medical
School, more psychiatric research done there than any other private institution in America.
And there's some people there that are experts in neurocognitive studies. And so I told them,
maps will give you a grant. There's this group of people. So we gave them a $15,000 grant.
It turns out they're fallen Mormons. The study took place in Salt Lake City, a bunch of Mormons
who had never done coffee, never done tobacco, never done marijuana, never done alcohol,
but had done ecstasy because it wasn't formally prohibited. And so this population did exist. So
they went and did a pilot study, then they prepared the data and they submitted it to NIDA
and they got a $1.8 million grant to a major study of people who'd only used ecstasy. And they found
virtually nothing. There really is no strong evidence, no weak evidence even really about
neurocognitive consequences in heavy ecstasy users. And we've done neurocognitive studies in our
people in our therapy studies who only get them to a few times. There's no evidence whatsoever.
So with George Riccardi though, after we found them, he didn't publish the 2.5 milligram. He
published the five milligram per kilogram where there was some evidence of nerve terminal
degeneration, but he didn't publish the 2.5 milligram per kilogram. So I started thinking
this is not so much about science anymore. There is a political agenda, but then I went to him and
I said, I don't feel hurt. How can you go even further? And he said, well, the only thing we can
do now is spinal taps. So I said, all right, I will volunteer for a spinal tap. And so it didn't
hurt that much. It was terrible. At that point in time, how often had you been at or above the
five MIG per KIG dose? I had never really been above it, but most people had not been above it.
So I basically said, I'll be your guinea pig. So I got a spinal tap. And I thought about it as if
women could give birth, I could give birth to my spinal fluid for my purpose. And once it wasn't
so bad, then I got over 30 people to volunteer for spinal taps, which were done initially at
Stanford and then at Hopkins. So all of this is to say that it didn't seem like there was any harm
to dopamine was still all focused on serotonin. It didn't seem like there was much evidence that
there was any problems with our serotonin either. You only get serotonin metabolites in the spinal
fluid. But what then happened was that the escalating fears of the rave movement and so
the serotonin hypothesis of MDMA causing serious problems, it started being challenged more and
more by other scientists, by people at the CDC Center for Disease Control. So their neuroscientists
started challenging this exaggerated risk estimates of serotonin. And so then what happened
with George Ricardi and Una McCann is they realized this is in the end of the 90s that the
serotonin damage theories that they were using to try to block research was getting increasingly
dubious and challenged. Plus more and more people had been doing MDMA for decades and still seem
fine. They published an article in science that claimed that MDMA hurt dopamine and would
potentially cause Parkinson's. And that was outrageous because the spinal tap studies didn't
show any evidence of harm and dopamine. Other studies had not shown any harm and dopamine.
They were just searching and they killed a bunch of the animals died during their experiments. But
this was published in science. Yeah, I was just about to say how did science publish that? There
must have been something they saw. Alan Leshner, who was the head of NIDA, later left NIDA, he built
it up. He pandered to Congress. He scared them about MDMA and other drugs. He increased the
budget of NIDA up to over a billion dollars a year. And then he left to become the president of
the AAAS, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, which publishes science.
Yeah. So that former head of NIDA, who was the main patron of George Ricardi,
Which is a real shame. I mean, people listening to this might not appreciate the significance of
what you just said, but science and nature are the two most high impact journals in the entire
field of science. So in other words, most scientists will go their entire career and not even have the
ability to submit an article to one of those journals, let alone have an article be accepted
in one of those journals. I don't believe there is an equivalent outside of science in terms of
what the prestige it would mean to have your work published in that journal. So it is certainly
troubling to hear that, not surprising, of course, but it's not the first time I've heard these
stories. But I think for the listener to understand what the implication is, this isn't the national
inquirer. Right. And then there was an editorial in science that talked about MDMA as being Russian
Roulette for your brain by Alan Leshner. And this study though, that was published in science,
actually just why a couple of weeks ago, this paper in nature about MDMA positively causing
neurogenesis and oxytocin release. And well, that's why that's so significant. Yeah, exactly. Now you
have nature and science being on bookends of this interesting story of this arc. Michael Mitovar and
I and others of our lead psychiatrist and I, we wrote a letter to science and we said that the
letter to the other, this doesn't make sense, this paper to us, you've killed a bunch of animals,
other animals have not died in experiments. You didn't give the animals the MDMA orally in the way
that people normally take it. There's all this evidence that MDMA doesn't hurt, don't mean.
Nobody we know has Parkinson's. And so we challenged them. And so what we didn't know then is that they
spent a year trying to replicate their results. So our letter did get published in science or
critical letter, but this whole year they kept defending their studies in the media. But we later
found out that they were having increasing problems in replicating their results. And they
later out of frustration after they couldn't replicate their results took some of the animals
that had died, did a tissue analysis and had discovered that they had given the animals
methamphetamine instead of MDMA. It's a slight mistake. It's just a slight subtle difference.
Yeah. And so they should never have published that paper because they should have known that.
Did they print a retraction? They did. They had to retract it.
That was 2004, end of 2003, 2004. So that was sort of the high watermark of the fear and
paranoia about MDMA neurotoxicity. Okay. So that relates to that's when we got the first approval
for our first PTSD study. So Charlie Grove, after we finished the safety study, he started getting
worried about MDMA being so identified with ecstasy and the wave movement and neurotoxicity.
So from a procedural standpoint, you have your IND filed, you've now documented through phase
one that this is not toxic. More importantly, you're not just winning that battle there.
More broadly, the scientific community is now realizing actually this is not a toxic compound
whatsoever. But in some ways, that's just the end of chapter one. Chapter two is great. You have a
safe compound. Now, what is the indication? What will be the medically valid use for this compound?
Yeah, we had thought initially MDMA for cancer patients with anxiety because cancer patients
would die and they wouldn't live long enough to supposedly show the effects of neurotoxicity.
But Charlie, who I was going to work with on this, he decided that MDMA was too controversial and he
wanted to switch to psilocybin. So that started the whole work with psilocybin with cancer patients.
I knew from 84 working with Marcella and just by the way, Marcella is now one of our lead therapists,
training other therapists. She later became a therapist. So it's a tremendous success
in her life. So I returned to PTSD and Michael Midhofer, who's our lead psychiatrist, came to me
in 2000 at a conference, the first conference ever on ayahuasca in America organized by Ralph
Metzner in San Francisco. And he was a member of MAPS, but I didn't know him. And he'd also been
trained in the holotropic breathwork by Stan Groff, which I'm also trained in. So it's
hyperventilation to bring out experiences that are sort of like LSD or psilocybin. So Michael
came to me in 2000 and he said, I want to work with you on creating an officer or clinic somewhere
in the world. Was there any developed country in the world or any country for that matter
for which MDMA wasn't scheduled? Because usually what happens is once the US schedules, other
countries follow suit. Yeah. So very briefly in 85 when we were suing the DEA, we became aware of the
DEA was trying to criminalize MDMA internationally through the world health organization, the
international treaties. That's where I went back to Robert Mueller and said, can you help set up
meetings? And just for the listener, because I know you've brought Robert Mueller up again,
this has no bearing. It's a different name. Mueller. Yeah. Yeah. This is spelled M U L L E R.
Yeah. And he was the assistant secretary general unit. And so he helped me set up meetings at the
world health organization in Geneva. So I went to Geneva in 85 and brought information there
to slow down the DEA criminalizing internationally. And in some incredible coincidence, the head of
that committee, the expert outside committee was Paul Groff, Stan Groff's brother. And the committee
endorsed the criminalization of MDMA except for one person, Paul. And he got a little footnote in
there saying that this was an important compound. He was worried that the criminalization
internationally would reduce research and the encourage the nations of the world to facilitate
research, which led to the Swiss government from 88 to 91 permitting people to do compassionate
use of MDMA and LSD. But when Michael came to me and said, so there's no place in the world
because it did get criminalized internationally. But Michael had been in St. Kitts where there was
a clinic that was set up for Ibogaine. Ibogaine is something that I very much want to research. It's
for opiate addiction. We're in the massive crisis for opiate addiction. Ibogaine helps people through
the withdrawals and it can give them spiritual experiences and brings up what they've
repressed. So it can be very, very helpful in both going through withdrawal and also in reducing
relapse. And it's illegal in the United States, but legal in Canada, Mexico,
multiple places. So Michael had a patient of his guanda St. Kitts and he went with, and so he came
to me and said, let's set up a clinic. Maybe we can find someplace where there's MDMA or LSD,
we could set up a clinic. And I said, I'm totally 100% not interested in doing that.
Because it sort of undercuts what you're doing at MAPS. It's sort of like saying, again, there's so
many moments in your story, Rick, where I'm sort of struck by the maturity of the hippie.
Like you're way smarter than anybody else. I wouldn't have had the foresight to have
you just played the long game at every moment. And I just, I want to applaud you for that as
someone who I just know personally, I just wouldn't have had the discipline or the foresight to have
played that long game over and over and over again, which was this is about the highest
integrity at the policy level. This is about the highest integrity at the scientific level.
And it's a hard decision because along the way, fewer people had access to something that you
felt very strongly could help them. But it was one of those examples of if it means that a few
hundred people or a few thousand people are denied this opportunity today, as much as that's
heartbreaking, this could mean millions of people can one day have access to this. And we won't
sort of taint or undermine the rigor with which we get them there. Yeah. Yeah. And I've always had
people in the back of my mind from the Holocaust saying, if we don't bring this forward and
mainstream it, we could have another situation. We have the rise of authoritarianism, the rise of
hatred for the immigrants. And we have a lot of that going on right now we can see. And so that
just is further motivation for me to try to mainstream it. Even that's where the compassion
for the police comes in. That's for them as well. And so I said, Michael, I'm totally not interested
in setting up offshore clinic, but I think first off, there's no place. But secondly, it's about
going to the heart of the system and making change happen from the inside out. Yeah. And your fight
is here. Your fight is in DC. Yeah, exactly. And then the US is one of our most successful exports
has been the drug war. And so other countries look around at us. If the US is changing, then the drug
war will erode all over them. So I said, Michael, let think that now is the time we can work with
the FDA. Would you work with me? And he was an expert in PTSD. And I'm like, fantastic. Because
PTSD is the next thing. And now that we don't have to worry about people saying, oh, neurotoxicity,
PTSD became the number one thing, the top priority. And Michael said, yes. Yeah. Before
we leave the toxicity and start talking about the efficacy, I just want to ask, based on everything
you know today, which patients would not be good candidates for MDMA from a safety perspective?
Are there some patients that we would still say today? Because, you know, look, any drug we can
say ibuprofen shouldn't be taken with by certain patients. Tylenol shouldn't be taken by certain
patients, either over the counter. Who in your mind is not a good candidate for MDMA therapy?
The most important thing is people with compromised hearts. So that MDMA increases
blood pressure, not overwhelmingly, not substantially, but significantly, I can show you. But we work
with people that have controlled hypertension, people that have had uncontrolled hypertension
and only recently got it controlled. We'll say you need to do a stress test. But of all the tens
of millions of doses of MDMA that are being used every year in the world, there's almost nobody
ever has a heart attack. Almost nobody, really. I mean, there's hardly any cases like that. So,
but still, that's the concern. When people are on a lot of other psychiatric medications,
we ask them all to taper off of them. The SSRIs blunt the effects of MDMA.
There's a remote chance that MDMA could trigger a seizure. Also, that seems to almost never happen,
but so we will not at least initially work with people who are epileptic.
I notice in the documentaries, the patients in the study have blood pressure cuffs on.
Yeah, we have to monitor blood pressure and temperature. We exclude people that are psychotic
we exclude people with schizophrenia. Although I think MDMA could be very helpful with schizophrenia,
but it needs a different container because we basically do outpatient. I mean, they come in
for the MDMA session, which is done under supervision. They spend the night after the
MDMA session and then they get more integrative psychotherapy the next day, but then they go home.
So if somebody was schizophrenic, we would want more of a longer containment window. Yeah. Bipolar.
I don't think MDMA is likely to be helpful for people with bipolar. My brother is bipolar and
he's tried MDMA and he had a good day, but it made him slightly manic and it didn't
change things on a long-term basis. Let's talk about that actually, which is I've experienced
MDMA in both settings. I've experienced MDMA in the setting of you're listening to music,
you're having fun, you're out and about around other people. I've also experienced it in a
very therapeutic setting and they're very different. It's so interesting that the same
molecule could have such a different effect based on the term that gets used so often,
the set and the setting, the intention and the way it's done. And I'm trying to think of the best
way to explain to people the difference because I suspect there are people listening to this who
have experienced MDMA vis-a-vis ecstasy, Molly at a party or something like that and can certainly
speak to how you feel wonderful on it. But what we've been talking about is very different. What
we've been talking about is very emotional. Anytime I've used it in this sort of therapeutic setting,
I mean it's endless rivers of tears and it requires a lot of processing afterwards. It requires
further discussion, journaling, these sorts of things. What is it about creating that setting
with that intention, ideally with a therapist and with this sort of follow through that transforms
something that is arguably one of the most feel-good drugs at a party into a drug that is healing
the deepest emotional wounds that people have? I think it's the intent and it's whether your
focus is external or internal. So the best way to understand these things, they're just tools
and they're not inherently therapeutic or inherently recreational or inherently dangerous
or inherently safe. These are tools and how they're used makes all the difference. So when you take it
at a party and you're externally focused and you're dancing and you're talking to other people,
people still process a lot of important stuff and people have insights and can make therapeutic
process even in recreational settings. They feel connected to this whole group. They feel less
isolated. A lot of good can come from recreational settings but in general, people who use it in a
recreational setting say they want to have the good slice of experiences and if something is
difficult or painful, that's not what they're looking for. The thing about MDMA that's different
from the classic psychedelics is you can negotiate with the content a little bit. By the way, I feel
that is completely true, Rick. I mean psilocybin and ayahuasca are beautiful and powerful tools
but I have never for a second in using them felt like I had even a modicum of direction. I mean,
I've never done bullfighting but when you watch it on TV where these guys are on the bull and they
got the little taser on the bull's nuts and that's what it feels like to be on those agents at high
enough doses which is there's probably something important to be gleaned here but I have no idea
where it's going. I have no idea what's going to come up and I have at least personally have no
ability to steer it even if it starts going in a bad direction. Yeah, the essence of doing the
classic psychedelics is the art of surrender. It's the ego dissolution and that's exactly the
difference that gives them their power but also to me there's just a finer therapeutic line.
Yeah, very much so and that's where like where we talked about with Marcella, she got stuck with
LSD. She couldn't control it. She couldn't turn elsewhere. It just was so powerful emergence and
she couldn't handle it. So there's a way in which what differentiates sort of a good drip from a bad
drip is this resistance. So what we like to say is difficult is not the same as bad. If you have
difficult material but you're not resisting it, you can learn from it. You can grow from it but
it's the resistance that freezes it in place and it causes friction and is painful but it's very
difficult if not impossible to negotiate with the classic psychedelics but with MDMA you can
so that people can say to some extent this is material that I don't want to deal with now and
then you're out of focus and you're not processing that and I think unless there's a real safe
setting people are going to say that that they don't want to deal with that because it is frightening
so that therapeutic context where you're focused inward and you're open to whatever emerges even
difficult things that's where the MDMA can be very very uniquely and remarkably helpful coming to a
different relationship with these painful experiences that have happened in the past. So I think if
many of the people that are in our study not I'd say most of them have never done MDMA before but
some of them have and those that have say that it was so different in a recreational setting is in
a therapeutic setting and so this idea of welcoming the conflict instead of trying to just have the
slice the happy slice is what makes it a difference and so from 1999 2000 to 2016 is when we did what's
called the phase two pilot studies. How many such studies were done? We did six different studies in
Israel, Canada, Switzerland, and the United States and the purpose of pilot studies is to prepare for
phase three. The whole purpose of phase two is to prepare for phase three. Which is to show efficacy.
Phase three is to show large-scale studies to show safety and efficacy. Phase two is to figure out who
is your patient population, what are your doses, what is your what's your indication. Yeah what are
the people that you exclude and include and so that's where we did a whole series of studies with
different patient populations. So basically from 1986 when I started MAPS to November 29 2016 it
was 30 years of getting ready. We had what's called an end of phase two meeting and that's
where the FDA said yes we could go to phase three. And is that when the designation of breakthrough
therapy was given or was that later? No. So what happens is once you end up getting permission to
go to phase three most pharmaceutical companies go to phase three but there's a program called
special protocol assessment where you can voluntarily engage with FDA where you negotiate
every aspect of the phase three design plus all the other information that they want to see. And
if you come to agreement you get an agreement letter that means that the FDA is legally bound
to approve the drug if you get statistically significant evidence of efficacy using this design
and if no new safety problems come up. Since MDMA is unlike any other drug that the FDA has ever
studied because tens of millions of people have taken it for multiple decades we have all this
information about the safety risk we're pretty comfortable there's going to be no new safety
things. So we went through this whole process of special protocol assessment and then we applied
for breakthrough therapy. So we got special protocol assessment and then a couple weeks later
we got breakthrough therapy. And tell people what that means in a sentence or two. Breakthrough
therapy designation is for the most promising drugs and if you get this breakthrough therapy
designation the FDA partners with you to try to make it into a medicine. So you have shorter review
timelines more meetings with FDA. And this is pegged to an indication in this case because the
indication of PTSD has no other option that is appearing to have any medical efficacy. Well
there are two drugs that are approved by the FDA for PTSD Zoloft and Paxil and both of those are
SSRIs that diminish symptoms don't solve the problem and don't work in many many people. So
it's the absence of other treatments a large group of treatment resistant people and breakthrough
therapy we were able to get. So it's the most important program that the FDA has and that was
the sign that now we had reached this place of legitimacy 30 years after we had started maps.
Has the FDA ever encountered another situation that you're bringing which is you're not
presumably just trying to seek legalization for a molecule that's going to be dispensed at a pharmacy
but it's tied to a therapy. So how does the FDA think about what you're actually doing which is
administering a therapeutic protocol not just a medication? It's new for the FDA. Yeah they've
never approved a drug therapy combination. And that is what they're being asked to do now? Yeah.
However there have been some drugs that have special risks that they approve certain kind
of educational programs that are required. So the best example there is thalidomide. So the only
person from the FDA that ever won the Presidential Medal of Honor was Frances Kelsey and she was the
one in the early 60s that blocked thalidomide from becoming a medicine in the US. It was used for
morning sickness caused all these birth defects. Years later, decades later, thalidomide became a
medicine. It's useful for leprosy and some other kinds of cancers. And so the FDA developed a whole
set of policy tools that they require a patient registry. Everybody who gets thalidomide is on a
registry to see if there's any birth defects. There's requirements of education for the
pharmacist, for the patient, for the prescriber. And so this has evolved into what's called the
REMS, the Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies, that the FDA can now regulate different drugs
according to their unique risks. So there's never been a drug therapy combination approved by FDA,
but there have been drugs where they've had different kinds of REMS to control the risks
and have required certain kind of policies. So the FDA is actually learning from and with us
about how to regulate psychotherapy, which they don't actually have the authority to regulate
psychotherapy. But we've came to them and said, the only people that we think should be directly
treating patients if this drug is approved is people that have learned the therapy as well as
the drug. And so that's what the FDA has agreed so that everybody who will be prescribing it and
will be treating patients has to go through our training program. So there's one phase three study
that has multi sites, I'm assuming. There'll be two. There'll be two phase three studies,
each 100 persons, depending on the effect size, we think that probably, hopefully it'll be each,
only 100 persons each. And we've enrolled 19 of the first 100. I've read that you think that this
could be approved as soon as 2021. Yeah, the end of 2021, we think. But what people should also
know is that because there's so many people with PTSD in America, and because we're only going to
enroll, hopefully 200 people, the FDA has a program called expanded access, which is compassionate use.
Yeah, tell me about how that works. If you have a disease that nothing has helped for you,
and there's a drug being studied for that disease, and if the pharmaceutical company agrees,
they will set up this compassionate use program where you can have access to the drug before it's
approved while phase three is still going on. So your therapist gets a special designation from the
FDA and the DEA to possess and use this not yet approved agent with you? Sort of. Because it's a
controlled substance, only physicians will be able to get schedule and licenses to work with.
So there'll be therapists working with the physicians or the physicians will be,
but there's an overarching protocol that we negotiate with FDA. It's different than phase
three, because first off, people have to accept the risk, and they have to pay for it themselves,
because the FDA doesn't use the data to approve it. So the pharmaceutical company isn't going to
pay to have all these people treated. So the protocol can also be riskier patients. So we
can let people in who, let's say we're talking now about certain kind of diabetes. For excessive
caution, we exclude people with diabetes, even though loads of people with diabetes have done
MDMA, but we can let people with diabetes in expanded action. What's the concern with patients
with diabetes? Some sort of vascular problems and maybe they... Oh, but it doesn't alter blood sugar?
No, it's not directly about that. It's more about a stroke or something like that. We are training
now people for expanded access already, and that was the meetings we had with DEA and FDA. How long
is that if I, for example, wanted to... I mean, I'm not a psychiatrist, nor am I a therapist in
any way, shape, or form. Is it even possible for just a regular Joe Blow to become certified?
Yes, it is. We have training programs. We're the only ones not with the training programs,
but our model is a male-female co-therapy team, and one of them needs to be licensed as a therapist
or a psychiatrist. But the other one doesn't. It can be a student getting a license, can be a nurse,
can be a social worker, can be somebody without a license. So what we're saying is that the two-person
team works better than one person. It's not twice as good, but most people that are traumatized
don't develop PTSD. Those that do tend to have a history of trauma before them, often going to
childhood and attachment disorders. And so having a well-functioning male-female team as people go
through their traumas can recreate sort of a loving kind of a situation that they didn't have
when they were young. But we don't want to make it so that it's twice as expensive. So the idea
will eventually be one person, licensed therapist, the other is a student working for free to get
their hours or working for lower cost or something like that. And so we are now opening up the
training to people that will set up expanded access sites. And the ideal, cities where we
don't have phase three sites or cities where we do have phase three sites but where there's a lot
of people that have PTSD. So to get into expanded access, you have to have treatment resistant PTSD.
It means nothing else worked for you, but people can have less severe PTSD. So psychedelic clinics
are going to be opening up throughout America at the end of this year. Someone listening to this
who has PTSD does not have to wait until 2021 necessarily. Their best option is, one, identify
a place where there's an ongoing phase three trial. You may be a candidate for it. And I assume
there's no placebo. Does that mean that everybody in it will be treated? Well, in phase three, there
has to be a placebo. It's a controlled study. So when you randomize, there's a chance you'll get
the therapy without the... Yeah, you either get therapy without MDMA or therapy with active
MDMA. However, everybody that gets randomized to the control group, once the study is over,
they can cross over for free. So everybody is offered. In the expanded access, because you're
paying for it, there is no control group. Yeah. Because I get asked this question all the time,
Rick, even by patients and by people who know of my interest in this, which is how long do I have
to wait? And it sounds like the answer is not as long as you thought really. In theory, this year,
you can find compassionate use exemption. Yeah, I think so. I think the other part though to say
is that in our phase two pilot studies, 23% of the people that got the therapy without active MDMA
no longer had PTSD two months after the last experimental session. So that's actually pretty
good in people that are severe treatment resistant chronic. So I'd like to encourage
people if they are thinking about it to volunteer for phase three, you will get therapy, which can
be very effective. And then in the end, you'll get MDMA. But there is a bit of sacrifice in a sense
that you have to wait potentially, you have to wait, but we need that. So if phase three starts
slowing down, FDA is going to shut down expanded access. I just wanted to add that the psychedelic
clinics that we're going to open for expanded access, people are also being cross trained for
ketamine. And eventually, these clinics will work with psilocybin. So the long term vision is that
these psychedelic clinics that we're opening initially become places where people can go for
therapy for MDMA or ketamine or psilocybin. But eventually, we hope that they become sites of
initiation, where people who don't have a clinical diagnosis can go for psychedelic therapy for
personal growth or for couples therapy or for a mystical experience. And then if it goes well,
in your first experience with LSD or MDMA or psilocybin, then you get a license to go buy it
and do it on your own. So the future is a system of licensed legalization, where people have access
outside of religion and outside of medicine, but that there's also these opportunities for medical
use that insurance would pay for if you have certain diagnoses. Psilocybin is sort of on the
heels of MDMA. Yeah. Where do you see LSD in this? How far down the line? It all depends on resources.
I mean, LSD, so we're anticipating that it's somewhere in the neighborhood of $40 million
to make a psychedelic drug into a medicine. That's about what you will have spent to go from your
phase one to three on MDMA. In the history of maps, we spent another $10 million on the phase
two studies. We've spent loads of money on a lot of the political work trying to get permission,
so that isn't going to be necessary anymore. So if some of these billionaires out there that have
the resources, if they wanted to make LSD into a medicine, what you've done is created a playbook.
In many ways, MDMA is far and away the biggest lift because you had to do everything from soup
to nuts, including the advocacy. Assuming MDMA is approved in 2021, there is now a playbook for how
to do this with other agents, and psilocybin, of course, is right on the heels. The last thing I
would say is I would encourage anybody who's listening to this, whose curiosity has been piqued
to watch a documentary called A Trip of Compassion, which is, I hadn't heard of it actually until Tim
Farris told me about it. I think he had just come back from Israel, but I can't remember if he had
seen it before. He saw it in Israel. He saw it in Israel. It's hard to watch. There's just no doubt
about it. It's very moving, but I think it's important. I think if you're listening to this
and you're still a bit unclear about what Peter and Rick have been talking about, you invest an
hour and a half in watching this documentary, just search Trip of Compassion and you'll find it,
and you can stream it for five bucks or something. I can't think of many better uses of an hour and
a half of your time, and I still maintain to this day that this, I acknowledge, is a slightly
hyperbolic statement. I'm not convinced that there is a man-made molecule that is more important
than MDMA. Again, it's hard to imagine a world with conflict if everybody had the opportunity
to experience this drug in a supportive setting through the lens of, we didn't talk that much
about it, but I think it becomes clear when people will watch this stuff, this ability to feel another
person's pain is also very powerful, and I think that's a big part of what helps the trauma victim,
is that someone else can feel that pain with them. They know that the person with them feels
what they're going through, and that in and of itself begins the process of alleviation.
That sounds hoity-toity, and if you haven't experienced it, I apologize. You will not know
what I'm talking about, and that's okay. Yeah, the Trip of Compassion is about three of our Israeli
PTSD patients in our Israeli study. So much of it is in Hebrew, some of it is in English, but it
has English subtitles, and it's three different kinds of stories too, so you really get to see
about how MDMA works. Sexual abuse, it's an explosion, like sort of terrorist violence,
and what was the third? The third was kidnapping. That's right, the kidnapping moment, yes, yes.
It's very powerful, and some of it too is where people are explaining what happened to them in a
peaceful way, but others you can see how trauma is trapped in the body too, so a lot of it is people
shaking and just letting out the fears that they had sort of suppressed in their body. So there's
a book by Bessel van der Koch, who's a psychiatrist PTSD expert called The Body Keeps the Score.
Yes. And so Bessel is actually the principal investigator of our Boston site, and so we're
working with the leading PTSD researchers all over the world, and I think that MDMA will make a major,
major contribution towards healing PTSD. And also, why I think it's so important, and why I think you
may mention that as well, is that it also heals multigenerational trauma, that we have conflicts
that are passed on through epigenetics from generation to generation, and they can keep
conflicts going for thousands of years. We can break those cycles within one generation,
within one session sometimes. I think that's the real hope, is how can we move from this weight of
trauma that has been plaguing humanity for thousands of years in our murderous nature,
and how do we evolve from that to appreciate the other rather than being scared by the other,
and to not have to define ourselves by who we're not, but how we're all more connected and celebrate
differences rather than be scared of them. Hey, just as a reminder, this was technically the end
of my interview with Rick. However, as I mentioned in the intro, we moved the first 75 minutes or so,
and we bumped it to what you are about to hear now. This section dives really deep into Rick's
background, his motivation for doing what he's doing, and basically what shaped Rick into becoming
the complete and utter force of nature that he is. Hope you enjoy. You dropped out of college,
and there was a bit of a hiatus there. What year was that? Well, I started college in 71 and dropped
out in 72, and when I dropped out, I had this really important exchange with my parents,
where I said basically that I wanted to drop out of college. I wanted to study LSD and become an
LSD therapist and bring back psychedelic research, and I wanted them to pay for it. They were
initially shocked. I would say I'm the oldest of four kids, so I was the first one out of the nest,
and then here I am at college, and within a few months, I'm taking LSD and deciding to drop out.
What I ended up explaining to them was that they were very open-minded in different ways,
and I felt that when I learned from LSD that I was unbalanced intellectually and emotionally.
I was overdeveloped intellectually and underdeveloped emotionally and spiritually,
and the world I felt was the same. Albert Einstein said that our technology has exceeded our humanity,
and so I felt that this was at a time of the height of the Cold War and not that long after
the Cuban Missile Crisis, and this whole concern that we had this nuclear technology that we might
not be able to handle as humans, mutual assured destruction, and that the world felt at risk,
and so I felt that this imbalance that was in me that was also in the world and this ability of LSD
to help me emotionally and spiritually. To explain a little bit more, I was a draft resistor to
Vietnam, so this was during a period of time when I anticipated going to jail. I did a lot of study
of nonviolent resistance, so I read Tolstoy and Thoreau and Emerson and Gandhi and Martin Luther
King and a lot about that, and so I felt that I was not a pacifist, and so to be a conscientious
objector to Vietnam, you had to be a pacifist. I was planning to go to college, and there's
college deferments, but I felt like that wasn't really the proper kind of way to protest, and I
felt like running to Canada was the wrong idea. I felt that it was important to directly confront
the draft and to suffer the consequences, so what I felt was the best strategic approach was to not
register for the draft at all, to drain the system of the most energy, to make them come after me.
What I didn't realize is that the system itself wasn't as omnipotent as I thought it was,
and roughly I learned later 60,000 people or so never registered for the draft,
and so absolutely nothing happened to me. That later became a moral dilemma, like do I need to
tell the draft board that I didn't register so they would come and put me in jail, but at this
point I had discovered LSD and was seeing that this move beyond ego, this sense of spiritual
connection, the sense of oneness, the sense of unity struck me as having incredible political
implications, and that's a lot of what I think was going on during the 60s, is that the common
narrative looking back is that psychedelics gone wrong is what caused the backlash. People took it
unprepared, they had psychotic episodes, they committed suicide, they jumped out of windows,
they did all these things, and therefore the drug war was to help prevent drug abuse. When actually
what I think happened more was that psychedelics went right, people had these experiences of going
beyond their ego, going beyond their different ways that they identified themselves by their
country, their religion, their gender, their race, their socioeconomic status, all these other ways
that we define ourselves and divide ourselves, and that by having that fundamental connection
to the earth, to the planet, to everybody, that that would be an antidote towards genocide,
towards tribalism, fundamentalism, towards fear of the other. And so I thought that at a time
where the world could go up in nuclear explosions, and earlier I had been traumatized by learning
about the Holocaust. So I was born in 53 and I have loads of Israeli relatives who fought in the
48 war, been there for a long time. I had distant relatives killed in the Holocaust. My grandfather
came from Poland in 1920 and so his family was left behind. My other relatives came a generation
before and I grew up in a town called Skokie, Illinois, and I thought everybody was Jewish,
everybody my family knew was Jewish, but I was six years old and it's kind of a family story about
when I learned that the whole world wasn't Jewish and then it was just a tiny tiny fraction and I
was like what if they're right, what if we're going to hell and Jesus is the only way, and but it made
me feel like this tiny tiny minority and then the more that I learned about the Holocaust, I just
had to wrestle with that level of magnitude of human cruelty. But I was protected by this
incredible loving family and at the same time I realized I've had almost all the possible ways
to feel safe. So I was born in America at the peak of American power and I sort of bought into
this American exceptionalism. I was also a male, I was also the first born male child, and I was also
my family, my dad was a doctor, my mother was a teacher, but my mother's father was an industrialist
and had made a big success in business and so we were economically secure and I was Jewish, part of
the chosen people. So I had every kind of thing to think about that I was safe and protected, plus
when we were 12 we moved to a town called Winnetka which was a further north wealthier town and
people were leading different businesses and government. Donald Rumsfeld lived across the
street and so I was I guess just thinking that I had the ability to make an influence on the world
and that safety gave me I think the sense of capacity in a way to look at bigger threats
without being terrified. I also knew as I was growing up that my grandfather had created this
trust for all of his grandchildren. By today's standards it wasn't that much but it was enough
that I would be able to pay for food and shelter and so that meant that I didn't need to compromise
with what I would do with my life. I didn't have to find a job for survival, I could find a job
for whatever I thought was most important and so there was also a period of time where I was just
wrestling with this the cruelty of the Holocaust and then as a young boy being in school during the
Cuban Missile Crisis and being told that you can hide under your desk and you might survive and
so it was the Germans were the ones doing it to the Jews now it's the Russians doing it to the
Americans then it was the Vietnam War my own country doing things and I got to know Daniel
Ellsberg and at one point he talked about how he realized that initially that he thought we were
on the wrong side of the war in Vietnam and then he realized we were the wrong side that sort of
sense of the world being crazy in peril and now my own country is wanting to send me to kill people
or be killed for dubious reasons and then I became this draft resistor and struggling with what do I
do with my life and so I felt that I was the product of three or four generations where
the third and fourth generation my great grandparents and my grandparents their job
was survival they left poor from pogroms from Russia and Poland they landed in America then
they made financial successes and then I had the ability to look at deeper threats so I interpreted
this freedom that I had to survive to buy food and shelter as a charge as a gift from generations
before for me to look at deeper threats and that became the threat of nuclear annihilation or
again threats of future prejudice and so I was just very much of a reader in high school and
started reading Jung and thinking a lot about Herman Hess and kind of spirituality and I looked
at what was going on in the 60s I initially believed all the propaganda that LSD was terrible
that it would cause chromosome damage that it would make you crazy if you did a certain numbers
of times but the more I wised up the more I realized that I had been fed a lot of propaganda
I actually was studying Russian to learn about the other my parents sent me to Russia after my junior
year of high school so I spent the summer in Russia learning the language that would have been unusual
right in the late 60s for an American to go to Russia it was incredible it was 1970 it was with
60 high school students and we went to summer condon Tashkent people there had never seen Americans
and ones that spoke Russian it was just an incredible eye-opener for me to see the other
at one point where we were outside of Leningrad for most of the time for six weeks they were
learning the language I went for a walk with a Russian girl down the beach and I just thought
wow you're not this devil or you're not a monster you're just a person and then I started realizing
these are conflicts between countries but the people aren't really necessarily hating each other
political systems political leaders and conflict but I did want to study the other and so I was in
my Russian class in my senior year of high school and a friend of mine knew I love books and he gave
me a book to read I love this book and I turned it back to him and I said this is one of the best
books I've ever read and he said do you know that this author wrote some of this book while he was
under the influence of LSD and I'm like that's not possible LSD you can't produce it makes you crazy
and he assured me that that was true and so I looked into it more it was one for over the
cuckoo's nest by Ken Kesey and it turned out he had written some of it while it was under LSD so
that's what really was the key turning point as far as me opening my eyes to LSD and then when I
ended up at college it was a new college in Sarasota Florida it was an experimental college
that had started in the 60s and it was designed as kind of an antidote to traditional education
so the fundamental principle was that the student's curiosity is the most important thing
IM Pei the architect had designed the buildings it was on the Ringling Brothers grounds the
Ringling Circus grounds because that's where they wintered in Sarasota and it had no grades it had
written evaluations it was very small classes independent study a lot everybody had to do a
senior thesis but when I got to this college this is before I had done LSD there was two things that
they didn't put in the brochure that I didn't expect but that both I was incredibly grateful
for one was that they had this tradition of all-night dances under the stars with psychedelics
and they had a tradition of people doing psychedelics individually for personal growth
at the time the average dose of LSD was 250 micrograms so that you would go for an existential
experience beyond verbal communication abilities and that was the standard dose now it's around
one fourth or one third of that dose is the standard dose because a lot of people got into
trouble and it was too much for them but they had this tradition of welcoming psychedelic use and
it was brilliant people from all over the place the other tradition that they had was surprising
there was a woman professor Marianne Hoppen who had studied directly with Jung and she had married
someone who was quite wealthy and the school didn't have a lot of facilities and so they
donated an olympic-sized swimming pool outdoors to the school and for whatever reason it turned
into a nudist colony so I was a super shy guy in high school for two years I couldn't even speak
to a girl other than my mother and my sister I was just too shy I just couldn't even do it now
here I'm sitting at this pool with all these beautiful naked girls and and it felt somehow
like this was a oasis of sanity that this college had created this place where we could be bringing
things up from the underground from suppressed things so sexuality physicality psychedelics
they were welcome the campus police job was to protect us from the real police they had two sets
of room notes where people were living there was one where the rooms that you were assigned the
other where the rooms where you really were living and so they would permit guys and girls
to live together on campus it was just this oasis of sanity in a crazy world and then I started
deciding to do psychedelics and so my first experience really it was difficult because I
wasn't very fluid emotionally but it touched certain parts of my psyche that I felt that my
bar mitzvah had failed to touch I thought the traditional rites of passage didn't work for me
I was left hungry and wanting more and didn't feel a spiritual connection and so I felt the
the psychedelics really had a big potential there and then I was reading the whole earth catalog
by Stephen Brand and in it they had this advertisement or this review actually up for a
book and the book was by John Lilly and it was called programming and metaprogramming in the
human biocomputer and it was about the research that he did in the 50s funded by the navy where
he developed the flotation tank and then he started doing LSD in the tank and trying to
understand his mind as if it was a biocomputer trying to really understand I mean we know enormous
amounts now about how specialized different brain regions are but they didn't really know that much
back then so this was an incredible book about LSD to go into the unconscious and at the same time
that this was happening this was 71 and 72 this was after the backlash against the 60s so the
idealism of the 60s the spiritually motivated move towards the start of a lot of movements
had backlash and had failed and a lot of it was because of the flaws of the advocates not just
the evil system trying to squash everything which was going on too but there was also this
sense that counterculture had failed people talk about the 70s as the me decade but I think a lot
of it was about this where did we go wrong that our own instrument was was flawed so I felt like
this deep work was necessary to kind of purify and to refine so that when we try to bring this
back again that it's mainstreamed and not rejected and I started doing flotation tank sort of we
tried to create our own sensory isolation experiments with gloves and eye shades and
different things we didn't actually have tanks at the time but some friends and I would do a large
doses of LSD in isolation environments and I started having a lot of problems with my LSD trips
also mexiclin somebody came by a campus with half a pound of mexiclin so I bought all of it
and capped it hundreds of capsules and friends and I just did it for months and just to give you a
sense of how new college was at the time I just had hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of mexiclin
capsules in my drawer in my room and people would come to me and they'd say I'd like to buy some
mexiclin I'd say yeah go ahead here it is take as many as you want here's the money leave the money
and nobody ever ripped me off nobody ever got in trouble it was just this sense that this was a
crazy world the Vietnam war was raging and here we were trying to find a new way now at the time
Rick was mexiclin and or LSD scheduled yeah yeah they were both illegal two things I just want to
interject for historical context the first is just give folks a bit of a background on LSD when it
was synthesized it's a completely synthesized molecule so it doesn't exist in nature and a
number of the psychedelics do exist in nature so we can contrast that give me like a little bit of
a background on LSD okay yeah also I'll say that Albert Hoffman who was the Sandoz chemist that
first synthesized LSD in 38 and they were looking for drugs that might be helpful for
Sandoz by the way is to this day is to a pharma giant well Sandoz has been purchased by Novartis
yeah yeah it's funny there Sandoz makes like there are certain hormones like thyroid hormones
where I actually always prefer patients get the generic Sandoz like the one made by Sandoz yeah
I'm very particular about it if they get lebothiroxine I want it to be Sandoz
wow that's neat what's really important for me symbolically is that are the maps public benefit
corporation which is what conducts our research our drug development research with psychedelics
it's led by a whole group of women who came from Novartis so we have the the Sandoz
relationship yeah yeah training so we've got big pharma so what was Albert's motivation or the
motivation of the corporation yeah they were looking for drugs for stopping postpartum bleeding
ergot has been used for that purpose and so Albert was doing various derivatives from ergot
and then chemically modifying them so LSD 25 is in the 25th of the series and they gave it to a
bunch of animals and found nothing interesting and in the height of world war two in 43 after
Albert had finished some other bit of work he had what he called a peculiar pre-sentiment that this
drug that had been studied and abandoned might have some potential he almost never did that is
gone back to drugs that he'd invented that had been tested in animals and found to be of no
interest to Sandoz he almost never went back so he writes a lot about this peculiar pre-sentiment
that he had and whether this was some kind of calling or so he re-synthesized it in April 16th
of 1943 so this was five years after he had originally basically come to the conclusion
this was not going to have any efficacy for postpartum bleeding yeah yeah or other things too i
mean they were looking for other things as well maybe it had other potential purposes but five
years later he re-synthesized it and during this re-synthesis process and he's an incredibly
meticulous Swiss chemist he didn't know how he might have contaminated himself but he started
closing his eyes and seeing colors and visions it lasted for a couple hours and kind of went away
but it was a weird kind of an experience for him and he thought maybe maybe somehow he had
contaminated himself with this LSD 25 that he was manufacturing and so that was on a Friday
April 16th 1943 and so he decided over the weekend that he would do a planned experiment
on Monday the 19th and it would take a tiny fraction of this drug that he thought would have
no effect but he would try to see if there was something to it if his visions that he had on
Friday were related to this drug and so he took 250 micrograms 250 millionths of a gram and
during that experience he went through this similar kind of vision so he became convinced
that this was the cause of what had happened on Friday but it got stronger and stronger and
he was starting to lose his normal frame of reference and worrying that he had poisoned
himself and that he was going to die and he started feeling like he was going to die and so
he ended up deciding that he would leave the laboratory and he would go home and so he rode
his bicycle so now Tom Roberts who's a psychologist who helps transpersonal psychology has called it
bicycle day and so now it's celebrated around the world that he took his bicycle home while
he was tripping and there's been videos made about this but Albert gets home and they call
his wife and tell his wife that he might be dying they get milk from a neighbor because they thought
milk would be an antidote and he drinks gallon of milk and stuff and none of this helps and he goes
through this whole existential crisis but then in the end he actually doesn't die and then he has
spiritual experiences he's written about it it's beautiful LSD my problem child by Albert Hoffman
we've actually maps has published that book we just got 3,500 copies of it delivered on Monday
and so it's a beautiful book about the origins of LSD and this was just something that Albert was
shocked about and then in the morning he felt great and so he thought that this drug
was like a temporary voyage into insanity so they called it psychotomimetic meaning it mimics
psychosis and they started sharing it Sandoz did they started well first off Albert's bosses didn't
believe that this could be possible that a drug in that small amount could actually have such an
effect it's worth noting for a listener what you said was micrograms so you said 250 micrograms
but if any person thinking about a drug that they take if you take a drug for your blood pressure
or your cholesterol or an antibiotic these are virtually always in milligrams which is 1000 times
greater so 250 milligrams is 1000 times more than 250 micrograms turns out Synthroid or drugs
for thyroid are some of the few drugs that are actually dosed in micrograms but you're right this
is a very potent agent to be at the level of millionths of grams to reach significant clinical
feeling I mean they obviously at the time didn't know what it was doing but they knew that they
were dealing with something potent so several of Albert's bosses didn't believe him and they tried
LSD as well and then they were persuaded that it really was from the LSD and then they started
trying to figure out what they do with this incredible drug and so they started shipping
it around to different researchers to see if they would look into it they said this could be used
for psychiatry to help you have a temporary voyage into insanity the first research in the
United States was in 1949 at Harvard and they ended up circulating it to different places in
the 50s in the middle 50s they sent it to Czech Republic that's where Stan Groff ended up using
it in the middle 50s but it also came to the attention of the military and began this whole
effort to study mind control drugs and what they called non-lethal incapacitants and it became
tangled up in the CIA they had a project called MK ultra they thought it would be good for
stereotypically dosing world leaders and making them embarrassed when they're giving speeches
or different things incapacitating a whole group of army people they tried to see if they could do
it in aerosol sprays so it had this dual track of military applications which were mostly kept
secret and then also therapeutic or temporary voyage to insanity but more people who took it
realized that it wasn't temporary insanity it was something different and that there was this
spiritual aspect to it it started being used in different ways for psychotherapy in particular it
was being used for alcoholism and heroin addiction in the 50s and in the 60s and in the 50s
w bill wilson who started aa actually tried lsd his first experience was of a psychedelic was with
belladonna which was kind of something used by the witches it was more disorienting but during his
belladonna experience he decided to get sober and then years later when this work with lsd was being
developed he explored it and so bill w did lsd and thought it had tremendous potential for
treatment of alcoholism and it helps the spiritual sense and it also brings to the surface things
that people have suppressed and so it's good for psychotherapy and then it's also good for
building sources of strength from these kind of spiritual experiences what also happened is the cia
funded some expeditions sent people to mexico with gordon wassain in 57 58 to search for mushrooms
for other drugs that might be psychedelic now why did they realize that was it based on the
similarity in chemical structure between a completely synthesized molecule like lsd and what they
knew were similar molecules that would exist in nature well mexcalin had been extracted
synthesized from peyote in like 1895 or so and it had been used in research a lot in the 20s and 30s
mostly in europe also william james the father of american psychology had experimented also in
like 1896 or so with nitrous oxide and wrote about it in the varieties of religious experience
so there was already knowledge about how other substances had these properties i mean the word
psychedelic didn't get developed until 1958 by um humphrey osmond who wrote this poem to aldis
huxley i'll just say that you're wearing the doors i've got a door shirt on here now i wore
i wore this knowing that that you would appreciate it yeah and the doors got their name from the
doors of perception which i read in high school and became obsessed with the band yeah and so that
was from aldis huxley's discussion about his mexican experience is is writing about that and so
there was this whole awareness of these kind of substances and so there was this expedition gordon
wassain was going to track down this idea that mushrooms might be used as spiritual tools by
the mazatec indians and the ci had somebody go along secretly as part of that expedition
and once they got these mushrooms they did have these psychedelic experiences but they gave it to
a bunch of different chemists and they weren't able to figure out what was in it what was the
active ingredient so they decided they would send it to albert hoffman and albert was able to figure
out that the active ingredient was psilocybin and the reason he said that he was able to figure it
out and nobody else was is that he was willing to drink the different fractions and see which
produced the similar effect to yeah what he had already known yeah and then he would continue
trying to separate it out to find out what was the active ingredient oh my god do you want to talk
about the citizen scientist right oh yeah but he's again working for sandos at the time and so
albert figured it out so 15 years after he discovered lsd in 43 discovered really the
psychedelic properties he was the one that isolated psilocybin and then shortly after that
there was this whole effort to understand other sources in nature of psychedelics and it turns out
that morning glory seeds have also been used for psychedelic properties and then albert looked at
that and morning glory seeds have lsa which is lysergic acid amide and lsd is lysergic acid
diethylamide so there is even though lsd came from ergot was modified so that it doesn't appear in
nature decades later albert was able to figure out that there is something in nature that's quite
similar to lsd it's not the same and lsd i think is more powerful more effective people have had a
tradition of morning glory seeds for getting high in different ways so because i know michael paulin
has done a great job writing about this and i would encourage anyone who's interested in this topic
to sort of go back and read his book how to change your mind where he details the history there is an
important point i want you to bring up because his legacy in many ways provides a little bit of
an undercurrent of the work you've done and that is the work of timothy leery where does leery fit
into this story specifically so leery was an incredible psychologist who had written a book
called the interpersonal diagnosis of personality that was heralded as brilliant it was the most
important psychology book of the year this is like 58 59 he was working for kyzer out in california
as a kyzer psychologist he was very rebellious kind of guy he had been in west point and got
kicked out of west point for i think sharing alcohol and doing different things and he had
actually had a friend who was involved in the cia who was a psychologist did a lot of work on
creativity frank baron and frank baron had had knowledge about the mushrooms and had tried them
and he recommended to timothy leery that he try these mushrooms and then tim had now also then
been offered this appointment at harvard so he got this appointment at harvard before he'd even
done any kind of psychedelics then he does these mushrooms and he thinks that he learned more from
these mushroom experience than in this entire time in school about the mind and so he started trying
to study psychedelics and got interested mostly again in psilocybin and so there was a series of
projects that tim was here at harvard only for three years from 60 to 63 i've done long-term
follow-ups to two of his main studies that he did at harvard one was the good friday experiment
that actually walter panky who was a doctor and a minister did this for phd and tim was his phd
thesis advisor can you explain that experiment to people yeah i'd say the other is the concrete
prison experiment i'll also explain so because of aldis huxley and writing about doors of perception
and writing about the sort of spiritual aspects of mexican and even bill w feeling that lsd had
spiritual capacities so what walter panky wanted to do was originally he was interested in doing
something about the sex lives of radcliffe students which his wife wasn't too happy about
and he met tim and tim suggested that they do something with psychedelics and since walter
panky was both doctor and minister they decided to look scientifically at whether psychedelics
really could produce spiritual mystical experiences whether they were similar identical pseudo whatever
and so the first thing that walter panky did was he spent a year trying to devise a questionnaire
to evaluate what the mystical experience was aldis huxley had talked about the perennial philosophy
that keeps coming up and so what walter did was he looked at wt stace who had done work on the
theory of the philosophy of religion and how you describe mystical experiences there's actually a
scale that stace had made and others and so what walter did is he spent this year developing a
series of questionnaires that were independent of any particular religious symbols or any
particular religious system so even though this was an experiment that took place on good friday
it didn't have any references to jesus this questionnaire and so basically the fundamental
core element of this perennial philosophy of the mystical experience is this sense of unity
and you get this from all different religions about everything's one everything's united
somehow one big system so there's external reality where you can see that nature is all connected or
internal reality sort of everything you know without form is still connected but that sense
that it's all one thing transcendence of time and space deeply felt positive mood a sense of
something sacred or holy a sense that it's ineffable that there's something beyond language about the
experience so walter had developed this questionnaire which is in very minimally
modified way is still used today in all of the psychedelic research to evaluate the mystical
experience so what they decided to do was to take a group of 20 christian divinity students from
andover newton theological seminary and bring them into church on good friday at boston university
and the minister was reverend howard thermon and he was martin luther king's mentor he was an
incredible dynamic black preacher and actually i was able during my follow-up study to obtain
copies from walter panky's widow walter died in 71 in the scoop diving accident but his widow had
the actual copy of the service that they listened to during good friday which is just profoundly
moving and it shows that in 1962 on good friday when they did this experiment that psychedelics
were just beginning to be controversial they really were not and so this was an experiment to see
if these 20 divinity students in church on good friday and this was like a three and a half hour
service three and a four hour service they all got a pill half got placebo half got psilocybin
and they were divided these 20 people into groups of four five groups of four and two experimenters
were assigned to each group of four and the experimenters also took these pills and one of
the experimenter would get the placebo one would get the psilocybin these were people like tim leery
ralph metzner richard alpert who later became ram das houston smith incredible people who were
experts in the philosophy of religion and psychology and they were trying to break down the us them
experimenter subject dichotomies and that's why they had the experimenters also took the pills
and what they then did was after the experiment after the service they had a chapel in the
basement so while the main service was taking place in the upstairs chapel downstairs was the
chapel where the experiment was taking place i've since visited its marsh chapel it's on commonwealth
out for boston university there's a statue out in front of it for martin luther king that actually
talked about my approach towards draft resistance it's like and the quote there is who believes the
law is unjust and breaks it and is willingly suffering the consequences to be an example of
others actually has the highest regard for the law so it's sort of showing the civil disobedience
is people that believe in the law but want to modify it so that's out in front of mars chapel
but then over the doorway to the main chapel before this experiment even took place
is a quote about experimental religion it's just amazingly historically resonant that that place was
sympathetic with this idea of experimental religion but the idea was then that they would go
through this experiment they would then give questionnaires about what their experience was
how they described it and then they would do a six-month follow-up about the long-term effects
as i mentioned walter died in a scuba diving accident in 1971 so i was convinced in the middle
80s when i was wanting to do a thesis at new college i had to do senior thesis i want to do
something with psychedelics but it was at a time when psychedelic research was all blocked
and so i thought wow i could do a follow-up study and ask people what they thought about it it
wouldn't involve drugs so i could get permission to do it so i ended up doing it to this 25 year
follow-up to the good friday experiment what was the finding of the original experiment that nine
out of the 20 people had a mystical experience and eight out of those nine had the psilocybin
so they concluded that under the influence of psilocybin people who were religiously inclined
in a religious setting could have what looked like a mystical experience and so either it was
genuine or it was similar but they concluded that according to this questionnaire that
that psilocybin did indeed have the potential to catalyze mystical experiences and what was the
approximate dose of psilocybin they took it was 30 milligrams so it was a major dose of psilocybin
and the placebo it turned out was niacin to give them a flush without knowing that yeah we'll come
back to this and psychedelic research one of the challenges is the placebos have to give you some
feeling yeah my dissertation at the kennedy school a big part of it was on how to do double blind
studies with psychedelics and the conclusion i came to and we'll get back to the good friday
experiment but the conclusion i came to was that the best way to do a double blind experiment with
psychedelics was to use low doses of the psychedelic versus full doses and that way
everybody has the same demand characteristics they all think they're going to be getting the
test drug they just don't know what dose and all the experimenters know everybody's getting the drug
and i thought that the real challenge was going to be to find the level of the low dose yeah so
that it's below this step it's below the real activation well it has to be high enough so that
you would have enough confusion between the full dose but not so high that you get all the
therapeutic potential so i thought you'd get a little bit of the therapeutic potential but you
didn't want to get too much because the more therapeutic potential you got the more difference
it would be to find differences between the two groups the more difficult it would be
and so in our work with mdma we'd looked at zero milligrams 25 milligrams 30 milligrams 40 milligrams
50 milligrams 75 100 125 and 150 what we discovered was that the low doses did produce
blinding that's what i had anticipated but what i didn't anticipate is that the low doses actually
made people uncomfortable it activated them without reducing the fear and so the therapeutic
effect of just the therapy was compromised and so people who had therapy without any mdma did better
than people that had therapy with low dose mdma and low in that situation was how low 25 to 40 25
30 and 40 milligrams and then the 75 milligrams actually was very therapeutic so when we opened
our meeting with the fda to talk about our phase three designs i started by saying there's a quote
from i thought it was william james but it turned out it was little i think one of the early
presidents of harvard and he said never forget there's always a harvard man on the wrong side
of every issue and so i opened the meeting by saying there's this quote and unfortunately i'm
the wrong side this person that's wrong is me because my dissertation was wrong and there is
no solution to the double blind problem at least for mdma and so the fda accepted that and i said
you could have us use low dose but you're going to make it easier for us to find a difference
between the full dose and the therapy with low dose because it blunts the effect of the therapy
and so the real question is if you can do it without a drug why add a drug if the therapy is
effective why add a drug so i said the best way to do this is therapy with inactive placebo versus
therapy with full dose mdma and fda accepted that and so has ema the european medicines agency but
back to the good friday experiment so what they discovered is that the double blind did not work
nycen did not work as double blind people were initially confused but after a while this nycen
flush wears off and then you've got these other people seeing colors and seeing sparkles and the
candle flames and having all these unusual experiences so everybody was clear by the end
of the experiment who had the nycen who had the psilocybin and at the six-month follow-up they
showed that people had reported long-term positive benefits and so this was considered to be the most
sophisticated experiment in the history of religion looking at the mystical experience
and it demonstrated positive long-term benefits although compromised because of course it
effectively wasn't blinded to the extent that you would say that's compromised yeah yeah what
makes me think that it wasn't so compromised is that i did my long-term follow-up 25 years later
87 86 88 is when i kept so i went to andover newton theological seminary i went to the alumni
office and to the president i said could we send a letter to everybody on your alumni newsletter
asking who was in this experiment oh because you didn't know their names there's no record leery had
no record the records were gone of who the people were andover newton this was at a time of nancy
reagan escalation of the drug war and this was probably the nadir of views towards psychedelics
and society andover newton refused to cooperate with the study they wouldn't put even a notice
in their alumni newsletter or help me in any way find out who the subjects were and so i was super
frustrated and i said while i was there i thought okay i'll just go into their library and see if
they've got thesis and if they've got the commentaries any discussions about this most important study
that was done with their students and so it turned out that they didn't even have walter panky's
thesis in their library it was so controversial actually that after the study was done you had
to get a permission directly from walter in order to look at the thesis in the harvard library they
didn't even put it out there they didn't want any people to know about it so i didn't even
see the thesis i thought this is like massive cultural amnesia and here how embarrassing this
is a school of religion and this is the most important study done and they don't even have
a copy of it they don't even want to talk about it and i just wandered through their library a
little bit and then i saw coincidentally a booklet of all of their alumni and their addresses and
which years they were in the school and this was from like a 1972 book but it had people who were
at school in 62 when the study was done so i ended up writing letters to like 300 people
and i got about three responses back that they were actually in the study and it took me multiple
years but eventually i was able to identify 19 out of the 20 of the people who were in the study
and my parents were sympathetic at this point and so i would fly to wherever they were in the
country and then interview them in person and what i discovered was first off shocking to me so at a
point where every cultural indication would be that these persons should deny the value of the
psychedelic experience massive escalation of the drug war republicans in charge people going to
jail for all this kind of stuff everybody who had the psilocybin experience except for one person
said that they had a mystical experience back then and they still considered it to be a mystical
experience and they had had many non-drug mystical experiences since then as well to compare and
contrast and they said that they preferred the non-drug mystical experiences because they tended
to be more positive more in nature more just coming over them gratuitous grace sometimes they
would call it but the psychedelic mystical experiences were more oscillating between fear
and unit of experiences that they were deeper in some ways but were more difficult to manage but
they validated the importance of the experience and then i felt like i discovered the clue to the
60s by doing these interviews because what they told me is that first off everybody who had the
psilocybin could remember with crystal clarity some moments of their psychedelic experience
something about psychedelics imprint on memory you don't remember everything but some portions
of it are just indelible and they validated that they were genuine but the key to the 60s for me
was that they talked about how that unit of experience motivated them in different ways
to get involved with social justice struggles now of course these were all ministers anyway they
were thinking in that way it's not that everybody who takes this will be motivated in that way but
one of them worked against the mx missile basing others of them participated in the civil rights
movement the women's rights movement the environmental movement they felt that there was
this connection between this spiritual experience they lost a certain fear of death so they were
more willing to take risks in their lives they learned the appreciation of the moment it's not
that they didn't care about death but they death made life more precious they didn't go for this
idea that heaven is later after you die it's like more that they wanted to create it on earth
and so they used that psychedelic experience to be involved in challenging the status quo to try
to make it a more spiritual loving world and i felt that that's where i really learned that
the crackdown against the 60s was not because of psychedelics gone wrong but because of
psychedelics gone right but i also learned something else which is that the placebo people
had a hard time remembering what was going on i mean they knew they were in the experiment but
they didn't have as clear memories about what happened some of them were so upset by what they
saw saw in the others in the others that they were disoriented that one person went up and tried to
be the preacher it scared them and they decided never to do psychedelics others decided that they
were so inspired by what they saw that they wanted to do psychedelics so some of them did
go back and do psychedelics from the placebo group but then what i discovered i started hearing these
stories about how one person who had received the psilocybin had been listening to reverend howard
thurman at one point where he's telling people that you need to tell people there's a man on the
cross this is your obligation this jesus story that you must tell others about it and so this
one person started to realize that he should do that and he thought well i should tell the
president if i'm going to tell anybody i should tell the president and he then said oh you know
the president's in washington and okay i'll tell the president of the university and so he left
the basement chapel he went outside and he was wandering down the road going towards the
president and this very much scared timothy leery and houston smith and they went after him and
they finally got him they protected him he didn't get hit by a car but he didn't want to go back in
and so they ended up giving him a shot of thorazine a tranquilizer which was used at this time and
when people had difficult trips sometimes they would tranquilize them we would not do that today
it's it freezes the struggles in place it's not helpful at all better to just wait it out even
if it's terrible because then at least you don't get the message you can't handle it if you wait
it out at least you survived so it turned out though that this whole administration of thorazine
to this one person was completely missing from any of the reports about the study which i considered
to be another key to the 60s in that leery and the advocates underestimated the risks and over and
exaggerated the benefits so the way this story the good friday experiment was reported in time
magazine and elsewhere was that everybody who got the psilocybin had the mystical experience which
is not the case eventually i did manage to figure out who was the one that was tranquilized and when
i called him he was still a minister he was married he had kids but when i identified myself
as wanting to talk to him about this experiment he was very upset and he said if i ever called
him again he would sue me he didn't want to talk to me at all so i think that this idea that he had
been he was traumatized by that experience he was very traumatized by it and it was embarrassing and
so he didn't want to talk about it but i heard about it from others and was able to figure out
who it was and so i felt that this was the height of scientific irresponsibility and many people who
have been through what you've been through meaning they have watched this journey are not especially
sympathetic to leery in fact many people just single-handedly identify leery's irresponsibility
as the sole reason for the backlash which of course strikes me as hyperbolic and unlikely to
be the case but i've certainly read accounts that you've written that come across as being slightly
more sympathetic to leery yeah i'm much more sympathetic in the sense that it's psychedelics
gone right that really caused the backlash and while he was irresponsible in a lot of different
ways and was delighted to be a rebel and to be against the system and i think this identification
as the counterculture was in itself a self-fulfilling doomed prophecy that you identify yourself as
counterculture you're going to be crushed eventually but i think he saw that the
propaganda for the other side the negative exaggerations of the risks were so strong
that he justified in his own mind that he could exaggerate on the other side and minimize the
risk so i do think he deserves a lot of criticism for what he said but he was very much about
thinking for yourself questioning authority challenging the system all of which we need more
of and what i fault him for the most was misrepresenting science it's okay to be a
cultural advocate but when science is holy in itself holy meaning h-o-l-y meaning that it's
sacred there's something sacred about our quest for knowledge through our bias i mean how we just
discussed the double bind the whole purpose of the double bind is to eliminate or reduce
experiment or bias we see what we want to see so how do we actually see what's really there
and i think that's the beauty the holiness of science and so when tim misrepresented
the scientific findings he had that i thought was a tremendous violation being a cheerleader against
the drug war and for consciousness i think he deserves a lot of credit for that i think where
he's also wrapped up in deserving criticism is that he underestimated the risks and overestimated
the benefits so you take this drug you get enlightened you're smarter than everybody else
and now you're part of this new counterculture and all you have to do is drop the pill
that's wrong people don't always have these good experiences people do get messed up and end up
worse off so so what i discovered during the good friday experiment follow-up was that there had
been this overhyping of the results and also this hiding of a problem and as it turned out
houston smith then validated it that it was true that this had really happened and that somebody
did get thorazine and it was really the case even though that one person wouldn't talk to me but
overall my conclusion was that the experiment was essentially validated that people did have mystical
experiences they had subsequent experiences in their lives that were without drugs mystical
experiences that they then said that made them think that the psilocybin mystical experience was
legitimate it had positive benefits in their lives it had long-term impacts what i find most
interesting having experienced this myself what resonates is this notion that after the fact
years after the fact in the case of your subjects 25 years after the fact with crystal clarity you
could remember something from that experience and i don't think i've ever been under the influence
of psilocybin that i can't look back and recall with just the most vivid detail some aspects of
it positive and negative some incredibly positive deeply emotional moving beyond words and also at
times very in different settings or different times within the same experience incredibly
frightening an incredible feeling of despair but with a degree of vividness that i can't remember
many things so what do you attribute that i don't know i mean i suspect that i don't know enough
about neuroscience i'm probably the wrong person to ask but i suspect that if you look at parts of
the brain the hippocampus where we imprint memory there must be something about these molecules that
enable during periods of the time because that's the thing it's such a non-linear experience it's
sort of isolating that there must be moments in there where there's an overlap and i'm sort of
putting my hands like a you sort of have to get an alignment of a couple of things one the experience
itself is profound enough and two so that's like the seed and then the soil itself at that moment
neurologically is fertile enough to take that seed and that produces this plant which is in the
metaphor is this memory that is never going away and what's also interesting is i can still describe
in some cases the feeling that accompanied that vision or that hallucination and what it connected
me to someone that i cared about or something like that so that to me is a very powerful part of your
follow-up whereas i can completely imagine that if you were getting the placebo i mean i've taken
nyas and i know what it feels like it's miserable actually if you take a high enough dose the flush
is real i mean there's no denying it but if you asked me to recall a nyas and flush i had two years
ago let alone 20 years ago i'd be hard pressed to remember anything about it so the sensory
experience alone is not enough what i really want to get to now is and it will require backing up
slightly from historical context is let's talk about what's happening right now with mdma before
we do that let me just explain briefly about the conquered prison experiment oh yes yes yes that's
right that's right this is the second major experiment yeah so what leery recognized was
that the good friday experiment you're basically relying on people to tell you what happened to
them so that's sort of subjective reports he wanted to try to find an objective way to talk
about the benefits of psychedelics and so what he started thinking about was prisoners at the
conquered prison which is not 20 minutes away from here we're not that far from harvard square we're
doing this four miles from harvard square conquered prison that was nearby and so he thought that
if you could work with prisoners while they're in prison and help them have a pro-social
experience this kind of mystical experience that that might once they were released it might reduce
their recidivism and he thought that that is an objective measure of benefit if we can show that
people don't go back to prison once they've released and that it's somehow correlated with this
mystical experience with psilocybin that that would be a really good way of communicating to
people so from 61 to 63 he started working with ralph metzner who was his phd student as well
and they started doing a project at conquered prison and they ended up getting permission to
do psilocybin inside the prison with prisoners and the same situation is that the experimenters
some of them would take the psilocybin as well and then prisoners were released and how many
prisoners over the period of that time were treated about 36 or so and what was the average
number of treatments per prisoner two and so what what they ended up saying though is that this was
one of the most successful experiments in the history of psychedelics showing benefit was there
a control group that were interacted with but without an agent no the control group was they
did a base rate study of everybody that had been released from prison in the year before they did
this and then they tracked them and so they had this base rate study and then they compared
against the base rate so one obvious flaw in this is that the people who are motivated to volunteer
for this experiment might be more likely to want to stay out of prison maybe they're more motivated
to get better so that would be huge and then the other one of course being this this performance
bias which is just the fact that they're getting some positive attention while they're there it's
funny if you were to redo that experiment you would randomize people you take everybody you
randomize them you're either randomized to the intervention with the psilocybin or the best
example you can come up with of an intervention that is without psilocybin counseling positive
therapy etc etc where you so you're not trying to be blinded to your point you're not going to be
able to blind people but at least you can try to identify that if there is a benefit in the
psilocybin group it's much more likely to be from the psilocybin than it is from selection
bias or performance bias exactly and so from the fda's point of view once we discussed how
there is no solution to the double blind problem for mdm a they said that there are two other main
ways that we had to incorporate into our protocol design to reduce experimenter bias and one was
random assignment that everybody similarly motivated and then they just happen to get
either your control group or your test group the other is the independent raters and how you
evaluate the outcomes so it can't be done by the experimenters you have to have a whole different
pool of raters and then how they are structured so that they don't track the people through the
study they don't know if it's the beginning measurement the baseline or the follow-up and
so what was the difference in recidivism between those two groups well it was substantial and so
it was terrific positive experiment so after i had done the or so it seemed so after i had done the
good friday experiment follow-up and published it in 91 in the journal of transpersonal psychology
then there was an op-ed about my study in the boston globe and i got a call shortly after that
from fellow michael forca who worked for the department of corrections and he said do you
want to do a follow-up to the conquered prison experiment i said i have been interested but
there's no record of who the people were in that study either and he said that they actually had
those records that the department of corrections had a storehouse of information about all their
interesting prisoners malcolm x had been a prisoner they had all these stuff and he said that they had
a record of who these prisoners were and that i could work with him if we wanted to do a follow-up
to the conquered prison experiment and i thought god this is fantastic now i can help call attention
to one of the most important and successful experiments in the history of psychedelic research
and so it took us a whole year to get permission to do this we had to go all the way up to the
governor's office it was william weald at the time who's now going to be running for president
trying to knock off trump in the primaries which won't work but it'll be good so william weald so
we got this piece of paper finally saying that we could go into the criminal justice system records
and track people's criminal records after they had been released from conquered but somebody had
written on it no psilocybin so we weren't asking for permission to give psilocybin but they just
wanted to underscore that we could not give psilocybin so i ended up going into the criminal
justice system records it took quite a while to do this and the more that i looked into it one by one
and tracked people the more i started realizing that there had been something amiss that it didn't
look like it was really working the data that i was getting about their arrests were that they
were arrested it didn't seem like there was this benefit that had been reported meaning during the
period when they were initially reported to have had a benefit you felt that those data were
incorrect or over a longer follow-up period of time both groups converged it was more that there
was some tricks in the way that leery and ralph metzner reported the data and it was also the case
ralph metzner once i published my findings basically it was scientific fraud not by ralph
but more by tim who was still alive at the time wasn't he was and i eventually visited him shortly
before he died i mean i got to know him in a bunch of different ways but i also visited him with two
other prisoners and one who had never gone back to prison and one who had gone back to prison and
we had kind of a reunion that was really nice but i didn't have the courage i guess to ask why he
fudged the data so what it turned out to be is that the longer time had elapsed from when the
experiment took place the more that tim would tell the story of how more successful it was so the
results kept getting presented in better and better ways the longer it was from the study
but even at the early stage what they had claimed was that their very initial thing was that while
some people did go back to prison from the psilocybin group that they were monitored more
carefully than others the normal prisoners and they went there for parole violations
minor things not new crimes but then over time the results just kept being presented better and
better and better and so i had not actually looked at the very early things but i'd looked at all
their other reports so once i started doing the follow-up i looked at everything and i could track
it and i got back to the base rate study which i'd never looked at and what was surprising to me is
here i am an advocate for psychedelics and this is one of the premier studies in psychedelics
showing benefits but none of the critics had ever actually gone back to the very original documents
the base rate study was published in a journal of criminology an obscure british journal of
criminology which i managed to find and so what it turned out first off is that the base rate
study was done an average of people out for two years the actual research with the prisoners was
done when people were out an average of 10 months and so what had happened was that obviously the
longer you're out of prison the more likely you are to go back to prison right it's an apples
oranges comparison yeah and so it turned out that the original study actually tracked people over
time so there was the data for 10 months in the control group the base rate when they were out 10
months their results were the same as what was reported in the psilocybin group so there was no
difference whatsoever but what i also discovered is that the way in which tim was saying about how
oh yeah people did go back to prison but for parole violations that they were actually
parole violations because they had committed new crimes for which they were later convicted
so i figured out how his counting rules permitted him to say things that weren't true
but that might look on the surface to be true and i found the original base rate study so what i
concluded and what actually happened was that leery got kicked out of harvard in 63 he thought of it
as the scientific prison and they had started to recognize that just having a spiritual experience
which many of these people did have in prison is not enough that you need support afterwards you
need to integrate the experience and have support yeah and the same with treatment for addiction
that you need support groups afterwards and so they had actually created this support group for
the prisoners but then when they got kicked out of harvard that fell apart so my conclusion was
that this experiment scientific fraud it didn't work but that some of the people who did have
the psilocybin who i was able to contact that was delicate because you're contacting former prisoners
so i had to make sure that i only spoke to them i didn't speak to their family members so they
might not have spoken about their experiment but but some of them said that the psilocybin was
really helpful so what i concluded is that this was an experiment that should be repeated with
the combination of the experience and the support afterwards and that that it showed promise but what
i really felt also was that this was leery violating something that was sacred which was
the scientific data and presenting it in a wrong way and so i think in some ways people appreciated
the fact that even though i was an advocate for psychedelics i was willing to report the data
as i found it rather than as i wanted it to be so i think it was good for personally for my
credibility but it was me ending up delegitimizing this crucial experiment that everybody had thought
was really successful that was my problem so those are the things that i fought leery for and i also
do fault him for just encouraging people to take psychedelics without sufficient cautions about the
need for people who are not tripping to watch over you about the need to integrate it about how it's
not automatically you learn something new it can be very frightening or terrifying but overall i do
think that leery was a positive and i think that i might not have ever taken lsd if it weren't for
him and this idea that he was trying to democratize the mystical experience and and i also think i'll
just say that i had a ketamine experience where i was transported above and behind hitler as he was
giving a one of those rallies this is one of the more profound psychedelic experiences of my life
and i was i think primarily traumatized by the holocaust i've had dreams of holocaust survivors
telling me that i needed to be a psychedelic therapist and that that was they'd survived the
holocaust miraculously and that that was their mission and they didn't know what it was and it
was to tell me to be psychedelic therapist so i think fundamentally what i've been motivated by
is how do we help people feel the connection so they don't dehumanize and murder others but
there was this way in which that i felt that the problem of leery trying to exaggerate the benefits
left people unprepared but that the effort to have people to think for themselves and to
question authority was inherently a good thing but that the justification that he gave himself
for twisting the science because others were twisting it in the negative way was ultimately
very harmful rick on behalf of many people who are never going to necessarily know your name
even after you're long gone from this planet people who have already benefited from your
work i want to thank you in the most sincere way that i can what you've done is beautiful
thank you peter yeah i think the ultimate success is being taken for granted
it is
you can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast there
you'll find the show notes readings and links related to this episode you can also find my blog
at peteratiamd.com maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame
once a week email where i'll update you on what i've been up to the most interesting papers i've
read and all things related to longevity science performance sleep etc on social you can find me
on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id peteratia md but usually twitter is the best way
to reach me to share your questions and comments now for the obligatory disclaimer this podcast is
for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine
nursing or other professional health care services including the givings of medical advice
and note no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the materials
linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk the content of this podcast is not intended to be
a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should not disregard
or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the
assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions lastly and perhaps most
importantly i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures the companies
i invest in and or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about