Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Dr. Vamsee Mutta. Vamsee is
a professor of systems biology at the Harvard Medical School. He has an appointment at the
Broad Institute, which is actually where we met to conduct this interview. And we talk a little bit
about what makes the Broad so special. He specializes in rare mitochondrial diseases,
as opposed to longevity per se, something that I love to talk about. But I think you'll see in the
interview why it's so interesting to talk to someone who specializes in rare orphan mitochondrial
diseases about longevity. His laboratory uses a blend of genomics, computational biology,
biochemical physiology, and systems biology to study mitochondrial function and dysfunction.
He received his bachelor's in mathematics and computer science at Stanford before going on
to Harvard as part of the joint MIT Harvard program in medical school. He stayed in Boston to
do his training in internal medicine, though as we discuss, he now focuses exclusively on research.
He's received more honors and awards than I could name here, but it's always worth mentioning it
when someone is a genius award recipient. So he won the MacArthur Foundation Award in 2004,
which obviously puts him in pretty rarefied earth. In this episode, we talk about a lot of things. We
start with, at least for me, one of the best discussions I've ever had on the mitochondria.
And you might think at first that some of this recapitulates things that were discussed on
previous podcasts. You may recall we had a great discussion on the mitochondria with
Navdeep Chandel, but we go a little bit deeper and we talk more about some of the evolutionary
pressure around the mitochondria. And even though at first you might think, well, gosh, this seems
awfully scientific. Where is the application? If you stick with it, you're going to see where it
comes and how understanding these rare orphan diseases that most of us have never heard of
can give us an insight into aging. We do eventually start to talk about metformin,
which I know many people ask about. And he provides a great insight into, or several great insights
into what metformin may or may not be doing. And again, for at least for me, this was like just
the master's class in mitochondrial biogenesis, electron transport chain, et cetera. Talk about
ways that we can target mitochondrial proteins and complexes to treat disease. But perhaps the single
most insightful and interesting thing that we talked about that completely blew my mind
was the role of hypoxia as a treatment. I want to repeat that again. The role of hypoxia,
oxygen deprivation as treatment. Now we're going to cover this in a way that I think is very
interesting. So I don't want to say any more about it, but I do want to add a disclaimer to this that
Vemsey and I spoke about after the podcast and I want to make sure it's here. So Vemsey emphasizes
that their published research to date on the beneficial effects of hypoxia in animal models
of mitochondrial disease is still in its early stages and it's restricted to animal studies.
It is not yet ready to be applied to humans. To extend these ideas to humans would be premature
and irresponsible since hypoxia can have life threatening implications. If and when the concept
is extended into humans, it will need to be done so in a clinical trial setting with the appropriate
ethical, regulatory and safety measures in place. So with that caveat and without further delay,
please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Vemsey Mukher.
Vemsey, thank you so much for making time today.
You're absolutely welcome.
Yeah, yeah. Sight unseen too. I'm always impressed when people I don't know in advance agree to sit
down with me. I'm kind of honored humbled. So thank you very much.
Thank you for coming and meeting.
Yeah, the Broad is quite an impressive place. Tell folks a little bit about where we are right now
and what makes this unique even within the hallowed halls of Boston Biomedical Research Institutes.
No, I think it's a really exciting place and I've had the pleasure of actually watching it
blossom from nothing. It's really the brainchild of somebody named Eric Lander who was one of the
leaders of the Human Genome Sequencing Project. And as that was being completed in draft form in
2001 and then in quote finished form in 2003, he saw the need to create some sort of an entity
that would take advantage of the power of genomics for improving biomedicine. So he created this
institute and it's unprecedented in a lot of ways. It's joint between Harvard and MIT. It involves
all of the hospitals here in Boston. And it's basically a incredible forum where people can
get together and basically pursue projects that they can't pursue on their own in their own
individual laboratories. There's a big computational theme here. There's a big theme on being systematic
in one's approach, not focused narrowly on the protein that they've studied in the past,
but being systematic and seeing where the data takes you. And there's a very pervasive theme
of collaboration as well. So Eric has always said that the Broad Institute is a bit of an experiment,
but now it's been about 15, 16 years. And I think without a doubt, it's been a wildly successful
experiment. Do most of you here at the Broad have an appointment elsewhere? Like I know you spend
much of your time at Mass General. Lots of people here spend, you know, they have an appointment at
MIT. Does everybody have another appointment outside of the Broad? Almost. So there's almost
two types of people that work at the Broad. There's some people that are actually formally employed by
the Broad Institute and there's others like myself that are employed elsewhere. In my case,
I work at Mass General Hospital and Howard Hughes Medical Institute. That's my primary
appointment. My paycheck comes from there. But then I spend a day a week over here working on
collaborative types of projects that I can't pursue easily in my own lab. So there's almost two types
of folks over here. I think one of the neat things about the Broad Institute is, you know, traditionally
there's this grad student postdoc assistant professor academic track, but how about for all
the other people that want to do research in a nonprofit academic setting but aren't interested
in applying for R01 grants or teaching? The Broad actually has an entire research scientist track as
well. And so you can be employed here as a research scientist doing science. And funded here. And funded
here. And I think that's a very, very different organizational model compared to any other academic
organization. Let's back up for a moment. You studied at Stanford where you did, were you a computer
science major? What was your major in undergrad? I was math and computer science. Okay, got it. Did you
know you wanted to get into biology and medicine? You know, when I was a kid, I'm an Indian American.
My father is a retired surgeon. As it turns out, my three older siblings would end up becoming
doctors also. So I like to joke that we had the medicine gene in our family. So growing up, I was
convinced I wanted to be a doctor of some sort. But then in high school, I fell in love with math.
I did the high school math competitions. I was pretty good at those. Did the high school
science fair competitions in math. Did well with those. And so I ended up going to Stanford with
the goal of being a math and computer science major. And that's what I was squarely focused on.
And then towards the end of college, when I was looking for a research project, my advisor told me
about the work of Sam Carlin. He's a statistician that was developing some of the underlying
methods for bimolecular sequence analysis. He's a fundamental
mathematician. And this is like early 90s. Early 90s. That's right. That's right. So I ended up
working on DNA sequence analysis as a college student writing code to try to analyze DNA and
protein sequences. And I fell in love with that. And then my advisor said, why don't you contemplate
a future career in medicine if for no other reason. Gung-de Medical School is a great way
of learning physiology. You know, I thought about it from a practical perspective. I applied
simultaneously to PhD programs in mathematical biology and also applied to MD-PhD programs.
And then I applied to this program joint between Harvard and MIT. I actually thought that it was
an MD-PhD program. This is all pre-internet. So I thought it was an MD-PhD program, but it wasn't.
It was a straight MD program, but it's a joint program between the two institutions.
Yeah. They would set aside like a, I remember like 20 students for this. What was it called?
The H-HST. HST program. That's exactly right. That's right. So it's a part
of the HST program and it was kind of catered to students that had slightly quantitative
backgrounds, math, computer science types of backgrounds. It provided a bit of a more gentle
introduction to medical school. I could have used that program. My first year of medical school was
just unbearable. I mean, it was such a culture shock of that. I don't know if I told the story
on the podcast before. The worst exam I've ever done in my life from the point when I decided
to care about school was the first semester histology exam in medical school because I very
arrogantly and naively assumed that if I understood the concepts of histology, I didn't need to
memorize anything. So I took this very pure math approach, which was I could just derive everything
in my mind if I understood the fundamentals. And that got me a 53% on a final exam in histology.
Like I just sat there looking at this number thinking, how is this possible? Am I the stupidest
human being that has ever walked the face of it? It was really a wake up call that said, you know,
you're going to actually just have to start memorizing things around here.
It's a big culture shock. I think when I know you have a background in engineering and applied math,
so very similar to my background. And it made for a lot of unhappiness for me also that first semester
of medical school, at least you were in California. I was facing the Boston winter at the same time I
was facing histology. That's a good point. I did have that going for me. So when you finished med
school, you did a residency in internal medicine. You stayed in Boston, correct? That's right. That's
right. That's right. I've been here now for, it's hard to believe, but about 25 years during
residency, the Brigham is obviously certainly among the top three most academic medicine programs in
the country. I was talking to one of your colleagues yesterday and he made the point that
when he looked at sort of his class or the cohort of people that entered medicine at the Brigham,
you just fast forward 20 years and they're basically the leaders within each of the different
scientific fields. So I assume that was a pretty deliberate decision on your part to
really preserve sort of academic optionality. You know what? I think at almost every single one of
these junctures, exactly from college to medical school, medical school to residency, I think maybe
I'm just inherently a bit of an indecisive person, but I was unsure as to whether or not I wanted to
do a residency. By then I'd fallen in love with basic research. And the question was, was I going
to do a basic science postdoc or was I going to do a residency? And so just as I did at the previous
node, I decided to just apply for both. So I simultaneously applied for postdoc positions
and for residency programs. That was the era when you would fill out your residency match
list with the number two pencil. So I'd fill it out every day. A decent type on a Rogan number two
pencil. I love those things. So I'd fill it out and then I'd rip it up the next day. I'd fill it
out and rip it up the next day. And I joke that the only reason I did a residency is because the
due date was an even number. So that said, I want to put you on the spot and ask you a question that
I get asked all the time. And frankly, I don't know the answer to it. And I feel bad that I always
provide sort of nebulous answers, but I do get asked a lot by either college students who are
contemplating medicine or not, or medical students who are interested in research. And the question
is a variant of one, if you're at the college node, but you're very interested in medical research,
is there benefit to doing an MD? And then the second order question is, if you're in medical
school and you're going to finish and you know you want to do research, is there a benefit to
doing a residency? Now, I generally tell people, and if you disagree with me, I hope you say so
very loudly. I generally say if you're in college, but undecided about medical school or not,
I would say don't do it. Pursue the PhD. If you are in medical school and presumably at least
somewhat interested in medicine still, do an internal medicine residency because there is
no substitute for doing that type of research and at least having the ability to understand
clinically why you're doing it. So again, do you disagree with that? And if so, how would you,
or how would you modify that? I also get asked this question quite a bit because I think there's
a group of people out there that love science are probably good at clinical medicine if they do it,
but they're also good at research if they do it. And maybe they're inherently a little bit
risk averse as well. So they're always trying to figure out what's the best path for me.
The advice that I had gotten when I was in college was that the reason to go to medical school,
if you're interested in research, is that it's one of the best curricula for understanding
physiology. How do all of the parts come together and operate? And trying to understand how an
entire living system operates, if you don't go through all of medical school, if you don't
learn anatomy, if you don't learn histology, if you don't learn cardiovascular physiology,
it's a bit tough. It's a good point you make, right? Which is in somewhere between 16 and 24
months, which is the preclinical part of medical school, it's almost impossible to get a more well
curated view of the human body because it's been optimized for that over 100 years.
That's exactly right.
More.
And it's a living system, right? I mean, you could study yeast, you could study Drosophila,
but the human is extraordinarily well investigated. And you're right, in about two years or so,
you have a very intense curriculum studying one living system, different aspects of it.
So from that perspective, I think it's a great education. It's a broad education
for biomedical research. At the other node, again, I spent a lot of time thinking about this. And
one of my advisors actually said, at least do an internship because then you'll be licensed. You
can prescribe medicines at that point. And there is something special about caring for patients.
There's something very special about going through the process of residency with your colleagues.
And again, you really get to see the human living system at some of its extremes. So I think it's a
great way of continuing to learn physiology and pharmacology as well. So I'm super grateful for
the path, of course, and of one experiment, but I'm really happy that I did medical school and
I'm also super happy I did the clinical training as well because it completely shaped my research
focus as well.
Okay. No, that makes sense. I generally say the same thing, which is, I don't regret the path I
took, though I'm glad I didn't know in advance what it was going to look like because it would
have seemed too indirect, but nevertheless. So right now you spend virtually all of your time
doing research. Is that correct?
That's right.
When did you stop seeing patients?
It's been about five to six years or so.
Was that a tough decision?
It was tough because we went through this entire medical school and residency process with the
goal of actually seeing patients and caring for them. The truth is the number of patients I was
seeing was asymptoting as a function of time. Emotionally, it was very, very difficult to go to
zero. So even though I was seeing probably one patient a month or so, five years ago or so,
going to zero was actually the harder part. But at some point I had to just do the math and say
there's only a certain number of hours per day. I'm running a pretty big research group that's
focused on mitochondria and mitochondrial disorders. And the long-term goal is to impact
these patients. And so I'm going to let other people be the ones that care for these patients
at the front line. And I'm going to try to develop new diagnostics and drugs for these patients.
So let's start talking about the mitochondria. When did you come to the realization that that
was the area you wanted to focus on? And what is it about the mitochondria that especially drew you
in?
So as a first year medical student, I was a little bit unhappy here in Boston. It was cold.
There's a lot of memorization that first year, that first semester in particular. I wasn't sure
if I'd actually made the right decision in coming to medical school from a math background. And then
right in the middle of that first semester when we were taking our histology and pathology class,
we had a very, very brief lecture on myopathies, muscle diseases. And there's one slide that
basically indicated that there's a rare form of myopathies that are due to mutations in the
mitochondrial DNA. Now, truth be told, I don't think I'd appreciate it at that time that we had
our own mitochondria with their own genomes. And so that immediately fascinated me. You dig a little
bit deeper, you learn that these were once bacteria, they're kind of swimming around in our cell. So
that's kind of cool. You see an image of mitochondria in the muscle. It's just beautiful. And there's
just something that really captivated me. And I kind of got hooked on that organelle that first
semester of medical school. And I've told this story to other people, Peter, but what happened
was a few weeks later, my dad's cousin, who is at that time, a postdoctoral fellow in the Harvard
Research, one of the research hospitals, she heard that I was unhappy. So she invited me over to her
house in Somerville for a Friday night dinner. So it started to snow. I took the red line all the way
to Somerville. It was a 20 minute walk to her house. By the time I had gotten in, my shoes were
soaked. I was freezing. She immediately looked at me and said, Oh my God, you look terrible. And so
she took my coat off. She tried to dry me up and she started cooking dinner. And then her boyfriend
appeared like an hour later. And now it's about eight o'clock or nine o'clock or so we had dinner
together. And then we found out that the tea had been shut down. And so not only was I an unhappy
first year medical student, but now I'm spending Friday night with my dad's cousin and her
boyfriend in Somerville. And so they create a makeshift bed for me in their living room. I'm
spending the night there at this point. And I look at the bookshelf and there's a textbook of
mitochondrial biology on the bookshelf. So just a few weeks earlier, I had this initial encounter
with the organelle. I saw this book, so I just took it off the shelf and I just started reading it.
I read about 100 pages that first night. I borrowed it and then I basically devoured that book over
the course of the next few weeks. And I just fell in love with the organelle at that point and
thought to myself that this is what I want to work on for the rest of my career.
That's an amazing story. And I think for people listening, they shouldn't be concerned that they
haven't had that eureka moment. I mean, I've heard a lot of amazing scientists talk about their
passion and not all of them, in fact, most of them don't have such a laser moment like that. Now,
of course, the stories of people that have those moments are even more vivid in my mind of that,
oh my God, I can't think of anything but this. So let's talk a little bit about the mitochondria.
You've already alluded to some of the really interesting features about it. So let's start
with the, well, gosh, which one's the most interesting? Let's just start with the lineage,
right? So how did these bacteria find their way into these eukaryotic cells?
Yeah, this is, I think, one of the most fascinating aspects of the organelle. So this is a process
known as endosympiosis. So the current theory is that there is an organism probably resembling
a modern day gram-negative rod, something like a rickettsial species that merges.
Folks might not even know what that means. So gram-negative is just a staining that allows us
to identify a type of bacteria. So you've got this bacteria that is shaped like a rod, literally.
And how does it get its energy prior to this encounter? The thinking is that it had a full
electron transport chain and was probably capable of doing aerobic metabolism using things like
oxygen as a terminal electron acceptor. And one of the theories proposes that that had
an electron transport chain that's not that different than modern-day mitochondria.
The hypothesis is that that somehow merged with something resembling modern-day archaea.
So there's three main domains of life. You have archaea, you have bacteria, and then you have
eukaryotes. And eukaryotes have nuclei. So the hypothesis is that there's an archaeal species,
there's a bacterial species, they form a union of some sort. And this is what gave rise to modern-day
eukaryotic cells maybe about one and a half billion years ago.
That's kind of remarkable. And is the idea, I mean, what kind of evolutionary pressure must have been
placed to create an entirely new species? It's also binary. It seems somewhat binary to me,
is it? In other words, when you look at the difference between, I don't know, say a chimpanzee
and an ape or an ape and a human, you can see lots of continuous evolution, you know, Neanderthal,
et cetera, et cetera. What you're describing sounds much more switched on, switched off. Is that the
case? Or were there lots of iterations that we can't even appreciate today in between the union
and the current paradigm? As far as we know, endosymbiosis of the mitochondrion only took place
once. Wow. So there are lots of eukaryotes, almost, not all, but almost all eukaryotes
have a mitochondrion. And if you look at the DNA of those mitochondria that still have a genome,
the phylogenetic analysis tells us that this was a monophyletic event. This took place only once.
Now that's not true for something like the chloroplast. That also arose through serial
endosymbiosis. And that likely took place at least two independent times in evolution. But for the
mitochondrion, it probably only took place once as far as we know. And the chloroplast, of course,
is to a plant effectively what the mitochondria is to an animal like us. That's exactly right.
So how many genes do we think that that gram-negative rod had?
Great question. Probably about a thousand to two thousand. And at the time, the species that it
merged with would have had how many for the best of our guessing? Probably also a few thousand.
So you had two things that had comparable numbers of genes merge, and yet today you or I would have
30,000, 20,000 genes inside the nucleus. And we'd have, is it 13 genes inside our mitochondria? 13
preserved genes. So in other words, to a first order approximation, the mitochondria lost all
of its genes. But a deeper dig says actually it somehow hung on to 13. Why do you think that was?
This is what we call reductive evolution. Modern day mitochondria actually represent a mosaic.
So you need about a thousand proteins total to make our mitochondria. And so some of those
are attributable to the original bacterial ancestor, and others are brand new innovations
that even that original bacteria did not have. But on the reductive side, approximately a thousand
genes from that original bacteria have either been lost altogether or have been transferred to the
nuclear genome so that that genome today is tiny. It's only about 16,000 bases, and it encodes 13
proteins. But that's only if you're looking at animals. There's a lot of different eukaryotes,
so there's a lot of mitochondrial diversity. So you and I still retain 13 proteins that are encoded
by our mitochondrial genomes. But if you look at malaria, it's also eukaryote. It has a
mitochondrion, but its genome only encodes three proteins today. So that's additional reductive
evolution. What about things like flies, yeast, are they also variable? Flies are also animals,
and so most animals you would put them in the category. Yeah, that's right. So they would have
about 13, sometimes 14 proteins. But if you look at something like Giardia, which causes a terrible
diarrheal illness, beaver fever, that's a eukaryote. It's actually lost its mitochondrial DNA
altogether. I know we talked about 13 proteins. Is it one-to-one mapping, or are there genes that
are non-coding? Right, so the mitochondria genome encodes two riposomal RNAs, 22 tRNAs, and then 13
proteins. So obviously to have 13, we pretty much have a good sense of what the function of each of
these are. How many diseases that afflict humans result from genetic disorders there? Inherited
mutations that produce dysfunctional proteins. Right, there's about 250 different syndromes of
the mtDNA of the mitochondrial DNA. And by syndrome, I mean there's a particular mutation that's
associated with a particular clinical phenotype. But that's only if we're talking about the
mitochondrial disorders of the mtDNA. That's right. Is that a higher or lower frequency on a
probability basis, given the number of base pairs? Because you said something like only, what, 16,000
base pairs? It's relatively tiny. We have genes in our nuclear genome that are 10 times that size.
So from a probability basis that you could have 250 mutations in that 16,000 base pair
that would each lead to these distinct mitochondrial diseases. Is that more or
less robust from a DNA perspective than our nuclear DNA? I don't think we have a good
answer to that question. There's a little bit of an ascertainment bias in clinical medicine.
So when I was going through residency, probably when you're also going through your clinical
training, the answer to almost every single question about mitochondrial disease was maternal
inheritance. And that's because the nuclear genome was sequenced in draft format in 2001,
but the mitochondrial DNA was sequenced in 1981. So that was almost exactly 20 years earlier. And
it's small. And so as soon as you saw patients that had a particular clinical phenotype that
could be a mitochondrial disease, it was easy to sequence the mitochondrial DNA. So beginning in
1988, when two papers were published reporting the first mutations in the mitochondrial DNA,
it's been relatively straightforward to sequence it and associate mutations of mtDNA with the
disease phenotype. And this is why now there's about 250 of these mtDNA mutation clinical
phenotype mappings. The nuclear genome has been a little bit slower to follow since 2001. In
beginning even a little bit before the completion of the genome sequence, we've now as a community
been able to identify about 300 different genes in the nuclear genome that underlie mitochondrial
disorders. And of course, that's 300 different genes, but then there's different
allelic variants as well. So I think it's going to be a little while before we can
answer your question in a satisfactory way, but it's a really provocative question.
And one more number to sort of extract from that is, do we have a sense of how many genes in the
nuclear genome are required for mitochondrial function? So in other words, what's the denominator
nuclear wise?
That's actually one of the areas that we focused on heavily in our laboratory.
So beginning soon after the sequencing of the human genome, we knew that the human genome
encodes about 22,000 proteins. It's an important question is, which of those find their way to the
mitochondria? It's going to be more than 13. These are elaborate organelles. So we used a lot of
methods in the early 2000s, things like proteomics, GFP tagging, microscopy, computation. And we're
able to identify about 1100 proteins that are made by the nuclear genome that find their way into
the mitochondria. So those 1100 proteins have to work with those 13 proteins in space and time
to do all the amazing things that the organelle does.
How do they communicate? Do we know how expression of MTDNA is coordinated with nuclear DNA?
It's a really, really interesting question. So some of the mechanisms are known,
but a lot of mechanisms are not yet known. So when you exercise, for example,
if you're deconditioned, and if you do a combination of aerobic training and strength
training, you can actually increase the number of mitochondria. And there's an entire transcriptional
program that will turn on all those nuclear genes. But that same program will also turn on
the replication factors that will go into the organelle and cause the mitochondrial DNA to
replicate as well. So it's a really smart transcriptional program that says in response
to exercise, make more of the nuclear encoded components and make more of the mitochondrial
DNA and make more of the mitochondrial DNA and go to proteins.
So that increases mitochondrial density in a given cell. So you have a myocyte muscle cell.
Do we know what the actual signals are? They basically instruct the cell to make more DNA.
So what is the input from the exercise? You mentioned two types of exercise,
strength training and aerobic activity. Those have very different physiologic properties.
So what is it that at the physiologic level is leading to this nuclear level?
One of the important signals is something called AMP kinase, the change in the ATP to ADP ratio.
That's known to be one of the activators of this particular transcriptional program
that induces mitochondrial biogenesis.
So this would be a decrease in AMP activity?
An increase in AMP kinase.
An increase, okay.
So that is basically sensing something like the ATP to ADP ratio.
Ratio is going down, yeah.
So when we exercise, the ATP levels are usually pretty nicely defended.
But then what's happening is there's another reaction that's taking two ADP molecules,
making an ATP-liberating AMP, while ATP levels are defended, some of these ratios change,
and that can be sensed.
And that's one of the inputs into this program that says, let's make more mitochondria.
Now we'll come back to this far down the line, but just because you mentioned it,
one of the effects of a drug called metformin that everybody loves to ask about is it activates AMPK.
Does that imply that metformin administration by itself alters mitochondrial density?
So I think when we talk about exercise, I think AMP activation is generally regarded
as one of the important signals for mitochondrial biogenesis, but I don't think it is sufficient.
It's not sufficient. It's necessary though, potentially.
I think it is, but I would need to review some of the older literature to really confirm that.
So what do you think some of the other signals are?
I think some of the other signals are things like calcium, and clearly there's other signals.
There's a couple of disease states as well, where we see a massive proliferation of mitochondria.
They're not functioning properly, but there's a massive proliferation of malfunctioning
mitochondria. So we're trying to work at some of those signals as well.
So as of right now, it's a bit of an open question as to exactly how the number of
mitochondria is sensed and regulated, but we know some of the inputs.
Right. We know crudely what the inputs are, right? Exercise, as you mentioned,
what are some of the other things that even hormonally, for example, did nutrients play a role?
One of the studies that I was a part of about 10 to 15 years ago or so,
show that even things like androgens and testosterone can actually influence the
amount of mitochondria. Disuse is a great way of rapidly eliminating mitochondria.
And then in terms of nutrients, NED is an important signal as well. This transcriptional
regulator that I'm talking about, it's called PGC1 alpha, and upstream of it is something called
CERT1, which of course utilizes NED as a cofactor. So there's a couple of these inputs.
I'm having lunch with David Sinclair later today, so we'll be talking plenty about this.
Absolutely. Absolutely. So I think a couple of these
signals are beginning to emerge. We're not at that stage right now where in a pill we can put
seven of these things, give it to a patient, and boom, we can replace exercise. We're not there yet,
but it'd be remarkable if we understood the process well enough so that we could one day.
Yeah, there's been lots of claims of exercise in a pill. I remember the New York Times wrote about
something called iris, and God, they wrote about it in 2011, 2012, and then I saw it again recently.
It's funny, of course, you see these stories which you realize they're being written about in such a
crude way that you can infer nothing. So you go back and look at the paper and you realize
it's kind of a ridiculous claim at this point. What is the turnover of mitochondria in a cell?
So if you have, let's put some scale to things for folks. So I'm going to take, I'm going to biopsy one
cell from your quadricep, one muscle cell. How many mitochondria approximately would be in it,
assuming you're a relatively well-conditioned individual?
Talking about the number of mitochondria is a little bit ambiguous because they're not
quantal units. Mitochondria will constantly undergo fusion and fission. So at any given
state, you can have a different, quote, number of mitochondria. The mitochondrial DNA is a
quantal unit. So you can ask how many mitochondrial genomes are there per nuclear genome in a cell
type. Okay. So a fibroblast will have a few hundred, maybe a thousand copies of the mitochondrial
genome for each of its nuclear genome. That's right. But there's a lot of variation. The
highest would be what, like a cardiac myocyte or something or a neuron? The unfertilized egg.
Wow. It has half a million copies of mitochondrial DNA. See, I wouldn't have guessed that. I don't
know why. I could have come up with 10 guesses and that would not have been one of them.
It's remarkable. And dad's sperm probably has a few hundred at best.
And I would have guessed the sperm needed more because it's doing the motion, right? It has to
fight to get to the egg. Part of the reason is that the egg is so big relative to the size of
the sperm. So that's to a first order approximation, the explanatory variable. But the unfertilized egg
is sort of the Olympic gold champion when it comes to MTD molecules. It's the Michael Phelps of MTD.
That's right. And then red blood cells, of course, have no mitochondrial DNA.
Then what's the turnover look like, right? So if you have a cardiac myocyte
that presumably lasts for a long time, you're in an individual, like these cells are not turning
over quickly. Are they turning over new mitochondria constantly? How often is that mitochondrial DNA
churning over? I guess what I'm trying to get at is what's like the half-life of these sort of
non-discrete mitochondria. I think in most non-dividing tissues, the half-life is on the order
of a few days. Wow. So we are cranking out mitochondria. That's right. That's right.
There's differences between dividing cells versus non-dividing cells. When you have a dividing cell,
obviously, as a function of the eukaryotic cell cycle, you need to double the number of mitochondria.
And then you partition that into two. Then you double partition. So dividing cells have very
different mitochondrial turnover dynamics than non-dividing tissues like muscular neurons.
There's like a hundred other questions I want to ask, but I also don't want to get us back to the
beginning so that we can set the framework to ask some of these other questions. So you alluded to
something, right, which was, I believe, something that at least for me until very recently,
I didn't think was challenged or questioned, which was the origin of said mitochondria being maternal.
So presumably in the early 80s when we first, we, like I had anything to do with it,
when people far smarter than me sequenced mitochondrial DNA, given how few the number
of genes were, it was not difficult to realize, hey, this all seems to come from the maternal
side, not the paternal side. And as recently as several years ago, that was considered almost
an axiom. All the DNA in your mitochondria comes from your mother, not your father.
Has that been called into question lately? Have there been exceptions to that?
I think the textbook teaching is that the mitochondrial DNA is transmitted exclusively
maternally. And the reason for that is related to...
This comes back to the egg, I'm sure, right?
It gets back to the sexual dimorphism. The egg is huge. It has half a million copies of MTDNA.
That sperm is tiny. It only has a few hundred copies of MTDNA. So by sheer dilution,
it's very difficult for dad's MTDNA to get transmitted, right? It's outnumbered half a
million to a hundred. But on top of that, there's actually active mechanisms that will seek and
destroy dad's mitochondria. So the mitochondria coming from the sperm are coated with a protein
called ubiquitin. So after fertilization, those mitochondria are actually actively eliminated
by a surveillance program. So not only is it very difficult for dad's MTDNA to compete with a huge
number of MTDNA molecules from mom, but those that do make it inside are actively destroyed as well.
So mechanistically, these are the two reasons why MTDNA is passed on almost exclusively from
mom to child. Now with that said, about 15 years ago or so, there's a case report in the New
England Journal of Medicine that took a biopsy of a particular individual and they saw MTDNA molecules
with two different haplotypes. And then they looked at the haplotype of the father and they
concluded that this was a rare case of paternal transmission. So that paper from about 15 years
ago was sort of the lone exception to this rule that we accept as an axiom. And then about a year
ago or so in 2018, another paper emerged, again claiming that in a few families there is paternal
transmission of MTDNA. It's a rare event, but this is an active area of research. Rules are made to be
broken. And I think two things. Number one, I think other people will have to try to replicate
these results to make sure that even if they're rare, they're real and not some sort of a technical
artifact. And then number two, if they're not technical artifacts, I think there's an opportunity
to learn something very, very deep about the mechanisms of maternal transmission.
Right, because that would suggest based on the explanation for how this takes place,
it's hard to deny that the first one's going to continue to take place, which is just the stochastic
sampling. But you could certainly see scenarios under which the find and kill program malfunctions
and therefore you sneak in a little bit of the paternal DNA. That's right. And in fact,
in one of these papers that was just published in 2018, they speculated that perhaps there's a
mutation on the nuclear genome in that program so that it's possible for dad's MTDNA to get transmitted.
Well, that is interesting. But I think to the first order approximation, we can still assume
that mitochondrial DNA is maternal. Yes. So let's talk a little bit about sort of
mitochondria 101. So you're a first year medical student learning about the mitochondria. Here's
basically what you learn, right? You've got this inner membrane, this outer membrane.
I forget what the term is. Do they call it the powerhouse of the cell or something like that?
Yes. I think there's some sort of glib term that I know that people who study mitochondria,
like yourself and have deep Chandel who I've interviewed sort of bristle at the simplicity
of such a term. But the idea is all things being equal, a cell takes in glucose, free fatty acid,
substrate for energy. And let's start with the glucose because we'll spend more time talking
about glucose today through what I can't even remember, 10 steps we turn glucose into pyruvate
more or less. We then basically have a choice, a cell has a choice based on the availability of
oxygen and the rate at which ATP is being demanded. So if oxygen is scarce relative to ATP demand,
you can take a inefficient route, but at least you guarantee to get some ATP, which is you can turn
the pyruvate into lactate. And lactate itself is interesting and maybe we can talk about it,
but you generate some ATP. If the demand for ATP is not as great and there's sufficient cellular
oxygen, you can take that pyruvate and make acetyl-CoA and that acetyl-CoA then becomes
one of the substrates leading into this thing called the electron transport chain you alluded to.
Walk us through what happens in that latter scenario. I like to think of the mitochondria
as being the key place where there's energy transformations. So in order for a cell to work,
it needs energy, but in the same way that in order to live our lives, we need to have one type of
battery for our iPhone, a different type of a battery for our laptop, a different type of a
battery for our automobile. We need energy packaged in different ways. So this is sort of the charm of
the mitochondria. What it does is it's going to take fats and carbohydrates and proteins and it's
going to break it up almost like a Kuzunart. And as it's breaking it up, it's going to harness the
electrons and that's what's called an electromotive force. That's one type of energy. So you're
probably familiar with things like the NADH to NAD ratio. That's basically an electron carrier.
So that's one form of energy. In certain times of enzymes can be powered directly by NADH and
NADH. But then that can also be converted to a gradient, a voltage across the inner membrane,
a different type of an energy form and that energy form can be used to drive transport.
So let's explain what that means to people. So everybody knows what a battery looks like. Like
literally a Duracell battery that you stick into whatever, you know, your kid's toy. And that's
typically about 1.5 volts, right? A 9 volt battery gets its name because it has 9 volts,
but everyone recognizes it as the goofy square one. We take this, I think, for granted because
we sort of have these backgrounds in math or engineering and stuff, but I think for the average
person it's helpful to understand what voltage means and you just alluded to it, right? It's a
potential, it's a gradient that is created by disproportionate placement of electrons.
And it's only with that that you can generate power. So why does a battery die? Why is it that,
let's pretend I'm still using a Walkman. I put my two 1.5 volt AA batteries in my Walkman.
At some point it stops working. Why? At some point it's not going to be able to hold charge.
And so I'm probably more familiar with the mitochondrial battery than I am with the
Duracell battery. But when you have nicely functioning mitochondria, you can charge them
you can create a nice voltage that can be used for work. You can dissipate it, you can recharge it,
but at some point when it gets older, when the membrane is a little bit leakier, when it can't,
it'll stop holding charge. So it's that ability to keep a difference in charge across the membranes
that is the same reason your little 1.5 volt battery in your Walkman, I love that I'm saying
Walkman by the way, there's half the people listening, this won't actually know what that means.
Or the 9 volt battery in your smoke detector, or frankly the fancy, I don't even know how many
volts a Tesla battery is, it's like 12 volts I'm guessing or something like that in an electric
vehicle, whatever. But there's a reason you have to keep charging these, but at some point, even
when you charge them, they cease to work if it's a rechargeable. And you're basically saying, look,
think of a mitochondria as partially being a battery. That's right. That's only one form of
energy, right? So that's taking chemical to electric. That's exactly right. And so you can
have an electromotor force, you can have a proton motor force. And then you can dissipate that
battery to basically catalyze a formation of ATP, which most people know is the energy form that's
used to power muscle when you exercise. So the mitochondrion is doing all of these elaborate
energy transformations from electrical potentials to proton potentials to phosphorylation potentials,
and different enzymes and processes and machines in your cells will use one or the other.
This is so exciting. Like, I've tried to have this discussion with my daughter who's 10,
and she's not quite at the point where she sees why I think this is amazing. But she's almost at
that point where I guess you can look at a piece of food on the plate and explain why eating that
is essential, right? Like, where is the energy in that food? So maybe we'll use this as sort of
the example to go full cycle. So you are looking at a cheerio on your plate, right? Now that cheerio
is mostly carbohydrate, so we'll simplify this. And it's got glucose in it, it's probably got
more complex carbohydrates in it, but at a molecular level, it's a lot of carbons joined to hydrogens,
carbons joined to carbons, and carbons joined to oxygens, and oxygens joined to hydrogens. That's
probably most of the bonds, correct? So bonds contain energy. There's chemical energy there.
Which of those bonds would be the most energetic? Probably the carbon hydrogen in total number,
just given the ubiquity of it, right? A carbon hydrogen has more energy than a carbon carbon,
I'm guessing. I'm not too sure. I think that's the case. In the show notes, we'll list what the
potential energy is in each of those bonds. But nevertheless, you go through this process of
actually eating the thing, you put it in your mouth, you break it down. Mechanically, you've
broken it by the time it exits your stomach. But it's really once it gets absorbed out of the
bloodstream that you begin this chemical process of breaking those bonds, and then you get something
for free, right? When you break those bonds, that's when you're getting the energy to create
this electron gradient, which you then use at the end to basically do this one thing you alluded to,
which is phosphorylate the ATP. So that energy gradient allows you to then put a phosphate
back onto an ADP. That's the most obvious one from food. Now you talked about NAD and NADH. Can you
say a little bit more about what those are and how they fit into this, in particular in the
mitochondria? Again, the classical teaching is that NAD is an electron carrier. When you have two
electrons, it's going to be in what's called the NADH form. And if you don't have those two electrons,
it's in the oxidized form, which is the NAD form. That's another way of holding the energy that can
catalyze reactions. What we're learning over the last few years is that in addition to this role
as an electron carrier, the NAD itself can be used as a substrate for other reactions.
Outside of the mitochondria or inside? Outside of its role as an electron carrier.
Okay, and that biggest role for that is in these, we'll come, I guess we'll allude to it, but there
are these complexes in the mitochondria. But that's still as a redox carrier. So the electrons go from
the NADH or transferred to the electron transport chain, and that's basically a wire that's going
to conduct the electron until they hit oxygen and make water. That's a downhill process. And during
that downhill process, these protons are pumped across the inner membrane, generating about 150
millivolts. And that can then be used to do work, including catalyzing the conversion of ADP to ATP.
And that's what we call oxidative phosphorylation. Yep. But then talk about the other example that
you were using there. And this is a newer area of biomedicine. And actually, David Sinclair has
worked in this area quite a bit. But everything that I just told you relates to electrons coming
on and off of NAD. So when we talk about NADH to NAD ratio, that's sort of the redox potential.
But that NAD molecule, it can also participate as a substrate in certain chemical reactions.
So sirtuins use NAD. Exactly. Sirtuins, some of the DNA damage response pathways, the PARPs,
they'll actually use the NAD as a cofactor. So that's important because it's possible in certain
states. Like when you have a damaged cell, for example, if you have a cell with damaged DNA,
that NAD can decline very, very rapidly. It's an electron carrier. So you're actually losing the
ability to carry some of this charge now. This is interesting, right? Because observations are,
as we age, these NAD levels decline. Is that due to greater demand for it? Is it due to
reduction in production? And of course, the clinical question that everybody asks is,
is there benefit to replacing it? What's really interesting is there's a couple of different
signatures of the aging process. So if you biopsy muscle from individuals of varying ages,
you'll see a gradual decline in the NAD content. If you quantify the amount of mitochondria,
using any of the different metrics, you'll see a decline. If you look at things like VO2 max
and skeletal muscle as a function of age, you'll see a gradual decline. So there's this gradual
decline in NAD and in mitochondrial activity as a function of age. And I think the big question
in the field is, do you just have an old and sick tissue? So you have sick mitochondria,
or will targeting the mitochondria actually somehow alleviate age associated decline in
tissue function? This is such an interesting question. And something that probably until a
year ago, I don't think I spent enough time thinking about, which is, what does it mean to
age at the level of the mitochondria? And what are the implications of it? And perhaps most
importantly, what can be done to slow the rate of aging? Now, you study a problem at sort of
a different node, which is you are looking very specifically at diseases that people,
most people haven't actually heard of. And I don't want to say you're not interested in those
diseases per se, because you are, but they're basically a gateway for something else. So later
on in this podcast, I suspect we'll come back to more of this mitochondrial fitness, health,
inflammation, mitophagy. There are many other topics I want to explore with you,
but let's now having laid the groundwork, go back and talk about your work and what you're learning.
So give me an example of some of the diseases that you study in your lab.
We've historically placed a lot of emphasis on a very large collection of individually rare
inborn errors of mitochondrial metabolism. These are typically single gene disorders.
They can be due to recessive mutations in the nuclear genome, or they can be due to mutations
in the mitochondrial genome. But at the end of the day, there's a component of the mitochondria
that's defective at birth. And so what we just spoke about is the fact that as all of us age,
there's a gradual decline in the activity of mitochondria. The big question in the field is
whether that's cause or consequence. These other 300 rare monogenic disorders of mitochondria,
there's no doubt, there's no question. The gene did the randomization for you,
you know cause and effect. That's exactly right. The mitochondria is defective at birth. And now
we can actually evaluate what the consequences are. You said about 300. What is the phenotypic
spectrum? How many of these, for example, are fatal within the first year of life?
They tend to follow a bimodal distribution. The recessive mutations in the nuclear genome,
they tend to present early in infancy within the first few weeks or months of life. The mutations
in the mitochondrial genome, those tend to present a little bit later in life. Wow. So let's focus on
the latter group for a moment. I mean, unless you'd prefer to start with the former, which one do you
spend more time looking at? We spend a little bit more time on the nuclear genes. Okay, because they
present earlier and presumably they're more severe. That's right. Okay, so give me an example of what
some of those mutations are and what their phenotype is. One of the clinical syndromes that
we study is something called Lee syndrome. So there's about 80 different genes that can be
mutated to give rise to this clinical syndrome, which is basically a sub-acute degeneration of
a gray matter. It's a very rapid neurodegeneration. It's a terrible, terrible disease.
And what age are people when they start to experience this neurodegeneration?
So most of these kids are actually born developmentally. Okay. And then within the
first couple of months of life, there's some sort of a stressor. Sometimes it's some sort of an
infection. Sometimes it's dehydration that'll put them into a neuro metabolic crisis. And at that
point, if you look at their brain MRIs, you'll see lesions in the brainstem, the basal ganglia,
sometimes the spinal cord corresponding to regions of necrosis. Wow. So quickly fatal.
And what did you learn? I mean, you have one syndrome, but there are many paths that produce
it. What's the, are there common threads to the genetic insults that lead to this awful phenotype?
Great question. That's exactly what we're trying to figure out. So thanks to genetics,
we've not been able to, we as a community, I mean, have been able to map out genes,
the nuclear genome. Some of these are in the MT DNA, but at the end, we get this thing called Lee
syndrome. And we're trying to figure out what exactly isn't about the broken mitochondria that
gives rise to this phenotype. And honestly, we don't know what the full answer is right now,
but it's a very, very active area of research right now.
It might be naive, but just listening to you describe this, I can't help but think,
can we learn something about Alzheimer's disease or other forms of neurodegeneration, which I think
many people are starting to argue are basically neuronal energy crises. So there are lots of
insults, right? You can have an accumulation of toxin, you can have a insulin resistance,
frankly, you can have microvascular disease. All of these things are predisposing people
to neurodegeneration. And something that they could all have in common is depletion of energy
to the neuron, which would be perhaps the most sensitive cell to an energy reduction. I mean,
anybody can think about that for a moment. If you know somebody who's lost their ability to breathe
for a period of time, usually the thing we care about the most is their brain, because that's the
first thing that you suffer from when you have a hypoxic event. So is that based on Lee's Center,
is that the explanation for why you're potentially seeing it disproportionately in the brain
versus skeletal muscle? Is it just the sensitivity of the brain to energy withdrawal? Or do you think
there's something specific about the mitochondria in neurons? Mitochondrial disorders can actually
impact almost any organ system. And so Lee's syndrome represents one type of clinical manifestation
of mitochondrial disease, but there's another set of disorders that impact the skeletal muscle as well.
I think at this point, we don't know why mutations in one subunit of the electron transport chain
gives rise to brain disease. A mutation in the neighboring subunit of the same protein complex
that's equally evolutionarily conserved will give rise to muscle disease. Wow.
There's a mass of non-linearity over here that we simply don't understand right now.
So if there is one and only one silver lining in these awful diseases, it's that scientists will
have no shortage of questions to ask for decades to come. No, I think this is a super active area of
research right now, in part fueled by the link between mitochondrial decline and aging.
So that's such a complicated problem. You're trying to understand why a car breaks down after
being in service for 25 years. It's hard. Is it some fan belt break? Did the battery stop charging?
Did the tire deflate? It's kind of hard to know why an entire car breaks down after 25 years.
In these rare mitoid disorders, we have 300 different forms of that automobile that was
almost broken at birth, if that makes sense. We study them in part because these patients need
new treatments and therapies. And so that's enough of a motivation for us. But we also do expect that
a subset of them, by studying them, will inform what's happening in more common form of aging.
Your lab studies oxygen, but not necessarily in the way that most people commonly think about it.
Most people, when they think of oxygen and mitochondria, something that comes to mind
pretty quickly is ROS. Absolutely. I spoke with a friend of mine, Navdeep Chandel, and we spoke a
lot about ROS. And now I've had a great take on it, which was, look, we think of ROS typically only in
the negative. And they do lots of negative things. But they may also be a signaling molecule, and
therefore an essential thing. Talk to me about the lens through which your group looks at oxygen.
So remember a while ago, you asked a very, very astute question. You have these 80 different genes.
When they're mutated, they give rise to this thing called Lee syndrome, which is a different type of a
neurodegeneration. What does that pathology pathogenesis look like? The traditional dogma
for mitochondrial pathogenesis is that when the powerhouse of the cell is broken,
there's not enough ATP, and there's a power failure. That's the traditional dogma. And
without a doubt, there's truth to that in some instances. What we've discovered is that in
addition to producing ATP, mitochondria are also consumers of oxygen. Most of the oxygen that you
breathe, Peter, is being consumed by your mitochondria. When a patient has a birth defect
in the mitochondrion, in addition to not being able to produce sufficient ATP,
they also have excess oxygen as well. So oxygen delivery tends to be patent in these patients,
but the utilization ends up being poor. And oxygen, just asking for people to understand,
how does oxygen even get to the mitochondria? So we all understand that we're breathing air that
has oxygen, and let's even go one step further and just take it for granted that there's a
gradient in the lung that allows oxygen to get into hemoglobin to a red blood cell.
Now that you have a fully loaded red blood cell in an arterial that enters a capillary,
how many things have to happen for oxygen to get into the mitochondria specifically,
not just the cell? Oxygen is not particularly soluble in water or fluids, and so we have an
oxygen-carrying protein called hemoglobin that's found in our red blood cells. And so
in the lungs, all of the red blood cells in the hemoglobin get loaded with oxygen,
and now these red blood cells are delivered to peripheral tissues, and the oxygen gets extracted
from the fluid, and as the fluid gets depleted in oxygen, the hemoglobin will basically offload its
oxygen. And so there's certain tissues that become extremely, extremely hypoxic. So the oxygen will
get extracted by a tissue, largely by diffusion, and the mitochondria is basically consuming most
of this oxygen. So a cell that is sitting there doesn't require an active transporter to get
oxygen across its outer membrane, so it just diffuses across. That's right. When oxygen enters
the cytoplasm, how does it get over to the mitochondria? Depending on the cell type,
it either diffuses or... How does it know that the mitochondria is the place it needs to go?
Well, it's being consumed, so it's a little bit of a sink, basically.
So that's what I want to understand. There are lots of places oxygen could hang out,
so what is the force that is drawing it into the mitochondria? Is it simply utilization
that basically creates a vacuum? That's right. That's right. Now, in certain tissues like skeletal
muscle and heart, we have other oxygen carriers in the tissue, things like myoglobin are oxygen
carriers, so they're almost little buffers of oxygen that are in the tissue. Yeah, they're more
like loaders, right? That's right. I think of them as another storage for oxygen inside.
Yeah. That's right. But that still has to get off the myoglobin and get sucked into the mitochondria,
effectively, right? That's right. So it's another little storehouse, if you will. It's another
buffer of oxygen, so that when you're exercising, for example, you may not want to be oxygen limited,
so you have a little extra oxygen in your myoglobin. But basically, your mitochondria is
where most of your oxygen is being consumed, so it's a sink. And so that's the reason that we have
gradients inside of our cells. It's amazing. I've never really even thought about it this way, but
it's sort of interesting to think at how efficiently the body disposes of carbon dioxide,
because, as you alluded to earlier, the end of that downhill gradient is a final path of
electron acceptance, generating H2O and CO2, both of which we manage to largely off gas.
So somehow those things have to exit the mitochondria, weasel out of the cell, cross
the gradient and go back to, well, in the case of CO2, get back to the hemoglobin molecule and get
carried back. It's like there's a lot of things going on here. Well, so one of the things that
we're discovering by studying these rare diseases, and this happened because of a CRISPR screen that
we did a couple of years ago, but what we've now discovered is that one of the consequences
of mitochondrial dysfunction is excess unused oxygen. So in other words, if a mitochondria
is failing to do its job, you will be failing to utilize oxygen. Therefore, you would see an excess
accumulation of oxygen. That's right. And we believe this is our hypothesis now. It's that
some of that excess unused oxygen is what is contributing to the pathology that we see in
some of these rare diseases. It's a very, very different type of an idea. It's not
all about the ATP. It's about excess unused oxygen. And we're not necessarily invoking
reactive oxygen species. Yeah, I was just about to say, is it through free radicals or is it
actually oxygen to oxygen, no extra electron oxygen? This is dioxygen toxicity that we're
talking about. The way that I like to think about it is if you have an automobile that's outside and
it's rusting, it's rusting in part because the oxygen is directly oxidizing iron. You may produce
a radical, but that's not the phenomenon. So the car outside is not rusting because of too much
superoxide or hydrogen peroxide. It's direct oxidation of iron centers by oxygen. And so one
of our hypotheses is that enzymes are tuned to operate within a particular oxygen range. And when
the mitochondrion is not functioning properly, oxygen levels rise, that excess dioxygen can now
oxidize enzymes that will damage them as a consequence. So it's a very, very different way
of thinking about mitochondrial pathogenesis. Now, why doesn't the body correct for that and note
that while the oxygen in the mitochondria is not being utilized as quickly as my evolutionary
prediction would allow, but therefore we're going to, there's less gradient pressure. So I'm going
to off gas, I'm going to offload less oxygen to the cell with subsequent trips through. Like in
other words, you almost think this would have been corrected in a few milliseconds.
Well, I think at a healthy human, that's exactly right. We have pretty solid matching of oxygen
delivery and oxygen utilization, but we're talking about patients that have broken mitochondria.
So this is one of the things that we're actually trying to investigate. One of the ways that
Ron Haller at the University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center has proposed diagnosing patients
with mitochondrial disease is to put them on a treadmill, measure their oxygen extraction,
and patients with mitochondrial myopathies will often have high venous oxygen.
Let's explain that to people because we're going to talk about VO2 max and you've alluded to it. So
most people associate that test with sort of peak athletic performance, but let's talk about what it
looks like. If I came into your lab and you were doing this, you'd hook me up to a device, you'd
put me on a treadmill, you'd make me, you know, have to do some work to stress the system.
You'd plug my nose and put a little miserable device in my mouth, basically creating a seal
that would prevent me from being able to get oxygen or dispose of carbon dioxide in any place
other than the gas chamber that is attached to the tube going into my mouth. You'd put me at the,
you know, you'd ramp up the speed of the treadmill and you would be measuring essentially two things,
the amount of oxygen you're putting in and if it's room air, we sort of know what that is,
but more importantly, the concentration of oxygen coming out and that difference is what you're
talking about. It's that extraction. Now, what happens in a normal person when you do this?
So Peter, we actually don't do these types of studies in humans and so.
When one does this, yeah, what would normally happen is what would you be measuring as a normal
person works harder and harder in the difference between provided oxygen and returned oxygen?
So again, we don't do these types of studies, but in these types of physiological studies that
people like Ron Haller, other cardiologists will perform, they'll look at cardiac output
as well as the oxygen tensions on the arterial and venous signs. And so by looking at all of
these numbers, you can actually figure out quantitatively the number of O2 molecules
being delivered as well as those that are being extracted versus those that are being returned
to the venous system. So you sort of do a, you can do a mass balance on oxygen effectively.
That's exactly right. That's exactly right. And as it turns out in these patients with
inherited mitochondrial disease, for some reason, the cardiac output is high,
the extraction is low in a healthy individual. Usually the homeostasis is such that you're not
going to be delivering more oxygen than you really need. So that homeostasis is somehow broken in
these patients with. So that patient would actually have a very high lactate level as well,
because if they're able to produce the cardiac output, but they're not doing it with oxidative
phosphorylation, they're using their escape valve. So they're going to disproportionately
have high lactate levels relative to a healthy individual. That's right. So Ron Haller would
actually argue that a high lactate in combination with a high venous oxygen is suggestive of a
mitochondrial myopathy. There's a researcher at the University of Colorado who is looking into
this very phenomenon as an early indicator of type two diabetes. And it's really fascinating.
I'm going to be going out there to spend some time with them this summer. They've made the
observation that in the early stages of insulin resistance, the muscle, the skeletal muscle in
particular becomes inefficient at oxfoss. So you start to see even at baseline, even a person
sitting at rest, their lactate levels could be twice as high as that of a fit individual. And
of course, he came to this through the thinking that if you want to understand that disease of
the mitochondria, look at the exact opposite. Look at the fittest people in the world, look at the
endurance athletes and ask the question, what do their mitochondria do well? And then what becomes
the polar opposite of that in disease? Now, what you're describing is the most extreme example I've
ever heard of this, right? Absolutely. What you're describing is actually very consistent with a
series of papers that were published probably in 2003 and 2004, including by myself in collaboration
with Leaf Group and David Altshuler, Ron Kahn, who used to be the president of the Jocelyn,
as well as Jerry Shulman from Yale, and Srikumar Nair at Mayo Clinic. All of us had sort of papers
at the same time. David Altshuler is here, right? David Altshuler used to be here. He's now at
Vertex, but he's one of the founders of the Broad Institute. But all of us had papers published at
about the same time that showed that if you take skeletal muscle from pre-diabetics, healthy
individuals that have a family history of diabetes, but are still healthy, they'll all have a reduced
number of mitochondria. The expression of those 1000 genes required for mitochondria, it's just a
little bit lower. If you look at any one gene, it's not significant, but if you look at the entire
pathway, the entire pathway is down, the VO2 max is down. So there's a series of papers back in 2003
and 2004 that led to the mitochondrial hypothesis for type 2 diabetes. The big question still to this
date, almost 15, 16 years later, is that actually causal for the diabetes, or is it just an early
epiphenomenon? There's something else, X, that lies upstream of the amount of mitochondria and
independently the predisposition to diabetes, or is that a part of the causal path? That's still
unanswered to this date. And there's nothing in a Mendelian randomization that can answer that question.
So as you probably know, these types of methods are only now becoming possible. So we're trying
to work on those types of projects right now. You need large numbers of heavily genotyped
individuals, you also need to have nice biomarkers or proxies for mitochondrial function. So those
are some of the types of things we're trying now. Because it comes up from time to time, do you
mind just explaining how Mendelian randomization works and why it's so powerful? Again, this is not
an area of my expertise, others are much more expert at it than I am. But the analogy that
they'll often use in describing a Mendelian randomization is a little bit like a drug trial.
So in a drug trial, what you'll do is you'll take individuals and you'll randomize them either to
a drug arm or a placebo arm, and then you'll look for an outcome. There's an intervention,
which is the assignment of a drug or the placebo, and then you can actually check to see whether
the outcome is correlated to that particular intervention. And if you see an effect, now that
effect is attributable to that intervention. Because the decision to give the intervention
versus the placebo was done randomly. If you didn't do it randomly, you can't make that assertion.
That's right. Now in a Mendelian randomization experiment, the idea is that there's a
randomization that took place at birth. And so if you look at something like LDL levels, for example,
an important question is, are LDL levels causal for heart attack? Or are they simply correlative
for heart attack? So thanks to genetics, we have a lot of genetic variants that can help explain
the population variation in LDL levels. Once you have a good solid genetic instrument,
now what we can do is we can take a very large number of individuals and we can actually draw
a bell curve for what their genetic LDL levels must look like. We haven't measured LDL in them,
but from the genetics, you can actually come up with a bell curve in the population. And now you
can say, let's take this tail, they've been randomized to a high genetic level of LDL versus
this tail, a low genetic level of LDL. Now let's see what the outcomes are. And based on the
statistics, based on the patterns of correlation, you can then make the inference that the LDL is
either causal for heart attack, or there's no evidence for causality. I am not an MR, Mendelian
randomization jock, but my recollection in reading some of the papers about this is the one place
that either as an investigator or a consumer of this science where you have to force yourself to
look closely is you can be fooled if the randomization of genes, meaning if the genes
that you're looking at can also control something else that is related to the disease that could
have a counterbalancing effect. Is that correct? That's one place where one has to be quite cautious.
I think there's multiple places where, I mean, as soon as you have feedback loops, you can get
phenomenon called reverse causation. Your genetic instrument also has to be really, really good.
So again, this is not my area of expertise. So it has to be pursued with care for sure. So there's
probably going to be a fair number of false positive results for all true positive results
from Mendelian randomization studies. Yeah, but it is interesting. I would love to see the MR when
it's done for this particular question. Because again, you know, the implications are significant,
both from the standpoint of preventing chronic disease or risk reduction in chronic disease.
But also as we try to approach the question the way that you phrased it a moment ago, which I
really liked, which is everybody kind of has the gestalt of that car that just sort of breaks down.
And sometimes it's attributable to a catastrophic failure. Sometimes you blow the head gasket in the
car and it's that it dies at that moment. And it just becomes economically not feasible to put a
new head gasket on. Other times it just gets harder and harder to start until it's just not
worth driving anymore. So taking this to humans, how important is mitochondrial health to that
process? In other words, does it become more often than not one of the drivers of this feeling,
this lack of robustness, this lack of stability within the organism? And it seems to me that it's
on the short list of candidates, right? I mean, when this process goes awry, you are interrupting
one of the more fundamental systems in human biology that affects almost every cell in the body,
right? Absolutely. I think it kind of cuts both ways because I think when other processes in the
cell fail, I think the mitochondrion is at risk for also failing. So it's a highly reactive
organelle as well, if that makes sense. It's going to be a tough question to fully answer. And this
is why we like these rare genetic disorders because they teach us about the pathology
pathogenesis of the organelle in a few defined modes. And the big question for our field is,
which of those rare diseases, which of those rare forms of pathogenesis bears any relevance to the
common form of wear and tear aging? So there may be a small subset of rare diseases where the fan
belt is broken at birth, right? But it may be the case that the fan belt, as it turns out, is so
resilient, you never have to change it. And it's rarely the cause of a car breaking down. But it
could be the case that it's actually the spark plug, right? It could be the case that there are
certain birth defects with a spark plug is actually not working at birth. And as it turns out,
with wear and tear aging, spark plugs have to be replaced. And so we have 300 different
forms of monogenic mitochondrial disease, right? You have 300 single point of failures to study.
And that gives you a beautiful picture of what it looks like. Some of these are going to bear no
relevance to the common form of aging. That's just going to be a fact. But the hope is that a
small number of these will bear some relevance to the common form of aging. And just to be clear,
we care about these diseases just because these are terrible diseases, and we need therapies for
them. And so that alone is motivation for our work in this area. But it's also our hope that studying
some of them will provide insights into the common form of aging as well.
You talked earlier about signatures of time. And another one of these signatures of time is
inflammation within muscle cells. There was a paper that came out about a year ago that used
Sting to basically block the ability of a cell to sense breakdown in mitochondrial DNA. Are you
familiar with this work? I'm a little bit familiar with the Sting pathway. My understanding, it's been
about a year since I read this, maybe a bit less, was that serially, if you study muscles as they
age, you see more and more inflammation. So the question is, what is drawing inflammatory cells
into muscle as we age? And the hypothesis was, going back to something you talked about earlier,
the DNA of mitochondria is bacterial in origin. And therefore, if you have a loose fragment of
nuclear DNA in the cell, it shouldn't be especially immunogenic. But if you have a loose
fragment of bacterial DNA in a cell, that should actually be quite immunogenic. Our immune systems
would think of that as foreign. So the hypothesis was, what if the increase in inflammation we see
is due to greater and greater mitochondrial damage that is leading to more and more exposure
of mitochondrial DNA? And I believe to test that, it used Sting. And remind me, I think Sting
actually blocks the ability of the cell to sense the mitochondrial DNA. Is that correct?
Not just mitochondrial DNA, but I think it's a general nucleic acid sensor. And so there could
be different sources. I think- It could block the sensing of DNA, period. I think ordinarily,
it's designed to sense the DNA of incoming viruses or incoming pathogens. But you could imagine that
if a mitochondria ruptures, that same DNA nucleic acids can also be sensed. And you're right,
because the mitochondria used to be a bacteria, a lot of the components inside of our mitochondria
resemble that of modern day bacteria, and can be very immunogenic. I don't know if you follow-
There's a study that came out of the Beth Israel Deaconess a few years ago on sterile crush injury.
And as a former surgeon, you'd probably appreciate it. But the observation was that when you had an
enclosed crush injury, so the skin has not been violated. There's a massive inflammatory response.
So this investigator was actually trying to figure out what the inflammatory nidus was,
did a lot of fractionation, and ultimately figured out that there was some mitochondrial
derived molecules. And I believe that they found that the mitochondrial DNA,
as well as something called formulated peptides, are highly inflammatory. So remember those 13
proteins that are made by the MT DNA, the translation of those 13 proteins resembles
the translation of bacterial proteins. And bacterial protein translation doesn't begin
with a methanol tyrene. It begins with a formal methanol tyrene. Remember this F-met peptides?
Yeah, this is my God, I feel like I'm back in medical school. Can you just for no other reason
than for me to remember that. Let's go through that. So your DNA makes your messenger RNA,
your messenger RNA then moves over to be translated and to actually have the amino
acids put in place to resemble the code that's being said. So talk about where the meth terminal
end shows up there. In you and I, in eukaryotes, protein translation begins with a methionine
residue. In bacteria, it's not a simple methionine, but it's a modified molecule. It's called formal
methionine. And first order approximation, it's almost a signature of a bacterial derived protein.
And we actually have receptors that are designed to detect formulated peptides. It's a sign of some
sort of an infection. As it turns out, our mitochondria have bacterial origins, as we have
discussed earlier. So these 13 proteins, they still begin with the formal methionine. Presumably,
they can get away with it under normal circumstances because they reside within the
mitochondria that's protected and shielded from the immune system. That's right. So in certain
injuries, this can actually escape and it can basically activate the same inflammatory pathways
that we have that are ordinarily designed to detect incoming pathogens. I can't wait to actually find
that paper. So who is the author on that? I forget his name, but he's from the Beth Israel Deaconess.
Okay, and it was like O2O3-ish. No, no, no, this was probably within the last five years ago or so.
Well, we'll find that paper and link to it. But basically that paper and the paper I was referring
to from about a year ago, which I think was in science, both point to a similar conclusion,
which is you can have a profound inflammatory response by simply damaging the mitochondria.
And both of them would point to consistent plausible explanations, which are the body confusing
the contents for bacterial contents. I think it's a very reasonable hypothesis.
Which then begs the question, if we believe that the aging inflammation phenotype is not beneficial,
how do we prevent mitochondrial breakdown as we age? I mean, this becomes one of the key
aging questions, right? If you believe that, and again, I don't know what the best analogy is, but
spark plug failure plays a role more often than not in the overall picture of decline,
the longer you can protect those things, preserve those things, the better.
Another way to evaluating the causality question is if we had a drug that could somehow rejuvenate
mitochondria, then you could ask the question, does directly intervening on this organelle
retard the aging process? And unfortunately, as of right now, we don't have that type of a
magic bullet, but exercise is one of the best ways of turning over bad mitochondria and inducing the
biogenesis of good mitochondria. But the challenge, of course, as exercise does lots of things.
Now that said, we always, this is one of the differences between, I think, being a scientist
and a doctor. When you're wearing your doctor hat, you just have to know what to do for that
patient in that moment. And it's a luxury to know how and why it works, right? So when we think about
the importance of exercise, I've always found that ironic that I probably classify or qualify as an
exercise addict, like in the true unhealthy sense of the word, you know, I probably meet all the
criteria of addiction and all of that stuff. But up until recently, I don't think I really appreciated
the value of exercise. I think it was honestly just something I did out of my neurotic pathology.
But I actually, I think if asked would have said that nutrition played a much greater role in health,
sleep played a much greater role in health. And that exercise, you know, I mean, it's great, but,
you know, if you, I'd rather you eat well than exercise a lot or something to that effect.
I'm certainly revisiting that. And of course, I also find it silly to do these sort of zero-sum
games, like it has to be one or the other, you know, presumably doing all of these things well
as the optimal strategy. But the deeper I look at exercise, and I'd love to know your framework
for this, because I'm still trying to create one. I'm putting exercise very loosely into three buckets,
strength training, very specific aerobic training. So this would be maximum mitochondrial output
with minimal generation of lactate. And then anaerobic training where you are basically demanding
ATP at such a rate that you are really running through that lactate production pathway. Do you
think that's a reasonable framework of buckets of exercise? Do you divide them even more granularly
as you think about it mechanistically? We're really not exercise physiologist. I don't think
I can comment. Just personally, do you think of it in a way like that? I think that's very reasonable.
You know, just in hearing you talk, I mean, again, we're not aging researchers, but
so I'll ask you a question. If that's okay, has anyone actually, you know, people have given
metformin to mice, they've given rapamyce into mice, but has anyone given mice
those three flavors of exercise to determine what the impact is on longevity?
Yeah, I believe those experiments have been done. And I believe all of them show benefit. I'd have
to go back and look at the literature in mice. In fact, I'm in the process of just starting to work
on that chapter in a book that I'm writing. The problem is I generally bias against heavy
mice literature, but you at least have the advantage of control. So the short answer is
definitely each of those as a medication, right? If you think of each of those as a pill,
each of those produce a longevity phenotype. Where it gets challenging, I think in humans is,
well, I think there are so many ways to die when you get old that, for example, accidental death
would rank in the top five causes of death for people over the age of 60. Now, the type of accident
can change around, but by the time you're in your eighth or ninth decade, falling becomes such a
significant cause of death due to the frailty of the individual that some of that exercise,
for example, strength training almost assuredly offers protection from that type of death.
So the question is, I think it's a little hard to tease out how much of that benefit is in the
cardiometabolic side versus otherwise. The other thing that's really challenging in studying humans
is we don't have really good prospective studies in anything that resembles a longevity phenotype.
So you are now stuck using something I think I recently described as the most
servile trash ever shat into civilization, which is epidemiologic questionnaires to try to impute
based on you telling me how you've exercised over the past 10 years, how that's going to predict
your longevity phenotype. And again, the problem there is the dose matters, the specificity, the
quantity, the quality, these things matter, and they're very difficult to tease out from these
retrospective views. So I think the evidence is very compelling that exercise matters,
and that's maybe less the question I'm interested in. I think what I'd love to gain insights into,
and we may have to rely on non-human models, is just as we now can tailor a drug to do something
very specific, can we tailor our exercise to be as optimal as possible? So if you took an individual
who said, Peter, look, I'm willing to exercise five hours a week, or I'm willing to exercise
10 hours a week, but I'm not going to be a professional athlete, how do I take those five
hours a week, or 10 hours a week, or whatever it is, and make the best use of it to impact
all causes of mortality, meaning reduction of the risk of atherosclerotic disease,
cancer, neoplasm, neurodegenerative disease, and accidental death from strengthening the
exoskeleton. So that's clinically the question I'm most interested in as it pertains to exercise,
but I'm convinced that at the center of that question is understanding the role of exercise
in mitochondrial health. I think this is a very important piece of the puzzle, and certainly much
more important than I appreciated even two years ago. I think what you describe about these
age-appropriate or age-acknowledged declines in VO2 max, mitochondrial density, mitochondrial
efficiency, venous O2 concentration, I think there's something really important there.
And even if exercise is affecting something upstream that is affecting that, at least we
have a great proxy through which to measure. I think there's going to end up being a lot of
really interesting nonlinear dynamics of mitochondria as a function of age, as a function of exercise.
There's a few vignette cell shares. You probably know if you don't use your skeletal muscle,
you lose lean muscle mass, you lose your mitochondria very quickly. How quickly? You
have measurable defects in the VO2 max after 10 days of hospitalized bed rest, and to recover the
VO2 max that you lose in 10 days, it takes about six weeks or so. Oh my god, yeah, I knew it was
bad. I didn't know it was that bad. So there's quite a bit of hysteresis over here, right? Quite
a bit of hysteresis. So it's going to be complex and nonlinear. The programs that turn on mitochondria
during exercise, they're really elaborate. And the idea of actually replacing it in a pill
may end up being kind of naive. I think that exercise does so many things simultaneously.
It's like 17 different inputs into the system. And it may be the case that it's only if those 17
inputs are provided with the right dynamics and the right off rates that you get properly
functioning more mitochondria. In certain disease states, some of the muscle disorders that I study,
the ragged red fiber that you may remember from your board exams, the ragged red fiber represents
an accumulation of poorly functioning mitochondria. So I think that if you try to bottle up just two
of these factors or three of these factors, we may be able to produce more malfunctioning
mitochondria. But it could be the case that we've evolved to require 17 inputs provided at the right
time and place in order to get proper mitobiogenesis. It's a really, really smart program, this
PTC1 alpha program, because it simultaneously turns on mitochondrial biogenesis while also turning on
some of the autophagy programs. And so you're actually turning over your bad mitochondria
while you're turning on your good mitochondria simultaneously. And that's what happens with
exercise. Well, you read my mind, and I don't know if you could read my little notes I'm taking over
here, because as we're talking, I'm making little notes of things I want to ask you. And that's
exactly kind of where I want it to go, which was, let's talk about what autophagy means in the
context of mitochondria. So people who listen to this podcast know that I'm a big fan of fasting,
periodic fasting, because even though we don't have great ways to measure autophagy clinically,
I think we have pretty good evidence that periods of really strict fasting, meaning
exclusively consuming water for some period of time, my hypothesis is three to seven days,
produces meaningful autophagy. But how does exercise impact that based on what you've seen
in the mitochondria? So I don't know too much about fasting, but when you do have proper exercise
regimes, what we observe is that there are transcriptional programs with multiple inputs,
some of which we discussed earlier, but those are probably not sufficient, that will basically
turn on all 1000 of those proteins to produce more mitochondria. But that same program is also
saying, Hey, let's turn over some of the previously produced mitochondria. So it's a very, very smart
system. It's not going to just produce more good mitochondria in the presence of bad might is it
actually cleanse the system as well. And remind me what you said. I know you already answered this,
I apologize. When you look at cells that are not turning over quickly, so myocytes, neurons,
what did you say was the approximate turnover of mitochondria? Probably a few days. A few days,
unbelievable. So it's just, this is an unbelievable amount of work to create the new and systematically
and selectively discard and recycle the old. That's right. That's right. And the signals,
given that you like exercise, I'll tell you one study that I thought was really provocative,
and maybe you already know it, but it came from, I think, Michael Ristow and Ron Kahn,
about 10 to 12 years ago in PNAS. Do you know this study? I don't. I don't think I do, but keep
going. It was a human study. They, two by two matrix, they randomized humans either to exercise
or no exercise and antioxidants or no antioxidants. Oh, yes. Okay. I know the study, but please keep
going. No, this is great. So which of the four quadrants do you think is best? I know the answer,
so I want you to, yeah, you keep going. Yeah. So most people would probably guess. Most people
would say exercise with antioxidants must be the optimal health. Absolutely. And what this study
showed that was a little bit counterintuitive is that antioxidants on top of exercise almost
prevents or erases some of the beneficial effects of exercise. And the authors concluded that things
like reactive oxygen species are probably playing an important signaling role as well. That helps in
the adaptation. You need some of those sparks in order to turn on new programs that are net
beneficial. So if you erase those sparks, yet you prevent the full benefit of exercise. So just
another reason why the entire system is so complicated. I mean, I think investigating
exercise, and again, we don't do that. That's not a core scientific focus of our laboratory, but
so many diseases, ultimately, their risk is reduced by exercise. So studying it is,
it should be a very important objective for all of us. It's so interesting because that's a,
that is a great example. I'm glad you brought that up. And Nav and I, though we didn't talk about
that study, we talked a lot about this issue of blocking ROS and how if one has cancer, for
example, the evidence is becoming pretty clear that the last thing you want to do in a cancer
patient is give them an antioxidant as sort of anti sort of dogmatic as that would seem,
because the ROS actually play an important role in selectively targeting a cancer cell versus a
non-cancer cell. Listening to these discussions makes you almost wonder how in the world does any
drug show up with a benefit in longevity. It's almost a miracle that rapamycin can so ubiquitously
across so many species extend life. When, as you point out, most of the things that do the heavy
lifting in longevity have 17 prongs that can't be replicated by a single molecule. I mean, it just,
it seems impossible. The one that has me very interested right now, and again, I don't know
how much you've studied this. My guess is even if you haven't, just your peripheral knowledge
will exceed that of anybody's is metformin. So again, I think most people listening to this
podcast know a lot about it. I had an interview with Nier Barzilay, who I'm also having lunch with
today, and Nier's certainly one of the world's experts on this topic. So we had a great discussion
of all of the benefits of metformin. Don't think it's really disputable how big those benefits are
in people who have diabetes. I think that is becoming very clear. And then by extension in
people who are insulin resistant. What I think is not entirely clear, and I think is the purpose of
what Nier is hoping to study with Taim is if you took a non-diabetic, non-insulin resistant
individual and gave them metformin, will you enhance their longevity phenotype? And the one area that
I'm most interested in this question is what is the impact of metformin on the ability of exercise
to improve the phenotype? And that's something that just on a personal level, I've been experimenting
with a lot. So doing a lot of lactate testing on myself with and without metformin and using
lactate as a proxy for mitochondrial function. So, you know, we were talking about this a little bit
before, but just for the listeners of what I do is take a resting lactate level. I shouldn't be using
any more ATP than I'm using at this moment. What is my level of lactate? Then on a bicycle that
allows me to control the wattage to the nearest watt, basically move in five or 10 watt increments
slowly, you know, spend 10 minutes at this wattage, go up by five for 10 minutes, go up by five for 10
minutes and keep measuring lactate levels. And you generate a performance curve, an LPC, a lactate
performance curve. And you do this with and without metformin, you see a difference. The question is,
does that difference matter clinically? And is it possible that metformin is actually not helping
in the context of exercise? Are you seeing that in the presence of metformin if you are exercising,
you're producing less lactate? I'm seeing more lactate in the presence of metformin. Now, again,
this is an N of one study on myself, but it makes sense that you could, I mean, that's a plausible.
How are you measuring your lactate? Using blood in the finger.
Yeah. We should do metabolomics on you. I mean, with our new instrumentation, we can measure not
just lactate, but literally. Measure everything. Hundreds of metabolites. It gives a little bit
more of a comprehensive snapshot of all of your metabolic pathways. Could we get an IRB to do that
easily? Let's do it. I'm all in. So we could do it. We could do an on metformin, off metformin
snapshot because, so here's my crude thinking on this is, if metformin is inhibiting complex one,
it wouldn't be beyond the realm of possibility that the body might preferentially not shuttle
pyruvate into the mitochondria. I mean, it's still doing so to a great extent,
but if it's disproportionately now keeping pyruvate outside and turning it into lactate,
that could drive up lactate levels. The thing that surprised me the most
is how high my resting lactate levels seem to be. I mean, I remember before I started taking metformin,
you would barely check a resting lactate level, but it was usually below one millimolar.
Now my resting lactate level on metformin is typically between one and two millimolar. It's
about 2x. And I'm doing this in as painful and, but hopefully valid a way as one can do it,
which is I'm using two separate meters, checked in duplicate on the third drop of blood. Like I'm
trying to be as systematic as possible. Anyone listening to this who wants to do this, I just
want to warn you in advance before you get started. Lactate meters are upsettingly expensive
and the strips are the racket. I mean, they'll sell you the device for 300 bucks and each strip
costs you about $5. So every time I do one of these dumb tests, which I typically do about once a week,
it's like dinner and a movie for five people. But it'd be amazing to see what a broader sequence of
metabolomics looks like to understand is there something that's happening. And by the way,
then the next question is do that in somebody who has diabetes and see if you see an improvement
or a reduction in performance. You measured your fasting resting lactate before you started metformin.
Do you know if it went up after you started metformin and then it went back down again or?
Well, so that's an interesting question. So before I started taking metformin,
I would do lactate testing, but I was interested in a different question. So it's not an apples to
apples comparison. We always had a resting lactate just because you wanted to basically calibrate
the machine and make sure your machine was working. But generally when we did what was
called this LPC, the lactate performance curve, it was mostly geared towards identifying a different
position on the curve, which is very crudely done. But you do a series of efforts at different
power outputs or in a swimming pool at different speeds or on a track, different running velocities.
And you'll notice that the curve is nonlinear. So it starts like this, I'm sort of drawing,
it goes flat, and then it starts to shoot up very quickly towards a vertical asymptote.
That can be approximated by two linear curves. And the intersection of that curve is generally
a person's lactate threshold. And that's different. That's usually a higher number than two millimolar.
Let's just say to make the math easy, that usually is in about the four millimolar range.
And it's that point where that corresponds to on the x-axis, that output is generally about the
fastest velocity or output a person can hold for a certain type of race that we're interested in
studying. So I have infinite numbers of those data for myself back in the days long before I took
metformin. But it was undeniable how low my lactate level started. So I at least have that data point.
I think that's really interesting. We published a paper in PNAS a couple of years ago where we
placed either healthy individuals or patients with mitochondrial disease on a treadmill,
did a 10 minute exercise test and then drew their blood at rest, peak exercise and post recovery,
just to look at the metabolome response to exercise. So of course, we get lactate. And the
mito patients, some of whom have complex one deficiency, not because of metformin,
but because of a genetic deficiency, they begin with a high resting lactate. And there's a parallel
rise in their lactate that parallels what happens to a healthy human. And it stays high parallel with
the healthy individual post recovery. Do you remember offhand how high their resting
lactates were relative to the non-insulted? It was single digit millimolar. It wasn't sky high.
I want to say something like two, three, four millimolar, but we should look that up just to
confirm. But it'd be interesting to see, this is purely science now talking to you is whether we
could repeat that exact same study, not with genetic complex one deficiency, but with
induced form and right exactly. Yeah. You know, a lot of people ask me about metformin and aging.
And again, we don't do aging, real aging research in our lab. We hope to be able to impact
that through some of our work. And I'm hoping that my questions are like prompting you to
celebrate your, you've got all these amazing tools to study it, right?
Absolutely. It really is a space that really captures anyone's imagination. But if you ask
me how I think metformin is working, I think it's probably related to the body's homeostatic response
to complex one inhibition. So of course, metformin hits complex one. I think that's undeniable. It
may have other targets, but without a doubt, it hits complex one. When complex one has been
blocked, the body senses it. And there's a feedback loop, there's a homeostatic response. And that's
probably what is net protective or helpful. And it may be the case that throwing a wrench in a
complex one, it turns on 15 of those 17 inputs that you need to sort of rejuvenate not just your
mitochondria, but other parts of your cell as well. I think there's some really interesting
experiments in worms. As you probably know, there's quite a bit of worm longevity work.
And there's early studies by my MGH colleague, Gary Rovkin, as well as Cynthia Kenyon, who
was at UCSF and is now at Calico. They did RNAI screens to basically look for
genes, which when disrupted, would lead to a longevity phenotype. And one of the
one of the gene sets that was most associated with a longevity phenotype
was the mitochondrial electron transport chain. At the same time, one of the gene sets that was
associated with a drastically reduced lifespan was the mitochondrial electron transport chain.
You can ask the question, it was a different subset of genes. Obviously, there's about 90 genes
total required for the electron transport chain and oxidative phosphorylation. So the question is,
why do loss of some of them lead to longevity? And why do loss of others lead to a shortened lifespan?
One hypothesis is that it's just the strength of the allele. If you, some of those RNAIs really
wiped out the electron transport chain probably led to early death of the worm. But if you just
gently block the electron transport chain with the right RNAI alleles, perhaps mimicking what
metformin does, you do get a longevity phenotype. So a hypothesis in the field, I'm not alone,
but I think there's others in the field that think that maybe one of the ways that metformin works is
sure, it does block the electron transport chain, but then it comes back and causes an entire
adaptive or a homeostatic response that is not adaptive at the whole organism level.
I'm not going to put you on the spot and ask you if you think people should take metformin.
I think the broader question is, do you think, based on what you've seen in the ETC
models, that it's quite possible that a drug like metformin can be beneficial to some and
harmful to others? Oh, I think without a doubt, I mean, we know that metformin is useful for type
two diabetes. So I think it's a fact that for a subset of the population, metformin is helpful
and beneficial. You know, in a rare subset of cases, you can actually have fatal lactic
acidosis from drugs related to metformin, things like FEN formin. Right, which is more potent.
That's exactly right. That gets back to this idea of the potency or the allelic strength of inhibition
of the electron transport chain. But if you took that acute toxicity aside, I mean, I think this
is really the question I've now become fixated on. If you take somebody who is already maximizing
the benefits of exercise, nutrition, sleep, these things that I think the more we look at them, the
more powerful they are. It's one thing to say the addition of metformin offers minimal benefit or
incremental benefit. It would be another thing if you're more in the ROS category that you alluded
to earlier. Is this actually undoing some of the benefit? That's why I actually think that the
experiment that you and I just discussed a few minutes ago, trying to see what the cross-product
of exercise and metformin look like, I think it could be totally fascinating. Is it going to look
like the Ron Consteady from a decade ago where there is at least one experiment out there that
suggests that, but again, I don't know how deep they look at this. So this is a very interesting
idea. The only drawback of this idea means I have to keep coming back to Boston. But now we're
entering the right time of year to do it. So that's fine. So changing gears from the role of hypoxia
as a therapeutic. I mean, based on what you see in the mitochondria, how do you see that as a
potential therapeutic option? This is something that we're really excited about on the preclinical
level. And I really want to emphasize this Peter, because oxygen follows the Goldilocks principle.
Too little is absolutely fatal, deadly. What we're discovering is that too much, in certain
instances, genetic backgrounds can be damaging as well. And so all of our work to date has been
focused in preclinical models. One of the things that we are discovering in these rare mitochondrial
disorders is that a lot of the ATP levels are actually nicely defended by glycolysis.
And so although the textbook dogma is that a lot of these disorders are disorders of
energy deficiency, under resting conditions, ATP levels are okay. But what we're observing is high
unused oxygen. And the important question is how can we now try to interdict and somehow try to
reduce the delivery of oxygen. So in least in our mouse models, we're using hypoxia chambers,
we actually dilute the air that the mice breathe with nitrogen. We use some of the devices that
the sports industry has created, nitrogen generators, face masks, tents, we place the mice
in those apparatus, dilute the air with nitrogen, and then we evaluate the impact. And at least in
some, not all, some of our mouse models of mitoid disease, the benefits are striking.
Let's explain again, just why this is so profound, right? So going back to the model you described
earlier, in a subset of clinical scenarios where mitochondrial function, for lack of a better word,
is impaired, you're seeing a much higher level of oxygen returned to the lungs, despite a high
output of energy, imputing that their mitochondria simply aren't working. That high amount of oxygen
itself can be problematic. So you're saying, well, rather than putting you in an environment where the
ambient oxygen concentration is 21%, we're going to lower that. How much do you lower that too, by the way,
in these tents with the mice? At sea level, we're typically breathing about 21% oxygen, we reduce it
down to about 11%. How is that? I don't know much about my altitudes, but that strikes me as really
low. Is that like the top of Mount Everest low? It's not Everest, it's probably base camp. So it's
18,000 feet. Everest is what, 7% maybe? Exactly, exactly. So we're talking about certain parts of
Bolivia, we're talking about Mont Blanc. Yeah, yeah. But my brother's been to base camp and he
did something really funny, which is something only my brother would do. He typed out a series of
questions for himself that at sea level, the answers to which are patently obvious, 10 questions,
and at 10,000 feet and 15,000 feet, and then at base camp is 18. And then I think when he was there,
they ended up not being able to cross the ice walls, but they could still get to like 21,000.
And then again, at 21,000 feet, he would video himself answering these questions. And it was
actually quite interesting, not just the huffing and puffing that invariably goes into it,
but the length of time it took him to think of the answers, which when you consider the fact that he
was answering the same questions and over and over again, it should have been the opposite. It
should have been easier and easier and easier to come up with what year did such and such happen
or whatever. That's no joke, right? I mean, that's still for many people quite a deficit. So how did
they improve? Earlier in the conversation, we're talking about this disease called Lee syndrome.
So we have a mouse model of Lee syndrome, it's actually due to a loss of one of the subunits of
complex one. So it's a recessive loss of one of the nuclear subunits of a complex one. And this mouse
is born looking okay, it's developmentally okay. But then right around day 3035, it starts looking
sick. And by day 55, it'll basically fulfill our hospitals euthanasia criteria, it's lost body weight,
it's become hypothermic, it's very, very sick. It has lesions on brain MRI. Is there anything in its
periphery that looks lesioned? Or is all of the insult to the brain? This initial cause of death
is probably brain driven. And if you look carefully, other tissues are affected as well. So that's what
happens at 21% oxygen, there's a very stereotyped trajectory. These uniformly fatal at about day 55
or day 60. If these mice are grown at 11%, instead of 21%, they now survive to about a median of one
year. Oh my god, so you've, you've restored them to half their normal lifespan. That's right. And
what's their function level? How do they interact? Are they do they act like normal mice up until
then? When we were doing these experiments, a very talented former graduate student, she's now
at UCSF and our lab manager over at MGH, they're doing these experiments. They actually thought
that there was a genotyping error because the mice looked so good. We actually thought that
we'd misgenotype them. And so they look they look great, they put on body weight, they put on body
temperature. So the results are striking. But again, I want to emphasize that this is all an
animal model still. If you're a parent who one day has a child born with this condition, to think
that the answer could be your child instead of living a few months could live into their 40s or
50s by moving to a part of the world, which would be the easiest way to accomplish this. I don't
think it would make sense to live at sea level and wear an oxygen deprivation mask for your entire
life. But if the answer is, guess what, you're going to go be a Sherpa. I mean, that's unbelievable to
think of. I mean, that's, I would not have predicted that at all based on what we've discussed, that
it could be that strong in effect. Well, what's interesting is in the past, people have actually
proposed hyperbaric oxygen as a way of rejuvenating that's what I would have stupidly suggested also,
which is, wait a minute, we got to try harder to get that oxygen in there. Let's go hyperbaric. So
have you done that in the mice? And did the mice die even faster under hyperbaric conditions? So we
didn't try hyperbaric because that's higher pressure, but we just tried hyperoxid. Okay.
So we went up to 55%, which is what is often given in the operating room as an example,
the mice will die within a few days of exposure to 55% oxygen. So there's something about how
to what about hyperbaric at 21%. We haven't tried, we haven't tried that yet. But just hyperoxic
at 55%. These mice will die within a few days of exposure. Peter, within a few days of us publishing
that paper, we actually got phone calls from across a country of cases where patients that
were on the outpatient had been placed in hyperbaric chambers, and then they actually ended up,
in some cases dying within 24 hours, or going blind in a good eye within 24 hours. And so
I think there's some anecdotes that suggest that super high oxygen levels on a broken
electron transport chain can be very damaging in humans as well. Well, this is sort of interesting,
right? Because on the cancer front, people have talked about hyperbaric oxygen being a very potent
tool, because the mitochondria of cancer cells are going to be defective on balance relative to
the non cancer cells. That's again, outside of your wheelhouse. But how do you think about
hyperbarics in terms of a tool to selectively target cancer mitochondria? We're super excited
about it. And in fact, we're really not a cancer biology lab, but there is a subset, a very, very
rare subset of tumors where we're currently exploring that idea. I think others have thought
about trying to starve cancers of their oxygen and glucose, our idea is the exact opposite,
maybe in certain instances, you want to flood them with oxygen. Do you have a sense of which
cancers in humans might be more or less susceptible to that pressure? We're looking into that now,
but it's going to be a rare subset of cancers where there may be some mitochondrial mutations
to begin with. So in other words, it might be less about the given histology and more. So,
you know, it's funny, I talked with Keith Flaherty recently, and this is a great example of targeted
therapy in cancer, right? Imagine you have your tumor, you get it sequenced and you realize,
oh, look, you have a tumor whose mitochondria are especially weak. You are a great candidate
for hyperbaric oxygen. Person B over here, the mitochondria in your cancer cell look perfectly
fine. Hyperbaric oxygen, if anything is not going to do, at best, it's going to do nothing. At
worst, it might actually harm your other cells. We've looked a little bit into this literature. We
have an oncologist in our laboratory that's looking in this direction and hyperbaric oxygen
has definitely been proposed as a cancer therapy in the past, but there have been mixed signals. And
exactly as you're saying, it may be the case that if you know how to precisely target it, maybe you'll
see a real signal. Anything else in your work have you thinking about cancer? This is a great example.
Is there anything else that you think about with respect to what you've learned and how it pertains
to cancer prevention or treatment? We had a series of projects about five, six years ago or so,
where some of the guys in the laboratory were looking at sort of omics data sets from large
numbers of cancers, just asking, what are the most consistently altered metabolic pathways in cancer?
So there's about 1500 metabolic enzymes encoded by the human genome. Which one is the most up
regulated or down regulated across all cancers? And that pan cancer analysis, it wasn't a
mitochondria focused analysis to be clear, but it revealed a few mitochondrial enzymes in the
folate pathway that are the most consistently upregulated enzymes across all cancers.
So the mitochondria is the powerhouse of the cell. It does produce ATP, but it's also a
biosynthetic machine as well. So there's a few pathways within the organelle that are designed
to produce one carbon units for growth, folates, things like that. That pathway was highly, highly
upregulated. It gave rise to the seductive idea that maybe mitochondria are not being used for
energy in cancer, but rather as biosynthetic machines for cancer. So that was an idea that,
we and others stumbled upon about five, six years ago or so, but it's not an active area of research
in our lab. Well, it's interesting because it's very consistent with other hypotheses that the
Warburg effect is less a deficit of the cancer cell due to defective mitochondria or inability
to undergo oxfoss. And maybe the Warburg effect is the result of a cancer cell wanting to get a higher
throughput of substrate to foster growth. Obviously, Matt Vanderheiden was the author on
a paper that talked about that in several years ago, about 2009. I hadn't heard the folate story,
so that's kind of yet another really interesting point. Single carbon biology is pretty interesting
stuff. That's right. That's right. And several investigators like Joshua Benowitz, David
Sabatini, our group. I had dinner with David last night. Great. Yeah, we actually were talking about
single carbon metabolism and the challenges of it. I went to med school with Josh, by the way.
Oh, wow. Yeah. Oh, wow. Okay. So actually, the three of us, about five, six years ago or so,
we all had sort of independently stumbled upon this mitochondrial pathway as being dramatically
upregulated. Josh with metabolomics, David with RNAI, us with computation. And I think to this
date, there's a lot of data that supports the idea that this is upregulated in cancers. Now,
whether targeting it is going to be beneficial, that's an open question still. But without a doubt,
this is one of the pathways that is powerfully upregulated in cancer states. On the topic of
cancer, and we've talked about these other chronic diseases, but it doesn't really appear that there
is a chronic disease in which the mitochondria remain normal. If you look at cancer, if you look
at Alzheimer's disease, if you look at atherosclerosis, and if you look at type 2 diabetes,
all of these diseases have mitochondrial signatures that differ from what we would
consider healthy. Well, it gets back to the opening parts of the discussion where we said that if you
take any age of tissue, it's going to be associated with dysfunctional mitochondria. And if you take
diabetic muscle, if you take Alzheimer's brain, Parkinson's brain, you're going to see dysfunctional
mitochondria. And this is why it gets back to, is it cause or effect? Or is it going to be some
complex nonlinear combination of cause and effect? And this is where using that systems biology
approach or trying to gain insights from these rare diseases may inform a subset, but not all of
these. I actually think that for Parkinson's, the causal hypothesis is pretty compelling out of all
of these disorders. Say more about that, because I don't know anything about Parkinson's that I
didn't learn in medical school, which if I recall is more to do with dopamine secretion out of a part
of the brain that the substantia nigra, is that it? Where you basically lose that. Those neurons.
Yeah. And so the patients that maybe start out with genetically fewer of those, because there's
a distribution of how many you get, maybe the ones most susceptible. I never thought of that as
a problem that shows up in the mitochondria. So expand on that. Again, we have two classes of
disorders, right? We have sort of common complex diseases and we have monogenic diseases. And the
big question is, does the pathology we see in the rare monogenic forms bear any relevance, right,
to the common forms of disease? It's funny. I mean, the way we're talking about it, your hands are
showing it in a way that I think is, is representative, right? You had your one hand out over here and
you said, look, these are the very simple monogenic diseases. Most people have never heard of them.
They're typically quite brutal, but they kill relatively few people. On the other hand, you have,
there's a divide, right? That's right. And it's quite discontinuous, isn't it? Well, also on this
side, the prevalence of these monogenic mitochondrial disorders is about one in 4,000. But then as you
cross the continuum- The prevalence is one. One in one. Yeah, exactly. And then you have these other
disorders like type two diabetes and Parkinson's and Alzheimer's that it's not one in one, but it's
also not one in 4,000. So you're saying Parkinson's may be the closest example that you can think of
that's spanning these two worlds? I think so. Okay, I want to hear more about this. Well, I think
there's a couple of reasons. One is if you take the common form of Parkinson's disease and if you
take some of the post-mortem material, the biopsy that, or if you take post-mortem material and you
look, you let you see mitochondrial lesions, you'll see an increase in the mutation burden
in the mitochondrial genome, you'll see complex one deficiency. Already we're seeing some of the
molecular features of mitochondrial dysfunction, but perhaps even more compelling is that there
are some toxin forms of Parkinson's. Certain types of herbicides and insecticides are actually toxic
to complex one. So you're saying there are people who have Parkinson's, and I apologize for my
ignorance on this, where they don't actually have a dopamine deficiency in the brain, but they have
a Parkinson's-like phenotype purely from an insult to their mitochondria from, say, a toxin?
Right, so in these instances what we think has happened is that because of an environmental
pesticide or insecticide, the mitochondria has been poisoned in some of these dopaminergic
neurons and those neurons actually die. So there is a dopamine loss ultimately. I see, I see, okay.
But the root cause is the toxin. The mitochondria, okay. That's right, that's right. So that's toxin
evidence where we know that a direct toxin to the mitochondria in humans can give rise to a
Parkinsonian-like disease. In mouse models, if you give a high dose of rhododenone, it's a complex
one poison. Okay. And this actually gets back to metformin. Exactly. So if you infuse into a mouse
rhododenone, which is a very potent. More potent than fenformin. Yes, right. And there's some
potential off-target effects as well. Like micromolar or millimolar potency? Micromolar potency.
It may hit other things like microtubules as well, but it definitely hits complex one of the electron
transport chain. That's been used as a model of Parkinson's disease in rats and in mice. And so
I think between the toxin evidence, the fact that sporadic forms of Parkinson's disease can be
associated with complex one deficiency or mitochondrial mutations, I think helps to support
the idea that mitochondrial dysfunction can play maybe in the causal path for Parkinson's disease.
Are you optimistic that we are going to be able to target mitochondrial proteins
as therapies? I mean, the more I listen to this, the less optimistic I am truthfully, just because of
the exceptions being exceptions and not rules. I'm actually pretty wildly optimistic. Okay,
that's great because I'm coming away like discouraged. Like there are too many moving pieces
to be able to use a single molecule. So are you thinking of stacking molecules or tell me where
your optimism comes from? Well, it comes from the fact that five years ago in some of these
mouse models or cellular models, we had zero ways of alleviating mitochondrial disease in a dish or
in a mouse. Now we have in our laboratory, we can use again in a preclinical way, we can use
hypoxia and it actually helps to restore cellular function and longevity and health span in mouse
models of my to disease. We're using other approaches that are evolutionarily inspired.
We call these protein prostheses where we take proteins from other organisms from other
kingdoms of life, we transplant them into human cells with mitochondrial disease, and we can
effectively rescue the cells. And so how do you how do you transfect all the cells? Are you just
saying that you can just you're just you're doing this ex vivo? This is all ex vivo right now, right?
But still, it's a proof of concept that's very powerful. I mean, nowadays we have nucleic acid
therapeutics, gene therapeutics, protein therapeutics. So give me an example of one of the protein
prosthetics. Getting back to the earlier part of the conversation, we spoke about the fact that
the electron transport chain was probably one of the earliest features of the early eukaryotes,
probably resembling the electron transport chain of bacteria that can do oxidative phosphorylation.
But then during reductive evolution, certain organisms lost parts of their electron transport
chain. Now there are certain organisms that have lost their entire electron transport chain. And we
think that one of the ways that they're able to survive is that they gained a new protein
that basically complements part of the activity of the electron transport chain.
So we've identified some of those proteins. If we place those proteins in a human cell,
you can poison the mitochondria any of five different ways. The cell will still proliferate
because it has that protein that evolutionarily, we believe, allowed that organism to lose its
etc to begin with. Does that make sense? Yeah, it just seems too good to be true.
Well, this is why we call it a prosthesis. It's not 100% fix of the solution. What it does is
it probably corrects part of the redox imbalance in the electron transport chain, but not the full
proton pumping capabilities. Yeah, so play this forward. You now could argue another treatment
for type 2 diabetes is in addition to making the changes we're going to make, right? Because I still
believe deep down that you can cure type 2 diabetes with corrective exercise and nutrition
and sleep. I think if you get those three things fully optimized, type 2 diabetes goes away with
the exception of the late stage cases where the pancreas no longer works. But what if you could
add another layer to that, which is, oh, by the way, here's some mitochondrial prostheses.
That's exactly right. It's not going to fix all of the functions in electron transport.
But it can become additive to other things, right? That's right. That's right. That's one of
the ideas that we're exploring right now. Can we actually in the context of things like fatty
liver and diabetes, can we use some of these mitochondrial protein prostheses to either
augment or bypass some of the broken functions of mitochondria to restore function?
I don't know if you've ever thought of this because the idea just popped into my head when
you said mitochondrial protein prostheses. Have you ever thought just in sort of random sci-fi
like thinking of the opposite, which is performance enhancing prostheses for
mitochondria? I mean, if you think about the efforts that athletes can go to to enhance
aerobic performance, the most obvious of these, of course, is blood doping and use of EPO,
which simply deliver more oxygen to the system. But in 30 years, will people be talking about
genetic cheating where mitochondrial performance and function has been enhanced?
Well, it's funny because the sports industry is so often, I mean, the sort of underground illicit
sports world of doping often is so ahead of the medical world. It's actually pretty amazing.
Yeah, it really is.
I mean, one of the compounds, it's like EPO, it's called FG4592. It's a small molecule that
blocks one of the prolyl hydroxylases. This tricks the system into thinking that it's hypoxic and you
end up producing more EPO. That drug was in clinical trials. And before the drug was even approved,
it was being used by cyclists, which is already amazing. But what's also even more amazing is that
the anti-doping agency knew to look for drugs that were not yet even approved by the FDA in some of
these athletes. And so it's like this red queen where everyone has to stay ahead of everybody else.
It's an arms race. Do you think like theoretically there are ways to enhance performance through,
again, I'm not a huge advocate on genetic engineering. I still think there's so much sci-fi
and the limitations of actually getting a virus that could be taken up your victim's way. But
putting that aside for a moment, could you engineer a better mitochondria? Could one,
I mean, I don't want to put you on the spot, but could one engineer an even better mitochondria?
How much waste is in the system? It's funny, I haven't, if I ever did this exercise, it's so
long ago that I don't recall. But from an engineering perspective, how much room for improvement is there?
I think it's going to take a while before things like that are possible. And I gather from this
conversation that you, like me, like automobiles. And so if you have an engine, the way to enhance
it is to turbo charge it. But turbo charging it is not taking one spark plug out and replacing it
with another spark plug. No, it's changing the way air flows through it and is recycled.
So you have like 17 different things. You have a turbo charger, you put it on top, but there's
like 17 other things that you have to alter so that the entire system connects up. You have
impedance matching, you have airflow matching, so that in the end you have a better performing
automobile. I think something analogous applies to mitochondria. It's not going to be just one
thing that you can turn on. If you want to try to, the system is already pretty optimized, right?
And so if you just change one thing, it's probably not going to, you can break it.
Yeah, you can break it with one thing, but it's hard to enhance with one thing.
That's actually a great way to just think about biology in general. It's pretty easy to break it
at a single point. Cyanide, I think the most extreme example, right? Detrototoxin, so easy
to kill and break at a single molecule, which comes back to a point I made earlier.
It's mind boggling when something like rapamycin works.
Right. Again, I don't, I mean, you had dinner with David last night, so he's clearly one of
the world's authorities on rapamycin and its function, but at least if we go to metformin,
the only way that I can conceive that it could have this total body impact is if it's doing
something that then causes the entire system to respond. Even when we talk about statins,
every medical student in the country knows that statins are life saving. Every single
medical student in the country knows that statins hit HMG-CoA reductase. But why is it life saving?
Is that enough? Right. Is there other things that it's doing that are also important beyond
the reduction of LDL? The way that statins work, my understanding is that sure, statins directly
target HMG-CoA reductase, but then what ends up happening is because you're not producing so
much sterols, you turn on an entire SREBP transcriptional program.
And you bring more receptors to the surface of the liver. That's right. More of the statin
efficacy is due to the LDL clearance than the reduction of cholesterol synthesis.
That's exactly right. But there may even be benefits beyond that is my point. In some argue,
there are actually a whole camp of LDL denialists who can't deny the efficacy of the drug,
and so the hypothesis is, well, all of the statin benefit doesn't come through the LDL reduction
through the mechanism you described. The unintended consequence is the wrong way of saying it,
but the non-obvious consequence, but it could be some of the anti-inflammatory benefits that come
from it or the endothelial protective benefits. But the point is that there's an entire response
to hitting HMG-CoA reductase, and a consequence of that program is that you have more sterile
production. So in the end, the amount of cholesterol that you're producing is kind of
balanced, right? You've inhibited it, but you've turned on more of the enzymes, so it's comparable,
but you've turned on these other 17 switches as well at the same time, one of which is the LDL
receptor, which helps to clear LDL levels. There may be other things as well that are turned on
that are net beneficial. So I think physiological systems are so complicated, trying to identify all
17 of those things and turning them on at the same time in general, I think is going to be hard
even in the next 30 years, but it may be the case that some of the interventions are, you know,
what people refer to. Do you think of this as when you, like, let's look at the three examples you've
just used. Estatin, metformin, and rapamycin. None of those are, I mean, they're synthesized today,
but they are all derivatives of naturally occurring compounds. I'm sitting here as you're
telling this story, trying to think of examples of purely synthesized de novo molecules that have
such benefit, and I'm, there may be examples, but it seems less obvious. Do you think it's a
coincidence that some of the most potent agents that we have in medicine, which by definition,
it seems, are the ones that have to do multi-pronged inputs tend to come from naturally
occurring substances? Does that just speak to our co-evolution with these things?
No, absolutely. I think there's been this arms race, right? The bacteria are fighting these fungi,
and the fungi are fighting these plants, and so there's all sorts of small molecules that are
designed to throw a wrenches into other mitochondria or translational programs or nutrient sensing
programs. So natural products are remarkable chemistries, and they've evolved over hundreds
of millions of years to target physiological systems, and so I'm a huge fan of natural products
and the biology that they expose. This is so interesting. We'll close with a question that's
admittedly kind of a tough question, so I apologize for putting you on the spot, and no qualms if you
can't come up with a good or great answer, but when you think about the world you want to explore
here with the questions that you want to ask. So much of what happens even at the level that
you're at is still constrained by resources. Have you ever had the thought experiment or the sort
of fantasy of what if you were in a totally resource unconstrained world? So you never had
to apply for another grant. In fact, you were given some lump sum of money that was beyond what you
could imagine, and even just from an IRB standpoint, there was nothing that stood in your way of doing
kind of something that was still ethical, but maybe today would be logistically too challenging.
Do you have a sense of what questions you would want to probe, but specifically what experiment
or set of experiments you would do in this dream state? It's a tough question. It sounds like you're
basically asking me not to be limited by anything except my own imagination, and I think so often in
biomedical research that is what limits us, but it's a great question Peter. One experiment that
would be kind of a fun experiment to try is really motivated by our recent work on oxygen.
So what we've observed is that at least in preclinical models when you have severe
mitochondrial decline, breathing thinner air appears to be beneficial. Now how about in
the common form of aging when there's a subtle decline in mitochondrial activity?
Is there excess unused oxygen and will breathing thinner air be beneficial?
And given that I'm not resource limited, I mean wouldn't it be cool if we could construct a Ritz-Carlton
hotel or condominium at 16,000 feet. That's extremely comfortable and perhaps another Ritz-Carlton
that looks identical at the plains, and we could take a very large cohort, not five, not 10, but
thousands of people that live at either the plains or at the high altitude for many, many months,
and we try to evaluate whether there are any biomarkers of aging age-associated disorders
that actually improve under thin air. Maybe they become worse under thin air, but it would be
something like a crossover experiment that would allow us to test the idea that thin air may be
beneficial for chronic diseases. I love that idea. That is elegant because one, you could do that. You
answer the question, right, which is in a resource unconstrained world, like that's tens of millions
of dollars would allow you to do that. Call it, you know, hundreds of millions of dollars could do
that longitudinally, and your intervention is elegant in that it is, it's going to touch lots
of things. That's interesting. So 16,000 feet. So following up on that, have you done or contemplated
doing the less beautiful version of that in mice where, or I'm sort of disdainful of mice,
but maybe rats or something that's less inbred where you have models of type 2 diabetes,
but they're genetically born with normal mitochondria. Has that experiment been done?
We're doing those types of experiments now in, of course, our focus is on some of these rare
genetic mitochondrial diseases, but we're going into some of these other conditions,
more common conditions that are also associated with mitochondrial dysfunction. So those are
currently ongoing. When we get back to that dream experiment, what is interesting, Peter, is
experiments like that have actually taken place in humans and they can be
They're natural experiments.
And one of the experiments, there's this one paper from the early 1970s
that was published by the Indian Army. It was the Indian Army reporting on the health outcomes of
a huge number of their troops who India has historically had border disputes with China.
I think it was in the 1960s, India deployed more than 100,000 troops on the Indochina border.
And don't quote me on the numbers, but about 25,000 of these people were at extremely high
altitude and another 100,000 or so were at the plains. They were there for about five to seven
years or so. And of course, the food that they ate, the temperature, the activity, all of these
were different between low and high altitudes. But one of the variables that was different was
oxygen. And after, I think it was seven years, the Indian Army actually wrote this paper. It's only
been cited a few, like maybe 20 times or so. They reported the long term health consequences. And
what they showed is that death from things like infections were much higher acutely upon going to
high altitude. But if you look at chronic diseases like incidence of diabetes, stroke, cardiovascular
disease, they were much reduced in the high altitude arm. Even after they returned to the plains? I
think for only as long as they stayed at the only only as long as they stayed in the altitude. I
don't think they had long term follow up actually. But it's this type of data that actually makes me
wonder whether what we're observing in some of these rare forms of mitral dysfunction and the
interaction of mitochondrial oxygen, perhaps some of it could bear relevance to more common conditions
as well. Super interesting. That can keep going on, but I've been generous with your time, especially
to a total stranger. This is really helpful. I want to thank you for the work you're doing. And
I want to thank you for taking the time to explain it to me and to a few people listening.
Thank you so much. This has been a lot of fun for me.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-laying
once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social, you can
find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is
the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the
practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the
givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical
condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such
conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously.
For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.