Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast. If you're listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things
I care most about professionally are how to live longer and how to live better. I have
a complete fascination and obsession with this topic. I practice it professionally and
I've seen firsthand how access to information is basically all people need to make better
decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating and sharing this knowledge
is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to me. The sheer
volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a great
team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one example,
our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a
natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As
you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot
of contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now, the
first and most important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you can trust me if I'm
telling you about something when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it
to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I
just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not absolutely
nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others
have proved can work over time, and that is to create a subscriber model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available
for free. It's that simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose
to support us at, you will get back more than you give. So for example, members will receive
full access to the exclusive show notes, including other things that we plan to build upon. These
are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of our shows.
Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me Anything
episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to hear
these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as
I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with
companies who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and
have them pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope
is that many of you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional
content exclusive for members. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen to this. If you
learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us directly
by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Dan Harris. For those
unfamiliar with Dan, he wrote the New York Times bestselling book, 10% Happier. He also hosts the
10% Happier podcast, which I've appeared on, and is the co-founder of the 10% Happier meditation app,
which by the end of this podcast, there will be no ambiguity about how much I love that app. In
addition to everything 10% Happier, Dan is also the co-host of weekend edition of Good Morning
America, and up until quite recently was the co-anchor of Nightline. I met Dan through a very
close friend of mine, and this is one of those times when I specifically just begged my friend
to make the introduction. I read 10% Happier almost the minute it came out in 2014, immediately
became a fan, and somehow I have spent the last five years stalking him, trying to figure out how
to get to know him, and eventually a friend of mine made the introduction. I talk a little bit
about that in the podcast about how much his work has had a profound impact on me, and just how
grateful I am for all that his journey into meditation has brought me. In this episode,
we talk about a lot of things. We do go into his story in a bit more detail about his upbringing,
and pretty quickly we get into the story of the breakdown meltdown slash crisis he had on
national TV in 2004 that ultimately began his journey that culminated four or five years later
with his discovery of meditation. What I really like about this episode truthfully is we get
into a lot of stuff that I've always wanted to talk about with Dan, and it's the exact stuff we
would have talked about over dinner. The fact that we got to have it in a podcast is exactly why I
have a podcast. I hope that you will find this discussion half as interesting as I did, and I
hope that for those of you who have not yet taken an interest in meditation, that maybe the topics
that we discuss here become the thin end of the wedge that at least get you to start exploring
a tool that I believe is one of the most important tools in the longevity toolkit. Without further
delay, please enjoy my discussion with Dan Harris. Before we start the podcast, I want to just make a
special announcement. As you're about to hear in this podcast with Dan, I'm a user and enormous
believer promoter of the 10% happier app for meditating. This is something that Dan and his
team have been working on for several years. I've been using it for nearly two years. I think it is
simply a remarkable tool, and I recommend this app and one other app, Sam Harris's app waking up to
any one of my patients who is finally willing to take the plunge and try mindfulness meditation.
Now, one of the things we wanted to do at the time of the release of this podcast was work with the
team at 10% happier to do a special subscriber discount code that's going to go along with the
podcast release. They were kind enough to do this at an unbelievable amazing discount, which is
available for only one week until September 30th. Now, they've also provided us with an ongoing
discount that will go on beyond September 30th. It's just not as much of a discount though. I still
think it's actually a pretty impressive discount. So if you're thinking about using this app or after
this podcast, you're thinking, hmm, you know, maybe I'll give this a try. This would be a great time to
sign up to become one of our subscribers. If you're already a subscriber, you can visit us at
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash members, where you can take advantage of the discount. And if you're
not a subscriber and you want to access this code as well as all of our other subscriber only
benefits, you can visit us at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. As a reminder, we are not
taking any money to promote, sell, or have any endorsement of 10% happier. We are doing this
solely because I believe in this product. I love this product. And rather than have this company
or other companies pay us to advertise, we say take the money you would have paid us to advertise
and please pass that discount on to our subscribers. So thanks for listening. I hope you enjoy my
interview with Dan Harris. Thank you so much for making time on no less a Saturday morning to sit
here and talk with Well, I'm at work anyway on Saturday. But anyway, it's a pleasure. And this
is cool to be doing it in an awesome studio like this. I feel like there's some pretty cool stuff
that's probably happened in this area room. Yeah, I mean, you we are sitting on the second
floor of the ABC News headquarters and down the hall is where the late great Peter Jennings used
to work. I've had some traumatic moments on the floor. And I can't wait to dig into some of those.
He's definitely one of the most handsome people I've ever seen. He's a handsome dude. This is a
general statement of handsomeness. 007. Yeah. Well, I've wanted to have you on this podcast for
such a long time. I've wanted to meet you for a really long time, probably about from the day I
finished reading your book, which would have been a little over five years ago. I read your book
because I read your book as soon as it came out. In fact, I preordered it. And as I've probably
alluded to a little bit on the podcast before, it's really your book that was the first thing
that ever cracked the veneer of meditation is irrelevant. You know, that that sort of ethos.
And your book is really almost single handedly responsible for my interest in meditation. And
in some ways for where I find myself today, which is in a much better place than I was then. So I'd
like to almost just start with that the title of the book, 10% happier. I think it's just such a
beautiful title because it doesn't over promise. And it's just such a glib cute thing. And what was
the alternative title? The voice in my head is an asshole. Which is just as good, probably a little
bit better technically as a title, rather than just make you tell the whole story of the book,
take me back to the moment that started it. You've talked about this and I know you're tired
of talking about it, I'm sure, but maybe one more time. What was the moment when you realized all was
not well in Dan Harris land? I've come to terms with the fact that I'm going to tell this story a
million times. So don't feel sheepish. The inciting event of the book, to put it in Hollywood terms,
was a panic attack. Not in this building. But at our studio in Times Square, where we do Good
Morning America every morning. It was 2004. Warm June morning, I was filling in for Robin Roberts,
who was at that time, the news reader on the show news reader. We don't have this position anymore,
but it's the person who comes on at the top of each hour and reads off a bunch of headlines.
They've done a few big stories at this point. And they'll say, hey, you know, there are a few other
headlines bubbling. Let's get it over to Robin Roberts, or Dan Harris, who's filling in for
Robin Roberts, take it away. So I had done this a bunch of times. I was in a phase at this point
where I was filling in for Robin and also the main host of the show, Charlie Gibson, quite a bit.
They were giving me a shot. And for reasons I don't fully understand why it happened this morning,
I was a couple seconds into my shtick. I was going to read six, what they call voiceovers off
of the teleprompter that was 20 feet in front of me. So voiceover is I'm talking to the camera,
but they roll video over what I'm saying. And a few seconds in, I just lost the ability to breathe.
My palms were sweaty. My heart was racing. My lungs seized up. I just couldn't talk. My mind
was racing. And the more my body freaked out, the more my mind freaked out. And the more my mind
freaked out, the more my body freaked out. And I had to do something I'd never done before,
which was just quit right in the middle of the whole thing. And this is live. This is live. I
later found out that the audience was 5.019 million. And it was just terrible. I lied to the people
around me when they asked what had gone wrong. I said, I don't know. It's fine. And I was able to
come on an hour later and do another bit. So and if you look at it, it has a tons if you just Google
panic attack on live television, it's the first result. It has millions of hits. If you look at
it, it actually doesn't look that bad. I'll just say something about that. If you've ever had a
panic or high anxiety, it will actually it's a little triggering for those people. If you haven't
a response I hear from many people is, you know, it didn't look that bad, which is true. And the
reason if I recall, it was you were reading about either a new statin or a new drug. I recall.
Yes. It's been so long since I've seen it because I don't think I saw it. I watched it when the book
came out. Yeah. I was like, Oh, I wonder what he's talking about. And I don't have seen it in five
years. Yes. Well, no reason to go back to it. Unless you're me. If I hadn't had the luxury of
tossing it the baton back to the main host, then it would have been truly epic. Because I was unable
to speak. I would have had to rip the mic off and run away. But I was able to get out the words back
to Charlie and I and actually said back to Charlie and Robin when it was actually Charlie and Diane
Sawyer. That's safe. Really, it doesn't matter because it's not this isn't about the panic attack.
Yeah, it's not about what it's about what led to the exactly so even more embarrassing than the
panic attack, what caused it, which is that I had spent a lot of time in war zones. After 9 11, very
ambitious guy, and very idealistic. And I want to say fearless, but in the pejorative. I didn't
really think much about what the consequences of going overseas would be. And so I was in Afghanistan
a bunch of times Pakistan, Israel, the West Bank, Gaza, made a couple of trips to Iraq that all added
up to about six months, which spans the pre invasion, invasion, and then all the way up until the
insurgency started really cooking. And I came home in this period of time and I got depressed. And I
didn't actually know I was depressed. I was having trouble getting out of bed and I felt sick a lot.
But I didn't know I was depressed. A friend I was at one night going out to a party and a buddy of mine
offered me some cocaine. And I'd never I'd smoked weed and drank. Not really even to excess. But I'd
never had hard drugs. I was always really afraid of them. But because I was feeling like shit, I don't
know why I said yes, that night. And the cocaine made me feel better. Just like took it away. In
hindsight, I think it's pretty obvious I was depressed from coming home from the war zones,
not because I was traumatized, but because I missed the action. I liked it. And I was in withdrawal
from the adrenaline. And the cocaine was a synthetic squirt of that adrenaline. And it made
me feel better. Obviously didn't last that long, which is a hard lesson every coke user has to
learn. And if you haven't used coke, I recommend you don't. Well, how does that relate to the panic
attack? After I freaked out, actually happened to me twice. I went to a doctor here in New York
City who's an expert in panic. He asked me a bunch of questions. One of the questions was, do you do
drugs? Which at this point, you're thinking that would never even register as a potential college.
I even know I make this joke all the time was when I said, yeah, I do drugs. He gave me a look. And
the look communicated the sentiment of okay, asshole, mystery solved. I wasn't a heavy cocaine
user. I was intermittent. It was only on the weekends. I wasn't high one on the air or anything
like that. It was just I partied once in a while. He was like, that's enough to change your brain
chemistry and make it more likely for you to have a panic attack. So that was a big aha moment. And I
quit doing drugs, started seeing him frequently. And that was really the beginning of me making a
change. And I want to talk so much about what came of that. But I also want to kind of dig into a
little bit of what got you here because I think there are a lot of people out there. I mean, I've
had patients who have done a lot of cocaine or have done some cocaine. And, you know, many of them
still don't experience what you experience. It may not be in life, Talib. That's right. They may not
have the same provocation or the same stress that can produce that phenotype. But I want to kind of
go back to something that's maybe even at the root of all of that, which was what was the void,
maybe is the wrong word, but what was the itch you were trying to scratch? What was the rush that you
needed throughout your life? I mean, you I could never do what you do. Let's start with that, right?
Like, I could never put myself out the way someone in your position puts themselves out. It's kind of
an amazing thing that you can talk to so many people every night, you know, like, every day or get your
start in this whole space of news. So in college, I remember you writing about how you, you know,
you worked at a local news station, right? You get this big break to come to ABC. You're getting a
dopamine hit every time you do something good, right? Do you have a sense of what that dopamine hit
was numbing? Because I do think that on some level, cocaine, perfectionism, performance, sex,
all of these things can numb. Have you ever read the book by Gabor Matei in the Realm of Hungry Ghosts?
I haven't, but I the Hungry Ghost is something I think a lot about. It's an ancient Buddhist idea.
Yeah, I believe that's where he borrowed the title for the book. And as you can imagine,
he writes a book about addiction. But what I love so much about the book is he does a great job of
making the case. He's a psychiatrist, and he mostly treats patients who are, you know, on skid row in
Vancouver. So usually opiate addicted. But you read the book and you come away realizing, wait a second,
you could be a high flying news anchor, you could be a, you know, Wall Street tycoon. You're an addict,
too. So the person on skid row, for them, the opiate or whatever drug of choice is lighting
something up in their cortex. It's a pleasure center. But you can get that from so many different
things. So I guess what I'm getting at in a long winded way is, when do you think your addiction or
your junkie ism started? Was your career choice in any way driven by that, which I would think for
most of us on some level it is? Yeah, I have been trying to think about this quite a bit recently,
because I don't think I've really satisfactorily answered it in 10% happier. I don't think that was
really the point. Maybe I should have and or maybe I shouldn't have I don't know, either way set it aside.
Just one point that's sort of adjacent. When you talked about Gabor Maté's work, I have a friend,
Dr. Judson Brewer, who actually might be a good guest for you. He's a neuroscientist, formerly
of Yale now at Brown. He's one of the lead neuroscientists in the fascinating push to figure
out what meditation does to the brain. But Jud is also an expert in addiction, and he actually treats
people clinically. He wrote a book published by Yale University Press called The Craving Mind,
but his initial title was, We're All Addicted. So it really goes to the fact that you don't have
addiction. These are my words, not his. And I don't know if he would have blessed them. But
what I take from what he's saying is addiction is a spectrum. You may think you're not an addict
because you don't have a needle hanging out of your arm, but that needle hanging out of your arm
is just the extreme end of the spectrum. But we're all addicted to lots of things. What's your
relationship with your phone? What's your relationship with professional success? What's your
relationship with sex, shopping, gambling, drinking? We are rats in a maze, and we go where the pellets
are. Yeah. And for the first time ever when I read Mathe's book, which I think I read in 2016 or 2017,
there was a moment in when I realized those of us with the socially acceptable addictions
actually have a disadvantage. If there's one advantage to having a needle in your arm,
at least everybody realizes it's wrong and you're more likely to do something about it. But if you're
a perfectionist, if you're a workaholic, you're getting a lot of attaboys before someone comes
along and says, let's examine your relationship with this thing. That's an excellent point.
So what drives me? What makes Sammy run? You know that book? There was a moment when I was a kid,
my parents were both academic physicians. And very prominent. I mean, your mom especially.
Yeah. My mom was one of the editors at the New England Journal of Medicine. She's just about to
retire. My dad was chief of radiation oncology at the Brigham and Women's. I'm one of the pioneers
in radiation therapy. But academic medicine doesn't pay that well. And we lived in Newton,
Massachusetts. And I was really keenly aware of the fact that we were much poorer than a lot of
the kids that I went to school with. My dad drove like a shit brown Plymouth Valiant and my mother,
a very bland Chevy Chevrolet or something like that. And we had a nice house, but it wasn't that
nice vinyl siding. And yet I knew one of my friends lived a couple doors down from
Subner Redstone. And interestingly, I also had a lot of, Newton's a pretty big city. So I also had
a lot of friends who lived in public housing. But it was the rich people that kind of got in my head.
And I felt insecure about that. I also remember during this period, my parents somehow took us on
a trip to Europe. And it was all paid for because they were going to give a few talks, lectures at
various institutions around Europe. But we were also going to turn a lot of it into vacation.
Most of the time we stayed in like not very nice places. But when we went to Paris, we stayed at a
really fancy hotel that whatever local institution they were speaking at put us up at. It's called
the Hotel Regina. And it was really fancy. And it was the first time I'd ever been to a really fancy
hotel. How old were you? I think 10 or 11. And I remember thinking, this is how I'm going to live.
I'm not going to live like the Schmucks, who didn't keep the heat on in the winter. You know,
we all had to wear like down vests around the house because they were so intent. They're so flinty.
They were so intent on saving money. And I think there was something in I don't want to say it's
not as simple as just saying it was the Hotel Regina that did it. But that to me seems like a
defining moment. The other thing I think that's going on that only really started to get clarity
on recently is I have an executive coach who I actually mentioned to you. Yeah, I mentioned to
you when you came on my podcast. This guy's name is Jerry Colonna. And Jerry is an executive coach,
but he's not interested in productivity hacks, or how to get your next promotion or how to manage
your inbox. He is really interested in like what's your what are the primordial wounds in your life?
What's your five year old logic that is happening in the backdrop of your adult life and many ways
controlling you like a malevolent puppeteer, but that you don't have visibility on. He tries to
help you see sort of like what are these characters in your head that are that have so much power over
you, especially when you don't see them. And he often talks about the fact that as a young person,
there are three primary needs we have love, safety, and belonging. And when I first heard him say that,
I said, well, that's that's bullshit. I don't mean that's pretty much my reflexive reflexive response
to anything. You're a healthy skeptic. Yes, I'm a healthy. No, I'm a well, I'm a skeptic. Sometimes
it's healthy. Anyway, so he's talked about love, safety, and belonging. And I don't know, Jerry's
got a way that sometimes I have to reject his first foray for a while before I accept it. But
over time, I started to realize that safety is actually something really important for me.
There is such a thing as intergenerational trauma. My great grandparents escaped the Cossacks.
Another great grandfather lost his family's meager fortune and put his head in the oven and killed
himself in the family kitchen. Lots of alcoholism, depression, poverty, fortunes lost and made and
lost in my family tree. You know, my dad's an inveterate worrier. So is my mother really,
if I'm being honest, I think that the desire for I never felt unsafe in the home. But I think the
world has always felt unsafe to me. And having been raised during the Cold War, which freaked
me out so much that I had to go see a shrink when I was a little kid. I think part of the drive is
the self protection. You mentioned one of your grandparents who had a pretty impressive temper
was that a grandfather? Yeah, Robert Johnson. So my maternal grandfather, he was raised in some like
shitty farm in upstate New York by an abusive really abusive father.
Was smart, though, when I got to got into Middlebury, and then got married a girl at Middlebury.
And it was smart enough to get into Stanford to do a graduate degree in history. He was going to
become a history professor. But he had a kid, my mother. And then he had another and another
and another ultimately five. And they didn't have housing for kids at Stanford and he couldn't
afford to go otherwise. And basically live the rest of his life. In business. Yes, not only them,
but the world he became a middle manager at the Yellow Pages. Remember what the yellow pages were
they said the big Bible of telephone numbers that used to show up on our doorstep once a year.
And he was part of the part of that team, but not a particularly successful part of that team,
really embittered and took it out as kids and was a bully with them slapped them in the face,
figured out what their weaknesses were and exploited them in public. And I remember when
I was a little kid, he came in one day, I came to his house and he took me into his living room to
show me his VCR and said, if you touch this, I'll break your arm. Like that kind of guy.
Fascinatingly in his eighties, he became very nice. He got a computer and he was really into
Twitter and email and he would email all of his grandchildren. And so this big radical change came
over him later in his life. Did you ever get to talk to him about what precipitated the change?
No, I didn't dare. So he's still alive? He is not alive. I don't know how he would have taken that
question. Didn't strike me as something that would be safe to ask.
Have you ever talked with your mom about him and his impact on her life and maybe what she's
transmitted of that to her kids, either directly or indirectly through trying to avoid patterns?
She definitely, I think both of my parents tried to, my dad's parents were quite kind,
but they had flaws of their own. I think both of my parents had this idea that they were not going
to repeat the mistakes their parents had made. And they were really good parents. But recently,
I've been talking to my mother more about her relationship to her father because I'm writing
a book about compassion and kindness, which are two words that most men don't want to talk about
much. And they're just kind of, to my ears, kind of, I'm almost slightly embarrassed to have them
past my lips. But I think there's going to be a way to talk about this stuff that can be more
attractive and aspirational because we clearly need it. And we need it as human beings, we need
it as a culture. For me, it's important to understand my mother's relationship to this guy
because I see so much of him and me. So I got to reckon with it. You have a brother and a sister?
Or just a brother? Just a brother. Yeah. Did any of that get transmitted to him in the same way?
Do you feel, does your brother have, feel that he has some of his grandfather in him?
I don't think so. My brother's a pretty menchy guy. He's just widely beloved. He's a pretty
prominent venture capitalist. And within that community, which I now know better as a startup
co-founder, his reputation is just, people really like him. He's got a wide, wide circle of friends
and is very, just kind of relaxed and affable. My wife has referred to him as the nice Harris.
So I don't see, he's got his own stuff. For sure. We all have stuff. It's not the kind of stern,
authoritarian vibe that I can emit. So I want to come back to the story, but I want to
sort of go off on one little tangent for a moment. You said that the words kindness and compassion,
you almost feel a little uneasy when they pass your lips. Or you said something to that effect.
Why is that? Because I think this, the words are encrusted in so much cultural stuff, like cliche.
I don't know that we found a great way to talk about kindness and compassion. It's Hallmarky,
ooey gooey, meaningless cliche, or it's bland, dogmatic, exhortation, figure wagging,
God is watching type of stuff. It's not often sold to us the way it can actually be sold to us,
which is in terms of our own self-interest. There's a lot of evidence that shows that
people who are compassionate are happier, healthier, more successful, more popular.
And it feels good on a moment to moment basis. It feels good. We are wired to get
feel good chemicals released into our brain when we're good to other people. Just by way of an
example, what does it feel like when you hold the door open for somebody? If you're mindful in that
moment, if you're awake, that feels good. Well, that is infinitely scalable. Not to the point
where you have to be an idiot or be a doorman, which I love my doorman, they're definitely not
idiots, but they can do that job, which is great. I'm glad they do it, but they could do lots of
other jobs. The point isn't the holding of the door. The point is that you can. My meditation
teacher has a great little rule that I've been trying to operationalize, which is if he notices
the impulse to give something a rise, he does it. So how many times during the days the impulse to
like, maybe I could compliment somebody on her shoes or his shoes, but you don't do it for one
reason or another. Or you know, you should send that note to that person just to say they did a
great job on something or walking down the street and you know you got two bucks in your pocket,
but you don't really want to make eye contact with a person standing outside of Starbucks asking
for money. No, actually, just do the giving. Why? Not because you're rah, rah, just trying to make
the world a better place, man. Do it because it feels good for you. And by the way, yes, it will
make the world a better place in lots of unpredictable ways. But my sales pitch here is that,
and I wrote a chapter about this in 10% Happier called the self-interested case for not being a
dick. And that's just a jokey way of putting it because it's me struggling with how to talk about
this incredibly important subject in a way that avoids all of the cliches that have made it so
meaningless to so many people. We all kind of vaguely want to be nice or we think we're good
people. We've thought about it. We certainly want other people to be nicer, but I don't know.
There's only one self-help book that I can think of that's been successful about compassion. And
that book does not advertise compassion on its cover. The book is called How to Win Friends and
Influence People. And if you read it, which I happened to recently do, it's actually a book
about compassion that's been kind of inspirational for me and thinking about like, how can you find a
way to talk about these things in a way that people will actually listen? You know, it's so
funny you bring this up because just by total coincidence, I think yesterday, the meditation
I did in your app. So for the listeners, if you haven't figured it out by now, which means you
haven't been listening to my podcast, which is fine. I still forgive you. But Dan is the co-founder
of an app called 10% Happier, which along with another app that I've talked about a lot waking
up are really the cornerstones of my meditation practice. And I've probably also talked, you've
probably heard me talk about Joseph Goldstein. Jeff Warren is a couple of the teachers that I really,
really like in this app. And I think it was just yesterday I did a lesson. I think Joseph, I'm
pretty sure it was Joseph. And it was talking about how even your physical characteristics change
in a moment of conflict, choose to do the kind thing versus the not. So sure enough, I do my
meditation in the morning, I go to the gym in San Diego, I have the luxury of working out at home,
which I love because I can be alone. I'm kind of alone. But in New York, I go to a big crunch gym,
right? Which always puts me in a little stressed state because I'm that guy who likes to be able
to control everything. And I want to be able to do a circuit between these two machines back and
forth, back and forth. So sure enough, I'm doing that. And I'm using a machine. But when I'm off
the machine, another guy sits down at the machine. Okay, no problem. I'm a civil enough guy to go up
to him and afterwards say, Hey, do you mind if I work in with you? But he says no. Like, I'm going
to sit on this machine until I'm done. And I don't want to trade. I don't want to share with you.
And I said, you realize it's a machine, we ought to do a switch the pen and he goes, yeah, but I
don't want to. Now again, old Peter, or maybe normal Peter, that would turn into an escalation.
But I had just listened to this meditation that Joseph had done that day about how my
external manifestation could change if I could be kind in that moment. And I said,
okay, no problem. I'll wait till you're done. I just walked away and did something else.
I really thought about it for the next three or four minutes. And sure enough,
a I stopped being upset about it very quickly. And this is going to sound crazy. But within about
five minutes, I felt bad for him. I started thinking, Oh, he probably feels like a jerk now,
because I haven't put up any fight. I've been very kind and pleasant. And I'm worried about him. I'm
worried that this guy is over there thinking to himself what I'd be thinking if I were in his
shoes, which is why didn't I just share with this guy? So you're right. Let's be completely
transparent. This is total self-interest. Yes, I just want to feel better. I'm just tired of
feeling ashamed of myself. That's right. This is not me making this up. The Dalai Lama, who's got
a reasonably good pedigree on the issue of kindness and compassion, says that there is a
kind of selfishness that's called wise selfishness. And it's the ultimate form of selfishness.
It is to be kind, because you will be happier. And there's all this data to suggest not only
would be happier, but also healthier and more popular as I was saying before. Nobody tells us
this. And that's why this is the book I'm working on now. And my ideas are not fully formed. So
you're hearing me speak kind of early on before I have my shtick down, which may be good, maybe
bad. I don't know. We'll have you back when the shtick is ready. But I like pre-shtick discussion.
The pre-shtick? Yeah. Well, I mean, maybe I'll figure things out by just talking to you about
it. But I really think we are on some levels, we are selfish. So I'm trying to, we don't generally
do things unless there's a, back to my rats and amazed analogy, unless there's a pellet in it for
us. And I fear that the way kindness is discussed is like the care bears or some religious figure
in Robes Wagon, his finger at you. That doesn't strike me as scalable, especially at a time where
we really need this. We've got epidemic levels of anxiety, depression, suicide, especially among
young people. And we have epidemic levels of political polarization. We've got global problems
that require cooperation like climate change. This is the time where we actually need to start pulling
our heads out of our asses. So I'm excited to see if I can make a little contribution in this way.
How much of understanding this concept you've described, do you think requires understanding
its counterpart? So, you and I've spoken before about this idea of the numbing effects of anger
and grandiosity, which in the short term are incredibly numbing. I mean, they are beautiful
anesthetics for sort of the maladaptive mind. Kindness and compassion are antidotes to that.
Do you think it's necessary for a person to understand the nature of their addictions,
their shames, their drives to these other counterparts to kindness and compassion? Or do
you think you could say, no, look, you never need to explore those things. You never need to understand
those things. You don't need to start exploring the relationship you had with your grandfather
or your childhood. And instead you can just focus on the behavior change one interaction at a time.
Well, I'll speak for myself. I think for myself, it's been very important to explore it.
And it's useful. I mean, it's like, you got to figure out the pain of holding onto the hot coal,
which then it feels really good to drop it. So for me, seeing both the psychological content of,
you know, exploring my relationship to my grandfather, etc, etc, but also the moment by
moment mental processes, what it feels like to suffer right now, really help you reorient.
The fact that it feels good. There's an expression about anger from the Buddha that I think is
useful, which is that he said it has a honey tip, but a poison root. I think the prerequisite for me
for seeing that is mindfulness. So in other words, having self-awareness, mindfulness is just the
ability to know what's happening in your head at any given moment without getting carried away by
this is a skill that we developed through meditation, but there are other ways to do it.
But I think meditation is the cleanest, clearest way to, if you have a couple minutes a day of
meditation, helps you have more visibility on your own inner weather. And then you're not so yanked
around by it. And I think having that mindfulness on board can show you that anger sucks. It feels
bad. It may feel good if initially it's a good release of energy, but then it's in your system
for a while. It takes a long time to detoxify. And same with the grandiosity. It feels off to
be toot your own horn as much as somebody like me is prone to do. I feel now that I've got enough
meditation on board and just like it doesn't feel good when I'm being braggadocious or even subtly
self-promotional. It's not even that. To me, they're really dangerous grandiosity because that's so
obvious. Is the grandiosity when I'm in the line at the airport and the TSA guy pulls my suitcase
out of the line because of no reason apparently at all and decides to take 20 minutes to come and
check out what's in it so that that means I don't get to buy lunch before I get on my flight. It's
the I'm so much better than you. Why don't you get over here and do your job? I'm doing my job. Do you
know how hard and you're not saying any of this to anybody, but you're thinking it right? Like,
do you know how hard I work? Do you know the effort I put into my job? Why don't you work as hard at
what you do as what I do? And that's the grandiosity that I think is the absolute poison. And I just
think if I'm going to be brutally honest with myself, that's the biggest struggle that I have
is that inner one-upmanship. And I mean, I love that expression about anger. I completely agree
with it. And I, you know, my therapist has shared that one with me many times. And it's,
you know, we're going to talk a lot about meditation, but you're absolutely right.
Mindfulness is what has even allowed me in the moments of anger to realize what the half-life
is of the honey. I read a tiny bit of a book called Assholes, a Theory. And it was like a kind
of an academic treaties on assholes. And it said the quintessential asshole rallying cry is,
don't you know who I am? Yeah. And again, you may never utter those words. I don't think I've ever
uttered those words. You know, they've never come out of my mouth, but I've thought them. Oh, yeah.
Me too. And the half-life of the honey is so short. And the shame that follows actually
precipitates the following grandiose act. Like that cycle is so vicious. That's good that you see it.
And that's really important. Seeing it is huge.
So let's go back because we're going to jump around a lot, but we go back to the meltdown.
Fast forward. Your therapist finally gives you the aha moment.
Your start, and I assume that he's helping you come to the grips with,
Dan, you're a bit of an addict, right? You're addicted to the high of your job, which is
soothing you. It's soothing something. Let's put aside for the moment what's being soothed.
What was the next step in your evolution to exploring this? Let me do the following. I know
there's so much we want to talk about that we won't get into it. I'll just tell the listeners that
unrelated to all of this, you'd been given an assignment at work, which was to sort of
explore and probe the growing religious movement, something that you didn't find remotely
interesting initially, but being the good soldier you are, you're sort of going through this. And
is it safe to say that the work you'd been doing in understanding religion created kind of an
opportunity for you to also start exploring the spirituality of mindfulness? Is that a fair?
I'll let you finish it in more eloquent terms. Sure. I mean, the assignment was given right
here on this floor on the second floor of ABC News. Was it Peter Jennings that gave the
who made me cover faith and spirituality, which I did not want to do as raised in the People's
Republic of Massachusetts, not particularly interested in this kind of stuff. I like to
tell the joke about the fact that I did have a bar mitzvah, but only for the money. So it was not
on my radar as an important subject. But it ultimately was great for me because first of all,
I learned a lot about faith and spirituality, which was I was totally ignorant on the subject.
And I made a lot of new friends. And I just brought me into parts of the world that I
wouldn't have otherwise seen. And it also ultimately brought me to meditation. In particular,
it came in the form of a self help writer named Eckhart Tolle. One of my colleagues here at ABC
News recommended that I read one of Eckhart Tolle's books, because she thought maybe he would be a good
story for us. And I read the book and I thought at first I was reading the book and I was like,
this is fucking bullshit, like really hardcore. Just awful. And Oprah had basically anointed him.
Oh, yeah, she talked about how she did this whole she had him on the show and then she did a whole
digital series with him. And then she told everybody that she'd put copies of his books
in every bedroom of every house she owns. And then Paris Hilton was seen carrying one of his
books when she went to jail to do time for DUI. Like there was a whole moment there in like 2006,
2008, where Eckhart Tolle was, you know, making a big... He was the guru. He was the guru.
And I was, you know, I react poorly to all of those kinds of things. And his writing has a
lot of grandiosity in it. He talks about spiritual awakenings and how he had a spiritual awakening.
And then he lived on park benches in a state of bliss for a couple of years in London. And
he talks about vibrational fields. There's a lot in there not to like if you're me.
I have to be honest, I couldn't read the book. It's the first time I tried.
Because even though and looking, I should go back and reread it now. But at the time, at least,
this sort of metaphysical nonsense, just, it was just too much. Like I just couldn't,
it became such a barrier to entry. I agree completely. It reads better to me now.
Yeah, I suspect it might as well to me. But what he does do when he's lucid is just
describe our inner lives in an incredibly incisive manner. He talks about how we have
an ego, by which he's not talking about the way egos used in our culture now is like,
Oh, yeah, that guy's got a big ego. He's a jerk. But he means that we all have this running
dialogue, this inner narrator, this voice that chases you out of bed in the morning,
and he's yammering at you all day long. And it's just blah, blah, blah, all day long,
thinking about the past or thinking about the future to the detriment of whatever's happening
right now. Our mutual friend Sam Harris has this joke, but when he considers the voice in his head,
he feels like he's been hijacked by the most boring person alive who just says the same shit
over and over. Most of it negative, all of it self referential. And Tolle's argument is when
you're not aware of this nonstop conversation, it owns you. That to me was incredibly powerful,
first of all, because it just seemed intuitively true. And second, because it described or it
explained the most embarrassing moment of my life, my panic attack. The voice in my head was why I
went off to cover wars without thinking about the consequences came home got depressed, was
insufficiently self aware to even know it, and then blindly self medicated. And it all just blew up
in my face. So that was reading Tolle's book was incredibly powerful. My problem with Tolle,
and I did ultimately do an interview with Toronto, if I recall, your hometown flew to Toronto and
interviewed the man. And first thing I asked him was, it was interesting to me because this is the
first time my whole covering with a religion beat where I felt like I had skin in the game. I was
really excited. You wanted to know I wanted to know wanted what this guy had. By the way, I didn't
think he was full. I didn't think he was a charlatan. And I had interviewed many charlatans. Yeah.
But he was weird. Yeah. And frustrating. The first thing I did is I said, well, you know, what do you
do about the voice in the head? Clearly, you're saying something that seems to me to be indisputably
true, except for I don't. Yeah, what do you how do you actually tame it? You acknowledge that there's
a jerk sitting in the corner. How do you make him stop talking? There's no practical advice in the
book. So I thought he maybe would be able to reveal his wisdom to be in person. And the first
thing he said was, take one conscious breath. And the voice in my head was like, what the fuck does
that mean? What are you talking about? And I asked him a bunch over and over and over. And he
just didn't say anything that made sense. I like I understood the individual words he was using,
but not in the order in which he used them. So I left that interview quite frustrated.
I noodle in this interest of time, I won't go into too much detail, but I spent a little bit of time
noodling around in the self help world generally. Your story about Deepak is pretty awesome.
To me, at least that one's my favorite. So Deepak and I started hanging around a little bit. And
I like Deepak. Deepak is actually more relatable in person than Eckhart Tolle. But Deepak talks in
this way that's like, it literally makes no sense. He used, he casually used the term with me one day,
the transformational vortex to the infinite. That's just the kind of shit he just says.
All the time. So he was just even more confusing. And I definitely didn't believe he was
enlightened because he was checking his phone all the time. And, you know, in nonstop,
in perpetual motion, always hustling. Which, by the way, I don't say as a criticism, I really
liked him. But he just seemed as miserable as I was in terms of professional desire, at least
Eckhart Tolle seemed like blissed out. Anyway, I ultimately realized and Deepak helped me realize
that the mechanism one can use for taming the voice in the head is meditation. And I was not
positively predisposed to the idea of meditation because I felt like it comes with some baggage.
Yeah, I mean, it was, I often say it was, it is the victim of the worst marketing campaign for
anything ever. Because the traditional artwork shows people, you know, sitting in an impossible
position, floating off into the cosmos. The rest of us sit to meditate and either we're in a bunch
of pain or we're noticing that we're distracted. And we don't feel at all like that. And therefore,
we think we're failed meditators. In fact, the experience of meditation is this constant
humiliation, where you sit, you try to focus on one thing at a time, usually it's the feeling
of your breath coming in and going out. And then you're distracted over and over and over again.
But the game in meditation is simply to notice you've become distracted. And in the moment,
that you notice you've become distracted, throw a little party for yourself, because you are waking
up from the automatic pilot, the daydream of your the hallucination of your life, this constant
discursive thinking, and then you're actually here now paying attention. And so the whole game of
meditation is not to stop thinking, which is impossible, it's to notice when you become
distracted and start again and again and again and finding out that the process was that simple,
and that there's an enormous amount of science that strongly suggests that it's really good for
you. I don't want to overly hype the science because I think that it's still in its early
stages, but it really certainly looks like a little bit of meditation every day can do quite a bit good.
And that is what got me over the hump to start. Have you read the book Altered Traits? Yes.
I think that that book does such a great job explaining that we don't meditate for the state,
we meditate for the trait, and that's hard to explain to people until they actually try it.
There's an app out there, there are many, that are tracking your heart rate and your heart rate
variability and levels of calmness during meditation. And I've tried these apps and come
to the realization that at least for me they don't make any sense, because I don't find meditation
generally to be that enjoyable. Sometimes I do, by the way, like we talked about how I'm fasting
this week. Something about fasting makes meditation really amazing. It sharpens the mind.
Yeah, there's just a much deeper connection. But there are many days when my meditation is
very difficult. It's really hard to do everything that you just described.
So that's the state, right? It's not a blissful state at all. But what I'm interested in is,
let's say if I meditate for 20 minutes in a day, I'm not meditating for those 20 minutes,
I'm meditating for the other 23 hours and 40 minutes. Those are the traits that I want.
And therefore, to me at least, an app that was helping me assess the change in my state
during 20 minutes is not nearly as interesting as a reflection on how is this going to help me act
the next time the TSA guy seemingly singles me out, which of course is a ridiculous thought.
But you know what I mean? I've always found this distinction helpful. And by the way,
going back to the whole drug thing, I view the entire distinction on drugs to be somewhat
arbitrary, right? Like is cocaine generally a drug that is good or bad? In my opinion, very bad.
Why? Because it's a drug that only impacts your state, but not your traits in a favorable way.
So it gives you a positive state and then a negative set of traits in the long run.
Have you ever been around somebody doing coke? It's not that positive sometimes.
Oh yeah, fair enough.
They're pitching you on new business ideas.
Yeah, they've got this awesome new cat food idea. It's the best cat food.
Conversely, when you look at things like psychedelics, psilocybin, MDMA, which is not
technically, I mean, sort of a quasi-psychadelic, but I think these drugs plants, for maybe lack
of a better word, when done correctly under these therapeutic settings are remarkable,
not so much because of the state, which they clearly alter, but much more because they can
change the traits outside of them, which is something, by the way, the authors of altered
traits argue against. Their view is that meditation is the only way to use the state to change the
trait, but that's sort of another issue. So kind of listening to you talk about that, I realize
this is a distinction that it can't be stated enough to someone who's new to meditation,
which I'm hoping some people listening are, because it's easy to get discouraged.
It's music to my ears to hear you say that. Richie Davidson and Danny Goldman wrote that book.
They actually sat in the chair you're sitting in. Now you're, we're doing this at ABC News
in the room where I record my podcast and they've both been on my show many times together and
separately. And I think it's an excellent point. And it's what trips up so many meditators, because
they sit to meditate and they think they should feel a certain way. And then they conclude that
they're failures because they're not feeling a certain way. But the point of meditation is not
to feel any specific way. It's to feel whatever you're feeling right now, so that you learn how
not to let your feelings push you around. And yes, of course, the real world application of that is
that you're better at life. We don't meditate, as is often said, we don't meditate to get better at
meditation, meditate to get better at life. Now, just to be clear, though, over a period of time,
as you and some people get to this point and some others don't. But if you're getting to the point
where you're starting to get actually quite serious about the meditation practice, at some way,
actually might want a teacher because getting better at the meditation itself actually can have
lots of benefits. That doesn't mean the meditation is going to be fun. It just means that you can
technically understand the nuances of your own mind and the nuances of various practices at differing
levels. And that I think can have a positive effect on your practice and on your life. And
it creates a kind of a virtuous cycle. I'm getting ahead of myself here. The thing to know primarily
for meditators is don't get hung up on feeling calm or blissful or anything like that. Just
tune in on your ability to see clearly whatever's happening right now. But if what is a distraction,
is it knee pain, is it an itch, whatever it is, pleasant or unpleasant, because what we're
training over time is the ability to notice that anger has come upon us off the cushion in our
regular lives. And can you resist the urge to say something that's going to ruin the next 48 hours
of your marriage? That's where the rubber hits the road. It's so powerful. And I kind of remember the
first time I was able to see the train coming before it hit. It still hit, to be clear. I wasn't
able to stop the train, but the fact that I realized, oh, the train started over there and
it rolled there, bang, versus always just seeing impact, impact, impact. The glass half full
approach of that realization is, okay, maybe the next time you could slow the train down.
And what if one day you could stop the train, the train hitting something being a metaphor for the,
you actually saying that thing that's going to nuke that relationship. Let's pause for a moment
and explain the distinction maybe between mindfulness and being present. I believe my
children, especially the two little boys, are very present. I don't think they're anywhere but
in the present. I absolutely don't think they have a shred of mindfulness in them.
How would you explain that distinction to people?
The way my meditation teacher, Joseph Goldstein, talks about it is like a labrador.
It's not dissimilar from a four-year-old.
I have a four-year-old boy myself. You look at a labrador, she or he is pretty present.
Which is to say they're probably not thinking about what they're going to eat tomorrow and
they're not thinking about the dog that barked at them yesterday.
Yes. They're not a lot in neuroses. They're not swept up in brewing past decisions or fretting
over the future or whatever. They're just right there doing whatever, eating the kibble,
sniffing some other dog's butt, chewing your sweat socks, pooping on the rug.
They're right there for all of that. Being present is necessary but not sufficient for
mindfulness. So you need to be present. But then there's a metacognition that also happens,
which is you know that you're in the present moment and you know that you know you're in
the present moment. We are classified as homo sapiens sapiens, the one who thinks and knows
he or she thinks. And that second sapiens has atrophied over time because nobody bothers to
point out to us that we're capable of this. We have this ability to step out of the stream of
our consciousness and notice, yeah, there's I'm having all these thoughts. I'm having all these
urges. I'm having all these emotions and to not be carried away by them. And by the way,
you're not going to step out of the stream forever. Like you can just do this for a nanosecond at a
time and just to see quickly, oh yeah, I'm having all of these racing thoughts. That's homo sapiens
knowing and knowing that you're knowing. Dogs can't do that. Your boys can, but it's not very
well developed. Mine can, but we'll get them to work on it. My son last night was aggressively
for 10 minutes trying to get me to smell his socks. And he was like, daddy, they don't smell
that bad. I'm telling you the truth. I'm like, dude, you're lying in how I know this because you
have the same face I have and I'm looking at it and that's how I lie. And yeah, it was like karma.
My wife was dying because I'm always messing with my wife. It's one of the hallmarks of our
relationship and me just kind of being a jokester with her. She's like, this is karma. Your son is
you. So what was your first foray into a mindfulness based practice of meditation?
So in this period of time when I was checking out Eckhart Tolle and Deepak, my wife gave me a book
by a guy named Dr. Mark Epstein, amazing human. Who you've had on the podcast twice, I believe.
Yeah. And he's a real friend. I read the book and I realized, oh wow, everything that I liked
about Eckhart Tolle was lifted without attribution from somebody known as the Buddha. Epstein's books
are all about the overlap between psychology. He's a practicing psychiatrist here in New York City
and he's written these beautiful books about the overlap between psychology and Buddhism. I didn't
know anything about Buddhism, but it was very clear that all the stuff about the voice in the
head, which the Buddha refers to as the monkey mind, really is thousands of years old. Much of
this philosophy honed by a guy heretofore known to me as a lawn ornament. But the Buddha is a
fascinating guy and really, really smart. And the Buddha that you're talking about is actually kind
of different from the big bellied lawn ornament, isn't he? Isn't he different entities altogether?
The big fat guy is known as the laughing Buddha, I think. Okay. That's not the Buddha. That's not
the historical Buddha, but there are plenty of you go to a spa that probably have the skinny one.
That's the Buddha, but they didn't make any representational art of the Buddha until hundreds
of years after he died. When did he live? He lived 2,600 years ago. So 600-ish BC and lived where?
India? I think he was born in what is now Nepal, but then was all over India. And talk a little
bit about his path, what we know. What the legend is. Because again, we think there was a guy named
the Buddha, but what's been passed down to us is quite sort of mythological in terms of his
biography. So we know his name was purported to be Siddhartha Gautama. And he was born according to
the legend into, he was the son of a king. He was a prince, like a kind of a minor king. And his
mother died in childbirth or shortly thereafter. And some wise man told his father, this kid's
either going to be a great ruler or a sage. And the father really did not want him to be a spiritual
leader. He wanted him to take over the job of being a king. And so built this world for him
where he would be not exposed to any suffering. So just, you know, fanned by palm leaves and fed
whatever the best cuts of the goat and surrounded by women and musicians, et cetera, et cetera,
against the legend. And at some point he gets out for a tour of the local village or the local city.
And normally they clean everything up. But he sees the suffering. He sees what are called the three,
I think three heavenly messengers. He sees an old person, a sick person and a dead person.
And he realizes that this whole thing, he realizes something that we all should know,
everything's impermanent. Suffering is a part of life. And if you try to pretend otherwise,
you're going to suffer even more. Then he runs off into the forest where he spends six years in these.
He's in his twenties here?
Yes. And he has a kid who he's named Rahula, which is poly, I believe, for
fetter. So speaks to what kind of dad he was. He viewed his kid as a sort of an impediment.
Flawed human being, again, this is all legend here, but runs off into the forest, spends six
years studying with great meditation masters. And the fashion at the time was to do this
self-mortification thing where you like inflict a lot of pain. You don't eat. You stand in funny
positions. You hang upside down, whatever. And he was doing, he was like, became the best at this.
He ultimately realized that this is, he was still suffering. So one day he actually
ate a little bit and stopped starving himself and sat down under a bode tree, a big famous
tree in Bodhgaya, India, and said, I'm not getting up until I'm enlightened. Again, this is all
legend. He sat there for a long time, ultimately got enlightened and had a big battle in his head
with the God of desire. And he transcended greed, hatred, and confusion. And went off and delivered
after he got enlightened, went off and found some of his former monks and delivered his
seminal speech, which was the four noble truths, which are one that life is suffering, which is a
mistranslation. Suffering is a bit of a mistranslation, but the idea is that everything is
impermanent. If you try to cling to things that will not last, you will suffer. So life is
unsatisfactory inherently because nothing lasts. Two, the root of that suffering is desire or thirst,
this kind of insatiability we have. And three, there's a way out of this. And four, the eight-fold
path, which is the way out of it, which includes meditation practices, ethical practices,
like right livelihood, right speech, right action, and then a bunch of meditation techniques,
like mindfulness and philosophical stuff about how to view the world. That's Buddhism 101.
Yeah, I mean, does it kind of amaze you that something that came to an individual or even
individuals, plural, 2600 years ago could prove to be so relevant today?
Yeah, well, so I mean, my question is whether the story that I just told you is in any way true.
Is it possible that this philosophy was? It's possible this was just built upon and
evolving over time. First of all, it seems probable to me more like. For sure the Buddha,
if he was a guy, if he really was a guy, and I think he probably was, there was somebody in the
Buddha, he was standing on other people's shoulders, but he had some real innovations,
including mindfulness. I guess what's amazing to me is regardless of whether it was one guy,
many guys, how long it took, et cetera, et cetera, there's no doubt that what you just said,
the four noble truths were devised in a period of time when no one could have imagined or
predicted the world we live in today. And yet here we are in a world today. And it's important
to take a step back here and think about this through the lens of evolution, right? As a species,
we are no different today than we were 2600 years ago. I mean, 2600 years represents
less than 1% of our genetic journey, identical species. But if you think about the world 200
years ago, no electricity, right? No irrigation, no sewer, no nothing, nothing, nothing. And you
think about the world today, again, not just 200 years later, but call it 2600 years later,
you simply couldn't imagine, like there is no one with an imagination that could have come up with
what we're going to be living in today. And yet in some ways, what you just said is more important
today. I can't imagine it was as important 2600 years ago. But it also tells you about the perennial
nature of human suffering. Which is... It's incredible. It's unbelievable. Yes, but the Buddha
had good news. It wasn't some death-defying dogma where, you know, like we can, at least not the way
I understand or practice it, it wasn't telling you that you can have eternal life or if you just
believe everything I say unquestioningly. It was more like, look, don't take it explicitly said,
don't take anything I'm saying at faith value. Try it out for yourself. Here's some meditation
techniques and you might be able to reduce the amount of suffering you're experiencing, much of
it kind of voluntary, in the face of life's inevitable vexations and vicissitudes. And I have
been trying this out for 10 years and in my experience, there's a lot to it. And the science
that has looked at it too has also been interesting. So how did you go from the meeting with Mark,
or the meetings with Mark? Because I know you talk about multiple meetings and just to say, I'm going
to give this thing a try. And then ultimately, what I really want to hear about is your first
extended meditation retreat, which is something I'm so fascinated with. Oh, the retreat. Well,
but even before that, because you'd obviously been practicing meditation before you went on the
retreat. So what was the... For a skeptical guy like you, what got you over the hump of...
All right, Dan, you're going to put your blackberry down. You're going to sit in this position and
you're going to focus on your breath. How did you make that leap? Or was it relatively easy to make
after everything you'd been through in the journey? No, I mean, I was really intrigued by Buddhism as
a philosophy. I cannot overstate the power for me of that initial Eckhart Tolle lifting of the
curtain on my own mind. Like, wow, the voice in my head is an asshole. And I'm suffering all the
time as a consequence of this. And then the Buddha's philosophy, which I think says it way better, was
also interesting. I was just reading lots of books about it, talking to Mark about it. And
the meditation practice as the corrective is just unavoidable as soon as you start exploring
the
Holy in some ways is really credited for being the first person that showed you what we would now,
as people who meditate take for granted, which is there's a thinker of thoughts. Those thoughts
are not us. Yes. And when neither is the thinker. Yeah, exactly. That's the transition that's very
difficult, which maybe if we have time to, I'd love to get into that. So you're basically saying,
I was already so primed because I realized the most important of the truths, the how to
tame that. I was I was so thirsty for that that basically when someone I came to trust and respect,
like Mark Epstein, who was completely rigorous, completely righteous, not a fraudster, when he
basically said, look, this is this is just a practice. You're just going to do start doing this
thing. That was pretty that was an easy step. I wouldn't say it was easy, but it got me closer.
Yes, that and also seeing the science. The science was a huge deal for me. And when it just became
obvious, I can lower my blood pressure, I can boost my immune system. There's all these brain
scans that show that you can have an impact on your prefrontal cortex and your amygdala. And
that was all very compelling, too. You know, it's really funny, just as a sort of aside for as as
much as I obsess over data and everything I do, whether it's this type of exercise, this type of
nutrition, blah, blah, blah, blah. The science has had the least impact on my interest in meditation
relative to anything I've ever done. In fact, I would argue that if you told me meditation raised
my blood pressure 10 points, I would still do it for the benefits on the reduction of my suffering.
And I would just figure out more drugs to take to lower my blood pressure to compensate for it. Like,
I literally couldn't care less about that science, which is not to be dismissive of it. No,
it's just to say that I don't care about any of that. I care about one thing, because there are
an infinite number of ways to lower my blood pressure, you know, do X, Y, and Z. There's only
one way I know about to understand the nature of my mind, which is an awful, awful demon.
I strongly, strongly, strongly agree with you. I use the science primarily, if not exclusively,
as an evangelical tool. Because I know how powerful it was for me as a skeptic. Oh, yeah.
Even if I don't believe this thing's going to make me happier, hey, apparently there's this other
stuff for me, and I'm always trying to optimize, so might as well do it for that reason.
My experience, the science gets people over the hump, and then they no longer care. Because once
you've done it for six weeks or so, and you realize you're less of a shithead, you don't care if your
prefrontal cortex might look different in MRI. That's utterly irrelevant. So for me, it's really
useful because my job is to get people to meditate, and science is enormously helpful there.
Anyway, it was helpful for me back in the stage in 2009, and ultimately, I was on a beach vacation
with my wife and some friends. We had a house at the beach, and I was reading yet another book
about this stuff. I think for 10 or 11 years now, I've read no books other than books on
meditation and Buddhism. Will you read my book when it comes out?
I will. I kind of count that. So maybe happiness would be a better way to say that.
Or self-improvement in some way.
Self-improvement, yeah. Although I love novels. I think I've only read one in that whole time.
Me too, by the way. I stopped reading fiction in 1999, so that's 20 years ago, but I,
three years ago, read The Alchemist. It's the first purview back in the day.
But that's kind of a, isn't that kind of a spiritual?
It's bigger than fiction, yeah.
But there's so much good fiction on television that I feel like I'm getting that...
You get metagrides.
Yes. So anyway, I set my blackberry down because this was 2009, and I went into the bedroom where
I was staying with my wife, closed the door, didn't want anybody to see me because this was
before meditation was cool. I did not want to admit to anybody I was doing this. I kind of
sat on the floor, sat a timer, and I tried to watch my breath coming in and going out,
going in and going out. And immediately, there was like a million thoughts,
where did your intervals run wild, blah, blah, blah.
I was going to actually bring in my copy of your book. I still have the hardcover
first thing that came out, and I was going to do it just to read that. That's one of the
funniest parts of the book. And you do it, I think, three times in the book.
You do the, these are my thoughts. And I remember the first time reading that how hard I laugh,
thinking, I'm not the only one. I'm not the only one whose mind is an idiot.
Just an abject idiot.
Well, I think the fact that both of us share an affection for Fletch speaks to the kind of
humor that we...
It's like a torrent of thoughts.
Yes. And they're like, how ridiculous they are. How ridiculous they are.
It's amazing. I get some like my best jokes in meditation. And then, you know,
I share them with my wife, who just says, you are an idiot. And my son, who also thinks I'm
more on it. You can, if you have a sense of humor about it, which I think is really important,
the kind of grandiosity and randomness and negativity and ceaseless self-referentiality
of it can be kind of funny. So that first experience was humbling, but I actually got
up after the five minutes thinking, wow, I suck at this. But...
But you saw a light.
Oh, absolutely. I knew this was serious.
So this is big. This is a, at this point, almost a three-year journey. Didn't this...
I know the panic attack was in 04, but was it 06 that you really, in earnest,
started this quest to find something out?
No, I actually think... So 04 was the panic attack, and I think it wasn't until 08 that
I encountered Tully. And then it was a year later that I got some meditation.
So only for the sake of time, though, I wish we could tell every detail of the story. How long
until you took what I consider one of the most remarkable leaps to do a silent retreat?
A year. But I want to be clear. I often, I rarely talk about the meditation retreat because
I worry, as somebody whose job it is to appeal to skeptics, that the skeptic hears, oh, well,
this guy went on a meditation retreat. I'm never going to do that. Therefore, I'm never going to
meditate. So in my world, here's what I would say. I routinely fast for seven days at a time,
but I don't expect any of my patients to do it. And I don't think you have to do this. I think
one can do a whole bunch of other things that approximate 80% of that value. So through the
lens of, we're not telling anybody that they have to go on a seven-day or 10-day or 14-day silent
retreat, though I'm infinitely curious and would like to talk about it. You should do it. Yeah.
There are moments that I go back to remembering reading your book the first time. And one of the
most powerful parts of what you wrote about is something that occurred during that retreat. So
that's sort of why I want to kind of dig into that. There was something you wrote about that
blew my mind. And at the time I read it, I couldn't understand what you were talking about.
And even though today I still have never experienced it, I now can comprehend it.
Which part?
It was like day five or six when you actually heard the wings of the hummingbird flap.
Again, when you said that, I was like, he must be making that up or he was imagining that.
But I've had moments like when I do walking meditations, which are great in your app,
by the way, I'm just going to plug 10% happier all day long.
My investors think.
But I think Jeff Warren does a great guided walking meditation. And I think I even talked
about this with Sam Harris on that podcast. It was the first time I noticed that when you
walk, you can actually feel the wind on your finger as your hand swings forward.
I remember thinking to myself, how have I been walking all this time and never feeling that?
And then the sounds you could start to pick up. Sometimes I would just do outdoor,
like I would do a morning meditation outside, not walking, but still. And I couldn't believe
the sounds you could pick up. So at least now I'm at the point where I can actually imagine what
you're saying. But then, of course, to think, well, what would six days of silence produce?
So one, how did you decide to take that leap of faith? And did you view that as more part of
your personal development or part of your professional? I'm going to take this story
to its most extreme conclusion. Both, but a big dose of the latter.
I think that should be comforting to the listener who's thinking,
maybe I'll do this. Maybe I'll do a couple minutes.
You are to meditation what I kind of feel like I am to fasting, which is it's my job to sort of
see what the boundaries are so that, A, nobody has to go past them. And B, I have a better view of
what the landscape is. That's a pretty good comp. So there were two people who were really influential
in terms of getting me to do this. One was both of whom have come up, Mark Epstein and Joseph.
And no, I actually didn't know Joseph yet. Oh, that's right. Because Joseph was the teacher.
Was the teacher and then Sam Harris. Yes. So Sam, I met Sam Harris, prominent atheist writer. And
this is before he had a podcast and before he had a meditation app. And he was best known at this
point, just as a guy who wrote a couple of best selling books. Yeah. And you narrated, or you
narrated, you moderated. I moderated a debate between him and a couple of people. But one of
the people on the other side was Deepak Chopra and Sam kind of warm up. That doesn't even seem
like a fight, by the way. He was like, I don't know Deepak, but I know Sam so well. And just
knowing the caricature of Deepak, like that strikes me as a little baby seal laying there
and the guy with a club. It was a tough night for Deepak. And I say that with affection,
because he's a really wenchy, if you meet him, he's a really hard guy not to like. He's a very
likable guy. But Sam is amazing too. And I spent some, I had met Sam once before, but Sam and his
wife, Annika, who I've also friends with now, were backstage at this event and I was chatting with
them and they're so, so impressive, both of them. And I mentioned that I was meditating. And to my
great surprise, they were both avid, active meditators. And Sam had this whole long history
of having spent a bunch of time in his twenties meditating. And in that time, he became friend
with this eminent meditation teacher by the name of Joseph Goldstein, who happens also to be the
teacher of Mark Epstein. So I knew who Joseph was, but I hadn't met him. But I knew that Mark
considered Joseph to be his teacher. And Sam was saying, hey, you should go on a meditation
retreat. And Mark had been telling me the same thing. And I was like, well, this guy says I
should do it. And Mark saying I should do it. And they're both talking about Joseph Goldstein,
I should do it. And so Sam, as he said, toyed with the laws of karma and got me into a Joseph
Goldstein retreat, which was a very hard thing to do. And I will off I went without a lot of prep,
and with quite a bit of trepidation, because I thought it was gonna be a bunch of weird people
doing a shitload of meditation, which I really didn't want to do. I mean, I think I was up to like
10, 20 minutes a day, or at this point, I wasn't doing that much. The idea of doing it like 530 in
the morning until, and at night just struck me as super daunting. Was this in Marin? Where did you
go? Is it Marin County, of course, and vegetarian food and blah, blah, blah. I was a dedicated
cheeseburger eater. And being away from my wife, I didn't have a kid at the time, but there's
nothing. It just seemed like the shittiest summer vacation I could imagine. And it was,
it was all those things. I get there and it's like, I thought my, I think I wrote in the book,
that I thought my roommate was going to be wavy gravy, but it turned out I didn't have a roommate,
but it was a bunch of faded hippies and weirdos. And at least this is what my judging mind was
saying. They're actually lovely people that met a lot of, I've become friends with some of them.
But my mind was on overdrive. I was like, these are all NPR, you know, socks and sandals folks. And,
and the meditation itself was just awful, just awful, like sitting there all fucking day. You
know, I was in pain. I mean, I don't sit, I don't twist myself into a pretzel. I sit in a chair,
but that hurts. And the walking meditation, I'd never done that before. I didn't know what I was
doing. I just hated it. And I was just, it was all over the place. I didn't feel like I was getting
anywhere. And by day four or five, I was going to go. I was ready to quit. It was a 10 day. It was
10 days. And I went to a teacher, actually a teacher I didn't like, but she was the only one
who was available. Because you have this sort of 10 minute window each day when you can potentially
speak with the teacher one on one. Yeah, but you would like, they give you a time. So I was going
to see Joseph every other day, sometimes in a group setting with like three or four people,
and then sometimes one on one. But I didn't have a time with Joseph this day. And this is the day
I was going to quit. And one of his assistant teachers who I had made all these judgments about,
spring wash them. She was the only one I could sign up to see. So I do begrudgingly went and
saw spring who I thought was like the embodiment of all like, everything I hated about meditation.
She talked in a really soft voice, had long flowing hair and wore shawls. And
spring saved my sorry ass. What did she say? She said, you're trying to hurt. Like no, no,
like ooh, we gooey, lovey, w stuff. She just listened to me whine for a little while. She's like,
anyway, you're trying to hurt. Don't try to hurt. Just do you know, notice your breath when it's
coming in and when it's going out, when you get distracted, start again. Don't, you know, you're
gonna get distracted. Don't try to make anything special happen. Just stop trying to hurt.
And I was like, all right, fine. By the way, spring has gone on to become some of a very
important figure of my life. She is a extraordinary human being. But I took her word for it. And
instead of sitting in the meditation hall, I actually took my chair out of my room and pulled
it onto the balcony outside of on the second floor of this building where the dorm where I was staying.
And I sat outside and I was like, I'm not trying to hurt. I just sat down.
Whatever happens, happen. And it was just like, as soon as I stopped trying, the whole thing unfurled
for me. And I was just so vividly present and mindful where I was just so quickly registering
how speedy my senses are, how I was going from hearing the rustle, the rustling of the leaves
to the clanking of the pots in the kitchen, which was down the hill to the footsteps in the hallway
to the feeling of my pain in my knee to an itch on my back, just to a thought coming up.
This is how reality works. It's this, you start to see how fast things are going
in your sensory life. And that's really thrilling. It's also accompanied by a huge blast of serotonin.
And this breakthrough, for lack of less grandiose word lasted for like 36 hours,
where I just was happiest I'd ever been. I wept at one point, which is quite a rare thing for me.
I'm not super emotional. It gave me an enormous amount of faith that there is so much to this
practice. And there's such a power to actually doing it in a container where that's all you have
to do. Your meals are cooked for you. You don't have your phone. The schedule is set for you. All
you have to do is get up and do the practice every day. But the big asterisk is, if you try
too hard, you will tangle yourself up in knots. One of the classic hindrances to meditation is
desire. If you want it too hard, you're going to shoot yourself in the foot. It's like a weird
video game where the only way to move forward is to not want to move forward. And that's a hard
thing to do. And the only way to get there for me is to surrender. And you can't fake surrender.
I go into every retreat now thinking I'm surrendered. I don't care. I don't care what
happens. I'm just going to sit here. But I do care. And my mind knows I care because it's
been there. The desire is in there. Yes, of course. I want breakthrough to electric boogaloo. You know,
I want like pajama jammy jam. I want the sequel to that breakthrough. And I can't get it. So what
happens is, sorry, you got a good pajama jammy jam, I'm laughing, I landed with you. This is like,
we're the right age where I can make a certain joke and you know the reference. What happens,
though, is if I'm on the retreat long enough, usually it's 10, 11 days, I cycle through the
reproduction attempts and I get to a genuine surrender. And it's like, I can't fake it. I
got to go through this process of trying to do this, of trying to get somewhere and then just
punching myself out. Do you feel like listening to you describe this, it's almost like the matrix
where and again, I don't think you have to be on a retreat to experience this, but there's a
realization that Neo has when he sees the matrix for what it is, that he's separate from that. And
do you think that that's a reasonable analogy for this idea of realizing that your thoughts are not
you? Yeah, except for separation is a problem. So the red pill of waking up and seeing that
reality is not what you thought, that works as a comp. But in fact, in actual reality, there's
no separation. So not to get into the biggest cliche of them all, being one with the universe,
but how can you not be one with the universe? Think you're separate from the universe? You're
created from the same atoms from the original exploding stars? You are nature. We feel our
lived experiences that we're looking out at the world fretfully from some vantage point that's
separate from nature. But like, your animal body is obviously part of nature and the workings of
your mind is part of nature. And that's mind blowing. And mind blowing just conceptually,
you might register it as I say those words, but you can experience it viscerally on retreat. And
that is incredible. So you get back from this retreat. And I mean, can one even draw a sort
of a linearity around this and says, look, a 10 day silent retreat is the equivalent of three years
of a daily 15 minute a day practice. I mean, I know the answer to that question is no, but you
see where I'm trying to go with this, right? Which is, are you leapfrogging in your practice such that
when you came back from that 10 day retreat, even if you went back to sitting for 10 to 15 minutes
a day, you were able to quote unquote, do something better? I don't know. I feel like you're leapfrogging
your practice, but I don't know if it shows up that prominently in your 10 minutes when you get
home. You know what I'm saying? You build up your capacity to concentrate. Here's the here's the
lowest hanging fruit is one important thing in meditation is the capacity to stay present,
which is your concentration. Work concentration is a little hard. The image that comes up for me
is a furrowed brow, hunched shoulders, trying to concentrate, but it's more like, can you just
be awake for an extended period of time with your capacity to stay undistracted? Of course,
there will be distractions, but your ability to be supple in the face of those also improves.
So you can stay on the object, usually your breath longer, and the distraction doesn't throw you as
much. So that's a skill that gets built, I think, in a way on retreat that because it's such a boot
camp, you're going to build those muscles much more actively on retreat. But then you also
occasionally will have a peak experience, not always. And wanting to have one, of course,
is again, a hindrance. But sometimes in my experience, you'll have a peak experience.
And that shows you something that just like when you take drugs, it's like it becomes a distant
memory, but it's still with you in a, and when I say drugs here, I mean more plants. I haven't done
much at all, but you know, a lot of folks who have my understanding of the way that works is
that you have a peak experience in it. It does stay with you in the rest of your life. So in my
experience, I'm only speaking from an N of one here, but my experience having had a few peak
experiences, it's not like every time I meditate, that's coming to the table with me now. It's more
just that, first of all, I'm imbued with a much deeper faith or trust that this is a worthy
endeavor. And two, it just, it's in my mind stream that this, that some of what I've seen and
understood, some distant echoes of that are still here. When you think about how you meditate today,
you think about the practice you did yesterday. Can I just say something to you? Yeah, yeah,
you said before, that often meditation is unpleasant, which is the same for me. So I was
actually happy to hear you say that because it really represents a wise perspective, which is,
we said it before, but it bears repeating, meditation is not about what you're feeling
right now. It's just knowing what you're feeling so that your feelings don't own you. But I will
say that 10 years in, again, just speaking personally, having done five or six retreats
and having done a reasonable amount of daily sitting, I'm now at a point where my concentration
is good enough. So the thing to know about concentration is that it often feels really
good. Which is why people love TM, because it is a concentration meditation you're using this mantra
that you're getting really focused on. It's less, it's more focused on concentration than it is on
mindfulness. And so being able to stay awake and concentrated on something feels really good.
And I find that my daily meditation actually is much more pleasant because there's like a body
high associated with it. It's called, there's a word for it in the ancient language of poly,
the word is P T P I T I. And it, I think the grandiose translation is something like rapture,
but it really just means like all the kind of like body tingling and high that you can get
from meditation. And so that's just something to look forward to. There's a schedule for when this
shows up. And even for me, I don't always get it and wanting it guarantees that I won't get it,
but it does show up on occasion, not infrequently and can make my daily sitting.
So nice to have, you can't get too focused on it. So maybe you're sort of answering the question
that I was about to ask, which is when you think about meditating 10 years ago versus today,
it's safe to say you still think about gerbils and wonder if your hair is okay and think about your
abs is the biggest difference that you are much more quick to realize that and come back to
whatever your object is. Yes. And, and my reaction to it is much warmer. And this I think is when
you start at the bigger difference, the speed with which you recognize it or the lack of pissed off
fitness that comes with it. I think the latter is in my experience more important. Both are important.
So there's a mental acuity piece to that, which is that you're, you're, you're, you're catching this
distraction more quickly, but if you're catching it and then self-flagellating,
it's the purpose. Yeah, it really does because you're, you're teaching the mind that catching
yourself getting distracted is going to come with punishment. So you're in some ways,
like not incentivizing the mind to wake up. But if you can train yourself to be like, all right,
I caught that welcome to the party distraction. That's a much balmier inner weather. And I think
that feeds on itself in a really positive way. I'm not particularly good at this. I catch myself
lapsing into judgment all the time, but I catch the judging faster. And I'm over time through
various meditation techniques gotten better at just having a warmer reaction to my own peccadillos.
What's the most difficult thing you've gone through personally and or professionally in the last
five years where, and where I'm going to go with this is I'm curious to how you have been able to
take this remarkable training that you've done in the last decade and begin to apply it to
difficult experiences, which is, you know, where the proverbial rubber hits the road.
Well, three things are coming to mind. I'll say them and you can just pick whichever ones you
want to dig in on. One was that my wife and I had a really serious fertility crisis. It ended well
with a baby. But that was really hard. And we were really under the impression we were not going to
have a child, which was very depressing. She also got breast cancer. Both of these were much harder
for her, of course, than they were for me. But obviously, you don't want to see the person you
love suffering and I or start to worry that they're not going to be around anymore. So that was
obviously awful. And then on a much more personal, selfish level, I got a 360 review, which I think
I might have told you about once before we were recording. For anybody who doesn't know what a 360
review is, it's often used in a corporate context. It's a way to measure performance of executives.
The way they do it is they talk to the executives peers, subordinates and superiors. So you get a
holistic, panoramic 360 view into this person's performance. I began writing a book about compassion
and the idea, as my wife suggested, she said, well, you know, a good way to jumpstart the narrative
would be to see what other people think you should do to work on in terms of kindness and compassion.
And then my editor, there were a bunch of people in the room when she said this, and one of the
people in the room was the editor of the book. And she, the editor said, oh, you ever heard a
360 review? And I had, and I was like, oh, that's a good idea. And so we found this Buddhist
executive coach, Jerry Colonna, who we're talking about before, he's got this coaching firm and
they do 360s, but they do the colonoscopy version of 360s. So often 360s are these like kind of
data entry thing where you give people a questionnaire and they answer multiple
choice questions and then you crunch the numbers and you see the data. Jerry's firm does
hour long interviews with everybody, anonymous interviews with everybody in your orbit.
And then they write up a lengthy qualitative report with direct quotes, anonymous blind quotes.
And in my case, we made it even harder because we threw in people from my personal life.
And so they didn't want to just, we didn't want it to just be a professional measurement. We wanted
to get a holistic sense of how am I? So my wife, my brother, my meditation teacher, Joseph Goldstein,
and all these peers in total, 16 people. That was a 41 page report. We also added on a bunch
of questions about where and when and how I'm an asshole. And it was devastating. I thought,
oh, this is this cute little narrative conceit for this book I'm working on. And I got the 360
and it suggested I was, well, the way I took it, it didn't say this, but I took it as monstrously
broken, defective, incurably selfish, self-centered narcissist.
I just want to pause you for one second because I did the exact same thing in 2015.
It's uncanny how similar the experience is because it was everybody who worked for me,
my board, like at the time I was running a nonprofit. So it was my board, everyone who
worked for me, 10 friends plus family. I mean, this was a tour de force. And as you were telling
the story, the only word I had in my mind was the word that described me, which was never once
written, but it was the only thing that came out and it was monster. The first thing you said was
monstrous. I believe that's what the first thing you said. I rarely slip into overt depression.
I usually slip into covert depression, which is a shortcut to rage. This was one of the few
times in my life I went into a overt depression after I reviewed that thing. I did not want to
leave a dark room for days. I was eviscerated by that report. Yeah. That's the way I felt.
It was awful. So how did you pick yourself up?
Well, for a while I thought.
But did you think I'm a fraud? How could I write this book?
Yes. That's literally the word. I've just been, because I am writing the book, I just
am working on the chapter where I read it. And fraud is a word I use because I was like,
clearly I'm pretending to the world that I'm Mr. Happiness and I'm a fucking asshole.
How did I pick myself up? Well, first I thought, okay, well, I can't do this book because
nobody can see this. One thing that helped was my wife and I, first of all, Jerry Colonna does a
lot of coaching. So I read it and then I saw him that day. And he said a bunch of things that were
super helpful. And we have an ongoing relationship. So I used to talk to him at least once a month,
often more. One of the things he said was, and this is very Buddhist. So you now see all this
stuff and know what we're going to do is we're going to love it. We're not going to get into shame
or anger or self-flagellation. We're going to be like, all right, this behavior was serving some
sort of need that some sort of primordial need you had that was not particularly skillful.
We're going to give it a hug and say, you're no longer needed. His pushing me away from shame
and more toward interest. Like, wow, what's going on here? Why would I do that? Why would I be
so snippy with my subordinates? Why would I be so snippy with my wife? Why would I be so
self-centered that I ignore other people's needs? Well, clearly, instead of just going right,
instead of calling me a monster, Jerry was like, no, clearly, you're following some old
script here that must have served you at some point. And putting in that light was incredibly
useful. And then I'll say one other thing, which is that my wife, who I'm very close to my wife,
a lot of us are close with our spouses or our life partners, but she's like a consigliere for
me professionally. So nothing leaves my desk in terms of what I write without her thoroughly
reviewing it. She's basically the uncredited co-author on both of the books I've written
and is deeply involved in all the aesthetic choices having to do with my app. And she's
just my right hand. That's actually not even a good way to put it because she has her own career. So
she's really just doing this out of the goodness of her heart. But I often say to people, and this
is not, this is like only kind of a joke. I don't know what I think until she tells me what I think.
So one of the things we started-
Does she have any extra time?
She does now because-
I could use some help.
Sure. I don't know how she would be great at this because she's amazing. But one of the things
that she got me to do was she and I would rent conference rooms around New York City, get out of
our house, go to a conference room and sit there and read the report together and discuss it
section by section. And one of the things she got me to do was focus on the first,
it was a 41 page report, but the first 15 pages were positive style. And she got me to really
focus on that. And then we went through the negative stuff. She was just like, it's not as
my first reading. Nobody was calling me a monster. They were just really describing
in unvarnished terms, me at my worst.
So are you like me in that, I think my report is about the same, right? It was the first,
maybe it was a 50-50 mix of some really beautiful, glowing, positive things. And then people who
I know were all like all care about me deeply, including people who describe horrible things
I've done. They love me despite those things. But do you just disproportionately naturally
focus on the negatives?
Well, I think we all do. Evolutionarily, we come by this honestly, we had to have a
negativity bias, right? For survival. You want to have...
You think you go above and beyond the evolutionary playbook? Like, I mean,
because I think I do. I think I am... If the evolutionary playbook is to wait at 70-30,
I don't know why. I think I've just adapted to 99-1.
Right. Well.
Which sounds like you do as well.
I don't have data to support my assertion, but yes, I strongly believe I dwell in the negative.
It's actually one of the things that I was dinged for in the 360. And so it was incredibly useful
that my wife take me by the scruff and say, you know, you're going to look at this positive stuff
and then we're going to look at the negative stuff and see if it's not as bad as you thought
it was. Nobody's actually calling you a monster. And yeah, you did do some things that are really
uncool, but you can fix this. And I'll tell you that one of the... There are a couple of comments
made to me by people in my life that really helped me get over it. One was Joseph... The aforementioned
Joseph Goldstein read it and said with a laugh, self-knowledge is always bad news.
Wow. Interesting. So counterintuitive, right?
Yep. And then my brother, Matt, another consigliere, prominent venture capitalist in New York City,
an amazing human. He said two things that I thought were funny. He said, well, first of all,
I'm sorry you had to read this. Second of all, now you got a good book. And for me as an
inventor at Showman, which is another thing I was digging for in the 360, that was actually
comforting to hear. It's like, all right, this is... I actually probably can talk about this
and it'll be useful for people. And it's actually useful for me to hear you say that you and I...
There's a huge overlap in the Venn diagram of our deficiencies. And okay, so I think there are a lot
of people out there who are really selfish and have really made a bunch of bad moves, but there
are reasons why we are like this and those can get untangled and we can work on it. And not only
will it be good for everybody, for us and those in our orbit, direct orbit, but if we do this in
public, it could help countless people. Now I'm really energized to work on the book.
So this is an awesome example of pain that you can pause for a moment and realize you have some
control over the outcome. The other two examples you gave kind of differ. Infertility and cancer,
you have a lot less control over. I think it's safe to say. I mean, in the end biology is sort
of a complex organism. Using either one of those, whichever one you're more comfortable talking about,
how did your practice either prepare you for and or allow you to suffer less through?
When she had breast cancer, I found that in some ways, I think she would agree with me.
He was actually really good for our relationship because I am not particularly, well, this is the
story I told myself was that I'm not particularly caring and nurturing. And yet here we were in a
situation where I really needed to be. I needed to step up and I found that I really liked it.
After a double mastectomy, she was in a lot of pain and I wanted to sleep next to her. But if
I slept in the bed, every time I moved, it was going to drive her crazy. So I felt good to sleep
on the floor next to her, set the alarm for every three hours to make sure I got up and made sure
she was ahead of her meds so that she didn't fall behind because she would have. And being of use
in that way felt really good. Not like I'm such a good person. I mean, there's a little bit of that,
but it feels good to be of service to somebody who you love. It feels good to be of service to
anybody, frankly. Why do you think that didn't naturally come to you? Selfishness, self-protective
selfishness, probably, self-centeredness. I had written a chapter in a book about it by this point,
so I kind of knew it. I knew it, you know, but this was a very powerful example of it. And also,
probably some of the dynamics of our relationship where she is very giving and loving and compassionate
and I'm not. Again, this is the story. But of course I am. There's a great description of
enlightenment in the Tibetan tradition, which is a clearing away and a bringing forth.
And that, to me, seems like a great definition of enlightenment. So I can clear away some of my
bullshit and it blocks me from being useful to other people and having a... I'm trying to find
a better word than connection, but here we go, connection. And a bringing forth of the parts of
you that actually are good at that. And so that I felt was an enlightening experience and that I was
forced to do all that. And I could see that in my mind, these registered, these acts of service
registered as pleasant. And again, there's science here. There's a thing called the Helper's High.
When you give to charity, the same regions your brain light up that are light up when you eat
chocolate. So this isn't new then it's not unique, but it's just a universal human thing that I
happen to stumble upon in this context in a powerful way. So I don't want to minimize that
because that's awesome, but you could argue that all of those things could be experienced without
being faced with a life-threatening disease. The part to me that I'm most interested in is
you are now faced with something that is, there's a probability that is non-zero and it's higher
than it was a month earlier. This woman who is clearly the best thing that's ever happened to you,
no offense, could be gone. So as I think about my own practice, when I've dealt with really awful
things that have confronted me, it's this realization that we are suffering so much in
our minds, probably more than in reality. And so much of that suffering is due to thought. It's due
to projection. It's due to playing out scenarios that, I mean, if we're going to be brutally honest
with yourself, we have no clue what's going to happen. And yet so much of our suffering is drawn
out by those projections. How much of that was going on for you and how were you able to sort
of tame that or maybe asked another way, if all of this had happened to you in 2008 versus
2017, 18, how would it have been different? Two things are coming to mind and I don't know if
either of them are going to answer the question or be useful in any way, but one of them is that
I think, frankly, I didn't think much about the fact that she could die. Partly I knew,
I had a pretty high level of confidence based on the original diagnosis that she was going to be
fine. Well, maybe the fertility one's a better example then, like where there must have been
a moment when you thought, wow, we might not be able to have kids. Oh, yeah. So in that moment
where let's just say before any of this happened, you think there's a 95% chance we're going to
have kids and now at some point you're thinking there's a 10% chance we're going to have kids.
I'm making these numbers up, of course. At that moment when it's a 10% chance we're going to have
kids, it's really easy to start the projection of, oh my God, are we going to adopt? If so,
how, where, what, but it's not going to be our, blah, blah, blah. I mean, I'm just,
I'm the author of that playbook. I could win a Nobel prize in literature for that type of
nonsense thinking. But the point I was really driving toward is that in neither case did I do
a particularly good job at relaxing into the uncertainty. Maybe why that could potentially
be useful to say or to hear is that there are limits to the practice and I am not enlightened.
I'm a schmo who started meditating 10 years ago and I'm good sometimes at applying the
lessons and sometimes I'm not. And I think when Bianca got sick, I didn't really forthrightly look
at the potential that she would die. And I think that when we had the infertility, I didn't really
allow myself to fully engage with the fact that we might not have a kid and then we had a kid.
So sometimes I'm good at this stuff and sometimes I'm not.
How has your practice made you a better husband? I mean, maybe that's a better question for your
wife, but where do you think it shows up most in your relationship with her?
So I think it's really the moment to moment stuff. So I, while I didn't,
I don't think I wrestled on a grand level with the mortality or the fact that we weren't going
to be able to have a kid, but my moment to moment basic blocking and tackling of being a human in a
relationship is much better. In other words, the mindfulness helps me see when I'm over
7% of the time, not always, helps me see when I'm over about to be overtaken by anger or fear,
whatever, irritation, and I can let it pass. I can feel the raw data of the anger, which by the
way, feels really bad, but I don't need to have the satisfying energetic release of saying something
tart that's going to get me in trouble. And that is just creates a much more seamless relationship.
Now, over time, actually, if you add on top of it, because you can make a case, I'm increasingly
leaning toward this, and mindfulness is just one piece of the overall Buddhist picture. And that
alone isn't enough, like warmth, friendliness, compassion, whatever you want to call it is also
incredibly important. And then there are also just like skills for better communication.
Adding all of those things in which I'm now really starting to do as I work on this book,
just makes it even better. So learning to be a better listener, learning how to phrase my
assertions in ways that are less provocative, training up through meditation, my, my baseline
level of friendliness, and ability to lean in and give a shit is all super useful. And by the way,
feels really good when you're doing it. Because that kind of emotional availability, or what did
you say before one of your three mechanisms were it was rage, upset, detachment, detachment feels bad
in my experience. Because you know, there's a bunch of stuff you should be doing, and you feel
guilty about that it just doesn't feel it's not doesn't feel good in my experience. So the actual
leaning in feels better. Again, I still do detachment, rage, and say I do all of that.
This is not you're not listening to a perfected human being talk to you now. It's just lowering
the it's like a marginal improvement. So yeah, I think she would say that our day to day is much
smoother. I doubt she can recall the last time I raised my voice, which I did do for this. And yet
I think she would still say there are times where she walks on eggshells. She can just sense you're
really pissed about something. Yeah. But then I think all the other thing is, over time, my being
easier to be around has allowed her to see that some of her walking on eggshells is her own stuff.
And she might not have gotten there if I was Robert Johnson all the time.
It's funny you bring up Robert, because I was just gonna I was literally just amazing,
like we can reach those minds here. When you think about your son, and you think about Robert,
Terry Reel, who we've spoken about a little bit has this great expression, which I'm going to sort
of butcher, although the expression which I have written down, I feel like it's going to be the
opening quote on this chapter in my book, which is every man is a bridge spanning the trauma of his
past, the legacy of his future, something to that effect. So you're a bridge, right? And you could
make the case that some of the traits you have developed have been in response to things that
were learned from him or his influence on others. And you, like every man have a choice about whether
you'll pass those on to your son. I mean, it seems to me like this practice is a big part, though not
exclusively the only part of it, but a big part of trying to leave Robert back where he belongs and
not let him come up to be a part of your son's life. I think more, and I'm stealing some of this
from Jerry Polona. I don't have a pat answer to this, but what's on my mind is I think it's okay
for Alexander to know that I have foibles and then enter Robert Johnson and enter, you know,
Sammy from What Makes Sammy Run and all that stuff. But I think he needs to see me being okay
with it so that he is okay with all of it. He's going to have negative parts of his psyche. And
I think the trick is not to stamp that stuff out, but to have a supple, warm relationship with it.
I guess what I'm getting at is not to get all psychological analysis, but I think a part of
what Robert Johnson did when he smacked his kids around and told you that if you touched his VCR,
he was going to beat the shit out of you. That's actually transmitting shame to you.
There's a feeling of shame that comes to a child that's hit. It's bullying. Yeah. That's what it
is, bullying. And the bullying is a transmission of shame. And I think that's the part that has to
be stopped. Yeah. It's not about perfection. It's about stopping shame. Yeah. And that's how I think
about it in my life is there were a whole bunch of things that shamed the hell out of me. And
I think of that as my single greatest purpose in life at this point is what do I have to do to
make sure that none of my shame makes its way to my three kids? If I can accomplish that and nothing
else, that's great. If I can accomplish other things in life, that's even better, but I have
to accomplish that. I mean, I sort of feel that way. And a big part of not transmitting shame for me
is recognizing shame when it shows up. So I would challenge that slightly, but again, not
slightly and lightly because I'm not sure I'm right about what I'm about to say, which is that
strikes me that so my dad and mom did not inject any shame into my life. It was mostly the outside
world. I had a very loving parents and they weren't perfect, but very loving. I don't walk
around resenting them for much of anything. I think it's possible I could get to a place where
really I'm not the source of any shame for him and nor is his mother and he's in a really loving
home, but the world is really tough. For sure. And so I want it to be a two-part thing. I want it to be
that we are bottomless wells of love and affection and wisdom for him to the extent that possible.
And that we show him that like you're going to have lots of dark parts of your own personality.
It's unavoidable and you can be okay with that. I think that's my operating thesis.
I actually think that's an even more eloquent way to explain what I'm suggesting, but I think
all I'm arguing is that the home should not be that your parents, you know, there's a term they
use for this, right? Which is your circle of origin or something to that effect, right?
Family of origin.
Family of origin, yeah. Your family of origin really isn't the place where you want the shame
to come from because you can't control the world. Like there will be bullies at school.
There will be all this other bad stuff. So yeah, I think the way you've described it is even more
sort of nuanced and probably more accurate. I guess what I would say is my two senses,
I think meditation has probably prevented you from transmitting some of your own shame,
which has been manifesting itself largely in very externally positive ways. The successes you've had
are in some ways driven, I think, by some of those attributes. In other words, your adaptations,
your maladaptation have been very socially acceptable, but at some point they leak out in
the weakest common denominator, which is generally to our family. Right. At least that's been my
experience. And my, unlike the people in my immediate professional orbit. Right, the people
who you can't fake it around for long enough. Right. So the Hotel Regina left us with a book
and a podcast and an app that have been useful in other people's lives. So it was like a maladaptive
thing that had a positive impact on society, but also some of the sort of not so pretty parts of
my motivation stayed with me and manifested in my being stressed and snippy and rushed and impatient
and greedy and all that other stuff. And now for future projects, I got to do a better job of coming
not from Hotel Regina, but from some other place. And this gets to something that you wrote about
in 10% Happier, but I'm curious as to how you've evolved. One of the big questions you're trying
to answer in your journey, as you've described it in that book is, can a person be successful
professionally if they give up that drive, that sort of somewhat negative insecurity that feeds us?
And I'll let the readers go through your thinking at the time, circa 2014, five years later,
where are you on that particular issue, especially as you've just described it, right, which is
Hotel Regina gave us a whole bunch of things that are externally and ostensibly very positive,
but it came at a little bit of a cost. Do you believe that one can be all positively
valenced without the negative or does that negative need to exist?
First of all, I don't think you're going to make the negative go away. In my, my experience,
I don't have a sense that I'm going to just conquer all my demons and just be operating out of a
position of pure love. Maybe, but I don't see that coming down the pike for me right now.
But I still think you can turn on the volume on the less wholesome motivations and turn up the
volume on the more wholesome motivations, such as, you know, being of service, et cetera, et cetera,
and the less wholesome one being like looking for attention and money. And not to say that attention
and money are all bad, but if you, if you're like really, really totally focused on that to the
exclusion of anything else, I think it's probably maybe not the best. Is there a way in there that
you can shift the ratios and still be successful? I, I believe yes. It may also require a little bit
of a shifting of how you define success. And I think in there I'm starting to form a thesis,
but I think I'm a little more nuanced in my view. During 10% Happier and the Subsequent
Never Ending Book Tour, I really was dogmatic about the fact that you're not going to lose your
edge. You know, look at all these professional athletes who meditate and C-suite executives and
all this stuff. You know, and I believe that to a point, but I think at my level of meditation,
where I've like taken it quite seriously, after a while you start to change a little bit how you
define success. And so for example, I recently went part-time here at ABC News and that was.
This is a big deal. This is announced a month ago. Yeah. So I was anchoring both Nightline
and the Weekend Edition of GMA. Now I've given up Nightline and I anchor the Weekend Edition of GMA.
I do my podcast, which is owned by ABC News and I do special investigative reporting for the network.
It's still a lot, but it's part-time and the rest of my time I'm working on the app and books.
Did I mention how much I love the app? Oh, thank you. I don't know if I mentioned that enough.
Yeah, maybe a couple more times. You know, that was tricky because I was thinking like in some
ways I'm dropping this dream I've had for 25 years of reaching the absolute top of TV news.
If you think about it, I'm kind of a B-level guy. I've been very successful, but you know,
I'm not anchoring the evening news or I'm not the main anchor of Monday through Friday GMA.
I don't have a prime-time cable show. Those are the folks who.
How many A-level people exist at ABC and then NBC? Like each of the three networks have how many?
There was a day when Jennings and Brokaw and Dan Rather were the three,
like the pinnacles of television. We were talking about this earlier. You said you could walk down
the street with Peter Jennings circuit 2000. Yes. And you might as well been walking down the
street with Muhammad Ali or Michael Jordan. It was crazy. Crazy. So, rough back of the napkin.
So, there are three main networks. Each one has a single evening news anchor and each of them has
three morning anchors. So, that's 11 people and then three cable networks. And I would say maybe
each of them has four stars maybe, true stars. So, that's 11 plus. So, 20, 25-ish. Yeah.
I don't think I'm going to be one of those 25. And by the way, there's massive gradations within
the 25. I bet I wouldn't recognize 15 of those 25. That's right. But you recognize Anderson Cooper.
Yep. Amazing person who's really been helpful to me. You would recognize George Stephanopoulos.
Yep. Diane Sawyer. Yep. Sean Hannity. Yep. Would you recognize Joe Scarborough? No.
For the listener, it's not that I'm a moron. It's just I never watch television. I can't
actually recall the last time I've watched a television event that was not a Formula One race
or a football game. So, we may have reached the end of the list. Yeah. So, there might be five
people on that list. I would recognize if I saw them. But we saw a picture of Michael Strahan
in the hallway and you recognized him. Yes. But that may have been from football. Yes. I mean,
I knew him from the Giants. But no, but I remember I've seen him on TV. Just because whenever you're
in the gym, that seems to be what they're showing. Right. And a lot of people who you might have
recognized have got me too. Matt Lauer, Charlie Rose. Of course, definitely Matt Lauer and Charlie
Rose. But everybody would have recognized Jennings and rather in Brokaw. What I was trying to say is
that I've had to... Look, if tomorrow... When did you decide it was okay to get off the train?
In the last year. Wow. Yes. In the last year. It's been a huge story. So, how... Was that a funeral
for a piece of your ego? Did you have to bury that little piece? I don't think it's clean like that.
I think it's like... You said to me on my podcast that you're a backslider. So, I've had moments
of realizing powerfully, okay, I'm letting this go. But then something triggers me and I start
getting competitive and weird again. And then I remember, oh yeah, no, no, no, I'm not playing
this game anymore. So, that's pretty much how it goes for me. I could spend a week or two out of
the building, you know, working on other stuff and just not even remember I'm a TV news journalist.
Unless somebody stops me on the street. And then I get back in the building and one thing or another
happens and I start... I'm filling in on GMA and I'm around. I'm filling in on weekday GMA and I'm
around all these big hosts and I have great relationships with these folks. But I start
thinking, wait, should I be trying to do this? I spent 25 years trying to do this. And so, it's
not clean. But the overall trend is toward not... My wife described it as like an app that was running
that was sucking up a lot of my battery life, but I wasn't using it. So, I think that's starting to
happen in a pretty big way. That doesn't mean I don't want to be in TV news. I'm actually...
And to be clear, the app she's describing is the talk, is the self-talk, right? Yes.
That's such a great... I like that because right now I'm having this awful issue with my computer
where Adobe is not working well. And if I have it open, it will take 50% of my battery in one hour.
So, my new rule is I can't have any PDFs open when I'm on the airplane and I'm working on battery.
But that's... Now forever I will be able to... Every time I open a PDF, I'm going to think about that
and think, hey, what's my mental Adobe reader right now? That's right. Just to close this out,
I still want to be in TV news. I just want to be in TV news in a way that's really enjoyable,
which is I'm not constantly angling for the next job. I'm just loving the one I have right now
and trying to ace this thing. And that's just, for me, it's much more pleasant. And it doesn't mean
I don't continue to have big ambitions. I have a startup company. I would like us to be a billion
dollar company. Did I mention how great the app is that that company makes, by the way? Yes.
Yes, you have. And I need billboards in Times Square with you giving this. But one of our
competitors is a billion dollar company. And do I think we can also be one?
I literally... Absolutely.
And I'm sorry to piss off all the comm users. I don't think it belongs in the same sentence as
your app. It's a different product.
It is a very different product.
So, I'm sure the defenders of that product will say yes, but it does A, B, and C, which I guess
I don't place a premium on. But I guess for the things that I'm looking for, I think yours and
Sam's are kind of in their own world. And I think as the market matures, you'll see...
Yeah, you'll create these niche lanes. Yeah. And I think comm is helping a lot of people. So,
I'm a terrible businessman in that I'm... You're a promoter of another product.
Yes, I am. Because I think if somebody comes to me and says they're using comm, I'm happy for them.
Yeah.
Or if they're using Headspace, I'm happy for them. My view is I like ours better. And I would put
Sam's in... I'm kind of obviously rooting for Sam. I think it's impossible to put a stake in the heart
of all of your demons forever in my view, speaking only for myself. I don't imagine all of my inner
hobgoblins evaporating permanently. But I do think I can turn the volume down and operate out of a
cooler space. Let me just give you an example. We talked about safety before.
No.
Remember how I noticed that Jerry Colonna has this thing about love, safety, and belonging.
Oh, yes.
I really keyed in on safety.
But the good three needs for the children.
Yeah. And I realized that like... It's not that my life is devoid of risk, but I can make a pretty
solid intellectual argument that if my startup goes pear-shaped and my current situation with
ABC News doesn't work, worst case scenario professionally, I'll still be fine. And can I
operate day to day from the place of feeling already safe? And how will that change how I show up?
It means that I don't go... I'm not so sweaty and super heated in meetings. Everything isn't so
stakes. The stakes aren't so high. I can operate from a much more relaxed place. And I've found
that experimenting with this, which is a bit of a leap of faith, has really changed the way I show up.
Now, how do we extrapolate that to somebody who works at Walmart? And every day they wake up and
think, is Amazon going to close this Walmart? So it's one thing to be Dan Harris, who I would
agree with your assessment. If ABC fired you tomorrow and the app blew up, I agree with your
assessment. I just think you're going to be fine. I don't see any scenario under which you're not
fine. But I don't know if I can say that about that person. And given that that person is not rare,
there's not 17 people in the United States that feel that way or that are in that experience.
And by the way, I feel much more like the Walmart person than you. Like I feel way more insecure
about my existence. So I'm asking this in many ways through a very selfish lens. How do we do
this if we're not where you are yet? I think it's an excellent, truly excellent question.
There's a massive amount of privilege associated with what I just said. I don't think there's any
way around it. We have to view this step out of the spiritual for a second and into step out of
psychological and into socioeconomic. He's a very easy thing for a white male wealthy, highly educated
quasi public figure to say all the shit I just said, as opposed to a Walmart worker. Never mind
if it's a trans person or a woman of color who happens to work at Walmart. I just don't think
there's any way around that. I do think it applies to you. I mean, you are going to be fine,
with the exception of the white part, although you present as white. You have all of the privilege
that I have, unless I'm missing something. Yes, no, I'm not suggesting I don't. I think I'm just
suggesting I don't feel it. I still feel a tremendous insecurity of everything could be
taken away tomorrow. I think if there was a better meditation practitioner and teacher in the room
right now, she or he would have an answer to how we can all feel safe, no matter what our circumstances
are. I just am not that person. We're bumping up against the limits of my
abilities here. And you said something earlier that I think is really important.
As I've been struggling with this chapter in my book on emotional health, right now it has
three pillars and I suspect it will evolve. The three pillars are mindfulness, developing the
capacity to be mindful, developing the capacity to reframe things, which is basically stoicism and
then some. And also cognitive behavioral therapy. Correct. And then the third pillar is relationality.
And you've basically said all three of those in your own terminology. So that makes me feel better
that I'm not on the wrong track. It might be that mindfulness is not per se the tool for that,
that one particular insecurity, or maybe it is to some extent. But the one thing that I do
that does give me comfort when I feel very insecure is if I lose the capacity to do my work tomorrow,
I don't lose my relationships. That's not really me falling back on a mindfulness tool. It's me
falling back on. It's a reframe. It's basically a reframe that says, you know what?
If I had to give up all of the things that I love in life and if I couldn't do what I do,
but I still had these people in my life, I'm not going to kid myself and say my life would be just
as good, but it wouldn't be all bad. And that's probably the closest I can come at this point to
thinking about, to be clear, I think I have so much evolution that still has to come because I'd love
to get to the point where I could show up from a place of zero insecurity.
Let me just stop you on that because I hope I didn't miscommunicate in that I gave anybody
the impression that I show up with zero fear and insecurity. It's just that I'm experimenting with
recognizing that I don't have any, there's no rationale for it. There is limited rationale
and that I can go into today's meetings from a feeling of like, let's just enjoy this. I can't
believe I get to have all these meetings today about this amazing company or this amazing story
I'm going to work on. And can I not be so clenched up because that's not helping the process or the
end result. That doesn't mean risk isn't out there and it doesn't mean I'm getting to zero on my
demons. It just means that I'm turning down the volume and that's the 10% happier spirit, which
there is no magic. It's really about marginal improvement over time with an escape valve for
backsliding. Because that's just, I think my understanding of how human behavior works based
on an N of one. But I think it's a pretty universal, I think we're all kind of in the same bucket in
some ways. I'll bring up another point that you brought up something earlier. And this is sort of
a bit tangential, but I think it is really important, which is one of my therapists, I know
you get a kick out of the fact that I have three of them. It's just such a type A way. Nothing in
moderation except moderation, Dan. Okay, that's my ethos. Such a type A way to do self improvement.
But one of them made a really great point, which was the importance of my daughter,
who's again, I think you commented on the age gap between my kids, but different, very different
relationship with my daughter than my son. The 11 girl. Yeah, right. There's one who's almost 11,
and then there's the big, the five and the two. And I was talking about something that I was very
uncomfortable about, something I was very ashamed of. And the therapist said, that's funny, I may
have been blanking on which one, it was either Terry or Esther, but it was Esther. She said,
it's actually very important that your daughter sees how much you're ashamed of this and how much
you're struggling with this. And it's okay if she sees you cry about this. And she really went
through all this stuff. And in retrospect, it seems so obvious that what she was really trying to say
was, you're not helping her by letting her think you're some indestructible force who's not,
who never struggles, who doesn't have remorse, who doesn't make mistakes, and then come to repent.
And as obvious as that sounds now, that has historically felt wrong. Like it's felt like
she should see me as perfect. And I should hide my mistakes from her. I think what made me think
of that was just something you said earlier about your son, but you just said it so much more
eloquently, right? Which is you want him to see your struggle. You want him to know that, boy,
daddy's knee jerk reaction is to lose his mind right now over whatever. But I've figured out
this whole practice and I'm just less likely to lose my mind now. And whatever it is that's sort
of pissing me off, that used to piss me off for four hours is actually going to upset me for about
two minutes. This is actually something I'm really looking forward to in life, is just as I feel like
I'm right in the midst of finally starting to win the battle there is actually sharing that with my
kids. My daughter is old enough to remember some of these outbursts. She has seen some brutal
outbursts. She has never been the recipient of an outburst, but she has been in the car when I have,
I mean, uttered such profanity at another driver that you just, and there's no way she's not
traumatized by that. There's no way, even though, you know, because another thing I've learned about
children is at that age, they can't sometimes tell that it's not about them. It seems irrational
to us. I'm clearly yelling at a person in a car who nearly killed us. How could she take that
personally? But, you know, on some level, she's pierced by that. So for her to understand that
your dad's flawed and he's trying to be less flawed, I think of this as like one of the greatest
things that we could do as parents. Yeah, because she's going to have flaws. And how is she going to
relate to them? Yeah. And that's, that's what I was trying to say before. That's the key. See,
that's the part that you're adding to it that I don't think I've thought through.
I'm stealing it from Jerry Colonna. So I think it's incredibly potent. You are modeling
successful relationships with your own complexity and own demons to your kid. That not only enriches
your behavior and relationship with the kid because they really know you, but it also just
gives them a tool for moving through life in a way that will reduce their own suffering.
When was the last time you saw Peter Jennings before he died?
He called me into his office down the hall here and told me he wanted me to go to off on a trip
to the Middle East to spend some time in Israel and then go into Iraq. And then also told me that
there was a perception I wasn't very good at foreign coverage. But this was before he told the
world he was dying, right? Yes. And this is just typical of him. He was like, give me this big
assignment and also like smacking me in the face while he did it. Just like little pointed jab at,
yeah, you need to prove to us once again that you're good at this thing, even though I had like
spent years getting shot at. And then when I was on that trip, he announced that he had
lung cancer. This was 05? 05, yes. That was in like late winter, early spring of 05. And then
I didn't see him again. He called me one time in the spring and he could barely talk. His voice,
the cancer had shredded his vocal cords. And I can't remember what he was telling me, but he was
kind of like correcting something I had done. That's how he operated. He was very into correcting.
And so we talked and then that was it. And then I heard he died in August. But you didn't see him
in that interim. You never came to visit him? No. Was he not the kind of person that would want to
have been visited? Or did you not feel close enough to him personally? No, our relationship.
I was certainly one of his mentees and he really took that very seriously. He really took me under
his wing. I don't know if he was receiving visitors, but I don't think even if he was,
somebody would have had to cajole or invite me. Because you just wouldn't have been comfortable
in that setting? I wouldn't have presumed that he wanted to see me. So Peter died young. He was in
his 60s, right? Yeah, 66 I think. So if you could go back in time to
the late 90s, you met him in what, the late 90s? 2000. 2000. So you can go back in time to then
when he say call it 60, but you are the guy you are today. So you're still younger than him,
but you're close enough, right? But you know these things that you've learned
and you were having dinner with him and you know all this stuff about him, right? Which is like,
he's this maniacal perfectionist. He is the best of the best.
Would you be probing these things? Would you want to know if he was happy? Do you think he was happy?
I think he could be happy, but I think fundamentally he seemed to me like somebody
wasn't super happy. And I think he was driven a lot by the dark spots, you know, the wanting to prove,
wanting to win. And yet he also, that dysfunctional part of him created so much value in that he was
just so such an intrepid reporter. And he also trained, you know, like we learned so much by
being near him. So there's so many journalists who are working today because, or do a better
job because of their relationship with Peter. I'm very reluctant to push meditation on anybody.
So I thought that's where you were going with it. But simply to probe his happiness level and what
might be contributing to unhappiness, yeah, I do think I would have done that. I actually think
that could have been interesting and productive. If I had evangelized meditation to him, I think
that probably would have backfired. I can't say one way or the other, but just as a general rule,
I think, even as I think about talking with some of my patients who have that phenotype,
usually meditation isn't the place to start. The place to start is just to try to get a sense of
the similarities between us. I'm not talking to anybody about this stuff as an authority who's
figured anything out. I'm talking about it as a schlep who's right there. Whereas a lot of times
when doctors talk to patients, there's this view of, well, the doctor's over here and the doctor's
figured it out and they've got a couple of stone pillars that are carved with instructions and
they're going to give them to you. But this is clearly an area where that's not the case.
And maybe even using Peter as an example, which of course is just such ridiculous speculation. So I
just want to caveat all of that. You've pointed out that one, he was arguably the single best
that ever did this job. Two, he spawned a generation of people like you who have been
imparted with a standard of professionalism. Anderson Cooper, Jake Tapper, Chris Cuomo,
John Berman, Bob Woodruff, Martha Raddatz, George Stephanopoulos, I mean, Jonathan Carl,
like on and on, just Pierre Thomas, just incredible people who came out of his orbit.
So it begs the question that we've sort of danced around. If Peter was a Buddha Zen dude,
could he have had that same impact or would it have simply been a different impact for which
it's impossible to speculate what the net ripple effect was?
My intuition is that you're going to have more of an impact on people if you're not
stressing them out so much that all they can, that you shut down their ability for
cognitive function. Because that's what he did. He was just such a bully that when you stress
somebody out, they can't learn well. But if he felt safe and was willing to sort of calmly impart
the many lessons he had learned over the course of his illustrious career, I think we would have
learned even more. Instead, one of the things we learned was how to deal with a bully.
Dan, there is so much more I'd love to talk with you about, but I think we should save it until
your book is in its next phase, which is to say about to come out. Talk to us about what that
timeline looks like. So you're in the throes of writing or are you still storyboarding?
Writing, actually writing, mostly storyboarded. It's mostly storyboarded. It's going slowly,
but I hope it will come out early. It may come out close to when yours comes out.
It may come out close to when yours comes out, early 2021 or mid 2021. We'll see. I mean, the
absolute best case scenario, which I think is highly unlikely would be New Year's 2021.
I think more likely it would be some point in that year.
Got it. Well, I can't believe we might have to wait that long to talk again. So maybe we won't,
but nevertheless. No, we're going to work out together.
Well, no, no, I mean talk on a podcast. Oh, it's happening.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. We'll definitely talk again.
Well, thank you so much. I mean, thank you on several levels, right?
Thank you for 10 percent happier. Just completely on a personal level.
I'm simply not sure if that door could have been pried open with any other tool and that door had
to be pried open. And even though it is, it's simply the beginning of a journey, I think it is
one of the most important journeys I've ever taken and will continue to take. And just thank you for
creating an app that I think takes something like meditation that comes with so many hang ups and so
much baggage and makes it so completely accessible. And again, I'm biased, but it's the type of
meditation and the type of practice that on a personal level I have found most helpful to
alleviate my abject misery and suffering that seems to be my default state. So thank you for
that. And lastly, just thank you for making so much time on a weekend. Thank you.
My pleasure. My pleasure. Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There,
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read,
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social,
you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but
usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the
obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition
they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.