Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast. If you're listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things
I care most about professionally are how to live longer and how to live better. I have
a complete fascination and obsession with this topic. I practice it professionally and
I've seen firsthand how access to information is basically all people need to make better
decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating and sharing this knowledge
is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to me. The sheer
volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a great
team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one example,
our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and their feedback has mirrored this. So all of this
raises a natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this?
As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot
of contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the
first and most important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm
telling you about something when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it
to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I
just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not absolutely
nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others
have proved can work over time. And that is to create a subscriber model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available
for free. It's that simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose
to support us at, you will get back more than you give. So for example, members will receive
full access to the exclusive show notes, including other things that we plan to build upon. These
are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of our shows.
Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me Anything
episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to hear
these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as
I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with
companies who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and
have them pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope
is that many of you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional
content exclusive for members. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen to this. If you
learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us directly
by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is David Light, the CEO of
Valisher, which is an online pharmacy and analytical laboratory that tests the drugs
it dispenses. As some of you may have heard, on September 13th of this year, a citizen's petition
was filed by David's company to the FDA requesting the immediate attention to and potentially removal
of a very common drug called Zantac or Renitidine from the market based on a lot of analytical
horsepower that they had thrown at it, suggesting that Zantac, Renitidine in its generic form was
unstable and it decayed heavily into a carcinogen known as NDMA. The details of this obviously we
discuss in the podcast, but they are quite staggering when you consider the magnitude at
which this decay occurs and therefore the level at which people could be exposed. Now the purpose
of this episode of course is not to scare people, though in the end I do something I rarely do,
which is make a recommendation, which is if you are playing this through the lens of standard
risk analysis, the better thing to do is to probably at least yourself stop taking this
drug even if the FDA, which at the time of this recording has not asked for a withdrawal either
voluntary or otherwise. It's important to note that at this time 30 other countries including
Canada, many countries in Europe, the Middle East have done that, have gone to the step of saying
this drug is off the market until we clarify what these issues are. In the first 20 minutes of this
episode we get into the background and it is kind of important to understand David's background in
chemistry and the background of how this company became formed and what the impetus was for that.
We then get into kind of their first real insight that they made at the public health level, which
was the discovery of a carcinogen in a very commonly prescribed blood pressure medication
called Valsartan. In this case it was a contaminant, meaning it was not unique to the entire drug, but
only to certain manufacturers. However, the majority of this episode is devoted to the
discussion of Zantac and Renidin. I don't need to really say much more. I think the episode
speaks for itself and it is timely. And again, if you've never taken Zantac, don't care about this,
great, might not be an episode for you, but if you know anybody who takes this and at last check,
15 million prescriptions of this were filled annually in the United States. And when you
consider the over the counter being easily two to three times, the number of that odds are if
you're listening to this, either you take Zantac or know somebody who does. At the very least,
you'd want to pass that on to them. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with
David Light. David, thank you so much for making time to speak on a Saturday evening.
My pleasure. Likewise. If the listener is wondering why we're having this discussion on a Saturday
evening, it's in large part I suspect because this is kind of a timely issue and so many of
my podcasts are scheduled out months in advance, but this was something I didn't really feel should
be put off for several months. So I thought if you were willing to talk on a Saturday night,
then I would too. Thanks for having me. Yeah. So let's spend just a couple of minutes on some
background before we jump into the real meat of this discussion. I first learned about you through
a woman named Catherine Eban. Do you know Catherine? Yes, I do. So you may know them that I interviewed
her a couple of months ago and it was honestly for me one of the most upsetting interviews I've
ever done. I guess I haven't interviewed enough bad guys in my life. Not that Catherine's a bad
guy, but she was really talking about a story that was for me very disheartening, but I think also
for virtually every listener kind of just blew people away. And I knew that the moment we published
that podcast, which we did in probably early September, that there was going to be a lot of
questions coming out. A lot of people were going to wonder what the implications of this were. And
even just in my own little tiny bubble of a world, which is my very small medical practice with fewer
than 100 patients, the implications have been pretty significant. We have basically changed the
way we do everything in terms of we now exclusively work with one pharmacy. That pharmacy while not
able to do what your pharmacy does, and we'll talk about that in a moment, they're able to do
something pretty darn good, which is at our discretion and without any hesitation, they will
dispense exactly which medications we want. So branded when the patient is willing to pay for
branded and if generic, then they are able to do what we do with them. Actually, we do the heavy
lifting, I suppose, which is we go and look at the company that makes the specific generic and look
to see if there's been any interaction with the FDA. Now that doesn't guarantee that we're safe,
but I think it's reducing our odds a lot. But let's now talk about what you do professionally
and within the pharmacy space and maybe a little bit about how you even decided to do that.
Sure. So Valisher company that I co-founded and the CEO of is an online pharmacy, but it's also
attached to an analytical laboratory. So it's actually the first pharmacy whether online or not
that is chemically validating samples from every single batch of every single medication that
comes to our pharmacy and screening out those that have problems and quite a few do. And then for
our patients only dispensing those that pass and we also dispense it with a certificate of
analysis and very much like nutritional information. I mean, you don't buy food without
looking at the nutrition label and seeing what's in it. But where is that for your medications? So
in that certificate of analysis, we're actually giving the information of what we've actually
analyzed for that particular batch of that particular medication.
Now, a lot of people might be saying, Well, David, why is that necessary? I mean, didn't the FDA
already do that? Isn't the point of having the FDA that when I go into my pharmacy and I'm
dispensed my blood pressure medicine, isn't the FDA's seal on that in the same way that the USDA's
seal is on the chicken breast that I buy at the grocery store?
So the FDA seal is on it. But I think a lot of people are rather shocked to understand that the
FDA is not doing chemical testing on the vast majority of medications that are out there. The
testing that is done sometimes and some of the batches are done by the manufacturing companies
themselves, which these days are almost entirely overseas. 80% of drug products in the United
States are manufactured in either India or China, and then self reported to the FDA. So there's
obviously a lot of options for problems and cracks in that kind of self reported system. These days,
you hear a lot about self reporting system problems with aviation and the Boeing 737 MAX. An
airplane exploding is obviously a very visible component of something going wrong. But your
medications going wrong is actually very hard to see or to find out. And then not to mention, as you
mentioned, Catherine, even before she did a very deep study of all the fraud that goes on when
there's a self reported mechanism. So we definitely saw that and said this is not acceptable for how
we would want pharmacy to be. Valisher actually started with a good friend of mine from college
that called me up one day was telling me about all these problems he was having with his
anti convulsive medications. Essentially every once in a while he'd refill it and just have this
terrible month get all these side effects and relapses sometimes and just felt very different
from how he felt otherwise. And he talked to his doctors, he's got some great doctors and the
doctor telling listen, you know, this system is problematic. 90% of what's out there these days
is generic and it can be made from all over the place. And I think as you're kind of alluding to
in terms of working with one pharmacy, just switching from generic to generic could be
problematic. They're formulated differently. They're allowed to vary in their bio equivalence by 45%
from one another. So our high level solution for this was we want to actually have medications
chemically tested at the end of the supply chain in the United States where it matters most and test
them see what's actually inside of them and then decide if we want to actually dispense them.
Forgive me for being skeptical. Because while today this sounds like a great idea. How long has
Valusher been around?
My friend Adam and I so Adam was the one that called me up with this issue. We started the
company in 2015. And originally looking at this as a technology problem. A potential reason why
nobody's been doing this before is that the technology can be very expensive and cumbersome
and really just tailored to one or two drugs when you do this in a manufacturing plant and in
pharma companies. But if we wanted to do this in an economical way at the end of the supply chain,
there's kind of this technology gap. And so we actually spent a number of years developing core
technology, a spectroscopy based approach, essentially applying lasers to pharmaceutical
analysis so that we can do some of the most difficult and costly components of this analysis in a
much higher throughput, much easier to use way while still maintaining high precision. And after
a couple of years of bootstrapping this whole thing and putting a lot of our own resources into
developing the technology, we achieved it. We got ISO accreditation on the system itself. That's the
international organization for standardization. We filed patents. We kind of thought of this as the
traditional biotech model, which is where the kind of industry that I'm from where a lot of the
original founders of Alisher are from. And we went and talked to the industry, the big distributors
and pharmacies and manufacturers. And it was a very odd discourse because all these major players
were telling us, yeah, you know, there are a lot of problems in the system and it looks like the
problems are getting worse. But it's not our problem. There's always ended up being somebody
else's problem. And we also realized that there actually seems to be disincentives. The established
industry actually looked closer at what's on the shelves. They may not like what they see. And so
this was really around now end of 2017, early 2018. That's when we decided, you know, we actually
have to attach this to a pharmacy. So we already had the credited laboratory control of substance
licenses and everything else around a laboratory. And then we built out the online pharmacy component.
And that launched just about a year ago. And when I was referring to my skepticism, I guess what I
was really getting at was in 2015, if you had pitched this idea to me and said, Hey, I got this
idea, which is we're going to actually test individually every single drug that gets dispensed,
I would have said, Gosh, that doesn't really sound like it's a significant enough problem. I mean,
there's two issues with it. Is there enough demand for it? I would have said no. And secondly,
the scalability of that strikes me as cumbersome and difficult. So maybe to give me a tangible
example, if my doctor called me in a prescription for 90 tablets of alopurinol, 300 milligrams of
alopurinol, 90 tablets to last me for three months, would you open a batch of alopurinol that you got
from your generic supplier? And let's say that batch that you got wholesale, how many tablets
would that contain? So you're actually getting to the exact root of the business plan of how
to make this economical is that at Valisher on the pharmacy side, unlike most other pharmacies
that are going to be buying every day or every week and are kind of just constantly looking for
the cheapest possible source and therefore also not having a lot of inventory, we buy large batches.
So we'll look six months out, usually at least to buy a lot of that medication up front. So we have
a larger batch of it so that when we sample it, when we do all of our analytics, obviously that
adds some cost, but that cost is amortized over the larger batch. So per pill that you're buying
from us, it's not adding a whole lot of cost to us, especially as we have proprietary technology
that also allows us to do this in arguably some of the cheapest possible ways. And we really optimize
for it. But we're obviously making less money than your standard big name pharmacy that's not doing
any of this. But you're seeing that a lot in the world of online pharmacy these days, there's all
these kind of value ads that are coming out there. So whereas our competitors are working on spending
money on specialty packaging or sending chocolates with your birth control pills that cost money to
instead of spending money on that, we spend money on analysis. And it obviously cuts into the overall
profit margins, but we're still able to make money as a company and offer this what we certainly
believe is a really critical service of analysis on that batch of medication. I don't know if you
ever heard the podcast with Catherine, but I believe in that podcast, I tell a story about
sort of the first time it occurred to me that generics, there might be something wrong with
a generic and it was several years ago and it was a patient who I had prescribed Crestor, which of
course got filled as resuvastatin, which is not uncommon at all. That's the generic version of
Crestor. And he had previously been on atorvastatin, the generic version of Lipitor, but there was just
there was something I didn't like. There was a blood biomarker I didn't I wasn't happy about. And I
thought before we abandon a statin altogether, let's give it one more try. So we put him on an
equivalent dose of resuvastatin, which is usually half the dose. So I think if he was on 40 of Lipitor
or atorvastatin, I put him down to 20 of Crestor, which got filled as resuvastatin.
Eight weeks later, I get his blood back and he's back to his baseline level of ApoB,
which is the thing that I'm tracking, suggesting he's not taking his medication at all.
Now, I'm not a browbeating doc, so I'm very straightforward with my patients. I just say,
hey, did you forget to take them? Did you run out like a month before the test or what was going on?
And he said, because and if that were the case, he would simply say, yes, I just my patients are very
transparent. And he said, no, no, no, I take it, take this thing religiously. And I remember
scratching my head and thinking, we know that he is statin responsive. So there's something about
this batch that could be different. So I just had my team call in and insist that we get the branded
version. We got it. He took it. It worked. I sort of forgot about it. That type of thing happened a
few times over the last few years. And then of course, reading Catherine's book, I was like,
oh, my God, the lucky times are the times when we see the drug and it has a very obvious,
measurable response in a biomarker. But then there's a whole other class of drugs for which
that's not entirely true drugs like blood pressure medications or seizure medications or antibiotics.
In fact, most drugs do not fit in the camp of a very clear biomarker. So when you set out to do
this again, based on your friend's experience, what did you expect to find? Because at the time
you guys started, Catherine hadn't done her complete investigative watershed expose of the
mass fraud coming out of India and China. So did you think this was a needle in a haystack problem,
but you just wanted to give people peace of mind? Or did you think this was a much larger systemic
issue? Actually, when Adam called me about the issues that he was seeing himself with
anticonvulsant medication, I mean, obviously, I was concerned about his own health, but
for a business, definitely wanted to understand, is this something more pervasive? And I myself
was not on any medications at the time. So I had no personal experience to relate it to and figured,
hey, as a scientist myself, let's look at the literature. And there's a lot of literature out
there, especially in certain areas, like antiepileptic drugs, you start talking to
neurologists, oftentimes, especially psychiatrists that see a lot of these issues between brand and
generic, between generic and generic substitution. And I recall even back then that one of the
papers that I looked at was a Harvard Medical School study that had almost 2000 patients and
showed simply the act of refilling your antiepileptic medication was associated with an over
twofold increased chance of getting a seizure. And I'm like, wow, as a scientist looking at this,
this sounds really serious, and especially in a kind of a class of medication where it's so clear
when your medication is off, you get a seizure. But to your point, this must be happening in all
sorts of medications where it's less clear. And once you really start talking to a variety of
different doctors, you start hearing it a lot too. Like it seems like a lot of doctors have
at least suspected there's a problem or have similar stories as you talk about. I know
certainly in Katherine Eben's book, Bottle of Lies, she talks to a couple of different doctors
from the Cleveland Clinic that have seen it in your heart failure medications and diuretics.
And it's very hard to actually pinpoint the exact problem and nobody's really looking and
analyzing. So what we thought in the beginning was at the very least in certain key areas,
like antiepileptic drugs, like antidepressants and various others that are very big markets,
and a lot of people seeing these issues, that at the very least there we could have a lot of
impact and start looking. But to answer your question, did we think the problem would be as
pervasive as we're already seeing? I don't think we quite predicted just how much we'd be finding
and how quickly and how the engagement of all this has just really, really increased in certainly in
the last few years. But if you look at it, there is a huge problem with well butrin and pubropion
back in the late 2000s, 2007, 2008. There's a lot of these cases that have happened. And I think
a big part of what we set out to do and what we're actually hearing from these doctors now
is that there really just wasn't much that a doctor could do. It's either brand or generic.
Brand you tend to trust more, but can't obviously afford very often. And then you have generic
that there's less and less trust in, but you can afford and essentially set out to create a
validated generic. So something that has actual chemical validation behind it. And you can still
afford same price as generic that you'd be buying anywhere else. Was the business model, and more
importantly, I guess your hypothesis that this was a problem confined to the generic market? Or did
you also intend to check branded drugs? And did you by extension, then assume that brand it's
could be susceptible to the same problems? I think that the general thesis was that this
is probably worse in generics than in brand. However, we had nothing to really back that up.
And obviously, the data just didn't exist, period for these kinds of things. So our intention was
always to say, we don't know exactly where these problems are gonna be from. And we're not going to
make any assumptions ahead of time. Just everything needs to be independently tested at the end of the
supply chain before a patient gets it. And David, one last question really, and as far as background
goes, you've alluded to the fact that you have a scientific background, but specifically, what is
it about your background that allowed you to come into this space and actually innovate?
I'm a molecular biologist by training at Yale University. And I spent most of my working time
in the field of DNA sequencing. So in biotech, essentially developing complex tools for analysis
of complex problems. I spent eight years most recently at a company called Ion Torrent, where
I was one of the original technology founders there and head of chemistry R&D. And we essentially had
this concept that we would sequence DNA on a microchip. It was based on some papers that we
spent millions of dollars proving was just noise. But luckily, we had some other ideas in mind and
had an amazingly innovative group of people there even early on, that were able to make it work.
And Ion Torrent is now the number two DNA sequencing technology in the world. So myself
and some of the other key developers, even at Ion Torrent and folks that I've worked with before,
I think we're well positioned to develop some new technology, which is, again, how we saw this
problem originally being solved is something that we can develop and then just plug into the existing
system. And that's what we started off doing, and then brought in some more folks to enable
the pharmacy side to work as well. All right, so let's fast forward to a little over a year ago.
It's the summer of 2018. I actually get a call from one of my patients, the only one of my patients,
who takes a medication called Valsartan, which is a drug called an angiotensin to receptor blocker.
It's a drug that we use in certain patients with high blood pressure. And in particular,
this is a patient who all the other boxes had been checked. Otherwise, a very healthy guy,
but just couldn't get the blood pressure where we wanted it. So here he was taking
this medication and he said, Hey, guys, I saw something in the paper today
about some of these things being withdrawn. Should I be taking it? Tell me a little bit about that
and your involvement in that. So Valsartan and Losartan and various other ARB medications or
SARTAN medications that have been recalled over the last year, I think are unfortunately a very
clear and visible case of how the system can go wrong and how many cracks there are in it.
The fact that this global supply chain is a self-reported, has a lot of visible fraud
that's happened in the past. And really what happened with Valsartan was there was a manufacturing
change to save some money in China or other places overseas that are making the variety of these
different active pharmaceutical ingredients. And by having this manufacturing change,
they were creating all sorts of impurities. So these impurities themselves being extremely
potent carcinogens, one of them that I'm sure we're going to be talking more about is NDMA,
nitrosodimethylamine. It's actually talked about as a probable human carcinogen, but you have to
keep in mind that's only because you can't ethically have a study where you give humans
a carcinogen. And the data in animals is extremely clear. It's been studied since the 1950s.
NDMA is literally one of the best studied, most potent carcinogens known to man. It's actually
used as a control to induce cancer in rats. If you're doing a clinical study and want to make
absolutely sure that a rat's going to get cancer, you give it NDMA. So this was one of the contaminants
that they were creating in this process that they obviously didn't do the proper quality controls
that they were reporting to the FDA and went all over the world. And this happened for years.
It was only detected years later, I'm sure just kind of randomly. And then as people were looking
more into it and then actually overseas countries started recalling it, eventually was also recalled
in the United States. And it was obviously a very real problem that even continues today. So we're
talking about it in 2018, summer of 2000 teens when it started. The most recent recall in Los
Arden, I think was like a week ago. And we're in October, September here of 2019. And this continues
to be a pervasive problem. Before we leave this topic and get to what we really want to talk about
today, which is Zantac and Renitidine. What is the take on message for patients and physicians
either taking or prescribing respectively ARBs, this class of drug?
It certainly seems like the problems even there are not over, especially the fact that there's
been recent recalls even now. We at Valisher are trying to be very proactive about this whole space.
We incorporated this kind of carcinogen analysis earlier this year. I mean, we just launched the
pharmacy at the end of 2018. Towards the beginning of 2019, we added nitrosamine assay and
incorporated the FDA recommended protocol for analyzing for NDMA and other carcinogens and
impurities. And we wanted to not just look where everybody else is looking. We also looked at other
seemingly obvious places to look. So when this manufacturing change happened, what the change was
is they changed solvents. And they started using this solvent called DMF, dimethylformamide.
Can you explain to people, David, what a solvent is and why it's necessary to make a drug or do
most organic chemical reactions with solvents? Sure. So a solvent is basically something that
you're dissolving different components of chemistry into in order to make a reaction. You can think of
it like cooking. If you're gonna make a soup and you want a whole bunch of things in it,
your solvent is essentially water. Or even if you're cooking an egg, for example, there's so
many different ways to cook the egg. But if you change your solvent, if you change how you're
essentially cooking that egg, although it's still an egg, all sorts of other things can happen. So
what they really did in this case of Valsartan was they might have been cooking the egg in water for
a long time. And then all of a sudden they decided to switch to oil. If you've ever fried an egg,
obviously it tastes different than if you boiled the egg. And those differences are because of all
these side reactions and side products that are happening that give it different flavors and all
sorts of different properties. But yes, it's still an egg. So they were still making Valsartan the
key ingredient they were trying to make. But there's just so much happening on the side that
they apparently were not doing the proper controls of trying to find out what's happening there.
And NDMA, true that it's hard to look for every possible contaminant that there exists. But again,
NDMA has been well studied. It's been talked about as a problem in pharmaceuticals since
at least the 70s. So it seemed like a fairly obvious thing to look for. And for us, when we
started seeing all this, of course, we were going to look for NDMA and DEA and a few of these other
common carcinogens that were being talked about as byproducts of this manufacturing change.
But we wanted to also look for this new solvent. I mean, if you're going to cook the egg in oil now,
there might also be oil still on that egg. And that solvent that the DMF, Dymethoformamide,
is itself a probable human carcinogen. It's in the same class of a carcinogen as NDMA. And this is
a categorization from the World Health Organization and the International Organization for the Research
Cancer. So we started looking for that too. And as soon as we started looking, we found it all
over Valsartan. We found two thirds of the manufacturers that were making Valsartan that
we actually looked at their batches at the time had hundreds of nanograms to over 100,000 nanograms
of this DMF contaminant, which is a probable human carcinogen. And so we put together an FDA citizen
petition and filed it with the FDA saying, listen, obviously, NDMA is a problem and there's other
problems out there that are certainly a good idea to continue looking at. But the solvent itself is
carrying over in this system. And whatever these companies are doing to try and clean up their
process, they're apparently not even cleaning up the solvent. So it certainly underscores the
importance of checking everything and also checking every single batch. I mean, we had
manufacturers that were clean sometimes. And then another batch had not only very high levels
of DMF even had levels of NDMA that were violating the FDA rules. So it certainly underscores the
pervasiveness of the problem and certainly in certain areas. David, some people who are familiar
with the biotech industry will have heard a term GMP. Do you want to explain what GMP means and
what the implication is for something that's manufactured according to that standard?
Yeah, GMP, standing for good manufacturing practices, anything that's under FDA purview
that touches the manufacturing process is required to be under GMP. And it's essentially hundreds of
documents and systems that are in place in order to make sure that things are very well documented
and done consistently and any errors or problems or manufacturing changes like changing over your
solvent, checking for contaminants, these kinds of things are all expected to be part of the GMP
process. And when you're following the whole GMP system, then it's supposed to catch these kinds of
issues. But this is certainly a very robust system. However, it's predicated on the concept
that you're going to self-report it to the FDA and that when the FDA comes and inspects, they're
going over these documents. They're not checking the chemistry of what's actually in that pill.
Is the implication here then that, well, let me just ask the question more directly. Is there any
evidence that any of the companies involved in the production of angiotensin receptor blockers,
drugs such as Valsartan and Losartan actually were criminally negligent? In other words,
saw that their chemical processes yielded molecules that exceeded the acceptable limits
of various toxins and failed to report it? Or do you believe the evidence suggests that rather
all of this was simply negligence and oversight? Honestly, I haven't looked at that kind of
evidence well enough to answer directly. I would say either is certainly possible. It could have
been maliciously covered up by a manufacturer or it could just be that they were saving a few pennies
per pound of these kinds of solvents and just didn't bother to look. I definitely don't have
that answer. I don't want to get too far down this rabbit hole because like I said, what I really
want to talk about is the most timely issue here, which is the Renidin and Zantec one. So I apologize.
I keep saying we'll get to it. And maybe we can park this question, but it's a broader one which
says, why do we have the FDA if not to do this? If not to be the one to ensure that every pill
that goes in a person's body comes from a batch that has a certificate that demonstrates not only
what's in it, but what's not in it. Yeah, look, what the FDA is there to do is a lot of things.
I know we're talking a lot about the oversight of drugs that are already in the market. Obviously,
a lot of what the FDA is doing is looking at new drugs and a billion dollars that goes into
developing something new. I think the bottom line is that with limited resources, there's only so
much you can do. And a lot of what the FDA oversight is about is going through that GMP process and
looking over a bunch of paperwork that's being self-reported by the industry. And that obviously
has limitations, which honestly, the FDA itself admits in a 2015 white paper direct from the FDA.
A, they're saying there's an unacceptably high occurrence of problems. And B, the FDA was saying
that there's no formal means for quality surveillance except through inspections.
And inspection findings have not been a reliable predictor of the state of quality.
Those are pretty much direct quotes. So we at Valisher and the original founders saw this as
further underscoring of industry should be stepping in and doing more. Why don't we actually
analyze every single batch at the end of the supply chain? FDA doesn't seem to have the
resources to be able to do something like that. But in the core of a new business model with some
new technology and everything else, so we thought we could do it. There's more I want to talk about
on that front, but I think I'm going to save it until we get to the end of our discussion. So let's
start talking about this drug Zantac. So Zantac, the generic name for that is Renitidine has been
around for quite some time. I can't tell you how long it's been, but I certainly know it's been
more than 20 years because it was among one of the most commonly prescribed drugs that I would have
written prescriptions for for patients in medical school. It's an H2 blocker, which means that's one
of there are three ways that you can reduce the acid secreted by the stomach. And this is one of
those ways is you can actually block the H2 receptor on the type of gastric cell that makes
hydrochloric acid. And therefore it became a very popular drug, not just for people with heartburn,
but more importantly, or at least as importantly, I suppose, even patients who didn't have heartburn
who were undergoing hospitalization in whom one needed to reduce the burden of insult to their
gastric lining. So I don't even have the stats on how many people take Renitidine or Zantac in the
United States. Do you know those numbers, David? The prescription Renitidine in 2016 was roughly
15 million. I was in the top 50 most prescribed drugs. And obviously that's certainly a small
percentage of the overall use being that it's largely used over the counter by the brand Zantac
or other various generics, practically any pharmacy that you used to go to, it's not there anymore.
But pretty much every pharmacy had their own versions and is one of the most common over the
counter medications used certainly by millions of Americans and folks over the world. Yeah,
I've been fortunate in my life to not have heartburn more than twice a year. But those two times a
year, I sure took myself some Renitidine. One other thing to mention there that was certainly
of particularly high concern to us is that the safety profile of Renitidine was considered so high
that is one of the only drugs prescribed to women while they were pregnant and given to infants for
similar stomach issues. Yes, my third child had reflux and he took a little liquid elixir of
Renitidine for about three months when he was little. And I also remember from doing my rotation
in pediatrics, that was not an uncommon thing to do. So tell me how you became interested in
Renitidine. In early 2019, when we're obviously responding to all these issues, as we've just
talked about with Valsartan and other of these blood pressure medications that had these carcinogen
issues, it was obvious that we needed to incorporate that technology and then be proactive
as we talked about, not just look for NDMA and the standard carcinogens that others were looking for,
but look for other common sense molecules and carcinogens at the same time, but also the same
time, not just look at the blood pressure medications. So our whole concept, of course,
in Valsartan is analyzing from every single batch of every single medication. And ironically,
Renitidine was pretty high in our list to go through the system because that same friend of
mine, Adam, his infant daughter also got a prescription for that elixir of Renitidine,
the syrup form. And as soon as we put it through the machine, following the standard FDA protocol
at the time, we were just floored by the results. It didn't seem possible what we were seeing on the
machine. And obviously we ran it a few more times and just consistently seeing millions of nanograms,
a detection of millions when the FDA maximum permissible exposure to NDMA is 96.
And again, there's no safe level of this kind of carcinogen. The ideal level is zero. And we were
seeing millions and that's how this all started. At some point, I'm sure it crosses your mind.
There's a mistake here. It's one thing if the FDA limit is 96, you're consistently seeing 100 to 110,
but you're seeing five logarithms higher than an FDA limit. What's your self audit on that?
Gut reaction right away being a scientist is that something went wrong. Something got in there or who
knows? Control went wrong perhaps and contaminated the column. The machines themselves we're talking
about don't get data wrong. I mean, these are forensic level machines. The machine specifically
is called a GCMS, a gas chromatography mass spectrometer. It's been the gold standard for
this kind of impurity analysis for decades, over 50 years. And so you start looking for
potentially human error or anything else. And I went to our chief scientific officer who brought
this obviously straight to my desk. Let's look through this system. Let's clean it. Let's run
it again. Let's run more controls. And we kept rerunning it and rerunning it and seeing the same
thing. It was very odd, but the other thing that we did at the same time was starting to look at
the literature. I mean, this is such an extreme finding. Five logarithms higher, five orders of
magnitude higher than what is even still not a good place to be. We started reading about this
and there's been literature about it for 37 years. So you're talking about it being out at least 20.
The molecule was approved in 1981. The first studies that came out that started raising
concerns about NDMA and Renidin were published in 1982. It wasn't approved in the United States till
1983. And there was literally decades of studies about the instability of the Renidin molecule.
There's 17 years of research in the United States over the potential of Renidin getting into the
water supply and then forming NDMA and drinking water. And they showed all sorts of instabilities
in the molecule, reactions with chlorine, with ozone, with all these components that happen in
wastewater treatment plants, which are pretty much benign for anything else. And that's when
we also kind of came to the conclusion, well, actually, if it's such an amazingly unstable
molecule, perhaps it's just even breaking down in the machinery that's meant to test these kinds
of medications. So does this mean that you were more leaning to the idea that this was not an
issue specific to a particular drug, meaning to a particular manufacturer, but rather to the drug? So
when you looked at the first sample where you see a million nanograms per dose, did I hear you
correctly? A million nanograms in a dose? We were actually seeing between two and three million.
Okay. I'm guessing the first call you make once you decide this isn't a human error is somebody go
and get me branded Zantac. You got to think that this is a contaminant from the shady manufacturer
of this generic. You got it exactly correct. At the same time as we're delving into the literature,
we said, okay, this is very odd about whatever was in this particular bottle,
but let's just go to all of the local pharmacies around us and buy exactly the brand Zantac. Let's
buy all the various pharmacy versions of Renitidine and test them all and get the cool mint version
and the standard version and the maximum strength and every single pill of every single
manufactured label or wherever it was coming from, including the reference powder. So not only did
we check every single bottle that we could get our hands on at the time, we also bought the
certified reference powder that's as pure as you possibly can get it to rule out inactive
ingredients or any interactions there. And even in the reference powder, we are seeing
millions of nanograms of NDMA being detected by this test.
Well, that's problematic. I mean, that suggests that let me rather than tell you what I think it
suggests, what's your Occam's razor explanation for at that moment? Meaning before you do another
assay, what is Occam's razor suggest is happening when branded generics alike are containing
millions of nanograms of something that should be completely absent?
I love Occam's razor and Occam's rater specifically said it's a problem with the drug.
Everybody's head has always been in this Valsartan and contamination and bad generics overseas and
these kinds of things which are a problem too, but this was a problem must be just a totally
different level as in the drug itself is just so incredibly unstable and not just unstable
in terms of, okay, maybe you're going to get a less potent pill. It's directly forming NDMA,
the extremely potent carcinogen. And actually, one of the reasons that the specific data around
these millions of nanograms was so important, regardless of the conditions and that's now
becoming one of the discussion points, is that there's no other way to get millions of nanograms,
which is milligrams. I mean, these pills are at 75 milligrams, 150 milligrams. So we're seeing
milligrams of this carcinogen NDMA. There's no other way that it could be there except if the
molecule itself was reacting with itself and forming it. There's no other source of nitrogen
for this carcinogen, a very basic organic chemistry. I want to double click on that for
the listener who might be misunderstanding what you're saying. This is such an important point
that I'm a little floored. So a standard dose of ranitidine is 75 milligrams to 150 milligrams,
correct? Correct. Okay. So, and again, just to state this for the record, when you test a, call it 150
milligram tablet of ranitidine, you could discover, call it 1.5 million nanograms of NDMA. Yes? At least.
Right. Which I didn't write it down, but I think that 1.5 million nanograms is 1.5 milligrams,
right? Correct. Okay. So that means 1%, one full percent of the supposedly active drug you're
getting is a potential carcinogen. And by the way, I want to come back to understanding the
carcinogenic nature of NDMA, but let's park that for a moment. What you're saying is just at a mass
balance level, the only way you could get enough organic building block inclusive of nitrogen to
make NDMA is if you're taking some of it from the ranitidine, meaning it has to be an almost
decay or chemical reaction of the drug itself. Is that correct? Exactly. Exactly. And from a
chemistry perspective, that's extremely concerning. And I'll say one thing also that makes it actually
10 times worse is that the NDMA molecule is a lot smaller or lighter than the ranitidine molecule.
So the molar conversion or the conversion of a ranitidine molecule into an NDMA molecule
is actually even more efficient than that 1%. The numbers are suggesting 10% or so conversion
of the ranitidine molecule into NDMA in an incredibly short period of time.
So what we're talking about in terms of this GCMS analysis is the way that it pretty much works is
you have this vial where we have a pill in it and some solvent. And then it goes into an oven,
chromatography oven, where it's being heated up and then you sample the gas and run it through a
column and then run it through a mass spec. Long story short, you need to heat it up for a little
bit to capture as many molecules as you can that's coming off and NDMA is a very volatile molecule.
It goes into the gas. It's 15 minutes. So it spends 15 minutes at 130 degrees Celsius,
which is benign for practically any other drug that we're looking at and is part of the FDA
standard protocol. And for just these 15 minutes, which in the chemistry world, there's very rarely
do you have such a short reaction. That's like cooking a scrambled egg or cooking a fried egg
in 10 minutes. That's pretty low temp. Exactly. And usually if you're doing serious chemistry in
a chemistry lab, you leave it for hours or days and sometimes it requires weeks, but 15 minutes
of exposure and you're getting at around a 10% conversion into NDMA. That's incredible instability.
And again, the reason you're saying 10% for the listener is even though it's 1% by mass on a
molar basis, the way we actually count molecules, it's much greater. Correct. Let's pause for a moment
and talk about NDMA. I certainly have a lot of questions about this. You've already stated the
formal name of the molecule. How big a molecule is it? It's just a few atoms, right? It's a couple
nitrogens and carbon and I don't have the molecular weight in front of me, but it's pretty small.
It's a tiny little thing. Yeah. NDMA is cataracts is a small molecule. It's particularly small,
even among small molecules. What is the mechanism by which it causes cancer in animal models?
Yeah. NDMA basically sticks to DNA. It sticks to DNA. It modifies what it calls alkalates it.
It also oxidizes it. Long story short, it's very bad for your DNA and by modifying the DNA is what
causes cancers. Yeah. Sticking to DNA is not the worst thing in the world. I mean, methyl groups
stick to DNA all the time and that's called epigenetic modification, which can be quite bad,
but can also be completely inert and in some cases can be good, but this isn't just sticking to it.
It's changing the structure in the DNA in such a way that, well, presumably if it's a carcinogen,
the definition is it changes the DNA in a way that the DNA in that cell no longer responds
to appropriate cell cycle signaling. So now you have growth of a cell that can be unregulated as
opposed to regulated. How well is that documented and in what model systems is that documented,
both cell type and in vivo versus in vitro? So the background in NDMA goes to at least the 1950s.
I'll say that it's extremely well documented in almost every clinical model, obviously other than
human in mice, rats, cell assays. It's been heavily, heavily studied for decades. And like I was saying
before, and I just studied, but also used actively as a control for inducing cancer in mice and rats.
Just to explain to the listener, in vitro means it causes cancer in a petri dish where you take the
cells out. And if something does that, that's interesting, but it's a lot more interesting if
it can cause cancer inside the animal itself. And that's called in vivo. And that's what you just
said. Do you have a sense of what doses are necessary to induce cancer in rats? So this part
is also well studied. I don't know the exact dose, but what I can say is that the calculus that the FDA
has actually already gone through in terms of its potential effect on humans is based on these exact
kinds of animal models and studies. So during all the Valsartan and Losartan issues, one of the
statements that came from the FDA was that, well, if somebody had been taking the worst case scenario
of what they'd found, which I believe was somewhere around 17,000 nanograms or so of NDMA,
taking it consistently for years, there would be one additional cancer case in 8,000,
which may sound like a low number, but when you multiply that by the millions of people taking it,
there's still thousands of cancer cases that shouldn't have been. Obviously, there should be
zero cancer cases that come from carcinogens in your medications. And if you ask me, I'd say that
number is concerning period to have thousands of cancer cases. So those animal models are actually
used to at least make a best guess on what would happen in a human. And again, this is also best
guess. It could be worse or could be better. It's obviously not something you can test and to
actually put inside humans. But that doesn't seem nearly as high as some of the other carcinogens
that we would expect. I mean, there are other carcinogens that are used in laboratory testing
that are guaranteed to cause cancer. Is the difference you think the dose that in the animal
studies when such agents are used, they are used at astronomical doses, but not the same here. I
mean, I'm going to tell you where I'm going with my question in a moment so that you can think about
it as you answer this question, which is when you look at the ubiquity of Zantac use, the question
is going to be where are the body bags associated with Zantac? So before we answer that question,
let's try to tease this idea out a bit more if you don't mind. Sure. Definitely when you'd be
doing a study with mice or rats and you're trying to get them to have cancer, the dosage that those
animals are getting is going to be much higher than these trace amounts that are being found in the
medications like Valsartan. I don't know exactly what those dosages are, but I could imagine they're
in the milligrams. Interesting. So let's now talk about this epidemiologic question. I'm not a big
fan of epidemiology in general. I've railed on epidemiology when it comes to nutrition, exercise,
so many things, which is not to say I think it is of no value, but I think one has to be very careful,
especially when you see weak hazard ratios and try to infer causality. So when you see a hazard
ratio of 1.17, meaning there's a 17% increase in relative risk when exposed to X, and X can be
something you eat or something else, I generally have a hard time with those things. And if that
is a statistically significant hazard ratio, it will have a confidence interval that is well north
of one. So the 95 confidence interval will not include the number one. That's how we statistically
get that. But I find epidemiology can be especially helpful when it's not there. In other words,
when epidemiology says there's no association between X and Y, it becomes a lot easier to say
there's much less likelihood that there's a causal relationship between X and Y. So again, when you
consider the ubiquity in size, 15 million prescriptions a year plus I would say easily
three times that in over the counter use. So let's just call it 60 million dispensed
Zantex over the counter for almost 40 years. If NDMA is problematic, there should be a good
collection of body bags, shouldn't there? Definitely possible. And when we were putting
the FDA citizen petition together that we filed, we tried hard to look up. There are these
epidemiological studies and we found one from 2004 published by the National Cancer Institute
where they looked at the anti-acids at the time, the prescription anti-acids at the time when the
study started in 1986, I believe. And they found a link to bladder cancer when looking at those
anti-acids, which were both reninidine and submittidine at the time. And so it's kind of
as far as epidemiology goes, obviously you want to look at the individual drugs, not have them
lumped together. But that was particularly concerning for us thinking about another study
that was done by Stanford University and published in 2016, which was the only clinical study that we
could find where somebody actually gave people a pill of Zantac and they found over 40,000
nanograms of NDMA in their urine. So we may want to talk more about that in a second, but to
answer your question about epidemiology is essentially, it was just so assumed that this
is such an incredibly safe drug that at least as far as we could find that there just wasn't much
of that study out there. However, we have been working with a number of folks at Memorial Sloan
Kettering Cancer Center and there's been for at least a few months now a lot of efforts led by
Leore Bronstein to look into exactly that question. I mean, obviously, as you know, to do
a full breadth epidemiological study, I mean, these can take years, but we are looking forward
to hopefully get the initial results from Leore Bronstein and his team as soon as we can get them
published in a journal. And so what it really suggests is if there is an increase in the risk
of human cancers from the use of this, it's not going to be a la smoking. I mean, it's important,
I think, for people to understand the magnitude of risk here. In the case of cigarettes and lung
cancer, the hazard ratios, depending on the epidemiologic studies that were done, I think
they varied somewhere between 8x and 14x. And I could be off by a little bit, but I'm not off by
much. So what that means is if you smoke, if you reach a certain dose threshold of cancers,
your risk of lung cancer is somewhere between 800 and 1400 times higher than a non-smoker.
In the words of one of my good friends who's almost assuredly paraphrasing someone else,
when you don't need statistics to see the answer, that's usually a scary thing. And that was
certainly one of the cases. You didn't need complicated statistical models to tease out
the relationship between tobacco and lung cancer. Now, that does not mean, because Zantac obviously
doesn't fit that. I mean, I just I can't imagine we wouldn't see some signal, but it could have a
hazard ratio of two, meaning it could double your risk of a cancer. And because it's so ubiquitous,
and if it's doubling a cancer that is itself ubiquitous, that's the fear. Let me explain why
to the listener, because obviously you would get this, David. The reason that lung cancer was easy
to spot from smoking is lung cancer, absent smoking is quite rare. So epidemiology is at its finest
when the signal is huge, and the thing you're studying is unusual. And that's why I believe
epidemiology is almost as useful as a warm bucket of hamster vomit when it comes to studying
nutrition, because when we study nutrition, we're interested in the diseases of civilization,
diabetes, obesity, and things like that. But the problem is those things are so ubiquitous. I mean,
there are so much of those things that it's very difficult to pick up signals associated with
lifestyle factors. So I guess what I'm trying to get at and feel free to disagree with me, I'd like
for you to disagree or refine my thinking, but I'm trying to make sense of this on two levels. One,
how big a problem is this? And two, what are our blind spots? I think you're basically saying we
don't know how big a problem this is, and that's the fair answer, because the study hasn't been
done. We haven't looked at the cases and the controls, meaning the people who have taken it
and the people who haven't. But the magnitude problem and the blind spot problem really come
down to we will not know the answer until we figure out which type of cancers, because if it
increases the risk of a very rare cancer, I suspect it would have shown up. I just think
if there was a huge uptick from 1980 until today of some very rare cancer,
that would be a lot easier to point to an environmental contaminant such as a drug.
But if it's increasing the risk of breast cancer and prostate cancer, which are large cancers to
begin with, it would be harder. Do you agree with my assessment? I know you're not an epidemiologist,
but you're a clever guy and you've thought a lot about this, and you've thought about it
more than I have. Well, I think it's going to be a very interesting conversation to get back to
when the results are published. And I will say that the big problem I think that's certainly
underscored with this runitidine issue is that just nobody was looking. You could argue that
how would they have known where to look, which I can also point towards lots of
studies and information of should have been looking at NDMA. But nobody was obviously looking
for the NDMA before, and nobody's been looking at the epidemiology before. There have been a number
of rare cancers that have gone up that have been unexplained, some of them starting in the 1980s.
So let's defer that question for when there's more data, of course. And then I think this is
this is something that is going to take years to really get down to what is the total impact for
real. But I can't imagine it's going to be zero. And anything greater than zero multiplied by the
millions of people taking it for 40 years nearly is a tragedy. Especially when you consider that
there are no shortage of substitutes that are equally efficacious, if not better. I mean, that
I think comes down to it's one thing if this were the only drug out there that could treat
patients with HIV, in which case you have to weigh out the benefits of a drug versus the costs. But
when we're talking about reducing gastric acid, which again, there are more drugs in that category
than I can certainly count, it begs the question why. Now, I want to go back to something you said.
So you brought up the study by Zeng and Mitch in 2016 at Stanford. I never heard of that study
until I started looking into this Zantac Ranitidine story. Presumably you hadn't either
until you made your discovery and went back. Why did the Zeng and Mitch article not get more
attention given the largely accepted carcinogenic nature of NDMA and the, I mean, staggering nature
of the study. If I recall the study, one pill, 150 milligrams given to subjects overnight who had been
not taking it before and you just collected the urine and you found, I don't know, was it
40,000 nanograms of NDMA? Right. Over 40,000 nanograms in urine, which in and of itself sounds
really bad and obviously it is, but it's actually at least a hundred times worse because the renal
clearance of NDMA, so how much NDMA actually makes it into the urine is that often 1% or less.
And that's because NDMA sticks to DNA and your body is full of DNA and it's reacting all over
your body. And so very little of it is actually expected to make it to the urine. So really what
those results were suggesting is that somewhere around 4 million or millions of nanograms of
NDMA are being exposed in your body with a single pill of Zantac and they were using the
Brans Zantac in that particular study, which again loops back into our results that we were
seeing in the lab conditions, also the potential of this molecule to form millions of nanograms.
So totally agree with you. It was an extremely eye-opening study. And to go back to when we at
Valisher were originally finding this problem and Corey Kuchera, our chief scientific officer,
brought it to my desk and we started looking at the literature. That was, we were not aware of
that study beforehand, but as soon as we saw that study, we're like, what? Like this is,
this is an extremely alarming study. Yeah. And it sort of validates your numbers because
if one pill is putting 40,000 in the urine, as you said, you could assume that there was 4 million
in the bloodstream. That's the same order of magnitude as what you found in your chemical
analysis, which may or may not be compromised by temperature, which we'll come back to.
So why didn't that study get more attention is my question.
I mean, honestly, professor Bill Mitch, great guy that is in the environmental sciences. So he'd
been looking at this ranitidine problem himself at Yale University, at Stanford University for 17
years. His first papers published in 2002 were concerned about where does NDMA come from when
it's in drinking water and coming out of wastewater treatment plants. And the irony
of how this all came up for him was actually that there's this big environmental problem where they
had this rocket fuel plant where NDMA is often a byproduct of rocket fuel manufacturing. And they
were dumping into a river and all of a sudden there's all this NDMA in drinking water and a
lot of attention to NDMA, a very well-known carcinogen. But what they found is that even
after they cleaned it up and even after they started looking in other cities, they were still
finding low levels of NDMA. Basically sparked the 17 years of research for Bill Mitch and all the
various folks that he's been working with and in this field of environmental science of water
quality. And I think this has been like this big red button serious problem in a more obscure
science than the medical community is used to. I'm sure yourself as a doctor, I try to keep up with
a variety of journals or scientific findings, but I don't know how often you're looking up
environmental journals. I can tell you the answer to that. It'd be never. Right. And look, I think
what we found ourselves in the position at Valisher was adding some new science, some new
discoveries that we found, but really we were just connecting the dots over 37 years of research.
And what was very clear also in Mitch's paper of that specific study was that there was some sort
of missing biological link because there's also been a lot of work at which we also recreated,
which Bill Mitch did as well. Looking at the stomach, just conditions of the human stomach,
and you tend to find hundreds of thousands of nanograms of NDMA, which is also very bad,
being formed by the Renidine molecule. But his study was pointing to the possibility of
millions and therefore Renidine forming even outside of the stomach and the body being
extremely complex, which drove us at Valisher to look more towards, well, is there a potential
biological link here as well? And we identified an enzyme, specifically DDAH1, but this enzyme has
also been well characterized for many years. And what it does is it just grabs onto a molecule and
breaks off this DMA group. So NDMA is the N and the DMA components. And once you break off a DMA,
it's very easy to form the NDMA. There's nitrite that freely circles in your body and lots of
other ways to make it. And so essentially we looked at this enzyme and did computational modeling
to find that seems that the Renidine molecule fits extremely snugly in this enzyme. And that
at least gives a potential biological mechanism for forming millions of nanograms throughout the
body, even outside of the stomach. We essentially had now that biological link and the chemistry
side and then all the way into the full body clinical study that Bill Mitch did that makes
a very compelling story that Renidine is just a toxic molecule in the human body.
So let's talk about the FDA's response to all of this. What was the first date you made public,
your findings? So we actually confidentially alerted the FDA back in June. I don't recall the
exact date we filed an FDA citizen petition that made our much deeper analysis with the biological
link and everything else that we were studying. We filed that September 13th, but we did even
without having the full story yet, we thought the results were so alarming that we did this kind of
confidential filing to the FDA. We didn't want to be publicly talking about these kinds of problems
if we didn't have the full story. Obviously cognizant that this drug industry can be extremely
litigious. A lot of lawyers don't like it if you're talking about a particular drug badly. So that's
when we did the initial alert and continued to analyze this. And then obviously the FDA made
their own announcement also September 13th. So the September 13th date you filed the citizens
petition was the date that the FDA said that trace amounts. Well, actually I don't have their
statement, but do you know exactly what they said? I mean, I remember reading it because at that level
it starts to even get it. Even guys like me will start to see it when the FDA is saying it, but how
did they word their response to the citizens petition? So the FDA's statement Friday the 13th,
September 13th was, I don't have the exact wording in front of me, but that they had found an impurity
and DMA at low levels. I think they made some references to barely exceeding those that's in
food kind of feels like no big deal, but they're still making an alert and wanted everybody to be
aware of that. And us, we've been working for months now on this issue and putting together this
citizen petition that has all the information that we've studied about the chemistry,
the biology side of the components, a bunch of citations of as much as we could find in terms of
epidemiology. But we also had Leora Bronstein and Amoris Lone Kettering folks there working on the
epidemiology, which we thought that's going to be the full story that we wanted to publish as a
complete document. And we were actually quite taken back by the fact that the FDA made this
kind of announcement on September 13th. And although the citizen petition wasn't complete yet
with epidemiological results, we felt it was very important to publish it, get it on file and have
everybody see the full story that includes these very alarming findings on the chemistry and biology
and underscoring Bill Mitch's study, which all these things even just by themselves are so
incredibly concerning that even though we didn't have the epidemiology done yet, we definitely felt
should be published. Now, the FDA has the authority to do a lot. I certainly learned what they don't
have the authority to do in talking with Catherine Iban. But did they have the authority on September,
since it was a Friday, let's give them the weekend to think about it. But on September 16th, that
Monday, did they have the authority to pull all forms of renitidine and Zantec off the market in
the United States? I believe they do. They definitely at the very least have the authority to
request many factors, recall it. When you hear about recalls, it's almost always voluntary
recalls, but the FDA can push for it. Interesting that you mentioned that the following Monday or
Tuesday of that week, that's when the first other health system, Canada, so Health Canada, made a
statement September 17th, that Tuesday, with a very strong message of requesting all companies
to stop distributing all forms of renitidine. And the second line in that statement was current
evidence suggests that NDMA be present in renitidine, regardless of the manufacturer,
which directly underscores what we were finding, that it doesn't matter how it was made or where
it was made, just that the drug itself is so incredibly fundamentally unstable, that it can
directly form NDMA in a whole variety of conditions and should just be taken off the market.
Yeah. Well, I'm Canadian. I'll take a little victory lap on the conservative nature of Health
Canada. Totally kidding. How many countries besides the great nation to the north of us
have followed suit with Canada? So to date, now we're still just only a few weeks away from this
September 13th announcement, roughly 30 countries have recalled or banned renitidine and not just
places like Italy and France and Germany, but you have Kenya, Libya, Bangladesh, Saudi Arabia,
Pakistan. Pakistan actually came out not just recalling all renitidine products,
they actually told all the manufacturers in their country to stop making it, as in stop
everything you're doing with anything related to renitidine. Stop it. And that was in Pakistan.
I mean, I just don't even know how to make sense of this, David, to be completely honest with you.
So I sort of get Canada's reaction because they were the first to react and they reacted before
the FDA had done what they've done over the past few weeks. Do you think a lot of these other
countries are just in a herd mentality mode or do you think they've independently taken a look
at your data, your petition, and come to the same conclusion? I know that's an odd question, but the
real question I'm getting at is why has the FDA resisted taking stronger action?
Each country has obviously their own health systems. I think a lot of these health systems
certainly look towards the FDA, but we were contacted by a number of press that were also
talking with the health agencies in their countries. We talked extensively to folks in
Switzerland, in Germany, in Poland, in India, in Russia, and it seemed that quite a few
agencies were running their own tests. We know specifically in South Korea, they even published
some of those results. They were finding at minimum 2,800 nanograms of NDMA and their worst was
32,000 nanograms of NDMA that was found by South Korea's regulators. And these numbers in of
themselves are obviously not good. But I think one of the unfortunate things that happened out of the
FDA's original statement is that it made this whole thing just sound like a contamination.
And I think you saw this a lot with countries too, is that some of them like Canada, I think,
realized early on, perhaps seeing our petition or just looking at some of the data like Bill
Mitch's study, that this is an inherent problem with the drug and therefore stop all manufacturers,
stop all distribution. Whereas some other countries were banning certain manufacturers
that maybe they tested or they had some data suggesting that this manufacturer had some level
of contamination in it of NDMA. But even that contamination, maybe we'll talk more about this,
of contamination versus inherent instability. There's actually a great article in India that
talked about this of why has France and Germany banned this substance versus at the time India and
the United States had not. And then a lot of what they were concluding is that some people are
looking this as a contamination that maybe happens here and there. And some are realizing the
reality that ranidity is a fundamentally unstable molecule and could certainly cause contamination
as a byproduct of being unstable, but has a seemingly very high risk of forming tremendous
amounts of NDMA in the human body and should just be taken out completely off the market.
So the FDA released a statement in early October that basically said to the effect,
hey, we're going to continue to test ranidity in its products. We're not saying there's nothing
wrong here. But they did very specifically challenge your method for testing. And they
said specifically in this, I do quote, it is not suitable for testing ranidity because heating the
sample itself generates NDMA and presumably they mean heating it to the low temperature of
130 degrees Celsius. Right. So yeah, that exact quote, heating the sample generates NDMA. I mean,
they don't mention that specifically, but they do say third party laboratory, which ironically in
the press, I don't think they even bothered talking about that. They just inserted the name
Valisher. But I think at the very least, nicely underscores that even just some heat, which again
is benign for practically all these other molecules is enough to generate NDMA. So yes,
exactly. We agree heat that could be happening anywhere in transit, could be in a hot car or
anywhere else could directly degrade this molecule, not just into falling apart, but into falling
apart directly into NDMA. So how did we get to the root of this problem? Because this could end up
being the jugular issue. I mean, in many ways, the Zeng and Mitch study suggests you don't need heat.
Has the FDA commented specifically on that study?
Not that I'm aware of. There's plenty of studies out there that look at all sorts of other
conditions that degrade raninidine. Like they're not even looking at in general, they're just
saying, okay, here's raninidine and let's see what happens when we add ozone that is commonly
emitted by all sorts of devices and things, or chlorine that you use for cleaning all sorts of
things. And there also is using wastewater treatment plants. And even the reaction mechanisms
were specifically ironed out chemically of how raninidine degrades directly into NDMA
with these relatively minor and benign conditions. And certainly the condition that concerned us at
Valcher the most was the conditions of the human body. So yes, we in the introductory paragraph in
our citizen's petition also comment on how the FDA method that we use, that was the method
available at the time for the analysis of NDMA. We suspect that this 15 minutes of 130 degrees
temperature is causing an incredibly efficient reaction of generating NDMA from raninidine.
And so therefore we modified that particular protocol. And I should also say that Valcher,
apart from having some great scientists that work with us, we are an ISO accredited facility
specifically for the analysis of NDMA. So we modified the protocol, did the proper controls
and put down the temperature. So we developed another method still using the GCMS and essentially
copying the rest of the FDA protocol and then bring down the temperature to body temperature.
And in this specific way of analysis, we didn't find NDMA in the tablets that we were looking at.
And so we used this low temperature version to analyze conditions of the human stomach.
Actually very similar, almost exactly the same conditions that Bill Mitch was using in his study
and others have used it in other studies before, where essentially we have simulated gastric fluid
and nitrite present, which seems to be particularly capable of reacting with raninidine in your stomach
and is just present in a lot of foods in general and in the human body, even without those foods.
So we created those conditions, put one pill of Zantac into essentially a hundred milliliters of
this kind of stomach fluid and then using the low temperature system, analyzed that and found
very similar numbers as Bill Mitch was finding is in the hundreds of thousands of nanograms of NDMA.
So we found up to 300,000 nanograms. Bill Mitch's study found up to 400,000 nanograms.
So pretty similar results, very high formation of NDMA in a body relevant condition.
So David, let me just make sure I understand that. So obviously the GCMS gold standard,
you can't get around it. You have to be at 130 degrees Celsius in the oven to incubate it.
That's going to produce the numbers we've discussed. But you're saying you came up with
a different test, which is instead of just taking the pill, crushing it, sticking it into the
GCMS, you dump it into a 37 degrees Celsius bath that is modeled after gastric secretion.
So it'll have a pH of two and it'll have this and that other cofactor and enzyme.
And you're saying when you took that little soupy bath, you did not have to put it into
the GCMS or you did, but you just ran it at 37 Celsius instead of 130. I want to make sure I
understand how you can do a low temp assessment. Yeah, important question. And that's somewhat of
the annoying part of where this discussion is now gotten to with these statements is now the
devil's in the details. So okay, what you described is how we prepared the sample. So the
kind of this bath that's emulating stomach conditions. And to analyze that bath, we had
to put it still in a GCMS, but now a low temperature profile of the GCMS, which
what that does when you lower the temperature in a GCMS is you've gotten less sensitivity.
So instead of being sensitive down to 25 nanograms, which is what the FDA protocol
gets and that they published and what we were getting in terms of the sensitivity when you
is 130 degrees, when you take it down to body temperature, now you're at 100 nanograms of
sensitivity. So a little bit less sensitive. So obviously, if you're trying to be a good chemist,
you would put it up to 130 degrees and get the highest possible sensitivity, which I'm sure is
why the FDA published that protocol at 130 degrees. And again, it's fine for Val Sartan and almost
every other molecule that we've ever looked at. Why is that the case? Why was it fine to go to 130
degrees Celsius with Val Sartan? Val Sartan is not unstable. In other words, the NDMA in Val Sartan
is thought to be a contaminant and not a product of degradation. Exactly. Okay. So can you run the
GCMS at 37 Celsius? And is that what you're saying? You can, but you can only detect down to 100
nanograms? Correct. Exactly. So this is splitting hairs here, but who cares when you're dealing with
a concentration as high as you're dealing with, right? Exactly. And who cares when there's already
a clinical study that was done? We can argue all day about the conditions of the stomach, of various
things. You can never recreate biology, right? As soon as we're talking about biology instead
of pure chemistry, which is when the data of using the FDA protocol and seeing milligrams of NDMA form
from reference powder of Renidin, that's chemistry analysis. So our conclusion from that is that
Renidin is incredibly unstable, can form milligrams of NDMA in 15 minutes. And there's
no other way you could have done this except from the source of the drug itself. As soon as we start
talking about biology and stomach conditions, really the ultimate test there is a clinical test
where you go through the entire human body, which is exactly what Bill Mitch did at Stanford
University. Although did he use 130 degrees Celsius on the GCMS on the urine? Because the
real gold standard might be, or I wouldn't say the real gold standard, another elegant test would be,
you take a person, you give them Renidin, you collect the urine, and without doing anything,
you run that urine at 37 Celsius. And if that showed what Mitchell found, or even close to it,
if Mitchell found 40,000, let's just say you found 4,000, let's just say that the difference between
37 Celsius and 130 Celsius on the breakdown product, because again, the question we don't,
what we don't know is, is this person peeing out some byproduct of Renidin that then further decays
to NDMA, or are they just peeing out straight NDMA? And if they are, then the temperature should
make very little difference in how much you detect, correct? Right, actually, when we saw Bill Mitch's
study, and also seeing what we were seeing in the GCMS, we called Bill and started asking about his
work and everything else. We were pushing on some of those questions as well. He wasn't using the
FDA method, but obviously the devil's in the detail of all these methods. And he went back
and did some significant controls to validate these kinds of systems was something being created in
the instrumentation. And after all of his validation, he was still seeing over these 40,000
nanograms of NDMA. So how confident are you? And again, the answer can't be 100%, or you wouldn't
be a scientist, which I know you're a scientist. So how confident are you that grossly elevated
levels of NDMA are being made from Renidin that is not at all an artifact of instrumentation,
human error, or most importantly, temperature contamination? Extremely confident. And you hit
it on the head that as a proper scientist, I can never be 100% on anything, of course,
but the data is just overwhelming. And the other part of this is, as you've mentioned before,
this isn't some life saving drug that there is no alternatives for, where we say, you know what,
we're 99% sure, but there's 1% that maybe we're a little bit off here. And people depend on this for
their lives. And let's think about that versus the fact that they may cause some cancer over time.
That's not the case. Plenty of alternatives, as you've mentioned, this is not a life saving drug.
So I don't see how any of that calculus plays into thinking that this should just be taken off the
market. Yeah. And I would add another layer to that, which I guess is why I wanted to speak with
you about this is I have a little bit of a background in risk, in a formal training in risk.
In risk training, one of the things you're always taught to look for is asymmetry of risk.
So if you have a bet, if you bet somebody $10 on the outcome of something, so you put $10 in,
they put $10 in, that's not a very asymmetric bet. You're going to win $10 and therefore walk away
with 20, or you're going to lose $10 and lose your money. Those are great bets to make because you
have a sense of what the downside is and what the upside is. But what I really struggle with here,
David, is this is a very asymmetric bet that the FDA is making. There's a chance you're wrong.
There's a chance that in a few years, all of the data will be in, including what I consider
arguably the most important data, which will be the human epidemiologic data that tracks the cases
and the cohorts. And it will show that Zantec is totally fine. And further chemical analysis will
reveal that there is some error in the methodology that you and countless others have made. It doesn't
sound like that's the case, but it could be. In that case, the FDA will have been the hero for
not recalling the drug. What's the upside in that situation? Conversely, in five years, if the
epidemiology or two years or whatever suggests the opposite, which is this totally unnecessary,
ubiquitous drug increased by two and a half fold, a risk of cancer, of fill in the blank cancer,
and when the FDA was notified of this, they did nothing, that's a very asymmetric downside. That
downside is infinitely greater than the upside of having done nothing. If anybody at the FDA is
listening, I'm sorry if I sound like I'm being a jerk, but I can't help but ask, what is your
chief risk officer telling you right now? Because if I was your chief risk officer, and I didn't
know a thing about biology, I'd be explaining this to you. Where is that discussion, David? Do you
know enough about the FDA to understand that? Do they have a chief risk officer? We have had no
interaction with the FDA throughout all this other than our submitting of the citizen petition and
seeing what they're saying about us in these statements. Huh. Well, I guess the only thing
I can tell you is here's what we've done. We've told that we have three patients in our practice
that take Zantac, so the first thing we did when I really figured out how serious this was, which
was not on Friday the 13th, by the way. The front of the 13th, I took the FDA's word for it. Stupid
Peter, sorry. But it was a few days later that a little bit more digging made me realize,
the FDA might be making a mistake here, that we went and scrubbed the medical
reconciliations of all our patients, realized three of them took Renitidine.
Luckily, none of them regularly. We just called them immediately, said, stop taking this drug,
do not pass go, do not collect $200. Here's the drug you're going to take instead.
Presumably anybody listening to this, I'd feel pretty comfortable suggesting they do the same.
What else is there to do? What can citizens do beyond not taking this drug themselves and
passing along that insight? Is there anything that the citizens can do with respect to the FDA? I
mean, how many citizens petitions does the FDA get a year, by the way? I'm not sure what that
exact number is. It's used for such a variety of different things, but I think they get a few of
them a week. But I assume that they're all different, right? I mean, obviously they're
all different. I guess what I'm saying is I assume they're of different magnitude of importance. I
mean, when a chemical lab of yours stature is submitting this type of data, that's probably
different than if I just rung up the FDA and said, Hey guys, I noticed when my patient took Crestor,
it worked. And when he took Resuvastat and it didn't, that's the type of citizens petition,
I assume that doesn't go too far. But do you have a sense of how many citizens petitions of your
nature and gravity hit their desk? I don't think very many. Do you know how the FDA set the limit
at 96 nanograms, by the way? Yeah. So the calculus behind that is basically ensuring that there is
less than one cancer case in a hundred thousand over the course of 70 years. That's an extrapolation
from an animal model, correct? Correct. So again, as a scientist, it could be maybe it's not that
bad or it could be worse. Humans are not the same as a mouse. Well, David, is there anything else you
want to say on this story? I mean, this is, I got to be brutally honest with you. I was a little bit
reluctant to speak with you so early in the development of this story because I know that
time always brings new insights. But at the same time, I think truthfully, I felt a little bit
a sense of responsibility. Feel fortunate that we have an audience now that is quite large.
And if for no other reason than if this message gets to a lot of people who then share it with
a lot of people, it can make a difference in at least some people's lives. And again, my calculation
is on the asymmetric side of this, if this is wrong, I still feel like we've done no harm in that,
at least to a person, meaning we've harmed a company. Let's be clear. If this is wrong,
all the companies that make, who makes Zantac, by the way, is it Sanofi? Sanofi bought the rights
to in the United States. It's made by a whole bunch of different companies. Right, right. So
you've got all the generics in Sanofi that makes the brand, et cetera. I mean, let's be honest.
Let's look at it from their standpoint. They're being hurt by this. And if this turns out to be
wrong, that's potentially devastating financially. I guess I am taking a slightly different risk,
which is that the risk of someone switching over to a different H2 blocker or proton pump inhibitor
is the worst thing that's going to happen. And the best thing that happens is hopefully some
cases of cancer could be averted over the next, God knows how long. That might be naive, but that's
sort of the reason I wanted to talk with you. But I'm uneasy of the fact that we, there's more
questions than answers too. One other thing actually that I think is important to underscore here and
could also play into this overall upside downside calculus is that the reason this whole issue came
up again in the scientific literature in the early 2000s is concern over water quality.
I'm an NDMA in drinking water. And what we mentioned in the petition that is getting very
little attention, unfortunately, is that now that there's all this news and everybody's worried
about it for one reason or another of whatever they're reading about Zantac and Renidine,
if you're throwing it away in the sink, down the toilet, even in trash, which goes to landfills and
bleach, eight runoff from that can be treated in chemical methods. All of this is exactly what all
these environmental scientists for the last 17 years have been saying is a potential problem
because it will form NDMA in the wastewater treatment plant, which then gets used as drinking
water. So we certainly feel that if you're making the decision to no longer use a Renidine product,
make sure you don't just throw it away or certainly don't throw it down the sink or down
the toilet. It needs to be disposed of properly. I mean, essentially, it's got to be disposed of
as toxic waste. It's got to be returned to the pharmacy or to all these facilities that do
medication disposal. Because another potential downside of all this is that everybody's dumping
it and it's going into the water system and then being converted to high levels of NDMA in drinking
water. And now you have another potential crisis. Well, that's a really good point. So again, just
to make sure the listener understands exactly what you're talking about, it's one thing to say, wow,
this is an issue. I'm going to stop taking my Renidine, but to flush it down the toilet or throw
it in the garbage potentially spreads the problem. Now, have you heard of pharmacies accepting samples
back and doing whatever is appropriate to dispose of it? I mean, from a practical standpoint,
what could somebody do the day they're hearing this? I think specifically, I believe it was
Walmart or some of the big pharmacy chains have said that they'll take your product back and even
give you a refund. I mean, I don't want to put words in their mouth, but it's something that
pharmacies are set up to do. And quite sure that a number of them have gone out and said that you
can even get a refund for this. Well, David, this may not be the last time we speak because I suspect
one, there'll be more to this story, but I suspect that there may be other interesting health issues
that crop up as a result of your work. But again, I want to thank you for speaking on very short
notice. I want to thank you for speaking with me on a Saturday night. And more than all of that,
of course, I want to thank you for the public service that your company does to take care of
a problem that honestly, a couple of years ago, I thought was non-existent. And now between your
work and certainly that of Catherine's, I've come to really, really doubt the veracity of the FDA
and in general, our regulatory environment. I don't say that lightly. I certainly think the
FDA is an amazing organization and I think we're richer for it with respect to what most countries
go through. I've met many people who work at the FDA. There's great folks there. I want to be clear
that I'm not disparaging the FDA, but there's something fundamentally wrong with this type
of decision making. And I don't know where the buck stops, but I'm definitely frustrated by this.
And I want to make sure that people are at least armed to make their own decisions,
which may differ from mine and yours, but at least they're informed.
Absolutely. And I would totally echo that there's tremendous good that comes out of the FDA and
tons of great people that work there. And I certainly hope that these kinds of scenarios
will at the very least bring more overall engagement on these issues. And I also not
entirely sure what all the decisions are being made here. And I wish that there would be faster
action on this specific grenadine case, but we certainly hope to work with FDA and regulators
as a whole on these real problems. I think obviously we have to come to the grasp, the
reality that there are problems in the medication system and generics, potentially even brand and
all sorts of holes that exist in how the system is now for medications. And we want to be a part
of that solution and work together to ensure that every patient is getting a high quality medication.
Yeah. Well, thank you very much, David. I appreciate your time and
look forward to seeing how this story unfolds.
Thank you very much, Peter, as well for spending the time on your Saturday night.
You can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at peteratiamd.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read,
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
Peter Attia MD, but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk,
the content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
peteratiamd.com forward slash about.