Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast. If you're listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things
I care most about professionally are how to live longer and how to live better. I have
a complete fascination and obsession with this topic. I practice it professionally and
I've seen firsthand how access to information is basically all people need to make better
decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating and sharing this knowledge
is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to me. The sheer
volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a great
team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one example,
our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a
natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As
you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot
of contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now, the
first and most important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm
telling you about something when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it
to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I
just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not absolutely
nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others
have proved can work over time, and that is to create a subscriber model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available
for free. It's that simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose
to support us at, you will get back more than you give. So for example, members will receive
full access to the exclusive show notes, including other things that we plan to build upon. These
are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of our shows.
Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me Anything
episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to hear
these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as
I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with
companies who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and
have them pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope
is that many of you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional
content exclusive for members. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen to this. If you
learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us directly
by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Kyle Kingsbury. Some of you
may recognize Kyle. He's a retired UFC fighter. He's been on the Joe Rogan Experience a number
of times. He's currently the director of human optimization at Onnit. I first met Kyle in person
during a hunting trip in early 2019, though we had both known about each other prior to that and
seen each other in interviews and things like that. We immediately clicked and become very close
since that time. Now, in this episode, which truthfully, when you're interviewing people that
you know pretty well, you don't really know where you're going to go. Honestly, this episode and this
interview went in places I did not expect it to go in and for which I'm incredibly grateful. We
could have spent a lot of this time talking about UFC and mixed martial arts and all of those things,
and that would have been interesting, but we went to places that Kyle has never talked about
publicly. In fact, a couple of things that he hadn't even shared with me privately before. I
was incredibly moved by this experience. We talk about his upbringing, playing football, going to
JC, then college. We talk about his experience with performance enhancing drugs, something I
don't think he's ever really spoken about before. As a little sidebar, we talk about something called
the Wizenator, which is about the funniest thing I've ever heard of. Talk about his transition away
from football after realizing he wasn't going to make it to the NFL. It's during this piece that
Kyle really opens up about this period of depression in his life and his thoughts of suicide that have
been somewhat recurrent and had started as early as the age of seven. He talks about his close calls
with suicide, his eventual transition into MMA and UFC. We end our talk with a conversation around
his experience with ayahuasca towards the end of his UFC career and how that really became the
turning point in his own journey towards being more emotionally healthy and frankly, what's
enabled him to become a father and become the father that he wishes he could have had.
Now, before we get into this conversation, I feel it's really important to have a couple of
disclaimers. First, in this conversation, Kyle really opens up about his past depression and
his thoughts of suicide and how close he was to it on a number of occasions. It's a very heavy
conversation. If you're currently experiencing any thoughts of self-harm or suicide, it is imperative
that you seek out medical help immediately. Second, Kyle and I have a very open and honest
conversation about psychedelics. The substances we speak about are illegal and by no means are we
advocating for anyone to use them or experiment with them. There are physical, physiological,
psychological and legal risks around the use of these plans. This conversation is purely
informational only. Kyle speaks about his personal experiences and how it has shaped his thinking.
So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with my friend Kyle Kingsbury.
Hi, brother. How are you?
I'm doing great, brother.
Happy Father's Day.
Happy Father's Day to you.
Thank you. I forgot it was Father's Day when I woke up and my wife left me this beautiful
little note on the counter. She had gone out running before I got up and it was like,
here's your coffee. It was like the sweetest thing. What did you do for Father's Day today?
Because you're not with your boy.
No, we head back tomorrow to the bay and we'll get like a Father's Day celebration there. My
dad's going to come up from Santa Cruz. So today is just living the dream. I mean,
I'm on your podcast. I'm staying at your house. We're going to shoot arrows after this with a
couple of great guys. So couldn't ask for much more.
So did you grow up in Santa Cruz or San Jose?
Right outside San Jose and Cupertino and Sunnyvale.
Got it. And you played a ton of sports growing up, I imagine. Was football your big one?
Yeah, I wasn't really good. I mean, I got into baseball late, 12. A lot of kids have been
playing for a long time. So I just played one year. Football I got into at 10. And I just loved it
immediately. Like I was playing. At that point, you had weight classes and age classes. So for my
weight and age, it was I think, I don't know, right around 105 to 110 pounds when I was 10.
So I was getting like a beanpole. I mean, then-
That strikes me as big for a 10 year old, but maybe I'm just comparing it to my daughter.
I don't know. At 12-
Which is not a good comparison.
Maybe it was less, but at 12, we were on the Sunnyvale micro rockets. That was 118. Because
I remember that was the last year I could play. We had a running back that weighed the same weight.
We both had to cut weight. And he was a great deal shorter than me. So he was just stacked.
I didn't fill out till much later, like sophomore year of high school.
That's interesting. Kids at 12 cutting weight.
Yeah, I'm not sure that's great. We'd get the seeds or something like that that are salted
and just suck and spit for hours on the drive out to games, that kind of stuff.
So in high school, you played football.
Football and wrestling and junior high in high school.
Got it. So how'd you decide where you wanted to go for college?
I had for a long time wanted to play in the Pac-10. It used to be the Pac-10.
I think every kid wants to get out of state when they go, a lot of them want to get out of state
when they go to university, as you call it. And you don't want to go too far, obviously.
Your parents will throw a fit. My parents would have. But a lot of my good friends that I grew up
with, I knew since I was 12 years old, they were like, dude, we're going to ASU. It's amazing.
And I had to go to junior college because I was garbage, garbage academically. I didn't resonate
a lot with the teachers I had. And you know, we talked about this on my podcast yesterday.
Literally, I can count on one hand, everyone that stuck out and took me under their wing and
saw something in me more than I saw myself. So going to junior college, I went for one year.
And then I realized I can, if I transfer to a different junior college that's right by ASU,
my likelihood of getting in is much higher. So that's what I did.
So why do you think that is, by the way, that high school didn't resonate?
We had a pretty high academic school for a public school. The Wall Street Journal published us as
one of the top 10 public schools in the world. And we had a lot of people from China and Asia
and India coming over. It's even higher now. It's about, I want to say 70 to 80 percent
Asian, including Indian. And the population is what roughly of the high school?
It was huge. I mean, I think we had 2,500 people in our graduating class senior year.
25, so what, you mean there were 10,000 kids in the entire high school?
I don't think so. Maybe that's the wrong number. 2,500 total probably.
Okay. Yeah, couldn't have been 10,000.
Regardless, that's still unbelievable.
They couldn't build whatever the portables. They couldn't get enough portables one year. So we had
breached the number that was allowed in the school district and the superintendent gave it an okay.
Because his son went to school with us.
In a high school that big, you don't actually know everybody in your class?
No, there's many, many kids that I didn't know from that. But we kind of, I mean,
like any high school, you stick to your core group, that kind of thing. And I was fortunate
enough to have those guys all the way through college and after. I'm still close with a lot of them.
I mean, obviously knowing you today, you're intellectually curious and thoughtful and stuff,
but I always find it interesting when you see people who have kind of gone through a transformation
of not resonating with any of that stuff until doing so. But I often wonder, like,
was there a precipitating event? Was there a bad experience you had with a teacher or
something like that? You know, I wasn't nice in high school or prior to that. I got in trouble
from kindergarten on, I'd get into the principal's office, at least three days a week, gotten a lot
of fights growing up. I mean, more than the fighting, just mess with the teachers, you know,
as a class clown and pretty disruptive. And I enjoyed that. It gave me some sense of control
in my environment. I always enjoyed entertaining people and making people laugh. So, like,
that checks off every box. If I can start riffing and clowning on people and everyone's laughing
and looking at me, then I can get a little attention and maybe be, you know, a little bit
of a jerk to the teacher, but it was worth it to me. So, it was actually at ASU, I was taking some
psychology courses in sociology and communication where I was like, oh, this shit matters. Like,
I will, it doesn't matter if I get a philosophy degree or a communications degree. Like,
this is, these are things that I will use the rest of my life. And that was the first time where it
really felt that way. You know, a lot of kids complain like, what am I gonna use algebra for?
What am I gonna use this for? You know, and I think that having that in college really made
me think like, oh, there's a lot to learn. And it's, there's really cool stuff to learn that
resonates with me. And in all those classes, I did really well. It was all A's and B's as well for me.
So, it's interesting because if it weren't for football, I mean, you jumped through a lot of
hoops to get to ASU, you're going to JC's before you get there, right?
And a walk on at ASU.
Okay, so it begs the question, right? If you weren't athletic, if you were the exact same
guy, but you didn't happen to have an ability to play, you know, division one football,
what would you have done after high school?
Something blue collar for sure. My dad, he had a Silicon Valley shelving was a company he created
in the Bay right as the tech boom started. And all these tech companies needed static
control shelving. So he was making a lot of money and he would pay me and my sister to
build a lot of this stuff. And it was fun for me. It was like giant Erector sets, you know,
like we'd we'd play with life size Lego. Yeah, huge stuff. And even you know,
like we'd get into a warehouse. And he and I would be drilling into concrete and pounding,
you know, giant hammers down to get this stuff anchored. And that was always cool. And it paid
really well, but I enjoyed it. So I liked working with my hands there. And he came from a different
era, you know, as every dad is, but he always worked on cars, and he knew a lot about things.
And then he would kind of shun me from living the same life as him. He was like, No, you're going
to go into sales, you're going to make a ton of money, you'll just pay a guy to work on your car,
you just pay a guy to fix your house, because he did all that he did construction since he was 20.
And I was just laughed at it was like, these are like really usable skills. It's nice to know how
to change the oil in your car. You know, like, why aren't you teaching me this stuff? So
thankfully, now he's kind of that have had a little bit of success. He's, he's happy to show
me those things. Why do you think he felt that way? Where did you grow up? Do you grow up in
the same area? He grew up in all my families from Oregon, in the Pacific Northwest, and then they
moved to California, my parents met in Alaska, and then moved to California, I think in large part,
to be by the sun and to get away from their families. And so you know, I grew up there. And
I just think all parents want better for their kids. You know, in that regard, and he saw
that as better, you know, financial success, stability, those kind of things as better.
And were they upset then in high school when you weren't doing well, academically?
Kind of, I mean, they paid attention, and I get in trouble a lot at home. I think for them,
it was really hard to kind of wrap their brain around how you can wrangle someone in at that
point. Because, you know, they fought a lot growing up. I talked about this before. But
one of the books that I really have a lot of love for is Nonviolent Communication
by Marshall Rosenberg, who recently passed away. And whatever that is, my childhood was not. So
they really didn't know how to communicate with one another. And it was like two rams butting heads
all the time. And then they got divorced when I was 13. And from there, that was like the deepest
sense of peace I'd ever had because it was less stress on both of them. They didn't know how to
communicate with each other. And did you and your sister spend time with both of them? Or you
pretty much my mom got full custody, but we'd see my dad every week, you know, twice a week,
something like that. And he was still a big part of our lives. And he lived right down the street.
So and I wanted to see him more because he was a gentler, kinder dad at that point.
Was one of your parents more strict than the other when it came to trying to keep you in
line at school? I'd say I went back and forth, you know, and who took the cake there? You know,
they had different ways of discipline. But yeah, it was, I don't know, I think they were at a loss,
really. But they still they never said, you're not going to go to college like the entire time.
It was you're still going to college. I don't give a shit if you have to go to junior college
for three years, you're going to go to college. So they were pretty pumped when I got an ASU,
which is funny. There was a Simpsons episode where there's the great flood and Ned Flanders
is like, Thank you, Lord, you've spared the righteous and damned the wicked.
And he sees Homer floating in a raft. And he's like, Looks like heaven's easier to get into
than Arizona State. We played that clip all through college. It was it was great. It was
a feather in our cap. But yeah, it is it is an easy school to get into. Yeah, but I mean,
it's a school that also has a great reputation as well. You get in there and and what ASU has got
to be huge. It was massive. It was still I mean, still to this day. And even at that point,
when I was there, one of the high most highly populated schools in the country,
huge campus, gorgeous campus, hot year around for the most part. And you know, the draw for a
young male is that a lot of the ladies there, they can't wear much, they can't hide it, you know,
because of the heat. And that was that was definitely there were some good times there for
sure. So you walked on. And what position do you play? I was defensive end and defensive tackle.
It was probably not probably I was for sure undersized to play the tackle, but too slow to
play the end. So it's kind of an in betweener. And thankfully, you were talking about these great
teachers that you've had one of them was my strength and conditioning coach actually both
strength and conditioning coaches ahead of Arizona State went on to become strength and conditioning
coaches in the NFL. And the head of the strength and conditioning department is going to Joe Ken
big house power is a kind of his moniker now was then to a big house. He's the only guy in
division one football history and the NFL to win strength coach of the year in both division one
football and the NFL. And he's the coach, he's the strength coach for the Carolina Panthers.
Mark ooyama, he was he went on to become the head strength coach for the 49ers. He's I think
he's now with the Vikings. And both those guys really pushed me past whatever limit I thought
I had, you know, like if there's a ceiling, they would push me so far past that I just began to
realize like there is no ceiling and you were how old when you showed up, you're two years older
than the other. Yeah, it was 20. Yeah, it was definitely an impressionable time. And I was
still working through a lot, not really knowing how, you know, drinking a lot doing the party
thing. We were number one party school in the nation. If that's any claim to fame.
One of my friends at med school went to ASU and the stories he told were, I mean, I couldn't,
I couldn't fathom what he was talking about. I mean, I was sort of like he was speaking in
other language. What did you guys actually do was my well, I mean, I can give one example. They
filmed a porno at one of the fraternities that my friends all went to a theater Kai and they
actually shut down all fraternities. Like they don't exist there anymore because of that. So
there was no extreme you couldn't think of that that didn't happen there. I mean, it was really,
it was wild and fun. And I've lost some friends to drug overdoses and many, you know, it was
polarized for sure. You know, and there were still people that went there that were, you know, on the
grind and they had all their ducks in a row. But I think there was a lot more people just
exploring what it felt like to be an adult for the first time. Did you sort of think about this at
the time? Like, I'm escaping from something I'm running from something or did you feel like you
were running to something? I didn't feel you know, it's funny because in those moments of play and
pushing the envelope, it just felt like we're going to tear it up tonight. You know, and it was more
of a celebration like I never was an angry drunk. I never never saw myself as leaning heavily on a
crutch. I mean, for a whole year in junior college, I would wake up and smoke pot every day, I'd have
to wake up my roommate to light the four foot bong for me because I couldn't reach it with my hand.
And that's how I'd start the day. And I had all my classes on Tuesday, Thursday schedule. So five
days off a week. And even in that whole year, I never thought like I'm overdoing it. It was just
the thing to do. And now obviously, that's, it's all much different. But we'll get into plant
medicines. But I think that was really where it lifted the veil and showed me how much I was
destroying myself without realizing it. When you decide I want to go to ASU to play football,
was that a means to an end? Where did you think that was? Was there some thought you had in back
of your mind, I might make it to the NFL. Yeah, I always wanted to play in the NFL. That was the
light at the end of the tunnel. And I think there was a lot of things driving me for that one, my
love of the game, like it was it was my greatest joy. It was my first legal outlet to let off the
steam. And because of the positions I played, I really got to you know, it was buttonheads,
every single play of every moment I was on the field. Once I got to ASU, I didn't play much,
I really was a bench warmer. And at ASU, I had to embrace my role as a secondary guy for the first
time in my life. Everyone who makes it to college was an all star in high school, you know, and the
jump is even higher to the NFL. And I remember seeing a guy who graduated a year before me who
had played, he started every game all four years on defensive line, which if you're a wide receiver,
that's fine. But defensive line, that's pretty tough to do that, to start every game your entire
and he didn't make it to the NFL. And that was like, oh, shit, all right, maybe I should think
about something else. Because even if I get playing time, my senior year, it's pretty unlikely that
that's going to happen. And there was a lot of guys going into Arena League and Canada football
and things like that. And it was like, I don't know, there was a piece of me that that wanted
to be the best or at least play with the best. And if I wasn't going to do that, there was no point.
And I think that there was a decision because I could have gotten a scholarship to play at like
a D two school or D one double A and I said, No, I'd rather walk on and play with the big boys.
So kind of having that mindset going in, I knew I wasn't going to play some subpar level of football,
even though I probably could have extended my career there.
It's amazing. I think for a lot of people that maybe aren't as familiar with that,
what those jumps look like between high school division one and the NFL, I think I was having
this with my daughter a while ago. It must have been during the college football season. And I
don't remember how it came up. But the point I wanted to make to her was, if you take the very,
very, very best team in college football, the team that's going to win the national championship,
and you put them against the very, very worst team in the NFL, it would be the biggest blowout
in the history of football. I mean, in as many possessions as you could have, that's how many
times the NFL team would score. And she just like couldn't understand like how that could happen.
And I didn't have a great explanation for I said, I think one, it's just a much tighter
selection process. And at the end of the day, once you reach the NFL, you're a professional.
And nothing else matters like this is your job. But it is interesting. And it must be sobering
to to get there and sort of realize, oh my god, like, even if you're exceptional in college,
it doesn't guarantee you get to this next level. Yeah, it doesn't guarantee that you're practice
squad. And that's where I was like, damn, and I had a lot of guys from our team did go pro.
Some of them played for a few years on practice squad, other guys actually had like decent careers
playing starting in the NFL, a couple started for the dolphins, different teams. And it was cool to
watch that. But it was like, it didn't seem like there was rhyme or reason to me, because a lot
of these guys in college, you know, they were good, and they made progressions, but they just
kept getting better. That was the difference. Like they were late bloomers, whatever you want to call
it, but they kept improving, kept getting faster, kept learning the routes better, or whatever the
position was. And I think a big part of it is they also are the guys that don't get injured as much.
I think injury avoidance is such an under appreciated piece of professional sports.
I don't know the exact numbers, but you know, the median duration of an NFL player is staggeringly
short, it's like three to five years. And so we can sort of celebrate these people that spend 10,
15 years in the NFL, but they're such outliers. You know, the name of the game first and foremost,
once you're there is just figure out a way to not get hurt. And you talk to Joe Kanner, anybody that's
a strength coach, that's all they're focused on. And it's really even in the offseason,
they might have periods of time where they're working on guys getting a little faster, or
guys getting a little stronger, a little more weight, that kind of thing. But come season,
it's just preservation. That's it. Had you done any performance enhancing drugs in high school?
No, I mean, I played, actually, my senior year started with testosterone, I had a guy
with sustenance 250. And I realized I wanted to play college football. So that was the
that was the place like, all right, I got to put on some size, I've weighed about 220.
Prior to or after?
Prior to and then 230.
And you're what?
Six, four?
Six, yes, extreme half. So that was the time where I think for me, it was about,
if I'm going to do this, let's do this. And being thin, you know, it was like, all right,
I got to put on some size unless I'm going to change positions entirely. But I enjoyed the
positions I played. So let's let's pack on the pounds. And I was pretty disappointed only
gaining 10 pounds. But there was, that was a catalyst to what sleep was, you know, and I had
my dad telling me like, you got to sleep better, you got to get to bed on time, you can't stay out
all night, those kind of things. And, and you got to eat well, you got to eat more. And at that
point, it was just a numbers game, you know, it didn't mean eating the food that I eat now is just
me eating more, you know, getting more protein and more calories in general. So I think once I
started to pay attention to that stuff, that's where I was starting to gain the size.
And then throughout junior college was testosterone still kind of the staple of supplementation?
Yeah, no doubt. And I gained fairly consistently still kind of undersized. So I think by the end of
my junior college, I was about 250, you know, and put that in perspective. I mean, that's big for a
lot of people, but there's linebackers that are 250 pounds, plenty of middle linebackers that are
that size. So for the position still small. Yeah. And then what's it like when you get to a place
like ASU? Not and again, I'm not singling out ASU. I think this is probably true. It has to be true
of every Division One school, right? Yeah. And I don't want to come across as Floyd Landis. So I'm
not going to paint a picture of what other people are doing. No, no, yeah. Just for yourself. Like
what? What was that step up? It was good because I you know, I was introduced to a doctor, a natural
path and he'd for better and for worse. And we'll talk about what that worse looks like. He would
give me anything that I wanted. Thankfully, we were doing routine blood work to look at something
my father who I included on this. We're pretty adamant about. So that's when I first experimented
with growth hormone, IGF one, different things. I think when I when I realized I wasn't going to go
pro, that was when I started taking a decoderbal and with testosterone. And that was great for
inflammation and just feeling better. At that point, it really was like how big can I get? And
I still had a ceiling. You know, my senior year I was 268. I couldn't gain a pound more. And I
was having just and just give me a sense of dose. How much you were you were mixing decadrone and
decipinate 50 50 or like one to one ratio of those? No, it was probably 600 milligrams of
test to P and eight and 400 milligrams of decoderbal and you would take a week. It's about a gram total.
Yeah, which is just amazing. I want to kind of put this in perspective for listeners.
I have a subset of patients who are getting testosterone replacement therapy for, you know,
hypogonadism, right? So middle aged guy who's you can't get his testosterone back into a normal
range with all the usual stuff beginning by the way with sleep is sort of rule number one. You
don't run a place testosterone until a person's sleeping reasonably well. But to put this in
perspective, I would say a normal starting dose of testosterone sip. You know, eight is somewhere in
the vicinity of 80 to 100 milligrams a week. And we like to divide that twice a week because the
half life of sip. You know, it's about three days. So you'll get a smoother dose. A couple of patients
will even do it daily. You know, they'll put in sort of with sip in a sip in a sub cue injection
and they'll do 10 to 13, 10 to 14 milligrams a day would be sort of a daily dose. And then that's,
you know, and you know, it's really interesting, by the way, with that you see no FSHLH suppression.
The natural range is about 11 milligrams a day, give or take for men. So that's like where you're,
you're kind of mimicking that. Yeah, that's the part that blows my mind is we just discovered
this by accident when a patient just on his own decided to start day, like he felt started out
doing it injecting once a week and then twice a week and you're cutting the dose down, of course,
each time and then he decided, well, daily must give you the most perfectly smooth way to do it.
And I said, well, yeah, if you don't mind giving yourself a little shot every day, but it's
actually a pretty, the sub cue with the tiny needle is not a big deal. So when we looked at his blood,
it was really amazing. He was like, it's the only pace I'd ever seen a testosterone sip. You know,
he had normal FSHLH he'd looked like he was not taking exogenous testosterone. And then we tried
this with a couple of other patients. And sure enough, that's the case. I think the highest amount
of testosterone I've ever prescribed to a patient is probably in the neighborhood of 140 to 160
milligrams in a week. And if you're talking, did you say 600 of sip, you need 400 a decade or vice
versa, but they're one to one equivalent. So it's a thousand a week, right? Which is, I've seen that
a lot in athletes and bodybuilders and stuff like that. What kind of side effects do you have from
a dose that high? Well, that's where I capped it, you know, and there's bodybuilders that'll go in
the three to five gram a week range. And from what I know, loosely, they likely have more receptor
sites and they're going to deal with the side effects, no matter what's coming up for them.
I'd get acne and season, but I think it was from the shoulder pads. I never washed those kind of
things. So yeah, I'd get acne and stuff like that on the back. I don't know how much that affected
my mind because it felt good. And with the amount of training that I was doing, it was a positive.
Did you understand what testosterone at the time? I know today you have a much better
understanding, of course, but at the time, did you understand what this molecule is doing to
transcription factors in your, you know, cells and how it's helping you recover better? Like,
or was it were you not? I mean, that's maybe a dumb question. What, what kid in college is
thinking of that? But did you just think like, taking this makes me bigger and stronger? Did
you have a sense of why? Well, I understood an increased protein synthesis, things like that.
I think there was a book called Anabolix 2000 by Dr. William Llewellyn, which is where I started to
take a deep dive in it. You know, that's the funny, so Llewellyn's Principles of Pharmacology is one of
my favorite books on the entire study of Anabolix. I have like, it's like, you know, the volume.
Yeah, it's like a Bible. It's a Bible. And it's, it's long and wide. It's not just thick. Like,
it's, it's a really, it's a great place if anybody's looking to do this. No, I can't recommend it
highly enough because one of the things I love about Llewellyn is totally unemotional. There's
no editorializing, right? It's not like these things are horrible. These things are wonderful.
It's like, okay, let's go through every single one of these molecules painfully deep. And we'll just
talk about the relative differences, similarities between them, what they do, what they don't do.
And yeah, I'm a big, I'd love to meet Llewellyn. I don't know if he, he must be still alive. He's
certainly got to be young. He's got to be, he was doing, I think the last one I read was,
I think he had 2007 was the last one that I read.
I have a more recent one than that. And I've seen pictures of him and he looks like he's young.
Funny of mine had like 2011. So like he's for sure still around if he's writing books.
He's not on his deathbed, you know, how hard it is to write a book.
So you're reading Llewellyn, which is actually kind of interesting. I'm guessing not everybody
who's taken testosterone is reading Llewellyn's principles of pharmacology to understand what's
going on. One thing I just curious about, you mentioned you were never the nasty drunk, right?
You were, so one of the things that people talk about is, well, if you take that much
anabolic steroid, you, it must change your mood. Did you experience that?
I didn't feel, and that's what I was alluding to with that positive well-being.
I couldn't wrap my head around roidridge for the life of me. And then to that note,
I began to see like whether the guy was on like five friends that had that particular outcome
from anabolic. They were that way without it. They hadn't unpacked their shit to begin with.
And that's why whatever amplifiers in them is going to draw that out. Same thing goes with
alcohol or anything else. You know, you, you give somebody a little fuel to the fire. And
I think it was Wayne Dyer who said, if you squeeze an orange, what do you get? Orange shoes. If
somebody squeezes you, what do you get? Well, it's whatever's going to come out of you. Right.
And that's, that's the difference. Not that I was all rainbows and fucking clouds in the inside.
I still had a lot of work to do, which wouldn't come for years later.
That's interesting to see at that dose. Cause I mean, I don't have experience clinically with
those doses. I've, I've seen it anecdotally like in cases like yours, but I've, I've never had the
ability to clinically observe what happens at what we call suprafysiologic doses, but at
physiologic doses, which I have lots of experience with patients, I've never once seen any of these
horror show side effects that people talk about. And I've come to the same conclusion,
which is steroids are a lot like money. You know, people talk about, well, that guy's a rich asshole.
And it's like, I don't think those are necessarily the same thing. He's an asshole who then got a
lot of money and that just allowed him to amplify his assholedness. And similarly, like, I think if
you take a really aggressive, angry person and you give them more anabolic steroids, you can probably
amplify that phenotype, but you don't create that phenotype. That's why I've seen some of the
most beautiful people in the world I've seen are some of the wealthiest people as well.
Cause they were just happened to be good people. You give them a bunch of money. Now they can
amplify their good through that. So yeah, I think, I think of those the same. And it, but, but what's
interesting is that at such high doses, my observation, at least anecdotally in you is still
the same, which is didn't, didn't it actually seem to be quite positive. This is a topic I'm super
interested in because I think that the science on this whole topic is so misunderstood. I think
that the fear mongering around these drugs, and by the way, to be really clear, I have no idea if
the doses you were taking are safe. My intuition is it's probably not a good idea to be clear.
So anybody listening to this who thinks that me having this discussion is somehow endorsing
taking a thousand milligrams a week of testosterone and testosterone equivalent is a good idea.
I don't think it is, but that's mainly because I don't have data. I don't have long-term data.
I've seen short-term data, right? I've seen studies of eight, 12, 16 weeks where you put
athletes on those kinds of doses, which is effectively 10 times the normal amount of
testosterone. These studies don't find bad outcomes. Of course, you were probably taking
it for longer than 16 weeks. And that's my whole point, which is, I don't know how to extrapolate
outside of the normal window. But when you start to talk about normal physiologic doses and all the
fear-mongering that comes with that stuff, I don't know what it is about our society. We really
love to misunderstand things. There was a very famous story that was talked about in that
documentary that Mark Bell, or sort of that Chris Bell made. You know the story about that kid?
Bigger, stronger, faster.
Yeah. I forget the boy's name.
He got really depressed when he jumped off because he didn't have post-cycle therapy.
Yeah. I would even put a different spin on that, which is, and again, this is, I don't mean to
sound unempathetic at all because I know that in the documentary they feature very prominently his
father, who's adamant that steroids killed his son. And if I were in his shoes, I think I'd probably
say the same thing. But this gets to the point of, I would argue that people who are going to take
steroids for non-medical use are probably searching for something anyway. There's a void that's
probably trying to be filled there. And in the case of this boy who, I forget his name because of the
T. I think it was like Tyler or Taylor or something like that. You know, high school kid,
I think he was a baseball player if I recall. You take 10 kids who play high school baseball,
there's a subset of them that are going to gravitate towards wanting this. Maybe it's
because they want to be better. Maybe they want to be better because they're sort of filling some
other void. It's probably that that at least increases their susceptibility to depression
and not that, not that the testosterone is causing the depression. That's sort of my view on that.
I think that's a bit too nuanced to explain, but it feeds into this discussion of which one's
driving the other. And that's why when you look at studies of this stuff where you get the luxury of
not having to rely on a person self-selecting into it and instead you can use the process of
randomization, I just think these findings just, they never show up in the medical literature of
testosterone use. Now you mentioned growth hormone as well. Why growth hormone? What did it offer
above testosterone? I think from a recovery standpoint, and I don't know how much of that
was placebo effect. And I was taking probably four IUs a day. Which is not that much actually
in the big picture, is it? No, but I could feel the side effects, like little tingly fingers in
the middle of the night, some level of carpal tunnel. And that's also for sure had to do with
the water weight I was carrying and just being a swole for lack of a better word. Did you ever take
growth hormone without testosterone? No. So we don't know what growth hormone alone would have
felt like. Yeah, but I do remember, I mean, playing defensive line, you get bumps and bruises
every day and I rolled my ankle really hard and the next day it was like nothing had ever happened.
And I was astonished. I thought I was going to wake up and have blue and purple around my foot
for a month. It was a bad, bad sprain. And literally the next day, like there was no swelling.
It felt great. I went right back to practice and I could do everything again. So I was like,
okay, this is worth a thousand dollars a month. Like it just made perfect sense to me at that
point. How did you come up with the money for all this? Was the growth hormone alone a thousand
dollars a month? It certainly was. So without, let's just say that part was sponsored.
We'll just leave it at that. And the testosterone, while nowhere near as expensive, at the doses
you're taken can't be, it's still got to be a couple hundred bucks a month, right? Yeah,
especially because it's through a doctor and obviously insurance isn't covering any of that.
Now, did you guys get drug tested in college? We did. And I don't know if you remember this,
but there was a thing, I think it was, I don't want to get the guy's name wrong. Maybe we can
look it up. Ryan, can you look up if it was Ontario Smith that got caught with the Wizenator?
So the Wizenator 5000. I forgot about the Wizenator. The old Wizenator.
It was so great. I remember going into the weed shop back then. Of course, they didn't have
cannabis there. They just had bogs and whatever. And I saw this thing and they had like seven
different colors of a penis. Like what the hell is this doing here? And they're like,
oh man, that's for your piss test. And I was like, are you serious? Okay. All right. We got
confirmation. It was Ontario Smith. He fucked it up for everyone. But you know, I've seen all the
different colors and I'm like, huh, so how does it work? You get somebody's clean urine. He's like,
no, you don't even have to do that. It comes with synthetic urine. And then there's a Japanese
heat pad that sticks to the outside. And then you have the other part of it pressed against
your pubic hair or whatever. And then when you're asked to pull it out, you just pull out that one.
And it's kind of like, do you remember the toy water weenie back in the eighties? It's got a
little click in. It's like surgical tubing you'd fill with water and then squirt people. So anyways,
you unclick this thing and just free flows and you can push on it a little bit to get it out. But
it's always at like one and a half X, whatever the a hundred milliliter standard is. Does the drug
test or not actually look at you voiding? I mean, I had a guy look at my penis and he saw the
wizinator, but I had my pants on. He didn't make me drop trowel, you know, whereas what does he do
when he sees a purple penis? Well, I have a funny story about that. So my penis,
my fake penis didn't look far off. This discussion is taken out of context, is out of control.
We'll have him clip this for social. My fake penis looked very similar to my actual penis in
terms of color. Loaning that out to one of my teammates, who was half black, didn't go so well
for him. Thankfully he said it as long as the test is clean when he got caught, I won't get you in
trouble. And of course he got off because he had clean piss. The issue, what we saw with the
wizinator in pro sports is that the synthetic urine contained no levels of hormone. So you'd
show zero on testosterone, zero sex hormones across the board. So then they know something was up.
That would qualify as a positive test. I was kind of rolling the dice with NCAA. I figured at that
point I wasn't going to get, you know, what are they going to do? Bust the guy who's fucking third
string, barely made travel squad. So yeah, I was rolling the dice there. They make you go to your
ankles with your pants or whatever you're wearing. The team guys, they just glanced down, see what
you got as long as it's a penis and you're not pulling something out of a cup, you're okay.
In other words, there was sort of the, was this the NCAA that was basically turning a blind eye
to this then? The team guys. And then the NCAA, they would have you pull your pants down, but they're,
you know, I don't, from what I understand, not super weird about it because
it wasn't invasive. Like I hear horror stories from, from the guys that are fighting now and
have you saw to knock on their door at 3 AM. Yeah. The wizinator is not going to work when
you saw that or Wada comes, right? No, not even close. Never would have. I'm amazed. I mean,
I've never really thought about this problem specifically, but I'm amazed people haven't
come up with artificial bladders and things that are more nuanced. Well, I think it was,
what was that movie with the old football movie? I think it was in the nineties with Latimer.
Latimer, Jack to the gills. Yeah. He did the oil change where he would pull urine out of his
bladder and then have someone else's injected in with a TCC syringe. How can I be blanking on what
that was? It wasn't any given Sunday, was it? No. The program. Yeah. Yeah. James Con. Yeah. Yeah.
I don't know how often that was going down. I don't think people were going to that, those
kind of extremes in college, maybe at higher levels of sport, but is growth hormone detectable
on any other tests? It certainly wasn't even something they were testing for in college.
I know a couple of people who have had that come up for them in fighting now with you saw to,
to what degree that's accurate. I'm not sure. So, you know, a lot of these guys have lawyered up
and are fighting it whether or not they were successful or not. I have no idea.
So college comes to an end, you sort of realize you're not going to make it to the NFL.
What are you thinking about as the next chapter? I was just in the moment. You can model the
Wizenator. That's always got to be on the table as an option, a work opportunity.
That's all right. That was my next venture. You know, I quit going after my senior year of
football and I was really starting to battle my own personal demons at that point, that same doctor.
So I talked about the better and worse of having a doctor that would give me anything. He was
prescribing me two milligrams Xanax, call them Zany bars because they had the four squares,
60 at a time, 10 milligram volume, 60 at a time with five refills on both, 10 milligram.
I didn't know that was even legal. Meaning I didn't know that.
It's not legal. He went to jail later.
Oh, okay.
He gone. One of my friends died. So that guy, I'm sure he's out now, but needless to say,
also 10 milligrams of Vicodin, 60 at a time, five refills. Now, thankfully for me personally,
and I've lost a lot of friends to opiates, it was very hard for me to take a high dose
and feel good. I would get nauseated and puke violently. So there was always like this.
You had a built-in governor.
Yeah, built-in governor when it came to opiates. But having had a lot of stuff that I hadn't worked
on internally, and we can dive into that, but it just, these anti-anxiety medications were
fucking perfect. I would feel great. There's a euphoria. I'd sleep very well if I was using
cocaine or ecstasy, and these are pressed shitty pills, not the type of MDMA we talk about with
Rick Doblin, just a whole different ballgame. I'd be up till 5am, then I'd take my Xanax,
something like that. And that's, you're playing that roller coaster.
So you're already done with football, but you're still like finishing college at this point?
And that's when I quit going to school. So I didn't see, I'd finished 95% of my communications
classes in sociology. And at that point, in order to stay eligible, I'd switch my degree so many
times, there was this bullshit degree called a Bachelor in Interdisciplinary Studies, which is
fine. It's like two minors to equal a major. And I enjoyed the coursework. But once I got to my
senior year, a lot of the classes became actual BIS classes where you would go in and have to
write these long ass papers that you'd present to a potential employer on why it was actually
better that you had a basket waving degree and not an actual degree. And I couldn't stand it.
Like it was just so fake to me. And really like not enjoying school at that point,
not having a reason to be there, not having a reason to stay eligible.
Are you taking loans out to be in school at this point?
Yeah, yes. Oh, yeah.
So you're paying to do this thing that you think is not helpful.
Correct. You know, I said I'd take a semester off, my parents didn't really fuss over it.
And really got into pills with alcohol and cocaine and ecstasy. And that was something that I've
been doing. But because of football keeping me there was a point in time where I knew I had to
straighten up each and every year. And really being a fan of the gym and who I was training with,
that also would kind of regulate me. So even in the off season, I was still kind of,
I was mindful of the debauchery. And then without that, it was mindless debauchery, really.
And I was very depressed. I didn't know what I wanted to do from that point on.
And probably came to one of the most depressing points in my life. And to give some background
from, and I talked about this on a solo podcast I did a long time ago, which for sure, I don't
think anyone here has heard it. But from about seven years old on, I had thoughts of suicide.
And like pretty vivid, like thinking of my dad's handguns or his rifles, or how I would use a bow
and arrow, put it plainly. I remember having a conversation with my dad on the deck of our condo.
And I asked him, what would happen if I fell off of this and landed face first in the concrete?
And he said, you probably wouldn't die. You just be really messed up from that point on.
And but that was me, he didn't realize at the time, it was me checking to see like,
can I kill myself by jumping off this fucking balcony?
And how old were you? Seven?
Seven, yeah, six, seven. And that would circle back. I mean, many times throughout the year,
that would circle back. What do you think was at the root of that?
It was really hard. It was really hard to see my family fight
so often, you know, it was constant. And my little sister is just a year younger than me.
And I could feel her shift, I could feel her clothes inside and wall off. And,
you know, being the oldest, my dad was the oldest, he was a little bit harder on me than her.
And that stuck out. It was just really, I mean, without too many details, it was very, very
difficult. And it really felt I think at the root of a lot of depression is this concept that it
will never get better. There's no light at the end of the tunnel. There's no way out of this.
And that's how I felt most of my childhood was just like, this is not going to get better.
I remember when I was 10, my mom said, I'm thinking about divorcing your father. And I said,
yes, do it. My sister was in panic. She didn't want her family to get broken apart.
But a part of me knew once that happened, like they would be better people for it,
because they weren't meant to be together. And it took three more years for that to actually happen.
But yeah, it was incredibly difficult. And I think coming to this place now,
where once again, I felt like I didn't have any viable option of doing something that was
meaningful with my life. And not to mention, from a neurochemistry standpoint, just playing with all
the buttons, you know, up, down, up, down, lack of sleep, you had Matthew Walker on three episodes,
like I now see that very clearly when I read his book, while we sleep, I was like, well, yeah,
no shit, no shit. I was I was messed up in the head. I watched the sun come up many, many nights,
in the beautiful double edged sword of an anti anxiety pill is that you feel fucking great while
you're on it. And the second you stop taking it, all that unworkthrough stuff is still there.
It's just waiting to come up once that chemicals out of your body. And so I had a fight with my
girlfriend at the time. And there really was this thought in my head that I'll never be loved,
I will never find love. And with that, I took every remaining pill that I had. And I drove up to
the top of parking lot seven at Arizona State. Thankfully, a security guard guard saw me pulling
up like 2am got out of the car stripped down naked and walked climbed one more flight of stairs and
was standing on the edge about ready to jump. And I heard, Hey, what are you doing up there? And I
looked back. Actually, let me rewind that I'd been to church growing up, but I didn't consider
myself a religious person. Most of that stuff didn't resonate with me at all. Particularly
with regarding gay people going to hell, like I was from the Bay Area, that shit really didn't
resonate with me. And there was a lot of other things that stood out to me as it didn't, it
didn't make sense. Yeah, hypocritical, that kind of stuff. And but as I was standing there before
the security guard said anything, that was my first real spiritual experience. Like this, I don't
know if it was the chemicals kicking in, but this wash of warmth came throughout my body,
from head to toe. And it was the most peace that I had felt ever in my entire life.
You think it's because you sensed it might be over?
Yeah, it was the time to go. For me, like there was no no reason to stay. And this voice and it
might have been a voice in my head, it might have been outside of me. I don't think that's the
point. The voice just said, not yet. It's okay. So this guy gets you off the ledge, literally,
gets me off the ledge. And I wake up in a hospital with all my family there. They flew out from
California, obviously to Arizona. I don't really have a recollection of what happened after that,
other than I remember asking my mom, like, why was this male nurse such a dick? And she was like,
you weren't very nice to him. You weren't very nice to anyone here. And knowing myself, I just
kind of laughed and said, yeah, that's for sure what happened. So I spent about a week in a detox
center. They had everything from group therapy to activities. They wanted to wean me off the anxiety
medication, knowing how long I'd been on that. And then, like I had mentioned, there was no real
problem with the opiates. So they didn't wean that. But they put me on colonopin for the week.
And the first dose I took, I remember walking up to the nurse like, I'm fucking high right now.
I don't want to be high. I want that. I want to go cold turkey. And they're like, no, it's
really important that we wean you because you can have potential side effects here. And I was like,
I don't care. I'm not going to take it. I'm telling you right now, I'm not going to take it.
So thankfully, they they cut my dose to nothing. That was an interesting time, because there was a
lot of people there that had, I mean, not to make comparisons, but people that didn't have all the
same opportunities that I had, and didn't look the way that I looked and weren't as young as me or
as fit as me or any of the things that I had going on. A lot of them didn't have family there
supporting them. My family would come in every day, they were staying in a hotel, they had nothing
else to do. But but check out after me. I think at that stage, you know, when you have other people
saying like, what are you doing here? You have so much going on. It's like you don't fucking know.
And that's, to my point, when someone's depressed, they see through their lens, they don't see through
anyone else's lens. It's just like this is water, right? And so you could have everyone on Earth,
fucking Obama could show up and say like, look what you have going on for you. And you'd say,
you don't know what's going on for me. And that's really how I felt. When I got out, I had a
psychologist and a psychiatrist and the psychiatrist, I was pretty adamant that I didn't want to go down
the SSRI rabbit hole. I had family members that had done that. And I saw it was just a merry go
round of different things. And finally, when they found something that would work, they didn't
inevitably have to increase the dosage. So I said no to that. I was prescribed lithium. And I took
it for about a week. And I remember thinking like, I am a fucking mute. My whole life, I've
been an extrovert. I've enjoyed talking to people. I've walked through public speaking classes in
college. Now I'm a mute. There was no high, there was no low. The diagnosis was bipolar.
What dose of lithium did they put? They must have put you on a very heavy dose.
Probably. I know some, you know, I think we know some people that benefit very greatly from a low
dose of that. But at the time, it was like, I can't do this either. And I remember talking to
the psychiatrist who actually resonated more with me than the psychologist. I've had great
therapists, but that guy wasn't it. Psychiatrist was like, all right, if you don't want to take
anything, read these. And he handed me six studies on fish oil in the brain. And that was my first
like, okay, from like a holistic standpoint of what supplementation can look like rather than
just creatine and testosterone. Maybe there's something to this and started something with
fish oil. More importantly than that, started creating space for myself to actually look at
my life and just create like a distance from the party atmosphere. Like maybe I can take a break.
And with that started to see a shift, started to get goals. Were you back in class at this point?
No, I never went back to school, never went back to school. So I'm still a senior at ASU officially.
You know, I had fought a lot growing up, like I talked about and I'd watched the UFC from its
infancy was a huge fan of pride. I had no intention of becoming a professional fighter,
but I knew what I was missing. And what I was missing in football was camaraderie. It was being
able to butt heads. It was some physical interaction with another human. And then the training, I would
go instead of training with all these guys and having some of the best coaches in the world hyping
me up before I lift, I'm lifting by myself a 24 hour fitness. I'm on a fucking treadmill. Like
there was no real draw to do that. I felt like a rat on the wheel. Knowing that's something I
missed. I wanted to start training in mixed martial arts just for the training, just for the
camaraderie, just for the ability to learn something new each day and not really know like,
I don't want to have to design my entire workout in the gym. Like, let me go here and learn
something brand new and maybe make some friends in the process. And probably three months into that,
there was a guy at gym owner out in Arizona who ran rage in the cage was a local,
very low level show. And he said, dude, you're big, you're handsome. You played football,
you're athletic, fight for me at heavyweight. You don't have to do it one time. If you don't
want to do it again, you don't have to. And so I said, all right. In my first two fights,
I won in under 30 seconds. I'm not saying I was great or anything like that. And what I am saying
is there is a difference between an athlete that comes from division one and a lot of the guys
fighting heavyweight at the time. And this was in MMA? Yes, mixed martial arts. And what are the
just quickly, what are the rules? What are the parameters? I think everybody's heard of MMA.
People sometimes don't understand the difference between MMA and UFC. Like they're sometimes
people use these terms synonymously. But let's start with what mixed martial arts means.
And analogy I like to use is mixed martial arts is to the UFC as tissues are to Kleenex.
And a lot of people will say, can you hand me a tissue? They'll say, pass me a Kleenex,
whether it's Kleenex brand or not. So the UFC being the highest level of sport that is mixed
martial arts. And then mixed martial arts can have there's there's MMA shows all over the world
now at varying levels. But mixed martial arts is the practice of bringing all things together.
Typically, they use four to five ounce gloves that are fingerless, you can grab,
you can't strike in the back of the head. There used to be varying rules, you know,
in pride, you could stomp a guy's face, you could soccer, could guys face while he's on the ground,
you can knee a guy's head while he's on all fours, none of that's allowed in the UFC,
or in all of North America, to my understanding.
Can't what else can you not? Yeah, it's probably easier to say what you can't do.
You can't kick to the nuts. Can't pull hair. And a lot of this stuff when when MMA started was
allowed, you know, it was no holds barred. What's the what? Where's the genesis of MMA? When did it
really first start? I think it's different. You know, for different people, different camps would
say it was Bruce Lee different camps would say so they would say jute kundo was the original.
Yeah, and kaji Kempo also was different forms of full contact karate kickboxing jiu jitsu.
We just had john hackleman on my podcast, and he was a kaji Kempo background out of Hawaii. And now
he created Hawaiian Kempo. So there's there's merit in both, you know, but it is that bridging
of different forms and the arc of MMA. If you haven't seen it started off as like, this is what
I'm good at versus this is what you're good at. It was like the Kuma tan blood sport. So you'd have
a boxer against a sumo wrestler. And then, you know, as it progressed, people begin to have more
than one trick pony a couple skill sets. So I'm good at defending takedowns, and I'm really good
at stand up. So I can stand at bangs brawling brawl, or terms that were being used or I'm a great
wrestler. And I can pound you when you're on the ground. So ground and pound became a thing. And
then as it's transitioned, and now you have to know everything in any position, because if you have a
weakness, it's going to be exploited. And in parallel to this, you've got this Brazilian
jiu-jitsu that is being, you know, you've got these incredible gracies and all these other guys
over there doing this other form of traditional jiu-jitsu. And when does that start to merge with
MMA? Because today, it's almost impossible to distinguish like, it's almost impossible to
imagine MMA without Brazilian jiu-jitsu, right? I think right as the UFC came along, that was the
point. And when did the UFC come into 93? So it was a different group of ownership. I forget the
guy's name, Bob something, but he started the UFC with in large part with the gracies. And they,
according to their story, wanted to bring in a guy who wasn't the best, wasn't the most fit,
wasn't the strongest. And they brought in hoist Gracie, just to illustrate like this is a technical
thing. It's not that he's a gifted athlete. And he's going to do this to you. He's not our best
athlete. He's not our best Gracie. And he can still do this to you. I mean, they showed what
jiu-jitsu was all about. It was awesome to watch that to see the difference. But now you see even
the sport of jiu-jitsu has really progressed. There's guys that focus on that their whole lives
and careers and you see them in jiu-jitsu sport competitions. And it's just a whole different
level. Their orders of magnitude greater than some of the guys in the UFC. Going back to when
you start training in an MMA gym and have these couple of quick fights. At that point in time,
outside of your fitness and athleticism strength, etc. Did you have any formal training in boxing,
kickboxing, martial arts? It was only wrestling. I had let me correct myself when I was 17. I went
with another wrestling teammate of mine. We didn't want to do tracker or any of that spring sports.
So we went into AKA American Kickboxing Academy, which is in San Jose. At that time, Frank Shamrock
was the coach there. This is today regarded as one of the most prolific training institutes
of MMA in the world. Yeah, still to this day. But you just got lucky. It just happened in your
backyard. Very fortunate that it literally was in my backyard. And we, you know, the first three
months I went there, that was about it. I went there for three months and started training for
football again. It was awesome. I loved it. And I was just thinking like, I'm going to learn this
stuff so I can kick more ass on the street. You know, that was really it. And it'll keep me in
shape and maybe help me be a better wrestler, those kinds of things. But it took some time. I mean,
once I got back into fighting, well, once I started fighting professionally and really
trying to learn this stuff, in large part, I had forgotten a lot from wrestling and most of the
things that I learned at AKA when I was young. So, but also having learned how to be coachable
was really just there to absorb as much as I could. And out in Arizona, we had some good guys.
It's not at the level that it is now, you know, you have some pretty great gyms out in Arizona
these days, but it was still still kind of young in terms of who you train with.
I didn't know that I'd fight in the UFC or anything like that. It was just fun for me.
And again, you could think for the listener, the UFC is like the NFL. And you have an infinite
number of other arena football leagues and all these other sorts of things. And you could be
playing in those leagues and maybe one day think you make it to the UFC or the NFL as it were.
Yeah. And that was the goal. I mean, or or pride, they were equal, but I, it wasn't my dream to play
or fight in Japan for that matter. I would have happily done it, but I just kept going,
you know, and I fought often. I wasn't training nearly by the standard I needed to be at. So as
I was building this record, were you sustaining at this?
Zero. I had no injuries at all. Early on in my career was only when I got to,
when I circled back. So I was six and oh, was now fighting in King of the cage, which you could
look at as kind of a bridge between the two. Still a massive jump from King of the cage to
the UFC. But a lot of guys that fought in the UFC had fought in King of the cages.
So how much are you getting paid per fight?
A thousand dollars a fight.
And how frequently do they let you fight?
It was four times a year with the contract. Prior to that, it was $100 a fight in rage in the cage.
It's just to give you perspective, $100 to go in and fight.
Oh, God. That's even worse than boxing.
Yeah, it was. I mean, that's still in the I don't know what it is today. You know,
this is still when things were starting or relatively. I mean, it's not like I was
fighting in 93. That's when it was starting. Got to six and oh, had a loss. My first loss
of my career in King of the cage. What happened in that fight?
I really hadn't hadn't trained much for it because it was walking through people. It was almost like
Tyson and Buster Douglas, you know, and my coach was trying to get me in there more. And it was
like, yeah, whatever, you know, and you think a humbling experiences like I was just had my head
in the clouds. I thought I was the shit thought I was going to just walk through people until I got
to the UFC, then I'd really have to start training. So I went into a fight. I think it was Laughlin,
Nevada, and just got the shit beat out of me. I mean, it was the first time I got stung with a
punch, need me in the head. It was Herb Dean who ref the fight. He actually stopped the fight with
me on my feet. I was getting beat so bad. I had a really good coach who actually had a
fight. It happened in the first round. It was a bad beating. My striking coach trained under
Dan and Asanto, who was one of Bruce Lee's main students. So he was a JKD guy. And I learned JKD
from one of Dan's six students. That's amazing. Yeah, this guy Vince Perez-Mazzola, incredible
human. He basically pulled me aside and he said, look, I can teach you all of this stuff, things
that people aren't doing in the UFC. But you need more than me. You need a team. You need training
partners. All my training partners fought at 185, a weight class underneath me, or two weight
classes underneath me. And he was like, you should go home and train at AKA again. They have a team.
They're great. There's many great guys that fight in the UFC and that's where you ultimately want
to go now. So you should move home. And at the same time, my strength coach from ASU hit me up,
Joe Ken. And he said, Kingsbury, I heard you're fighting right now. You got to go back to AKA.
What the fuck are you doing? And I was like, I don't know, coach, I kind of like it here in
Arizona. He's like, no, fuck all that. Kane's there. So Kane was the heavyweight wrestler at
ASU. He took fifth, I think, in NCAA senior year in nationals. And he's one of the greatest heavy
weights of all time. But he was only two and O at AKA at the time. So I moved back in with my dad
and started training at AKA, largely just getting my ass beat every day until I could finally get
my skills and endurance and everything up to par to be able to hang just to hang with Kane for
one round. We were rotating fresh bodies on him. I mean, it was a really hard entry point into what
being a real pro looked like. And how did you guys spar? Like, obviously very familiar with
boxing where you can spar, you're using slightly larger gloves. You've got headgear, though I don't
think headgear does much except prevent cuts. And it's just a little easier to dial back the intensity.
But when it comes to elbows, knees, things like that, like how are you sparring basically at 100%
all the time? So we weren't using elbows at the time. If you had knee pads, you could knee.
Generally, we wouldn't need the head. It was full go. I mean, it was it was a fight three days a
week. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, you're in a fight period. Thankfully, that we've seen the sport
evolve. And that's not really the case. There's still some smaller gyms and backwoods areas that
still spar like that. It was a huge issue in the UFC for a long time. Fighters would get to camp.
They'd train like animals that spar as hard as the fight was. And then a week before the fight,
they get hurt or the week of the fight, they would get hurt. It was a real issue. And I think it
still happens now. But thankfully, people are being more mindful of the approach. And also knowing
once you have that level of experience, and you've kind of weeded out who's not going to make it,
you can scale back and work technically. You look at things like Muay Thai, which is a form of kick
boxing from Thailand. They fight on a weekly basis. So their sparring is just touch and go.
It's highly technical, and they're never trying to hurt one another. So I think we're going to
start to see that more and more in the sport of mixed martial arts. I did Muay Thai for two years
when I was in college. And some of the most painful injuries I had were, you know, blank
Shin to Shin contact. My God. That's the only thing that hurt me in in actually inside the octagon in
a fight in the UFC was Shin to Shin contact. I could get drilled and actually touch canvas,
snap out of it and get back up and I wouldn't have felt the punch. Like a hard rib shot. If I get
the wind knocked out of me, that hurts. But the Shin to Shin, that's the one where you're like,
wow, I might not be able to walk tonight. Well, I trained I was trained by a guy from Thailand who
can I still remember his name to I'd love to I'd love to know what he's up to now. But
his name was Eric and his shins were so badly conditioned, meaning so well conditioned for the
concept of the sport that you could hit them with not all out, but you could take a baseball bat
and somewhat like just gently, not gently, but like with medium force whack his shins and he was
unfazed at a level where even if you roll a baseball bat across a normal person's shin at
the wrong angle, it's very sensitive. And yeah, I was kind of like, look, I mean, I'm done with
trying to be a professional fighter here. I go to college now. I don't think I'm going to
do the work that's necessary to make my shins look like Eric's over there.
It's just not. I mean, it's just it's true, even though I didn't know much at the time,
I sort of knew like that's just the bridge too far right now. But gives you an appreciation about
sport. I mean, I used to love I mean, I love Thai boxing, but we would spar mostly with really heavy
equipment that would enable us to do this. And we would focus on sort of different types of things.
Like there were some days when it was just all going to be low leg sweeps and you were going to
be in shin guards and you were really heavily guarded because I always felt the worst thing
you could do is train at half speed because then it conditions you to be doing something at half
speed. You want to be able to be explosive. So you just have to have more more barrier there when
you're doing it. But having never done mixed martial arts, it's just nothing but I have for
how you have to be so prolific at so many things. You can be a great striker and I can sort of relate
to that because at least I know what those things I know it would be like to be great at that I was
never great. But I understand those sports well enough. But then you think you could spend your
whole life doing that. And if you're a horrible grappler, you get destroyed. Yeah, and vice versa.
That's where it's at now for sure. Yeah, I mean, I think when you look at guys like Daniel Cormier
and john jones, anybody who's great in the sport these days, they came in with something already
in their back pocket, you know, a lifelong wrestling pedigree, or a lifelong in traditional
martial arts pedigree, and then they could just focus on these other things. Because you only have
so much bandwidth, there's only so much time in the day to really learn and acquire new skills,
to polish them to feel comfortable enough to use that in a fight at full speed with all the pressure
of people watching you and pay per view and that kind of stuff going on. It's a lot. And I started
kind of late when you consider things. Thankfully, I wasn't missing the athletic background. But from
the technical standpoint, I entered the UFC as a white belt in jujitsu. I mean, there was there
was gaping holes in my game that remained there until I finished. While this whole new thing is
going on, how are you processing or what's the state of your mind with respect to this near death
experience you've had? And the culmination of really kind of what's been going on since you
were a kid? Like, has this has this now backburnered and sort of been supplanted by a new addiction,
so to speak? Yeah, for sure. I think having something to look forward to and train for and
really some level of meaning of what I want to do, I didn't obviously know it wasn't going to
fight for the rest of my life. I'd already experienced that in football. But this kind
of gave me a second go at it as a professional athlete, in that as I was working towards being
the best that I possibly could. Those are the things really, they weren't coming up for me
because I also had an outlet. If I was feeling weird inside and I go and fucking punch someone's
lights out, like that's a good feeling, right? Like it's letting the lead out. It was a great outlet.
In tandem, there was a couple catalysts, big catalysts that changed my life forever. One,
I started working with a sports psychologist who introduced me to breath work, and some level of
mindfulness. And the idea was because I mean, early on in my fight career, there was there was
no issues, I had ultimate confidence, I was going to walk through people. But now I'm at the UFC.
All these people are are as good, you know, as me, if not better. And that negative monkey mind
chatter that comes up, it was nonstop. So how do I control that? And the breath was really my first
entry point into quieting my mind and finding some level of stillness at least right before the fight.
And this was holotropic?
No, we would do various forms of slow breathing, trying to get down into parasympathetic. So at
least two to one exhale to inhale, four seconds in seven seconds hold eight seconds out, things like
that, or 1010 1010, 10 in 10 out or 10 in 10 whole 10 out. And those were I mean, fairly basic
forms of breath work, but I could feel the difference. And practicing that right when I
woke up and right before I went to bed helped me sleep at night. Because there was, I mean,
it's one thing to say I'll fight a guy on this certain date, but you sign a contract
every day up until that date happens. It's very hard to sleep. Cannabis helped me with that too.
Specifically THC, not just CBD, but there was a lot that helped me there to actually fall asleep,
breath work being a big component of that. The second piece that really was a game changer was
a boxing coach that I had who was Native American and Mexican. And he would take me to the reservation
to do traditional sweat lodges. So we do the Tim has call before every fight camp started to kind
of zero in on what we wanted. And after every fight for healing and reflection. And it wasn't
long before I just kind of looked at him and I said, coach, when are we going to use lamadicina?
And he just started laughing. And he said, I've been waiting for you to ask. And we started working
with psilocybin. Had you ever done it before? I had done it before highly inappropriately,
you know, at a house, like, creationally, yeah, at a house party on alcohol and cannabis with a bunch
of people I didn't know. And ultimate horror stories, ultimate horror stories. But this is
my first real introduction to use intention to have respect and reverence for the plants being used.
And in a completely safe and perfect environment, you know, there's no running water, no lights,
you're just out in nature, you know, and it's just my coach there watching me and maybe a couple
other fighters. And really, that's where I started to begin to uncover some things and really sort,
not too much from the childhood, but really getting direction and a true sense of peace inside
that was lasting. And at a certain point, I had a friend go down to Peru, he was going to hike
Machu Picchu. And I was like, that's awesome, man. Tell me how it goes when you get back.
So he actually calls me early and I'm like, aren't you in Peru? And he's like, yeah, yeah,
I just got here. But here's the thing, I can either hike Machu Picchu, or I can go do this
thing called ayahuasca. It's going to take five days to do either. And I was like, hike Machu Picchu,
why are you even calling me? That's why you went there. And he's like, no, you got to look it up.
So I went to arrowid.org. I'm not sure if you're familiar with the site. It's got every drug from
caffeine to meth in there, including all plant medicines. They give the pharmacology of it,
they give the chemistry of it, they give the legality of it, and there's trip reports.
So I remember pulling up a trip report from ayahuasca and the first thing it was titled,
it said the apex of teacher plans. And I thought, hmm, maybe there is something to this. And so I
asked my coach if he would come with me to Peru because I didn't speak Spanish well, and I wanted
him there. And he's guided me in every meaningful experience I've had thus far. And he said, I'll
bring Peru to us. And we found people that would work with ayahuasca with us locally. And that was
an absolute game changer. That's where I mean, it that shifted more things in me on how I perceive
the world than anything else in terms of the catalyst for that. And again, you know, like,
as we talked about before, it's not to glorify these substances, there's a right way and a wrong
way to do anything. But under that guidance in that setting, with that medicine, no doubt,
some of the most powerful changes in the way I view consciousness, my spirituality.
Were you still fighting while you were experimenting?
I was I was introduced, I was fighting when I was using psilocybin when I got introduced ayahuasca,
to be clear, I was using psilocybin from then on still to this day. Not often, but yeah,
still using psilocybin. When I was introduced ayahuasca, I had just torn my labrum. So it was
after a brutal fight in Nottingham, England, where I had my orbital, my left orbital blown out for a
second time, and my left eyebrow was fractured from a head kick in that fight. And it was my
third loss in a row. I had always said if I get to be a 500 fighter at any level, then I'll quit
because it's it's not fucking baseball, you know. And I am taking damage is clearly if somebody can
punch me hard enough in the face to break bones, it's taking its toll on my brain. At that point,
I had some time off. I mean, I tore my labrum. It's it took me it was a year to fully recover
from that. How are you supporting yourself at this point? Are you making enough in the UFC?
I was not making enough in the UFC, even when I was fighting. So I lived in my mom's detached
garage for probably the last four and a half years I was there. And I worked at a pseudo strip club,
it was a bikini bar out in Sunnyvale as a bouncer manager and bartender. And I'd go in
twice a week, thankfully, I go on weekends and pull off to 11 hour shifts. Losing sleep, of course,
not in the best environment. But I still have a lot of gratitude because that put food on the
table the entire time I was fighting. At that point, sponsorships were starting to be pulled,
people know, or maybe not. But there was a reebok deal that UFC did, and they no longer allowed us
to have our own personal sponsors. So money was being taken out from under our feet, left and
right. And it was really important that I had a side job while I was fighting.
So the ayahuasca started when you were in this year of the torn labrum?
Correct. So you're three, you've lost three. What's your record in total at this point?
In the UFC, I was four and four. So winning record overall, but four and four, I think 11 and
11 and four at that point. Okay, so you're at a real crossroads, which is am I retiring from this
or do I have one more hurrah left in me? Yeah. And I wasn't getting super clear on that from ayahuasca.
I don't think it was my intention to make that decision until I had repaired my shoulder and
was able to train again. But all of the important things in my life were coming up for me, the deep
work. I mean, everything from childhood stuff to how I treated myself with drugs and alcohol,
you know, seeing seeing those patterns come up. I remember I was I was in Colombia, getting ready
to do it. And they told us we were going to use a plant, they use a lot of different add mixtures,
but there was this plant of 1000 ants. They said, Why do you call it that? And it said,
Well, we're going to rub it on you in the middle of the night, it feels like 1000 answer biting you.
And so I kind of chuckled. And I said, What does it do? They said, You're going to think of a
negative emotion that you want to remove could be anger, it could be sadness, could be whatever,
just something that keeps coming up for you. And I said, anger, and we got in a long conversation
about that. But it also talked before that ceremony about alcohol addiction and cannabis addiction.
And immediately, I thought, Oh, this is for everyone else. Like, I'm good. This is for
everyone else. And then you know, it does affect a lot of people, you know, and so I just thought
of it that way. And then a great chunk of that night was me reliving, puking violently over
a railing in my chonies and telling my sister to get away from me. You know, I didn't want people
around to see me like that. And I had countless nights like that. And even when I was fighting
in the UFC, it was really a polarized way to live in fight camp. I was a perfect little angel,
I wouldn't watch TV, I would read every night trying to study things that would help me in
fighting from mobility to diet, nutrition, you name it, eating super clean food. And then the
second the fight is over, it's whoppers and alcohol and blow and whatever I can get my hands on.
So that went back and forth for a while up until this ceremony, I was like, wow,
okay, time to scale back outside of camp and really treat myself better.
It's so interesting. When you look at the statistics, I'm borrowing a lot of this. So
the numbers might might be a little bit off, because it's been a while since I've read it.
But maybe you've heard me talk about it in the past. One of the most important books I've ever
read in my life is this book called I Don't Want to Talk About It. Did we talk about this in Hawaii?
We must have. I think so. Yeah. By Terrence Reel. And he talks so much about the difference
between covert and overt depression. So overt depression is what most people think about when
they think of depression. It's the person who can't get out of bed, who's weepy, who's unmotivated,
overeating, under eating, your classic picture of depression, the person who's sitting there
morose in their psychiatrist's office or whatever. And then there's covert depression, which is the
same underlying pain, but it manifests itself typically with addiction, anger, aggression,
workaholism, all sorts of other things that are numbing this sort of discomfort.
And one of the statistics that Terry talks about in the book that just blew my mind,
because it's so obvious when he says it, like I didn't think, I guess what I realized was I can't
believe I've never thought of this before. But he talks about the stark contrast between men and
women. So when you look at, for example, what's the proportion of men in prison versus women in
prison? It's something about, you know, it's like 93% of incarcerated people in the United States are
men, not women. Rates of alcoholism, you know, it's about 20% in men. And again, I could be
directionally, I could be a little bit off, but directionally, it's, you know, it's about three to
one in favor of men for alcohol abuse, obviously, you know, nine to one in prison, drug abuse,
violence, all of these things are vastly more in men than in women. But when you look at women with
clinical diagnosis of depression versus men with a clinical diagnosis of depression, it's the opposite,
it's disproportionately men. And he goes through this exercise in his book of adding up the absolute
numbers. What's the absolute number of women that are receiving therapy for depression, that have
issues with alcohol, drugs, violence, etc, etc, do the same exercise for men, it turns out it's the
same number. What's the difference? The difference is the form in which it exists. And this just sort
of blew my mind, right, which is all of this time, like, you know, whether it's you me, I think,
this is my anger issue, or this is my addiction, or whatever it is, and you realize what's
underpinning that is the same pain that in a woman might lead to depression, that we will label in a
certain way, and we're not seeing it this way. And so it's kind of listened to your story is so
interesting, because I'm just sort of watching the arc of numbing vehicles to numb pain. If it's not
this drug, it's the pursuit of this sport. And if it's not that it's this fight, if it's this thing,
and it's interesting, just it sounds like the ayahuasca became, along with the psilocybin became
one of the first sets of tools, these plants that and I don't put words in your mouth. So if I'm not
right, I'm nodding my head yes, right now, as you say, but it sounds like that was the first time
when you finally saw through the bullshit of you're on a hedonic loop, a treadmill of one next fix
after another. And again, it's so common in men, especially that, like, we're sort of drawn to using
our body as a shield, right, like the bigger and stronger and tougher you are, the more that seven
year old is not going to hurt, which, again, when you say it that way, it sounds so stupid. But
that's because we're now sitting here talking like, like it's a rational thought, and not realizing
that there's a wounded kid that had to come up with sort of a set of skills to adapt to a situation.
And those adaptations were actually very positive. For the large part, they saved you, right, they
prevented you probably from jumping off a balcony when you were seven. But they start to become
maladaptive. And it's it to me, this is the stuff that's interesting is this transition from
adaptive to maladaptive. And it starts to come crashing down. Yeah, I mean, it peels back layers,
they talk about the infinite onion, every time you go. And that's the something. That's something
that really resonates with me. You listen to people like Dennis McKenna and Gabra Mat.
People I find fascinating is that they've done hundreds of ceremonies, and it's completely
unique each time they go. And I say ceremony because of the respect and reverence that's
used when they utilize these plants. But it's the fact that if I give enough space between
ceremonies, and I come back and have a reason to be there, that's important to me, I'm going to get
a lot that has to do with that and maybe even more than what I came for. And that peeling back
at the layer really shows such a deep reflection of what's going on inside right now. And it also
has shown me the ways that I behave due to how I was programmed. It just blows my mind. We just
got back from Sartar, we did another four ayahuasca ceremonies there, about three weeks ago. And
each one just took me away took me in a different place. And they were completely unique from one
another. And I continue to learn how to work with it. It's continuing to evolve. And listening
to guys like Dennis, that will continue on well past 100 ceremonies.
Have you had some really negative ones?
Negative?
And by negative, I want to caveat that by saying highly, highly unpleasant.
Yeah, so I'll all happy to jump into this. One of the hardest nights of my life was in Colombia.
And ayahuasca has a visual component where you can have quote unquote visions in a dreamlike
state. Oftentimes, they're very personal, what you see. There was a night where I had none of that
and all of the purgative effects of ayahuasca. So I shit water violently, barely made it to the
bathroom the entire night, didn't sleep one minute, puked violently the whole night. It was incredibly
hard, but it was in many ways cleaning me out. And that's, I think, what I needed at that point.
Now that's physiologically unbearable. But have you had, I mean, I've had one experience on ayahuasca
that was emotionally unbearable.
And I'm gonna get right.
Yeah, yeah. Those are the ones that interest me.
Having had a night like that, generally speaking, for the most part, and I've done now 26 ceremonies
with ayahuasca, there would be some level of back and forth. So if I had a really challenging time
physically, I could purge and then I'd feel euphoria. If I had some challenge emotionally,
maybe I'm reliving some hard memory from my past, I would see within the same time span,
you know, within I don't know, 30 minutes, that that other side of that coin and see the beauty
in it and realize all the things that it gave me and understand it with a new perspective.
My second to last night in Costa Rica recently at Sultara was for sure the hardest night of my life.
I had my first dose early on and didn't feel a whole lot. And it was very peaceful. And then
I asked for a second dose and it was my intention for healing. And I remember asking, then you can
argue one way or another what how much intention plays a role in this, I think it plays a huge role.
But I remember opening the door to any and all emotional and mental healing. And if there's
anything left from my childhood, because now I'm 37, I've done a number of ceremonies with ayahuasca
and even higher number with psilocybin and other MDMA of many things. And I've worked through a
great deal of stuff with my childhood. So I didn't think there was a whole lot left. And I just asked
like, if there's anything remaining from my childhood, please show me. It was fucking
everything. It was the entire night I made it back to the room, ceremony had ended. And it kicked off
into a whole second ceremony. And it was almost unbearable at many points. I remember just begging
for mercy, like, please, I've seen enough. Let's let's we can run this back a different time, like
any trying to rationalize or beg for a way out. So I wouldn't have to keep seeing this and to
end up in a just a small picture of this. Sometimes if I was to have a vision, it's like
watching from the third person or watching a movie and I can see from a different lens.
This was like reliving it for the first time through your lens through my lens first person,
like it was happening to me, the exact same feelings I was feeling as a six or seven year
old or 15 year old in that moment, all the fear of my father, my mom screaming at me an inch from
my face and spit flying into my mouth. Things like just it was in and it's so real, but it just
kept going and going and going. And I realized, holy shit, like all that's still there. Finally,
as the sun came up, I just kind of surrendered to it. And that's one of these cornerstones
that I've learned through working with the plants is you're not in control. I'm not in control.
Anytime I do these things, I can I have some level of direction, but really what I'm being shown is
for me, it's not happening to me. So the ability to surrender that and let go of trying to change it
really helped. And then having a degree of gratitude from my parents knowing they were
doing the best they could with what they could at that time. And also seeing how hard it was for
them growing up. And then seeing my son, that's really where it shifted. So we have a four year
old son named Bear and seeing him and realizing like that's where it ends. Like that's where it
ends. We all want to do better for our kids than what we were given. And then it applies to
everything from finances to education to what kind of person they become. But knowing that
he will never experience what I experienced or what my dad experienced and my granddad experienced,
that generational pain is going to be gone with him. And seeing that I had so much gratitude
for him and just knowing like, oh, okay, this breaks here. Like that was really cool. And second,
I thought that it all washed away and I felt euphoria and I felt gratitude. And I just, it was
for sure the hardest night of my life and one of the most beautiful in the end by far.
There's not much to add to that because it's funny. I had made a note on my page to kind of
come back to this point. All I had written down was break cycle son. Do you feel that part of your
edge is gone as a result of this journey? Yeah, there was a fire that was in you before that was
partially constructive, partially destructive. And you sort of were balancing those two things.
There were moments when the destructive side was winning and then there were moments when the,
you know, constructive side is winning. But it's hard to look at most professional fighters and
not realize how much pain unfortunately is at the root of why they're doing what they're doing.
It's very difficult, I think, to put yourself in the position of getting in a ring and fighting.
I know this because I did it. You've done it. You've done it professionally. I never did it
professionally. There's so much pain that predisposes a person to be willing to do that.
Now I'm sure there are exceptions to this. I'm sure there were like people with the
most wonderful childhoods who have ended up becoming fighters. But I used to study boxing
at a level that would border on me getting an honorary PhD for it. And I can't actually think
of an example of a professional boxer that I'd studied who wasn't fueled by some awful thing
that had happened to them. You know, it can be something little, but oftentimes it was not
right. Oftentimes it was generational and misery. Do you sort of feel a bit remote now from that
sport in the way? I mean, I'm sure you still enjoy it. But do you also, I mean, is your
relationship with it complicated as a result of this new insight or these new insights?
I mean, I for sure have let go for a long time after retiring. I retired five years ago
this month, actually. And I knew I wasn't going to fight again, but I still love the sport. I wanted
to watch every fight. Never missed a fight. Trained. I didn't do striking because I knew
that would lead me to fighting again. But I did a lot of jujitsu, competed in a couple of times.
I think now I would call myself a casual fan. You know, I still have all the guys that I used to
train with at AKA, I'll watch them when they fight. It's on ESPN a lot now. So I'll watch that too,
if it's on TV. But I don't like scheduled stuff like, oh man, there's someone so fighting. I got
to stop everything. You know, like if I catch it great, if I don't, it's not a big deal to me.
It didn't necessarily change the way I look at fighting. I have a lot of gratitude for what
fighting gave me and what fighting taught me. And I feel very fortunate that I retired at 32 years
old. And retired without the catastrophic injuries that many people leave with. Yeah, yeah.
And that's huge. You know, I want to be able to read to my son and any, all of our children and
then chase them around and play and be the dad I want to be, you know, but with that chip on my
shoulder, yeah, that's for sure washed away. I mean, I remember when I first started fighting,
I just wanted to, there's a line in Fight Club, and forgive me if you've heard me talk about this
before, but there's a line of Fight Club where Edward Norton's character beats the shit out of
Jared Leto, the blonde guy. And Brad Pitt looks at Edward Norton. He says, what the fuck is wrong
with you? And he just says, I just wanted to destroy something beautiful. And that's it. Like
that resonated with me. I wanted to beat the shit out of people. And over time that shifted to I
just want to be the best version of myself. And then now I see that still being the case, but it's
from a much different lens. Like what being the best version of myself is applies to so many
more things outside of athleticism. And I think that's a likely transition for people who have
started to age and whatever, you know, there's a lot of older people like, Oh, you have an age,
you're 37. But I feel different than when I was 27. Sure. 37 year old athletes and old athlete.
So you're not even halfway done life. And yet the last four or five years have probably been some of
the most important. Not that it's necessarily productive or constructive. Do you ever ask
yourself the question, like, what do you think you'd be doing right now? If you hadn't had this
fortuitous set of events, meeting the right boxing coach, being introduced to the plant medicine and
being able to sort of extract from it what it gives you. Cause I don't think the plants aren't
neat. They don't give you little turnkey, just take this. It's all okay. It's really messy.
It's really messy work. And it's as much about the work you do before and after is it is what you do
under the direct influence of the plant. But, but if you hadn't been as lucky as you've been to
experience that, I mean, what's a 37 year old former UFC fighter doing who hasn't worked through
the issues you had? Because there's a lot of those guys out there. I mean, this isn't about the UFC.
This is like maybe someone who's never thrown a punch in their life, but they're still suffering
from the same pain. Yeah. A lot of, I mean, I think the cliche thing to say is debtor in jail.
I don't think that applies to me. I think I really turned the corner, but I wouldn't say it's far
fetched to think that I'd still be fighting in some low level show getting the shit kicked out
of me losing brain cells. I for sure wouldn't be with Natasha, my wife. I mean, in many ways,
we were together for about a year before we did ayahuasca for the first time. And
like that changed the course of our relationship. It unpacked so much of the arguing that we had
allowed me to see things in myself that she could, but I could not. And vice versa. As we
grew as individuals, we grew together in our relationship. And there's no way that would
have worked out. How do I just continue to fight and treat myself the way that it was, you know?
And so I think that's, that's a pretty, if I look at probabilities, that's probably,
probably the highest probability is that I'd still be fighting somewhere, making peanuts
and taking my life. And getting hurt. Yeah. Getting hurt regularly.
How does all this sort of shape the way you think about raising your son?
Because you alluded to the most important point a moment ago, which is if nothing else, the cycle
of pain and the, and, and shame and trauma and all that stuff, at least it stops with, with you now
to bear. But what else do you think about as far as like, cause now it's beyond not just having
him be hurt, but showing him something that maybe. Yeah. Well, can I give him, you know,
in the world? And I think a lot of things fascinate me. People talk shit about the paleo diet and
that's fine. And what did paleo man actually eat and all that? And yeah, I get it. I get it from
both sides, but to think through the lens of how our ancestors lived, that fascinates me.
This is a giant test and it's a huge test of what we're doing now with everything that's in
the modern world. It's being done for the very first time. What are the ways that we can kind
of reconnect to our roots and still live in the modern world? And I think when I think about
things like that, what are the most important pieces that I've learned and what are the most
important pieces that I'm learning about now, I want him to have some degree of confidence.
And I think martial arts is really good for that. I don't necessarily want him to fight,
but that's his decision. And it'll always be his decision. Even if he says,
fuck martial arts, I want to play piano. And that's totally cool. I have to let go of that.
But still giving him the ability to trial these things and see what he enjoys. He loves, I mean,
he's athletic, me and my wife are both athletes. So it's not confusing to me, but he's doing
jujitsu now. It's pretty early, but it's kind of the equivalent of tumbling or gymnastics.
And he absolutely loves it. And our Russell time is probably the most fun. We have a hundred
square feet of MMA mats in our living room. So we can do yoga, we can roll, we can do whatever,
and rough house. And we can play soccer or frisbee, and those are all things that he loves,
but he doesn't love anything as much as wrestling me. So like, and getting him into jujitsu now,
it's pretty cool to see that. I don't know how long that's going to last. It really doesn't matter.
Getting back to this ancestral stuff, I think it's critical that we at least try to find some
rite of passage, especially for our young men to bring them into adulthood. And I think that
Ben Greenfield's buddy, Tim Corcoran, he's doing a lot of good stuff. He has these wilderness
survival camps for father and son. When the kids are old enough, he takes them out there and they're
solo, or they're in a small group and it's just him kind of watching over. And they learn how to
build fires. They learn how to feel safe in the environment. They learn how to forage wild mushrooms
and different things that they can survive on. And I think that's an incredible piece,
taking it a step further. And again, if we're having that conversation with the DEA sitting
on the couch, I don't know that I'd say this, but I think it's a very strong likelihood that I'll be
taking him to the Amazon or maybe not me, maybe Uncle Aubrey will, or somebody else. Because
oftentimes that was the case in rite of passage. The kids would have to leave their parents and go
off with the elders, the aunties, the uncles, and go through their work. And I think having a close
uncle like that, who also has experience with these things, taking him to the Amazon for a
rite of passage with something like ayahuasca would be really transformative and powerful for him.
And to most people hearing about this for the first time, they're going to be like,
that's fucking nonsense. You're right, you lost me here. But I know quite a few people
who are some of the most beautiful humans I've ever met that did that. Perongi being one of them.
He's an incredible musician, one of the most kindhearted people I've ever met. And his first
ceremony was when he was 11. So it's not to say that happens for everyone. But again, if you
understand set and setting and who are really good practitioners, and that's something I say a lot of
times is there's black belts, and there's white belts in martial arts, there's black belts,
teaching ayahuasca and white belts teaching. And there's everything in between. And some people
spend a week in the Amazon and come back and say, I'm going to give this to all my friends and
everyone I know. And it can have really bad consequences from that. So, you know, having a
place that that has been vetted, at least by somebody you respect and know, I think is critical
when it comes to these things. Because, as Aubrey says, you're performing psychic surgery. And that
done incorrectly can leave some really lasting damage. But correctly, it can be everything that
I see in it. Everything that Dennis sees in it. Yeah. And anyone listening to this who has not yet
read Michael Pollan's how to change your mind to have such a great storyteller and a great writer,
take on such an important topic. I think it's hard to come away from that without realizing
that there's there's a lot here that we need to understand better. But the promise is enormous.
Yeah, yeah. And we do need to understand it better. There's no doubt.
Under those circumstances, I think I can give to him a lot of things. You remember being in high
school thinking, maybe you didn't because you had boxing, but I remember being in high school
thinking like nothing is more important than this than how I'm perceived by my peers,
status, things like that popularity, who my friends are, what kind of girl I'm going to date,
and like, when the world ends, I went up on graduation day, what am I going to do and those
kind of things. And there's a lot of weight and heaviness to that environment, especially now when
you see kids that are glued to their iPad, and you got eight year olds with cell phones and things
like that. It's, it's really hard to get them to unplug and to see the big picture. And I think,
I think a medicine like that could be really important to reconnect them to what matters and
you get them to see with a wider lens to things that matter to them. At that point in time,
I think it could be a great tool for young people.
It's amazing. How has your relationship come full circle with your parents? I mean, is that
is it just this incredible place of forgiveness? Is it still difficult?
It's funny you say that because right after this ceremony, or series of ceremonies in
Atsultara in Costa Rica, my wife and I flew back to the Bay Area where our sons being watched by
my family. And then we all flew out to Puerto Vallarta for a family vacation. And there's a
famous quote from Terrence, I think it's Terrence McKenna. No, it's Rhonda's where if you think you're
enlightened, spend a week with your family. It's like, fuck man, I went from one ceremony to the
next. And it came with its own set of challenges for sure. But as far as my relationship goes,
I have a great deal of compassion for them. I've also learned from the medicines that everyone
walks their own path. It's not up for me to decide how or when they should learn their lessons. And
just as it was the case with me and my wife, I can't always see what's going on where I'm
fucking up. Everyone has a blind spot. So somebody that's close to you might be able to see what's
going on in you better than you can. And it certainly was the case in my relationship.
And I can see all the faults that my parents have that they don't see. But it's not up to me to
decide that they will learn their own lessons at their own pace. And they may go to the grave
without having learned some lessons. That's okay, I'm for sure going to do the same thing.
But that compassion, to me, that's one of the most powerful parts of the story is to feel
and experience empathy for another person who may have indirectly or directly hurt you.
And to realize, wow, they didn't mean to hurt me, or even if they did mean to hurt me, which is not
the case, I think, in your situation. But this is the set of circumstances for them. And that sounds
crazy, right? That sounds like we should accept horrible things that people have done to us. But
in reality, what's your choice? Yeah. And something that I've gathered too is forgiveness has very
little to do with the person I'm forgiving. It has everything to do with taking that fucking
weighted vest off of me. Because I'm held down by that. Whatever anger or pain or resentment that I
feel towards another person, the longer I hold on to that, they might not even fucking know,
it might not be on their radar. But I'm keeping that in me. And it's affecting the way that I go
through the world. So if I can release that, what greater gift can I give to myself, let alone the
other person I'm forgiving? Well, I want to thank you for being so open about such difficult topics.
There were a whole bunch of other things I thought we were going to talk about that were super nerdy
and sciencey and stuff. But I get to talk about that stuff all the time. I thought this was far
more interesting, far more valuable. And I honestly, I think more people will find this
resonance. So I really appreciate it. Awesome, brother. Thanks for having me. Happy Father's Day.
Yeah, happy Father's Day, brother. You can find all of this information and more at
peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast. There you'll find the show notes,
readings and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog at peteratiamd.com.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week email,
where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read,
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID peteratiamd,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare
services, including the givings of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice
for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest
very seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise,
please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about.