Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives.
Curating and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast,
that became clear to me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming.
I'm fortunate to have a great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information
with you. To take one example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a
full-time person that is dedicated to producing those and their feedback has mirrored this.
So all of this raises a natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support
this? As you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of
contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most
important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something
when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason
selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time
advocating for something that I'm not absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about
something, I don't know how I can talk about it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads,
I've chosen to do what a handful of others have proved can work over time, and that is to create
a subscriber support model for my audience. This keeps my relationship with you both simple and
honest. If you value what I'm doing, you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for
you. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple.
It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back
more than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Sasha Cohen. For those of you
who may not recognize her name, she's an American figure skating legend. In fact, the last female,
I believe, to win a medal in figure skating. She was a silver medalist in the 2006 Olympics, and
I don't waste any time in this episode going straight to that moment because on some levels
it is one of the most remarkable parts of her story, frankly. And I don't want to spoil the
story, but needless to say, if you only watch one video from all of the videos or anything we talk
about in this talk, that's the one you want to see. And I actually, frankly, this might be one
of those times where I recommend you, before you even listen to the podcast, you go to the video
of the final for the long program in the 2006 Olympics and you watch this six-minute video,
seven-minute video, whatever it is, obviously it's linked to in the show notes, but for those of you
who aren't subscribers and don't get the show notes, I still want you to be able to go see this video
because that's exactly where I go to at the outset of this discussion. We then work our way
a little bit backwards and talk about her life growing up and how she was able to channel and
focus all of her insecurity into becoming such a great skater, but much more importantly, we talk
about this life post-skating for her. And I think in many ways, Sasha is kind of a remarkable example
of how a person can remake themselves from being completely focused on one thing and having their
entire identity tied up in one thing and moving past it. And again, I think what comes across here
is the just maturity and wisdom of a person who is remarkably adept at understanding the
hollowness, the shallowness of achievements. For me, certainly this is something that just really
resonated to be able to hear her talk about this. So even though, again, we're talking to a former
world champion Olympian superstar, there's a lot in this episode for normal people like us who
aren't that way. And again, we explore the depths of depression. We talk about the statistics of
how many Olympians they want to suffer depression, and I talk about her involvement in a project
that's meant to bring a lot of awareness to this. We talk about a lot of other things as well.
So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Sasha Cohen.
Sasha, thanks so much for coming over. Thank you for having me. I'm really excited for this.
There's so much I want to talk with you about. And this, as I was saying even before, interviewing
somebody, you get to know a lot more about them than you may have known before. It sort of
accelerates your learning about a person in the weeks leading up to the interview. I mean, if
you're sort of doing your homework, which you obviously want to be doing, you're learning so
much more. And I think I forgot, you know, 2006 is a long time ago. On some levels, it doesn't seem
like that's not long ago. It's like, guys, 2006, like I sort of remember that. But, but you realize,
oh, that's 13 years ago. And to go back and watch the footage of the Olympics, I sort of forgot a
few things because I sort of remember watching that at the time. I mean, as every Olympic athlete
knows, that's the time when the rest of the country completely stops what they're doing to focus on
sports that aren't football, basketball, baseball, hockey. But I was really blown away by what has to
be one of the more challenging and yet remarkable achievements of your athletic career. And I say
that because it's a small footnote to what I think will be the broader arc of your life, which we'll
talk about. But I wanted for a moment, go right there and then back up and give people some context
about the sport of figure skating. But take us to the 2006 Olympics, you were favored. What was the
expectation for you after being a 17 year old almost making the podium? I think you were fourth
in 2002, correct? Correct. It was my second games. And I was one of the favorites going in. There was
strong competitors also from Japan and from Russia. And it's a moment in your life where it's
rare as a figure skater or a gymnast or in certain sports to go to one Olympics, let alone two. And so
you know that most likely this will be your last games. And figure skating, the ladies competition
is at the very, very end of the Olympics. And so the whole two weeks before most everyone is gone,
the Olympic village has turned into just a party scene. And so. Sodom and Gomorrah. Exactly. So
generally the figure skaters are not staying in the village. We're isolated, perhaps we're missing
opening ceremonies to really focus in and hone on this one moment that we've spent our whole life
basically since we were toddlers training for. It was difficult because six months before I was
flying high, I was in the best physical shape, mental shape. I was very, very strong. And then
over that winter, I had a series of injuries, equipment problems. And it was really tough
because I was going into the Olympics, not feeling prepared. And I've said that it feels like you have
to walk a pirate's plank. And you know that you kind of have to just jump into the sharks and you
don't feel prepared or equipped to handle it, but the show must go on and you have to keep
putting one foot in front of the other. So that was kind of the mental state that I was in, even
if you're in the best shape of your life, it's still the enormity of the games and this, these
few minutes you have to fulfill a lifelong dream is just immense pressure. Now, is that different
from the pressure you feel in 2002 when nobody knows you? And it's amazing that you're there.
I mean, how much of what you just said is not just the fact that you're going to the Olympics,
but that you're going to the Olympics as a favorite? I think definitely going in as a favorite. You
just, so a 17 year old brain and a 21 year old brain are a little bit different. And my first
Olympics was actually my first huge international competition. I'd never been to a world championship.
So I was thrilled to make the team. I was competing on my home soil in Utah and Salt Lake City.
And I went to opening ceremonies and I was just like a kid in a candy shop. And it was just
incredible how Salt Lake was transformed. So it was pretty magical. And of course,
I was nervous in these moments, but the spotlight was really on, on these favorites and that were
duking it out. And I was disappointed that I, you know, it was close to a medal, but didn't
medal in Salt Lake. But really when it came to Italy, I felt in 2006, I felt all eyes were on me.
And this is, this is the moment that I've been waiting for to redeem myself from four years back.
And I'm not at my best. I'm not ready. As an athlete, you're generally homeschooled and you're
analyzing videos and you're training and you're spending your whole life planning like four years
out. And so you're always analyzing every little thing you might've done wrong or how you could do
something better. And I couldn't help thinking like, how am I here about to compete in the Olympics?
And I'm not prepared. What did I do wrong? And I think something that I've learned a lot about
myself since then is that we can't control everything. And as athletes, we think we can,
that we can control and prevent any injury that might arise or any equipment problems. And,
and it's very hard to admit to yourself that you can't control everything.
Cause that's what you spent your whole life trying to do. That's what's up to you.
Does anybody else in your really inner circle, and I'm guessing at this point, your mom and your
coach are probably the two closest people to you when it comes to what you could be feeling.
Is that a fair statement?
Yes. Mainly my mom, you know, she was the one that, that came with me in all my competitions,
took me to the rink and physical therapy and off ice since I was seven years old. So we really
bonded and she was, she was probably the only one I was super vulnerable to, to the outside world.
It was, I'm fine. I've been training. I'm prepared. You don't want to admit weakness. It's like,
everyone's a shark and they can smell blood. And so you're always putting on this brave face and,
and it's kind of a fake it till you make it. Because if you show fear, you give others
confidence and you undermine yourself.
When did the Olympic trials take place for figure skating?
They're usually in mid early to mid January. And then the Olympics are kind of, uh, the middle,
like kind of early to the end of February.
So it's very close to the Olympic games.
About a month.
So how did you do in the trials? I mean, I don't mean how did you do in terms of what
was your position? Obviously we know you made it to the Olympic team, but how did you feel at the
trials and what did that do to your confidence?
I was going in with the flu and had a high fever. So I had missed a week of training going in.
And so I was pretty weak and frail, but I, I managed to, to skate well. I won that national
championship, but it wasn't this really strong at my height showing. And, and then after that,
it proceeded not to get better, but to get worse in my training at home with other injuries.
Going into, into the games where I was in physical therapy every day and had ionophoresis on my,
my inner thighs. And, and it was just, is a tough place to be because you want to train harder, but
then you push yourself and you become more injured and you set yourself back.
And so it's just this, this delicate balance of, of trying to, to navigate.
So let's explain to folks how this program works. Most people sort of know there were a couple of
different skates. There's a short and a long. The long is sometimes referred to as the free skate as
well. What are the parameters involved? The short program is usually two minutes and 50 seconds.
There's three jumping passes. There's a footwork sequence, a spiral sequence and three spins.
And, and the long program is a little over four minutes, four 10. And it, the rules keep changing,
but at the time that I was competing, I think you're allowed eight jumping passes and you could
do jumps in combination as well as requirements of three to four spins. And then a footwork
sequence and a spiral sequence as well. But there's more flexibility in terms of if you do a
combination or you don't do a combination and it's all about trying at the time that I was
competing to aggregate more and more points. At the end of a short program, so there are,
how many judges? You're testing my memory now. So different competitions vary, but I believe
it's usually nine and there's a backup judge. Got it. And it's like some, it's up to six points.
Is that the most? It used to be a six point oh system that shifted in the early, early 2000s.
And by the time that I was competing, no one really knew what their score meant until they
compared it to someone else's score because every competition would have new highs and,
and it was, it was all relative, but it was, there was no cap to how high you could go.
And so you didn't know if your score was the best score until you compared it to others.
Got it. At the end of the short program, which I assume is sort of done in reverse order of
favorites such that the, which we don't get a sense of when you're watching this on TV,
because you're not actually watching every single person there, but how many women would
have skated in the short program, for example, they eliminate after the short program. So I
believe it could have been up to 30 people in the short program, but it's a random draw for the
short program. Only the long program is done based on results in the short program and in groups of
six. So it's not a complete reverse of order, but it's in six and you draw. And then after the short
program, I think the people like that last six places are eliminated. So then when you go into
the long program, it's more like 24 skaters. And this is, this is rough approxinations.
It is still amazing. We'll come back to this in more detail, but it's sort of hard for mere mortals
like me to even understand what it means to make an Olympic team or in a time sport to even make an
Olympic standard. You know, there are some countries in the U S we take this for granted,
but there are many countries where you don't even have to, you just have to make the Olympic standard
and you get to go. Like there are so few athletes that could even do that in a given event. Like,
you know, a running event, for example, it is sort of hard to believe that all of the athletes in the
world are windowed down to 20, 24, 30, whatever it is. And then away you go. So going into this,
would you say your strength was more on the short program and the long program or how did these
differ? I mean, the difference in duration must obviously pose a different physiologic stress.
What are the other differences between them from the standpoint of the athlete either,
either it be mentally or physiologically? I think the short program, the margin for error is,
is zero. There's fewer elements. And so if you make one mistake, you really drop in the ranks.
And if you make two, it's just, you're, you can put yourself out of the running for a metal
and the long program, it's definitely more, for some people, it can be more mental. It's longer.
There's more elements, but there's more of an opportunity to take risk, to try harder elements.
And different athletes tend to favor different formats. I tended to like the short program
format more. It was more condensed, more fiery. And I think it's just very different depending
on what kind of athlete you are. Like you're saying there's more endurance and play in the
long program, mentally and physically. And there's also a finality to it. Whereas in gymnastics,
events are usually standalone in figure skating, the short and long program are combined. So
you're setting the stage with a short program, but it's by no means final. And it's not weighted as
heavily as the long program is weighted. For some people, they see it as more pressure because
you can't make a mistake. And in some ways it's less pressure because it doesn't count for as
much as the long. And it's just, it's everyone kind of getting initiated and seeing where you rank.
You were first coming out of the short program in 2006. How did you feel? I mean,
you're probably your own harshest critic. How did you judge your performance in that short program?
It certainly wasn't my strongest short program that I had done, but considering
the level of preparation that I had going in and in my mental confidence, I was thrilled with it
because I hadn't done a clean and clean mains making no mistakes. I hadn't done a clean short
program in weeks. I had struggled to even do full run-throughs because I was nursing injuries and
just really struggling. So I think I skated towards the end, if not last, after my competitors had
skated good programs and there's this immensity that you feel in the air and knowing that this
moment has arrived and you're not ready. And so when I went out there and ended up landing
my three different jumping passes and making it to the end, I was just exuberant and thrilled and
relieved. And then when I saw my name on the leaderboard and I was in first place,
I couldn't believe it. It was a thrill and it's a temporary victory, right? So you have one day
off and then you're back to the long program. But in that moment, I was triumphant.
So how did you spend that day between the short and the long program?
I had actually strained my leg during my performance. And so I had decided to take
the day in between off in order to be fresher and to not continue to
exasperate the injury in between the short and long programs, which really confuse everyone
because no one skips a practice. You get 40 minutes a day and people are used to training
for hours at home. So people just jump all over that time.
Oh, I never even thought of that. So of course, you now have whatever the 20, 24 skaters that
now have one day to get ready for the long program. And you're not going to put them all
on the ice at the same time. So everybody gets their 40 minute block and you're not showing up
for yours. I'm not showing up for mine. And that certainly confused people. The idea was...
Was that your decision or your coach's decision? I think it was a joint decision.
The physical therapist was coming to see me a few times a day. It seemed like a good decision.
Again, I think you always second guess everything in hindsight. But considering where I was and how
injured I was at the time, it did seem like the best decision because at a certain point,
you've done everything so many times that it's how you feel physically, which really informs
how you feel mentally in the moment that you step out to perform. You step onto the ice now
for the long program. You know, I've watched that video many times. It's hard because when you're
watching it now on video, knowing the outcome, it's different than watching it live. And truthfully,
I can't tell you that I see in your face any reduction in confidence. I can say I do because
that's the narrative I'd place over it. What do you see when you go and watch yourself? First of all,
do you go back and watch that? It took me a very long time to watch it. I believe it took me a few
years before I ever watched it. I was in an acting program and one of my classmates found out that
I was a skater and watched my performance and was like, it was so dramatic and it's so great and
we should watch it together. I'm like, I'm not watching it with you. So he finally convinced me
to watch it with him. But even though I didn't do the warmup, the longer 40 minute warmup, there's
a five or six minute warmup before you skate. And during that warmup, I fell on jumps that I
usually don't fall on. And I fell on a triple flip in the warmup and I fell on a triple lutz. And it
just, I think it really shook me. Figure skating is a sport where you're jumping and if you hesitate
for a millisecond, you throw off a whole timing of a jump. And going into that program, I knew,
wow, I just fell on things I don't normally fall on in my warmup. And now I'm going out and this is
it. Everything that I've prepared for, this is my second chance, this is my moment. And I don't
know what's going to happen and I'm not as prepared as I want to be. But again, you can't admit any of
this to yourself. It's all gets buried and compacted deep within you. And so you go out and you just
try to stay in the moment. So getting ready, all you need to do right now is put on makeup. All you
need to do is put on your pants. All you need to do is get on the bus. All you need to do is jog
around the arena and keep it simple because the enormity of the expectation and everything you
need to do and the crowds cheering can really unravel you. And so I think that's a training
and a skill set that you develop over years of competing. And when I went out and when I started,
it was a surprise to me when I fell on my first jump. And you partially register it.
And I partially registered just this kind of hush from the arena.
This was the first one, the triple Lutz.
The first one was a triple Lutz combination that I explained for folks who haven't watched
figure skating much. I don't know that I know I could recognize a Lutz. I don't know how I just
would describe it. So you're skating, usually taking most of the rink to prepare and gaining
speed, skating backwards and people jump both ways. But for me, I would be skating on backwards,
on my left foot, on my outside edge with my right foot in the air. And then my right foot would
reach behind me and tap kind of like a pole vault. And then I would begin, I would jump
and begin to rotate counterclockwise. It's considered one of the harder triple jumps and
the triple axel is the hardest.
We'll come back to the triple axel because I don't think a woman has ever landed a quad
axle. Has that ever been done yet?
I don't think a man has ever landed a quad axle.
Oh, I thought a man has landed a quad axle.
Well, maybe I'm thinking a man's done a triple, but a woman's not done a triple.
Midori Ito has done a triple axle. And then I think in the team competition,
Mariah Nagasu has done a triple axle. But I believe that was not in the lady's singles.
Okay, got it. But you're saying it's possible a man has never landed a quad axle either then.
I don't know why I thought.
Not that I know of. They do all the other quads.
Elvis Stoico had done a quad, but maybe.
He's done a quad, but not a quad axle.
That would be four and a half turns.
Yeah, I want to come back to all of that because growing up in Canada, figure skating is,
you know, along with hockey, it is a sport we paid a lot of attention to growing up.
And there were some great Canadian figure skaters.
Yeah, Elvis and Kurt were icons.
Just to put this in context, like I'm still struggling to understand how one trains for
this because I can't imagine like you go to a practice and you would do that whole four
minute, 10 second routine by itself. Right. I mean, wouldn't you practice by breaking that down into
short segments and doing those and working on the transitions as opposed to just going through the
whole thing?
Mariah You would do both. There would be a lot of
emphasis placed on the whole run through and then mocking competition conditions.
So that might mean you go into a five minute warm up, you get off the ice at home and you wait.
And then you go out and no one else on the ice and you have to go with someone's press
press play for you versus getting to restart or skating with everyone else and taking 30
minutes to warm up. And then you'll also just repeatedly train segments. And sometimes it
could be the beginning and the end or maybe just at the beginning three times in a row
to work on cardio and stamina. And so you're, you're trying to train yourself mentally.
You're trying to train physically so that stamina isn't an issue when you're at the end.
And everyone's a little different. And that's, I think the thing that was always so tough for me
is there's no, there was no formula. And with some people, more was better. And for, for other
people, more means you break and then you ultimately set yourself back. And so it was
always this tough push pull of, am I being lazy or am I being smart? And sometimes that,
you know, the person, something inside was just like, I'm not sure, but I have to do this again
and again and again. And then you end up injured and then you feel like an idiot. Cause now you
have to take a week off. But that was, that was a very hard balance for me because I, I did get
injured easily. One of the things that has always amazed me about figure skating. And again, your
fall in that triple Lutz at the outside of the long program was yet another remarkable example
of it to me is the ability that the skater has to immediately resume the choreography as though
nothing happened. And that amazes me for two reasons. The first is physically, anthropometrically,
meaning where you are in space can't be predicted by a fall. So it's one thing to go through a
series of movements and do them perfectly every time. And therefore know exactly where you're
going to be that next moment. It's quite another thing when you fall and you're never going to
fall exactly the same way twice. So every time you fall, you're going to land in a different
position slightly or roll into a different position. And yet you have to be able to go from
a first time being in a given position to right back into it. So that has always amazed me.
The second thing that's amazed me amazes me actually a lot more, which is the sort of courage
to be able to stand up when at that level, a fall of that nature almost guarantees you can't win.
Right? I mean, sure, as we'll see in your case, you didn't miss by much a gold despite that fall.
But who has the processing speed internally to do the math and go, well, technically I could still
be perfect the rest of this. I mean, in the end, it's just so crushing to your confidence in that
moment. And yet it's that ability to stand up and go again that I find more moving, I think,
frankly, than any aspect of the sport. And it's different from other sports, even individual
sports where it's crushing like tennis, you know, you're out there all alone. You're, you know,
there's no one to hide behind, but you make the worst play in the world. The most your damage is
capped. It is finite loss. It is. It is not finite loss in a sport like figure skating when you make
a mistake, it can be catastrophic and you can lose the entire competition, especially if you
can't get up and get back into the zone. So is there anything going on in your head consciously
as all that's happening? Or is it that in practice, every time you fall, the practice is getting up
and going right back into it as opposed to falling, thinking about why you fell, reflecting on it and
repracticing it, if that makes sense. Practice is certainly a component of it. And my coach
always taught me, you don't fall, you bounce. So as soon as you hit the ice, you're up.
Not only do you have to find physically where you go in space, but musically it has to match. And a
lot of times when you fall, especially if you're sliding or you hit the board, all of a sudden you're
late and you're trying to make up time because you know, on the next musical indication, you're
supposed to be halfway across the ice and you're still trying to get yourself up. So there's
certainly that element, but I think it's a combination of things. First of all, there's
so much going on that you don't have time to sulk in it, to let it hit you, the implications
of that fall. You have to block that as fast as you can because the firing is continuing.
For me, it was like I felt myself hit the ice. I heard the audience just go,
and that is not always your own disappointment and something I've always struggled with is not
wanting to disappoint others. And so now I have a stadium full of people that are just
audibly groaning and disappointed and you have to keep going on. And it's kind of being in this
embarrassing catastrophic nightmare where you can't hide. It's like someone's ripped off your
clothes, but you can't run off and hide. You have to hold your chin up and keep going and pretend
like you're fine. And then I go into the next jump, the triple flip. I didn't quite fall,
but I had a very severe step out and then I hit. And both your hands hit the ice. Yeah,
it was pretty much as close to a fall as you can get. I mean, I've been watching the video again,
I've watched it now so much in the preceding few weeks, but I forgot. I mean, it's amazing. You
don't break your wrist sometimes the way you would put your arms down. And you're not the only
skater I've seen do that, but that's a hard hit. You probably don't even recall it.
No, I don't know what to ascribe it to other than I generally have loose ligaments. I fall
all the time and people look like, how did you not tear your ACL and everything?
I would break my wrists if I fell into the position you did. But again, for the person
who's, and anybody at this point who's listening to this is going to go back and watch this video
and it will do more justice to what I'm trying to articulate. But again, it hadn't even started.
I mean, the music you chose for that piece, which I'd like to talk about all elements of this,
we're focusing on sort of the most challenging parts of this. But in terms of like the music
and the actual choreography and the performances, I don't think I'm alone in saying it's certainly
one of the more beautiful performances in all of women's figure skating. And yet it hadn't
even really started here. Sort of one, two punch. And if I was amazed the first time that you got up,
that says nothing about what it felt like to watch you get up the second time. It's like,
how is she doing this?
I think you get very good at denial as an athlete and at blocking things out because
they would be too much to take. So if you actually process what's happening and where you are in
space and time, because you have to understand going into this, I saw the Olympics as this just
huge looming, like the sun, like the horizon. I couldn't imagine anything beyond it. And it's
the same way that we know that we one day will die, but we can't imagine that actually taking
place and what's beyond it. And that's the same way I couldn't imagine March of 2006. I'm like,
I know it's going to come, but I don't understand that.
Let me pause for a moment then and ask you a question, which I'm going to ask you to try
to answer through the lens of February 2006. Because you've heard all these surveys and
questions where you walk into the Olympic village and you ask all of the Olympians there, like,
would you be willing to be dead in 10 years if it could guarantee you a gold medal at these games?
And I don't remember the numbers, but the numbers suggest that the answer to that question is yes,
in a staggeringly high amount, which I think speaks to, look, if you can't even picture March 2006,
what the hell would March 2016 even mean? Do you understand or can you relate to that ethos of
like you would die in 10 years to have been the best in the world undisputed on that day?
It was never posed to me as making that type of trade. I think now I can't imagine it, but
you know, who knows at the time, but it just, it was everything. It was an identity. It was your
chance to prove yourself to the world. It was everything that you were. And so everything was
riding on it. It was just so absolute and failing was the worst thing. And the sad thing is in a
sport like figure skating, if you're a medal contender, failing is getting second. Very few
people will say, oh, congratulations. You have an Olympic medal. It's more that you lost the gold.
You just don't know what to do with yourself. You have your own disappointment. You have the
disappointment of everyone around you, Team USA fans, your family, and the people that flew out.
And it's, it is kind of sad in hindsight to see just the nature of the interviews that,
you know, I had a string of interviews right after I competed and it was just like,
you know, your dreams are kind of dashed and you fell twice. Like how could you do this? Like how
devastated are you? And that that's what it's all about and reinforcing. And I think when you grow
up in this bubble and your whole identity is as an athlete and as a figure skater, and all you
want to do is prove to yourself and the world that you're good enough, but good enough means first.
And that's a very hard game to play. And I think it's not something that you can fully realize
at the time, you know, as a teenager or as a 21 year old. And I think it's something that takes
years to deconstruct after. And something that I've always found so interesting is I've,
I'm an overly analytical person and I've thought, oh, if I had just skated perfectly on that day,
and if I had, if I had won, then there would be nothing to resolve. There would be no searching.
And what I found is even fellow athletes like Apollo Ohno or, or Michael Phelps, who have won
multiple Olympic gold medals and are heroes and icons still struggle because I think so much of
what we gear our lives and performance for is for a moment. And even if you win in that moment,
that moment passes and then you still need something new to define you, to prove that you're
still good enough because now you're just last year's or last Olympics. And then you constantly
need a vehicle to prove yourself. That's such a great example. I mean, as you know,
I'm really close friends with Apollo. We're going to be seeing him next week. We're going to play
patty cakes together. But you know, swimming is a sport I love, right? And that's a sport that from
the standpoint of following it and knowing the metrics, there were a few people who could rattle
off more swimming statistics than me. So I followed Michael Phelps from 2000 actually, you know, even
before most people knew who he was when he was just a kid who made the Olympic team and managed
to get fifth in the 200 fly, which is a huge deal in Sydney. And I was kind of amazed last month
when his world records in the 200 fly and the 100 fly fell. So at the world championships this
year, 2019, I was amazed at how people were writing about him as though it weren't that impressive what
he had done. And I mean, I'm reading these things and I'm like, these people have lost their mind.
Like they have no idea what he has accomplished in the water. And yeah, these two incredible swimmers
have come along and broken world records. In one case he's held for 18 years. And it might even be
the case now, I haven't checked in a while. It might be the case that the only world record Phelps
still holds is in the 400 IM from Beijing. But the point is, as someone who doesn't know Michael,
but just has always been a fan and knows, I can tell you his place and time in every race he's
ever done. I'm amazed at how quickly he, his greatness is also fading in the memory of the
average person, right? Like we will likely never see an Olympian like that again, ever, ever, ever,
ever in another hundred years. And yet only three years after his last Olympics, he's sort of
yesterday's news, which I think speaks to this point you're making, which is maybe the brighter
that star is, the longer it takes to fade, but every one of these things fades. It's interesting
what you're saying. It's, which you, it's almost like you're suggesting that you went through a
period of time thinking, if only I had won, things would have been different, but it seems that you
don't really buy that rhetoric. Regardless, you lose an identity. So win, lose, or draw.
So much is signified and held within a gold medal and being number one, this absolute, this peak.
It symbolizes that you didn't leave anything on the table. It symbolizes no regrets. It symbolizes
that you accomplished what you set out for and, and the world recognizes you as the victor. And
all of a sudden silver just brings up all these questions. Like what went wrong? Was it you? Was
someone better than you? How are you going to live with that? It just, there's another element to it.
But, but regardless, when you decide to retire or if an injury forces you to retire,
you still lose the identity. And I think that is what is so challenging for so many Olympians,
because you have sacrificed everything homeschooled, you have no balance. You generally don't have many
other outside interests. And if you do, they're certainly not developed few friendships and,
and it's just this one thing. And so even if you win, and then all of a sudden that identity is
taken from you, it's like, I'm a figure skater. That's who I am. That's how everyone sees me. But
once you stop figure skating, then who are you? And as, you know, someone in my mid twenties,
trying to figure out who that was, was very difficult. Cause I didn't develop other
interests or hobbies in, in middle school and high school. I didn't develop close friendships.
I didn't go to college at the age of 18. So you're kind of left on your own, somewhat isolated.
And Olympians aren't really sharing this when they retire. Cause I think they're kind of with
their, they're in their own heads, they're in their own sports, and they're dealing with this
with their families or maybe with some of their close friends. And so you don't really realize
this is normal. And everything about being an athlete is about projecting confidence and power
and that you're fine. And you're always fine. You just kind of get in the habit of not portraying
weakness, of not asking for help. And it's always you, it's always your fault. I think athletes are
some of the most accountable people. We're generally not saying, Oh, it was, it was the ice
or it was that, or these outside influences. It's all you. My training wasn't good enough,
or I mentally got distracted or the pressure was too much. So we feel like we have to fix everything,
because it's, we've been told that it's all up to us and it's our moment and we're either going to
make it or we're not. So I think that's something I'm trying to find a balance with life now,
is this balance of making life happen and allowing it to happen, allowing for serendipity and
opportunity. And these, all these things that happen in life that as an athlete, you think
you can control everything, but you can't. When you finished that long program, which again is
beautiful, right? I mean, if you take these first 30 seconds out of that program, I don't think I'm
alone in saying this. I think many people have written and certainly I've read many accounts
of it, describing it as one of the greatest programs in all of women's figure skating.
Were you proud of how you finished? I was certainly proud of how I finished. And
I think in that moment after I had missed my second jump and I was heading
15 seconds later into my third jump, a difficult jump for me, you just kind of like, what's going
to happen on the other side of this? But you have to go in and just remind yourself, okay,
like set the shoulders, like pull back, snap, and just get back into the word by word guidance that
you give yourself through the program. And I landed that jump and it was kind of a relief. It's like,
okay, now I have a second and I had a spin and a few moments and the music shifted.
But at that moment, you're still kind of realizing like there went the gold, but you're just trying
to keep your head back because your head wants to go all these places. But as an athlete, you've
taught yourself to suppress emotions, feelings, and doubts, and especially in when you still
are on the line and you have to perform. And so as I ended up landing each consecutive jump,
there was this sense of relief and the music was very emotional. It was Romeo and Juliet from the
movie. And I just loved it. And so I allowed myself to really kind of get into some of the pain
and the expressiveness of the music. And I was relieved when I was done, but I was also
crestfallen and it was still trying to process everything at once. And in some ways, it was
kind of a messy night. A lot of girls were falling and that usually doesn't happen at an Olympics.
At another games, I would have been eighth or 10th and I ended up second because the top three
girls all made mistakes. So I can see that silver medal is just, wow, I was so lucky to medal,
considering how I skated. But I think at the same time, you just know that this wasn't the
state of preparation I wanted to be going in. This wasn't the performance that I wanted to give.
And I don't know what I could have done differently. And I think that's the biggest
thing for me is I'm a perfectionist. I want to understand everything. Things should be rational
and I want to fix everything. And so when you don't really understand,
sometimes it's hard to have closure and figure out what it means and what you could have done,
if you could have done anything at all. When you accept the medal, when you go back with your
family that night and your coach, are you already in your mind starting to think about the next
thing? Are you already thinking about the next world championships or the next Olympics, God forbid,
four years down the line? Or are you able to, in this particular moment I'm referring to specifically,
able to take some comfort in what you've just achieved?
I would say usually if it's a national championship or a Grand Prix, you're thinking
about the next thing because those are events gearing up to bigger events. But the Olympics is
just... Well, this one in particular.
Yeah. So this is just...
As soon as I was done competing, it was press conference, drug testing, and then media circuit
hitting all the, I believe it was hitting all the morning shows. And then every time they put
a microphone in my face and I could get through 30 or 40 seconds before I started to cry and have
a hard time talking. And that was eight interviews. So you don't really have much time to process then.
And then we have a show the next day. So all of a sudden it's, okay, now what's your show program?
Block it out with lights. And it's just go, go, go and trying to keep everything together. You're
kind of a porcelain doll that's shattered and glued yourself together to try to keep going
for the next two days of the Olympics, which is basically doing this exhibition, closing
ceremonies and leaving. And so you don't really have the time to process. I was saying with my
mom in, we'd rent an apartment and you kind of just come home to silence at the end of it.
It's too much to process at the time. And I think the most, the biggest concern is to keep yourself
together in front of team USA officials, in front of the media, in front of even family. It's like,
it's fine. I'm all right. Like it's okay. But certainly not thinking about the next competition.
Because after that world is kind of like a throwaway. I ended up going, but different athletes
handle it differently. But I think I tried to create a wide vacuum between skating and myself
and a persona just to get away from the pain of it. Again, I didn't watch the performance.
I fully embraced all the fun opportunities I had post games, which were quite the Oscars and,
you know, all these different events and skating. Unlike other sports, you have a chance to tour.
So you know, you're busy doing shows and live TV events. So I kind of lost myself
there and then put skating aside. I went to acting school. I just...
But did you formally retire in 2006?
No. And I actually ended up competing in March at Worlds. And then I ended up touring for a few
years while taking time away from competing and ultimately decided to come back and train in 2009,
2010 season. So it's interesting, you sort of delayed that. I remember Apollo talking about how
post 2010, I forget what he said, somebody the effect of like two weeks after the Olympics,
it all sort of hit him that that was it. On the one hand, that seems like a very short period
of time. Like, oh my God, like two weeks after, you know, the Olympics, it all sort of crushes
down on you like a ton of bricks, like you're no longer a professional athlete. And on the other
hand, that seems like a really short period of time. It seems like in your case, it was different.
It seems like in your case, you were able to stretch that out more partly because of the
nature of your sport, I think. And when you mentioned that you were taking acting classes,
was that in the spirit of making you a better skater or was that really in the spirit of
thinking about your next career?
I think it was about exploring other opportunities. I guest starred on CSI New York and on Las Vegas.
And I did a small indie film. I wanted to move to LA and take acting classes. And it was,
it was a wonderful diversion from this intense world of pain and disappointment, which I think
I didn't really want to process or look at. It was like, oh, here's all these fun, sparkly things for
you. Because right now you're cool and sexy because you just competed in the Olympics. And,
and then this is kind of something that all Olympians go through is you work really hard.
You have tunnel vision, you spend your day between the gym, your home and a training facility. And
then all of a sudden the whole world cares about you. And everyone wants to meet the Olympian right
after the Olympics until the next games. And then it's like, oh, who are you? So it's, it's a very
fun, amazing opportunity that some Olympians are fortunate enough to have. And I think for me,
it was just a wonderful relief of the disappointment and pain of my games. And then it was, I was just
busy working. So it was, you know, I went on tour for a few months and you're doing shows every,
every other night. And when you go and see a figure skating show, how much are you guys dialing
back your athletic sort of movements to guarantee that you're not falling? Like in other words,
at the Olympics, you're at the limit obviously. And that's why you will see someone fall at the
Olympics because they're the best in the world doing the hardest thing in the world. But when
you're doing like Disney on ice or whatever other show, they're obviously still amazing skaters,
but is that such a step below? Are you skating at 25% of your capacity in those situations?
So first of all, it's not Disney on ice. That would be a, you'd be a character if you're doing
Disney on ice. It's generally stars on ice or champions on ice at the time.
But the Disney on ice people, I mean, they're obviously very good skaters too. I'm using that
as an example, but yeah, yeah, yeah. Just clarifying, but no, it's certainly a much lower
level of difficulty in terms of your technical elements. And a lot of times you, you may not
have practice or time to prepare. You might be on a small ice and you're skating with light bulbs
around and no boards and you've got spotlights on you and you might be taking a red eye. So people
are definitely dialed down the level of performance, but it's more about entertaining. So at this
point the fans are there, they've watched you compete over the years. They're there to see you.
And so people are skating to songs with words and it's about entertaining and connecting with
the audience and you're still doing difficult triples, but it's not like you're packing your
program every 15 seconds with a very difficult combination. You mentioned already something that
I think is lost on a lot of people, which is the relatively small window in which you can be at
your best. And again, people like Apollo and Michael create, I think a false sense of what
the true longevity of an athlete looks like. It's very rare for someone to be the best in the world
over three or four Olympics. In many ways, I think it's a lot more like horse racing. And if you look
at thoroughbreds have one season in which they can be the best and it's very early in their life,
right? They're usually three year olds when they're at their absolute best. The horse might live 20
years, but it's going to race from ages two to four and it peaks at age three. I don't know if
you know these statistics, so I don't mean to put you on the spot, but I know how involved you are
in helping Olympians as they think about this transition. I mean, do we even have a sense of
how many people go to the Olympics and what percentage of people get to only go to one Olympics
and what percentage of people even get to win a medal? And it might just be even in the United
States where you probably would have better access to those stats. I don't have the stats,
but I know that most people only go to one Olympics and very, very few people medal.
I was surprised just thinking about it because I think the last winter Olympics,
Sean White won the hundred gold medal, Olympic gold medal, I believe for the US and you're
thinking the Olympics went going back to the twenties and there were breaks in there,
but you're just like, whoa, there's very few people have actually won medals.
And very few people get to go to an Olympic twice and certain sports, I think, like swimming or
speed skating tend to allow for someone to go perhaps twice, but, you know, three times,
four times is very, very rare. And in a sport like gymnastics or figure skating, especially as a
woman, your body changes. And then it's this complicated window where you have to be 15,
but some girls were peaking like a lot of these Russian girls were peaking at 12 and 13 and 14,
but then they couldn't go and compete. And by the time they were old enough to go,
they were off their peak. It's unbelievable to see that again. It's sort of like,
if you could really only peak for one to two years, it's like, imagine the Kentucky Derby is
only every four years and yet those three out of four horses wouldn't even get to peek in their
thing. And, and again, it does create this and it really breaks my heart. There's it. There's,
there's an amazing American female swimmer, Missy Franklin, who was an absolute phenom in 2012.
I mean, just sort of knock the socks off of people. You just couldn't believe how well
she swam in 2012. Well, in 2016, she was obviously not the same swimmer. I just found it so
heartbreaking to watch the reaction to this as though somehow she had failed as though somehow
like she had let us as fans of US swimming down, which I actually found infuriating,
truthfully, because I was able to sort of in a moment recognize that, wait, like it's okay to
be sad for her. Like I wish Missy was doing better here in Brazil because she strikes me,
I don't know her, but she strikes me as a beautiful human being and obviously a beautiful swimmer.
But to think that I could be disappointed, like she was somehow not living up to her potential.
It's ridiculous when you imagine here's a girl who's already got world records and gold medal
and Olympic titles to her name. It's almost like we as the fans create this awful expectation and
this sort of toxic environment of expectation around. It's never enough. You're only as good
as your last Olympics, right? You're only, you know, as you pointed out by 2010, it doesn't really
matter anymore what you did in 2006. It's can you make this 2010 team? And the media is a big part
of it too. It's a story, you know, will they live up to expectations and how will they do? And it's
you build people up and you tear them down. And I don't know why people do this. People are busy
living their own lives and then I think they just project everything, project failures and they
don't know these people, but they're somewhat public figures. And so it seems easy to kind
of slash them at the ankles and just like, how could you disappoint your country? And like,
why weren't you prepared? And there's really no sensitivity to this person being a human being.
We see athletes as resources and you need to perform. You need to meet expectations. And
there's not a lot of compassion for them as a human being just struggling on this global platform
and just having their heart ripped out. Well, you're absolutely right. We just can't,
we as fans, I'm saying now, we sometimes have a hard time believing you guys aren't machines.
For example, like you watch Djokovic win Wimbledon and then a month later have to pull
out of the US Open and people are booing him. I mean, I just can't believe it when I watch it.
I really, it embarrasses me to be a member of the public when you realize like a guy whose
shoulder is obviously in tremendous pain has to pull out of a tennis match and people are
pissed about it. And look, maybe if I'm going to take the other side of that, I would say, well,
maybe they paid a lot of money to come and see the Wimbledon champion at the US Open. It's funny,
when I was growing up, I was, I guess I still am sort of a football fan and I had this poster
on my wall of Jerry Rice. I don't know if you know who that is, but very famous wide receiver,
arguably the greatest wide receiver to ever play the position. It's just a very famous,
I think it's like a Nike poster and he's in the end zone and he's holding the football up. He's
just scored a touchdown and there's a player, I think it's like a Cincinnati Bengal player.
You don't even know who the player is because he's on the ground with his feet trying to grab
Rice's ankles. Obviously, he has failed to stop Jerry Rice from entering the end zone. And I
remember one of my best friends in high school, Jeff Bajoni, made the most astute observation ever.
We were like sitting in my room one day, we're like seniors in high school and he looks at that
and he goes, isn't it amazing that that dude, when he points to the guy on the ground, is a better
athlete than anyone we ever know. And I think people don't realize, we're so used to looking
at Jerry Rice or Michael Phelps or whatever that one exception is that comes along and truly bends
the arc of a sport that you forget. Even the people seven rungs beneath them are still doing
something that most of us can't fathom. But it's almost like we get numb to it, I think. We get so
used to seeing you guys be perfect that you make a mistake and maybe there's a part of us that
likes seeing it because we know you're not perfect and maybe there's a sense of, well,
you failed, therefore I'm not so mediocre in my existence. I don't know, maybe that's sort of
an overly skeptical view of it. Human nature is complex. I think a lot of it is invisible,
meaning the athlete, especially the Olympian's journey, we see him pop out of just nowhere for
a month around the games and then he kind of goes back into obscurity. Whereas you're kind of seeing
half the season, if you're watching the NBA or NFL, you're kind of constantly getting updates
on what's going on and there's multiple games. So you're part of the process a lot more, whereas
someone that is a skier or a swimmer, all of a sudden they pop out of nowhere at the age of 14
or 15 and you see them for a month and then they disappear again for four years unless you're
following the world championships. But I think most people would really just tune in for the
Olympics. So we don't really know what their lives are like. And I think that's what these
fluff pieces going into the games try to do is track this person training in their rundown
facility. The fact that they're homeschooled, you see them at physical therapy, icing everything,
taking 30 vitamins a day, trying to optimize their performance and then also having to take
painkillers because they're performing with a broken foot and humanizing the pain and the
struggle behind it and the sacrifice. And I think when all those things are taken into account,
all of a sudden this person becomes more human and someone that is overcome versus someone in
kind of a shiny USA outfit kind of going across your TV screen for 20 seconds and then they're
just a racehorse to you and they're a time. But I think once you know the human and you know the
story and what it takes and that the four years in between, there's really kind of this nothingness
for them and there's no glory for most Olympians and there's no money for most Olympians and they're
working second jobs and they're in debt to pay for their training and the sacrifice that they
go through. I think when you understand all those elements, it really, really humanizes the athlete.
Is the United States, I can't tell, is it a good or a bad country to be an Olympian from? Because
I've seen, for example, like in other countries where if you're even in the top five, top certainly
the top three in the world as a swimmer, you can make an amazing living because it's so great.
There's so few athletes in that country that could do it whereas in the United States, if you won a
bronze medal in the 200 IM in one Olympic year, you're not going to make that much off that.
But at the same time, the US seems to have a lot of great resources to help Olympians but just
on balance, you get the sense that it's great to be an American Olympian relative to other countries.
Well, it's certainly incredible to see the US flag and the sense of camaraderie and
you know, America still is this icon for so much of the world and so there's this immense
sense of pride representing the US. But I think the difference is the US Olympic and Paralympic
Committee is solely responsible for funding the athletes. The government is not any part of it
and in a lot of other countries, I believe like Russia and in China, the government is putting a
lot of money into the athletes and paying for their training and so they just have the resources
that they have to work with are at another level. You know, in Russia, if you reach a certain level
of success, you get an apartment and you get a car and you get a stipend where that doesn't
happen because the purpose of the Olympic Committee is really to find young talent and support them
leading up to their Olympic journey but they don't have the resources that these other countries do
and for other countries, especially during the Soviet Union, it was all about how do we beat the
US and everything and no expense is spared and look at five-year-olds and do they have the right
bone structures? Like, okay, take them away, take these 55-year-olds away, put them in camp and
maybe one of them will make it. We don't care if we work them all to the bone because it's about
winning and it's an Olympic machine. Your mom's from Russia, right? She came to the US when she
was what, a teenager? 16 and it was the Soviet Union at the time but she was from Odessa.
She was from Odessa, okay. Did Russian fans have a negative view of you? Did they want you to be
competing as a Russian or were they just opposed to you? They seem to boo you disproportionately.
Was it just because you were American or was there something more going on there?
I think it's because there was another Russian, Irena Sutskaya, that was a favorite as well and so
there was really no association with me being a president. I see. It had nothing to do with you
not competing as a Russian though it was in your bloodline. It was purely just the fact that you
were the competition to a Russian. Yes and I think in other competitions where there was no Russian
favorite then the Russians were supportive of me because I was closer to who they were but
I competed in Moscow against Irena and I was thoroughly booed. It was really that it was
kind of when I was ever up against one of their own that I certainly, they were not rooting for me.
Let's go back a little bit because I still, I don't understand how a seven-year-old girl decides
I'm going to subject myself to this much practice and this much deliberate effort. I mean you've
talked about this before in other interviews I've heard where like many athletes your parents are
told you probably have attention deficit disorder and was it framed as she should either probably
take this pill or she needs to find something to do for three hours a day? I mean was it sort of
like that? I was a hyperactive kid. I was constantly climbing trees just on rooftops wild and I would
race the boys, I would do cartwheels, I would just kind of, I would wear this same neon stretch
two-piece suit because I you know I had no sense or care about fashion. I just wanted to be running,
jumping, climbing at all times and I went through three different elementary schools because I
didn't know how to sit still in class or stand still during roll call. I would be off being cartwheels
or if art was over I wouldn't put my art project away because I wasn't done.
So I had a very difficult time being in a group setting and listening to direction. One teacher
thought I was deaf, another teacher gave my mom a book on juvenile delinquents and it was just kind
of clear that I couldn't conform to a system and you know my mom finally found a school that was
like mixed grades, no desks, mainly art that seemed to jive with me. This was in California?
In Pasadena. Then I was put into gymnastics at the age of five because I just I was bouncing all
the time. It's so much energy so I went to gymnastics for four hours a day and we were
literally a hundred v-ups, you know 300 jumping jacks, 100 push-ups and this is as a five-year-old.
I look like a little cut sumo wrestler. Were there other five-year-olds there or were you with
older kids? No I was with other five-year-olds. It was a very intense training center and yes you
know I was diagnosed with ADHD and my mom didn't want to medicate her five-year-old and so she
thought okay well we'll just get it rid of her energy in gymnastics. Through that a friend threw
a skating birthday party and I found skating and this feeling of gliding and freedom and I could
channel all this energy I had into something I loved and could focus on. And so then for me
it was very easy. It didn't feel like a sacrifice because all I wanted to do was be on the rink and
to be skating and learning new jumps. So I never really saw it as a sacrifice early on in my life.
It was something that gave me clarity and purpose whereas I didn't really fit in at school.
I was a lot smaller than everyone else and I just had a very different, I think I didn't know how to
socialize. I was climbing trees or I was painting pictures come sixth grade when everyone's getting
ready for dances and figuring out what they're wearing and figuring out what boys they should
spend time with at the mall. I just completely completely over my head and skating gave me this
channel to express myself to work hard to become something and it just clicked. Even by the
standards of a figure skater you would still be considered kind of an outlier in terms of your
artistic ability. Again the way you know your your movement exceeds even that of your peers.
You've now even just in the time we've spoken discussed this constantly as this sort of creative
expression. Do all, I mean I guess it's hard for me to ask you that question, but do you think that
that's common as the the thread towards getting somebody into figure skating or do are there
different paths that get people there? So in other words you don't have to know much about physics to
understand the strength and power that is required to jump the way you guys jump. I mean that's a it's
a very explosive sport so there's probably a very athletic component that's required to it in terms
of those raw athletic inputs. But there's also this huge artistic component where I could imagine you
take the most powerful female athlete on the planet but if she doesn't have the ability
to create lines and flow and spin in a certain way and dance in a certain way or choreograph in a
certain way it wouldn't be the same. I think it's the same is true for men and women. I'm just using
women as an example because we're talking about you. Did you start to figure out which of those
was your leading edge? It's interesting because on the spectrum of sports I think figure skating is at
the very end of sport and then the next is ballet and ballet is an art. And I think the physicality
channeled my energy but I think I've always been very expressive and creative and and I felt that
the music was a way for me to channel my feelings. So I think I was always much more of the artistic
skater and while I definitely had physical talent and capabilities that was by no means
my strength. Like some people were jumping machines. They were they were robots and they could do it
the same jump over 20 times just boom boom boom and for me I always struggled with that. It took
me longer to learn my jumps. I would lose my jumps and for me I excelled at the expression and the
line and the flexibility which I'll thank my mom for because she wouldn't let me watch TV unless I
was sitting in the splits. And so growing up I was either in the splits or practicing holding spirals
but everyone I think is is very different in a sport like figure skating and even ballet because
you have the range of the more athletic and then the more emotive artistic and you really need to
be a mix of both. Although the way that the system is evolving is with a heavy emphasis on
the technical abilities because that racks up points and so you don't need to have as much
personality or artistry because the points are really not captured there. Certainly it's part
of it but but you can rack up so many points with technical capabilities that it outshines.
And that become in some ways a criticism, hasn't it, of women's figure skating which is okay I get
it we're going to add more and more points to these greater and greater degrees of staggeringly
powerful jumps. But the critic would say well shouldn't we be subtracting points for the lack
of beauty in this, for the lack of grace, for the lack of spin, for the lack of line, for the lack of
choreographing as well so that we do try to preserve that balance. I mean I guess ultimately that's just
so subjective though right it's very difficult to enforce that the way you can say look you have to
do a triple Lutz and it's very clear what is and what is not that jump right. Figure skating is very
complicated as is gymnastics because it's not a race with you know did you beat this other person
what was your time. It's really an art that's also a sport and and so it's it's a philosophical
argument. Do you want to treat figure skating purely as a sport and a sport is about technical
ability and progressing and pushing the body to more rotations faster and treat it purely as a
as a sport because then what happens is you peak at 14 you get injured quickly you can't sustain
and evolve and have the kind of skaters you had in the 90s and early 2000s like Suriya Bonnily and
Kurt Browning and Michelle Kwon where there were personalities that developed and people matured
and became more like well-rounded athletes and performers because we're now choosing to treat it
just as a sport. We're not valuing the artistry but but who's to say that we should that's subjective
obviously I appreciate the artistry I couldn't my skills that wouldn't have been conducive to
competing in today's environment and I think a lot of what the audience loves is the personality and
the artistry of figure skating but is that what makes it a sport and I think that's a very
philosophical subjective debate. I don't feel qualified enough to weigh in the the fact that
I always have a very strong opinion in swimming for example you know the most dominant male swimmer
before Phelps was a guy named Tom Dolan and I mean not a beautiful swimmer to watch swim I mean
he looked like he was beating the crap out of the water the whole time and yet the fastest swim I
mean back to back gold medals in the 400 IM in 96 and 2000 so amazing swimmer but you know you
gotta say look in swimming it just matters how quickly you get to the wall it shouldn't you know
it's pretty clear in swimming or running to your point it doesn't matter if you look ugly doing
it who cares if you're there first but at what point in your figure skating career was it clear
to you that you wanted to do this as your life's mission at least for the foreseeable future
when do you make that decision where which is okay it's time to start whole homeschooling and
living on the road and training six hours a day I was 12 I was going into seventh grade my first
day of school and I just felt that it was such a waste I was at a public high school in California
everyone was focused on shopping and surfing and it wasn't a very rigorous academic environment
and I just I would often get heckled it's like oh what are you doing here do you lose your way
the elementary school's down the street because I because you're short yeah I was I was short I
was little I looked a few years younger than I was like I looked like I was in third or fourth
grade I was tiny when I was competing at the age of 15 I think I was four nine and 70 pounds
um so I was I was I was really little wait a minute wait a minute you were four foot nine
and 70 pounds at 15 I was tiny you know you had you I mean if you don't mind me asking I mean had
you even had your period yet no not tell much much much later wow yeah which is not uncommon
obviously for for female gymnast figure skaters ballerinas I don't remember why I had the tests
where you're kind of submerged dunked underwater yeah I think you know it was like five percent
body fat just just tiny it's kind of amazing to reflect on that for a moment I mean I think again
maybe even for you it's hard to appreciate now this is me getting to talk with some authority
right on what the implications are of totally arresting your endocrine system for six seven
years literally a third of your life being fully stopped to prevent your body from developing I
mean that speaks to what a physiologic stress it is for a young boy or a young girl it's just the
the I think there's a fundamental difference right which is for boys the training effect can
actually sort of help puberty but for women it can be really suppressive as it obviously was in
your case in the case of many others that that's and for me it was pretty easy until I was 17 and
then when I was 17 everything changed with with diet and with training meaning you got more dialed
in at 17 when I was 15 I could eat whatever I wanted I see and I was just tiny I had a kid's
metabolism and I was also working out hours and hours a day but when I was 17 16 17 you know
things started to change you started to get a little more pudgy and and all of a sudden there's
this focus and your coach and everyone's just like oh I you know I see you you know they would pinch
your stomach and it's like we that's not just skin there there's fat and then as you get to know your
body better and and every because it fluctuates you to get down to a pretty low weight but you
can't really sustain that during the year and so you'd gain 10 pounds after the end of the season
and then you would try to get back on the ice and do a jump again and it just you really feel the
difference in terms of your spring and being able to rotate rotational inertia for sure
how prevalent are eating disorders amongst figure skaters they must be quite prevalent
I'm sure they are but it's something that everyone keeps pretty private and even the men
have their own versions of them it's it's yeah I don't eat breakfast or lunch I just have coffee
and then then I have dinner but I don't have an eating disorder I think everyone has found their
own method for what works for them and it's very difficult because it's not so much about the
energy to train it's it can be very much about what your body looks like and how you can propel
it into the air and every body type is very different and has its own kind of physics where
you'll see a lot of the North American or European skaters being very very very muscular to to vault
themselves up into the air and and some of the Japanese skaters like the Japanese men you don't
really see a lot of muscles on them but they're just the most incredible light springy jumpers
and so everyone has to find their own dynamic and I think that's why you see a lot of girls kind of
get sidelined when they go through puberty is because their body really changes their bones
change and no matter how they try to control what they eat or how they train it that time has passed
them by it is a little bit of uh you talked at the outset about one of the challenges is you don't
you think you're in control of everything but you're not well this must be one of the greatest
example right because a 15 year old girl who has yet to go through puberty has very little control
over what her body is going to turn into I mean you don't know if your hips are going to do this
your breasts are going to do that and that can be all the difference in the world so our coaches
at that age also sort of hedging I mean how are they communicating to the parent because I'm trying
to put myself in the shoes of a parent whose child is 12 or 13 who's being told your child has the
potential to be an olympian but oh by the way when she goes through puberty all bets could be off
like you know her body could change in a way that's simply not conducive to the movements of the sport
is that ever explicitly discussed or is that just always sort of we just keep our fingers crossed
and we just go for it every model is different if you're you're in in Russia or in a different
training environment you know you might the coach will only take on a few students it's much more
intense whereas in the US it's like every skater has to pay for lessons so coach will teach someone
that might never make the olympics because they're getting paid and it fills this hour later on
there's you know as someone proceeds through the ranks and they're senior and they're close to
making a world team the coach gets more involved and there's more at stake but but ultimately
it's on the athlete can you control your body and it's again this everything that we think we have
to be able to control everything and and I think it is very dangerous because you get the validation
from your coach and from the world like if you have a longer line and you look more balletic
and at the same time it's easier to jump and you're also controlling something in your life which are
kind of all these things that are tied into having an eating disorder but then it's like
is that what's necessary for this sport when you look back at your entire career in figure skating
so from age call it five or seven until what 2025 when you stopped when was it the absolute most fun
it was the most fun when I first started and then probably when I was 14 15 years old
14 15 years old I was just beginning to get really good to get national attention go to
my first international grand prix's burst on the on to the national stage and get second at nationals
and then be invited to do tours as this young kid this whole world this this carpet unfolds before
you and now you're touring with your your idols with Cristiano Magucci and and Brian Boitano and
people you've watched on tv and you're just this little kid and all of a sudden
the olympics are two years away and and it's just it's all at once and it was this inundation
so I think that was probably the most exciting I was still super motivated it was all ahead of me
and I was young enough that I think the pressure the immensity like the enormity of the where the
level of pressure would go had not yet sunk in that is a response that I've heard from
a number of athletes which is the best time in their life with respect to the sport was actually
before they became the best do you think that's common I mean I you probably have a much larger
sampling of that than I do I think later on it just becomes about expectations I think it's a
matter of appreciation so before you have it it's just you idolize these these athletes at the
olympics and it's a dream just maybe one day I could get to go there and then all of a sudden
when you're going there you're like if I don't win I am the biggest failure in my life is ruined
and so I think it's all about framing and lenses and when you're young it's it's all ahead of you
and you see things with rose-colored glasses and you're doing something you love because you love
it and then later on it can change and I had a very difficult time between 2002 and 2006 I moved
across the country I had different coaches was dealing with like gaining weight and you know my
body not cooperating with me and losing all my jumps and just being super super devastated
weight did you gain between 02 and 06 so in 02 year 17 and I was you know six year 21 it would
fluctuate a lot between off season and on season but I had very low estrogen and low bone density
and so doctors wanted me to be on birth control to strengthen my bones and that just completely
put my body out of whack and completely didn't work for training and so it's like all these
things that your your body is like this finely finely tuned instrument and you do
you switch blades you you try birth control you and it just completely puts your body out of whack
let alone all the emotional repercussions and it was really tough but I knew the olympics were
two years away and I had to be there and I had to redeem myself and I had to win because this was
everything my life was for so despite how difficult it was and how hard it was failure and quitting
wasn't was never an option there's just you know something inside that's propelling you and I don't
know if it's there's so many different factors going in but it's it's something that there it's
not pure joy and like the love of what you're doing that's driving you it's the need to fulfill
a quest at points it can be a lot more painful and difficult than it is exciting and motivation
is serving as your source in some athletes case it's it's usually obvious at least if you're
playing armchair psychologist it's obvious what what void is trying to be filled you know it's
an athlete that's trying to you know win the approval of someone you know a parent that's not
there or a person that rejected them do you feel like or do you see or sense looking back any sort
of motivation that could make you feel like you had you know everything you just said i'm not
going to repeat it because i can't i won't do it justice everything you just said was that in
service of some thing some void you think or is that just the inevitable fuel that one needs to
turn to if they're going to compete at that level in other words can you win an olympic gold purely
purely from the place of bliss pure joy and love for the moment that you're there being a part of
every bit of the training win lose or draw have the same bliss is that even possible at that level
i think it's certainly possible i think you see it with kids just coming up so they might be 15 go
to their first games and they're so excited to be there and wow they won i think it also happens
towards the end of a career when people have had dealt with hardship and maybe it's their fourth
olympic games and they realize that this is the last one and how incredible it is and that they're
performing and they're competing with the appreciation of their legacy and that this kind
of final punctuation on their career but i think it's difficult especially when you're it's your
second games and you feel like there's so much pressure riding on this performance because it's
no longer about your olympic experience it's about will you deliver in these few minutes and that's
what everyone's been been talking about and waiting for so i think it is complicated but i think it's
possible and it's not to say that even if you are using this kind of not negative motivation but
just this you know a certain dry that doesn't come from pure joy not to say that you don't have the
most exhilarating moments when you you find this piece of music and you choreograph and you program
or you land and you jump combination for the first time it's you realize that the great things in life
take hit in your head against a wall over and over and over and over and over for years and you just
don't give up because giving up isn't an option i think this sense of obstinacy is it it makes you
great as an athlete but then when you apply it to life it's it's kind of you have to it's like the
zumba in the room it's like no that's a corner we actually should move the zumba and like start
banging against something else but that's what it takes to be a great athlete is not accepting
failure you keep showing up again and again and again and i can tell you that two years out when
you're out from the 2006 olympics i didn't even know if i was going to make it because i was
struggling so much the one season before the olympic season i had to withdraw in 0405 yeah
i lost all my jumps that year i pulled out of every grand prix and i i thought i've stuck around
this long and i'm not going to make it to 2006 like how is this happening but but you don't give
up you just keep showing up every day you keep showing up every day and then things get better
and it kind of teaches you that that if you don't give up if you show up that that has a lot of
weight to it one other question i just want to ask you about the actual olympics because it just
blows my mind how long does it take you to to choreograph say that the long program of 06 right
so you do you pick the music first you say this everything is going to be built around this song
and then we're going to build it in or do you largely sketch out what you want to do movement
wise and then pair music to it i mean especially for an olympic season you're listening and then
you're taking music to the ice and you're seeing how you move to it does it inspire you and then
you might work for a few weeks with a choreographer not only cutting the music but trying different
series of spiral sequences and jumping combinations and figuring out what really suits you and you're
really choosing music to suit your style if you're more lyrical or if you're more of a power skater
you really want the music to serve you and your style of artistry or how you skate was romeo and
juliet do you think your best work in that sense it certainly was one of the pieces of music that
i resonated with the most and i always felt that i just melted into the music and it's it's funny
because i get nervous with public speaking and and for some reason it's when i'm in front of a
microphone and i'm nervous and i speak it's very different than getting out into the middle of the
ice being incredibly nervous and nauseous but hearing music and then somehow you can melt into
the music and and moving your body and i think romeo and juliet was a piece of music that i felt
really at one with it was a love story and had so much drama and especially this the movie version
i think it was the prakofiev that and spanish music i intended to skate to malaguenia and
karman and these kind of fiery character pieces which you know also suited another side of my
personality you've described the feeling i'm sort of paraphrasing but profound nausea and the feeling
of thousands of pounds crushing your chest or something to that effect that's what it feels
like when you go out there and yet it's sort of amazing as i you know i think that's partly why
maybe as we get older we find something different in watching the olympics you know when you're
young you're watching it because it might just be all about the achievement but i think as we
age a little bit and we experience our own setbacks and we start to sort of understand
what our demons are all about part of what i think is amazing about it is trying to imagine
how they feel you know trying to imagine whether it's you know the start of the hundred meter free
it's like there's eight people lined up on a starting block one of them's going to win one
of them's going to finish last right one of them will finish last there's no denying it he or she
will still be the eighth fastest runner in the world for that day but what is the anxiety like
in that moment i don't know there are a few sports like figure skating where the margin for error is
so small because one you're out there for so long so the duration is long the technical complexity
is very high and three the aesthetic component matters meaning how you present yourself matters
again you can be scowling when you jump in the pool or get on the bike it doesn't really matter
you can't be scowling when you're standing there on the ice it's always amazing to listen to the
announcers as though they know what the person's thinking try to project that but presumably that's
been a skill as well right i mean is there anything in your current life that puts a fraction of that
pressure on you in a moment certainly not and i think it's it's something i was able to really
describe because i stepped away for a few years and then came back to compete again at the age of
24 25 and and i could finally articulate what it felt like and it was like battery acid running
through your chest with a thousand pounds of weight crushing you you're like how do i even move
and and again this is what really taps back into denial is you can't really identify with your
feelings you have to shut them down and i think that's why i found acting so appealing when i was
done skating was because there's there's a spectrum of humanity and actors are on the far
left and athletes are on the far right and normal humans are in the middle where when as an athlete
if you are have fear any feeling you have to shut it down you have to be impervious you're always
fine you're a robot you're projecting confidence and as an actor you have to take in every emotion
from the outside every vulnerability cultivate feeling because that's that's your paintbrush
that's how you live and as a as a human in the middle you have places you feel safe to be
vulnerable and open but you certainly aren't at work you don't cry when you see every homeless
person and and you learn in the middle but athletes are on the far far end of the spectrum
where you just learn to shut everything down because you're dealing with so much all the time
and just this is pressure and i think it's hard to learn to be a normal functioning human being
after you're an athlete it's i think it's almost in the same way you you're a soldier and and i
you know i hesitate that some ways to make the comparison because obviously we're not putting
our lives on the line and this is sport but the element of the human is shut down for the task
and it's all about the task and and that's something it takes time to learn how to be
a human again after it's so interesting you the way you explain that which i guess i now see it's
after 2006 when you go and you take acting classes as you say that's a big part of i think
what enabled you to maybe come back in 2010 with a different perspective perhaps i mean yeah i think
it was the break from it because i think a lot of it is habituation so if you start competing from
the age of of five years old you're you're nervous but you're a tiny little competitions
and you know kids are really nervous even when they're seven years old you see them running to
the bathroom to throw up before they skate and they're pacing and they're crying and they've got
butterflies and these are just seven-year-olds at tiny little local competitions and so you're kind
of habituated at a young age and then your competitions get slowly bigger and then they're
national and there's more people but at the time you get to the olympics even though this is the
biggest stage you've ever been on it's been this steady ramp up to that and then i took three years
away from it and then i came back and so i and i was just doing shows and so i think i wasn't
constantly stressing my nervous system with these kind of nerves and feelings and so i think when
i took a break and came back i was just like part of you is like i'm never doing this again this is
how could i ever subject myself to this but then once you go out and you're performing it's this
most incredible high and so as an athlete i think you get used to these high highs and these low lows
of these lonely difficult moments where you're injured and you're dealing with so much psychological
stress to these moments where you're out doing what you ultimately love to do and the crowd is
cheering for you and you feel like you know you're paused in this most unique moment in time doing
what you love and after i retired you know life was just nice and that was wonderful for a year
and then life just felt flat because everything had evened out the high highs were gone the low lows
were gone and then you're kind of learning how to live without that paradigm i've read that 80 percent
of olympians or former olympians suffer or have at least experienced in some transient form a
form of depression does that i mean does that sound believable to you having been on the inside
certainly and i'm sure that the number might even be higher because again we don't as athletes we're
taught not to admit weakness and it's not only to the outside world it's to yourself because if you
admit weakness to yourself then you're undermining what you're capable of and the biggest tragedy
there's a you know there's multiple factors one mental health issues can be a stigma and so people
generally don't talk about them and they should and then on top of that as an athlete if you admit
that you're struggling it's going to undermine your own performance and and you don't want to
admit that to yourself or let your competitors know and then once you retire you lose your
identity and you lose your purpose and something you've spent a decade or two decades your whole
team of support and everything you do and everything you wake up for which is like this
moment four years down the line you like imagine yourself on a podium and and you've charted out
this whole path to get there and then all of a sudden you don't have the goal anymore you don't
have the identity anymore you're watching other people do what you did but they're doing it better
because they're the next generation and and you don't have a skill set that everyone else your age
does who was actively pursuing an academic education and went to college and interned and
really setting themselves up for the next 40 years of your life it's all been this rug has been pulled
from underneath you and so not only are you mourning your identity and have lost your sense
of purpose but now you see yourself as 10 years behind normal people and you don't even know what
you want to do but there's this interesting thing i've observed which is there's there are a subset of
people and you and apollo would be great examples of it where you seem to have made the transition
so easily now you've made it look easy i'm not suggesting it's easy of course but you were
basically able to take the rumba mentality of i can go harder i can go faster i can go longer i
can go deeper than anybody just give me a new skill set and you know you emerge at one of the
best colleges in the country and you kick ass and you know today you've got a great job in finance
there are a handful of athletes who just make this transition and if you're saying it's hard
i mean what's happening for most athletes i mean i mean i'm not asking that rhetorically like
what does the graveyard look like for especially olympic athletes it's different if you've at least
played five years in the nfl and you've managed to stash away seven figures but most olympians
don't come close to scraping together that kind of money so what are they do they go on to become
coaches and like how many of them are able to resume where they would have been or get back on
that same path if they had chosen something else because they're obviously very capable but they're
going to need new you know they're going to need to be retrained there's so many variables i think
the mindset of an individual athlete versus someone that was on a team sport yeah that's
a good point and then is this something where they went to their first olympics at 27 or 30 and
they've kind of developed this identity and this group of friends were they actually in where they
did they actually go to college and were they playing a collegiate sport because then you
develop very differently than if you're a gymnast or a skater or speed skater and you've been
homeschooled since seven and this is your world and it's it's myopic and then your personality
type like how neurotic are you and what do you see as success and what's your appetite for
the unknown i think some you know across all sports some people continue to coach they judge
they they want to be in their sport and they want to be the big fish in the small pond and they
continue to hold on to that identity as this greatest moment of their life and what to find
them and then i think there's others that that prefer to be the tadpole in the ocean and you
have to deal with this sense of insignificance and feeling lost and realizing the more you learn
about the world the bigger you realize it is and then the more confused you are the more options
and and i think i definitely chose the the tadpole and the ocean route and i moved to new york and i
went to columbia and and i'm still learning who i am and and what it is i want to do and and
redefining success because i think at the age you know when i when i was competing and when i was
21 it's like oh well what's the next thing that seems really competitive and athletic and i can
define winning and to me that seemed like finance you know i went i got a liberal arts education and
you start to realize what's out there you realize that success is what you define it to be
and that actually happiness starts to be more important to you than what society quote unquote
deems success because success is fleeting and maybe success is a moment but you're quickly
replaced and what are you building your life around and so i think there's a there's definitely
a value shift instead of just like this plug and play at first it's like i'm going to take
everything and all this intensity i had in my sport and put it towards something else
and be the best and just like show everyone and this is this is my new vehicle it's like
just show me what to do and i'll get to the top and then you realize like is this mountain worth
climbing even this is a formula that i knew before but applying it somewhere else this
isn't actually what i want and i think it takes a lot of time and reflection and kind of self
growth to realize like what's worth doing like what's worth like what actually is winning in life
what do you think enabled you to figure this out because honestly talking with you sasha it's
blowing my mind that you you are so wise beyond your years when you talk about that right i mean
you have figured something out that most people never figure out in life and yet you have two
thirds of your life still ahead of you in terms of years how do you think you made that transition
think you made that transition i mean obviously there's some deliberate choices so you made a
decision in 2010 not just am i going to leave the sport but i'm not going to wrap my identity around
this sport either i'm going to go beat the tadpole i'm going to go and roll at columbia
where frankly i'm going to suck because i'm competing with a bunch of whippersnappers that
came out of high school and they're way better prepared than i am and i'm going to be doing an
internship in something with a bunch of kids that are 10 years younger than me and probably a bunch
smarter than me when it comes to these tangible sets of facts and skills that one would have
learned and i totally appreciate what you're saying that part of that was the challenge of
this is my new olympics my new olympics is going to be graduating first of my class and doing x y and
z but but then what you described at the end there was another transition which is wait a minute like
that's not even the way i want to live my life anymore which is it's not about being the best
tell me how that realization and the application of that came to you i think it's in finding things
to be hollow it's going down a path that you think oh if i'm just the most successful in this if i
work my way up to the top i'll find identity and fulfillment and i'll be good enough
and then you realize as you do it these things look sexy from the outside but once you're in
them it's really not what it appears to be it's like people do this so they can show you the
country club in the car and the the business card and maybe some people really love what they do
and these are these are side effects but i think a lot of people do things for approval and for
status in society and i think at a very young age i got used to being rewarded by the public but for
for achieving and so i felt that what i needed to do had to be publicly visible and needed to be
appreciated and to be validated and then i think as you you get older you know i i've spent a lot of
time become very very interested in different buddhist texts and in meditation and just
understanding this this bigger picture of life because i think we get so singularly absorbed
in like what's in front of us in the moment and we think it's the most important thing and then
the biggest struggle for me and something that i daily work on is what do i actually want to do
versus what do i think other people will be impressed with and again i think this is like
the resume versus the eulogy are you a fan of the book by david brooks the road to character
or the second mountain being the more recent one i actually haven't read the road to character but
i i read the second mountain and found it very very compelling and powerful and i think that's
the phase of life that i'm certainly in and i have a lot of questions and i'm exploring like
what makes a meaningful life and what actually brings me joy if i can peel away all the layers
that my upbringing through sport and society have projected onto me because sometimes you you don't
really know the difference and you end up doing things that people around you do because that's
what they respect and ultimately we're we're social animals and we want to be respected by
others to have a sense of of self-worth if you can really strip all those things away then you can
start to have the dialogue with yourself of what you actually like and what if you really like
something that the world doesn't validate who's gonna win like are you going to do something for
them or you can just think for you and this is still you there's still tension there yeah of course
yeah well let's play a hypothetical game because what i'm not hearing you say to be clear is
you regret the decade and a half you spent killing yourself to be the world's best figure
skater i'm not i'm not hearing you say that but i want to just play a thought experiment which
is i'm going to put you in a time machine and i'm going to take you back and you're going to get to
spend the next 10 years with 15 year old sasha so we're going to take you back to circuit 1998
you're two years outside of your first olympics but now you i'm going to change the way you look
so that the 15 year old version doesn't realize this is the adult version of her but you now get
to become another coach slash mentor to the girl and you know everything you know so you know how
the story ends if she stays the course how would you counsel her that's such a hard question because
it's going backwards and tweaking something you don't know what's going to happen going forward
admittedly yes we we run the risk of the butterfly effect here big time well let me ask you then i'll
start with some broad themes well this is the more i think about this question the more interesting
it gets in that through the lens of if you only have knowledge through 2010 versus seeing where
you are today it might it might be different let me make it an easier question then which is the
question i didn't want to ask because it's such a common question which is what advice would you give
yourself let's take a hybrid of that basically which is how much would you let her worry about
what she's doing even if alleviating some of that worry subjected her to the risk of not being as
successful it's really an interesting question because i would want to go back and say enjoy
this time right this is enjoy being at the olympics enjoy being on the ice and moving and
having your body like honed and trained to this this such this this incredible degree right it's
it's such a rare fleeting moment later you're going to be jogging and you're going to be winded
very different it really is incredible because ultimately it's like the a piece of this
incredible journey that it means to be human right and it's it's a very extraordinary exceptional
piece that you can get to you know the top of a spore that you can represent your country that
you can see the world like it's it's such a gift but at the same time if you if you tell this
younger girl there's so many things after you're going to go to college like the world is so much
bigger than this maybe you wouldn't stick it out maybe you wouldn't stick out those really
difficult times i remember a few years before my second olympics fourth of july everyone was
barbecuing i was training at a center in connecticut i had the key to the rink opened up was just
training by myself and then i went with my off ice coach to the outdoor track and was doing
sprints and 100 degree heat and just broke down crying and i was like i don't want to be here i
want to be with my family i don't want to do this and this is like oh nine this probably would have
been in like 2004 oh before the second one just complete breakdown and in that moment if you're
like you know what college is going to be amazing you're going to find poetry and you know your
philosophy and it's going to blow your mind and buddhism be like why am i what am i doing like
how many days am i going to have groundhog day of doing the same thing over and over in this rink and
to this day i go to an ice rink and i smell that that musty smell of rubber mats and that's there's
visceral there's like some ptsd associated with it certainly it's visceral and i think if you know
that there's more and i guess i'm a person that i've got so many interests and there's so much i
want to do and i have so much fomo i i want to be in every country and i want to get a phd and
in you know buddhist studies and i want to do everything so i think if i knew more about the
world in those hard times i think it would have been much harder to stick it out when that
versus that being your only identity and your whole world well there's there's certainly a
reason why they have to put blinders on race horses i don't know i guess that's sort of the
thing that that about it that that feels i've had this discussion with a number of my friends who
are you know in your situation right so people who were at one point the best in the world and now
they're they're normal quote unquote right anything but trying to be yeah but you know what
i mean there's a sadness there's a very famous athlete who was incredibly well celebrated and
decorated 20 years ago he's really fallen on hard times now substance abuse a whole bunch of other
things and you know sort of behind closed scenes there have been a handful of people that have
tried to help them to really you know get him back from the from the edge of drugs alcohol
all of the things that have sort of taken him to within about the inch of his life repeatedly
and it's hard to look at him because i still i can't get the image out of my mind of him when he
was the best in the world at what he did and there was a whole country that viewed him as the most
amazing thing they'd ever produced and now this entire country would abandon him in a heartbeat
out of pure disregard and shame for who he is and what he's become and what seems unfair to me
is that the same forces that lifted him up he was a national champion at 17 that you know the
greatest that that country had ever produced the same forces that put the blinders on him to enable
him to spend a decade of his life being the identity of a nation in a sport are the exact
same forces that have abandoned him and given him nothing to cope with the complete emptiness and
bitterness of his existence and the shame that has followed it if i had the ability to tell the whole
story with all the details it would be a more powerful story but i think you get what i'm
talking about because even though this is an extreme example it's not actually that extreme
in terms of the emotions it might be extreme in terms of the net effects you know the near death
and the drug overdoses and stuff but i think this is sort of the guilty this is sort of the guilty
part that we have as the spectators right is we don't realize that the same thing that we throw
on the athlete to sort of praise them is the very same gasoline that is to a bad fire as it is to a
good campfire kind of thing if that makes sense athletes generally start young and so there's a
conditioning that sets an early validation through performance and through through winning so
it's Pavlovian and you're trained that that's how that's how you're defined and that's how you're
respected and adored and so you you very much try to prove yourself to the world to get this
this validation back but i think something that's important to remember is like you can be a healthy
functioning human being or you can be the best in the world at something but you can't be both
you believe that to be true i do because i'm talking about sports at this point in time but
you have to sacrifice all these other things you have to sacrifice your emotional well-being
time with friends like socializing in school these other things that would make you well-rounded
and knowing you know someone telling you it's like oh it's okay if you fell or you want to
take a week off and you're not defined by this you are a full human being and that's not what
we value you for but that's not true and i think what happens is in sport you become valued for
what you do and as soon as you stop doing it or stop doing it as well as you did all your value
is gone and so it's like you spend you know it's like all blood, sweat, and tears creating
the social cultural value by winning and as soon as you stop winning the value just like it just
disintegrates so quickly. Being versus doing is a very eastern versus western sort of mantra
yet when it comes to sports there seems to be no eastern it's all western isn't it in other words
there's no buddhist athletes in the sense of it's just being like even if you're competing in the
olympics from eastern parts of the world in the end athleticism always comes down to to what you're
doing. Nike's slogan just do it we don't care how you feel it's about what you do it's funny i was
recently reading an older version of the art of war and 50 pages was the introduction it went back
to the genesis of eastern and western thought and philosophy back to confucius and back to
aristotl and plato and in the west we always think that we do something that there's a mover
and a move a cause and an effect that there's god and he created everything else and you go into to
eastern culture and and it's symbiotic everything is a relationship god is everything and it's about
relationships and the belief isn't that you cause something but that you are part of something and
it's all interrelated it doesn't apply to sports but i think it really goes into the philosophies
and the way that people in eastern versus western cultures have historically lived and and that
really stuck with me because there's it's a lot of responsibility to feel that you cause everything
that it's all up to you to a certain extent it's true in certain ways but there's there's so much
that we don't control and that we still don't understand and that how things are all interrelated
and i think that's that's important to remember and i think it's helpful as an athlete to remove
yourself from this cause and effect way of living to understand that you're you're also a part of
something one of the exercises that i find really helpful when i really get in my head is and it
sounds morbid but i just start imagining the world in my absence it's a game you play if you go to
enough funerals but you realize the earth wouldn't slow down by one millisecond on its axis if i cease
to be here which is not to say that i can't make a difference or that i don't matter i do matter i
matter to at least a small group of people if nothing else my family but it's a way for me to
get out of what you're describing which is like taking on more sense of importance it is really
interesting the number of people for whom their removal from this planet matters is really low
now of course the flip side of that is how do you create meaning and purpose which as you've talked
about i mean did you know steve hulkam i did not you know i heard many stories about him and he's
featured quite a bit in this documentary the weight of gold tell us a little bit about that
how did that come about so a friend of mine germany bloom had found the director his name
is brett and he was actually wanting to do a comeback story because steven was i think coming
back for a second or third games had won multiple olympic medals he was living in a training center
in lake placid and he thought oh what a great comeback story i'll kind of film him going into
the games and had interviewed him 12 days before he actually died before he committed suicide
and then all of a sudden that changed the whole direction of the film and then brought in all
these other athletes some other athletes who had committed suicide and other athletes that had
suicidal thoughts or really struggled with depression and really put a voice to what it's
like to lose that sense of identity and for steven in particular he was living in the training center
felt very isolated was starting to lose his vision was driving the bobsled car and you know
felt all this the enormity of it the pressure and not really having an outlet for how to talk about
it and and would would say that after this olympics even if i win i'm gonna have to go live in my
mom's basement because i don't have any money and you don't make any money doing what i do in this
sport and i think it's just kind of the isolation and the pressure starting to lose his vision and
just the enormity of it he really suffered with with mental health issues and
there's a whole spectrum you know there's people like him and like speedy peterson
who ended up committing suicide as well who might have had intrinsic mental health issues
but then there's all these things that are aggravated by the fact that you you lose an
identity when you're done competing and even if you're still competing just the enormity
of the pressure and you're handling it alone and i think it's so important that athletes michael
felds is a part of this so is shawn white and apollo ono are coming together and really talking
about what the process of training is like and what the loss feels like on the other side of an
olympic games and how they try to process it and from the outside it may look like they have
everything and that they're this epitome of success but the sense of hollowness they have
on the inside this loss of identity and where it takes them because you have these really incredible
type a personalities that will do anything and sacrifice anything to achieve and then all of a
sudden their whole platform for achieving it has been erased and i think it really leaves you like
a fish out of water we want to say well all these people that have depressive tendencies or that
have committed suicide have mental health issues but we make it sound like that's a binary
distinction or something like that like they have cancer they don't have cancer or something like
that i mean in the end i think we're all quite susceptible to quote unquote whatever mental
health means you know i'm writing a book on longevity and probably the reason the book is
taking so long to be completed is because i just can't finish this chapter on emotional health
it's the final chapter it's the 17th chapter in a book but i feel strongly about writing it because
through my own sort of journey i've realized that none of this other stuff like it doesn't really
matter how long you live if you're miserable longevity means nothing if it's married to misery
but it's very hard to do and people keep asking me oh how's the chapter on mental health coming
and i keep saying well i'm not i'm not calling it mental health because it strikes me as just a bit
of a loaded term it's really emotional health and it doesn't come with a diagnosis and it doesn't
come with an icd 10 code it doesn't have a chapter in the diagnostic and statistical manual
the dsm 5 and all these other things i don't know if it means that steve had quote unquote mental
illness i mean the bottom line is it's just a tragedy in in this sense and it's just an extreme
example but it doesn't in any way it comes back to this point which is maybe it's true 80 percent
of athletes may have this total loss of identity that that can be coupled with some form of
depression that follows this and i guess the bigger point because i imagine there are people
listening to this who on some level might be saying like i can't even relate to what she's
talking about like i'm saying this is the listener and it's true as myself like i'm not even close to
being the best at anything like i'd give my left arm to be the best at something for one day
what would you say to that person it's fleeting i think it's an incredible thrill but i think
ultimately it's complicated we're driven by so many things but it's the life that you build it's
the relationships and i think where mental health can be exasperated is when there's a lack of
relationships steven was living in a dorm and a training center maybe some people love that and
have a sense of camaraderie but maybe some people feel isolated from family and friends
and so i think we don't realize how social we are and how much we need each other and we need
friendships and family in our lives we become such an individual society that it's all about me and
how good am i and what am i doing versus the community and i think that's why there's been
such a spike in rates of depression is this feeling of disconnection and i think it's important to
realize that the things that we see people winning an oscar or winning an olympic gold medal or
achieving some great feat it's incredible and it's a life's work and it should be
applauded but that shouldn't take away anything from the value of a connected loving life doing
something that is fulfilling no matter what that is because ultimately that's something day in and
day out that you have to hold on to because all these other things are moments they're moments
that pass by where you're quickly replaced by the next person that wins the oscar next person that
wins the olympic gold medal and you're holding on to a memory but that feeling is it's something
you've done that you'll always have but you still have to step on to that next chapter and try to
build those relationships and find satisfaction and fulfillment and build a life again so it's like
be careful what you're trading for what how would you help somebody make that transition i mean
obviously the first part of it on some level must be accepting what you've said i mean i accepted
fully because i've seen it as well right i've i've spent time with the people who have been the best
in the world and without exception everything you say is entirely correct based on that experience
there is no sum of money there is no number of trophies there is no number of oscar statues that
can accommodate for or compensate for bad relationships or a bad sense of self but the
how question is hard right it's what do you do when you wake up in the morning to begin
resetting your identity around these things that are less fleeting it takes a lot of work and the
work isn't easy because you are letting go of a whole system of values that have defined you
to an extreme in your sport and to some extent define society as a whole what we value who we
think you know it's the young it's the thin it's the beautiful who we put on billboards and applaud
and read about in in magazines and so you have to be willing to let go of what society is projecting
as this they're selling thin beautiful you know what are we selling as a society and is that
actually making anyone happy you know we think oh when we lose 10 pounds we'll be happier like oh
when i'm in this relationship i'll be happy and then you start to realize that these are kind of
mirages or false illusions because it's profitable for companies to sell you something and it's
easier than looking inside yourself and beginning to change the way that you relate to yourself and
relate to the world and i think that's just there's many many books to read but it's a slow unfolding
it takes time and you have to kind of be curious and want to put in the work but it's very difficult
to let go of the only thing you've ever known of the way that you're supposed to live and what
everyone else applauds it's much easier to just play the game the way everyone else is playing
the game and then hold up the trophy and then everyone applauds you but then at the end of it
you it's great for the day and then it just kind of wears off and then it's just like this
this trophy but what are you now it's funny in some ways athletes have it the worst and maybe
that's why athletes become some of the most powerful examples we have to talk about these things
because i'm sure you've heard david foster wallace's this is water so anybody who's
listening to this podcast will hear me go on and on about it constantly and i can't recommend it
highly enough anyone who's hearing this at this point in time and don't know what i'm talking about
hit pause on your podcast player right now and then go to youtube and then put in david foster
wallace this is water and about a 24 minute talk is going to come up and i want you to
sit down close your eyes and listen to it and then i want you to do that every day for the next
week and then every week for the next three months and then every month thereafter that's
that's the doctor's prescription right now but he talks about not athletes specifically but he talks
about this idea of self of worship we worship things we worship our intellect our bodies
our wealth whatever and to your point they're all hollow i think it's just that athletes figure
this out quicker because the window in which you can be great is so much narrower than say the
window in which you could be rich or the window in which you can be the smartest or the window in
which you can be the fill in the blank it's condensed it's so condensed it's just a super
amplified play on the same theme in some way i i was actually just in ireland and it would rain
and there'd be sunny for a little bit and there would rain and be sunny for a little bit and every
time it would rain i would take it so personally like no like the day is going to be ruined and
how did i plan a trip at this time and it's a short summer and i should have figured this out
but then it'd be sunny five minutes later and it just showed me how much we identify we it's all
about grasping and aversion we want to be successful we don't want to be forgotten and we
usually things are on a longer timeline so we can't really see it because we're in it
but the weather was changing so fast in ireland that i could kind of just see the folly of it and
the undulation of human emotions that aren't completely rational it's only when it was that
close together and tying over to being an athlete it's at such a heightened extreme it's such a
short period of time where you're like this hero you're on a weedy's box you're everything and
then you're forgotten and you know it's the next olympian that they put on the weedy's box and is
going on a speaking tour and it's like okay you're just not that relevant anymore i mean i guess
taking what i said a moment ago olympic athletes are literally the most extreme version of this
because even you know the average player in the nfl might have a tenure of three or four years
which is relatively short compared to baseball or basketball but as you said an olympian on average
is one olympics which means two weeks can you imagine being the best in the world at something
where your entire pinnacle is two weeks that is a real manifestation and it's hard for me to imagine
that that's just a coincidence with this idea that 80 percent of olympians post their career
could experience depression it's hard for me to believe that's just a coincidence the way that we
identify the way we see ourselves is completely responsible for our sense of well-being
and if you set impossible standards or you know that if you're second best in the world that's
the biggest failure and disappointment you're making the margin for feeling successful so
narrow and that even if you meet it it's only a temporary high it's irrelevant you're going
to pass through it before you experience it and it's a temporary high too you know it's like
a chocolate cake you eat the chocolate cake you feel great and then the chocolate cake is gone
and you're like i shouldn't be in the chalky not exactly like that but it passes by and and i think
that we have to think about the way we set up and define success and is success the same thing as
happiness because i think in sports being successful means perhaps sacrificing and being
unhappy and enduring for a very very long time to be successful and to be gratified for for moments
or days but it's not the same thing as cultivating a sense of well-being and being content and loving
your relationships and having meaningful work and what you do that has been very much undervalued
in our society and i think we're seeing a little bit of a a lashback in the sense that a lot of
people are interested in meditation and in yoga and in the sense of community and there's a little
bit of lashback on this individual achiever as being the kind of wherewithal for for success and
joy and the answer because people get there they're like hello this actually isn't it like you know
turn around although it doesn't show at all you're expecting a little guy soon huh i am it's a
testament to how tiny you are that even when you're pregnant you still look super tiny it's so exciting
and the idea of being a mother and moving into this next chapter of my life is
i i guess there's not words you know i try to think about what it means my whole life was so
focused on myself and what i did that i think having the chance to live for someone else and
to create a life for someone else is just again it's part of the arc of being human and i'm so
excited for all that it brings and it's been a complete diversion from planning to see every
country and to so many books that i wanted to read which have now all been replaced with books on
expecting and babies and i'm just like oh this is putting me so behind in my reading
but it's such a joy and reminder that that life is so much bigger than just you and
and the gift and wonder of creating life you know all these things that we consciously work so hard
to do and create and yet the magnitude of what our bodies can unconsciously do and create and
give life to is just so incredible uh if you stop to think about it you know it's just it's a huge
joy and as i was telling you earlier i would like my child to not play sports at a very high level
but i want to fulfill you know in a healthy way all the fantasies that i never had in my childhood
and you know the debate team and playing guitar and spending time in the you know wilderness
classes so well i'm sure that there'll be a lot of detours and opinions of the child's own is your
olympic metal somewhere in your apartment is it is it featured is it one of those things that
sits in a sock drawer or is it something that that sits out there it's so funny my mom actually has
it and it's it's on top of her it's kind of like mounted on top of her dresser it's as much hers is
yours isn't it yeah and i think when i moved to new york i kind of left some of that stuff behind
and it was very important for me to split and and create a new identity and not hold on to that so
i really i really let it go and just focused on you know i adopted my legal name alexandra and
i was alex at school and i just really pushed forward but when i wanted to take i had two
olympic rings i wanted to take them with me and wear them my mom said i i should get to keep one
of them she's like i you know i'm putting a lot of time in work and to be fair i can't even imagine
now you know as i'm expecting just sacrifice and dedication for you know over 15 years of her life
was about me with taking me to different ice rinks and physical therapists and and i was like
you know what i'll leave her both rings you know she she deserves that but it's again you just
really the metal is a metal and i'm not again it's what it represents and the journey of my life and
how figure skating and sport define me is incredible and i can't imagine who i would
be today without that but again it's an object so it's not something i feel compelled to have
or put on a wall or have near me but it is representative of this moment of my life
you were really fortunate to have motherhood demonstrated for you like amazingly right when
you think about what you learn from your mom and how you're going to write your own playbook
that's going to look different right i mean presumably your kid's not going to be figure
skating 10 hours a day so it's not going to be you're the way you spent enough time in an ice
rink yeah it's like it's not allowed but what are the one two or three things that you will take from
the lessons your mom lived the practice that you saw in her as a mother to your son and potentially
other children down the line i think a sense of selflessness and commitment to the family
and just what it means to be a mother and and what a privilege it is and i think
in society we don't always honor and worship the mother in the way that she should be and that she
gives life and and it's you know it's kind of in the past has been relegated to kind of like the
home but what we respect is what people do out in the world it's just part of creating your own
set of values and and thinking for yourself of like what is actually valuable and i think
at the end of anyone's life they'll say it's like the time they spent with their kids and their
loved ones you know even these little small moments i think for me having been homeschooled
and had my my whole you know a lot of the team around me focus on what i did it created a
self-centered way of seeing the world and so i think this opportunity to step back and have not
life be about like what am i going to do am i going to be good enough or what's the next thing
or how are people perceiving me but giving the gift of life and having my my son and you know
show me to kind of reawaken you know i think a lot of times when we get to a certain place in life we
we're a little bit set in our ways of like what we expect what disappoints us how things should
be and i think what i've heard from from friends and parents is that your child is your greatest
teacher because when they see something for the first time or they ask you about something it's
the sense of play that you kind of forget about because you're worried about responsibilities
or how things should be i'm very much looking forward to that and i think you know i want to
expose my child to to the world to travel to show him how big the world is and to really just
explore it and you know life is this incredible adventure and so it's not really about becoming
anything like becoming a product or becoming really good at something it's i think just having
this huge life full of love and an adventure well i mean i can't seem to the future but my
intuition tells me you will embrace and succeed it succeeds maybe the wrong word but for lack of a
better word you will certainly embrace and succeed in motherhood in a way that you've done in
everything else to date and i suspect it will only enhance this journey that you're on and i want to
thank you so much for taking the time and the being vulnerable with us to sort of share a lot
of this stuff i i know it's hard sometimes for normal people like me to try to extract insights
from the best people in the world at something but i think you've done a great job of reminding
us that whether you're the best at something that seems you know like there can only be one best in
the world it is fleeting there's probably no arena in which that fleeting nature of greatness is more
evident than in the olympic arena i'm glad you've brought us along this journey thank you sasha thank
you for having me on and opportunity to go back and kind of reminisce so thank you i enjoyed it
you can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast
there you'll find the show notes readings and links related to this episode you can also find
my blog at peteratiamd.com maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively
non-lame once a week email where i'll update you on what i've been up to the most interesting
papers i've read and all things related to longevity science performance sleep etc on social
you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id peteratiamd but usually twitter
is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments now for the obligatory disclaimer this
podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine
nursing or other professional health care services including the givings of medical advice and note
no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the materials linked to
the podcast is at the user's own risk the content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute
for professional medical advice diagnoses or treatment users should not disregard or delay
in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance
of their health care professionals for any such conditions lastly and perhaps most importantly i
take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures the companies i invest in and or
advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about