Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. I guess this week are Dr. Deborah Kimless and
Steve Goldner. I'm not going to say much about them by way of background because I opened the
interview by asking them to introduce themselves because their backgrounds are so relevant to the
discussion we have. I sought out both Deb and Steve because I wanted to have a discussion that
would frankly first inform me, but obviously provide the necessary and relevant background
information to all of you as listeners on a topic that frankly it confuses me to no end, which is
the entire morass of THC, CBD, hemp, cannabis, that whole landscape. Truthfully, I've never
fully been able to understand this in part because I think it's just very confusing in part perhaps
because I haven't put enough effort into it. Preparing for this podcast was a great exercise
in doing just that. In this episode, we talk about a lot of things, but we start frankly with some of
the semantics. What is the difference between THC, CBD? Where do these things work? How do they work
in the body? What's the difference between what it's doing in the brain and what it's doing
elsewhere? How do molecules work that aren't neat and clean like designer drugs where one molecule
hits one receptor? As you'll see, cannabis, it works very different from that. We also then get
into some of the safety issues. At the time of this recording, which was in late October 2019,
there is obviously an epidemic, or at least a perceived epidemic around the dangers of vaping.
We touch on some of the reasons why that may be the case, but really for the past three years,
we have been witnessing both a market evolution, a scientific evolution, and certainly a policy
evolution, which may be the most important as it pertains to this subject matter. Again, I think
as you'll see in the first few minutes, Deb and Steve are really great people to have this
discussion with because collectively between them, you have a medical, a pharmacological, and a
regulatory expertise that is brought to bear. Now, it's worth pointing out that both Steve and Debra
are involved in a company. Steve is the founder and CEO of Pure Green, and Deb is the chief medical
officer. I point that out to say everything must be interpreted with a grain of salt. Obviously,
Steve and Deb have a commercial interest in this space. Now, I will tell you that after spending
two hours with them, or slightly more than two hours during this podcast, also spending another
hour with them off mic, getting into stuff that we just weren't comfortable talking about on mic,
I come away thinking very highly of them, very highly of their work, and believing that their
intentions here go far beyond just the commercial intentions of people involved in this space.
This is a confusing topic, and I won't represent that this one podcast is going to answer every
possible question you have. The good news is it might not matter if it did, because frankly,
this is an area that is evolving so much, and I suspect this is a topic that I will need to go
back to probably a year from now. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with
Steve Goldner and Debra Kimless. Debra, Steve, thank you so much for making time to come and
talk about this stuff today. This is kind of an unusual podcast in that we weren't introduced
through anybody. I sort of organically reached out to you guys on the basis of so much demand
and so many questions about this topic, which is something, as I've alluded to, I'm completely
ignorant of. So this is a topic I've been really looking forward to learning about because patients
ask me about it constantly. I think the implications are only becoming more significant as we watch the
evolution of the legal environment. So having a physician and a lawyer to talk about this is
perfect. Deb, can you give me a bit of background on your interest in this? You're an anesthesiologist.
I know you specialize in pain. Tell me what drew you to this specifically. So what drew me to this
is that my mom was dying from a complication from a pharmaceutical drug, and because of that, I
started really thinking about what we learned in medical school, how we were trained, and what else
could there have been for my mom as an option other than a pharmaceutical. And as she lay dying,
my significant others in Israel, he said, you know, they're studying medical cannabis in Israel.
And unfortunately, my mom didn't have an opportunity to try medical cannabis as a pain
reliever because she died. But I spent really since 2013, until now, studying and investigating
the veracity of whether or not cannabis truly is a medicinal molecules. Steve, how did you guys
meet and how did you get involved in this? Well, I've been involved in pharmaceutical
formulations as a scientist for almost 50 years now. As a forensic toxicologist at the New York
Medical Examiner, I worked on 18,000 autopsies. So I developed and formulated the drug liquid drug
methadone about 47 years ago, because friends of mine were coming back addicted from the Vietnam
War. So that worked out pretty well, developed that formulation methadone has done very well
of helping people around the world. And I went on to become FDA attorney working in the pharmaceutical
industry, but always working in this arena. I became interested in cannabis as a medicine
almost 45 years ago. A friend of mine came back from Vietnam War with PTSD. And he asked me to
develop a drug that would help cure him of that. And I noticed that when he smoked marijuana, he
felt much better when he drank or got pills from the VA, he did not. And so I realized that cannabis
could be a medicine, but it just wasn't legal at the time. And I wasn't that right kind of lawyer
to get that legalized. Now I have that opportunity to be able to do it. That's what brought me into
it. He also, my buddy who's passed away of cirrhosis of the liver about seven years ago,
made me vow to do this. So developing methadone at the beginning of my career was a first bookend
and now developing all these formulations to help people with cannabis is the second bookend on my
career. And how did the two of you meet? So I lecture around the country and around the world,
and I present studies that I have done on my own. These are case studies. I treat over 400 patients
free of charge, a bad business model, but what I've learned from these patients is tremendous
using diet changing cannabinoid medicines. And I share them with colleagues so that they too can
understand cannabis is a medicine. And Steve and I met two years ago at Cologne, Germany, I think it
was at IACM where I was presenting a poster and he tracked me down and we had our first conversation
there. And together you guys are part of a company. We'll probably hear a little bit about that company
today, but the aim of this company, I assume, is to create sort of what you perceive to be the safest,
most efficacious form of delivery of cannabis. Is that a fair assessment? Yes, that's exactly it.
I think to understand why you guys do what you do, we have to understand a whole bunch of things that
I don't understand right now. So let's just start with some history. How long has cannabis been
consumed by humans to the best of our knowledge? Historically, it's been used as a medicine for
5,000 years. I mean, this is crazy. It's new for us now, but it's not a new medication. In Asia,
the king fancied himself a pharmacist and he was treating people for all sorts of disorders from
gout to absent memory, believe it or not, even though people are like, dude, where's my car?
Here he was helping people with memory loss with it. The ancient Greeks used it
topically on their horses, which is why I do know that the acid forms of the cannabis medicine
actually work because they love their war horses. They applied the cannabis leaves to the horse's
bodies to reduce the swelling, inflammation, and infection after a war or a battle. Historically,
when did it sort of fall out of favor, back in favor, it said, I mean, for most people,
when they think about marijuana, they sort of think of the sixties and seventies as this era
in which the public sort of got to know it and it became then sort of demonized. When was it
actually scheduled, Steve? I think that was the beginning of around 1930 or so. That is, there were
a number of individuals who thought that this was just a completely inappropriate
drug to be allowed out, a recreational drug. And there was a lot of movement towards controlling
people's appetites in many ways, including drinking alcohol that have floated in and out through America
and across the world. So it began then with an idea of prohibition and it was really given a much
more emphatic push under the Nixon administration for it's often said for their own political
purposes of being able to disenfranchise people who would utilize marijuana, young people or people
of color. And that became essentially the war on drugs policy that was promulgated through the
United Nations and around the world because the United States often was the funder of those
activities. That's continued for quite some time, but is now, as everyone knows, dramatically,
dramatically changing. Now, unlike the sort of psychedelics, which were actually scheduled
only about 50 years ago, you're saying marijuana was scheduled in the thirties. I mean, this is
before the FDA? Well, FDA has been around for at least that long and the originally scheduling
of this was under DEA as a narcotic drug and therefore it would not be allowed. And DEA really
had much more of a law enforcement orientation while FDA does have a staff of essentially
policemen working with them. They're not organized in that manner. So they're much more organized
towards what is a medicine, what's a food and how to be able to keep our American health policies
the best possible for people. You talked a moment ago, Deb, about topically applying this. How did
people do that? Was that an oil and what was it? I mean, not that you were there at the time and
we could go back and figure it out, but to the best of our understanding, what is it that was
being applied to, for example, a horse or how was it being used medicinally 5,000 years ago?
It varied depending upon the indication and what they wanted to do. But the horse example was they
were actually applying leaves to these horses, the actual, you know, family is irregular leaves.
There are small amounts of trichomes on those leaves with cannabinoids in them. So of course,
it would work. It was really interesting. In India, they would mix it with heat and milk and make
something called bhang, B-H-A-N-G, and they would drink it as an anesthetic for people. So it really
did vary. It was very interesting that people apply these things in different ways. So today,
when people think about marijuana, the thing they probably have in the back of their mind is more
related to the properties of THC. Is that correct? Yeah, I think that most people, when they think of
cannabis, think about it as THC, intoxication, and smoking. So let's talk a little bit about that.
So you've used the funny reference of Dude Where's My Car? So Jeff Spicoli falling out of the van,
big plume of smoke coming out after him. He is taking a leaf. He is smoking that leaf.
More, I mean, he's with broken pieces of it rolled up into a joint and being smoked.
Right. So cannabis as a plant is very interesting, right? So when it grows in nature,
it grows as a flower. The leaf does have some cannabinoids in it or some of those medicines in
it, but really the most bang for your buck, it comes from the flower where that's what it is.
So Spicoli was probably buying off the street and maybe he's getting some leaf, but he's hoping for
some flower because that's where the majority of the medicine is and, you know, drying it out and
rolling it up and then combusting it. The interesting thing is you can eat the cannabis plant all day
long. You may get a belly ache from all the fiber, but you won't get that intoxicating feeling
because its chemical constituents are not in a way that can get you intoxicated.
I see. Okay. So let's talk about how that intoxication works. What does THC stand for?
Tetrahydrocannabinol. And what does it do in the brain?
So our brains have these sort of docking stations called receptors and chemicals act on different
docking stations or receptors in order to affect a change. So THC works on these docking stations
in our brain and our peripheral nervous system known as CB1 receptor, cannabinoid 1 receptor,
wasn't very interesting name for it, but that's what they call it. And there are also cannabinoid
2 receptors or CB2 receptors were found purrfully predominantly on immune cells, but also on other
tissue as well and in other organs. And so THC has this really unique ability to activate or sit on
the CB1 and CB2 receptors. And did you say both CB1 and 2 are peripheral?
They can be CB2 predominantly is peripheral. CB1 is predominantly in the brain and then other nerves.
So the peripheral nervous system. And what is the next chain of events? So once THC binds to these
receptors, what happens inside the cells? Oh gosh. So depending upon where in those
receptors are located will determine what happens. So for example, if it's in the hippocampus,
it may stimulate areas in that area that will help you extinguish memory. So for people with PTSD
who cannot stop thinking about certain things, that area of the brain extinguishes
memory and helps somebody with PTSD maybe to get some sleep.
How do you think it acts with respect to pain?
It's a multimodal different way of doing it. So centrally, it does interfere with periaqueductal
gray areas. These are areas of the brain that conduct pain signaling where a brain actually
understands this also works perfectly on immune cells to decrease inflammation and reduce cytokine
expression. So it works in a whole host of different ways. We're used to thinking in medicine
actually as an alipaf of a single molecule, single target. But what you really learn is that that's a
great way of understanding how a drug could work, but that's not how it works in a biologic system
known as a person or an animal. And so contrasting this with what you talked about with respect to
your mom's care, for example, she was probably being prescribed opiates, I'm assuming.
So my mom actually died from fracturing to death from a pharmaceutical known as a bisphosphonate
from Phosimax. The weird thing about my mom is that she was one of the 20 to 30% of people who
when they took opiates had an enhanced response to pain, not a decreased response to pain.
So basically, she was using acetaminophen and non-steroidals to try to reduce her pain, which
when she spontaneously blew out her pelvis, didn't really help that much. So we were just
hoping that since medical cannabis works in different methods for pain relief, it could have
been an option for her. Wouldn't have cured her, but could have helped her. Now, one of the other
effects of inhaling marijuana for many people seems to be an increase in appetite. Do we have
a sense of why that's the case? And that's, I remember certainly in medical school, that was
even something that we talked about a lot was patients that had wasting syndromes either with
cancer or AIDS. This would be a great way to help them eat. Exactly. So there are areas of the brain
that control appetite and nausea and vomiting as well in the area in the medulla. In those areas,
is replete with CB1 receptors. So when those areas are stimulated, your appetite is stimulated and
you actually have a desire to eat, which you're right is life-saving for somebody who has wasting
syndrome or who has chemotherapy, induced nausea and vomiting. There's this other thing that now
people talk about a lot called CBD. I probably hadn't even heard of this until maybe four or
five years ago. I mean, Steve, how long has CBD been understood as a distinct part of this equation?
So this is a truly revolutionary new molecule to come out into the public consciousness so quickly.
It's always been in the plant and available to use, but it's because people were so entranced
with the idea of let's get stoned or then let's do some science on this stoning aspect of THC,
that that drew most of the attention. It's just really in the last two or three years that CBD,
because of its non-hallucinogenic effects, has become interesting to people because it appears
to have, it does have so many medicinal applications and at the same time, doesn't get a person stoned.
How is that possible? What is it doing chemically to create that distinction?
So different than THC, CBD does not sit directly on CB1 receptors or CB2 receptors,
but works either indirectly activating the endocannabinoid system or it works on completely
different receptors. And so together it has a synergistic effect with THC or all the other
molecules that live in the cannabis plant or by itself is pretty effective as a medicine.
Now in nature, do they come lockstep one and one for every molecule of THC is one CBD coming with
it or how does that work? So in nature, it doesn't exist at all, right? It isn't until you apply time
and temperature and get rid of that acid form, that carboxyl group on either THC or CBD or any
of the other cannabinoids. So that's kind of interesting as a baseline anyway, but CBD, there
are cultivars or plant strains as known in the street can grow in higher concentrations in certain
cultivars. It can occur as a one-to-one, one molecule to one molecule. It depends upon the
strain that you're growing. The legal definition of hemp is something that's higher in CBD A and
less than 0.3% THC. I'm glad you brought that up. Tell us a little bit more about the difference
between hemp and cannabis specifically and again using the CBD THC delineation. So the legal
definition is for a hemp cultivar is to have less than 0.3% by weight of THC or THC actually
compared to the rest of the biomass or the rest of the molecules in the plant.
Technically, that would make anything hemp that doesn't have THC in it, right?
Exactly. So people use cannabis plants and just crossbreed so that THC is less than 0.3% so that
they can grow it. But the term of industrial hemp back in the day when our constitution was written
and sales were being made out of hemp, it's a totally different plant as it is today,
just because of crossbreeding and farming the way we're doing it.
Steve, the Farm Bill brought this to the forefront recently. Tell us about the Farm Bill and why
that's relevant. I want to come back to this, but just while we're on the topic of hemp,
it's important I think for people to understand this distinction.
The Congress decided, pushed forward by several legislators who had large numbers of farmers,
that this would be a really good cash crop for them. When you think of it, these products are
selling for thousands of dollars a pound compared to 50 cents or a dollar a pound for lettuce or
tomatoes. So if you're a farmer, you'd much rather grow something that you can get thousands of
dollars for. The idea was put forward that this should be something that's allowed now.
We can see across America that people really are interested in it, that medicine can be developed
from it. So it was with this idea that a number of legislators, particularly Senator McConnell,
had a number of farmers in his jurisdiction, wanted to be able to help them in their businesses
and in their personal lives to be able to develop this. Otherwise, these products are imported from
overseas, and we'd like the American population to be able to have a good, well-regulated source
of product here. I think that was the entire idea behind it, was that we would bring the U.S.
Department of Agriculture, as well as other scientific bodies like FDA, to be able to begin
to study these products and help the growers. All of the growers that have worked on cannabis hemp
products have had to do this for generations without having someone like the USDA around to
tell them what pesticides were appropriate to use, how to grow it, how to have good growing conditions
for it. So this has really helped, I think, to be able to advance it. Was the farm bill basically
just an economic package that made it more attractive, or was there some legalization
that was previously not there? The farm bill really provided legal cover for farmers to be able to
grow the hemp and then to be able, for processors, then to be able to process it into oil and be able
to turn it on into other products. So it started out as something to just aid farmers, but now it
is moving through the economic distribution chain, and that's why we can see it now in nearly every
drug store or big box store as finished goods on the shelf. What are some of the products that come
from the hemp plant? There are vape cartridges, certainly, although they're not at the moment,
not all that perhaps professionally done except by those who are licensed to be able to do it.
There's a very large gray or black market in it, but there are lotions, creams, ointments.
You can find CBD products in ice cream and tea. Soon it'll be in coffee and nearly every other
consumer product that's available. Is the idea that there are certain hemp products that do not
contain CBD and certain hemp products that do, or is the implication that all hemp products are
containing CBD? So I think what you're asking is about the industrial uses of hemp beyond the
cannabinoid. And so you can put that flower into seed and make hemp seeds from it, which has a
wonderful profile of omega 3 to omega 6, probably better than anything, and a wonderful source of
protein as well. The fiber that it comes from, hempfryer has a tensile strength of steel or greater
than steel. Where you see plastic goods, you can actually substitute for hemp. It's just really
expensive machinery for now until they figure it out.
Meaning it displaces the petroleum in plastic or what is it displacing?
Yes, it displaces the petroleum in plastic. So you can make a credit card out of hempfiber.
You can make hempcrete. So instead of concrete, you can actually use it, make it to make it
concrete. There are BMWs right now that are using parts of their door panels and dashboards using
hemp. You can make cloth, you can make clothing, you can make sellers sales.
Do you have a sense of you take all of the biomass that's being produced in the United States from a
hemp crop today, how much of it is being used for all of these industrial uses and how much is being
used just for CBD? I assume the latter is a tiny fraction of it.
Oh no, I think CBD is the lion's share of it because that's where the money is right now.
The de-cortication machine, the machine that is required to break down the stock, which is
incredibly fibrous and tough, is very expensive right now. And I think that there's such a
huge interest, at least in the United, well everywhere, but especially in the United States,
for CBD as a potential medicine or tonic, that's where the money is. So it's a lot easier to extract
and make derivative products than it is to create a lot of these other iterations that I just
described as an industrial use. But let me just interject that some of these other uses are just
remarkable and have been around for a long time. Henry Ford personally was very proud of having
developed a hemp mobile. And he actually had built a car that ran and its fuel was fueled by
hemp oil. So the entire car in the 1930s could have been put out on the road and they had to
shelve that project because suddenly hemp was illegal, because it came from the marijuana
sought marijuana plants. When did CBD become federally legal? I assume it is federally legal
today or is it still state regulated? Well, it certainly is state regulated and each state has
its own regulations. The federal regulation of it is continuing to unfold. The farm bill has legalized
hemp itself. It has not directly said that CBD is okay to put into products.
Rather, there's been an intense push on the Food and Drug Administration whose responsibility it
is to regulate those kinds of consumer products that they should move expeditiously and actually
Deb testified before FDA about five months or so ago on the safety and effectiveness of CBD to
help them in their data gathering. So when you spoke to the FDA, Deb, what were the main points
you tried to get across? The main points that we discussed was about a clinical trial that we ran
using a water soluble iteration of CBD for mild to moderate pain in a 16 patient cohort and the
results of it. I wanted to share that with safety, efficacy and our results. Let's talk a little bit
about that. So you said 16 patients that had mild to moderate pain, meaning what was the etiology of
their pain? So it was multifactorial. I didn't just stratify to one condition because I just
wanted to see it was a proof of concept trial and I actually didn't think it was going to work.
Steve was kind enough to let me formulate an ultra low dose, five milligrams of CBD with some
curated terpenes in a water soluble tablet. I gave it to 16 patients who had mild to moderate pain
for which they were treating their pain with an over the counter medication. And we ran this
trial for two weeks and we had statistically significant decrease in pain across all 16
patients. How do you control for the placebo effect there? Was there a control in that study?
There was not. Again, it was a proof of concept study to see if this ultra low dose of CBD would
even work and it did. There's no control for placebo for really for anything. I mean, I know
lots of patients I'm sure you do as well that seem to really respond to a whole host of medicines,
whether it comes from a double blind randomized trial or not. How does CBD in your mind differ
from THC? We know obviously how it does from an intoxication standpoint. How do you think it
differs in the remainder of the profile? It works in a different mechanisms of action.
For example, CBD doesn't sit on a CB1 receptor, but what it does is it interacts with the breakdown
products of our naturally occurring endocannabinoids, which does sit on a CB1 receptor.
So by enhancing that, that's one pain relieving mechanism of action. It interacts with
dopamine, norepinephrine, epinephrine type receptors and enhances those chemicals as well.
So it works in a multimodal way, just like all of our other medications.
I'm trying to in my mind wrap this idea around a Venn diagram of THC and CBD. Does that make sense
where you have certain things that they both do and then things that are unique to each of them?
Does that make sense to think of it that way? It does and it doesn't. So I understand as an
allopathic physician that that's how we like to look at things. That's a very reductionist view
of it. And I think this is really botanical medicine. We really have a lot of different
constituents within it. There's over a hundred different cannabinoids, over 80 plus terpenes,
flavonoids, and probably constituents were not smart enough yet to even have figured out.
What do the terpenes do? Terpenes occur in nature in all kinds of plants and in foods that are
giving the taste and the scent to all kinds of things. And they're anti-inflammatory. They're
actually secondary metabolites like the cannabinoids as well. And it's used for the plant,
not for our benefit, but for its benefit as a natural pesticide, a antioxidant. And it works
that way in our bodies as well. I want to come back to sort of the THC side of the equation.
Let's start talking about some of the health risks and or benefits and let's start with the risks.
What do you think are the most important risks to understand from THC use?
So I think everybody is different. We're all an N of one and we all respond differently
to the same type of thing. So if I give one person an aspirin, their headache may go away.
Somebody else may die of an allergic reaction to it. In some people who are very sensitive to THC,
they may not just feel intoxicated, but they may feel so much anxiety and panic that they are
incredibly uncomfortable. And some is dose dependent, but some experience that even with
a small amount. Some people experience a feeling of well-being with a little bit of THC. Some people
have a rapid heartbeat and their blood pressure shoots up and have an uncomfortable experience.
How much of that do we think is setting dependent? So if you took the same person,
administered the exact same dose by the same route, but under different settings, either the
actual physical setting they're in or the emotional state they're in, how much can that impact the
response? I think anytime you're dealing with something that plays around with neurochemistry,
set and setting is always a huge important thing. Same thing with alcohol. I think there's one part
of this is while we're talking about the safety or potential adverse events from this that we
should also address. In my experience, this has the lowest toxicity potential of any pharmaceutical
nearly of almost any product I've ever seen. That is in the course of history, we really do not have
any deaths or truly serious events that are attributed to THC or CBD at all. It is so less
toxic than what are common over the counter drugs, aspirin, Tylenol, etc. and certainly far and away
compared to alcohol, which is truly toxic. What is the reported LD50 of THC?
So there really isn't and you cannot dose. Maybe explain to people what LD50 is.
Okay. So LD50 is the lethal dose that it takes in order to kill off 50% of a population,
usually in mice or rats. With THC and CBD and all of these cannabinoids, it has never been possible
to dose them with enough to be able to do it. So that there is just a simple cut off generally
that it's something more than five grams per kilogram. So that's a tremendous,
absolutely tremendous amount of cannabis to be able to take on. In the 70s, an attorney for the
DEA actually was writing in support of de-scheduling cannabis said that the lethal dose 50 would take
a 75 kilogram man to smoke 1500 pounds of cannabis flower in 15 minutes in order to die and he
wouldn't die from a cardi respiratory effect from cannabis. It would be from probably carbon monoxide poisoning.
Did Willie Nelson try this? I think so. Okay. But he wasn't able to do it.
He's still alive, right? So it's interesting what Steve was saying is that the receptors,
those docking stations, there are no CB1 receptors or very few in the cardi respiratory centers of our
brain, different than the opioid receptors, the mu receptors, where you overdose because that docking
station gets activated by heroin or Percocet or OxyContin and you slow down your respirations and
you stop breathing and your heart slows down and your heart starts beating and you die.
That doesn't happen with cannabinoids because those receptors don't exist in those areas of
the brain where that would happen. And so literally to this day, you can over-consume
cannabis and you may feel like you want to die with this incredible anxiety or psychotic event,
but you're not going to. So it's sort of like LSD in that sense where it really
doesn't have a known upper limit of toxicity from a pure cardiorespiratory standpoint.
By comparison, Steve, you worked in the medical examiner's office for so many years.
What's the LD50 of ethanol? That's a great question and I can't remember the answer right off hand.
However, I do remember that the level at which people are intoxicated by this, and generally
we all know to be one or two shots of alcohol or wine or beer, and that it very quickly becomes a
disorienting drug with just a second one. Particularly the problem is that people don't
think they're disoriented by it and that they are actually under control. It's a very different
situation with cannabis. Usually as people take on these substances within their body,
they actually know that they're stoned and have a sense of it and are able to be able to
rectify their own behavior. Usually it's called just sit on the couch and watch TV or something
like that. Yeah, there's another point here I think on the toxicity that probably is worth
mentioning and you could probably speak to this with more accuracy, but it's sort of how I explain
toxicity to people. It's not just what the LD50 is, it's how far the LD50 is from the Eustose.
Consider acetaminophen. You'll very easily go and take a thousand milligrams of acetaminophen.
I don't know what the LD50 is, it's probably between 10 and 20 grams. That's not that far
away. That you could only miss the dose by 10x and kill someone is amazing. I'll tell you a
ridiculous story. I don't know why I'm getting it, but it's just an illustrator at this point.
I remember in residency once during our internship, a guy accidentally wrote a prescription for one
gram of adavan instead of one milligram of adavan. He wrote for a thousand times more of the dose,
which is a clerical error that came from his just being careless. Unfortunately, the nurse working
that day was very new and she took the order as one gram of adavan. To make matters worse,
the pharmacist on call that day was also new and realized in the pixus system, we only have 20
milligrams here. That's 21 thousandths of what you've ordered. I'll send it up right now and go
and get the remaining 980 milligrams. That patient was actually administered 20 milligrams of adavan
and of course had a respiratory arrest. That's toxicity. That's a lawsuit.
That's a therapeutic index. They say for over the counter drugs, it's like one to 20. You take
two aspirin and your headache goes away 40 and you're going to be in the hospital for something
like Valium or adavan. It's usually a one to 10. Look at alcohol. That's really my point I wanted
to make. Look at the therapeutics index of alcohol. Three drinks shouldn't kill anybody.
30 would kill anybody. Right, exactly. They say that for the therapeutic index for cannabis,
so one to 20 is over the counter, one to 10 is like adavan or Valium. It's one to 20,000 to one
to 40,000 is a therapeutic index. The greater that second number, the bigger the safety profile.
We call it a therapeutic window. I call that a therapeutic garage door.
Right. There are certain drugs that are simply just narrow therapeutic index drugs and need to
be very, very cautiously prescribed. I should point out for anyone who's listening that there
really isn't a therapeutic reason to dose alcohol as far as I know, unless you're rubbing it on an
insect bite or something like that. Alcohol is not really recommended for curing any particular
disease. I want to just kind of go back to something that I forgot to ask you earlier
because I got distracted in my thinking about the next thing I was interested in.
Why do you think during the Prohibition era alcohol was brought back into favor and marijuana
was not? Because I think it would be very difficult to make the case that alcohol is less toxic
than many things. I mean, alcohol is about as toxic as it comes, and yet it is completely
accepted societally. Why do you think it was... I mean, this is again just speculating on...
My sense of it was it's the sociology at the time. We live in very difficult times, and certainly
they were very difficult at those times. And it seemed that people really need to have a release
from the tensions of the day. The idea of creating the prohibition of alcohol was pretty quickly
recognized as not successful. That is, it simply drove it underground. People continued to imbibe it.
What happened was there was no control. There was no tax stamps. There was no health inspections that
went along with it. And the people who were utilizing it were demonized even more than
they were before. So it was sort of a contraindication for the society, although it certainly
came out of people in their heart thinking they could make their fellow man better by not having
them be allowed to drink. Then cannabis was not brought back. I think at the time it was societally,
it was a bridge too far for people to be able to reach. And it was apparently not a plant or an
intoxicant that was used by, frankly, the people who were in control of writing the rules and the
laws. But the legislators felt pretty comfortable drinking, and they didn't think they knew anyone
who smoked marijuana. A lot of people talk about the idea that marijuana is a gateway drug.
What is the state of the evidence of that argument? In other words, what are the pros and cons of that
argument to the best of our understanding? So it's an interesting question. I always say that
cannabis is a gateway more towards health than to other drugs. And in fact, NIDA, the National
Institute of Drug Abuse, on their website has agreed with that statement and no longer considers
cannabis as a gateway drug. But I think what people are looking at or concerned about is
young people participating in the intoxicating effects of cannabis or alcohol or high fat and
sugar foods, just like anything else, can be leading to other addictive behaviors. But there
really isn't anything that proves that cannabis is a gateway drug. We sort of have natural
experiments that have gone on with the legalization in the states that were at the forefront of this.
Are there data that we could take from, I guess, Colorado would be first, Washington State would
be second. Are there data we can take from those states that could point to either a rise or fall
in the utilization of drugs beyond marijuana that have either gone up or down since the legalization?
It depends on how you're spinning this question. If you're saying to this question that as a gateway
drug, Colorado has shown proof positive that there is not an enhanced utilization, at least of cannabis
from the black market in young people who shouldn't be taking it unless it was for
medicinal purposes only. If you're referring to the opioid epidemic, for sure, you know,
Bachhuber has looked at states with medical legal programs with patients that have access to
dispensaries. There has been a statistically significant reduction in opioid prescriptions
in patients for those for people who have access. Do you think there's an association? I mean,
again, I don't know this literature, so I'm not asking a loaded question. I'm, but I sort of know
these arguments, right, which is nobody takes heroin without first taking marijuana is the
argument. Therefore, heroin, the precursor to utilization of that is taking marijuana,
which of course is a silly argument, even if it were true. I don't know that that's entirely true,
but it's a silly argument because you don't know what the denominator is on the other side of that
equation. How many people would take marijuana and not go on to use cocaine or opiates or other things
like that? So A is correlated with B does not mean A causes B and A precedes B does not mean A causes
B either. Is there any argument though that one would make from a cautionary perspective about
certain individuals who are predisposed to addiction, who, if in the presence of marijuana,
are more likely to take on harmful addictions? I'm not sure that either Deb or I are that well
qualified in figuring out who could potentially have addictive behavior, nor have I really seen
any studies that are able to talk to this. My sense of it though is having grown up here in
America for quite some time with children myself and even growing up here in lovely New York City,
is that as people move through their teenage years, they experiment with lots and lots of things,
lots of behaviors that are important, interesting, and sometimes risky behaviors.
Marijuana is generally more available than any of these other perhaps hardcore drugs,
so it may appear that people are starting with marijuana, but frankly you can get cigarettes
on every street corner, so therefore I think we should blame cigarettes more for beginning this
inappropriate behavior that is sometimes addictive. I don't think that marijuana itself,
cannabis in any way, causes or leads people on into, let's call it more hardcore drug addiction,
and I just have not seen data to be able to prove it or disprove it one way or the other.
How addictive is THC? Like using formal definitions of rats pressing levers and things like that,
compared to things where the addictive potential seems to be very high, cocaine, opiates seem to
have a very high addictive potential, LSD seems to be the exact opposite, right? They'll never
push that lever again. Where does THC fit on that spectrum? On the low end of the spectrum,
for sure. It's below alcohol, I believe. It's below alcohol. Tobacco is probably one of the higher
percentages than heroin, believe it or not, below tobacco, and I think they say the studies are 9%.
Remember, these are recreational markets or using animals at high doses, lever pressing,
so it doesn't really reflect real world behaviors. To take that a little bit further,
there are medical centers right now that are running clinical trials utilizing CBD and sometimes
CBD with THC as dosage forms to move people off of other addicted substances.
That's to move people off of methadone, to move people off of heroin, so it may very well be that
THC and CBD are truly an exit drug, not an entry drug. What do we know about the effect of THC on
a developing brain versus a more developed brain? The three of us sitting here presumably have done
most of our brain development, but the 15-year-old is still probably in the throes of developing.
What do we know about differences under those circumstances?
What I say to patients and other physicians is that I don't think we're advocating using any kind
of chemical substance on a developing brain unless they need it.
But do we have actual data? I did try to look into this about a year ago, maybe two years ago,
at the request of a patient. What I found difficult at the time, and I'm hoping maybe you have better
data, is that we just didn't have great studies because everything was confounded by recreational
use without control. Even though at first principles, it seems illogical that a 15-year-old
is going to benefit from using marijuana, it wasn't really clear from the data what the case was.
Two years later with legalization in some states or decriminalization, can we say any more than that?
Not really. Unfortunately, there haven't been the robust double-blind randomized trials in people,
but when you talk about the 15-year-old and should cannabis be used, again, people think of cannabis
as inhalation. Let's take that off the table for a second. Let's think about it as a medicine.
This 15-year-old has a seizure disorder and there are constituents in this plant that can help with
that. That makes sense to use. If this 15-year-old has attention deficit or anxiety or depression
and other medicines are not working or maybe the risks of those other medicines are a lot greater,
I think these are reasonable tools in our medical toolbox that can be used.
People think about just THC as a very high intoxicating chemical. It doesn't have to be.
You have to have the receptor, you have to have the drug that sits on that receptor,
and you have to have enough of that drug to sit on those receptors to get that intoxicating effect.
Let's go back to something we talked about a little while ago, which is the different modes
or routes of administration. We talked about the spicoli route. I guess the advantage of that
route is it's relatively quickly. The active ingredients become engaged with the receptors,
both peripherally and within the CNS in a very short period of time. I'm guessing one of the
drawbacks of that route of administration is dose-to-dose consistency and presumably you're
inhaling other things that might not be too good for your lungs. Is there data on that?
You're correct. Your bioavailability in an inhalational method is fast and furious. You miss
the whole GI tract, which is great. If you're somebody with MS and has muscle spasm that's
acute, inhalation method could be a godsend for them, for sure. You're right that the length or
duration of action is a lot shorter than other methods of administration. If you're somebody with
a chronic pain issue, that's probably not your method of administration that you want to employ.
Yes, you get products of combustion. If you're smoking plant material, you have a whole bunch
of other things, no differently than tobacco, that can cause some issues. There have been no
studies. In fact, Dr. Tashkin has shown that there has not been an association between
lung cancer and smoking cannabis flowers. Yeah. Why do you think that is, by the way?
I'm sort of surprised by that. Me too.
Do you think it's a dose effect or?
Or maybe it's the anti-inflammatory effects of the cannabinoids themselves that sort of are
kind of pre-treating it. I don't know. I'm not smart enough to know that. That was one study.
Maybe we need to look at other studies. I can't answer that. What I can say though is we do know
that heat does cause cellular change. So for that reason, I'm always concerned about it. And for my
patients that I treat, I don't recommend inhalational method at all.
Any inhalational method.
Only because I don't understand how to help them titrate because inhalation is different. A small
inhalation gives you one dose. A deeper inhalation gives you a different dose. Your inhalation is
different than somebody else's. Thinking about this as an anesthesiologist from a clinical
perspective, outside of anesthesia where we're totally controlled, we don't like to give drugs
or we don't know the dose. I think patients who are really sick want their hands held in a way
that they can wrap their head around it as much as I can. So if I say use X, Y, and Z and they
come back to me and say it works, then we understand what they should take. If I say take X, Y, and Z
and maybe it doesn't work or it only does part way, then we have an understanding as to how to go,
how to pivot from that point. Inhalation doesn't allow me to do that.
Is there anything else, Steve, from a chemical perspective? So when I think of inhalation,
I guess I think of two vehicles. I think of the sort of bong joint method where the temperature
is literally from the flame burning the material, combusting it, that then gets inhaled. And then
you think of sort of the vaping method where, well, tell us how vaping works actually.
Vaping works at a lower temperature than the pyrolysis that goes on when you use a bong and
some people even take it a little bit further and heat up a substance using an acetylene torch
on a nail and then inhaling it. That's really hot. The vaping goes on at a much lower temperature
and there are other dosage forms that are going to come out soon that are simply inhalers like
Bronco inhalers where there won't be any temperature gradient at all and the product will be brought
into the lungs through an inert carrier gas. So that will allow a much more controlled dose.
Those just aren't really on the market very effectively yet.
There's been a lot of talk about vaping lately and this is both from the lens of the use of THC
and nicotine itself totally separately. What do you guys know about this as it pertains to safety?
Let's start with that. That's an interesting question. I don't think anyone really can put
a finger on a specific reason for this problem that these vape partures are causing.
Tell people what the problems are that we're seeing. So it looks like an acute respiratory
distress syndrome. So almost looks like a chemical burn to a lung where people have a respiratory
failure that requires a huge amount of support in the intensive care unit including intubation
and ventilation and other support measures. So it's pretty severe and pretty significant.
When you extract cannabis, it comes out as a thick goopy oil and you need to refine that oil
in order to put it into cartridges. And those methods of getting the right viscosity for that
oil to be put in that cartridge is done in a whole host of different ways. And I don't think it was
done intentionally to hurt people. I think people thought, oh, let's thin this oil out using PG or
PEG because it's a grass ingredient generally guarded is safe. But it's generally regarded
as safe if you eat it and no one really understood what happens when you combust it. For those two
things, I think it's formaldehyde gets created when you combust or heat up PG or PEG. Other
people are using, we're using vitamin E acetate. Again, generally regarded is safe if you ingest
it, not if you heat it up to a vapor or steam. Does the FDA not require a reanalysis? So if the
FDA says substance A has a grass designation and substance A has historically been consumed at room
temperature and subject to a first pass effect in the liver, can anybody come along and say, I'm
going to burn said substance and it still maintains its grass designation? How does the FDA think about
that? The FDA allows something to be grass generally recognized as safe for particular uses,
either as direct food ingredients, indirect food ingredients, part of packaging. But once the
product is out there in the marketplace and available to use, it's America. People will do
whatever they wish with it. And that brings us to part of the issue here is that this is,
while this is a regulated environment within the states, there are many actors, many producers who
are not yet regulated. It's kind of like alcohol was legalized. And then there was still bathtub
gin being made for many, many years. There were hundreds, thousands of deaths from it on this
vaping issue. In particular, I had some experiences at the New York medical examiners some years ago
on a syndrome that came to be called SIDS, Sudden Infant Death Syndrome, where we had to look
at the lungs of a number of infants that had died in this way. And so something similar is happening
here. We're in the midst of a quiet, slow moving epidemic where there are now thousands of people
in hospital. I think we have over 34 deaths directly attributed to it. And week by week,
the toll continues to mount. It's just not been brought out all that widely. It does look like
these are chemical burns within the lungs, but then the lungs seem to be not regenerating
themselves, but the wounds are getting worse. So does it behave like ARDS?
That's what it sounds like. It's a lot of cellular recruitment and then oxygenation
doesn't occur, but they're not a hundred percent sure.
Are they getting edema as well?
There's so far been a good deal of a lid kept on a lot of the discussion as both CDC as well as
other health organizations are trying to find epidemiologic locuses where events have occurred.
In a couple of cases, they've been able to identify that there were individuals who made
some vape cartridges where there is a higher proportion of people who have been hurt
from other vape cartridges, but there is just no clear cut etiology so far.
So if I'm understanding you correctly, we have no idea if the uptick in these acute toxicities
is potentially manufacturing related, loci related, diffuse. We don't know any of those things yet.
That's exactly correct. From having worked in this industry for a long time, I'm very familiar with
every time a new product, even if it's something as innocuous as a lipstick is changed, there is a
slight uptick in adverse events, even from just changing the coloration in a lipstick or an eye
shadow because there are millions of uses of it. You're able to see what happens in products like
that that are where people are using them external to their body is it's a slight irritation.
And the person simply decides, I won't use that eye shadow anymore or that lipstick anymore.
And they self-select out of the population. Here, this is a sudden onset of a serious nature,
but even with all of these numbers of, well, a terrible amount, more than 30 deaths and
hundreds, thousands in hospital, this is against millions and millions of uses. And it just doesn't
seem to be a clear cut cause that we're able to find so far. You said something a moment ago,
and I want to make sure I understand it because it seems staggering to me. The FDA, if you go down
to the grocery store, the corner store, and you buy a bag of, I don't know, jelly beans, and they
come in a plastic container, does the FDA have oversight into the plastic that holds the jelly
beans? Yes, yeah, they do. And the FDA says this plastic is grass. Yes, that the individual
chemicals that went into making that, they don't look at the overall plastic bag, but rather the
individual polymers or monomers or the colorants have all gone through extensive testing. Now,
let's say I'm an idiot and I decide to create a new product, which is I'm going to take the plastic,
I'm going to take those constitutive elements in that plastic bag that holds the jelly beans,
and I'm going to combust it for inhalational use. So, new use of previously agreed upon grass
constituents. Does the FDA say, Peter, you can't do that? Or does the FDA say, well, gee whiz,
each of those things were safe to be touching jelly beans, therefore you can be burning them?
The FDA actually would be very annoyed at you. What's the legal recourse? Oh, the legal
recourse was if you had turned that into a business, is they would come and shut you down.
Okay, so the FDA still has their pants on and they would still be looking out to protect people from
me doing that. Yes, absolutely. But not in the cannabis world. Why? Because it's federally
illegal and the FDA is not a participant. So, you're saying that the fact that cannabis is still
illegal federally means this entire discussion is moot and it would be at the state's discretion
to police this type of use switching? Exactly. That's exactly correct. And that is part of the
difficulty right now is that state agencies are not used to having the scientific horsepower
or the manpower or woman power is much better to be able to figure out what of these ingredients
can or cannot be added to it. And on top of that, the producers of the products are not required to
test them for safety or efficacy before they start shipping the products, which is very different
than products sold under FDA auspices where you have to demonstrate at least safety for foods,
products, and for drugs. You also have to prove efficacy before you can make it and ship it.
Prior to the explosion of these acute events of toxicity, I was much more
personally curious about chronic toxicity. Let's take tobacco as an example. Very few people have
acute toxicity to tobacco use, but by the middle of the 1960s, it was abundantly clear what the
chronic toxicity was from tobacco use. Alcohol is an interesting one. Alcohol has lots of acute
toxicity. You could kill yourself in a moment with alcohol. That's a very easy thing to do.
But I don't know if your friend who died of cirrhosis had complications of alcohol use or
whether it was hepatitis, but certainly the chronic toxicity of alcohol in this country
is the longest, fattest, widest tail we see along with tobacco, perhaps. Maybe fatter, actually.
What do we think is the chronic toxicity or do we believe that there's any evidence of or against
chronic toxicity from vaping? Things that we just haven't, it hasn't been around long enough and we
don't know, but you're sort of playing with fire, that logic. I mean, that's a feeling because it
really hasn't been available as widespread as it is now. Remember, 2014, 2013 was when really other
states started really coming on board. I mean, California was the first in 2009. There was
nobody vaping then. People were using cannabis as a flour to smoke. People were using it in food
stuffs to eat, but nobody was using this vaping thing. I don't think it was until the popularity
of the vaping through the e-cigarette market when the cannabis market turned and went,
hmm, this is an interesting business, an interesting mode of administration,
no products of combustion. People feel a lot better about it and I think people honestly and
truly thought it was a better mousetrap. Do you know what the people who favor that approach will
argue in their defense? There's a couple of arguments. One is it's better than smoking
and getting products of combustion. Two, it's helping me get off nicotine, so I'm vaping instead.
So that's better. And three, people who have an acute pain issue or a muscle spasm feel like the
instantaneous nature of the effects of this is what they require. I think that manufacturers
of cannabinoid medicine are looking to do things with the cannabinoids. I know we are and I don't
want to push our product, but we are looking at changing the solubility from a fat soluble to the
water soluble method of administration makes the bioavailability a heck of a lot faster. It's just
not available across the country because we have a state license in Michigan and we can't sell it
across state lines. Yeah, I want to come back to talk a lot about your product because when you
said that a moment ago that I couldn't understand how you were talking about water solubility of
this. So let's between the three of us remember to park that and come back to that because I could
use the chemistry lesson. Going back to the toxicity point, we talked briefly about edibles
earlier. We sort of indirectly did. You said that if Spicoli ate that flower, he might have got a
belly upset, but he wouldn't have got high. Why is it that when people consume edibles, they get high?
Because it's a different constituent. They're not using the raw plant. They're heating those
chemicals. So when people are making brownies, yes, the batter's yummy, but they generally bake it at a
certain temperature for a certain amount of time. And there are actual curves that show when THC in
its acid form, in its raw form, gets converted to or some people call it activated form into THC.
So it takes time and it takes temperature before you make that conversion. And at that point when
you eat it, that's when those chemicals can sit on the receptors that make you feel high or
intoxicated. So again, it's very unlikely you'll make two batches of brownies identically because
time, the area under the curve is almost always going to be different. So everybody gets a different
brownie. Now, when you get the candies or things like that, is it the extraction of the THC required
heating to get the active ingredient into these commercial edible products? So it depends on what
you're making. I mean, there are medicinal chocolates and candies and stuff, but there are medicinal
properties in the raw form as well as the heated form. So if you're making it for the direct
purpose of intoxication, you're going to heat it, the starting material first, the active ingredient
first, the THC, and then you're going to put it into your chocolate. So this might be a bad analogy,
but you know how anytime you make coffee, you're basically running hot water across a bean,
but if you're a real coffee snob, you'll do a cold brew so that you can extract the flavor
without the temperature and you avoid the bitterness. It seems to me that whether you're
talking about smoking a joint, lighting a bong, vaping, or eating a candy or chocolate or a
brownie, heat always seems to be required if you're going to get this active ingredient out.
Is that the case? If you're trying to get THC- For intoxication. Right, for intoxication. So the
answer is yes. You have to apply time and temperature in order to make THC, and then
you put that THC as your starter ingredient into whatever it is. And the variables for the edibles
is not just the preparation of the food, but that our digestive process varies hour to hour,
person to person, as well as our body mass and how we feel about things and what the time of
day is and the circadian rhythm. So it's almost impossible to expect out of eating any food that
contains THC or CBD to expect that you will get a reliable, repeatable dosage experience from that,
even if the label is completely correct and completely accurate. And that's a big if.
It's huge. Yes, it is. The legitimate laboratories in cannabis have gotten better and better and
better all the time, but still when you make a batch of a thousand brownies and you just sample
one or two of them, there's an awfully good chance that the batter may not have been mixed
appropriately. Pharmaceuticals solve that because of the consistency by which we make things in a
pharmaceutical way, but foods are not quite that precise. And you can buy a brownie at a store one
day and then buy a homemade brownie the next day and it can taste very different. How many strains
are there of cannabis that are commonly used? From what I've heard, there's over 800, but people
are crossing and backcrossing all the time. But back to the edibles thing that I think is even
more important is that when you eat something and it goes through your stomach and it goes to the
liver and gets cleared, it gets chemically converted. And so therefore you're really not
even ingesting THC anymore. You're ingesting its metabolite and that metabolite is even more
intoxicating than THC itself. So there are people who are experienced in inhalational methods of THC
that do it all the time that say they can't even eat a THC brownie or a gummy bear or drinking a
soda with it in because it's far more intoxicating. Do you think there are any, a Priet might be the
wrong word, but just call it, what are the best use cases for edibles? I think the best case use
edibles are for somebody with a chronic pain. So let's take example, somebody with a chronic pain
that can't sleep at night. Let's take an extreme case, somebody with cancer that's spread to their
bones. Right. And they literally can't sleep. So what I would do with a patient is I would trial
them on a certain edible or something that I believe is consistent. It wouldn't be held within
a food stuff. It would most likely be in a capsule or a tablet because it makes sense. Again, remember
we talked about wanting to understand the dose and wanting to understand what it is. We would dose
it in a way that it would be the same time every night for this patient. And we would see how they
would sleep. The bioavailability takes about 60 to 90 minutes in the best case scenario. You only
get about 8% of whatever it is that you're taking, but it can last up to eight to 10 hours. We haven't
talked about tachyflaxis or tolerance. How does the body respond to repeated administration of THC?
That's really interesting. THC sits on these docking stations known as receptors, and there
are chances of over-consuming THC and down-rate regulating these receptors that actually can be
reset very quickly by just stopping for a couple of days. But there's an interesting study out of
the Netherlands since they've had a medical program for a very long time, I think since 2012 or
something or 10, where they looked at patients, the average patient only takes 750 milligrams of
cannabis a day. And you would imagine if there was so much tachyflaxis, you would have seen an
increase or a rise in that, and you didn't. It seemed like they stabilized at 750 milligrams,
and that was it, which is contrary to what I just said. So explain the opposite. Talk about
opiates. You've obviously, as an anesthesiologist, had lots of experience with them. What typically
happens to a patient who has prescribed opiates for pain? That's the problem with opiates. Opiates sit
on their own docking station, and they do down-regulate very quickly, which means that you require more
and more for the same effect, and then it does something really strange. It flips. And after a
certain amount of opiates, your pain gets enhanced, not decreased. And it's called hyperalgesia. It's
a strange phenomenon. And you said 20% to 30% of people experience that? Actually, 20% to 30% of
people experience that from the beginning, where they experience an opposite reaction to pain
relief. But I'm saying people who traditionally get pain relief, who require more and more and
more for the same amount of pain relief, suddenly they are experiencing a hyperalgesia, an increase
in pain. Whereas before, a month ago, two months ago, they were actually getting pain relief.
Nobody talks about that. So we don't think that this is necessarily happening
with THC and the CB1 or CB2 receptor. No, we're not saying that yet, as of now.
Let's talk a little bit about how THC mixes with other drugs. What happens when THC is combined
with alcohol, for example? Alcohol is a known depressant of the central nervous system.
I still don't really understand what THC is doing in the CNS. I'm still confused by
the intoxicating versus non-intoxicating effects. I know that I can tell what you're thinking,
which is, Peter, that's the point. It's a plant, it's complex, it's doing many things.
But it's multimodal, actually. So a little bit of THC won't cause any intoxication. You need the
receptor, you need the drug, and you need enough drugs sitting on all those receptors in order to
express those things. And I joke with Steve and say, I like to be called the queen,
basically, but the queen of microdose, which means I like to use very small amounts of
cannabinoids to activate things on a cellular level. So you actually don't feel the intoxicating
effects because most patients don't want to be sidelined by their pain, and they don't want to
be sidelined by their pain medicine. So that's kind of off topic.
Is that the majority of your personal focus? I mean, I want to come back to, obviously,
what your company, Pure, does. That makes sense there. But what about people who actually want
some of the intoxicating effects because, well, let me unpack that a little bit more. I was about
to say because of things like anxiety or stress, but you could make the argument that if one has
their anxiety and stress reduced without intoxication, that might be just as beneficial.
Have you thought much about the particular demand, the consumer demand? What is it that people
actually want from THC? My sense of it is that they would actually like relief. That is,
over and over again, I did an extensive survey of, in Michigan, we have over 400,000 people with
medical marijuana cards, and of people who were going into cannabis dispensaries, two-thirds of
them were really there for medical reasons, not to get stoned. They had learned over the course of
their lives that they could reduce their pain, often chronic pain from very serious accidents
or operations. They could reduce their anxiety, and they had learned that they could find strains
of marijuana, and they were using them and smoking them because it was all that they had available
to them. So these are people generally who were just looking to live happy, normal lives like
all the rest of us, and that they have found that this is a relatively inexpensive and pretty
harmless way to manage what are otherwise very, very severe symptoms. So that if, going back to
your question about utilizing alcohol at the same time, there are some people who utilize alcohol
regularly in order to, frankly, numb the pain, even without listening to any Frank Sinatra songs
about the heartache and why we're all still in a bar at three o'clock in the morning.
It's for pain relief, for it's psychological and sometimes straightforward physical pain relief.
Once people discover that they can achieve that by using a small, relatively easy titration form,
people who utilize cannabis smoking or vaping are readily able to titrate themselves, which is
just remarkable to be able to do that. Certainly, I did when I was smoking cigarettes. I could
learn how to accelerate my heart rate or relax by just puffing in a different way.
I gave up that addiction myself. Interesting. I don't think I appreciated that you could have
that distinction from, presumably from the nicotine, depending on the speed.
By the speed at which you take on that nicotine, I could either excite myself to be able to get up
for something or you could use it to calm down and relax by just simply dosing in a different manner.
Do you think there are certain medical conditions that are contraindicated from the use of THC?
For example, I'm making this up. I have no idea. Someone with schizophrenia or someone with severe
psychiatric illness, can it be exacerbated by THC? The shorter answer is yes, but that doesn't mean
that they should not be availed to cannabinoids because again, there's over a hundred different
cannabinoids specific to the cannabis plant that could be and has shown to be incredibly useful.
Yes, high dose THC alone could stimulate somebody who has schizophrenia to have an exacerbation of
those things, but CBD and maybe even a low level of THC along with it could actually be hugely
beneficial. Back to your question about THC and other drugs, THC plus opiates has shown that a
reduction in opiates with a greater pain relieving efficacy without that tacky full access or
tolerance that we know to be true for opioid use. How much time do you still spend in a hospital
setting or an inpatient setting? Do you have any, you spend any time there? Zero anymore. Do you
have any sense of how long it will be before THC and or CBD make their way into the, for example,
post-op surgical patient world? Dronabinol, which is a synthetic THC, has been on the market since
the 1980s and we as doctors are allowed to write prescriptions for it across the country and patients
can travel with it. That's available now and it's being used for chemotherapy induced nausea and
vomiting in some settings, not very well because straight up THC is really uncomfortable. It does
increase your heart rate, does make your mouth dry, does make you feel agitated and uncomfortable.
I mean, the rest of the constituents within the plant sort of modulate all of that. I'm glad you
brought this up because I was going to ask you about the synthetics. The synthetics have a pretty
bad rap. There's sort of the teleologic argument of nature always packs the right amount of this
antidote versus that antidote. I mean, what is your take on synthetics through that lens in particular?
That's a complicated answer. I mean, I think what I'm really wanting to focus more about is a single
molecule as opposed to looking at many of the molecules within the cannabis plant and try to
find utilization. So a single molecule like CBD from Epidiolex from GW Pharma came from a plant,
but it is isolated and purified to 99.99% and it requires a tremendous amount to get the effect
that GW Pharma wanted to get on to types of seizures. We formulate using isolated cannabinoids,
but we join them together along with other constituents so that we use less and we capitalize
on the synergistic effects of a lot of the molecules. No differently than what we do in
medicine as an anesthesiologist, we just don't push one medication. We push a lot of different
medications to lower the bad effects of one particular medicine and capitalize on the good
effects of all of them. Say more about the GW CBD for epilepsy. What is the purity of it? You said
it's 99. It's pretty high. It's greater than 90%. Tell me about the success and utilization of that.
So it's plant-derived, but it's isolated, so it's purified and they have it for two particular
types of seizures. Those kids with these rare seizure forms that are refractory to multiple
other traditional pharmaceuticals, I think they have like a 30% reduction in their seizures,
but there's side effects. I mean, there's GI effects, there's liver issues. I mean,
there's side effects in high, high doses of epidiolex. What do you think is the potential
for CBD and sleep? Something that gets talked about a lot. What is your take on the efficacy
of CBD oils? Let's start with the oils, which are very commercially abundant. Well, let me first
mention my bias. I took it this morning at one o'clock in the morning because as usual, I'm up
for an hour trying to do something and it's a little noisy in this city and I need you to go
back to sleep. So it is in our hands and in our experience, it works. It simply works. That is,
people are able to take CBD. We think that taking it as an oil is less effective than taking it in
a water-soluble form, but it is certainly effective. We have pharmacovigilance data on
several hundred thousand people that demonstrates that they generally go to sleep pretty quickly,
have a great night's sleep, and wake up refreshed with no feeling of what other sleep aids give,
of grogginess or anything like that. Most people think it is just fabulous.
Do you have any insight into what the mechanism of action is?
So remember, multimodal mechanisms of action. So anti-inflammatory, it also activates the GABA
receptor, decreases anxiety, and a lot of people have that three-year-old running around in their
head at night and prevents them from going to sleep. So we think it is central activation of
GABA that would be one of the more potent mediated. There is a molecule out there called
phenibut, which is an oral form of GABA that crosses the blood-brain barrier. Now, the FDA
has not designated it grass, so therefore it is no longer available easily. But for something that
was for so long over the counter, it was kind of a remarkable sleep aid. So one should not underestimate
the potency of CNS GABA activation. Is there any sort of polysom data that talks about staging of
sleep with CBD? In other words, it is one thing to say, great, a person can sleep for this many hours,
uninterrupted, but do we have any sense of the impact of CBD on sleep architecture?
I have not seen any data like that, and your questions are remarkably and remarkably
perceptive. You have to realize that at this current time, because of the still illegality of THC
and the confused legality about all of the others, that pretty much every university, especially
medical universities, do not allow research to be done on the facility unless someone has a DEA
license. And even then, getting the DEA license is a long drawn out process, so that very little
work is able to be done. And there are thousands of medical researchers who would love to work on
these problems, but they can't, just like they haven't been able to for 50 years. But is CBD
not permitted for research if the THC level is low enough? That's only come about in the last few
months. So it certainly takes a lot longer for research protocols to be developed, to move through
NIH, to move through whatever funding opportunity there is. And I expect that in the next year or
two or three, that there'll be much more research done on that. It's still a highly restricted,
highly restrained, and frankly, the university administration in almost all of these schools
and universities are very, very worried about jeopardizing their federal funding for billions
of dollars of other projects. In other words, it's not that there's a dearth of funding. If
a philanthropist came along and said to somebody at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, hey,
here's $5 million. I want you to study the effect of CBD on sleep duration and architecture.
The university would say, well, thank you for that, but I don't want to jeopardize the billion
dollars of NIH funding I have. Am I understanding you correctly?
Yeah, well, I wouldn't pick on U of M because my wife works in pathology there. But it's a great
school, terrific school, football's coming back, folks, that any university in these stages will
move much more carefully to consider what the research is and who is the researcher,
simply because of 50, 60 years of illegality. It's just so surprising to see how far behind
THC and CBD are when you have a beautiful roadmap from organizations that have been funding so much
psychedelic research. I mean, when you look at MAPS, the Multidisciplinary Association for Psychedelic
Studies started by Rick Doblin. I mean, he started this organization in 1986. 33 years later,
they are now in phase three studies using MDMA, which is, as you know, obviously, schedule one.
I'm kind of amazed. Is there not a comparable group that is advocating for the judicious study
of THC and CBD? We are. We run clinical trials regularly. Dr. Kimless here is running clinical
trials right now, and there are others, but they're from, let's call it private sources.
Is that the business model of your company? Is that you have a product that you sell and the
proceeds of that help fund the research? Yeah, that's pretty much it. We came up with
formulations that we felt would work, and then we ran pilot clinical trials to see how they would do
in a small patient population. And once we saw that that was getting a very good response among
people, then we were able to distribute the products within the state because we were state licensed to
be able to do that. And now we are taking the funds from essentially from that cash flow and
scaling up to be able to do studies under FDA offices, auspices, which are frankly much more
expensive to do because of all the controls that go along with it. Talk to me now about this idea
that we alluded to twice already, which is the water solubilization of something that I didn't
assume could be water-solubilized. We have a number of patents on it, and a number of them
are moving through, so you'll have to forgive me for sort of speaking generically about that. We
have one issued patent out of the seven that we filed for, and that was to figure out, we figured
out how to freeze dry cannabis, and that's an industrial process, and it helps. So that's an
awarded patent, and anyone can look that one up. THC and CBD and all of the molecules that are in
cannabis that appear to be useful and viable are all oil soluble. They are not water-soluble.
So if you put them in a glass of water and stir it, you'll have little oil globules on it.
So we figured out how to be able to convert that instantly into a water-soluble molecule
so that when a person puts a drop of this or a powder of this on their tongue,
it doesn't taste oily, it doesn't feel oily, and it doesn't act like an oil. And as everyone knows,
yeah, you can have some oil and vinegar maybe on your salad, but the body doesn't really like to
have a lot of oil in it on a regular basis, whereas everybody can drink pints and pints of water,
gallons of water perhaps a day. So these molecules are rendered to be water-soluble,
and because they're put into very, very fast, rapid-dissolving tablets that disintegrate in
about 15 seconds or so. Do they disintegrate under the tongue and therefore escape the
first pass effect of the liver? That's exactly right. Under the tongue, on top of the tongue,
mushed around the tongue. But they're not to be swallowed. They're not to be swallowed.
They're called sublingual because it's under the tongue, but what happens is as the tablet
disintegrates literally in the mouth, the molecules move towards the tissues of the mouth, the tongue,
or throughout the oral cavity. What we see is in about a minute, the molecules have moved into
the bloodstream, and for those who are sensitive enough, they can actually feel their toes tingle
in two minutes, which teaches us that we have full systemic absorption, frankly, the molecules
have reached a person's toes. And then we find following that that people are able to experience
whatever effect, medical effect, that we are looking for in about eight to ten minutes.
So that's the onset of sleep for sleep formulations, the onset of pain relief for
pain relief for anxiety. So that has the advantage. It avoids first pass metabolism. It gets much more
of the active drug into the bloodstream and to be distributed throughout the body. So in theory,
you could actually lower the levels of drug that are necessary to do which. How potent is this?
Is this a millimolar or micromolar drug? I would say that this is closer to micromolar. That is
someone who's, we found very effectively that sleep works in someone who takes 10 milligrams
of CBD and one milligram of THC, and that's spread across a body that's maybe 70 kilograms,
80 kilograms of weight. This is really interesting to me, is that the optimal cocktail
for sleep may actually have some THC in it as opposed to just pure CBD. It's our experience
over and over again that this concept that's called the entourage effect when it's applied to
cannabis, but yet this is used throughout medicine as Deb mentioned as an anesthesiologist. She used
a cocktail of medicine. Certainly in oncology, it's very, very common to prescribe multiple
drugs at the same time or in some sequence. We found exactly the same effect and did it by
clinical trials of seeing how it would be with patients, getting feedback from them, revising
the formulations, redosing them, and seeing how those effects changed. Does your company have a
501c3 attached to it that allows people to fund research in the way that MAPS works?
No, it doesn't. So far, it's me. I drained my retirement account in order to do this.
As you said though, as you move towards the more and more rigorous FDA studies,
it's something you should consider. I think the public support for this type of research is
strong. I think the public's appetite for this is strong. If you think about it, you have a
harder problem, in my opinion, to solve than the psychedelic community does because at least there,
there's no ambiguity about the molecule. We know what psilocybin is. We know what LSD is. We know
what MDMA is. There is no purity concern. I mean, there is if you go to a club or a party or
something like that, but from the standpoint of doing clinical research, we know exactly what
we're talking about, whereas you're dealing with in many ways a more complicated set of molecules.
You have two issues, which is not just the straightforward safety, efficacy, effectiveness
chain of phase one, phase two, phase three. You have a problem that lies beneath the surface of
that, which is route of administration, cocktail, chemical composition, all of these other things.
I mean, I generally try not to give unsolicited advice, but my view is I don't know that you want
to go alone at this problem because I think the work you're doing is very important. I was at a
dinner the other day and somebody at the dinner table was talking about telling a story and you
hear these stories all the time. I think the person is totally well-intentioned, and I just
sort of sat there silently because I didn't really feel like debating it. The claim was a friend of
my friend's father was in hospice with stage four pancreatic cancer, had weeks to live,
and they put them, you know, the family snuck in CBD oil for him, and two weeks later he was home
and cured. And you know, the problem with those types of stories is not only that they're almost
assuredly incorrect, it's that they sort of damage the credibility of a body of research because
you start to have absurd claims that are thrown in with sort of legitimate claims. How do you
think about the sort of stigmatization of this and trying to manage the hype and the potential?
That's a really awfully good question. So I should point out while there's only two of us here in the
room, this is a research team with a great deal of depth and breadth. That is everyone I've worked
with in pharmaceuticals for the last 40 years have said, oh my goodness, please let me work with
you on this. And so we have that as well as a number of people who are fairly well to do,
who are looking at this as a business opportunity and an investment, which I really appreciate and
my wife is especially appreciative of so I can stop draining our own retirement account.
Many of these anecdotal experiences are true. I wouldn't have believed it myself, honestly,
except for the fact that we have now sold 600,000, 700,000 tablets to tens of thousands of patients
repetitively in Michigan and I watched, it sounds funny to say, the week in the lane get up out of
their wheelchair and move and say, I don't know how to tell you this, but what the heck is in your
tablet? And I just say, well, it's THC or it's CBD in a particular ratio with these terpenes.
And families would say, thank God, my husband is living, my mother is living, my child's anxiety
is greatly reduced. And I know to classically trained scientists and physicians that in this
society at this time, that seems damaging or inappropriate. But in other societies,
it is not that way. This is a sociologic event that is just beginning to spread. And I know among
many of my friends in police forces who are EMTs and firefighters, first line responders,
who frequently have a great deal of anxiety in their life and frequently a great deal of pain,
just straightforward physical pain aside from everything else, that their personal experience
with selected, extracted, purified cannabis has completely changed their thoughts about what they
have for generations thought was completely inappropriate behavior. Now they say, oh, jeez,
gets rid of my pain and I don't feel so bad. And they are still able to function perfectly well.
They're not stone at all, not in any way at all, partly because the drugs are relatively easy to
self titrate. I know I do a lot. No, no, no. I'm not suggesting that one can't see improvements in
those things. But I do sort of bristle against the notion that there are people with stage four cancer
that are being sold a bill of goods that says, take your metastatic pancreatic cancer and in
two weeks you're cured with this. I'm waiting to see the first documented case of that and I'll
continue to be an incredible skeptic of that sort of logic, which is not to say that a patient with
cancer wouldn't benefit immensely from relief of anxiety or pain, but yeah, I just, I very much
struggle to imagine cancer remissions. So THC and other cannabinoids have been shown
in the laboratory to have a multimodal effect on cancer. So in apoptosis, which is cell death,
in migration or metastasis, in neovascularization, it reduces it. So there are actual reasons and
rationale behind it. You're right. Is there a double-blind randomized trial of people? I think
a doctor would go to jail if you had somebody who could have XYZ traditional chemotherapy and,
okay, here's a cannabis concoction that we've come up with. I wouldn't have believed it myself. I can
show you pictures afterwards. We can't do it on a podcast. The story is an eight year old girl in
hospice. She was on methadone and morphine. Our goal was to just treat her to get her off it. So
she had a better quality of life before she died. And we transitioned her from hospice to second
grade to third grade. What was the underlying pathology? She had a chronic lymphocytic leukemia
and a leptin meningeal spread. She failed chemo radiation in a couple of bone marrow.
She sadly died this past summer. Again, this gets back to the broader point, which is I'd like to
see this studied more aggressively because my greatest fear is watching patient. I mean,
my greatest fear is safety. I think that's followed with predatory behavior. Oh, absolutely.
And I just, I can't tell you how frustrated I get when I hear stories about people who
are spending their last dollars on cockamamie schemes that have absolutely no bearing. I mean,
and, and, you know, look, there are lots of things that kill cancer in vitro that aren't going to work
in vivo. So we just have to be cautious about it. And yet I know I've definitely remember the
pathways of even autophagy and apoptosis and all these things where, where the cannabinoids play a
role. So again, I think this all just speaks to the idea of kind of loading the boat to, to more
effectively study this. And of course, I mean, the criticism is you have a conflict, right? The
criticism is how can you be fully objective? And again, this is something that the maps people can
get away from because, you know, MDMA has no IP associated with it, right? Merck developed this
drug in the twenties. Now there's an interesting business model, which is how would you incentivize
people to study something where there is no profit center at the end? My view is you should be able to
pursue this. I mean, I want to be clear. I'm not suggesting that you guys aren't sitting here with
the purest of intentions. It comes across very clearly. And I hope the listener can tell that I,
I can tell how pure your intentions are and that creating a company is just a vehicle through which
to pursue more research. But as I think about the broader objective, which is broader than just your
company, again, I'll come back to this idea of creating a research initiative around this that
even exceeds the reach of your company. Because remember the number of questions here is harder,
right? Like I'd like to hear from you guys, what question you're most interested in knowing the
answer to in five years. It would be great that the NIH could carry some of that burden, right?
It would be great that independent MROs, medical research organizations could carry some of that
burden because no one's retirement account should be depleted in an effort to hold a promise true to
a friend, which is a, in some ways a part of what started this for you, what the sort of this journey
for you. It is exactly. Tell me a couple of questions. Like what do you not know the answer
to today that you want to know the answer to with respect to THC, CBD and its associated products in
five years? What would make the world a better place? For me, I've made a vow that I will find
a formulation that will relieve PTSD. I made a vow to do that for people who were heroin addicts
and you know, methadone may not be the best of all formulations, but that's what I did when I was 23
years old and I got a little better as I went along. So that is the driving force for me to be
able to do this. And then my goal is to be able to discover as many of these disease conditions,
psychological or physical conditions, as we can extract value from these stunningly non-toxic
molecules. Steve, are there INDs affiliated and associated with these molecules? Like are you in
that phase one pipeline now? Yes, we are. We have three filed. We actually just met with FDA
three weeks or so ago over one of them and we are pursuing that very, very actively.
So each time you reconstitute something, it's a new IND. That's right. Okay. Explain to folks,
because you're the expert on this, explain to folks what an IND is and how important this is
in this regulatory pathway. In order to sell a drug in the United States, you have to have
an approved new drug application that's called NDA from the Food and Drug Administration. So
what do you do before you get that? You have to go investigate that drug. So that's what an IND
is. It's an investigational new drug exemption from all of the rules that say you have to have
this approved drug. So you go and meet with FDA. We provide them with the data and the documents
that we have available and say, dear FDA, we would like to run the following clinical trial
and here's all our evidence and do you folks agree with us? And in the course of hashing that out,
they will come back and say we'd like you to do a little more work in with an animal model or we'd
like you to do some additional studies in humans in a particular way. And so we are in the process
of doing that in three different therapeutic indications. What are those three besides PTSD?
One of them is an animal model that is for pet dogs who have pain from osteosarcoma and the other
osteoarthritis. Osteoarthritis of the knee and then PTSD. Right. So those are pain in dogs,
pain in people, particularly osteoarthritis pain as well as PTSD, which I think of as a combination
of anxiety and pain. It presents in a number of ways, mild, moderate, severe, et cetera.
Again, for the listener to make sure I understand the distinction, there are currently products you
are legally selling in Michigan that do not require an IND. They're currently grass products.
They're not basically pharma grade products. Is that safe to say or is that a-
No, these are pharma grade products simply because this is the space that I live in. I
have always thought that that was the only appropriate way to make products. It's called
meeting good manufacturing practices. It's a couple levels higher than any of the states require
for safety or efficacy. And so we just make products to meet FDA specifications because
to me that's just easier. In other words, this is going to sound crass, so excuse it and you can
clarify it, but you're like a supplement company that adheres to GMP practice.
I don't think of us as a supplement company. Meaning you make a supplement to a GMP,
this product, for example, like something that you can sell currently today without a prescription.
Right. We work within the medical legal rules in Michigan, but those rules do not mandate
GMP manufacturing. And you hold yourselves to that standard. That's the point I'm trying to make.
Yeah, that's exactly- I'm trying to pay you a compliment. I'm making it sound backwards,
but yes. And this is, as most everyone knows, doing an adequate amount of testing to go through
the FDA process is very expensive and very time consuming. And let's put some numbers to that.
And on average, it's about a decade and a billion dollars to create a new drug. Yes,
that's exactly right. Let's say that again. You want to make a new drug from IND to approval
is order of magnitude 10 years and $1 billion. Yeah, that's right.
I don't think your retirement account is that big. That's correct. So anyone out there who-
This is going to turn into a telethon. Let me ask, why have you not pursued a product yet on sleep?
Because I, again, I think anecdotally what you've said resonates with many people, the power of CBD,
including probably very inferior products compared to what you're capable of making
with your IP. Is the view that you don't need to go down the IND pathway to produce that,
or is it just a matter of resource allocation? It really is resource allocation. Truthfully,
we have 14 indications that we are going for and you have to prioritize, as everyone does with
everything in your life. And we looked at them and said, which ones are easier or faster or less
expensive to test and be able to prove? Sleep studies, frankly, are very expensive and they
are variable just in the methodology of it. Whereas it's a lot easier to be able to measure pain
and there are scoring systems that are more reliable in that way. Tell me a little bit about
what you can sell in Michigan and how does a business work that can only limit itself to one
state? So it's quite challenging. We drove at getting a license, a first license, and we were
successful in getting the first license in Michigan to be a processor. That is, we can take in cannabis
that's been grown within the state and turn it into an extractive and then turn that into
tablets. That's what the process of processing is. We could also make it into gummy bears and vape
cartridges and we sell those also. And then we are able to ship those to just state authorized
dispensaries. Historically, people in Michigan needed to have medical marijuana licenses in
order to get into those stores. But now, like many states, it's called recreational or adult use.
You only need to show that you are 21 years of age to be able to go into those stores and buy.
So that's how we started. But now we have grown to have, we have liaisons with subsidiary
companies or affiliated companies where we're growing about 5,500 plants, bringing it to our
facilities, doing the extraction. And we have relationships with all of the 70, 80 dispensary
stores throughout Michigan. That's how that business has grown and that's to a large extent
so far what's been able to fund our research studies. But once again, this is a telethon,
folks. You can call in. How large is your team?
So we have overall about 100 employees working in various aspects of production and sales and
administration for the company. In terms of the research team, Deb is our chief medical officer
and then there are about another 10 or so direct people working on it and then another 30 to 40
consultants who come in and out of the projects to be able to work on those.
What will be required from a legal standpoint for products like this or similar products to be sold
across state lines? Does that only happen at the federal level?
Yeah, that only happens at the federal level. We think that the first number of indications
that we've picked and worked on with FDA are going to go through fast track approval and that's
without getting down into the weeds of all of the legalities of that. That frequently allows a
product to get through the FDA process in somewhere between two to four years. In the space of drug
development, that's the blink of an eye and at the same time we're beginning our international
aspect. Deb and I will be in Berlin presenting our data at an international meeting of cannabis
physicians so that this activity is very, very quickly spreading not just here but across the
country and across the world. I was lucky enough to be able to be at the United Nations in 2016
testifying and telling the UN that they should change the war on drug policy from incarceration
and retribution to medication and treatment. While things move slowly through the political
process, we see that that is taking hold in country after country that this war on drugs policy is
changing dramatically as countries are able to see the medicine and science for themselves.
It's very, very encouraging. Deb, how often do you get invited to speak at medical conferences
that are not about THC or cannabis? In other words, how often is the anesthesiology society
saying, hey, come and give us a talk on pain and the use of this because as physicians,
we're seeing that our patients are using these things and we're ignorant?
Right. Sadly, not often enough. I do lecture to grand rounds for individual physicians and groups
and departments that have heard me speak or seen me on YouTube and said, wait, we need to have her
come in. I'm actually lecturing in Detroit next month to a group of scientists and engineers and
biopharma developers who are interested in what we do. That's a unique space, but I am actually
hoping to target in California at the end of Q2 for 2020 that I'm going to speak with the
society of pain. So I'm looking forward to that. Now, this might sound like a dumb question,
but if you have a state like Colorado or California in which you have the same legal
framework basically as Michigan, why can your product not ship from one state to another state?
Because I have to leave Michigan and pass into another state before I get to Colorado.
Even if I shipped next door to Illinois or Ohio for a microsecond, it will be in federal land
as it goes from state to state. It's called interstate commerce. And there was a very classic
law case on this 150 years or so ago that defined what is interstate commerce.
And it's essentially just stepping over the border and sometimes even more than that,
just being on a federal highway. What does the, if you had to guess, I know you don't have a crystal
ball, but if you had to sort of think about what the legal framework is going to evolve into,
do you believe that cannabis will always be illegal at the federal level or do you think
that it will have a change in legal status? Oh, it's absolutely going to change. Absolutely
going to change. No question about it. It's so clear. How long do you think this could take?
Well, we see that it is beginning. That is hemp right now is part of that story. It is the nose
of the camel in the tent to be able to move this forward. At this point, we have more than half
the states have said that these products are just fine for their patients, for their population.
And FDA is currently very, very actively involved in this. I was fortunate enough to be part of a
task force that started some years ago to be able to move this forward. FDA is struggling to find
literally a legal pigeonhole to put this into my suggestion for any of the FDA officials who might
be listening to this podcast, and I hope it's all of them, that there's the over-the-counter drug
review that has been used for many, many years to be able to take products onto the shelves of drug
stores to be able to use this based on the fact that people could self-prescribe some medications
for themselves. They didn't need a physician to write a script. So we think that many of these
products have sufficient safety, that they are self-prescribable, and I think we see that because
frankly, there's about 30 million, 40 million people using these on a regular basis right now.
And other than the vaping crisis, they're not filling up hospital wards due to toxicity from
these products. They're able to use them. Okay. So do you think that the farm bill is really the
single most important thin end of the wedge because it was the first piece of federal
law that decriminalized the first part of the value chain here?
Yes, absolutely. It really was. I think that that will continue actually from many of the
cannabis business people who are struggling in this area because the tax laws are incredibly
burdensome and require a lot of dancing in order to be able to just simply run a business.
But we see ourselves a year and a half ago, I had to switch bank accounts four times in one year.
If anyone ever tried having to switch your bank account where your bank suddenly closes out on you
every three months, that's terrible, especially as you're just trying to run a business and pay
bills. Now though, we have completely solid, reasonable banking relationships. We're able
to get insurance. Everything is becoming normalized and we do not see patients or consumers
acting foolishly in any way. Quite to the contrary, they often are reducing the amount
of smoking of cigarettes and alcohol use and are becoming more law abiding citizens than less.
Deb, what concerns, if any, do you have about what this industry looks like? I mean, I can't go
more than a week without getting pitched some CBD, THC, hemp company. I mean, there must be
more companies sprouting up in some part of this value chain than any other industry. I mean,
from an investment standpoint, this is an area where people are very excited.
I just don't imagine most of the people bring the expertise that your team is bringing, which is why
I wanted to talk with you guys as opposed to every other person out there who's peddling a
cause. But do you see that as being a concern? In other words, can a few bad actors set the stage
back? Yes, especially in the stigma area for patients. That's my major concern is patient
safety. There are a lot of people out there that see a gold rush or a green rush and they just want
to make products, sell them to people and get a Dodge and enrich themselves. And that's a concern
to me. When patients unfortunately are not understanding that just because you can buy
something off the shelf of a big box store or from an online source that it's tested and it's safe,
because there's no guarantee to that. And so my recommendation of patients is if you live in a
legal state, you should buy from a legal dispensary, ask for their certificate of analysis, take a look
at it, make sure that there's no adulterants to the best of our knowledge in the science right now.
This is why I'm happy to work with Steve because this is his passion as well because we really
don't want to hurt people. I mean, that's the thing that kills me. That's the reason why actually
it should be de-scheduled. I mean, so it would allow for robust testing, a standardized testing.
I mean, just because there's testing in states doesn't mean they all use the same methods.
That's sort of something you guys brought up today that was news to me, which was
the inability of the states to rise to the level of federal testing. And so in many ways,
the decriminalization state by state is not a great approach. You can't just run that out to
its natural conclusion without decriminalizing it at the federal level to get the full muscle
of the FDA and the protocols behind testing. Absolutely. I mean, from laboratory to laboratory,
there are no standards. And the problem is there's no guidance because it's been illegal.
And so the sources that laboratories would use to go to to say, well, where do we get our standards
from? And what are the methods of extracting from this gummy bear or this brownie in order to test
the potency or test the microbials or to test any of it don't exist. So look, there are people
listening to this in 49 states that are not in Michigan, not to mention people that are listening
to this outside of this country. What would be your playbook for them to protect themselves as
they go into their local dispensary or purchase online? You can buy CBD across state lines if
it's pure enough. How would you give people a sort of instruction list of things to do to first and
foremost protect themselves? Right. So this is a human rights issue. You hit the nail on the head.
I mean, that's a huge problem for me as a physician to guide patients, which I do, I guide over 400
patients privately free of charge because I'm a terrible business person. But for me to guide them
and have to understand their state in order to help them access certain medicines is just
horrific to me. But what I would say to them is go to a legal state, become certified as a patient,
meet with a physician there and get the guidance from that and buy from a legal dispensary.
Do you think that's enough? So I mean, a physician in another state, do they have the expertise
to help them navigate through the dispensary? There is a society called Society of Cannabis
Clinicians where they have a list of doctors by state who actually are experts in cannabinoid
medicine for which they can go seek out and help themselves. I mean, this is a nascent industry.
It's still federally illegal, which allows for all of these hoops to have to be jumped through.
I would recommend not buying online. I would recommend not buying off the street. I mean,
we tell our children don't take candy from strangers because you don't know what it is.
Why would our medicine be any different? So I don't know that it's widely known,
but I developed the actual essay methods to detect LSD, marijuana, cocaine, amphetamines,
and I published those results when I was 21 and 22 years old. So I really have a pretty solid
sense of what these laboratories are able to do. That was, well, almost 50 years or so ago,
and it was my first scientific publications. The labs are capable nowadays because I just
recently set one up a few years ago of doing remarkably accurate and precise work on all of
these cannabinoid products and to be able to do it. But the state rules vary and the states are
still learning. What should the pesticides be that are allowed or allowable? What are the levels
of heavy metals, et cetera? So from state to state, the rules vary and they are getting
more learned as the work is done. So this is a great developing field. Some labs are better than
others to be able to do it. So that's why to echo Deb's recommendation for people who want to
utilize these products, they really need to ask for the certificate of analysis,
see if they can become educated enough to be able to do that. Certainly physicians should. I know
that these systems, endocannabinoid systems were not taught in medical schools. They certainly
weren't taught in the chemistry schools that I went to. And this is a remarkable societal
experience in allowing non-toxic substances to be used and self-prescribed. I think it's a
challenge for the physicians to catch up because you are a learned intermediary to help patients
be able to do this. And I hope out of this podcast, that's why we're here, is to help encourage all of
these educational programs. Because frankly, our hands are full enough just running the clinical
trials and being able to run a business. So we're going to have to leave that part of it up to you.
Well, on that guys, I want to thank you very much for coming down here today and for making time and
for sharing kind of all your insights and for the work you're doing. I mean, I think this is,
I don't know, I've got to be honest with you. I think I'm still somewhat confused about all
of the different permutations and combinations of these molecules. And it's complicated by the fact
that interstate commerce prevents easy access of higher quality products to individuals. So I guess
the thing we can all hope for is that, and again, I would say this frankly, even if you are still
undecided on the safety or efficacy of these, everyone still seems to benefit from the
decriminalization of this because it allows far more rigorous testing and it de-stigmatizes
so much of the research funding that goes into this. But I think one way or the other, we get
answers quicker. And that's probably what we're kind of missing at the moment.
Right. This is a process that's unfolding in a very, very short length of time. I was at a meeting
with FDA, DEA, and Department of Defense just four and a half years ago and NIH, where I brought up
the idea, hey fellas, you're the federal regulators and it looks like cannabis is going to get approved
state by state. Why don't we try and set some federal health policies here around that? And
just four and a half years ago, everyone in the room except me said, are you kidding? That's never
going to happen. And now we see it actually has. And so the people who are in a role to be able
to bring these forces to bear are trying to play catch up and do it and more power to them.
And I think that everyone should just try and continue to do just as you are doing here,
allow folks like us to bring our thoughts to bear and happy to hear from anybody. We're not certain
we have all the best right answers. We have a particular predilection towards medicine and the
idea that above all else, do no harm first. We're kind of pushy about it though.
Thanks very much guys. I really appreciate it.
Thanks for having us.
Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my
blog at peteratiamd.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame
once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social, you can
find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID peteratiamd, but usually Twitter is
the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have
and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Lastly,
and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures,
the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about.