Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast. If you're listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things
I care most about professionally are how to live longer and how to live better. I have
a complete fascination and obsession with this topic. I practice it professionally and
I've seen firsthand how access to information is basically all people need to make better
decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating and sharing this knowledge
is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to me. The sheer
volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a great
team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one example,
our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a
natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As
you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot
of contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now, the
first and most important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm
telling you about something when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it
to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I
just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not absolutely
nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others
have proved can work over time, and that is to create a subscriber model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available
for free. It's that simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose
to support us at, you will get back more than you give. So for example, members will receive
full access to the exclusive show notes, including other things that we plan to build upon. These
are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of our shows.
Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me Anything
episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to hear
these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as
I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with
companies who make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and
have them pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope
is that many of you will find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional
content exclusive for members. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen to this. If you
learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us directly
by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Mark Messier. Mark is considered one
of the greatest hockey players of all time. He had a career that spanned 25 years in the NHL,
and he's played the second most games of any player, second only to Gordie Howe. And there's
interesting story that we'll get to in the podcast about how close he came to that record. He's also
the second leading all time scorer of all time, or as he likes to put it, the first leading all
time score amongst mere mortals with Wayne Gretzky being the only one who scored more than he did.
It would take me too long to kind of go through all of Mark's professional accolades, six time
Stanley Cup champion, the only person to captain two different teams to win a Stanley Cup, the
Edmonton Oilers, and the New York Rangers, in addition to all the number of all-star games
he's played in and the number of MVPs that he's won, etc. I wanted to talk with Mark about a number
of things today. I wanted to obviously talk about his career, and this is kind of a boyhood dream of
mine to speak with one of my heroes who I've had the privilege of getting to know over the past
couple of years. But also I wanted to just talk about Mark's philosophy in life and leadership
and amazing transition he has made and the ease with which it seems he's been able to transition
out of the limelight into his family life and his work outside of hockey. We touch on many things
here, but we do sort of go through it chronologically, and I think if you're a hockey fan, this is a no
brainer for you. But I would encourage you, even if you're not a hockey fan, to listen to this one.
I think you're gonna get a lot out of it. I think I was really on the edge of my seat, honestly,
during so many parts of this. And even though a lot of the stories I knew, but I don't think I
really appreciated growing up watching Mark was the subtlety and the maturation process that came
along with his leadership and his growth as an individual. You know, I almost forgot that he
entered the NHL at the age of 17 or 18 years old, which seems almost unimaginable today. I'll leave
it at that. And without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Mark Messier. Mark,
thanks so much for coming into the city today. Good to be here with you. How often do you come
into New York City these days? Actually, quite often, especially with the emerging Kingsbridge
project up in the Bronx, which set up an office down on 21st Street and was coming in for at least
a couple years, at least four times a week. And then Ranger Games and other charitable initiatives
and dinners and meetings. New York is still friendly. I'm a regular on the on the subways
and trains now. Yeah, I was about to say, I mean, you know, you took the subway in today,
the most days to someone recognizing the train. Every day on the train coming in from Greenwich,
then on the subways, obviously takes a lot of selfies on the subway, but it doesn't get old.
It's just amazing. You know, almost 20 years later, the passion that's still in the city and
the people that were involved with the Rangers at Europe, if not actually there during their
regular season of the playoffs. And of course, the Stanley Cup in 1994. So yeah, this is 25 years,
which 20, 25 year. Yeah, it is hard to believe. Actually, we're we had a reunion last year. We
couldn't believe it's been actually 25 years. Yeah, we were talking before we started this
podcast about even just it seems like you didn't retire 14 years ago or whatever it was 15 years
ago. Like it seems I guess that's what happens when we get older. Time goes seems to be going
by quicker. Life does not stand still. That's for sure. Especially when you have kids, you can see
the growth obviously every year. And it's fun though. Every stage of the development of the
kids has been amazing being a part of their lives and being retired so I can be home for that has
been incredible. So yeah, I've enjoyed the retirement, but still when you start actually
reminiscing and talking about my career, it's hard to believe I've been retired now almost 14 years.
We'll talk a lot about your career, but I mean, I think one little factoid that's always worth
mentioning is the length of it, right? It's that I mean, you played in the NHL for 25 years, correct?
25 years in the NHL, 26 years as a professional started when I was 17. And the that back when
they had the WHA, which was the secondary league, a lot of the NHLers Wayne Gretzky, Craig Hartsburg,
they used to call that it was, it was a big race to sign the underage players back then, especially
for the WHA who was competing with the NHL. So I was able to play as a 17 year old for two teams
and I have the distinction of being the youngest player ever to fold a professional franchise in
hockey. Cincinnati or the Indianapolis Racers, I played five games and they folded, went home
back to Edmonton for a couple of weeks and then Cincinnati signed me about two weeks later.
It's interesting to look back at because that's as you know, because we've talked about this before,
but I mean, the Oilers were my team growing up even though I grew up in Toronto. I mean, one,
the Leafs were just such a bad team in the 80s that, you know, hard to be a Leafs fan, but also
Edmonton was just the most exciting team in hockey. So I remember those early 80s
years and those were, I think it's, unless you're in a real hockey diehard, I don't think most people
remember what the Oilers were like in the 80s, like what it was like to have
Gretzky, Messier, Curry, Coffey, Lowe, Fuhrer, Anderson, like that all of those guys were on
one team. Yeah. Like a free agency wouldn't permit that today, right? It would be hard to keep the
players for as long as we did, but just to put it in perspective, I used to travel a lot in the
summertime. I had to travel bug and went all over the world and the Oilers literally in Wayne
Gretzky put Edmonton on the map. There wasn't anywhere we didn't travel that someone didn't
know where Edmonton was because of the hockey team, which was always kind of gave you a sense of pride
just because of what we're able to accomplish, but also what we're able to do in the sporting world
that was being recognized with people all over the world. That was eyeopening for me coming from
Edmonton and traveled a bit with our family. But once I started really going abroad and
that really hit at home that we were doing something special and actually we had a really
special team with some amazing players that was being recognized around the world.
So you grew up how close to Edmonton? I know you're from Alberta, right?
Yeah. So Edmonton, Alberta grew up right there.
Were you in a suburb of Edmonton?
Eventually, but when I first came back, my father was playing hockey in Portland, Oregon
for the Portland Buckaroos. I think we moved back in 1968. He came back and taught school.
I think I came back and was going to grade one or two or right around there. And then right about
when I was turning or getting into, ready to go to grade four, we moved out of Edmonton to St. Albert,
which was a small community at the time just north of the city, finished my schooling there and
played junior hockey until I actually signed as a 17 year old to go to the WHA.
So when did you start playing hockey?
Well, I think like everybody else, I started skating fairly early, but I think my first
organized hockey team was pretty much like everybody, like right at six years old.
Actually started in Edmonton or in Portland. My father started the whole minor hockey league
programs in Portland. They didn't have kids hockey back then. He was responsible for really
getting the whole minor hockey league system up and running in Portland, Oregon.
How did it fit into other sports and other activities you were doing?
Was it one of those things where everybody talks about Wayne's story where he's two years old,
basically you can't stop him from playing, right? It's like you won't come in from the rink. He's
taking shots on his grandmother in the kitchen. Was it like that for you or was it just another
sport that you played in addition to baseball? No, I loved hockey. Back when I played, it was
it was completely different. We played hockey in the wintertime. We had 120 hour program. We had
two practices, two games a week. We didn't travel to tournaments. Everything was right in Edmonton.
When this winter or the spring came, we played baseball or soccer. We played multiple sports.
If you talk to Wayne and you listen to what he talks about is exactly that.
He was a great athlete in the other one.
Great athlete. He played all sports. He played baseball. He's a great baseball player. He's a
great lacrosse player. He played hockey in the wintertime. That's the way it was. Now it's
been more professionalized at an early age, which some would dispute is not the most healthy thing
for kids, but that's the way it is now. What do you think of that? My reading of the literature,
so this is a very academic view of this, not as my kids aren't in Southern California, hockey is
not even on their radar, even though obviously lots of kids in SoCal do play hockey. It would seem
that the approach that you took was a better approach actually, which is a broader sampling
of sports and developing a broader set of athletic abilities before ultimately narrowing your focus.
I mean, that looks to be the better formula, but it's not what's typically happening today, is it?
It's not. And I think because of it, it puts a lot of pressure on the parents, both on the time
issue for parents and the pressure puts on the rest of the family, but also on the
financial by having to travel consistently to different places to play tournament,
hockey and whatnot. But until you get to the age of 14 is really the kind of the age where
kids start separating themselves into what they really want to do and they're more focused into
what they want to do. But up until then, I've always believed that it's great to try a lot
of different sports and become a better athlete total, a total better athlete in all regards.
And I think the science would probably prove that. And there's all kinds of examples of some hockey
players that actually made it to the NHL that didn't really start playing hockey till they were
14 or 15 years old, which debunks the myth of that you have to be playing hockey 365 days from the
time you're two years old to the time you get drafted. It's just not the case. You got to be
blessed with a God given talent to order in order to make it. And then at the right time,
you have to hone those skills and you have to have the desire and the passion to put the work in.
But there's a lot of kids that go through that whole process that never do make it. So where is
that fine line and that balance that's really healthy for the family structure, healthy for
the kid and give him the best opportunity to fulfill his own dreams. So what's the earliest
memory you have of your dad playing? Because I got to believe that that sort of at least planted
a seed in your mind or? No question. I remember I wasn't even in school yet and we were living in
Portland, Oregon and my father would take me with him to his practices. Sometimes I probably was
maybe four, three, four years old. And then we'd be able to go skate on the ice in Portland before
his practice started. So, you know, I have very early memories of him playing. I can honestly say,
I don't really actually remember him being on the ice in a game vaguely. We got some old pictures
and some old videos that we watch once in a while, but no question him being a hockey player really
cemented the passion. And it's amazing how much you learn sitting around the kitchen table,
talking about hockey when you have a parent that was so entrenched in the game itself,
not only as a player, but as a coach and as a mentor to a lot of young kids after his retirement.
When did it start to make sense to you that like this thing that you love doing or one of several
sports you like doing, you actually could do this as your job. I mean, how old were you when it became?
Yeah, you know, I always played up. My brother was four years older than me or three years older
than me, I guess. So when we moved back from Portland to Edmonton, Paul was basically a Pee Wee.
I think he was 10 years old or somewhere in there. I was seven. So my dad was coaching and he didn't
want to go to two different practice times and two different ranks. So he just put me on the team. And
so I was always playing against older kids. The joke was I had a career as a Pee Wee. I think I
played four years as a Pee Wee, but I was never really that great growing up. I liked the game. I
always watched hockey night in Canada. I did all the things that most kids do when they love a
sport. I guess, you know, I didn't have very much success as a Bantam. I think one of my Bantam years
or one of my Midget years, we've won one game the whole time of the whole year. So individually,
I wasn't really kind of standing out maybe because I was playing against older kids.
But do you remember if you were Hessel having fun? Oh yeah.
Do you remember how you felt about it? Oh, loved it.
Oh yeah, loved it. Loved it. Oh yeah. Never question about, my dad was really cool about
practices and all that. He always knew if I was just being lazy or if I really just needed not to
go because of tired school or whatever. So there's never any pressure in that regard to go to the
ranks. But we would, besides our practices, we would go with our friends and play outside. And
that's what we would do on the weekends when we weren't playing. I mean, that's how we spent our
time. The outside ranks with our buddies and sipping hot chocolate and playing a shinny.
I had a real passion for the game, but I had a passion for all sports. I loved being outside,
playing, throwing soccer, football, lacrosse. I tried them all. I wasn't that great in any of
them there, but certainly had the passion for hockey. And it was probably looking back and it
was my, probably my main sport. So when you're what, 12, 13, 14, did anything start to change
at that point in terms of your. Not to why I was a late developer. I didn't really start growing
at 15. I think I had a Legrosper. I shot up to like five, nine and 150 pounds. I actually made
that next fall after turning in 15 in January. The next fall I made the junior team, which at
a 15 was pretty good. By that time I was maybe growing a little bit more, but I was a late
developer physically. I played four years of junior. When I finished junior, I was six, one,
couple hundred pounds. And that's when I left to go play probe. So when I was right around 14,
I really started to kind of, I used to practice with my dad's junior team. They're all 20 to
15 to 20 years old when I was younger and trying to do all the drills and catching up. But I was
working hard, but I couldn't really generate any speed. And my dad was, come on, you got to skate,
skate, skate. And I was in my own mind, I felt the other skating, but all of a sudden I started
getting, growing and getting stronger. All of a sudden my stride getting started getting longer,
started getting more speed and everything just started to fall into place once I turned 15 and
became a junior. Were you weight training at the time? What kind of off-place training were you
didn't start weight training till I was 15. You know, at that time, you know, the conventional
wisdom, he had to wait a certain time to your growth plates and all that. And I think it's still
true till today. We had an assistant coach, my after my first year of junior, who befriended one
of the world's strongest men in the contest, huge guy. And he had brought home a program that he did
and it was Monday, Wednesday, Friday, three hour sessions. And, you know, we just used to lift,
it's all changed now, but back then it was heavy weights. And, you know, we couldn't even lift
our arms up to wash our hair after in the shower. It was one of those real beefy, big weight, heavy
weight, weight lifting programs, but that really, really cemented it for me. I love to work out. I
could see the changes happening there. So between getting the power on the ice, so I could skate
faster and handle myself. And it really all started to kind of come together for me at that,
right around that 15 years old age. So you're 17, you're in the WHA, which as you pointed out a
moment ago, I mean, the WHA was absorbed, at least four of the teams I think were absorbed by the NHL
when the WHA folded. But there were a lot of great players in the WHA. I mean, many stars in the NHL
came out of that league. What was it like back in the late seventies was the idea that you play in
the WHA and then eventually go to the NHL, or was it a totally parallel path that you pick one
or the other? No, not really. It was just, there was a lot of underages being signed by-
Did the NHL have a cap on what you could sign at the time?
No, there was no cap, nothing like that at the NHL. And the NHL wasn't too happy about losing
these young, great players to the like Gretzky, to the WHA. So it was a little bit of tenuous
relationship, obviously, between the two leagues. The WHA folded before those teams went, I think
was Winnipeg, Quebec, Edmonton and Hartford joined the NHL from, so went from a 16 team to a 21 team.
I think the city, the team in Kansas, or somebody became, I can't remember, I can't remember now.
My trajectory was, I was going to go follow my brother's footsteps to a college scholarship to
Denver University. So I had kind of a verbal commitment from Marshall Johnson at the time,
who was scouting the Western teams in junior and that felt like a great, great idea. And so I stayed
in junior B, which gives you the ability to go play college hockey instead of the major junior,
where you can't, it takes your eligibility away. So that was what I was planning on doing. And all
of a sudden the opportunity came to go play in the WHA and I was kind of getting bigger and stronger.
Obviously looking back, I was never ready to go play pro-hockey as a 17 year old,
but I can honestly say it was a great experience. What did your folks say? What did your mom say
about that specifically? I don't think my mom was too happy about it. My dad was a little more,
he kind of realized that I was at the point of, it was my fourth year of junior hockey. I was kind of
playing pretty well at that particular time for that league. I couldn't go to college yet. I had
to finish the year. And so I was kind of stuck in this kind of place. But was playing going to take
that college eligibility away? I'm assuming a year in the WHA. Oh yeah. I became a pro.
No, I became assigned a contract. I became a pro. That wiped out the college.
Was that a hard decision to make? For you personally?
I would have liked to have gone to college, but for me it just seemed to be the right thing for
me at the time, emotionally and for what I was really trying to accomplish. I wanted to be a pro
hockey player at that time. I'd kind of thrown everything into the ring. So, you know, and
someone's going to sign you and give you some money to go play hockey. It didn't seem like a
bad idea. I'm kind of amazed how small many of those contracts were at the time. I mean, Gretsky
had, I think, a huge contract with the Indianapolis Racers that ultimately got bought by the Oilers
while they were in the WHA. Even his wasn't big. But relative to WHA. Well, Bobby Hulsey signed
for a million dollars back in the early 70s, which was huge money for anybody back then.
So they were given some money out to try to get some recognition. And wasn't Gordie Howe
in the WHA at this point as well? Gordie Howe. I played against Gordie Howe in the WHA. Because
he was playing for the Whalers at the time, wasn't he? He was playing for the Whalers, yeah. And he
had a bunch of old Boston Bruins, Davey Keon, Johnny McKenzie. I mean, I watched these guys play
on Hockey Night in Canada my whole life. And here I am as a 17-year-old in the WHA playing against
Gordie Howe and Johnny McKenzie and Dave Keon and all these amazing players that I'd watched for
years in the NHL that had finished their careers in the WHA. So it was amazing, actually. Do you
remember the first time you met Kratzky? I do. I always tell the story. When I was flying from
Edmonton to go play for Indianapolis, it was shortly after he got traded with Peter Driscoll
and Eddie Meale. And he was on a plane flying from Indianapolis to Edmonton. And so our paths
crossed in the air. And so I didn't meet Wayne other than playing against him. I didn't meet him
until training camp when the leagues folded. I was drafted by Edmonton. And then we met at training
camp in 1979. And that would be in the NHL now? That was in the NHL. So you guys didn't meet? I
didn't realize that. I thought you guys crossed paths in WHA, but you actually didn't really meet
until you were both now. No, I was playing in Indianapolis. They folded. Then I went to Cincinnati
to finish the year for 52 games. And Wayne got traded to Edmonton. So we played against each
other but didn't know each other. And how many of the other foundational players of the Oilers came
in that merger? Who else was there? Was Fier there? No, Fier didn't get drafted until 80,
two years into our NHL. And Currie came later. Currie came maybe the second after the second
draft. What about Lowe? Lowe was the first draft for the Edmonton Oilers. Yeah, Kevin was the first
draft ever of the Edmonton Oilers back in 1979, 80 draft. I think Currie came the next year, Grant,
and Paul Coffey came the second year with Currie. Currie was like a fourth, fifth rounder.
Then Grant was drafted early in the third year. And so we basically, that whole team from the
draft came together. So Andy Moog was the goalie coming out of WHA? Andy Moog? No, he didn't come
until later either. He was playing, he came from Penticton, was playing Major Junior. He got there
before Grant. He came the second year when we upset the Montreal Canadiens. Yes, which was 1981.
It was 1981. I think our goalie got hurt or Glencie either put him in on a whim and they
stole the show as a rookie goalie. That was back when, I mean a lot of people don't remember what
the NHL looked like back then, but my recollection, I was only eight years old, but I was still obsessed.
One played 16, two played 15. It was done like a sweet 16, independent of conference, wasn't it?
Absolutely. Yeah, 21 team leagues, 16 made the playoffs, eight from each conference,
and you seated yourself depending on where you stood during the regular season.
Edmonton gets in there 16th, the top seed is the Montreal Canadiens.
The second year, first year we played Philadelphia. We made the playoffs the first year. We had to win
nine of the last 10 games of the regular season, our first year, just to make the playoffs. Of
course, Philadelphia was a team who we played. They beat us in, I think they beat us three straight
back then with the first series. Yeah, the first series was best of five. Best of five,
so they beat us pretty handily. They had a really good team.
And then it's that second season, which is 81-82, if I'm not mistaken.
It was 81.
81. Yeah.
Well, we played the Montreal Canadiens.
And you upset the Canadians.
We upset the Canadians, which was one of the most, to this day, one of my
best experiences playing hockey, that whole series against Montreal. And I can't remember
everything that happened, but I just remember coming home and people can Google it. And it's
the impossible dream. We were under the dressing room, obviously, waiting to be
come out onto the ice. And they played a video with the song, Impossible Dream,
with all the highlights, because we won the first two games in Montreal,
and coming home to close it out. To this day, it makes it here in the back of my neck stand up of
how energized that city was.
Was that the moment you realized that you were going to win a Stanley Cup?
Whether or not that year. But when was the moment when you thought,
this is a really special group of people?
Well, it wasn't quite that soon, but I think what we all recognized was that Wayne was on
a different trajectory than most any other hockey player that ever played the game.
And the chances of Wayne winning a Stanley Cup were going to be pretty good.
And if we all played our cards right, and we were able to grab an oar and start rowing,
and fill a need on the team, our chances increased significantly if we could
follow Wayne. And that's true. That's the way we felt. Wayne was completely different than any
hockey player. He was chasing records books. He wanted to smash every record that it was ever made.
Well, 81-82 is sort of a crazy year, because those are some of my really first memories of hockey.
So I grew up in Toronto, so you guys always were two hours behind us. So to watch an Oilers game,
it was really a big ask of my mom. I do my mom's permission to stay up late,
because you guys weren't starting your games until 9 PM Toronto time.
On a school night.
But I would beg and plead, and I think my mom just gave up. I mean, it was just like,
oh, for heaven's sake.
Yeah, it was must-watch TV. I think he tied Marcel Deon his first year with 165 points,
and then the second year, I think he smashed it with 190-some points, and went on going away,
and then onto 215 points.
212, and then up to 15.
And then he'll score 50 goals in 39 games.
Well, it's that night I remember. So do you remember that night in Edmonton against Philadelphia,
when he's got 45 goals going into the 39th game, and at that point, everybody knows 50 and 50 is
going to go down, but nobody knows it's going to be five goals in one night.
Everybody's just trying to anticipate where to be and where to get tickets when it's going to happen,
but nobody going to that rink that night thought he was going to score five goals against the
Philadelphia Flyers. The big, bad, tough Philadelphia Flyers, there were no way they were going to
let that happen. And sure enough, he did. He scored five goals, and Pete Peters, and
what an amazing time to sit there and watch that genius on a day-to-day basis.
How often in anybody's life can they look at one of their own peers, a guy that's your same age,
and look up to him as a role model, but that's what Wayne was for us. He was so far ahead of us,
in his own mental preparation and the way he prepared for games, both physically and mentally,
and his ambition of what he wanted to do in the game of hockey, all those things were just so far
superior. And then to be able to sit there and watch how he practiced and his practice habits,
and how he prepared for games, and it was just remarkable to have someone like that to learn from.
I wanted to understand that a little bit more, because I think most people are familiar with you
as one of the greatest leaders in hockey. I mean, you are the only person to captain two Stanley
Cup teams. You've captained Edmonton to a Stanley Cup in the absence of Gretzky, and then you
captained the Rangers to a Stanley Cup, and no one's done that before or since. And yet, what
I'm hearing you say is some of your early sort of lessons in leadership came from watching Gretzky.
Well, not only Wayne, but a lot of people. Obviously, my father, who was a great mentor
and role model for not only myself and my brother and my sisters, but also a lot of hockey players
that he coached. He was a great coach, a great mentor, and then all the people that helped you
along the way. And then you turn pro, and then you start watching other players, and you start
watching and listening to coaches, and you start filling up your bag with all this experience. And
so you kind of learn through successes and failures of what actually works for you as a player and as
a person. So you're kind of collecting all this data, you know, all the way along. Wayne just
happened to be a teammate that was obvious to everybody that he was going to become the best
hockey player to ever play the game. He proved it as a kid from the time he was four years old to the
time he was in junior hockey. That's the time he turned pro, and here he is, you know, scoring 215
points unheard of numbers in any sport, no matter how you compare it to. It's worth pausing on that
for a moment because I don't think a non-hockey fan can put in perspective what Wayne Gretzky did
during about a seven-year run from 81 to 88, right? What you just described. To my knowledge,
no player has ever scored more than 200 points in a season. Gretzky averaged that for seven
consecutive seasons. Yeah, I know you're probably true. I know that he had, you know, 215, 212,
202 a few times, 198. I mean, there was years when he was winning the scoring title on assists alone.
Yeah, the only guy that I can actually say that was, you could even talk about Wayne in the same
breath in that regard as far as that offensive genius would be Mario. Mario had some injuries
earlier on, and so he never had that consistency that Wayne did. But he would be the only guy that
I could even think about comparing to to have that, you know, offensive genius that exists in a guy
that was able to do that. It was amazing having that kind of role model there, right? For a guy
that was my own age. That's right, because you guys are both born in 61. Eight days older, yeah.
I remember reading a funny story once, and again, it can be totally BS because it was just
blown out of proportion, but early in your days in Edmonton, you sort of got in trouble for something.
I don't know, did you fail to show up to a practice? Were you disciplined for something
very early in your time in Edmonton? Yeah, I was living at home my first year pro and
punctuality at that time in my life probably wasn't my best asset.
But this one was actually harmful. You were super punctual today. Whatever lessons learned.
Lessons learned, it's taken a while. But I was living at home and my mom was driving. We were
leaving on an extended road trip, and so I packed my bag and my mom was driving me to the airport.
And she asked, you know, because back then there was two airports in Edmonton. There was a downtown
airport and there was one out in the suburbs, the international airport, and I told her that
we were coming back into the municipal airport. For whatever reason, we just didn't think about it.
We drove to the municipal airport. So when I got out of the car and she dropped me off,
this is back in the day with no cell phones or anything, I looked around and normally you see the
guys in trench coats and their bags and everybody huddled together waiting on their tickets. And I
didn't see any kind of sign that you'd normally see. So my heart started beating a little quicker
and sure enough, I looked at the itinerary and we were leaving to Detroit from Edmonton International.
So my heart sank. I quickly jumped in a, actually I went and phoned on the pay phone and phoned the
oiler office and the secretary said, no problem, Mark, there'll be a ticket waiting for you at the
counter at the Canada counter. So when I got to in a taxi and got out to international, went up to
desk and got my ticket, except it wasn't going to Detroit, it was going to Houston. I was being
sent down to the farm team to teach me a lesson. So that was a tough moment for me at that time,
knowing that I missed a flight and was being sent to our farm team. I spent two weeks down there,
played five games and they called me back up thankfully, but that was not a fun experience.
But that must have left an impression. I mean, that's a pretty harsh lesson.
Well, you think it would have, but there was a couple other ones along the way that
had to cement the lesson. But what you realize is that when you're playing on a team and you're in
a team format, nothing is about you as an individual. It's all about what's best for
the team and your time is not your own. It's a team's time and you have to be respectful of that.
So there was a lot of lessons for me growing up as a young adult in a professional environment
that doesn't always happen. But when you turn professional 18 years old, you grow up quickly.
In those days, I mean, even by today's standards, Gretzky was tiny. How explicit was it that
someone on that team or some group of guys on that team needed to make sure that he didn't get hurt?
Well, back then, that's where the game was played anyways. I mean, it was a completely different
set of rules of what was acceptable behavior in the National Hockey League. It was tough hockey.
Not long before that, there were still bench clearing brawls during the game. I remember
in the WHA my last year as a 17 year old having three bench clearing brawls in one game. Insane
and big, big tough guys I'm looking up to. So yeah, I think every team had a lot of muscle under
teams and everybody had to stick up for each other. You had to be able to count on your teammates
for protection. Everybody had to be a cohesive unit and everybody had the answer to Bell for
the protection of the entirety of the team, not to mention something of Wayne's caliber because
he was obviously targeted in many different ways. And we had to be there to help him get through an
82 game schedule. So let's fast forward to your first Stanley Cup Final, 83 against the
Islanders. The Islanders have won three consecutive Stanley Cups right now. Mike Bossi, Brian Terracie,
Billy Smith, who I hated. If you're an others fan, you hated Billy Smith, right? And it's now
basically you guys are going to try to stop their fourth consecutive Stanley Cup.
How well do you remember that series? I remember every series I ever played, but that one in
particular because how much respect we had for the Islanders. And don't forget two years before
that we had taken them to six games and we didn't even know what we were doing back then. And we were
just doing it on sheer talent and adrenaline and youthful exuberance. And at that point, I mean,
the average age of the Edmonton Oilers is probably 22, 23, right? Well, we had some new veterans that
mixed in with some of our young guys. So then there was a good mix of vets and some young guys, but
we didn't have as much talent then as we ended up having the first year we won. But we still had a
good team. And of course any team with Wayne on it was X factor. So you make it to the finals and I
don't remember what the odds makers said going into that final, but I certainly remember as
a kid, it was like the Oilers are definitely going to win this.
Well, we felt good about it, but we had suffered some painful losses on our way to that first
Stanley Cup final, losing to LA, being up five nothing in the deciding game. There was a lot
of painful lessons along the way of what it took to win. And we were on the trajectory and we were
taking those defeats and those failures and really implementing into our game. And so by the time we
got to the Stanley Cup final, we felt pretty good about our game. We didn't realize how much of a
cohesive unit the Islanders had become by winning three straight Stanley Cups. There was a huge
disparity about where they were as a team and how they played as a team compared to where we were.
It was not even in the same league and they pretty much dismantled us even with the great Gretzky.
They dismantled us in four games and that was a real eye opener for us that if we're going to
take this to the next level there, we have to figure out first of all how to play much better
defensive hockey and then be able to recognize what teams are trying to do to us and then be
able to counterbalance that very quickly in game and make in-game changes and alterations to the
style of play we're playing. So it became a real chess game after that for us. We realized we were
playing checkers and they were playing chess and we had a lot of catching up to do in that regard.
Do you remember leaving the arena on the night that they won the Cup?
Yeah, that's a much often told story. I mean, you can only imagine nowadays a team winning
four straight Stanley Cups and the toll that would take on a team, not only as a team but on every
individual and we did. We walked by their dressing room and expecting a big celebratory
champagne fest and most of them were just sitting around quietly around their stalls by this time
with ice packs on their bodies and that told us that we weren't paying the price that we needed
to in order to win a Stanley Cup. So a lot of lessons, a lot of lessons leaving that rink that
night in that playoff series there that we came back to next year and started implementing very
early on in training camp. You talk about like any professional sport but like take hockey for
example, there's 21 teams. Well, 20 of them end the season as losers, right? I mean, there's just,
you know, there's only one team that's going to win the Stanley Cup. So there's 20 teams that either
don't make the playoffs, get booted out earlier or like the Oilers did in that case, get booted out
at the very last moment. But it would seem to me that losing in the way that you guys did in four
straight, as you said, just getting your asses handed to you makes that a very long summer.
I'm sure there's a part of you that just cannot wait to come back in the fall. Well, we didn't see
it coming because we had actually taken them to six games two years prior and so we felt good about
the matchups and we felt and we knew what we're getting into. We knew the players. It wasn't like
they surprised us from a player standpoint, but what they really surprised us with was how they
were able to take our strengths away and expose our weaknesses and pretty much completely take
us off our game and the game that we like to play. They never allowed us to get into our rhythm and
that high pace, high tempo game that we were so used to and accustomed to playing. And we realized
that if we're going to beat the Islanders there, we had to beat them in the streets, in the alleys,
and eventually we're able to do that the next time around. But what did Glenn say there say
after that fourth game? Do you remember what was said in the locker room when you guys lost?
At that time, not much is said. It's a long year. Everybody's nerves are pretty fragile.
Everybody's emotions are high. It's not really the time to start kind of dissecting what had
happened. I think we all kind of had to live with it ourselves throughout the summer and then come
back and start to address it. And that's what we did. And to everybody's credit, they came back
with even more vigor and determination to get it to the next level. And sure enough, we were able to.
And it's kind of amazing. So the next season, 83-84, you guys face the Islanders again in the final.
And now it's there. They're going for five consecutive Stanley Cups.
And it was easy for them. They had to win an amazing series against Pittsburgh and scored
game seven overtime to get there. So you can imagine it's amazing, actually. To this day,
it's incredible that they made it. We won five cups in seven years, but to win five straight
is incredible. So I think I have a good understanding of what it took on you physically
as a person, but also as a team. And sure enough, there they were again.
Now, if I recall, you guys won game one close. They won game two, not close. It was kind of a
blowout game two, wasn't it? It was pretty good. Yeah. And then you won the next three. And it was,
I always thought like I just, what do you remember about the psychology of those last three games?
Because that was the passing of the baton. That was one dynasty to the next.
To this day, it was so amazing to see that team hang on to
that championship banner and how hard they fought to relinquish it. You would think at some point,
you know, we could have just willed it away from them that we couldn't. They would not relent their
grasp on it. And it was all we could do in that third game to win that third game. Once we won
that third game, I think it kind of was the start of kind of the wear and tear of them starting to
kind of show. And then our confidence went this way and they were beaten up and tired. And then
we're able to win the next games, not easily, but pretty handily. But to this day, I give those guys
so much credit because they would not let go of that, that mantle of being Stanley Cup champions.
And it was so much pride and hard work had gone into it there. And it was just even as no, I think
they knew in their hearts at their time had come. It was just devastating. I think they just were so
devastated that they finally lost there. But it was a great lesson in humility and sportsmanship.
And what a real pride a champion has to watch those guys go through that whole fifth year of
trying to win a Stanley Cup for five times in a row. Now going into game five, when you guys are
at home, if you win the game, you win the cup, which you go on to do. Was there even a tiny bit
of a thought in the back of your mind that not only could you guys win this thing tonight, which I
guess there was that thought, but that you could be the MVP of the playoffs. Was that even something
you never even thought of that, you know, every time we allowed ourselves the night before to
think about maybe we might win the Stanley Cup, it just was over wrought with fear of losing that
game and giving them a chance to get back in the series. We were terrified of the Islanders.
We knew how good a team they were. And even though they were banged up, we knew how dangerous they
were. And if you lose game five, you're back to New York to play game six before you know it.
Game six and game seven. Yeah. Yeah. You could be hosed if you lose that game.
It was not a good thought going all the way back there for a number of reasons, but none more than
than that we were terrified of getting this close and not finishing it off.
Where does that first Stanley Cup first of your six rank in terms of the emotion you felt when
that final buzzer went? Well, I get asked that question often about, do we know what was the
best Stanley Cup? And I can only say that every Stanley Cup had so many of their own unique
storylines because there's always different players and he's obviously the first Stanley Cup
growing up watching it being delivered to a team every year from the time I can remember watching
TV to the time that I actually had a chance to do it ourselves was a huge moment, both from
every individual on the team and then collectively what we had gone through to get there. So that
was that was incredible. But then the next year, it was the same kind of feelings again, because
of how hard we had to work and different set of circumstances, different set of motivating
factors that led into the team. And then the same thing happened all the rest of the time.
And the next year was Pelli Lindberg, right? That was the year you played, you faced Pelli Lindberg
was in the 84-85 Stanley Cup, right? It was the 84, it was the 85 Stanley Cup against Philadelphia.
You go from facing Billy Smith to Pelli Lindberg. I mean, I guess that's why these teams make it to
the Stanley Cup. I mean, these are. The Flyers had an amazing team. When you get to that point,
I mean, obviously playing a team deserverly of being there and nothing's going to be easy. And
at this particular point, we were pretty confident and we knew how to win and we knew what it was
going to take in order to win. We just needed to go out and execute. And we felt that if we
executed our best, we were a better team, but didn't make it any easier. So now you've won
two Stanley Cups by the 85-86 season. Edmonton looks unstoppable. The team is now fully connected.
I mean, you basically could have four or five 50 goal scores on the ice at one time.
In grant fear, you have my personal view, the greatest goalie that ever played the game,
maybe not by the statistics, but in terms of like just pure big game acrobatics.
It seems like there's no way you guys can't win a third, fourth, fifth, sixth, seven Stanley Cup
consecutively. And then you come up against your nemesis from the town next door, the Calgary
Flames. And I, I, you know, by this point I'm in seventh grade. So now my, by sort of my,
I'm watching every minute of every game and studying every statistic, reading my Toronto
star newspaper after, and it's just like, I'm dissecting every detail of this. And I can't
believe what's happening, but all of a sudden it's game seven against the Calgary Flames.
Somehow you guys have each won three games going into the final game, the Northlands Coliseum.
And I remember that night having dinner, getting ready to watch the game and thinking,
trying to paint a glass half full view, which is, well, you know, maybe, maybe, maybe Edmonton just
needs, this was a good little wake up call and maybe they're getting a little too complacent
going into this game. And I've never gone back and watched that game again. So like,
I remember, you know, I watched it in 1986. I've never seen it since. I don't know. Have you ever
seen that game since that you watched it from start to finish? No. So if my memory serves me
correctly, it's two, two in the third period. Is that, I couldn't even tell you exactly what the
score it, I know, I know it was tied late in the game. Yeah. It's tied. It's tied. I think it's
tied one, one or two, two or three, three, but I think it was two, two in the third period.
Steve Smith behind the goal has the puck. He's going cross ice pass a million times a game pass
and it just didn't go in the right place and it hit the back of Grant Fuhrer's leg and in the net
it goes. And you guys are down three to two with less than a period to go. What do you remember
about that moment? Oh, I just remember Calgary building a team that could compete with this,
the Smite division back then was whoever seemed to be able to get out of the Smite division had a
good chance of winning this Stanley Cup. Winnipeg was a great team. Calgary was really amassing a
great bunch of talent and putting a team together that believed they could beat us. And they were
tough all year long. So we knew once we got into that series with them, it was going to be a tough
series. And it didn't surprise us at all that they were playing us every bit as hard and we're
matching us in every bit of the game, both physically and from a talent perspective. And
it got into that series where we knew it was going to be tough to your point where here we are in
game seven and that sports stuff happens. When you're in the middle of it, when something like
that happens, you got to shrug it off pretty quickly. We weren't able to rebound from it and
score a tying goal and end up winning the game. They beat us in that seventh game, but that sports
things happen. There's so much along the way. Yeah. And there's so much about it to me, right?
Like, do you remember in 91 when the Bills went to their first Superbowl and at the very end of
the game, Scott Norwood has to kick this field goal for them to beat the Giants and it misses,
it goes wide. And he's, you know, on some level, this big scapegoat and you sort of imagine, well,
is that how Steve Smith felt? But a really critical analysis of that game of the Giants
versus the Bills says it's really not about Scott Norwood at all. If the Bills had played
half as well in that game as they'd been playing all the way to the Superbowl, they never would
have been in a position where a last second field goal was necessary. And I think that was sort of
my feeling of the whole thing with Steve Smith, which was sure, it would be easy to sit here and
beat this guy up, not you guys as his teammates. I never got the sense, you know, reading the
newspapers that that was happening, but that the public could sort of beat this guy up for the own
goal, as they would call it in soccer. But it was like, look, that was just a symptom of there
were seven games in this series, right? Normally, good bounces, bad bounces over seven game series,
they all equal out. So I would never blame any one incident on winning or losing a seven game series.
You know, that whole game and the whole way it unfolded with Steve is we could do a whole
podcast on the psychology of that alone. It was an amazing time for all of us to, you know, just
look at ourselves and the vulnerability that we all face in a team game and how much you require
everybody to be in the moment and put the work in and trust and all the things that you talk about
in order for a team to win a championship. And it could have been any one of us. And I think the
compassion that everybody felt for Steve even drove our team closer together in some crazy ways.
Again, you know, another tough lesson along the way. But things happen. And that's what we took
out of it is you can take nothing for granted in this game, as good as we were, as much as we
expected to win ourselves as much as everybody else expected us to win. You can never take it
for granted of exactly what's happening here. And so we just collected ourselves again and dusted
ourselves off and came back the next year. Even more determined. And the next year you play the
Flyers again, if I recall, right? Next year exactly. We played with Ron Hextall. Now it's Ron Hextall.
Now it's Ron Hextall. So we play them the next year and we're able to, Wayne was able to accept
the Stanley Cup and the first guy he hands it to is Steve Smith. I mean, that's why sports is so
important in everybody's lives because it transcends sports. It goes much deeper than
sports, especially when you're playing on a team and doing the things that we were doing there.
It wasn't just about hockey. It wasn't just about shooting goals and scoring pucks and all the
things you would think about. It became much more about life and life lessons in order to sustain
that kind of remarkable level of play for the... Did you know Gretzky was going to do that?
Didn't surprise me when he did do it. Wayne was always looking out for people around him, always
had the ability to get outside himself and make sure everybody felt good about being on the team
and part of the team and all the things you would expect from a leader. So it didn't really shock
anybody that he was the first one that he handed the cup to was Steve. I remember that very clearly
and I'm glad you brought it up because I don't think I would have remembered to have brought it
up but I don't know, it just sort of warms your heart. I mean you compare it to the most extreme
grotesque example of the opposite which is 1994, the World Cup. Andreas Escobar scores on his own
goal and he ends up getting killed. I mean he literally is murdered in a parking lot of a bar
and here Steve Smith at least a year later gets to hold the Stanley Cup.
That's part of any human development for him as a person and as a player and what it did for him
and his own confidence and his own self-esteem and his own career. I think you know those are
the things that define you ultimately and stuff happens to everybody but you know he was able to
be strong enough to absorb the criticism that came along his way, strong enough to come back
the next year and go through the process of getting back in that exact same position and
then succeeding ultimately all the way through until we're able to win the Stanley Cup.
I mean that's what defines you not him shooting the puck in our own goal. What defined him was
absorbing that and having the strength to absorb it and the infrastructure around him to help him
absorb it and I think that's what good organizations, good teams do. They help people grow not only as
athletes and hockey players but as people because you need people and you need good character people
in order to win. So if you're just talking about developing athletes and hockey players and trying
to win a Stanley Cup it's just not going to happen. And do you see examples of that either in hockey
today or in other sports then or now where you have all the talent in the world but there's
something lacking in the character of the team? All the time, all the time. You see it all the time.
When we were kids we saw good teams that had infighting amongst each other and jealousy about
who was playing and it just never dawned on us to ever think that way. Let's reflect on that
for a second Mark because the talent on that team was staggering. As we've discussed earlier it
would be very difficult to imagine in a free agency era like we have today where you could
amass that much talent under one jersey. We could amass it but then you couldn't afford it. You
couldn't keep it. Yeah, you couldn't afford it. So again maybe there were stories that you're not
telling but you don't get the sense that this is a team of prima donnas where everybody's sort of
pissed that the other guy is getting more air time and more attention. Well it helps when you have the
the leadership that we had and it helps when you had the character that we had. I mean it's part of
it that Gretzky was so good that everybody was happy to acknowledge that this is our leader and
this is the best player on our team and we're watching history right now. I mean as you said
it was part of it but it was also the way he included everybody and this is crazy and the
stats that he was having he had a way of making Dave Semenko feel like he was the most important
guy on the team and the list that goes on and I think that in the end is really we always talked
about the stage is going to be big enough for us all to stand on. There's not one or two of us are
going to be standing on the stage when we win the Stanley Cup. The stage is big enough for everybody
so let's make everybody feel accountable and let's make everybody feel important and let's hold
everybody accountable for the job that they have and let's help them understand that even though on
another team they may be able to play a different role but in this team this is a role we need you
to play and we need you to do the best of your ability and anything less than 100% isn't going
to cut it and together we are able to help convince everybody that that was the path to success and
we never felt jealous of Wayne. We never felt that he shouldn't be on the ice at the end of the game
when he already had four goals and four assists. We wanted him on the ice. We felt a part of his
success. We felt that we enabled him and put him in position to have the success that he did so in
a crazy way we felt part of the reason why he was able to smash all those records so it was really a
team philosophy that we had that we're all in it together and you're right I mean one year in the
All-Star game we had 11 players off the Edmonton Oilers dressed in the in the All-Star game and you
would think everybody would have been vying for you know Glenn Anderson never once complained
about not being on the first and he was a 50 goal scorer and he couldn't get on the first power play
unit never once did he even think it was a problem. Didn't Paul Coffey almost score 50 goals one year?
He scored 48 goals. I mean a defenseman, unbelievable. He had a hundred and some points I mean it was
yeah so everybody had a role Kevin Lowe was an offensive defenseman he realized right away we
didn't need another Paul Coffey so he worked on becoming the league's best defensive defenseman
and that was where he got his pride of being able to shut the other team down. He knew that that
was our best chance to win as if he and Lee Fogeland could be the go-to guys to to shut it
down late in the games and so he took the pride to do that and everybody on the team did the same
thing. When you look at the way the NHL is today and again we'll talk about the arc of your career
but the league you finished in is very different very different style of play from the league you
started in. Could a team that played the way Edmonton played in the 80s could that type of a
team be successful today in the league? Oh yeah we you know Edmonton was the first I mean Glenn
Sather took the European flavor that had infiltrated into the WHA with all the European
players and all the Swedish players and Anders Hedberg and Alke Nielsen and Bobby Hall and
all these great European players that came over and then the Russians in 72 and the flavor that
we got from that kind of that infiltrated into the WHA and Glenn really realized that that was the
wave the next wave of the way hockey would be played and so when we came into the league in
1979-80 we were all really good skaters and and Glenn allowed us not to play we called it we
should call it tabletop hockey you know those games that you'd play with your hands and the
winger would go up and down but that's all you could go that was traditional NHL hockey and next
thing you know you know the Oilers come in with all the talent and we're all weaving and
going all over the ice and creating havoc for most teams so that style of play is basically
a refined version of what's happening now so to answer your question our style with Edmonton would
have fit perfectly with the way the game is being played now. It's amazing so you've now won it's
sort of July of 1988 you've just won your fourth Stanley Cup in five years when do you first hear
any sort of inkling or rumor about the trade? There was some kind of rumblings towards the end
of the season through the playoffs and you know we didn't think much of it you know how could they
ever trade Wayne Gretzky nobody would even think about it so we didn't really pay too much attention
to it we got wind of it you know normally with the smoke there's fire as they say there was
becoming more talk about it and I was actually in the summertime playing golf and got the word that
the trade had happened and I was this was like August early August was my recollection somewhere
in there who called you I remember being playing golf and stopping at the at the halfway house
and hearing about it on the radio that the trade had gone through nobody could still believe it so
until I got the phone call from Wayne or somebody that then I realized that it actually had come
through. What did you think at that moment I mean you're obviously thinking by this point you've
had now eight years to hone your own leadership skill I mean just listening to the way you talk
about those eight years you can see like I can just hear you describing lesson after lesson after
lesson up and down up and down hard you know hard lessons so on the one hand you still have a job to
do you became the captain of the Oilers that day right basically de facto even if they didn't put
the sea on your jersey until a few months later but it's got to be kind of heartbreaking too I mean
Gretzky was probably your closest friend on that team as well. Well it was devastating for everybody
it was certainly devastating for the players we felt that we were only just beginning of what we
could accomplish we're all in the prime of our careers. That's the part that's so hard to believe
is you guys literally were right at your prime you were not near the crest yet. No we were right
there in the sweet spot so for the players it was devastating for the fans and the people in Edmonton
it was devastating it was just a really tough day for everybody. Did you talk to Peter Pocklington?
No no I never talked to Peter about that there was no need to I mean what was there to say
obviously the feelings everybody had were obvious but to your point when all the dust settled and
the training camp came around you know what were we going to do about it you know we realized that
we had first the responsibility to each other in the room and we had a responsibility to the team
as much as we're disappointed with a decision to do something like that and
and then we added a responsibility to the fans and to the city and so we just like again collected
ourselves again and came to training camp and tried to do the best we could throughout a tough
year. Now in 88-89 I'm blanking who won the cup that year was that Montreal? No Calgary. Oh that's
right that's right that's right Calgary won so another Montreal won in 86. That's right and of
course Montreal would go on to win in 93 after that amazing series with LA but then in 90 you
guys make it back to the finals. Again you're playing the Bruins in the finals in 90. Yeah
we're the Bruins. What does it feel like to go back to the Stanley Cup without Gretzky
and now you're the captain I mean you've always carried the expectations in many way but now this
is the captain didn't change much for me I mean I was already entrenched and most of players on
the team knew me so I didn't really have to change anything. Did you create a narrative like I can
imagine it could very easily spiral out of control psychologically where you think well if we don't
win now it somehow means that all those years we won it was only because of Wayne. I mean did you
did you did anyone even allow that? It was true. It was true one of the reasons why we won all those
cups was because of Wayne but it was because of a lot of other guys too. Well to me that's the
point of 1990 right it's that you want to know how great the Oilers were yeah they're the best team
that probably ever laced up skates and with Wayne Gretzky if you never interrupted that team they
probably would have won nine Stanley Cups. But we didn't look at it as validation of how good we
were weren't as hockey players because we won in 1990 without Wayne. Never even crossed our minds
in fact the opposite in fact we were disappointed Wayne wasn't there to share it with us because of
all the great times we had had with him. So I don't think anybody on the team was looking for
validation that we could or couldn't win without Wayne. I just think when the training camp came
along like every other year you set your sights on winning a Stanley Cup and you go through the
whole journey all year long to win a Stanley Cup and you go through the process of winning a Stanley
Cup because now there's new players on the team and players that hadn't been before in that culture
and so you're trying to establish this culture with new players and you go through the whole
process. When ultimately we we did win in in 90 I don't think anybody felt like all right I will
show everybody that it was it was more that we were proud of the process that we had to go through
with younger players and different players with a lot of the players that have been through
the grind years prior and we were able to elevate ourselves and everybody else in order to make it
happen. So there was never any validation from us that we were able to do without Wayne. It was
we were way past that in my opinion as far as our own careers and our own thoughts of where we were
and where we stood in the game and and how we can look at ourselves as winners and all that kind of
things. It was a great victory don't get me wrong it was an amazing victory to bounce back and win
you can't put it ahead of any other other ones but it was it was just as satisfying to win that
that one as well. When did it start to look like because you your contract with Edmonton was through
what 92 or later maybe even longer right? Yeah I can't remember signing a contract at some point
I can't even remember if I had contract left or I had a couple years left or no I don't even know
I just knew it was over. When did you know it was over when did you know you were leaving Edmonton?
I knew it was over the last year I was there which was 91, 92, 90, 91. Yeah a lot of changes
the team would was breaking up a lot of injuries it just felt different whatever reason we ended
up losing to Minnesota I think you could just tell that. It was back when they were North Stars right?
With yeah yeah yeah you could just tell that that chapter and all our lives was over and it was time
to go do something different in a different place different town and you just know you can just feel
you can't explain it never even tried to figure out why or you know why I felt that way it was
just so evident to me that it was just time to go. Were you keeping this to yourself were you talking
about this with your parents other teammates I mean how were you processing this? No I didn't
it wasn't really that I was talking about it during the regular season because you're so
focusing on trying to win and I had to hurt my leg that year and I missed some time and
I think I'd missed like six weeks with a knee injury and came back early and my knee was never
really that great the rest of the year into the playoffs. When it was over at the end of the year
and we had finally lost we got to the semifinals again which was amazing and it was over when the
final game ended against Minnesota it was it was like the book that someone just took the two
chapters and closed a book and it was over as quickly as that. Did you know where you'd end up?
No idea hadn't even had the conversation with Glenn or anybody hadn't even talked about it with
anybody but had to have that conversation I don't even know when it was with Glenn at some point and
and he was great about it. What's it like to come to New York? Well as I mentioned earlier I was
into a lot of travel and you know I was 30 years old I was looking for a new challenge both
professionally and personally and when you start looking at the choices from where I was
in my own self-development what an amazing. What mattered to you the most in that next chapter?
Lifestyle, opportunity, excitement. Was it I have to win another cup or I want to be part of building a team?
I was 30 years old I was still at the peak of my career I was playing good hockey still yeah no
the hockey wasn't over but I just wanted to do it in a different venue a different environment
something completely different and then you just match it all up and the pin. New York's a
pressure cooker right I mean it's a this is in a sense that you know the Rangers haven't won a cup
since what 50 1950? Well I thought I didn't care about that. Oh 1940 they hadn't won a cup since
1940. Yeah I thought that wasn't a problem because of the pressure that wasn't Edmonton because it's
such a small community and players can't really go anywhere I mean it's really a small community
I loved it I'm from there we embraced it we didn't hide from it we immerse ourselves in with the people
and at restaurants and at bars and at parties and at fundraisers and at charity events and we're
we're part of everybody else we were just we've meshed in just like everybody else those years
in Edmonton so the pressure was always there with us so when I come into New York I didn't think it
would be a big problem I quickly underestimated that impact because of the size and the pressure
here in New York City but it it didn't bother me I mean it was something that I just really wanted
to focus in on. Yeah why do you think because there are some people Mark that just get crushed
in that environment I can only imagine what it would be like to be a professional athlete in New
York where you've got the world watching you right and this is a city that can put more pressure on
you than maybe even the country could like Canada. Well one lesson I learned very early on was from
Wayne when he mentioned something that the everything he has is because of hockey and he
never jeopardized his performance with something that had to do with off the ice so everything off
the ice took a back seat for Wayne. Hockey was his primary focus and so when I came to New York I
realized that I had to take that same philosophy in order to be successful here and because of
the distractions that are obviously abundant in a city like this and so my focus was purely
on hockey and everything else that came along with it would take a secondary role if I was able to do
it and that sustained me well and don't get me wrong we had as much fun as anybody that's ever
played in this city but and for myself personally my main focus was from seven to ten at night
playing that game to be and making sure I was at the best my ability to do it and I think that's
one of the reasons why I was able to perform here with arguably one of the toughest cities to play in
because of the distractions that just made it more fun for me more challenging and all the things
of being able to juggle that and that's kind of the juice that I was looking for as a 30 year old
coming off five Stanley Cups in seven years and feeling pretty good about my own game and and
excited about to live in the city and and try to be a part of a team that conquered
at that time a 50-year drought or a 51-year drought. What was it like when you showed up
for training camp in 92-93? Was it 91-92 I guess your first year? Well I missed training camp
because I didn't get signed till after the training camp had finished I actually met the team
in Montreal when the season was just getting going. And how were you received? Was it just
incredible excitement on the part of the players or was there a bit of trepidation?
I'm probably not the one to ask that but I was excited so I think the players were excited. I
hope they were. I think they were. I remember the Rangers hadn't won in Montreal in a lot of years
and we won to end up winning that game and it just seemed to start unfolding and I think that year
we won the President's Trophy. We missed the playoffs next year and won the Stanley Cup
the third year so I wrote this huge roller coaster of emotions through three years and saw
the great side of New York all the way down to the depths of missing the playoffs and the coach is
getting fired and taking the blame for the whole debacle and then all of a sudden rising up the
third year to winning a Stanley Cup. It was an amazing roller coaster and maybe one of the
reasons why it made the experience so much more powerful is that I was able to see both the good
and the bad of an athlete in New York and it wasn't easy when we didn't play well. Let's start
with the bad. 92-93, you guys don't make the playoffs. What is that like compared to other
pain you can experience as an athlete? For example, the year you guys get swept by the Islanders or
the year you guys lose to the Flames. How does it compare to say you don't make the playoffs?
Well, I think the year that we won the President's Trophy, it gave me enough time to realize the
importance of the Rangers in this community and the generations of fans that have supported this
franchise for so long and so by the second year I was fully aware of the impact that the Rangers
have in this town, in this area and then to go from the disappointing playoffs obviously and
failing again which always seemed to happen to the Rangers but having a great regular season so
that was kind of like a little bit of a trade-off to the next year just not having a good year.
And what do you think was wrong that year? We had injuries, there was a lot of things that
happened that didn't allow us to play as well as we should have and but anyways I got to see the
other side of the city and the pressures that can go against an athlete that's expected to
bring a championship. Luckily I guess I had enough experience to absorb it and articulate it in my
own mind and take the responsibility and then have enough support around me to help get through it
and then make the right decisions obviously the next year in order to allow us to get to the Stanley
Cup. Before you get to the Stanley Cup you got to get through your arch nemesis the New Jersey Devils.
Well we beat the Islanders and the Devils that year so it was a good hockey in this area in the
metro area there so we started off with the Islanders then played Washington in the obviously
the great series against the Devils. Let's talk about that end of that series so you're down three
games to two correct you now have to win the next two games and you make this bold promise right
so you sort of follow in the lineage of Babe Ruth and Joe Namath. Yeah wasn't thinking about that
long at the time. I mean did it occur to you what you were saying and how boldly you were declaring it?
It occurred to me what I was saying because I was trying to as a captain you're always monitoring
your team's confidence level every day not only during the playoffs but every day you walk into
the room your spider senses are up and you're just gauging everybody's emotional state good
better and different in that particular time I was just trying to instill a confidence in the
players and our routine on that day was to kind of get on a bus and go gather on a bus and go to
New Jersey have a pre-game skate in the morning have lunch have a rest and then go back to this
so I knew everybody would be on the bus reading the morning papers because we had done it all
year long so I said well what a great idea to let the guys know that I believe we can win this. I
wasn't even thinking about that it would be splashed across the papers it was only supposed
to be for our 20 guys on the bus. It wasn't supposed to be for 12 million New Yorkers and
certainly the New Jersey Devils but that particular point it didn't really matter to
me I mean you do anything you can to swing the momentum back into your favor and that's what I
was trying to do is instill the confidence that we had displayed all year is that we could go in
there and win game six we had done it numerous times it wasn't like we couldn't do it we had to
figure out a way to play better we had to figure out a way to stop the momentum of the Devils and
that's where the inspiration came from. So going into game seven how do you feel? Well we feel good
we feel good about winning game six we feel good about going home for game seven it's been a
friendly place for us all year long we love playing in front of our home fans there's nothing
not to like about our position going into game seven other than the Devils are a great hockey
team and could play a spoiler very easily which was terrifying we knew in order to win game seven
we were going to have to earn it they weren't going to roll over they felt that they could
win the game just as much as we did and ultimately is one of the best series I've probably ever played
in. Was it game seven that you got the hat trick? Game six. It was game six you got the hat trick to
win the game to come back what was the score of game seven? Two three two two one one go
Matov the greatest the great Matil goal in overtime. Yeah so now you're back in the Stanley Cup finals
before we get to that I want to go back to something you said a moment ago because it
honestly like the way you articulated it I've heard great CEOs say the same thing right which is
the job of a great CEO is to monitor the confidence of the team is to boost morale
is to provide leadership in a meaningful way not just a sort of hollow way I want to kind of
understand how how these things developed in you like when did it become apparent to you
that like what you did mattered more than just how you played on the ice what you said mattered
how you spoke in the locker room mattered like what was the evolution of that from a 17 year old punk
who can't even get to the right airport to the guy who on the eve of game six is calling a shot
heard around the world guaranteeing victory yeah good question I think it really stems back when I
was all the lessons that I had from a father who was a hockey player who was a team player who was
a tough defenseman who protected his teammates and knew the value of a team in every sense for
protection for success for individual accomplishments he really understood what it meant to be a team
player then I'm a stick boy for my brother's junior team when I'm 14 years old actually 12 to 14
and got to see my dad coach and how he treated his players and how he talked to his players and how he
motivated the team and how he brought the team together and how he made everybody feel
comfortable and accountable and important and valued you just see the power of what a team can
do when they are completely synced and linked together without ego and without all the things
that can undermine any team in any sport and then get to a professional level as a young guy just
trying to get my own footing as a professional but still seeing and understanding all the things
that I've learned all along the way and then seeing it play out in different formats and sometimes
positively and sometimes very negatively and so you start to realize that geez some of the things
that you know are actually really good and smart and healthy and productive and this thing and the
way that this is happening is very toxic and detrimental and not good for anybody and so you
just start kind of like I said earlier just start building the confidence of what you're doing not
only as an individual but what you're trying to do as a team and and how you're carrying yourself
on the team and the decisions that you're making for the team as an individual and
and it just starts to come together and then you start to see other players and other great
leaders and hear about other great events and and it just starts to accumulate over time until
you're finally put in the position to have to pull the lever on some of the things that you've
learned at critical times and having the confidence that it's the right thing to do
and and I think you know with any great leader will tell you there that they no great leader is
is mistake free every leader makes mistakes but it's the equity that you've built up into the
people that you are around that will forgive you for making an honest mistake that just didn't
work out well it was a calculated decision it didn't work out but the players or the people
aren't going to abandon you because of that mistake they trust you it was a bad decision didn't work
out but they still trust your vision and and how you can get there and so that's we're kind of all
evolved into some seminal moments in my own career as a captain in the 1990 Stanley Cup run all the
way into through New York until we're able to win the Stanley Cup with a bunch of great character
talented kids here in New York City. You've obviously talked about the role that your dad
had that Wayne had and probably some of the other guys you played with in Edmonton how much of this
was modeled for you by people not on your team were you able to look at opposing players and see
some of these characteristics that would ultimately come to define your leadership? No question both
positively and negatively we would watch other teams and good teams be fighting with each other
on the bench and yelling at each other on the ice as a leader on the opposing team I'm using that as
a galvanizing force for our players to say look at these guys they don't even like each other they
don't even win I'm using every any tool I can to convince our guys that we can win no matter what
it is and so if I see a weak link like that that's gonna we're gonna expose that anything because
it gets down to such small detail when two teams are so evenly matched the smallest things matter
and you're always looking for that little bit of evidence that little bit of self-doubt on the
other team or any kind of pressure cracks that are starting to happen and to use that for your
own team to expose that there's so many things that go along and so you really start as you get older
and you're in a different position of leadership you're looking for to play the game within the
game and that's oftentimes where you know series and Stanley cups are won and lost if you can win
the the war of not only attrition but also the the mental war that goes on against another team
of all the players you played against but never with so I know you played against Gretzky but
let's discount Gretzky and Curry who you played against eventually but because you played with
them but of guys that you only played against who did you respect the most first as a player
but also as a leader and you can think of those separately you know I was looking at looking at
the other day with my son my younger son about there was a wall somewhere of all the names and
I looked at it and I was gonna I played against every one of these players and go and it went
back to some of these guys that were playing in the 60s that were still playing we're still
playing at the end of at the end of their career at the beginning of yours yeah and then to evolve
over four decades so you can imagine the amount of players that I played against and with over
over 26 26 years pro you know just off the top of my head I just had so much respect before I
was just as a kid with Bobby Orr he was my favorite player I loved the way Bobby played I loved
everything about him I loved the way he dressed I loved the way he's he looked in his equipment
so I had a lot of respect for him I had a lot of respect for when did you first meet Bobby Orr by
the way not too much later when I was already a pro I didn't get a chance to meet Bobby as a young
guy at all I got a funny story for you so when I was a kid I had a Bobby Orr signed hockey stick
on my wall and it was like you know one of my prized possessions I had your autograph I had
Gretzky's autograph Curry Fuhrer like I had half the Oilers posters and stuff autographed
and I had this Bobby Orr hockey stick autographed as you know being a good Canadian kid all you're
doing is playing ice hockey and street hockey every day and so sure enough I'm out there one day
and we're playing street hockey after school and I break my stick and I don't have another stick to
play and you know what I did it's like the worst thing I've ever done in my life I go into my
bedroom I take that Bobby Orr stick which is way too big for me I go and get a saw I cut the top
of it off which is the part he'd signed and I go back out and I just start playing with it and all
I've got left is the signed top end of a Bobby Orr stick and my dad comes home and somehow he
had got me this stick you know somehow I mean he wasn't pissed at me but you could just tell he was
sort of like I don't think you're supposed to do that son I mean I was like you know I was probably
like all for the love of the game 10 years old and I just can't to this day I still think I cannot
believe I saw that stick you just said Gila Fleur as well now you did play against Gila Fleur of
course Gila Fleur but I always remember the great series against Boston that rivalry and
when they had to go back to Boston and Mike Milbury said he wouldn't get out of there alive
and the story goes out Gila Fleur was at the Boston Gardens at two in the afternoon in full
equipment smoking cigarettes and went out and scored a hat trick when I heard that story I
said wow because I know what it was like going into the Boston Garden so I can really appreciate
performing under that kind of pressure back then but loved the way he played but there's so many
players that I played against that were ended up being not only great leaders but great players
great people off the ice great in their communities and that's one of the I think the assets of our
game is is really the people not only as players but what they've been able to do off the ice as
well I always felt like Eric Lindros was a player that never fully reached his potential he was just
always getting you know something about his style of play that lent itself to just him getting hurt
too many times yeah it's health and it's not only injuries but just health in so many different ways
and that allow a player to do what you're talking about and have an extended career I think but
Eric played 12 years or when he first came in the league looked like he could play until he was 100
well do you remember before so the year he was playing for the Oshawa Generals and he was going
to get drafted and it was really clear Quebec was going to draft him I mean this was non-negotiable
and he kept signaling guys I'm not playing for Quebec so don't bother drafting me trade me trade
me trade me but they don't but I think Sports Illustrated came out with an article that said
this kid is Lemieux, Gretzky and Messier melded into one and I remember thinking
guys are you freaking kidding me like how much pressure could you put on a kid like
taking the three greatest players in the NHL and telling me that this kid in junior A is going to
be the next him and I grew up in Toronto so a lot of the kids I went to school with actually played
with Eric during like the junior junior like MTHO you know triple A like through probably fourth
grade before Eric really started to leapfrog ahead so you knew he was great there was no question but
I thought that was like that was a bit much pressure to put on a kid I thought yeah I think
so too you know he was, Kour got cut short the fact about the NHL there's a lot of great players
there's a lot of great players and to elevate your self to the likes of Lemieux and Gretzky
those are pretty lofty standards well and as you said there's the longevity thing I mean I still
can't believe you played 25 years like in fact I gotta be honest with you I never had done the math
until I was preparing for us to sit down and talk today like it was really on the last couple of
weeks that I did that actual math because I just didn't realize it was that long in fact I forgot
that Gretzky had played a full 20 years like that just doesn't make sense in a sport like hockey
like that's the exception not the rule you you really and especially the way you played because
you played such a physical game I mean what's the worst injury you've sustained that I got so lucky
um I had both knees ligament stretch MCLs probably four times in each knee I had arthroscopic
surgery on my shoulder towards my second last year how many concussions did you have hard to
count yeah they just don't really keep track of them the same way they keep track multiple
concussions but didn't really keep track and back then you made sure you woke your roommate
up a couple times if you did get a bump in the head make sure he woke up you know we just didn't
know we just didn't have the the knowledge of of what concussions were and the impact that they
had so it was completely different back then what was the hardest part about retiring for me I
didn't really have a hard time retiring if you can believe it just so like I recognize it was kind of
finished in Edmonton I kind of recognize that well it's funny I asked my trainer I said okay
if I train every day am I going to be able at 44 am I going to be able to compete with the younger
guys on that kind of level and he goes no because you're going to need more work to rest yep your
recovery is my recovery is just not there so every time I work out I need three days of rest or
whatever it is and so it's diminishing returns over 82 games but do you ever think like imagine
there's a model I've often thought about this and it's you know you have to change the economics of
the sport but it's like you take a guy like you who's now in his early 40s and you say look we're
going to reduce the amount you're getting paid but you're only going to pay it play every third game
you know could a roster support that because in many ways what you're bringing from a leadership
and an experience and an intelligence standpoint is not going down it's only going up but you just
as you said you don't have the reps in you you can't practice and play with 22 year olds
yeah I personally probably wouldn't have liked that I mean I love playing every day I love being
in the pit I love being in the trenches that wouldn't have worked for me I couldn't have sat
on the bench for two out of every three games I just don't think you have the equity with the
players I think you you you can do that and be a great resource and you can actually play and it
would be for some people but I think to be in a big leadership role I think one of the parts of
being in a leadership role is being is actually got a hurt with everybody example and being in
those tough skates and being those tough it's not the worst philosophy and so I just knew that if
I couldn't do that then what else do I have left to play for I didn't want to play for money I didn't
want to play for anything I didn't care if I was eight games behind Gordie Howe I didn't mean
anything yeah that's that was another stat that I had totally forgotten which was so you retire
as the second leading scorer of all time so you know somehow these two little kids that showed up
from the WHA no I was a I retired as a leading scorer of mere mortals that's why you were the
leading scorer of all time he doesn't count he's way easier so I was the when I retired now I'm
I'm third of the mere mortals that played the game but what's amazing is what you just alluded to
a second ago you were only what eight games behind Gordie Howe for like an air base and play another
year playing I you only eight games behind Gordie Howe I said I never played the game
ever you never played for a record never played for a stat never played for any kind of goal
record any kind of a cis record any kind of a game record I never played for any of that
wasn't even on my radar when I first came in the league I was just trying to make the NHL I never
thought I would even be in a position to hold any record and so I it wasn't even in my DNA as a
player to to even consider something like that and all the things that came along were just by
coincidence of playing a certain amount of time but feeling a part of the of the whole journey
with the team and so just to come back and play on a promotional tour to be Gordie Howe I mean what
was that gonna define me with it didn't mean anything to me that's telling though Mark I mean
I think there are a lot of players who would have come back for another year or half a year or as
you said kind of just the record tour I think a lot of people would and but but I think in some
ways I think the fact that you didn't the fact that you you finish eight games behind one of the
most storied records in sports says more than if you had the record maybe you know I guess that's
for other people to decide for me I you know I was so focusing on being a team player and trying to
win a Stanley Cup every year so that was the only thing that kind of motivated me and finding that
whole chemistry within a different team every year and and it all came in different ways and
different teams were motivated for different reasons but finding that motivating galvanizing
factor every year that we could all rally around was the juice that kept me playing for 25 years
if a young player comes up to you today and says I'm starting my career I mean was there a moment
when you were just so nervous that you you know going into a game or going into a series or going
into a tryout or something and and you actually had to will yourself off the ledge because
obviously stress and anxiety and nerves are a very positive thing I mean you can totally harness
those things but when they go too far they can be crippling do you recall a time when you actually
were on that edge and you had to pull yourself back from the sort of destructive to the
constructive utilization of that force that's that's such a great point and the fear factor
of failure is always evident you know we were terrified of losing in Edmonton all the time as
good as we looked from the outside I can only imagine inside we were terrified of not losing
and probably more terrified of underachieving which is worse than anything is being an underachiever
so how do you get yourself that you're able to be ready enough and relaxed enough to be able to
execute in the most important situations and I think it really gets back to what we talked about
earlier as you know your preparation trusting in the preparation trusting in the evolution of the
team over the course of the season and and repetitive scenarios there that you know you can
do and you can trust yourself and you got trust in your teammates that they're going to be in the
right position because it's this whole choreographed ballet that's happening on the ice at 40 miles an
hour with 24 switch blades traveling 60 miles an hour and dangerous and but everybody's got to be
in the right position at the right time in order to make that cohesive systems work so I've felt
it myself but when you do fail there because you're not always going to play your best when
the chips are on the line you are going to fail you are going to make mistakes you are going to
be the guy that gives a puck away to to lose the game and just being able to be strong enough to
have an unwavering self-belief in who you are and what you're trying to achieve and a lot of that
comes from the preparation and the commitment that you put into the game so there's been a lot of
questionable moments along the 26 years where you doubt yourself and I remember standing on
my first Stanley Cup final along the blue line in Edmonton and being so amped up that
when the anthem finished my whole right side of my eye got blurry and I played about 20 seconds of
the first shift and then went off to the dressing room I had to lay on the training room table for
five minutes in order to just get vision back whatever happened just way too amped up way too
ready to go way too excited and that was a great lesson as well because when I looked over at the
Islanders they were just kind of in a nice groove and a nice relaxed state and so how do you marry
that with too much not enough and that perfect sublime state and then of course a lot of philosophy
and some other things that I worked on in my career from a self-awareness standpoint and things like
that. Say a bit more about that you live a different life than most people can relate to right I mean
most people finish high school get a job or go to college or do whatever but you were sort of
thrust into a limelight from from a very young age you had to make a bunch of mistakes in front of
a bunch of people and and before you know it you're you're sort of 44 years old or whatever you were
at 43 when you retired I want to talk a little bit more about retirement and the next phase of your
life but I want to know a little bit about how you like what kind of introspection and self-reflection
were you able to do as an athlete or was that mostly something that came after? No I think it
was an evolution all the way through I became curious why to start with why Wayne was the best
hockey player in the world and so I started watching him I started watching him in practice
and his practice habits and what he did in practice to become a better player and how he
was able to saucer the puck on his forehand and backhand and where he would go in certain
situations and all that and then I so if you're curious enough there's a lot of answers out there
how to become a better player both physically and emotionally and tactically and all the things
that you would think because you don't rep your the way you represent yourself you're just an
average guy right like you're not a guy that had this god-given gift now of course you obviously
have great natural athletic talent but you're this guy who as you tell the story no one could have
predicted on your first day in the NHL you are going to be the second leading score of all time
or the first amongst mortals whereas in the case of Gretzky if someone said that on day one it was
believable it was more evidence and that's why it's so amazing that you are patient with and
there's certain things that you look for in athletes about any sport not necessarily when
they're younger but in how they can change and evolve so there would have been no evidence up
until I even turned pro that that would have happened so I think that yes you are given
god-given talent it has to be nurtured and and honed and then you have to be willing to
absorb a lot of information in order to become a good pro and a good teammate and then you know
how do you elevate your own game from a fourth line fighter to a second line left winger to a
second line centerman to a first line centerman through the course of a career right like but yeah
so I think curiosity won and I felt that there was a way that I didn't believe in the zone
say more about that I didn't believe in that it was just by chance that a guy would have a good
game you would hear these people talking about wow it's really in the zone tonight I don't know why
I don't know what happened couldn't feel my legs I could skate all day never got tired the goal
looked like a soccer net you know didn't feel like anybody else's on you know you never once
felt that I felt it but I didn't think it was just because it just was you didn't think it was just
a chance you think that's something happened along the way in order for that to manifest itself at
that particular time so I started asking questions about you know okay well what is that I mean what
there's a there's a bigger so what is your take what is your take well I think it's a level of
concentration that doesn't get discovered you know it's a whole nother that's another whole
nother podcast but I just think it's a it's a deep level of concentration that you're not even aware
of that's mixed with preparation that's mixed with belief that's mixed with repetition of the skill
all that comes together at a certain time and I think that in to just very quickly I just think
that in a in a professional world there's a lot of external things that go on outside the game
that can be conflicting and be distracting and take away energies from you not only physically
but also emotionally and if you in a perfect world you have everything in your personal life
in complete order you have one thing to think about on a big game like a game seven or whatever it is
so when you guys were like literally these 23 year old kids in this town called Edmonton
do you think you were able to take it more seriously as a combination of things one
it's not New York City right so you're not or Montreal or Toronto where the pressure is
unbelievable it was unbelievable in Edmonton too but almost a result of how well you how much
potential you guys brought to it and then secondly you have this thing around Gretzky
which is you all figure out very quickly you are in the presence of greatness and this is a once
in a lifetime opportunity you're a piece of history in many ways do you think that somehow that all
galvanized to produce this environment you're describing which is you could focus so much on
your on honing your craft at a time when it could have been easy to have put 80 percent of that
effort in but 20 percent of that could have been put elsewhere I think again it doesn't just happen
overnight I think this is something that if you're interested in it takes a long time to get there
and I think that there are a lot of questions that need to be answered along the way of anyone's
career you know why am I here what am I here for you know what are my intentions what is the end
game how am I being perceived by my teammates how is the sporting hockey world perceive me
what am I doing off the ice to be a good citizen what am I doing to contribute to the community
that doesn't happen when you're 18 years old that doesn't happen when you're 20 years old
that happens over a duration of period as you evolve as a person so for me when I came to New
York I was 30 years old and I had a lot of time for introspection to think about you know what I was
needed to do in order to be successful as a player and all that maybe if I came here at 22 it wouldn't
have been the same result because I wasn't ready for it or mature enough to handle the external
things around the city who knows I just look at it it's it's an evolution of anyone's I think that
the sport has to mirror the maturity of anyone's and if those two things kind of keep going on a
parallel track then you get into players like Tom Brady and players that are redefining their sport
and doing things that are considered unattainable whether you're playing into your 40s and
still you know you're you know as quarterback you know I'm just using him as yeah sure but I think
if you asked him his own trajectory of when he first came out and got thrown in well I think
there's something else about I don't know Tom Brady but I would infer from the outside that
there's something about Tom that's very similar to what you said earlier which is I don't get the
impression he's playing for another Super Bowl ring of course he wants to win another Super Bowl
ring but that's not the reason he's playing I get the sense he's playing because he believes he can
continue to perfect his craft and I and I suspect that that's what the greatest winning is the end
and that result it's the way you can measure that it's the way you can measure it and of course
you know every time you come to training camp you want to win but I don't think you can just say you
want to win I think there's certain things especially at his age that he needs to do in
order to be put himself in position to be efficient enough at that position in order to
take his team to another and so I think that's where that whole thing I'm talking about where
where sport and life finally come together at a certain age and they parallel the tracks where
you become more evolved as a person which only helps you in your sport because you have a better
understanding of who you are as a person and all the things that are it takes to be successful
from a physical standpoint and the training and then the involvement of the knowledge of the game
and the experiences that you had so it's it's quite remarkable and it's one of the things that
I'm sure he would tell you because I can say for myself is one of the things that keeps you in the
game at that later stage of the year is is honing that walking on that razor's edge
that very few people have done and to try to do something that has never been done before
you look like you're still in great shape what do you do today for exercise how do you stay in shape
a little bit of everything obviously weightlifting is important cardio and I can get cardio from many
different I was never a runner but I ran the New York City Marathon back I guess 2011 10 year
anniversary of 9-11 are you deliberate about it or sometimes professional athletes when they're done
they're done with structure they've spent their whole lives being very structured in doing this
doing this being here at this time being in this training camp being you know eating this way doing
this doing that and then when they're done it's like look I'm gonna work out but I don't want to
program I just want to do what I feel like doing I mean where are you sort of on that spectrum
yeah I'd say that shortly after I retired I was doing some other stuff and I I kept waiting for
that because I used to give myself three hours to work out when I was training you know it'd take
me a minute to get in the gym and it'd take me you know 10-15 minutes to get myself with a deep
enough concentration to be able to actually put the work into that I wouldn't that would need I
didn't need three hours to actually physically work out but I to get myself mentally ready to
work out and then when I retired I kept waiting for that three-hour window to come along and
never came along never came along because of the kids and all that kind of stuff so I'm kind of
pretty loose about what I did find though is that I feel better when I work out I physically feel
more awake I feel more alive I feel more energized more energy fresher and I guess it's a probably
net result of doing it for so many years that your body just becomes accustomed to it and you feel
sharper so you know when I did retire I wouldn't work out all the time and it became apparent to
me that I actually feel better when I when I get some kind of work in it doesn't have to be anything
like I did when I was in the three hours in the gym and all that but if it's a 20-minute cardio
or if it's a anything a yoga session or so I'm kind of resigned to the fact that if anybody's
doing anything I'll kind of jump in on it and try it and obviously got a little bit of a routine to
three four days a week but I'll try anything do anything and just to kind of keep the body
moving how often do you get back on skates playing some charity events every once in a while I'm on
the ice quite a bit because I coach my son's team so I'm on the ice I use actually a friend's
rink up in wire mill Paul Orland the great guy he's got a little private rink there so I go there
and just do some cardio you'll just get out there and skate I'll just get up there and just do
skating exercises because it's just so good for your core and for your
and you don't have the impact and you don't have the impact of running and all that and so it's
just and it's just so much development of your core and your legs and all that so keep that strong
how fast can you skate relative to your 28 year old self what percent well what you realize is that
you have such massive leg power when you're playing and when you stop that atrophy is pretty
quickly so if I had to say put a percentage on it yeah like I'm curious as to how far you would
fall in 20 years I would say I have 10 percent of what I had wait wait 10 percent less no overall
you're that far from where you were 20 years ago I would I would say so but my guess is if you
can't so I'm still in good shape I can still skate but if you get back on the ice with a bunch of
40 year old dudes I bet you skate circles around them right depends on what you're skating I mean
if I if I took six months and skated and started to develop some of the muscles that you really
need to skate and for your edging and all that yeah maybe but you know I'm 58 so you know it's
just atrophy unless you skate every day those muscles atrophy you know your growings and your
hip flexors and your quads and ham I mean that whole muscle group of of your legs and so that's
just straight away speed skating around circles what about the ability to change direction is
that even more lost is that even a loss because you instantly become fatigued because you don't
have the muscle part of their source it's just it's amazing actually in fact it wasn't it was
about two years after I retired and I put my equipment on to do something and it felt like I
didn't have my I felt like I felt like you were wearing someone else's equipment because my legs
were about twice the size and my pants fit different and all of a sudden my legs were in
the pants that I had retired with and it felt like they were just swimming on me just because
of the atrophy what do you weigh now weigh about 215 which is not that far from what you play
I played right there at 215 or so just distributed you think it's just distributed differently yeah
you just don't have the muscle mass you lose muscle mass just because of age but you also
you lose muscle if you're not using it well I mean you can't just admit it's amazing how much power
it takes to play hockey from a leg standpoint and a cardiovascular standpoint it's incredible and
you know when you do it from the time you're a young boy to the time you're 40 something and
you retire you don't even think about it because it's all you've known get on the ice and not even
think about it what does your son think about hockey the one that you coach he's how old well
lines 30 the older boy is 32 and he's coaches he loves hockey he's made a career of coaching kids
and up in Washington the little caps uh douglas loves hockey he's 16 playing midget hockey and
that's the one you coach yeah yeah does he want to play pro I think you would love to play pro
is it hard how do you feel about letting him be his own guy oh I think he needs completely needs
to go on that journey of self-exploration to see what he can extract from himself does he ask you
about it oh we talk often about hockey I think he knows what's required even before whether or not
you have the talent it's an interesting journey for him to see where he can take it ultimately
that'll be defined by him and not by me it's got to be interesting it's got to be a mixed bag of
emotions for you to watch your watch your kids play this game and know that I you know I know
enough about you to know that all you really care about is you just want your kids to be happy you
want your kids to sort of find their own way and you want to stay out of their way enough but also
be there enough to answer a question and support I mean it's just I think it's just harder when your
dad is mark messier to no balance I mean your dad was such an important part of your development
is it sort of like you want to be able to provide exactly what your dad did no more no less is that
sort of how you think about question being the son of any professional player and any sport is going
to come with some baggage for the kids whether they feel it as they're expected to be a great
player because their dad was and and all the things that go along with it ultimately the
reason why sports in my opinion is such a great thing for all kids is that it does take you on
that self journey of self-awareness and what you want to do and are you able to do and are you able
to put the discipline in and the time in and that's required to be the best you can be it doesn't
matter how good everybody else is what do you have and are you willing to extract every ounce of
talent and work out of your own body that ultimately no matter how far you take it
will serve you well in wherever you land whether it's in a sport or in business or whatever that
kind of journey can only be beneficial for for all kids and certainly for for my kids as well
and i think there's something else about team sports which is all the stuff you've alluded to
around this type of leadership and the difference between you know i always love that movie miracle
because i thought it did such a great job of showing how at an individual level that team
was not nearly as talented as the soviets right but on that one moment in that tournament
everything that they had done under her brooks sort of came together and they outplayed the
best team on you know in the world as a team not as a collection of individuals and so much of what
you talk about is really you've repeatedly emphasized this importance of both leadership
and team play and the dynamics of the team and again i think you've you've paid a lot of that
tribute both to your dad and to Gretzky as being two great role models of that and many more but
yeah there's there's a lot of information out there for for any young aspiring sportsman
sportswoman girl boy no matter what their dance music acting hockey baseball football whatever
it is if you're interested there's a lot to learn if you're interested tell me about the
mark messier foundation what do you guys do well when i first came to new york it was really
important for me to entrench myself into the community the first charity i ever got involved
with was the alberta lung association when i first became a pro in in emilton and glenn saether our
coach there really kind of emphasized that we'd get out into the community and pick a charity and
attach your name to it and help the alberta lung association was an incredible learning experience
for me because it was all about the babies that were born premature and had unhealthy lungs and
whatnot fast forward to coming to new york the inundation of requests to get involved with some
kind of charity in the city was overwhelming so i had to figure out a charity to involve myself
with and then help out as much as i could everywhere else and that became the tomorrow's
children's fund at the hackensack medical university and years after retirement it became
the parent that i could start my own foundation and really kind of focus in on the things that
inspired me the most and that was giving back to in providing access and opportunity to kids that
didn't have the means to do it like hockey in the city so the mark mister foundation is basically
that it's about creating access and opportunity in different areas of kids lives or that they
would never have had the opportunity otherwise and for different circumstances whether it was
financial or infrastructure not available or school plastics or whatever and so that's what
it focused on and it spun out of the kingsbridge national ice project that we're trying to build
here in the city that that would provide a lot more access and opportunities of kids to play
hockey in the metropolitan area here with three nhl teams you you would think we could do a better
job of creating more access for kids to play a sport that's so much entrenched into this metropolitan
area it's hard to imagine you not living here isn't it you have so many tentacles in this in
this new york area business-wise philanthropy wise family-wise which is again i think it's
for me i always think of you as being from edmonton which of course you are from
but you've probably lived almost as much of your life here as you have there right yeah well that's
close i came here when i was just 30 and i'm 58 now so it's been a you know i remember my first
press conference saying i hope my second career is this is good as my first we weren't able to
quite win as many championships here in new york but we were able to win the one but my experience
here in new york has been incredible i think the thing that really drew me to come to new york was
not only the challenge of breaking the 54 year old drought of the stanley cup but also immersing
myself into a city of this magnitude and and the culture and all the things that go along with it
that was very appealing to me and it didn't disappoint me in any way i've can't tell you how
much i've enjoyed my time as a player in retirement in this area and the people and the amount of
experiences i've had with so many different types of people in the city it's interesting i mean the
last thing i really want to talk about mark is this idea where there just seem to be two types
of athletes there are those who retire who can never sort of get over the fact that they're not
still 28 years old and that their glory is no longer going to be wed to that and then there
are another group of athletes who retire and move on and continue to like live life to the fullest
with respect to whatever the next chapters of their lives fit and you're obviously in the
latter category i mean you know we could have in a whole other podcast talking about what you're
doing in business today and all the things you're doing outside of hockey do you have a sense of why
you're able to make that transition and when it was time to say goodbye you said goodbye
and you know your identity doesn't have to be wrapped up in that and why others have such a
difficult time doing that what do you think defines that difference i think you just nailed it i think
to put it very quickly i think the thing is i didn't identify myself only as a hockey player
i think that in order and for me to be able to do that i needed a good family around me and good
people around you to remind you that there's a lot more to life than hockey although it's a huge part
of my life from the time i was you know very young to the time i turned pro and is one of the things
that i had to really focus in on when i was 18 because it requires all your attention to perform
at your highest level but it wasn't who i was as a person big difference and i think with good
people around you to remind you of what's possible outside the game you eventually realize that you
do something that you love and it's the most amazing time of your life but it's not going
to define you in the end and i think those two things became very apparent to me you know sometime
in the middle of my career where there's just more to this than playing hockey
and that's where it became so apparent that you are an important part of any community that you
play in and there are the things that are going on and the way you conduct yourself and how you
give back and all the things that are so important to a to a professional athlete in order for him to
do and i think those are things that really kind of separate you from the player and so when it's
time to retire yeah i sure i miss the game i love playing hockey there's nothing better than playing
hockey and being a part of a team but i was able to walk away because i had a new family and there
was more to do in life in a different way that alleviates that need to go to the rink every day
and have your ego boosted because of your playing on a professional hockey team so i think that kind
of really made it easy for me to retire and to kind of go on to the next phase of my life when
at 40 some years old now look at if i was 25 years old and forced to retire because of
injury or something that would have been tough to retire i no question no question so i'm only
speaking for myself that i was i fulfilled everything you know for you know 26 years pro
44 a young family in my own mind was there anything left to prove do you know from a hockey
standpoint no was there is there a lot more to prove from a philanthropic standpoint there's
a lot more it's amazing mark do you still keep in touch with any of the guys from edmonton i uh
everybody everybody yeah we just had another reunion in edmonton not long ago we had one here
in new york and what's amazing about uh the city is that everybody seems to come through here at
one point during the year so being able to stay connected to a large portion of the guys on a
fairly regular basis is is quite easy i would love to be a fly on the wall for one of those
reunions literally just sitting up there in a raft or watching like the greatest hockey team
that ever laced up reminiscing about gosh what it's been now 30 to 35 years ago the 85 team was
voted the top team in the last hundred years and so we had a reunion for that team in edmonton not
long ago and it was remarkable actually to get that team together and see everybody that some
of the guys i hadn't seen a lot of the guys i had but just to be able to get to to your point
to get to get to the room and and everybody uh sat in exact same seats on the bus on the way to the
rink and it was it was just did you guys get on the ice and skate we never did that would have been
we should have done that actually we should have had some kind of yeah just some came
a game a quick pickup or something like that we should have been with both andy and grant there
you had two goalies oh yeah oh the whole team was there unbelievable it was amazing actually we
should have done that i'll remember that for the next one you know i i got to meet ronnie lot
recently who was one of my favorite football players ever growing up and we were you know
after we're shooting the breeze for a bit i said you know do you guys ever get together and play
a game of pickup football you and montana rice and everybody goes yeah yeah we did it actually
kind of recently and i said what was it like and he goes it was awful i mean i hurt for like three
days after he's like you know jerry was the only one who was really really in still in amazing
shape which of course if you look at ronnie lot by the way he looks just like you he is exact same
weight that he played at so it's not like this guy got out of shape but he's like look jerry was still
sort of you know really in shape but but it's the same idea like to get that 49ers team of the 80s
together and the oilers of the 80s i mean i don't know there's something there's something very
special about those uh well i think it is i think the connection is so strong because you have such
a deep respect for what you did together and the commitment that each individual put
forwards towards the common goal i think that's where the uh gratitude comes in do you think that
it's just impossible to ever reproduce that again in the sense that like has money changed that i
mean back in the 80s you guys just didn't get paid a fraction of what players get today do you think
that has changed the game in order to win you in order to win you got to get there somehow or
another the team has a shorter window to do it to bring it all together but they have to get there
on an emotional level in order to win st louis did this year you know you look at them
just before christmas they weren't even into playoffs yeah kind of an amazing turnaround
amazing turnaround but somehow or another they were able to emotionally connect on a much deeper
level than they had ever in the past and it's without that so yeah i think the principles of
winning are the same you got a much shorter window to do it it comes and goes for some
organizations where they don't quite get there but any team that actually wins will tell you there
that the team connected in a way that they didn't probably feel possible at some point prior
notwithstanding that your kids are still at a point where you don't want to be away from home
but fast forward a few years your kids are all in college or doing their own thing
would you want to coach in the nhl it's hard to say i obviously feel like i have a lot to offer
any organization any team because of my experiences that would lend itself well to any part of the
organization coaching is something that i enjoy and i don't think there's a big difference
philosophy speaking coaching a 16 year old team than coaching an nhl team because you do have to
communicate the bench awareness the things that come have to come naturally to some of the coaches
and it doesn't come naturally to everybody it just doesn't i recognize that i do have a
unique ability to coach and i think i get it from my father and to communicate so it'll be
interesting and see if that ever happens one day and last question sort of out of your purview but
will toronto ever win the stand like that i'm asking seriously i do i do think so
you know the toughest part about our game is it's such a tough league
but the good news is that you can see a team like st louis bring it together in a short period of
time i mean they obviously had the pieces they couldn't have won if they didn't have the pieces
in order to do it but somehow or another they are able to galvanize which in a way that they hadn't
previously and so when you look at the turnarounds of teams that have gone on to to win the stand
like up in the last 10 years you know you look at la you know when it's finishing eighth and
winning the stand like up the league is structured now that every team has weaknesses there's no
perfect team out there right now every team has to decide where they're going to put their strengths
and and absorb the weaknesses because of the salary cap era and what it does is it lends itself to a
very competitive environment where it's a tough league and but it also gives a lot of teams a lot
of hope that it can win and i think it's good for the fans it's good for the league it's good for
the players it's good for the organizations it's going to be hard for someone to dominate
perhaps like we did in the 80s or something like that but to answer your question i believe uh
does the toronto may believe they're gonna with the nucleus they have there right now they should
be able to get it done and it's now probably longer than the rangers drought because wasn't
the leafs last cup in 67 67 so uh what are we working on now yeah so you're that's long that's
that's actually that is now longer than the rangers four years is a long time well long long
long time but i love the leafs no i guess it's not quite there yet another couple years but
i think it's funny growing up in toronto i never liked the leaves because i just think this sort
of that harold ballard era was so bad and i mean we would go to the gardens but you were going to
watch the other teams that were coming i mean every time the oilers played including exhibition
games i was sitting up in those crappy gray seats to watch a game but now i'm always amazed when i'm
back in toronto just what an ordeal it is to get to the air canada center to see a game i mean it's
got to be one of the toughest towns to get tickets well i just know coming to new york an original
six team and the passion behind the generations of fans that were here it didn't take me long to
understand the gravity of it and if you and then when i when i say i love the leaves i love the
leaves because of that same yeah yeah original six teams are just in a different league the history
the passion the heartbreak all the things that go into an organization that make it so compelling
to go to the game and to cheer the Leafs on if you're a leaf fan and even if you're not a leaf
fan you still got to respect where they've been and where they've come from and and the way the
organization has moved into the modern era and this juggernaut organization that is just
so compelling well if they win this year i've done the math now it'll be 53 years if they win this
year so they've got one they've got two years left well i'd say 54 is a long a long time but
they're working on it so hopefully they can get it done sooner or later it'd be nice to see a
canadian team get in there but oh yeah for sure it's the it won't be i can guarantee it won't be
given to him mark this has been awesome thank you so much for all these insights you know the first
time we met i remember you never know when you're a kid you know you meet you meet your
boyhood heroes you sort of you just never know like can they live up to the poster on your wall
can they live up to that time you got that autograph then you got to stand in front of
them for 3.7 seconds while they scribbled something on your hockey stick or whatever
it's been a pleasure getting to know you and i think that this podcast i think is just hopefully
a great way for folks to get to really understand your style of leadership which is certainly not
about boasting but about just sort of a quiet passionate yet highly intuitive and introspective
form of leadership that i i don't know i guess i'm biased but i don't think we see a lot of that in
sports anymore if nothing else i'm i'm highly appreciative of it and i know that others will
be also well thank you great being on great talking hockey as always and uh we'll be watching those
leaves all right let's go get some dinner you can find all of this information and more at
peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast there you'll find the show notes readings and links related to
this episode you can also find my blog at peteratiamd.com maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign
up for my subjectively non-lame once a week email where i'll update you on what i've been up to the
most interesting papers i've read and all things related to longevity science performance sleep etc
on social you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id peteratiamd but
usually twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments now for the
obligatory disclaimer this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health care services including
the givings of medical advice and note no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this
information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk the content
of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or
treatment users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition
they have and should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions
lastly and perhaps most importantly i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures the companies i invest in and or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash
about