Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast. If you're listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things
I care most about professionally are how to live longer and how to live better. I have
a complete fascination and obsession with this topic. I practice it professionally and
I've seen firsthand how access to information is basically all people need to make better
decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating and sharing this knowledge
is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to me. The sheer
volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a great
team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one example,
our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a
natural question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As
you probably know, the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot
of contemplation, that model just doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now, the
first and most important of these is trust. I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm
telling you about something when you know I'm being paid by the company that makes it
to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to me is because I
just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not absolutely
nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others
have proved can work over time, and that is to create a subscriber model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm
doing, you can become a member. In exchange, you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's
available for free. It's that simple. It's my goal to ensure that no matter what level
you choose to support us at, you will get back more than you give. So for example, members
will receive full access to the exclusive show notes, including other things that we
plan to build upon. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical
nature of many of our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate
in the regular Ask Me Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA
portal and also getting to hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something
I'm really excited about, I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products
that I love. And as I said, we're not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd
like to do is work with companies who make the products that I already love and would
already talk about for free and have them pass savings on to you. Again, the podcast
will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will find enough value in one,
the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members. I want to thank
you for taking a moment to listen to this. If you learn from and find value in the content
I produce, please consider supporting us directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My
guest this week is Dr. Bill Harris. Bill is an internationally recognized expert on omega-3 fatty
acids and how they can benefit patients across a broad range of medical conditions, but particularly
with attention to heart disease. He's a professor in the Department of Medicine at the Sanford
School of Medicine in the University of South Dakota. He's also the president and CEO of Omega
Quant, which is a company he started about 10 years ago that we spent a little bit of time at
the very end talking about. Again, the caveat being of course he does have a vested interest
and therefore conflict with respect to involvement of his company. I can say I've known Bill for 10
years and I know people who have known Bill for much longer than that. His reputation amongst his
peers is really someone who is a very honest broker of the science. He's been the recipient
of five NIH grants for the study of the effect of omega-3 fatty acids, particularly EPA-DHA. On
human health, he's published over 300 papers on the topic and we discuss just a couple of those
here, some of the really interesting ones. He was also the author on two of the American Heart
Association scientific statements on fatty acids. He earned his PhD in human nutrition from the
University of Minnesota and did a postdoc in clinical nutrition and lipid metabolism with
Bill O'Connor at Oregon Health Sciences. I was introduced to Bill, like I said, probably nine
years ago from Tom Dayspring. This was around the time that I was really searching for insight
around the polyunsaturated fats and in particular EPA and DHA. Since that time, Bill has been a very
generous, generous mentor to me with respect to just one of those guys. You send him an email with
a simple question and he responds with a very thoughtful, 600 word response that contains more
insight than anything I could have drummed up. We talk about mostly the landscape of polyunsaturated
fats here, but this is a great episode. You don't have to know anything going into this episode when
it comes to fats. We're going to explain what saturated fats are, monounsaturated fats, polyunsaturated
fats, omega-3s, omega-6s. You're going to come out of this and have a better understanding of this
topic than if you went to med school and took a course in this subject matter. I think I'm just
going to leave it at that. The show notes will be very helpful for this episode because some of this
stuff, it really makes sense to be able to look at a diagram as we go through it. Then of course,
as usual for subject matter like this, we're going to go heavily into studies, so you'll want to be
able to reference those studies and see that. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation
with Bill Harris. Bill, thank you so much for making the time to talk about a subject matter
that I think is incredibly confusing and incredibly important. That intersection of things that are
confusing and things that are important tends to be very important and sometimes overlooked
intersection in medicine. So with that, I want to thank you for making the time.
Yeah, my pleasure.
How long have you been the guru of this? I mean, for the listener in the background,
I'd give a little bit of your background, but I was introduced to you in I think 2011 from Tom
Dayspring, who basically said anytime I had a question that had to do with anything around
fatty acids, you were the guy to ask. And over the past eight years, you've steadfastly answered
more questions than I can count. Tell me a little bit about how you got to be the guy that knows so
much about this. Just hanging around a long time. So I got my PhD in nutrition in 1978,
and I went to work with Bill Connor in Portland, Oregon for my postdoc. His first assignment for
me was to study the question of what does the effect of salmon oil on cholesterol levels?
Because we were very familiar with the effects of vegetable oil on cholesterol and animal fat,
saturated fat, but we really didn't know what a fish oil would do to cholesterol. So my first
really metabolic ward study I organized, recruited subjects, did the protocol, and we fed people
huge amounts of salmon oil, basically all of the fat in the diet. So people were eating salmon
steaks twice a day. And this was a 28 day inpatient feeding. Well, actually, it was outpatient feeding,
but metabolic ward. And beyond the salmon steaks, they were drinking about 100 milliliters a day of
salmon oil to strengthen it straight. And so it was a huge load, 25 grams of EPA DHA per day. And
we found that the omega-3's lowered, well, actually salmon oil did lower cholesterol relative to the
saturated fat diet. And it was about the same lowering as we saw with the vegetable oil diet.
But the thing that was unique about salmon oil was that it lowered triglyceride levels. And
nobody had known that at that time. So we published our first paper on that 1980. That's
really coincident with the time that the Greenland Eskimo studies were finally becoming well known
from Iraberg and Bang. And the omega-3's had been sort of discovered in the sense at that time.
And so we started chasing omega-3 effects on lipids and platelet function and all kinds of
other things. And so I've just been able to stay with it. I've had five grants from the NIH to
study omega-3 related questions. And so just again, it's been a field that's continued to be
fascinating and ups and downs, but enriching. And as you said, it's confusing right now. It's been
confusing for most of its history. That's kind of an amazing story. And I want to come back to that
study because it's possible the listener right now doesn't understand the context of what 25
grams of EPA would mean. But that's a dose of a type of fat we're going to talk about when we get
into the nomenclature that is almost unprecedented. And I already have a dozen questions for you about
that exact study. And were there any side effects such as bleeding noses and anti-anabolic effects,
all these things, but I'll refrain from going down that path to instead make sure we can get
everybody on the same playing field. So I'm going to start and give a little bit of a framework,
but I'm going to very quickly hand the baton over to you to get into the weeds on this a little bit.
So obviously fat is one of the four or five, depending on how you look at it, macronutrients,
right? So fats, proteins, carbohydrates, ketones, alcohol. And I think most people know that fats
come in different chemical families. So you've already alluded to one of them called a saturated
fat. And then everybody's probably heard of a mono unsaturated fat. And then there are these
things called polyunsaturated fats, which then get further divided into these omega
threes and sixes typically, but there are others. Do you want to say a few words about what separates
a saturated fat from a mono unsaturated fat from a polyunsaturated fat, and then how we further
subdivide those polyunsaturated into the omega threes and sixes? And I guess if you can answer
the question, Bill, not just through the chemical explanation, though I'd like you to provide that,
but also through some of the examples and characteristics of each of them so that
folks have a sense of what we're talking about. From a chemical structure point of view,
a saturated fatty acid is a long single chain of carbon atoms all hooked together.
And there are what we call single bonds between each carbon atom. In chemistry, you can have
single bonds, you can have double bonds, you can have triple bonds. But in a saturated fatty acid
or a saturated fat like lard or butter, any of those saturated fats have the vast majority of
fatty acids that make up those fats are saturated, meaning they have long single chain. And they're
solid at room temperature. I think that's the most common characteristics. The simplest way to detect
a saturated fat is at normal room temperature, they're solid. Mono unsaturated fat fatty acids
are the next class and these have the same long carbon chain. It can be 12, 14, 16, 18 carbons long.
And there's one double bond in a mono unsaturated fatty acid. So when there's a double bond in a
molecule, it now has a point of unsaturation. And why they pick that nomenclature is not worth
talking about the moment, but that's what that means. The classic oil that is rich in mono
unsaturated fatty acids would be olive oil and canola oil now too. Those are both very rich in
mono unsaturated fatty acids. They are liquid at room temperature, but you put them in the
refrigerator and they'll get hard. That's kind of a way of telling a mono unsaturated rich oil. If
it's out at room temperature, it'll be liquid in the fridge overnight, it'll get solid or certainly
get very cloudy. The pollen saturates the next group, it's really instead of one double bond,
now we have two or more double bonds and that's the poly. So again, the same long carbon chain
with now two or three typically. Actually in foods, all you really find is two double bonds.
The oils that contain poly unsaturated fatty acids are liquid at room temperature and they're
typically liquid in the refrigerator too. You have to put them in a freezer to get them to get solid
or to get cloudy. Even some fish oils will not get solid even in a freezer. The polyunsaturated
fatty acids are, again, they are what you find in oils. We say fats in oils. When we say fats,
we're usually talking about things that are solid at room temperature. Oils, we're talking about
things that are liquid at room temperature. And again, the oils are going to be mono or polyunsaturated
rich and the fats be saturated fat rich. Again, in the polyunsaturated fat world,
we have two families, two major families. It's called omega six and omega three.
And they're called omega because when chemists start first started naming chemicals, naming
fatty acids when they were discovering the structure of them, there was the beginning and
the end of the molecule and the way they designated what was the beginning of the molecule, they call
that was the alpha carbon, the first carbon. And the last carbon in the molecule was always the
omega carbon taking from the Greek alphabet, the alpha and the omega, the beginning and the end.
So the omega carbon was at the end. If you have an omega six fatty acid, it's actually said omega
minus six means that if you count back six positions from the omega or final carbon,
you get the first double bond in the molecule. And that's specific for all the fatty acids that
are omega six family, they all have that characteristic. First double bond, six
counting back from the omega or final carbon and the omega three fatty acids all have the first
double bond in the third position. And that sounds like it really shouldn't, you know, so what,
but actually chemically, it makes quite a bit of difference in the physical properties of the oils,
as well as the other molecules or metabolites that these fatty acids are converted into by
enzymes in the body. So that's the omega six omega three family fish oils are the ones that contain
omega three, predominantly vegetable oils, safflower oil, corn oil, sunflower oil are rich in the omega
six fatty acids. It would have taken me an hour to have tried to explain that Bill, and it would
have been half as clear. So thank you for that. The thing that's always amazed me is how many
different pieces of information can be conveyed in the nomenclature of fatty acids because
you're dealing with the extent or degree of saturation anywhere from fully saturated to
not as mono and poly. You then have the actual number of carbons in the molecule. And then you
have the position of that first double bond in the case of the monos and the polys. So even for
someone who's taken a course in organic chemistry, like it still requires a little bit of thought
when you're looking at detailed chemical drawings of these things. And I suspect that represents at
least some fraction of the challenge that people have when talking about this is we tend to distance
ourselves from what we're talking about because of the confusion. But as you point out, it sounds
like it shouldn't make that much of a difference, right? The difference between coconut oil and
olive oil is one double bond, and yet their properties are almost entirely different. I don't
know if you have insight into this, but from a nutrition standpoint, does the specificity of
enzymes for these fatty acids, is that kind of unique in terms of just how much difference you
can see in the output relative to the starting structure? Or do you see that to be relatively
conserved across all of nutrition, outside of fats that is?
No, I think it's probably a truism that every molecule is unique. Every molecule is special
in our foods, in our bodies, from water, which is probably the most special molecule in the world,
or in the universe, which makes up what, 70% of our bodies, to down to the fats and fatty acids.
And of course carbohydrates and proteins are all very unique molecules. I appreciate you mentioning
the number. I should mention how they are numbered in case people ever see them written out in the
number format, because any saturated fatty acid, let's take a fatty acid that has 16 carbons,
and it's a saturated fatty acid. Its common name is called palmitic acid. It comes from primarily
from palm trees, palm oil. So it's called palmitic acid. Its designation is 16 colon zero.
16 means how many carbons are in the molecule, the colon, what follows the colon is the number
of double bonds in the molecule. So all saturated fats is just a number, colon, and then a zero.
When you get into monounsaturated fats, again, it's the carbon number first, like the most common
one is 18 carbon fatty acid, 18 colon one. And the one tells you there's one double bond.
That fatty acid is called oleic acid. We get oleo from that word, oleo margarine.
Once you start putting a double bond in a molecule, now you have to tell the reader where it is in
the molecule. And to your point, when you have an 18 colon one, you've got to know where is that
thing. And in this case, it's at position number omega nine. It's the ninth position back from the
end. So that'd be 18, one colon n. Oh, yeah, here we go. Here's the other confusion part of
we say omega, we like to say omega three, omega six, omega nine, but chemists like to talk about
them using the term n like the letter n. It's the final carbon in the molecules, the nth carbon.
It's the last one. It's just the nth one. Exactly where they came from. I don't know.
Sometimes you'll see an omega three fatty acid called an n minus three fatty acid,
n dash three fatty acid. Same thing. We're talking about the same molecule.
I think there's mathematicians that have snuck in there so that the nth terminus
is where that n must have come from in a geometric series or sequence.
Yes.
We're going to include a lot of figures in the show notes that go through what these pathways
look like because at least for me, I don't find I can wrap my head around these things without
actually looking at the chemical structures. I still remember probably a figure you sent me
eight years ago that really walked through the pathway from linoleic acid and alpha linoleic acid
all the way down through the desaturases, elongases, all of these enzymes.
I think I just had to decide like, look, I'm going to sit here and I'm going to learn this.
I remember printing it out, laminating it, carrying it around with me and just going through it.
It's like, okay, well, it's a desaturase. Okay, that makes sense. It's an elongase.
It's going to elongate here one, da, da, da, da. At least for me, that was just the way to do it,
which was just I'm not going to be intimidated by all of these names that by themselves don't mean
much to me. But if I can look at them in the context of what you just said, which is they're
simply referring to positions of double bonds and things, it makes it a little easier. Now,
of course, I think most people listening to this are going to be like, okay, guys,
why are you going so far into this? And I think the answer is these fatty acids
basically make up the most important parts of our body, right? I mean, every membrane of every cell
is formulated with these. And it seems that they have a profound impact on our health.
They do. And we're just discovering that more and more.
And there seem to be quite differences. I mean, on the one hand, I'm struck by
the relative convergence that you can see across people consuming vastly different things. So
there's sort of a dampening effect, if you will, that the body can do where it kind of converges
all sorts of inputs to modestly banded outputs. But at the same time, I'm struck by the differences.
So I'll give you one example, which is in the weeds clinically. But it's hopefully for the
listener gives them a sense of why we want to understand this. So when we do blood tests on
patients, one of the things we always like to do is look at the EPA, DHA, AA levels in their
red blood cell membranes. And the laboratory will spit out what percentage is EPA, DHA,
total saturates, total monouns, saturates, etc, etc. The ranges on those are not that big. And
most people tend to fall within them, no matter how much they're eating, but they can be at really
different ends of those ranges. So you don't have people that differ by two and three fold,
but people can definitely differ by 20 or 30%. That's my observation. Is that fair?
That's true. And that's true. And because when you're talking about a blood test,
and specifically, you're talking about a red blood cell, which is the test we like to do,
and measure the fatty acid composition of the membrane, as you alluded to, every membrane
of every cell is made up of fatty acids. And I would venture to say that there is a unique
suite of fatty acids, a unique pattern of fatty acid for every type of tissue in every cell. It's
not the same anywhere. They're all a little bit different. And that's because the body and the way
the wisdom of synthesizing cells, each cell has its own role to play in metabolism. The membrane
has to have certain physical characteristics being real loose and floppy or being real stiff,
depending on the need of that cell. And the fatty acid composition is unique to afford a certain
kind of chemical flexibility. It's an amazing thing. There is certainly much wider variation
in the fatty acids we eat than when we see in our blood. That's because the body is making the
membranes from the raw materials we eat, and it picks what it wants. And it puts the fatty acids
largely where it wants them to be. When you're making a red blood cell in the bone marrow,
the fatty acids that are selected and put into that membrane are taken out of the blood, and
the bone marrow takes what it wants. You can influence it a little bit, but you can't influence
it like two and threefold different for most fatty acids. To give you one real example that
is just a great illustration of this, if you take somebody who is on the lowest fat diet in the
world, or specifically someone who, for example, goes out of their way to avoid saturated fat,
someone who's consuming in the neighborhood of 10 grams per day or less of saturated fat,
and you counter that with someone who's on a super high fat diet that's eating 75 grams a day
of saturated fat or more, you might see a 20% difference or a 10% difference in the amount of
saturated fat within their cell membranes. As you said, the body tends to be a heck of a lot smarter
at putting things together than just doing it based on what's available in the diet.
Yeah, thank God. That's true. Let's talk about why this stuff matters, and let's maybe take a step
back and go back to 1980. You do this experiment where, and I guess just to set the context for
listeners, in 1980 is really we're witnessing the height or I would say the wave is about to crest
in the major fat phobia 15, 20 year run that's about to sweep over America. In 1977, George
McGovern presiding over the Senate Select Committee on Health basically comes to the conclusion that
even though the evidence against or implicating saturated fat and heart disease, even though that
evidence is not great, it's good enough and they have to make a decision, and the decision that's
put forth at that time is that Americans should greatly reduce their intake of saturated fat.
I suspect that it's that decision that largely triggers an enormous interest in the type of work
that you carried out as that first paper, that first major experiment you led as a freshly
minted PhD student, which was, well, gosh, if saturated fat is going to do this, does polyunsaturated
fat do the reverse? At that point in time, Bill, if I'm not mistaken, there had already been a number
of studies that had suggested that broadly speaking polyunsaturated fats, mostly omega-6s,
actually showed a reduction in total cholesterol. Is that correct?
That's correct. In fact, in those days, even starting back in the 70s, people were taking
tablespoons of vegetable oil to lower their cholesterol. It was taken as a medicine.
What is the mechanism by which taking tablespoons and tablespoons of sunflower oil or corn oil
would lower a person's cholesterol?
It's complicated. It's been fairly well worked out since, but what that does, again,
we mentioned what you eat is not directly reflected in your cell membranes, but when
you're taking the omega-6s or the omega-9s, the monounsaturates, you're replacing some saturated
fatty acids in the membranes. If you're reducing your saturated fat intake, like McGovern et al
suggested or said we should do, you're reducing the amount of saturated fat to an extent in your
membranes. That has an effect on the physical, chemical fluidity of the membrane. There is
buried within all of our cell membranes hundreds and thousands of these receptors, proteins, that
are sitting right in the middle of membranes. One of these is called the LDL receptor, low-density
lipoprotein, which is the primary lipid particle that carries cholesterol in our blood.
And that receptor is sitting there in the liver membrane. And if you remove saturated fat or lower
the amount of saturated fat in that membrane, it changes the properties of the membrane so that
that LDL receptor is more efficient at removing and binding to and removing LDL particles from
the blood. That essentially lowers your cholesterol level.
So the cholesterol lowering comes through more lowering of the LDL than the HDL?
Correct. It's the LDL that's affected primarily by the saturation of fats. There's some effect on
HDL cholesterol, but most of it is LDL. On the surface, that would sound like a very positive
thing. So as tempting as it is to look back at the low fat mania that swept across America 30
years ago or 40 years ago and just sort of dismiss it as buffoonery for a handful of reasons,
especially with the sort of substitution of what became the go-to default, based on just the
mechanisms and the studies of the day, it was not an entirely unreasonable thing to suggest.
No, particularly, as you said, McGovern's committee said saturated fat should be reduced. Didn't say
all that. I think that's where the message got mixed because if Americans had just reduced
saturated fat and replaced it with mono and polyunsaturated fats, we wouldn't have had this
problem. It seemed to get replaced by sugar was one of the big things that got... Right. It was
take all the fat out and that was the mistake. The question you were trying to ask when you
did that study where patients were consuming, in the end, I think you said 25 grams of EPA.
And I guess I should, before you answer this, maybe let's go back and explain what EPA, DHA,
and all these other things are. And again, assume for a moment, Bill, that there will be a large
figure, multiple figures in fact, will be in the show notes. We'll have the really detailed
chemical ones, but we'll also sort of have the cartoony ones. So let's assume that someone's
looking at the cartoony figure that takes linoleic acid down to arachidonic acid,
and then the one that takes alpha linoleic acid down to EPA and then down to DHA. Can you explain
what's happening there? And let's start with the Omega-6 one, I suppose. Sure. The left-hand side
of the slide that I have in my mind, and I think you have in your mind. I'm probably having my mind
a slide you've shared with me, but we will make sure we use exactly whatever you're speaking from
in memory now. It's always done this way for some reason. The left-hand is always the Omega-6. So
it starts with linoleic acid, which is an Omega-6 fatty acid. It's the principal Omega-6 fatty
acid in our diet. It is an essential fatty acid with a capital E, essential, meaning we cannot
make it. It's very much like a vitamin. It can't be made from scratch, and it is important for
metabolism. So it is an essential fatty acid. Hey, we have to eat some Omega-6. And what are
the dominant sources of that, Bill? Vegetable oils. Soybean oil is probably 80% of where we
get our linoleic acid in our diet. So sunflower, corn, soybean, cottonseed would be the big four,
right, as my recollection? Yeah, actually, sunflower and safflower nowadays are not...
Linoleic has been pretty much stripped out of those oils. Now they're what's called hyaluric
sunflower, hyaluric sun... safflower. It doesn't say it on the label, but what's in the bottle has
vastly changed from the natural fatty acid pattern. But corn and soybean are still high,
Omega-6, meaning 50, 60% of the fatty acids in that oil are linoleic acid. And linoleic is 18,
carbon, so it's 18 colon two, two double bonds, Omega-6 position. So what happens is you eat that,
and a portion of it is glommed onto by certain enzymes in the liver that want to make a longer
fatty acid. And so they add two carbons, and they get a 20 carbon fatty acid now. And then they add,
the liver has enzymes that will add instead of having two double bonds, it'll now have four
double bonds. It goes through a three double bond molecule, and now we're at a four double bond.
When you get to this molecule, it's an Omega-6 family, 20 carbons, four double bonds, that's
called arachidonic acid. And that is an extremely important fatty acid in metabolism. If your
listeners have ever heard of prostaglandins, this is the stuff of which all prostaglandins,
well, most prostaglandins are made. It's the substrate, it's the beginning, and it's
terribly important throughout the body. The liver can even take that molecule and make it even
longer, 22 carbons, and add more double bonds up to five double bonds, but there's not much of that
around. And we really don't know what it does. I think the most important end point of Omega-6
metabolism is to produce arachidonic acid, 20 carbon, four double bond.
Well, the way you explain it, like I think going back to the bio-chem, anyone who's listening to
this who's a college student or a med student or something, I mean, that's not rocket science,
you elongate it with the elongase enzyme, and then you further desaturate it, take two of the
saturations out, and there you go. So you go from 18, 2 to 24. Now, arachidonic acid has a real bad
rap, doesn't it? It has, yes. We'll get into it in detail, but just is it safe to say that that's a
bit misunderstood and that the binary view of arachidonic acid might not be the whole story?
That's safe to say. All right. I would agree with that. We'll get into that later then.
So we'll come back to the demonization of arachidonic acid. Let's go over to the right-hand
side of the picture we both have in our mind that is hopefully about the same picture.
It is, right? Now we have at the top, instead of linoleic acid, we have linolenic acid. Just add
one of M to the name, and you get linseed oil. Most people are familiar with linseed oil. That
is rich in this particular fatty acid. Flaxseed oil is similar. Chia seed oil are all sources of
this linolenic acid. It's in carbons, again, same length as the omega-6 cousin. It has three double
bonds instead of two, and the first double bond is in the omega-3 position. So it's an 18 colon
3 N minus 3 fatty acid. It also is essential in the same sense that the omega-6 cousin linoleic
is essential in the diet. Alpha, it's just called alpha linolenic acid is also essential. We can't
make it, and it's important for metabolism and health. And so the same game happens. This 18
alpha linolenic acids, we call it ALA, thank God. ALA is consumed, and then again goes to the liver
and is elongated. In other words, two more carbons are added, and more double bonds are added to the
molecules. It goes from 3 to 4 to 5 double bonds, and now you have 20 carbon, 5 double bond, omega-3
fatty acid, and that's called EPA. The EPA stands for icosa, E-I-C-O-S-A, which is 20 in Greek.
Penta is 5, which is 20 carbons, 5 double bonds, and then we say enoic acid means it's a fatty acid.
So it's a 20 carbon, 5 double bond molecule, and that's EPA, one of the two most important of the
quote omega-3 fatty acids. That fatty acid then, EPA, can then be further converted to two more
carbons. Again, elongates the chain and desaturates, replace single bonds with double bonds. So you end
up with a 22 carbon, 6 double bond molecule, and that's called DHA, which stands for docosa, 22,
hexa, 6 enoic acid. So it's a 22 carbon, 6 double bond. So EPA and DHA are the two.
When people talk about omega-3s, that's what they mean. Those two fatty acids are the principle ones.
Going forward, just to make everybody's life easy, we're going to talk about ALA, alpha-linolenic
acid, as the omega-3 that you get mostly out of flaxseed and chia seed, I think. Are there any
other sources of high, high dose of ALA? Well, no, not a high, high dose, but if you look at what's
the principle source in the American diet, it's soybean oil. Soybean and maybe canola to some
extent, has a little bit. To some extent, to some extent, soybean is such a, it's the gorilla in the
room when it comes to vegetable oils in America. And it's about 7% of the fatty acids in soybean
oil or ALA. ALA goes through a number of steps, adds a couple carbons, desaturates a couple bonds,
and you have EPA. Though I don't think you stated this, I do believe there's an equilibrium. EPA and
DHA can go back and forth between each other, or is that mostly a one-way street? We thought they
kind of went back and forth, but now I think we know, based on a paper that was published a couple
months ago, it looks like EPA goes to DHA. DHA does not, what they used to call it is,
gets retroconverted. In other words, it goes from a 22 carbon, 6 molecule to a 20 carbon,
5 double bond molecule. That's retroconversion going backwards. We thought it happened. We don't
think it happens anymore. It's more straightforward than what I used to. Yes. My laminated sheet's
got to be updated. So it's basically ALA to EPA to DHA on the right-hand side of the page. That's
your omega-3 family. And then for the sake of simplicity, we're basically going from LA,
linoleic, not linolenic, linoleic acid, down to arachidonic acid, AA. So LA to AA is your big
omega-6 pathway. We'll pause there for a moment. With all of that said, what was your state of
understanding circa 1978-ish, whenever you probably started this study, about EPA and DHA,
which today we know a lot about and we'll talk about it, but what did you know then?
I didn't know anything about it. All I knew was we were using salmon oil. And I don't remember,
at the beginning of our experiments, to see what the effect of salmon oil was on cholesterol.
I'm not sure I even knew EPA and DHA existed. In a very simple-minded way, we were asking the question,
we know animal fats that are solid at room temperature raise cholesterol levels. And we
know that vegetable oils, plant fats, basically, plant oils lower cholesterol, and they're liquid
at room temperature. So we have animal and solid, and we have vegetable, plant, and liquid. So is
it the liquidness that's important, or is it the animal-ness, animal versus plant-ness that's
important in controlling cholesterol levels? And so the uniqueness of fish oil is it comes
from an animal, but it's a liquid. That's really a funny and cute way, yet an elegant way to think
about it, right? It's a two-by-two of solid versus liquid, animal versus plant derived, and the fish
oils sit in a unique part of that two-by-two, as you said, liquid but animal derived. Okay,
so that makes sense. That was the question. So is it the animal-ness or the liquidness of the oil
that lowered cholesterol? It turns out that fish oil lowered cholesterol, and it's an animal fat.
So it's the liquidness that was important, not the source, not whether it's a plant or an animal.
It's the physical property of the oil. That's the important thing. But EPA and DHA, we really,
I mean, I don't remember knowing anything about them until well into our study, and I started
reading the papers from the Greenland Eskimo studies. And that's when I said, oh, these things
have EPA and DHA in them. How about that? Now, the average American today who is not
supplementing with fish oil will get approximately how many grams of EPA and DHA in their diet?
Well, let's talk about milligrams, because it's about roughly 100 to 150 milligrams,
0.15 grams per day is about the average, EPA plus DHA.
You mean 150 milligrams combined EPA and DHA?
Yeah, right. It's about how much arachidonic we eat too, as a matter of fact. It's about the same
scale. That's kind of mind boggling when you think about how much fat the average person eats,
right? Oh, yeah. Out of 80 to 100 grams a day, that 0.15 grams might be EPA and DHA. That's too
bad. Historically, was there a day when we consumed more of that, or where is that in line
with history? Certainly, any culture that lived off seafood was eating more EPA and DHA.
So let's use the Okinawa as an example, not including this generation, which I've read
have sort of fallen off the rails. But if you go back a generation and beyond of the Okinawa,
who obviously would have been consuming seafood daily, how much EPA and DHA would they have
consumed? They were probably in the neighborhood of one and a half, maybe two grams, 2000 milligrams
maybe. I mean, the Eskimos, when they were discovered by Dyerberg and Bang in the 1970s,
documented six to seven grams a day, the EPA and DHA. As impressive as that is, let's come back to
your study, you were giving 25 grams of EPA and DHA to these subjects. So this was, there had
probably been no, I mean, I assume that your rationale for doing this was,
if this doesn't show an effect, we never need to study this again.
That's exactly the rationale. Do it once. What was the magnitude of the reduction in total
cholesterol, LDL cholesterol and triglyceride that you saw in that study? Not to put you on
the spot with something you did a hundred years ago, but directionally, was it significant? Not
just statistically, but clinically. Oh no, it wasn't marked. Like cholesterol might have gone from
250 to 230. Okay. What about triglycerides? Triglycerides went from about a hundred to 75.
Okay. So that's a pretty big reduction in triglycerides. As a percent, it is.
Yeah. Any other phenotypic changes you observed in those subjects or was that,
those were your primary end points? That's all you had the budget to study.
You alluded to it earlier. Platelet function bleeding was something we looked at because
by that time, Jorn Dyerberg had published a paper in Lancet in 1978 proposing that EPA
was an anti-platelet or like a blood thinning fatty acid. And that is why it prevented blood
clots. And that is why Eskimos didn't have heart attacks. That was the proposal. And EPA had been
shown by that time to be anti-platelet. So we were very interested in the effect on bleeding.
And we saw a significant prolongation of an old fashioned test called the bleeding time test,
where we actually cut the skin and count how many seconds it takes to stop bleeding.
It didn't prolong it any longer than aspirin did. So not outrageous, except in one patient. It
wasn't a patient who was a college student, but he had a marked drop in his platelet count. We wrote
a whole paper on this guy. He had a marked drop in his platelet count, a really prolonged bleeding
time. And we stopped him on the omega-3 diet because of that. But everybody else had a just
kind of a mild prolongation of bleeding, which is an, so the platelets were less reactive,
less likely to clot, which is a good thing. So that fit with the idea that these are
protective against heart attacks. Now, if I did the math somewhat correctly on your salmon burger
versus salmon oil distinction, is it safe to say they were getting about two thirds of their EPA
and DHA through consumption of salmon and about a third of it then through actual concentrate oil?
It probably would be the reverse because let's say they were getting two four ounce servings
a day of salmon. And let's just ballpark that at two grams. Let's be generous. Say that's each one
of those has two grams of EPA and DHA. So there's four grams and then they were getting 20 grams
from the liquid oil they drank. It was almost, I don't know why I thought it was only 10. Okay. So
that was the reverse. So they're getting most of it in concentrate. They're getting, you know,
maybe a quarter of it or even less potentially through consumption of salmon. Going back to
the Eskimo for a second, do you have a sense from those studies, what percentage of their total
calories were fat and then how much of that was saturated versus poly? And I'm guessing mono was
not a very abundant source in the North Pole. Very high fat diets. Again, I'd have to look it up,
but their diet was largely seafood. And we're talking about seal blubber and whale meat and
some fish. This is pretty much what they ate. You know, Greenland, you don't grow anything,
at least not until global warming comes along. But for now they, they didn't grow anything.
So fruits and vegetables and grains were, you could get them at an occasional store, but
fundamentally they were living a traditional lifestyle in eating what they killed out of the
sea. So they were probably 80% of their calories were fat. And of that, do you have a sense of how
much was polyunsaturated versus saturated? Probably about maybe six or seven grams a day out of,
let's say, let's say they ate a hundred grams of fat a day. So, so six or seven percent of it might
have been the Omega three, the polys, polyunsaturated, very little Omega six and probably
70% of the fat was saturated. Huge amount. I mean, this is what was so amazing about the
Eskimo studies because we had this paradigm that high fat, high saturated fat, high cholesterol,
of course eating very high cholesterol diet because everything was from animals.
Those are bad diets. And yet the evidence, which has been challenged nowadays, but at the time,
the evidence was these Eskimos were virtually free of acute myocardial infarction of heart effects.
It just didn't make any sense, which is why the couple of Danish investigators went over there
and started studying them, majored their plasma, their food, and they kind of discovered Omega
three fatty acids. So was your conclusion from the study in 1980 that the high amounts of EPA and
DHA and their diet were offsetting or protective to the high amounts of saturated fat? Or was your
conclusion that maybe the saturated fat because it came from fish was somehow different from,
say, dairy or land animals? I mean, how did you reconcile your experiment with this broader
volume of data though, you know, they're obviously asking very different questions and looking at
very different things. I mean, how did you begin to square those things? For one thing, again,
we didn't feed any blubber or any whale meat or seal meat, any of that really high. So we were
feeding salmon oil. Your subjects didn't really have a significant increase or change in macros,
really. They were just basically getting an extra 25 grams of fat that happened to be
polyunsaturated Omega three, but they weren't that largely true. Largely true. So where do you go
next, Bill? So obviously, well, you've never stopped looking at polyunsaturated fat since. So tell me
how that study basically peaked your ears. I think the interesting thing, the way that played out is
actually 1985 was a turning point year for Omega three in that year in May of that year,
the New England Journal published three back to back Omega three studies. One was our study in
giving very high doses of Omega three and looking at effects on lipids. And we showed huge drops in
triglycerides as we were studying people. Some of the study I did was with normal volunteers. We
later did studies with people who had lipid disorders, had very high triglyceride levels,
for example. And we found that giving them fish oil just knocked the socks out of their triclacides.
Instead of their triglycerides being 2000, they were down to 250. It was a huge effect.
And how much EPA and DHA did you have to give them?
That was the 18 to 20 gram. We're still doing play in the same game. We were still giving
high doses of salmon oil. So New England Journal publishes our paper. It publishes a paper on
kind of arthritis or inflammatory disease. And it publishes a paper on kind of molecular biology
cell, the effects of EPA on what's called leukotrienes in inflammatory molecules. It was a basic science
paper, but it was bang, bang, bang. Three papers in a row, literally in the magazine in a row
in May of 1985 that just put Omega threes in lights on the map. And people got very excited about.
What we did subsequent to that, instead of patients completely controlling their diet,
by that time we were able to, because Omega three supplements, concentrated pills were now becoming
available. And so we did some studies just giving 18 capsules. So we were giving six grams a day of
EPA and DHA in capsule form without changing anybody's diet. What happened in that setting
was very different in that setting where we didn't change their background fat intake,
just added Omega threes. Triglycerides still came down very nicely, but the conundrum was LDL
cholesterol, the bad cholesterol started to go up. That was one of the downsides of the Omega three
story. Because all of a sudden we published this, it gets a lot of press, American Heart Association,
and the, and these fish oil companies that were just starting to advertise their product
as cholesterol lowering based on our earlier studies and others is not just us. Fish oil,
folks were marketing their fish oils as cholesterol lowering products. And then we show,
when we directly test them that they don't lower cholesterol. In fact, in some people
at high dose, they will raise cholesterol. So FDA sends out all these letters to these companies
and says, you can't, you're false advertising. You can't say this anymore. So that was what they
call a gut punch to the industry at that point. At the time, was it clear whether LDL cholesterol
alone was going up? Was APO B going up as well? What other parameters of the, of the lipoproteins
were changing LDL cholesterol and APO B. There were more particles. How much were they going up
based on just this six grams of additional EPA? They might've gone from an LDL of 120 to 140 or
150. That's amazing. I mean, we're talking about six additional grams of a very specific type of
fat having that much of an impact on LDL cholesterol and presumably, as you said,
the particle number APO B. So mechanistically, what do you think was happening there?
That's been hard to figure out, but more recent studies have suggested that there's actually
an effect primarily of the DHA component on LDL receptor activity. It actually can slow down
the action of LDL receptors. So the LDL receptors are not removing LDL particles from the blood
as fast as they used to be. So the blood levels go up. So it's an effect on clearance, not an
effect. It's not an effect on production. In the previous example, were you saying that the part
of the saturated fat issue on clearance, because there's obviously a big effect of saturated fat
on production, but you're saying that saturated fat on clearance was altering membrane permeability
and the LDL receptor was therefore losing efficacy?
Yeah, right. That's, I think, our current understanding of why saturated fats raise cholesterol,
raise LDL. Now here, several years later, we kind of begin to see evidence that fish oil, and again,
I want to emphasize this is in people that have high triglyceride levels. This is not just a
normal people taking one fish oil pill. This is completely out of that realm. We're six grams a
day of EPA, DHA in people with elevated triglycerides. And that setting, the LDL and
April B went up. Now there's another little wrinkle here, Bill, which is if you're going to
take people that have triglycerides that are that high, how many of them are insulin resistant or
have metabolic syndrome as the underlying disease state versus how many of them are
metabolically very healthy, but have a hypertriglyceridemia, a familial, I think that's a
Fredrickson-Levy-Lease type three, but I'm probably wrong on that. But how many of them
are genetically seeing this high triglyceride in the context of perfect metabolic health versus
metabolically ill? Yeah, that's a good question. And I'd have to look back. I mean, you're right
about Fredrickson types. It's not type three, it's type four, which is the isolated hypertriglyceride
person. And there's type 2B, which is high triglycerides and LDL. In both of those settings,
the LDL cholesterol went up. We had never heard of metabolic syndrome in the mid 80s. We'd have
to look back, what was their glucose level? I don't know if we measured it. I'm sure we measured
their blood pressure and their body weight, but other metrics of the metabolic syndrome weren't
even crossing our minds in those days. So it's hard to say. That's interesting. But today,
the largest dose of EPA that is given pharmacologically is about four grams. Is that
correct? Four grams. Isn't that indicated primarily for people with elevated triglycerides?
It's indicated for people with very high triglycerides. So we got two levels of high
triglycerides. You've got garden variety, high triglycerides, which is maybe 200. So a normal
triglyceride may be 100, 150. I mean, maybe that's not optimal, but that's kind of normal. 200 to 500
is what we call hypertriglyceridemia. And over 500 is now very high triglycerides.
And there's kind of a bright white line. The FDA indicated when the first omega-3 drug was approved,
it was Lovesa or Omacor. And it was approved by the FDA for treating triglycerides over 500,
not under 500, over 500. And it was approved at this dose of four grams a day, because that's the
dose that the company did the studies at. They could get better triglyceride lowering with
higher doses, but now you're talking six or eight pills a day and it becomes totally impractical.
So it was a compromise. Let's make the dose four grams a day. It does lower triglycerides,
and it works to some extent. And so that's what the FDA approved. And so FDA has now set four
grams as the standard dose. Their product, is it any different from what one buys
over the counter? That product that I was just talking about, what's called Lovesa,
it's now Lovesa, that's about 85% EPA plus DHA, it's ethyl esters. You can buy over the counter or
dietary supplement, essentially more accurately. Dietary supplements that have that much EPA and
DHA as ethyl esters in one pill. Typically you have to buy, the pill is not a one gram pill. So
maybe we're going to get into this, the confusion about a thousand milligrams of fish oil.
But the standard drug, the Lovesa drug is 1000 milligram capsule of which 850 or 85% is EPA and
DHA. Oh yeah, no, we should definitely cover that now. So if you go on Amazon, I mean, I'll just
share my bias. I've talked about it before. The two brands I typically recommend to patients are
Carlson's and Nordic Naturals. And I'm sure there were several brands out there that are
quite reputable. On a hot O'Connor at the New York Times wrote a story on this probably four or five
years ago, looking at lots of different brands of fish oil. And it was looking to basically see
how many of these were made at GMP standard, how many of them actually had in them what they said
they contained from a content perspective, what was the level of contaminant, all sorts of variables.
But for whatever reason, again, those two brands I've just gotten to know and I've gotten to trust,
but you still have to read the label very carefully because one, these are very large
capsules to the entirety of the capsule is not EPA and DHA. So we tend to think about how much
EPA and DHA we want. And we then have to sort of reverse engineer it out of the capsules.
If you're taking 2000 milligrams of fish oil and let's say 1600 of that is true EPA and DHA,
which is 80%. That's not an uncommon finding. What's the other 400 milligrams?
It would be a mixture of some monounsaturates and some polyunsaturates, just to kind of general
standard fatty acids you'd find in most foods is just a very small fraction of what's in the fish
oil, particularly fish oil concentrate. Now, am I being paranoid about this stuff or do you think
that most of these things that are sold as dietary supplements are reasonably safe or what is your
view on that? I don't have a problem with dietary supplements. I think that the vast majority of them,
when they've done consumer reports testing, they've done it twice in my memory. Their final conclusion
is generally the products have pretty much as much EPA and DHA as they say, and with some variation.
They're free of toxins and any meaningful levels of environmental pollutants.
So, I don't have a problem with it. The challenge is if you're going to try and get four grams a day
of EPA, DHA, or three and a half grams is really what four capsules of LaVaza would give you,
because it's again 85%. So, you're going to be taking a whole lot of dietary supplements,
a lot of pills, because most pills are not that concentrated. Typically, nowadays you can find
very highly concentrated products and the line between a drug and a dietary supplement is getting
a little bit fuzzy, which is something some of the drug manufacturers are pointing out more and more
loudly that there's a lot of products that are being sold as dietary supplements that fundamentally
have the same chemical composition as FDA approved drugs. There's going to be a fight about this
coming on, but the processing of omega-3 rich oils has advanced tremendously over the last 20,
30 years and they can really concentrate these, take a raw fish oil which might have 30%
of its fatty acids, EPA and DHA, and you do lots of processing to get rid of all the other fatty
acids and all you have left is EPA, DHA, and you're really highly concentrated and that's
not all that different than the composition of some of these drugs. It's going to be confusing,
I think, to the consumer. Bill, what is our current understanding of the health benefits of
EPA specifically? I want to actually talk about this and then do the same thing on DHA and then
do the same thing on arachidonic acid. Cover these three end products of the omega-3 and omega-6
pathways, but let's come back to EPA because that's where we got off on this little side tangent.
Today is the consensus view that EPA is a quote-unquote heart-healthy oil?
Yes, and you could say the same for DHA in my view, but EPA is heart-healthy. Its mechanisms
by which it is heart-healthy are multiple and they include being converted into, again,
some metabolites, some prostaglandin type molecules that make the blood platelets less likely to get
sticky. It's kind of like taking aspirin without some of the side effects of aspirin.
So that's one of the arms of the benefit. EPA is also able to produce a whole series of molecules
that we call resolvins because they resolve inflammation. So they're kind of anti-inflammatory
in that sense. When EPA becomes incorporated into cell membranes, it changes the
flexibility, the fluidity of the membrane just because of its own physical properties,
and that changes the way the enzymes that live in the membranes work in such ways that makes
cellular metabolism run more smoothly, I mean, to try to simplify this. Those are really primary
ways that EPA, I think, is heart-healthy. We've only had one big study with EPA only, free of DHA.
Let's talk about that one now and then I want to come into potential risks of EPA and then I want
to circle back to DHA. But let's talk about the EPA only study. What was the patient population,
what was the dose, and what was the objective of the study?
The study was called Reduce It, which was an acronym as they all are for something. Reduce
It was the name of the study. The product was called Vasepa, like vascular EPA, V-A-S-C-E-P-A,
a company that makes the drugs called Amarin. And the way the study was done, they gave four grams
a day of this EPA, it's EPA ethyl ester. So it's a very purified EPA that has a ethyl ester,
which is the typical way that they use, they concentrate omega-3s nowadays.
Four grams a day versus the four grams of a mineral oil placebo, which has had some controversy,
whether that's a real placebo or not. Roughly 8,000 patients who all were on statin drugs to
control their cholesterol levels. And they all still had triglycerides between two and 500,
roughly 150 to 500. So triglycerides were still elevated even though they were on a statin.
Cholesterol, LDL cholesterol was roughly in the 70s. So there was low or healthy levels of LDL.
And they also had to have either a history of heart disease or some other risk factors,
like having diabetes, for example, was another way you could get in. So if you met that criteria,
that kind of patient, you were given either four grams of placebo or four grams of Vasepa.
Do we know what fraction of those patients were metabolically ill? I assume most of them were.
And I know the study is only about a year and a half old, right? I mean,
I remember this when this came out. Well, it was reported in November,
so six months ago. So almost a year. But okay, I've lost track of time.
Time flies, right. Exactly.
But how many of these people were sort of metabolically super healthy,
but just happened to have these genetic triglyceride elevations?
Nobody checked in the study what any kind of, they may be someday, they probably have blood
for them and they'll check things later. But as a recruitment strategy, they just took people who
met those criteria. You're on a statin, you have triglycerides between 150 and 500.
And you've got some other risk factors for heart disease. And that's it. And you're in.
What did the study show? Because it sure made a lot of headlines.
It should have. And it did. It showed a 25% reduction in risk for overall cardiovascular
events over about a four or five year period, which is not that long. And it was effective across
myocardial infarction need for angioplasty, a variety of different cardiovascular unfortunate
outcomes. So it was a big hit. It was really, for the last 15 years, we've been searching for other
lipid lowering drugs that, or other drugs that will improve the outcomes over statins.
The statins have been established in the 80s, 90s, and 2000s as very effective in reducing risk
for heart disease. But there's still people even on a statin that still have events, cardiac events.
So that's called residual risk. We have leftover risk. So what do we do for that? And they've,
they're probably even 10 or 15 drugs that have been tested to try to improve upon a statin.
Really, none of them have worked without going into all the details. But this one,
pure EPA worked and it worked great. And it worked with virtually no side effects.
And you can take it with any other medications. It doesn't have any drug-drug interactions.
I think it was a big hit and well deserved. I should mention the name, the trade name
of the drug is Vasipa. The generic name is called icosapent ethyl, two words. And this spell starts
with an I, I-C-O-S-A, icosapent, it's really just a flipping around of the spelling of icosapenta,
you know, like acid or EPA. Now, Bill, one of the issues with this study, of course, is the inclusion
criteria assumes that the patients have very high triglycerides. I must have received 12 emails in
the span of a day from patients of mine saying, Hey, should I be taking this? To which my answer was,
well, your triglycerides are 86. So I'm going to go with no on that because I can't infer that the
mechanism by which this worked in these patients is going to have a benefit in you. Do you know if
there's any plans to repeat that study or a study like it in a normal triglyceride population?
I don't. I know that what's fundamentally being reproduced is the same type of patient,
but with a EPA plus DHA product. Why was that study done with only an EPA versus a combined?
Well, in the late 80s, a EPA only drug was approved in Japan called EPDL,
which is essentially exactly the same thing as Vasipa. In the Japanese, back in the 1980s,
believed that it was EPA that was the active agent in fish oils. So a drug company called Mochita
developed an EPA drug and they got it approved. And they've been using that EPA drug for years
and years. And the JELUS trial, which was done published in 2007, which was a Japanese Omega-3
trial, used this product called EPDL. We call it Vasipa. And it was successful. This company in
Ireland, which Amarin has the same molecule essentially, I think they're trying to carve
out a unique niche in the Omega-3 world that they can get an approved drug. EPA plus DHA is
already approved. That's Lovesa, Omakor. They said, well, let's just try the EPA part and see what
that does. And it works well. What nobody's ever done and nobody is doing yet is the counter part,
a DHA only study. What is your take on this from two standpoints? The first is,
if you can speculate for a moment, do you believe that EPA and DHA from a cardiovascular
standpoint are as beneficial or have benefit in people with normal triglycerides? Yes.
I don't think the benefit, the cardiovascular benefit comes from lowering triglycerides.
In fact, in this study, the reducer study I just talked about with EPA, triglycerides were lowered
15% maybe. It was not a huge drop in triglycerides by any means.
What was the reduction in LDLC and APOB? I don't recall.
Yeah, virtually no change.
So unlike PCSK9 inhibitors, which really have had the biggest impact on residual risk in
cardiovascular disease over the past five years, very similar population to what you've described
in Fourier, more so than Odyssey, where they started with patients already maximally
statinized. These patients was independent of their triglyceride level, but they had to be
maximally statinized. I think they came in with an average LDL cholesterol of 74 milligrams per
deciliter. And in a very short period of time, something to the neighborhood of two and a half
years saw an amazing event risk reduction. But the event risk reduction in reducing it was greater
than the PCSK9 studies.
Yeah, it was a longer study, wasn't it? About five years in reducing?
Yeah, right.
Yeah. And Fourier was like 2.2 and Odyssey was about 2.4, which again, I think all of those are
amazing. I'm not saying that to be one up on reduce it or one down. I actually just, I think
most people don't understand the time course of cardiovascular disease well enough to appreciate
the fact that you can take a disease that is a time course disease that starts at birth.
And in somewhere between two years and five years, actually reduce events. It shouldn't happen. And
in fact, I remember, I don't know if I actually said it out loud, it would be great if I did,
because I could go back and maybe someone would remember, but I certainly remember thinking
Fourier is going to fail because not that I didn't have faith in the mechanism of PCSK9 inhibition,
but because I simply didn't think you could bend the arc of a disease like cardiovascular disease
in two years on a group of patients who had an LDL cholesterol in the 70s. That just struck me
as impossible. It is really quite amazing that all of these things work. And in some ways, it's even
more amazing, frankly, that just pure EPA could have this effect, which again, I'm bringing you
back to the question that I keep interrupting you when you start to answer. I apologize.
Why in the world would four grams of EPA reduce events, especially as you said, when it's not the
obvious mechanism of, hey, we're going to drop triglycerides, which all things equal should drop
ApoB. And by the way, you're seeing a greater magnitude of event reduction than you're seeing
with aspirin. So the pure antiplatelet effect also seems a bit counterintuitive. What else do you
think is going on here? Right, right. It's not enough. Whatever role inflammation, and it's such
a slippery word that's thrown around so much, but EPA definitely gives rise to molecules that are
pro resolution of inflammation. So inflammation starts, the EPA will shut it down. To whatever
extent, a cardiovascular event is precipitated by an inflammatory event, the omega-3 EPA could
participate in that. It could stop it. The omega EPA could also play a role in even the control of
the heart rate. The heart rate variability can be reduced. I'm not sure in this study,
they measured it. But we've done studies with omega-3 showing heart rate variability, which is
a marker of autonomic nervous system control of the heart is improved. So that's another piece of
the puzzle. It could just be several different things that in each one of itself, they add up
and they multiply. And you said heart rate variability improved. Before that, you said
reduced, but I think you mean improved or increased, right? Correct.
Do you recall if in reduce it, they measured other cytokines, inflammatory cytokines beyond
the usual suspects? Like did they look at the, all of the suite of interleukins and things like that?
Was that published in the original study? So presumably, as you said, they've got a bio bank
that may be able to look at other markers of what was the signature of this event reduction.
Going down this path you just described, it'd be great to see what happened to IL-1, IL-6, TNF.
If you look at all of these other things that could be playing a role in the inflammatory component
of atherosclerosis, that would be interesting to see, right? Because then it would give you
more confidence that this has broader applicability than just people with sky-high triglycerides.
Back again to the inclusion criteria, these are not sky-high triglycerides. And this is not
triglycerides over 500. These are not people at risk for pancreatitis. This is much more garden
variety hypertrugular sardemia. I don't know. In my practice, Bill, 150 to 500 is sky-high.
Okay. Well, I guess I'm used to hearing type 500,000, 2000, people have that. But
that's the place Omega-3s first got their approval in that very high triglyceride world. And so when
we bump it down to under 500, to me it seems like garden variety. But you're right.
Well, but that's a fair point. I mean, it's certainly representative of the US population.
Did that study, did it look at how much of that EPA converted to DHA? In other words,
one of the advantages presumably of giving mega dose of EPA versus mega dose of DHA is you're
higher up the food chain. So presumably you're covering any benefit that's unique to EPA if you
believe there may be one, and then you're also transmitting into DHA and getting that. Or do you
believe that all of the benefits of EPA are transmitted through DHA?
I think it's probably all the benefits of EPA are transmitted through EPA,
not through conversion to DHA. Not through the conversion to DHA.
No, no. In fact, when you look at a couple of papers looked at the effects of giving pure EPA
programs on red blood cell DHA levels, for example. And DHA levels actually go down a little bit.
EPA goes up, of course, you're feeding EPA, but the DHA component in the red cell membrane goes
down. Or in other studies stays the same, but doesn't grow up. You're not increasing DHA tissue
levels. That's really interesting. So in other words, if EPA is being converted to DHA, which
I assume we still think it is, it's not necessarily, I mean, it's just increasing the substrate pool
of DHA, but not necessarily the incorporation into cell membranes. Right, right. That's
interesting. And that actually explains, I think, some of what I guess I would see when I look at
people's laboratory values. While we're on this topic, if I consumed staggering amounts of flaxseed
oil, by the way, a friend of mine once gave me a recipe to make flaxseed tea. And A, it tasted
really good when I had it at her place. So part of it is just, it was really amazing. And part of it
is the recipe was so complicated that I took pride in like taking two days to make a vat of
flaxseed tea that could feed a small village. I was never able to get it quite right. But let's
assume I could get it right. And I could consume a near infinite amount of flaxseed oil. Could that
amount of ALA ever give me sufficient enough substrate EPA and DHA to rival what we're talking
about in these supplemental doses of four grams? No, it's never, when people have tried giving
12 grams of ALA, not just flaxseed oil, ALA. Just straight ALA. Yeah. Yeah. You don't even get,
you might take an EPA level of 1% in a red cell and maybe drive it to 2%.
There's two questions I have, and I hope I'm going to remember the second one.
Is there a risk that looking at the red blood cell, which of course is the most obvious and easy
cell for us to access the membrane in, is there a risk we're missing something that's not occurring
in cells that we can't access like as easily? We can't look at the membrane of adipose cells or
muscle cells. And we typically, even though it would be just as easy to look at leukocytes,
I assume we don't look at them at least clinically or commercially. Do we run the risk of just looking
at one, one pony here? Right. Everything's a compromise. So the red cell is the easiest cell
type to get at. Leukocytes are not that easy to get at. Right. You need some A for recess or something
like that. Clinical lab. Right. Right. And just a clinical lab setting is very difficult. Red cells
are thrown away by the gallon day by day, just because all you really wanted was the plasma,
right? So the red cells go to the bottom and you take the plasma off and you throw them away.
Red cells are, we've shown red cells correlate with quite a few other tissues
in terms of the omega-3 levels. So they are a good reflection of other tissues, probably the only one
that's the least reflective of is the brain, at least in the adult. It's hard to add a
composition of the brain. Yeah. I don't think anyone's going to sign up for the brain biopsy.
So what are some of the tissues that you've seen high correlation with with RBC? Well,
we did it originally with the heart using heart transplant patients who were being followed up
every six months with a heart biopsy to see how their heart was doing, of course. And we were able
to get their red cells and the heart biopsy and measure the omega-3 content and show the nice
correlation to higher the omega-3. And the red cell, the higher the omega-3 and the heart. Other
people have done this too. And you can do it in animals, of course, you have lots of tissues.
Is there a high correlation with liver as well as myocyte, skeletal myocyte?
Right, muscle and liver and guess is small intestine, large intestine.
Wow. Okay. We'll make sure we include all these papers, Bill, as well in the show notes,
because that's actually something I've just been too lazy to personally go back and check. It's on
my list of 2000 things I want to go and check. And that's one of them is I always wanted to go
back and look at what the association between RBC membrane level was and other tissues. The other
question I had was what are the, we've kind of glossed over it because it's a little bit of the
stepchild, but what are some of the direct benefits, if any, of ALA by itself? Because you just noted
that it's not that having all the ALA in the world is not really meaningful to conversion to EPA. So
if there's benefit to ALA, it needs to be through ALA, right? We don't really know. There's certainly
some hints in some of the population epidemiologic studies that higher ALA intakes, presumably
independent of EPA and DHA intake, is associated with reduced risk for disease. So that's a good
thing. I have no problem with ALA. I just have a problem with it being a substitute for fish oils,
for omega-3, long chain omega-3s, because it doesn't. But ALA itself, I mean, I don't think
it's a bad idea to take ALA products, rich oils, as well as take fish oils. But we don't really
know the mechanism, but I think there's probably going to be some metabolites of ALA itself in the
same sense that there are prostaglandins, leukotrienes, and other metabolites from EPA and DHA.
There probably are from ALA too that are doing things we don't know about. It's all dark on the
inside, so we don't really quite know what's going on. I think there's going to be benefit,
but it's not because it's converted to EPA and DHA as far as we know.
And speaking of which now, let's go down the bottom of that chain. We've talked about EPA.
Let's talk about DHA. As you said, we haven't had the study that takes four grams of DHA,
administers it in either a high, low, or normal triglyceride population. But based on studies
that have looked at high doses combined and maybe trying to contrast with high-dose EPA studies,
plus looking at all the animal and mechanistic studies, what is your best guess as to what a
high dose of DHA is doing? In a sense, much the same thing as EPA. There are parallel mirror
image molecules being made. What DHA's are called instead of resolvents are called protectants.
These are the metabolites that are very active in anti-inflammatory processes. DHA will improve
platelet function, make platelets less sticky the same way that EPA does. We did different
mechanisms with the same outcome. DHA is probably better at actually lowering triglycerides and
raising HDL than EPA is. So there could be actually a lipoprotein benefit there. Although DHA does
raise, particularly in people who are hypertriglycerideemic taking fairly high doses of DHA,
there will be an LDL raising effect. Whether that's a bad thing or not, nobody knows,
but it's been observed. That's one of the differences between an EPA-only product and
an EPA-plus DHA. There have been folks who have been trying to say that the EPA-plus DHA products
are not good for you because they have DHA, which can raise LDL. I think that's a big stretch.
This is a lot of caveats. But nevertheless, that's part of some marketing programs now,
which I find unfortunate. DHA is certainly, if you look at biology at the membranes of any
of our membranes, red cells or heart, DHA is by far the most common, much higher levels of DHA.
Like the red cell, 85% and 15%. If you look at the total of EPA-plus DHA.
Yeah, I usually think of it in terms of absolutes. So I know I was looking at my labs from,
I draw my labs every once in a while. I think the last check was a few weeks ago and my
red blood cell EPA level was about 2.2% and DHA level was about 8%. So it's comparable to what
you're saying for a total of about a little over 10%, 10 to 11%. At what point do you worry? Is it
too high? We really haven't seen any adverse effects in higher doses. And there are major
international bodies that are saying up to five or six grams a day of EPA DHA is no problem.
And five or six grams of EPA would give you what level in the RBC, the highest level I've ever
seen in RBCs. I've had a patient who was just taking this stuff by the truckload, which means
he was probably taking about three grams a day, maybe four, I'm not sure. But was sitting there
at about 16% EPA-plus DHA in the red blood cell. Is that comparable?
We have seen higher, but that guy is probably 99.9% percentile. We've seen people over 20
who are not taking fish oil, which is pretty... So there's some interesting biology here.
What do you think is going on in there? How is that happening? Are they just eating a lot of fish?
This particular lady I'm thinking of was when we interviewed her said, yeah, she eats
baby fish once a week, some salmon, but it's not like she's not doing anything Eskimo and she
wasn't taking a supplement. She was a woman of Indian, East Indian extraction and drank a lot of,
the thing that really stuck out, she drank a lot of kefir, liquid yogurt. But what in the world
that would have to do with Omega-3, I have no idea. So we don't know what happened to her,
why she's that way. And there's other people that have been up that level that I think it's
just genetic. I mean, that's a cop-out word, I know.
I know. It is funny, but I was just about to say the ubiquitous cop-out of genetic, but
I've absolutely seen patients who eat one serving of fish a week and need four mega EPA DHA.
And it's the same brand, so it's not a brand issue. They'll take a mega dose, four capsules
a night of the big stuff and you might get them up to 7%. And then I've seen other people who eat
fish twice a week and they walk around at 9%. You're seeing this as well and you're equally
stumped by it. Yeah, right. We published a paper recently looking at, in something like 3,500
people that have submitted blood to us and have told us how much oily fish they eat and whether
they take a supplement or not. That's all we asked. And we found out that the group that has
the 50-50 chance of an 8% Omega-3 index were eating three reported eating three oily fish
meals a week and taking a supplement. But below that, the chances of having 8% are diminished.
But there's even within the category of people that were not taking any supplements and eating
maybe one fish meal a week, there were some people that had 8%. It's just they're real outliers.
There's a tremendous variability in the level in the blood compared to what's in the diet.
Bill, just based on your knowledge around this, and we haven't fully finished the DHA stuff,
with that caveat, do you have a recommendation for physicians or patients who are monitoring
EPA and DHA levels in red blood cells for a target? I mean, the lab that I use,
I think gives a range of 8% to 10% is ideal. Do you have a view on this?
We think, in what we call the Omega-3 index, which is EPA plus DHA in red cell membranes,
our target is 8% to 12%. That's a range we think is a healthy range. The average American
is around 5%, maybe, 4% or 5%, twice as high as normal. I've seen people at 2%, which are
obviously people who don't supplement and don't eat fish, but I've also seen people who don't
supplement, don't eat fish, and they're at 5% to 6%, which again comes back to this
question of the role of genetics in driving this. So let's come back to DHA for a moment.
A few years ago, there was certainly a little bit of hoopla around the neuroprotective benefits
of DHA. What is the state of the art and science around that particular question?
It begins with the observation that the brain and the retina, which is really just an extension of
the brain, are very rich in DHA, virtually no EPA in the brain. Beginning with that,
the logical conclusion is DHA is important in the brain and the eye because they're there. People
have then tried to jump to the conclusion that therefore if you give more DHA, you're going to
get better brain health and better eye health. Well, that's not necessarily panned out,
particularly like in depression studies. That's the most clear area at the moment where
folks have tried to give high DHA products to try to affect depressive symptoms, and they don't
really work. The products that seem to work to actually have an effect on depressive symptoms
are ones that are richer in EPA than DHA. So you look at a meta-analysis, a compilation of lots
of different studies. The positive ones are the ones that are richer in EPA, but there's no EPA
in the brain. The logic was that if the meat of the brain has got DHA in it, the actual physical
flash of the brain is DHA, then DHA should be given and it would be beneficial, but that's not
a logical assumption. I think what's happening is EPA is probably providing some unique anti-inflammatory
effects in the brain circulation that's affecting, because we don't understand depression at all,
but it's somehow affecting the expression of depressive symptoms like DHA doesn't. I can't
say that DHA is the brain omega-3 and EPA is the heart omega-3. I don't think that's true.
I don't think we can at this point say one of them is better than the other for any given system.
They come together in nature in all fish that contain EPA and DHA have both of them.
It's not 50-50, it's usually 60-40 or 40-60 in terms of ratio, EPA and DHA. I think that's
the best thing to do is to get both of them at this point for any condition, all conditions.
Because you've done a PhD in nutrition, I'm going to ask you a nutrition question.
If you recommend fish for people to eat, if someone says, look, I want to get as much of the EPA DHA
as I can through my food intake as opposed to supplement intake, and then being mindful of
fish that contain toxins, particularly mercury, what's the best yield for safety and then high
quantity of EPA DHA? Salmon seems to be at the top of that intersection, right? Is there other
fish you'd put there? Sardines, herring, mackerel, almost all the oily fish are going to have high
EPA levels just simply because they have high oil, because they have fat in their flesh and their
tissues. There's really only about four or five fish that are because of the mercury have a
mercury concern and they're fish that are really very rarely eaten, tilefish, swordfish, king mackerel,
and shark. So those are the ones that everybody agrees that pregnant women, lactating women,
should not eat because they affect neurodevelopment of the brain. There's anecdotal stories of people
eating vast amounts of tuna and getting high levels of mercury and sure, I'm sure that can happen,
but by and large, albacore tuna, for example, is twice as much EPA and DHA as
chunk light tuna. It's more expensive, so it's a great source of EPA and DHA, but it has more
mercury than chunk light tuna has. I think people get that balance way out of whack. They're far
or more concerned about miniscule amounts of mercury and they will forego the good benefits
of EPA and DHA in a food like albacore tuna, white tuna, because they're afraid of the small
amount of atoxin. The benefits of eating fish, even if there's some mercury in it, far outweigh
the downside of the mercury. Yeah, I probably need to go a little further down this rabbit hole,
but again, this is another example where I've seen amazing individual variability. I've seen
people who eat three servings of tuna a week who have a mercury level below 10 on a laboratory
assay like LabCorp where the upper limit of normal is 15 and there are people that walk around at 10,
so they're perfectly fine and they're eating tuna three times a week. Then I've
seen people who consume tuna twice a month and they're right at the upper limits.
There's a lab called Quicksilver that we use to further scratch at that a little bit and look at
the inorganic and the organic, but one of the things we've learned through that is clearance
matters a lot. In fact, clearance seems to matter at least as much and maybe not surprisingly as
intake. The Quicksilver test looks at the hair, urine, blood. It basically quantifies how they're
clearing inorganic and organic and then you get a sense and then you're measuring organic and
inorganic, so you're getting a sense of, is this coming in through food? Is this coming in through
the environment? Yeah, it's another one of those things that's complicated. My general rule and
advice to patients is salmon and small bait fish is open field running. If you're going to go haywire
on tuna, which I could do, I could eat tuna every day. I love it so much, I don't. You're probably
best to at least measure your levels, but to your point, maybe we don't know exactly what the
toxicity curve looks like. It's worth exploring. I do want to come back to something else in the
Omega-3 broad front, which is there are a handful of studies. I've seen one of them, but I believe
there are others. I think one of them was the Honolulu Heart Study or something about,
this has got to be over 20 years old now, that actually looked at a reduced amount of
lung cancer in smokers who had high Omega-3 levels. Am I getting that right?
I've not seen that. I'd like to see that, but I've seen papers recently that looking at smokers,
some of the adverse effects of smoking seem to be mitigated by a high Omega-3 intake. Sort of the
same idea. It's the same idea, yeah, and maybe I'm just not remembering the study correctly, but
it sort of goes down this theme of there was a protective benefit of high amounts of EPA and DHA.
Let's pivot back over now to the other side of the axis. We talked about linoleic acid or LA as an
essential fatty acid. I believe you said we get the lion's share of it from soybean and corn oil,
correct? Right. Linoleic acid, you described through the process of elongation, desaturation,
ultimately becomes arachidonic acid. How did arachidonic acid get such a bad name? Is that
all Barry Sears that we have to thank for that? Partly Barry, partly Bill Lands, partly Artemis
Somopoulos. The way I look at it is if we think back to the 1960s and 70s, we had this thing called
the P to S ratio in oils. Do you remember that? Polydicetrates, right. For heart health, you want
to eat high P to S ratio foods, oils. The ratio mentality, that was the idea. And that made sense.
We want less saturated fat, more polyunsaturated fat was good for your health, good for your heart.
We move a couple decades in and now we have the omega-6s and the omega-3s and we know that they
eat the L, linoleic and ALA, omega-3 side, compete with each other for enzymes to metabolize up to
other EPAs and arachidontites. And so there's a competition there. So people like ratios,
black and white, you know, black hat, white hat, arachidonic acid does give rise to several or many
pro-inflammatory compounds. No question. It's a good thing. It's what it's supposed to do.
The concern is, does that get out of whack and does it go on and on and on and never get resolved?
So arachidonic got this black hat idea. It's the pro-inflammatory one and an EPA and DHA
are the anti-inflammatory ones. So let's just do an omega-6 omega-3 ratio. I have a lot of problems
with that ratio. I think it doesn't make any sense, partly because it presumes that the omega-6s
actually are bad and they really aren't. The evidence now coming out from large meta-analyses
where people are, and we were part of this study, where they looked at plasma linoleic acid levels
or blood linoleic acid levels. So omega-6 levels in the blood and arachidonic levels in the blood.
And they measured it in thousands and thousands of people and they followed them
for the development of heart disease and diabetes over between five and 30 years. And it was a very
clear signal that the higher the level of linoleic acid, meaning the more you eat,
that's the only way you can raise it, is by eating more. The higher the level of linoleic acid in the
blood, the lower the risk of heart disease, the lower the risk of myocardial infarction,
the lower the risk of diabetes. And arachidonic acid levels were unrelated to either of those
outcomes. It was neutral. It wasn't higher or lower, it didn't make any difference.
So what's the correlation between arachidonic acid level and linoleic acid level? And what's
the correlation between arachidonic acid level and ingested linoleic acid?
Virtually none. Even though we know arachidonic can be made from linoleic acid,
only less than 1% of the linoleic we eat gets made into arachidonic. Very little of it's made.
And you may have already said this and I was too busy trying to think about something you
previously said, but just as ALA conversion to EPA is virtually irrelevant, is that a similar
statement for LA conversion to AA?
The same idea. When the people have given radioactive tracers and measured how much
actually goes from LA to AA, less than 1%, very little. And people have also looked at,
if you give a huge dose of LA in the diet and then you measure the effect on a plasma arachidonic,
no effect. If you completely strip the diet for weeks and weeks of LA, arachidonic levels
don't go down. It just doesn't respond. So arachidonic is very tightly controlled
and it's not driven by a linoleic acid. While we're on the subject of ratios, Bill,
one of the other ratios that people like to talk about is the ratio of AA to EPA and AA to DHA.
Do you put that in the same category of helpfulness as total omega 3 to total omega 6?
It's a little bit better. One of the problems with the total omega 6 to omega 3 is it doesn't
define what the fatty acids are. Right, because the omega 3 can be dominated by ALA, which is
what it is. That number could be dwarfed by how much is EPA and DHA.
Correct. Right. And the same on the omega 6 side. There's seven different omega 6 fatty acids you
throw into that recipe. Which one are we talking about? And so that's a problem. The fact that you
can have the same ratio of Omega 6 to Omega 3 with very high levels of Omega 6 and Omega 3 or
very low levels of Omega 6 and Omega 3, same ratio, doesn't make any sense. And it's very hard to,
the other problem is it presumes that the Omega 6 is bad and the Omega 3 is good. I love a quote
I read somewhere that the guy said, what's the point of the Omega 6-Omega 3 ratio? It's good
versus good. So why are we doing this? AA-EPA ratio is better because it at least defines which
fatty acids you're talking about. That's good. I don't think it's any more informative. It leaves
out DHA completely, which I think is unfortunate. Again, it's a ratio that presumes arachidontic
bad. And I don't think we can presume that because arachidontic is not only made into
pro-inflammatory, it's made into anti-inflammatory molecules too. What drives that balance? First of
all, what are the top two or three things that drive the pool of arachidontic acid? And then
secondly, what are the top two or three things that drive its destination, either pro or anti-inflammatory?
That's tough to say. I don't know what controls arachidontic levels, substrate levels to begin
with. That's kind of amazing, right? Some that you make, the tissues get incorporated with a certain
amount of arachidontic and the body likes a certain level. And it's released from membranes
when you have a stressor of some kind and you make prostaglandins. But there are like 100 different
metabolites you get made from these molecules. And it's almost virtually impossible to study all of
them in vivo together. You can take one particular metabolite and sprinkle it on a cell in a test
tube and see what it does and then write a paper on it. But it may have nothing to do with reality
because in reality you've got a hundred different molecules all banging on the door, fighting with
each other, one balancing the other. It's an incredible dance that you can't replicate
outside of the body. And people draw these conclusions about this fatty acid is bad and
that fatty acid is good based on really naive views, I think, of the complexity of the biology.
What's most compelling is let's look at blood levels of fatty acids and who's actually having
diseases. Who's getting sick? I mean, I don't care about looking at metabolic charts and what pathway
intersects with what pathway or competes. That's swell. But at the end of the day,
if omega-6 levels are high and that's associated with reduced risk for diabetes and heart disease,
that's a very powerful testimony to me that the omega-6s are good.
When you say omega-6, in that situation, is the bulk of it made up through LA or is it a proxy
metric of LA plus AA? LA. Because that's what we eat. Again, we eat, on average, we eat maybe 15
grams a day of LA and we eat about a tenth of a gram a day of arachnonic. You have a bit of a
contrarian view of the sort of plant oils, the canolas, the safflowers and the sunflowers,
et cetera. Many people view these as sort of unhealthy oils. Do you view any of those oils
when consumed in the quantities that Americans consume them as unhealthy?
I thought you were going to say people, when you talk about canola and olive oil,
people think those are great because they're mono. They're mono-rich oils.
Well, yeah, that's actually funny. The canola and the safflower, at least in its original form,
and olive oil are virtually indistinguishable by fatty acid composition.
Well, canola and olive, yeah. But in the safflower, it was like 77%
linoleic acid originally. And now it's down to like 15%.
Right. And isn't it largely boosted in omega mono-unsaturated now, omega-9?
Mono is right. They call them high mono, high mono saff and high mono sunflower.
And I think those are a problem. I'm sorry to see that happening. I know what's happening
because partly because omega-6 fatty acids are unstable or more likely to go rancid.
So they like to get rid of them, which led to the whole trans fatty acid thing,
but we're not going to go there today. So we're reducing omega-6 levels in our oils,
which is going to reduce them in our blood, which if the evidence is pointing in the right
direction, that's going to show lead to an increased risk for these major diseases.
Wasn't there a day when we really didn't have much omega-6 in our diet?
Sure.
Isn't it a relatively recent thing? Like more than a few hundred years ago, wouldn't we have
only been consuming saturated and mono-unsaturated fats primarily in addition to EPAs and DHA?
Right, right. We didn't live very long either.
Well, is that really true though? I mean, the mortality curve had more to do with infectious
diseases, infant mortality and things like that, but we certainly weren't dying of chronic diseases
either. Are you suggesting that the addition of plant seed oils is protective against the things
that were killing us or are we surviving despite them?
I don't know what the case is. I know that people have shown huge increases in little
like acid intake over the 20th century. They do that with the intent of scaring people.
Look at how unnatural this is, but then you look at death rates from heart disease,
heart disease rates as the levels of LA go up, they seem to go down.
Although it's so hard to look at that, the problem with that type of data is that we
superimpose the use of statins and advanced cardiac life support and defibrillators and
smoking. Yeah, so I think it's very difficult to do that. But if we look at the literature as far
as what we can say, I mean, it seems that we're on more stable ground saying that EPA and DHA
are probably protective. I'm still at a bit of a loss as to what to say about Omega-6. I mean,
on a personal level, I just find them kind of disgusting, if I'm going to be brutally honest.
I just think they're disgusting oils. I think they taste like crap.
But that's just my taste, right? I think canola, safflower, sunflower, corn oil,
they just taste gross to me, but I think that's because I've just acquired a taste
for saturated fat and monounsaturated fat over time.
Oh, well, yeah, that could be. And most people don't eat it as oil. It's incorporated in
salad dressings. Well, but that's my point. I don't know the last time I had a salad dressing
out of a bottle because it just tastes disgusting relative to being able to put real olive oil on.
And by the way, we should actually say, most of the time when you buy olive oil,
you're not really getting olive oil, right? I mean, it's a very, very diluted olive oil.
But assuming you're getting real olive oil, which actually has kind of a strong taste to it,
away you go. I don't like to get too far down the omega-6 pathway other than to say I don't think
it's the evil that people think it is. And the problem is that we need to get more EPA and DHA
in our diet, not necessarily get all hung up on omega-6. Yeah, it seems to me that that's the
bigger place to move the needle is if you can increase the EPA and DHA in your diet,
the body's ability to buffer high amounts of LA seems impressive. Is that a fair statement?
I don't know about the second half. I don't know that it needs to be buffered.
Maybe buffer is the wrong word. Again, I think I use this term of a reducing function or a capacitor
in a circuit. It just seems like you can have people like I consume virtually no,
none of those seed oils, meaning I probably consume one-tenth of what the average person
does because I, again, I just don't eat many processed foods and I don't have any of those
oils. I don't have salad dressing or any of those oils in my home. So they're going to sneak in a
little bit somewhere, but I'm not consuming them in high amounts. Well, sure, they're going to be
in the beach, animal products. Sure, exactly. So you're going to get them through those things.
But if you look at my blood levels, my RBC levels, and compare them to someone who's eating
literally 10 times the amount I'm eating, we might only differ by 10 or 20%. That's what I mean by
there's sort of this huge buffer capacitance function to it. Whereas on the EPA DHA level,
it seems that what you eat matters a heck of a lot more in the output. Is that a fair assessment?
Absolutely true. Your cells respond to EPA and DHA much more strongly than they do to
changes in LA intake. Do you think there's clinically a role for looking at the AA to
EPA and AA to DHA levels? Can we infer anything from that? I prefer the Omega-3 index. Yeah.
Just look at the EPA DHA total. To me, that's the problem. The problem is the lack of EPA and DHA.
If you get those up, your RACADONATE levels will go down. That's the best way to lower. If you want
to lower RACADONATE is to take fish oil. And so your ratios will change. You can change ratios
all day long by just changing the denominator. And what I don't like about AA-EPA ratio or
Omega-6 to Omega-3 is it distracts people from the real problem, which is the lack of EPA and DHA.
It lets them run and say, okay, well, I can fix my ratio by eating less Omega-6 and not eating more
Omega-3. That doesn't help. Whereas if you just look at the Omega-3 index, EPA DHA, that's your focus.
It's too low. Fix it. Raise it up. Everything else will settle out.
What do you think is the best case for and against the notion that, I mean, the REDUCE-IT study,
in addition to at least one or two other studies, makes a pretty compelling case that you don't
have to eat fish to get these benefits. You can get the supplements. I know that prior to a year ago,
when REDUCE-IT came out, there was still a piece of me that wondered, did you have to actually eat
the fish? And is the consumption of fish itself and the EPA DHA level that rises with it more of a
proxy for some subtler thing that we're not measuring? Is the Omega-3 content of fish and
hence of your blood levels really just a marker of fish intake and there's something really
beneficial in fish other than Omega-3 that's really doing the good work or something?
Or even complements it. Yeah. So even if you posit that the EPA and the DHA are part of the benefit
from eating fish, is there something else in the fish or other things that one would eat with it
that augment or transduce that benefit that you could be missed? And REDUCE-IT now makes that
question much less likely, makes the answer to that question being yes, much less likely. But
just I want to round that out and make sure that you haven't forgotten anything you wanted to talk
about there. I agree with you. I think it can be done with we prefer to do with fish if possible,
but there's a lot of challenges with that. Not only just personal taste and cost and ecological
issues. So yeah, you can do it from EPA and I think you can do it from EPA plus DHA supplements.
I think we need to talk about the other study though, the vital study, which was reported out
at the same meeting as REDUCE-IT. And it was widely reported. It was not done in people with
high triglycerides. It was done in normal, relatively healthy Americans in about 20,000,
25,000 of them. What was the dose that was used?
It was one low vasocapsule, so 850 milligrams of EPA DHA.
Yeah. And that study didn't find a difference, did it?
Well, that depends on how deeply you want to look in the study. If you just want to read the
primary endpoint.
Yeah. Well, my take on that, well, who cares what my take is? Tell us your take,
but starting with the dose.
You're not a standard doctor, but the typical doctor, his take on it is it didn't work
because that's what the press said. That's what the abstract said because they were looking for
an effect of less than one gram a day of EPA and DHA. And they were looking at a composite endpoint
of four or five different elements of cardiovascular disease, stroke, non-fatal stroke,
stroke, non-fatal heart disease. A composite endpoint, which three of the elements maybe
were not affected, but one was affected tremendously. And it was heart attacks were
significantly 20% reduction in heart attacks and 20% reduction in fatal heart attacks were
one of the findings. I mean, that's impressive for 850 milligrams a day. It's amazing to me
that you can even do that now. And they found that if you look at people who report eating
less than 1.5 fish meals a week, there was a significant benefit on the primary endpoint
of cardiovascular disease by taking just one capsule of a vasa. There was some really positive
stuff in this study, but it was buried in the press headlines that fish oils don't work
without any caveats. If you exclude the composite metric and you just look at the CHD metric,
how did the magnitude both in absolute and relative risk compare to reduce it? This is
one of the things I like doing to sense check studies, which is kind of do my own analysis
of them and say, well, like that, again, an example would be comparing Odyssey and Fourier
and saying, well, based on the fact that one came in heavily statinized, the other was not heavily
statinized, durations are about the same. Where would we be fooled versus not fooled on this?
Can you do that sort of analysis between these two studies as well and say, did they at least
have a dose response with respect to the reduction in MI, for example?
Yeah, that's a good question. I never looked at it that way. I've never broken it down,
done the math that way. I know that there was a 9% or 10% reduction in, maybe it was 20%. I can't
remember at the moment, of risk for heart disease. But again, these were not people at high risk. So
your absolute risk reduction was pretty small. Relative was pretty big, but also the dose was
very low. Yeah. So you had normal triglyceride, low risk people on one fifth of the dose. So it's
very hard to compare those two studies. Do you have a sense of what they were really trying to
find out was the goal of that study? Does a low dose of an easily accessible supplement matter in
people who are healthy? I mean, I assume that's at the most basic level. That was the question.
First primary prevention study, really, that's been done. So they wanted to use it,
was planned 10 years ago. And at that time, one gram of low VASA. So they didn't use a supplement.
They use low VASA, pharmaceutical, but they just use one gram instead of the four grams
indicated by the FDA. And they were looking at cardiovascular disease and cancer. I mean,
it was a huge thing in primary prevention. So they found no effect on cancer. And they found
in their composite endpoint, no statistically significant. It was reduced, but it wasn't
significant. But if you look at certain elements of the composite, they were strongly benefited.
20%. I'm trying to think if there's a 20% reduction in MI, that's what sticks in my mind.
Do you think the most important takeaway from that is if you believe that the study
had a methodologic issue that prevented it from reaching the clinical and statistical significance,
one would want to move forward. Is the bigger knock on that study, the dose,
the patient population that was studied, or the composite endpoint?
All of those together can conspire to have a neutral study when there really are some good
effects that are overlooked. I mean, what people don't balance is the extreme safety of these
products and cheapness. We're looking at something, even one capsule of VASA. It's cheap, completely
safe. It doesn't interact with anything. And if there's even a hint of benefit, why wouldn't
you promote it? Do you think that if a person's listening to this and they're deciding, hey,
this has got me over the goal line as far as I should be using EPA and or DHA, is there an
advantage to using the pharma grade product versus a reputable supplement company? Again,
the two that I like are, and I have no financial ties to any of these companies, just like them
through reputation and having read analyses of their product, but like Carlson's or Nordic
Naturals, for example. I don't think there's a substantial difference at all in quality.
There's a lot of Omega-3 supplement companies that make very high quality stuff that they just
aren't going to the trouble of going through an FDA approval to get it treated and developed as a
drug. But it's the same chemistry. And sometimes, if you get the EPA covered, it might actually be
cheaper than the supplement. The supplements are actually not that cheap. They're actually on the
spectrum of supplements that I take when you compare something like magnesium oxide versus
fish oil. These fish oils are pretty darn expensive supplements.
It's a lot of work to get them to be that pure. One thing I'd say about reduce it,
and back to that one again, you can't buy a pure EPA dietary supplement as far as I know.
No, I think the best we can do, Carlson's does make something called EPA gems.
I'm going to get it wrong, but the gist of it is it's probably 75% to 80% EPA to DHA. So it's heavily
skewed in a direction that's concentrating EPA, which is not the way it normally occurs, of course,
but that's the closest you can get. And is there anything that we haven't talked about, Bill,
on this topic that you would like to add? Is there any other trial that you think it's just really
important that we get to? Well, I don't think there's necessarily a trial, but if I can just
get into what I do now over the last 10 years is I think measuring blood omega-3 levels are really
important. And whether it's the test we do with the omega-3 index, which is red cell EPA, DHA,
or a plasma test or a plasma phospholipid test or whole blood test, whatever, I just think we
need to see more doctors measuring omega-3 status because it means a lot. Low omega-3 means something,
and you know this, but I really want to encourage people to make the assessment of omega-3 status
in their patients as important as measuring cholesterol. Your company is called OmegaQuant,
correct? Right, right. And you've been at the helm of that for about a decade, right?
Yeah, this is our 10th year, right? Yeah, that tells me how much time has flown because I remember
when you had just sort of started that. That's a tough business to be in, right? Because just
laboratory, specialty labs, anything that's not sort of garden variety off the shelf tends to be
sort of misunderstood by the payer environment. And this tends to be a tough place, isn't it?
Yeah, but we're not in the payer environment. We're all cash pay.
Are you? Okay, got it. That's where the quests and the lab cores in the Cleveland's and the
Boston's are. And you used to be health diagnostic lab, of course, back in those days.
So can patients come directly to you or do your tests have to be ordered by physicians?
People can come directly to our website and order the tests. It's $50.
So for $50, a patient can basically receive a kit from you that they take into it. I assume
it's a blood test, not a saliva test or something. It's a finger stick test.
I got it. So they don't even need to go into a lab.
No, no, they just do it at home and send it to us.
That's the same test that I'm getting embedded within my much broader panels, I assume,
where I'm seeing the percent of EPA, DHA, or is that a different company?
What lab is doing it? Well, for example, what was True Health Diagnostics using?
Okay, True Health. So that, yeah, True Health took over from Health Diagnostic Lab and Health
Diagnostic Lab took my test. So they're using my test.
I see. Okay. Do you think there are other tests out there that are directionally comparable or,
I mean, I guess you're a bit conflicted to say that there's other, yeah, it's a loaded question.
Yeah, they're certainly directionally comparable. It's just the number.
Don't do a plasma omega-3 test and expect to get 8 to 12% EPA, DHA.
Plasma doesn't go that high or it's very hard to get that high. So plasma levels are lower
numbers. They correlate pretty well, by and large, with red cells. But red cells are much
more stable long-term marker of omega-3 status than plasma is. So I like the red cell test for
that purpose. So that's pretty much what we use in our research studies is red cell. I'd rather
see a doctor measure a plasma omega-3 than not measure anything.
That's something that people can also get through LabCorpQuest and all of the sort of
more generic labs, I assume. Yeah, I'm not even sure they can get it at LabCorpQuest. It has a
plasma phospholate assay they do. What does Boston Heart do? Do you know?
I think they do a whole plasma. I see. Okay. So going forward, if we're not using THD,
we'll have to figure out a way to come do directly. That'd be great. Love to do it.
We've got a lot of doctors who do it. But I don't know what kind of reimbursement is being paid
for these tests in the insurance world. I think it's not much.
I was about to say I'm going to go with the not much box on that one.
Yeah. Yeah. So.
But again, these aren't tests you have to get every two weeks, right? I mean,
this is the type of test where you get it maybe once a year and you make a change and you look
and see, hey, am I taking enough of this supplement or am I eating enough fish?
Yeah. You see about every four months. It takes about four months after you make a change,
your omega-3 intake to see a new steady state.
Oh, okay. Well, actually that's very interesting. I'm glad you brought that up. I wasn't aware it
was that long actually. I thought you could see a change quicker, but
it's the life of the red blood cell, I guess, to fully turn them over.
Red cell, exactly.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well, that makes sense.
Bill, is there anything else that we didn't discuss on this particular nuanced and super
enjoyable topic?
Golly, I think we ran down the omega-6 stuff. We talked about EPA and DHA alone. There is a big
study that's going to come out, should finish a year from now called Strength that is bigger
than Reduce It and using the same dose as Reduce It, but it's EPA plus DHA.
What dose approximately? So that would be four grams total?
The drug is called Epinova or Epinova. It's from AstraZeneca. It's a 13,000 patient trial,
virtually the same inclusion criteria as Reduce It. It'll be about a five-year follow-up. The
same as Reduce It. I'm pretty sure they're going to get much higher omega-3 index levels than Reduce
It did.
Again, their drug is four grams EPA plus some amount of DHA or four grams total?
It's very much like Lovesa, EPA plus DHA at around about 85 percent, but they're not
ethyl esters. They're free fatty acids. They're unasterified.
Do you think that actually makes any difference?
They're much more readily absorbed.
Because the esterified ones presumably, is it like cholesterol where esterified
variants are much harder to absorb and you risk actually not absorbing them at all?
Well, yeah, that's the problem. It's been shown pretty clearly that if you take an
ethyl ester of omega-3 on an empty stomach, the absorption is quite low, almost none,
as opposed to taking it with food, which improves the absorption quite a bit,
but a triglyceride-based oil or a free fatty acid, more to the point,
free fatty acid doesn't require any enzymatic conversion to get absorbed at all.
The triglyceride has to have, and the ethyl ester both have to have enzymatic conversion in the gut.
Well, that's actually really interesting. I'm glad you brought that up because,
as you know, a lot of people these days are fasting more and more or time restricting
their feeding. It does pose a little bit of a problem the way I've always got around it.
If I don't eat breakfast, which I don't, a lot of the time is I sort of take my fish oil at night
as close to dinner as possible, but it's easier to forget that way. But you're saying another way
around that is if you really just want to take these things in the morning and be done with them,
you basically have to take one of the pharma grade versions because they're the ones that
come as free fatty acids. Right. It's only experimental. I mean, it's not experimental.
It's approved by the FDA, but it's not being marketed. It's the only one that's a free fatty
acid right now is this epanova. The Vasipa and Loveza are ethyl esters.
So basically it'll be about a year before we even have the option to get a free fatty acid version.
That's when their study will finish. And I think it'll be as or more successful than,
than reduce it. That's my guess. And that will be released at the American Heart in 2020.
On their clinicaltrials.gov website, it says the studies will finish in October of next year.
So whether they'll be able to
Scramble an abstract.
We'll see. Yeah. Yeah. Whether, I don't know.
Well, maybe when that study comes up, Bill, we'll have to sit down in early 21 and discuss it.
Love to.
Well, Bill, thanks again. This was really interesting. For me personally,
I learned a lot talking with you about this kind of stuff. I just know that this episode will be
one of those episodes that a lot of people end up coming back to over and over again,
because it is so confusing. So thank you for the historical context, the overview,
and perhaps most importantly, just the sort of nitty gritty details on the health benefits of
these things. Oh yeah. My pleasure. Thank you very much for inviting me. I've really enjoyed it.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
at PeterAttiaMD.com. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame
once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social, you can
find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD, but usually Twitter is
the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the obligatory disclaimer.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the givings of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials
linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this podcast is not intended to be
a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard
or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should seek
the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most
importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies
I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.