Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com. Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode
of the drive. I'd like to take a couple of minutes to talk about why we don't run ads
on this podcast and why instead we've chosen to rely entirely on listener support. If you're
listening to this, you probably already know, but the two things I care most about professionally
are how to live longer and how to live better. I have a complete fascination and obsession with
this topic. I practice it professionally and I've seen firsthand how access to information is
basically all people need to make better decisions and improve the quality of their lives. Curating
and sharing this knowledge is not easy. And even before starting the podcast, that became clear to
me. The sheer volume of material published in this space is overwhelming. I'm fortunate to have a
great team that helps me continue learning and sharing this information with you. To take one
example, our show notes are in a league of their own. In fact, we now have a full-time person that
is dedicated to producing those and the feedback has mirrored this. So all of this raises a natural
question. How will we continue to fund the work necessary to support this? As you probably know,
the tried and true way to do this is to sell ads. But after a lot of contemplation, that model just
doesn't feel right to me for a few reasons. Now the first and most important of these is trust.
I'm not sure how you could trust me if I'm telling you about something when you know I'm being paid
by the company that makes it to tell you about it. Another reason selling ads doesn't feel right to
me is because I just know myself. I have a really hard time advocating for something that I'm not
absolutely nuts for. So if I don't feel that way about something, I don't know how I can talk about
it enthusiastically. So instead of selling ads, I've chosen to do what a handful of others have
proved can work over time and that is to create a subscriber support model for my audience.
This keeps my relationship with you both simple and honest. If you value what I'm doing,
you can become a member and support us at whatever level works for you. In exchange,
you'll get the benefits above and beyond what's available for free. It's that simple. It's my
goal to ensure that no matter what level you choose to support us at, you will get back more
than you give. So for example, members will receive full access to the exclusive show notes,
including other things that we plan to build upon, such as the downloadable transcripts for each
episode. These are useful beyond just the podcast, especially given the technical nature of many of
our shows. Members also get exclusive access to listen to and participate in the regular Ask Me
Anything episodes. That means asking questions directly into the AMA portal and also getting to
hear these podcasts when they come out. Lastly, and this is something I'm really excited about,
I want my supporters to get the best deals possible on the products that I love. And as I said, we're
not taking ad dollars from anyone, but instead what I'd like to do is work with companies who
make the products that I already love and would already talk about for free and have them pass
savings on to you. Again, the podcast will remain free to all, but my hope is that many of you will
find enough value in one, the podcast itself, and two, the additional content exclusive for members
to support us at a level that makes sense for you. I want to thank you for taking a moment to listen
to this. If you learn from and find value in the content I produce, please consider supporting us
directly by signing up for a monthly subscription. My guest this week is Inigo Sanmala. Inigo is a
assistant professor at the University of Colorado School of Medicine where his areas of research
focus on exercise metabolism, nutrition, sports performance, overtraining, diabetes, cancer, and
critical care. And I realize at least one of you at this moment is thinking, how in God's name can
one person study all of those things? And the answer is if you come out of the lens of the
mitochondria, it turns out you can have a breadth of focus that covers all those things. And of course
that's exactly what Inigo does. He studies mitochondrial performance and mitochondrial
efficiency. And it's based on that that the moment he and I met a year ago, it was a sort of love at
first sight. And we've been geeking out together ever since. Inigo has had a profound impact on
my training, the way I talk to my patients about exercise, and the way I've thought about
longevity through the lens of mitochondrial performance. He is an internationally renowned
applied physiologist. He's worked for at least 20 years with many professional teams,
elite athletes across all sports. He himself is a remarkable athlete, which we barely get into. He's
so modest and unassuming. He currently works with a number of professional cycling teams at the
highest level, including at the level of the Tour de France. He's pioneered a number of things
that we get into here, everything from using high frequency ultrasound to assessed glycogen levels,
to more importantly, ways in which we can use biopsies at the invasive level and blood tests
at the less invasive level to draw on the insights of mitochondrial performance. It would take me an
hour to simply explain the treasure trove of stuff we explore in this episode. So I'm not even
going to try to say what we get into other than if you're interested in mitochondria, if you're
interested in fitness, if you're interested in exercise, if you're interested in metabolic health,
all of the above. I think you just need to listen to this one and take my word for it without seeing
the running commentary. The show notes, of course, will be especially important for this one because
some of this stuff just is better explained through pictures than words. And of course,
there will be a nice effective table of contents there. So without further delay,
please enjoy my conversation with Inigo.
Inigo, thank you so much for making time to sit down today in your new office here.
Thank you very much, Peter. It's my pleasure and honor that you're here with us at the University
of Colorado at the School of Medicine. I emailed my team. I emailed Nick and Bob and a couple of
the guys today when I was on the way over here. I was on the plane and I was reviewing my notes.
And I thought, I am so excited to sit down with you today and Rick tomorrow, because we've had so
many kind of off the cuff sidebar conversations about mitochondria, mitochondrial function,
health, efficiency, etc. And it's sort of like we never have enough time. It's like 15 minutes here
and 12 minutes there and an email here and an email there. But it was in preparing for this,
the team helped me really kind of put a lot of my thoughts together. But I think
before we kind of get into the really hardcore stuff around mitochondria, which is something
that I think anybody who's interested in health at any level, whether it's really at the deep cellular
level or just at the level of I want to live as long as I can, as healthy as I can, everybody sort
of has a sense that all roads point to the mitochondria. But your path to getting there to
me is particularly interesting because it starts with looking at athletes and you yourself, even
though you downplay it a lot, you were quite the athlete growing up. So you grew up in Spain and
what sports did you play? Yeah, I grew up in Spain and I played for Real Madrid for the academy for
six years. And I was always very passionate about sport. Then I, when I turned 16, I discovered
cycling and that's the way I changed sports. So my dad still thinks that was the dumbest decision
of my life. But is that true statistically with a child growing up in Spain who's already in the
feeder program for Real Madrid, would they have a better chance of having a career as a professional
football player than a professional cyclist? That's hard to say, but when you're already
at that age in Real Madrid, you can be getting to the top team is very difficult obviously, but
definitely be a feeder to other smaller teams. That's a higher possibility, but you never know,
but you have to follow your passion, I guess. And I followed it and I changed to cycling and
I got to race professionally for two years at a low level. So I always say that I admitted I'm
a truncated and a frustrated professional athlete because I never got to the top. But that said,
I learned a lot and it's been a school of life all my life since I was nine years old. I've been
in the high level of competition up until today on the other side of the table, working with
athletes. And that's what I became very familiar with everything related to the elite sports and
that everything that involves. I don't think most people who have not themselves been on a bicycle
and trying to do something at a reasonably high level can appreciate that even being a professional
quote unquote low level, I guess what you're saying by that is you were not necessarily on a team that
was even going to go to the big grand tours and such, but I still think most people don't understand
the level, how much higher that is above a general fitness athlete type of thing. So when you were
at that level, what was your specialty? Were you a time trialist? Were you, you look too tall to
be a climber, but who knows what you weighed back then? Yeah, I was very skinny though. You're
taller than me. I'm like 5'11. Okay, so you're an inch taller. But I used to be 143, 145 pounds.
Oh wow. So I was very skinny. So I used to be a good climber. I was good overall, but I'm better
as a climber. But yeah, I, is that I appreciate it now when I see people who are category ones or
twos or threes as a cyclist or so that their fitness level is very good, that definitely my
fitness level was better. But at the same time, there is like a whole world between my fitness
level and what the two of the friends guys have. It is unbelievable when I was sort of going
through category five, four, three, two, by some metrics, I could maybe time trial at the level of
category two, three, but of course, my climbing and sprinting and everything else would have been
like a category four. And you realize that the guy who's category one, the guys I used to train
with who are collegiate athletes who are exceptional at category one, they're still not even pro.
They're still a step between them and a domestic pro. And then the domestic pro to get from that
level to a European pro and then the European pro to get to a major team. And then to be on a major
team and the difference between the GC contender and everybody else. We're talking about log orders
of ability. It's not subtle. No, and I have all the data from all these years collecting the data.
And I know very well the physiological parameters typical of a top junior athlete or category three
category two, one domestic pro average pro tour, cyclists and best of the best. And the difference
is amazing, but they're very significant. You can really categorize people accordingly. We're going
to come back and start to talk about professional cycling and things. And there's so many things I
want to talk about because I think for also the person who's not immediately wed to the sport,
might too easily want to dismiss the accolades of these athletes and the physiologic prowess
as simply, well, you know, those guys all use drugs. And while that's probably true at some level
with respect to some drugs and certainly a certain class of athletes, it in no way diminishes what
their physiology looks like completely off drugs. So we'll come back to all that, but going to you.
So after two years at a professional level, what made you decide, I'm not going to continue doing
this. I'm going to pursue my education and the other things that you've gone on to do.
I realized that it's very difficult and you need to be in the right place at the right time,
at the right moment, and that different planets need to be aligned. It is not just the best.
Always get up there to call it destiny, call it whatever. But a lot of things have to happen to
become a pro and I were not on my side. What at the same time I needed to make a decision either
trying to get an education that can not assure me, but at least give me some future,
professionally speaking, outside the sport or try to go for the sport where the planets were
not aligned. I didn't know if I could even make it and it would take that sacrifice. So that's
what I decided. I think this is not good for me. And then as I was studying also, I had a good
possibility of doing a very good internship at a top, if not the top sports medicine clinic in Spain.
In fact, the famous PRP therapy was born in that clinic. And that's where I said,
I had a good possibility to start internship and then became a part-time job. And at that time I
said, okay, I'm just going to stay here and continue. And how long have you been here at
the university of Colorado? 11 years. Okay. Now you and I met through an interesting circumstance.
It's a funny story. I don't know if you remember the very first time, but I had just flown into
Abu Dhabi and I think I came straight from the airport to the training facility and it was like
11 o'clock at night or something. And you put me right on the bike and we did a VO2 max test. And
which anybody who's done a VO2 max test on a bike knows there's nothing very pleasant about it.
You've got this mask that is incredibly restrictive. I hadn't done one since I stopped cycling. So that
was probably six, five years or six years. And then I think you weren't happy with the air mixer
because we were getting weird numbers. And it was at some point, I think when I hit about 50 milliliters
per milligram per kilogram, we sort of said that's enough. And that was a good thing because
I don't think I had much more. It's amazing how much you lose when you stop training that zone.
I never thought there could be a day when my VO2 max could be below 50. I thought it'll be 50
when I'm a hundred, right? That's not true. It really falls away. Yeah, it falls apart. Yeah.
So I would be surprised if I could hit 55 today actually. But we connected immediately because
it was a great point in my life where I was almost, I was sort of looking for direction
as a former, I don't even want to use the word athlete to describe myself, but as a person who
formerly took training very seriously to now someone who was trying to think about reshaping
my training around longevity, it was a perfect collision of ideas because I was sort of in
search of what to really focus on. And what we immediately clicked over was your protocol for
zone two training, which you were instituting heavily with the UAE team and other folks that
you were training there. And the rest is history. I mean, it's really completely shaped the way I
think about using this type of training as a way to improve mitochondrial function and as a way to
test it. I almost think at this point for the listener, we should pause for a moment and explain
these energy systems because so much of what I want to ask you about and so much of what your
research focuses on assumes a level of understanding I don't want to take for granted.
So maybe explain for people what aerobic metabolism means.
Okay, so there are different energy systems and those energy systems, they're also used by
different muscle fibers in the muscle. There are different conditions like the aerobic condition
and anaerobic condition. We tend to believe that the immense majority of activity that we do is
aerobic. We tend to believe that any hard effort is anaerobic and therefore the concept of anaerobic
threshold. But actually even what we call the anaerobic threshold is an aerobic activity. So
the majority of the efforts that we do are in an anaerobic environment except for when you do
sprint or when you do maybe like a one minute maximum. I would say that the majority of the
activities that we do are in the aerobic state. Then what changes is the fuels that you use to
produce energy. So at the end of the day what we want to do is to contract the muscles and not only
to contract them as fast and as forceful as possible but what we want also is to do this as
efficiently as possible. So for example for a marathon race or for a 1500 meter race you need
to calculate when you pull the trigger and go for it and then when you have to deploy all the
maximum efficiency that you have. So you need to be very efficient metabolically speaking. So the
fuels are very important for that. So the main fuels that we use for exercise are the fatty acids
and glucose and those are oxidized or burned in the different skeletal muscle fibers that we have.
So we have the slow twitch muscle fibers and the fast twitch muscle fibers. The fast twitch muscle
fibers are divided into the type 1a and type 2b if you will. Two people contact 2x as well but
there are two kinds of muscle fibers. I just want to interject for a moment because I know a lot of
people listening to this have heard the term fast twitch and slow twitch and the assumption is that
they twitch at different speeds but really it's that they twitch with a different force and the
speed is referring to how quickly they fatigue not the speed with which they fire. So when you're
talking about a type 1 or a slow twitch muscle fiber it's just a less forceful fiber whereas a
type 2 fiber and as you said they're divided into a's and b's with each firing with each time the
muscle fiber fires there are more motor end plates and therefore it's generating more force
but the trade-off is it's going to be more quick to fatigue and why is that? Why does it fatigue
faster because it comes down to what you're talking about. Yeah it's because metabolically
they're more stressed. The way we recruit muscle fibers or base sequential pattern that is very
similar to the stick gears of a manual car. So you first start and you go on first gear and as the
rpms go up then you get to a point you get to the red zone so that car cannot keep up with that
first gear. You need to shift the second gear and you speed up and the rpms go higher and then
eventually you need to shift to third gear. This is very similar to what happens at the skeletal
muscle. The type 1 muscle fibers slow twitch they can produce ATP which is the energy coin
the classic that we always hear about which is what releases that muscle contraction. So at low
exercise intensities we don't need to contract the muscles nearly as forceful nor as fast as when we
do high intensity. Meaning we don't need to go back and keep firing and keep firing and keep
firing. Exactly and for that we don't need to generate ATP as fast as we do at higher intensities
and it's about ATP generation that's exercise intensity. So at low exercise intensities those
slow twitch muscle fibers or type 1 muscle fibers they are very well designed to use an energy
that is good enough to provide ATP and yet you can do this for a very long time and that's the
diesel gasoline and that is the fatty acids. However as exercise intensity increases
the necessity to produce ATP at a higher rate increases as well and it gets to a point where
fatty acids alone are not enough to produce ATP and therefore you need another energy system
and that energy system is the glucose which is a faster energy system which going back to the
analogy of the car is like if we had imagine a car with two tanks one is gasoline and the other one
or regular gasoline and the other one is diesel gasoline. So if you were to go from here to Denver
to Kansas where everything is flat and you need to accelerate or go fast you would try to be more
efficient and we'll try to use then the diesel gasoline it's more economical you get more
malaise per gallon but if you want to go to the mountains and you need to accelerate fast that
diesel might not do the trick you need extra acceleration so that's where you utilize the
glucose and that's a very I mean the regular gasoline which is like the glucose for the
muscles and that's kind of how the bioenergetics or the muscles kind of principles start. I like
the way you've explained it and I did a much worse job I think probably seven years ago I wrote a
blog post on this the insight I was trying to get across I don't know if I did was that we should
not think of aerobic and anaerobic as with or without oxygen which is sort of the way people
are taught in high school biology aerobic means in the presence of oxygen anaerobic means not in the
presence of oxygen no it's always in the presence of oxygen it comes down to the speed with which
the muscle is demanding ATP aerobic means you're generating ATP at a rate that is slow enough that
all of the metabolic demands can be met through mitochondrial oxidation of hopefully mostly fatty
acids but even glucose anaerobic just means exactly as you said the demand for ATP has now exceeded
the capacity of the mitochondria do you agree with that and even the cytosol so the cytosol which
is part of the cell that's where you can oxidize glucose there into parruvate and that parruvate
doesn't enter the mitochondria but you produce lactate but you produce energy and ATP there
and that can perfectly be still aerobic capacity and my colleague George Brooks from Berkeley he's
been studying lactate since the 80s and he's the one who proved that that you can produce lactate
under fully aerobic conditions not necessarily in the mitochondria but in the cytosol however
when the ATP demands even exceed the cytosolic production of ATP that's what you need to use the
ATP that is already stored in the muscle you just don't have time to synthesize it you need
just to use it and that's why the body stores very very minimal amounts of ATP and that's what
you develop in the sprint where you use in the sprint but you need to re-synthesize it very fast
that's the pure anaerobic you don't need any energy systems and that goes also that of the
confusion that is out there too and are you saying this is distinct from the creatine phosphate system
yeah you can use the creatine phosphate as well so you can have ATP and you can use the
creatine phosphate systems those two they don't need oxygen necessarily anything else can be under
fully aerobic conditions like even cytosolic production of ATP in in the cytosol without
mitochondria oxidation necessarily can happen under fully aerobic conditions and in fact
that's what we also call aerobic glycolysis and in other areas of biomedical research or medicine
it's called the Warburg effect which is now a lot of people are into cancer talk about it
the Warburg effect is that is the production of lactate or the utilization of glucose
in the cytosol not in the mitochondria but in the cytosol outside the mitochondria production of
energy well i want to come back to the warburg effect but you brought up brooks and there's a
paper that the two of you wrote together somewhat recently i think it was maybe 2018 if not this
year but it's actually i'm in the process of writing a book as you may recall and in the
exercise chapter i actually really explore that paper that you guys wrote which looked at the
zone two efficiency of world-class cyclists recreational athletes and people with diabetes
that's an unbelievable paper and that's an unbelievable example of i think the clinical
applicability of what we're talking about so to put it in context when we got talking back in
Abu Dhabi last year about this i remember you saying i'm paraphrasing so you should clarify if
i'm not saying it correctly that your interest in athletes is in large part due to your interest in
diabetes because if you want to understand how to fix an example of arguably the most
effective mitochondria why not at least study what the perfect mitochondria look like is that
a fair statement yes and that's kind of what i'm trying to bring to the table in the elite
athletes have the perfect metabolism and mitochondria is at the epicenter of metabolism and health as
you said earlier there are no other population in the planet with the mitochondria of elite endurance
athletes i was about to say yeah you said elite athletes i would go even sharper it really in
my mind comes down to cyclists and runners yes and triathletes even more than swimmers because of
just the duration of it it's these people who can go out and function at their anaerobic threshold
for hours and that's only really found in two sports oh yes and that's what we we see that even
with an elite athlete and i work with many elite athletes yeah you compare them and they're huge
differences i guess i should add one i think cross-country skiers are probably yeah those
levels as well yeah so this population is the population in the planet with the healthiest
mitochondria so that's what i call perfection and that's what i try to bring to the table that
in order to study other diseases where mitochondrial dysfunction is at the epicenter as well
we need to understand what perfection is in order to understanding perfection and what we see in
people with type 2 diabetes for example they are on the opposite metabolic pole of what a war class
cyclist or runner is so by knowing the mechanisms of why that metabolism in this war class athletes
works we can get to understand the imperfection or the imperfect metabolic pathways and potentially
develop diagnostic tools and even therapeutics for them as well as prevention programs yeah and
really cancer and type 2 diabetes or insulin resistance as part of a spectrum do represent two
very common findings in the population so if you look at what percentage of the united states
population either has cancer or is insulin resistant or has metabolic syndrome and or
type 2 diabetes or fatty liver disease all of these things which are part of a continuum
you're talking about half the country basically that has some form of dysfunction in the mitochondria
in the case of cancer we can debate how much of that is a genetic insult versus other things but
because i want to talk so much about that i want to go back and understand perfection a bit more
so there are lots of different ways people codify energy systems when i was cycling we used seven
because that was andy coghans ftp based energy system you write about six zones and others have
talked about five but i want to talk about your six zones because one i think they're a little
easier to explain than the ftp based ones which if you don't know if a functional threshold power
number doesn't mean something to someone then seven energy systems based on it is harder to
understand how would you walk us through zones one through six what do they mean because when we
start to talk about zone two i want people to understand the difference between the normal
person and the super person and the sick person so what is zone one what does that so that's from
25 years working with athletes and also my experience from being a former athlete and
being obsessed with training and and all these things that's kind of it led me to develop this
i'm not saying that they're the right things and maybe in 10 years i change my mind or someone
else comes with different things are better but that's what i have right now at least so i do this
along with the muscle fiber recruitment pattern and the energy systems so the type one muscle fibers
we know also that because they're the ones who oxidize fat burn the fat very well they have the
highest mitochondrial density and content because fat can only be burned in the mitochondria type
two muscle fibers especially the first type of muscle fibers type two the type two a's they have
lower mitochondrial function because lower mitochondrial function or density i'm sorry
because they don't necessarily need to oxidize glucose in the mitochondria they can do it in the
site in the cytosol of the cell and therefore i produce lactate but they can produce it to be fast
so those muscle fibers they don't content as much mitochondria and then the second type of muscle
slow fast twitch muscle fiber the type 2b or 2x that is the one that is the pure anaerobic if you
will and that is the one that barely has mitochondria has very minimal mitochondria so starting with
that that's why i start breaking down the zone so the zone one would represent the minimum stimulation
the muscle fibers receive it's just pre-reconstruction that's what will you do on a recovery day or
recovery mode you have very low exercise intensity and you burn a little bit of fat
mainly and that's what we see also we look at also fat and carbohydrate utilization
scientifically we call it fighting carbohydrate oxidation rates how many grams per minute of
carbohydrate and fat you burn so we know that at this intensity is you burn mostly fat although
you also burn a little bit of carbohydrates which we can go through that yeah i want to come back
to it because there's such an interesting clinical observation that i've seen over the past five or
six years and your paper your recent paper with brooks just hammered it home in a much more rigorous
way so yeah we are going to come back to our queue at rest as a harbinger of these other things that
follow under distress yeah so that's the zone one so just to put that in energy terms for people
you and i walking up the stairs we were coming from the lobby we're in zone one yeah walking down
the street walking down the street or review or very fit and you go for a jog very easy recovery
day that's your zone one and then for the elite give us an example so if you took meb or someone
who's going to run a sub 210 marathon you have a sense of how fast they could run and still be in
zone one someone who's used to running 445 to 450 miles could their zone one be as fast as like a
seven minute mile yeah yeah absolutely you can see world class athletes that their zone one it's
my sprinting for example it's kind of what we see also in cyclists the recovery day is 200 watts
average and for most murmurals 200 watts they can do that for 15 minutes yeah i just wrote a post
about this recently using as an example for people who ride a bike 200 watts is about how fast it would
take you to go 30 kilometers an hour without wind or without elevation and that's certainly not all
out but that's pretty fast and if you can imagine being able to ride at that level indefinitely
without any metabolic consequence that's what an elite athlete is doing and that says nothing by
the way about their weight they're doing that at a body weight that is a fraction of most people
yeah that's what they call the coffee right yeah they go for a coffee or ice cream right and
you cheat chat and they're like it's an unbelievable so zone one does lactate get produced it should
not get produced well we start from the base that there's always lactate producing the body
so if you were to poke my finger right now or poke your finger right now we measure lactate
in millimolar what would you expect to measure in me or you you would be about one millimole okay
0.7 to one millimole that's kind of like a standard resting levels in a healthy individual
and in a normal person so not an elite athlete but sort of a recreational athlete
what's the highest lactate you'll typically measure in that person if you put them in a
treadmill test or it depends on the protocol that you do if it's a very violent protocol or is a
longer protocol violent protocols they produce more lactate you might see 10 12 millimoles whether
that protocol let's say a six minutes maximal effort and a rowing machine right and the concept
for example i've seen war class rollers it's a maximal effort with 20 millimoles of lactate
it's very rare you see very easily 15 16 17 that's because we can talk about that later their
glycolytic capacity it's off the charts whereas people who they're not elite athletes it's for
them that's in protocol it's more difficult to go over 12 millimoles 10 millimoles because
their glycolytic capacity is not so good as the one that the elite athletes have and sometimes
elite athletes have the opposite issue which is they don't make much lactate at all they're so
efficient i've actually discussed this with lance armstrong after i erroneously had been on a podcast
and made the case that he had a very high lactate tolerance he were talking about it one day
informally and he said no it's actually the opposite i would barely produce any lactate
he was usually producing less lactate than others and again this was when everybody's on the same
drug or everybody's off the same drug i mean just genetically there are some people who probably have
more mct which will come back and talk to and they become more efficient at it but okay so that gives
us a sense that lactate will go from maybe one to ten if you're a normal person maybe one to 20
i actually measured it difficult i measured a lactate of 24 and a friend of mine once wow the
highest i've ever measured in myself was 19.7 wow and that was only a four minute protocol
wow pretty impressive but also i almost wonder like maybe it's i wasn't even in particularly
great shape at the time but i wonder if that same exertion under better fitness would have
produced less lactate potentially right it depends on the protocol right if the protocol stops there
and what you intend is to produce mobilize the glycolytic system to the maximum yeah you will
produce a lot of lactate if you want to continue and do a longer protocol eventually you just
cannot mobilize as much lactate i mean as much glycolytic system because you have a little more
of fatigue i think the difference between the really good people i mean i hit if i hit and
i've been above 18 and maybe a dozen times i'm done for half an hour like i can barely get up
off the floor to go and take a shower whereas this friend of mine who was at 24 i saw him go
from 24 to 14 in a span of about seven minutes and then jump in the pool and swim another race
and he's world-class so that's sort of the difference i think the world-class athlete
can also clear the lack much quicker than i can for sure and that's what happens in the mitochondria
and any other part of the body because one thing with lactate we believe that is a waste product
however lactate is the most important if not the most important fuel for the body that's a profound
statement yes i completely agree with you that lactate is not a waste product but
say more about that point so one of the things the brain prefers to use lactate so i have heard
this talk to me about the data on this so my colleague george brooks who is lactate man
so yeah he started in doing research with tbi traumatic brain injury patients at ucla it's
typical to give them glucose and then what there's like a brain injury but the brain in the first
place has evolved to use glucose as the main fuel so when the brain is injured they use more
glucose however when it's injured different metabolic pathways might be dysregulated so
what my colleague george brooks suggested was to give them lactate and he showed and he probably
stayed do better better than beta hydroxybutyrate which also seems to be really beneficial in tbi
patients for maybe a different reason than lactate although it could be all similar which is
if you buy the argument which i find favorable that part of the insult of tbi is pyruvate
dehydrogenase becomes resistant to insulin that would explain why glucose becomes ineffective in
those patients and it would explain why beta hydroxybutyrate can bypass it and the same could
be true of lactate yes absolutely it's an alternative substrate that doesn't get limited
through pyruvate dehydrogenase is that what you think is happening yes because it has its own
transporter in the mitochondria and doesn't need pth for that it can enter the mitochondria
directly for energy systems like hydroxybutyrate as well but the thing is like lactate is a faster
fuel so the thing is like also yeah bhb is not a fast fuel exactly whereas lactate is as fast if
not faster it's glucose because it doesn't have to be processed if you will now the listener might
say wait a minute what are you guys talking about anyone who's ever done a lactate test knows how
much pain you're in when your lactate level goes up so one of the other i think misunderstandings
is what's actually causing that pain because that's i think why so many of us have a negative
association with lactate it's not actually the lactate that's causing the physical discomfort
that you feel when you're vomiting on the floor after a maximal lactate test it's the hydrogen
so explain why that's the case and why we tend to confound the two i mean there are many causes for
pain or fatigue that in different hypotheses from the central fatigue to the peripheral fatigue
and it's very possible that both are interconnected at some point and we don't know the exact
mechanisms at some point the central fatigue calls for the brain to be the ruler where the
peripheral fatigue is what happens at the cellular level so it is possible that there's like a
crosstalk among both of them and either the chicken or the egg right either one of them says stop but
what we know is that yeah it's not lactate itself but the hydrogen ions associated to lactate they
build up one of the things that and it's been researched they can decrease both the contractive
capacity of the muscle fibers as well as the force by up to 50 percent or more so that's one of the
things that what we see is like the muscles they cannot contract as fast or as forceful as before
and this is an important point for people to understand because if you haven't taken a
physiology course when why would most people do so it's also not obvious why you even need ATP
to make your muscles contract it's actually to unleash or unlock the actin myosin contact it's
the relaxation phase of the muscle that requires energy exactly so now if you imagine anybody
who's done that sit on the rowing machine for four minutes and go as hard as you can well
at the end of that anyone who's done it will acknowledge it feels like you can't actually
contract your muscle you've lost the voluntary ability to make them do what you want to do
and it's really two things going on it's this hydrogen poison and then on top of that you're
not generating enough ATP to hit all of those fibers that need to be uncoupled from their actin
and myosin so anyone who's been there knows like it you think i'm going crazy why can i not make
myself do this yeah and that's where maybe the central fatigue component the brain might be
factoring in as well kicking in and say hey dude you know you slow down you're getting to a point
that this is not physiological so i'm going to protect your muscles and they're telling me through
different signals one might be the hydrogen ions which also are produced from the hydrolysis of the
breakdown or ATP they produce also hydrogen so you have the lactate on one hand and the ATP of the
fast rate of ATP hydrolysis also produces hydrogen ions but yeah as you said very well like you're
conscious once but there's something at the neuromuscular level also that impedes that could
be at the local level specifically but could also perfectly be that the brain says hey let's stop it
and one of the things that we know when people are fatigued is that there's a decrease in adrenalin
secretion to protect yourself because adrenaline or I mean epinephrine we call it here in the US
epinephrine in europe is called adrenaline is the major or one of the major elements involved in the
breakdown of glycogen into glucose we can talk about that later as part of the overtraining but
uh the adrenergic activity it's also decreased as well when someone is in a fatigued state so by the
way Alex Hutchinson has written a great book on this have you have you read his book Endure i
heard about it but it's really good again it's good for someone like me who comes into this without
world-class knowledge and i found it a very interesting survey in fact i hope to have him
on the podcast at some point to go into some real depth on that so now we've talked about the two
ends of the spectrum the most extreme end and the first end let's now get into zone two what's
happening physiologically is that athlete or that person enters zone two so the zone two is that now
then when you start stimulating those slow twitch muscle fibers to the fullest let's imagine that
you're in that first gear that i mentioned earlier in the manual stick car and then you're in that
red zone and that's where the car is asking you hey shift the second gear and that's where like
you're forcing physiologically because the body adapts to say no you get stronger at this gear
that's kind of that zone too is like when you stimulate those muscle fibers before you start
changing to a whole different environment where you start then recruiting fully the type two or
fast twitch muscle fibers and therefore the different energy system which is the glucose
so the zone two coincides also with what we call the fat max which is exercise intensity at the
one you oxidize the highest amount of fat and then we can see that clearly in the laboratory
as we saw in the graph that we can show yeah we're going to include a lot of great pictures here
so if you're looking at the show notes there's something called the metabolic map which is a
great slide that we'll walk through this and i think what's very interesting here this occurs
so often in physiology it's a bit counterintuitive as you go from zone one to two to three to four
five and six you're generating more and more ATP as you go up that chain so that part is monotonic
it's increasing without stopping but there's a local maximum that's occurring in zone two
which is your highest amount of fat oxidation so as you go from zone two to three to four
you will still produce more energy you will consume even more oxygen your vo2 max has not
been achieved which is your maximal uptake of oxygen but you will now become less efficient
and you're moving to a less efficient fuel you're moving away from this diesel example or the fat
so again i think for a lot of people the semantics get confusing here because you just said that
zone two is your maximum i mean maybe a better way to explain it for me is zone two is the place
at which your mitochondria are producing the maximum amount under purely aerobic conditions
of ATP is that fair i would say that too and that's where you're still recruiting those type
one muscle fibers that's the extra intensity where you're cruising the most and they had the
highest stimulus without tipping into the twos that's basically it and since that type one muscle
fibers have the highest mitochondrial density you're really stimulating them a lot as you said
before you need to tap into the fast twitch muscle fibers and in the moment you tap into the fast
twitch muscle fibers is because the ATP demand that you need cannot be covered by fat and you
need to switch to a different fuel and that's where we see a big drop in fat oxidation and we
see an increase also in glucose oxidation and that's when we start seeing also an increase in
lactate as well because lactate is always and we forgot to mention that earlier lactate is the
mandatory byproduct not waste product byproduct of glucose utilization mandatory every time you
use glucose you use lactate and at higher intensity you produce more let's talk about that because
again i think that's more nuanced than most of us would come to this discussion with we learned in
physiology class that a molecule of glucose in the cytosol is turned into two molecules of pyruvate
under conditions of sufficient cellular oxygen to meet the ATP demand the pyruvate enters the
mitochondria where it undergoes oxidative phosphorylation to make ATP and no lactate is generated
if that ATP demand exceeds the capacity that you just described in zone two we now have to
start turning some of that pyruvate into lactate to generate additional ATP that's faster to generate
in the first case that i described is there still by necessity some lactate production yes there's
some lactate production and and we can see that even at rest we have or with a little bit of lactate
in our bloodstream which is what you said at the outside you said if you checked my finger or your
finger now we would probably still have somewhere between 0.7 and one millimole of lactate why is
that that's where we're trying to understand and we believe my colleague george brooks and i
that lactate is a major signaling molecule that when it's regulated it can signal and maintain
homeostasis of different metabolic pathways it's kind of like a visa for the body as my
colleague george brooks calls it when it's dysregulated as we're starting to see in cancer for
example or we can see in type 2 diabetes it can dysregulate different pathways every cell in the
body produces lactate and pretty much every cell in the body consumes lactate including red blood
cells i'm guessing yes they produce a lot of lactate red blood cells because they don't have
mitochondria yeah i wonder it's glycolytic mechanism yeah do the red blood cells account
for most of the lactate production we see at baseline not necessarily because there's not
so much hemolysis and there's not so much lactivity in the red blood cells but there's
always some metabolic lactate produced from glucose utilization because we always use a
little bit of glucose of course the brain but uh that lactate escapes to the blood to the circulation
and for us is significant that is always so steady also and every cell in the body produces lactate
and almost every cell in the body utilizes lactate so it's gotta be a why and we believe
and that's what we're trying to scratch the surface that it's a very important signaling
molecule that goes beyond being a byproduct or metabolite and that's something that we're
already seeing in cancer where we have seen that lactate stimulates the expression of the major
oncogenes transgusion factors and cell cycle genes in breast cancer so it acts and we have
the paper under review now it acts as a signaling molecule so this is interesting because again in
physiology class you sort of learn that all of that waste lactate goes back to the liver and the
core cycle converts it into glucose and it becomes now stored glucose but what you're saying is it's
much broader than that i mean obviously the core cycle still exists but it's not even clear how
much of the lactate that we're measuring is undergoing that pathway to be converted back
to glucose versus itself being consumed as a fuel correct yes and thanks to the great work that my
colleague brux did starting the 80s what he saw is that the majority of that lactate is oxidized
by the slow twitch muscle fibers by the mitochondria of the slow twitch muscle fibers
and each mole of lactate gives how many moles of ATP under those conditions i don't have it on top
of my is it a small number or big yeah it'll be smaller number as well but it's not like the 16
or whatever you know no no no no i don't think i don't have it on top of my head but the thing is a
constant flux of lactate from the fast twitch muscle fibers to the slow twitch muscle fibers
that's when you start entering that zone three you start mobilizing more of the glycolytic system
and that's kind of a transition state where you still mix fuels fatty acids and carbohydrates
but you start using more carbohydrates and therefore you start producing lactate
that say that lactate is transported from mainly from the fast twitch muscle fibers into the
mitochondria of the slow twitch muscle fibers where is used for energy it enters directly
the mitochondria for energy purposes and that is the ability that elite athletes have they can be
recruiting fast twitch muscle fibers they can be utilizing a lot of glucose and producing a lot of
lactate but since they have a very well developed mitochondria in the slow twitch muscle fibers
they don't need to export it to the blood and it doesn't accumulate yeah this to me is the grail
this is the stuff that sets apart the best from the rest going back to zone two tell me where
you typically see a lactate level there you and i have talked about a bunch of these numbers when
i try to explain this to my patients because i have many of my patients on a zone two protocol
for a lot of the time we just use voice we use ability to talk i sort of say look if you don't
want to go through the protocol of poking your finger zone two is about the highest level of
exertion at which you're still able to carry out a conversation but let's talk more technically
we're really seeing what lactate levels of about 1.7 to 1.9 millimole yeah 1.5 to 2 that's something
what we see and that's kind of what corresponds also to that fat max so today my data that i showed
you from my ride this morning i was 1.3 and 1.2 on my two meters so i always do two separate meters
so i averaged 1.25 millimolar that was clearly not zone two that was a zone one the feeder
that you get like for example a world class athlete at zone two is really high yeah well
i'm not world class but just by lactate levels that's probably not quite there yeah it might
not be quite there because it's slightly above resting levels so there's no accumulation and
it's this accumulation there's a homeostasis or a steady state below two so call it 1.7 1.8 1.9
where you're right at the limit of not accumulating at a net level correct yes yes so you're pretty
much that lactic comes you obviously see it in the blood and it comes from the muscles so that means
that the muscles overall are good first they're not very metabolically stressed so therefore
they're not utilizing a lot of glucose and even if they're stressed they're clearing the lactate
very well because you see in blood 1.5 1.7 2 millimoles slightly above resting levels
however when you start seeing higher lactate levels in the blood that means that your muscle
clearance capacity cannot meet no i think what you're saying if i understand is once you hit
two three four five millimolar you're saying that the muscles ability to recirculate and utilize
the lactate is going down it has to export into the circulation exactly and that's where it goes
to every cell in the body it goes to the brain it goes to the kidney goes to the heart the heart is
great utilize or lactate and obviously as you said earlier goes to the core recycle to be
resynthesized back to glucose or to a certain length for form of glycogen but yeah that's when
we see that in blood that means that that athlete cannot clear the lactate efficiently and therefore
that's why it shows up in the blood and that's where we can see that for example one professional
athlete a 300 watts a world-class athlete my let's say yeah 300 watts might have three millimoles of
lactate let's say or two and a half and a mermural might have 12 that means that the power output is
the same but how do you get there it's different in the first place the elite athlete might not
need to use so much glucose and if they do they produce lactate but they clear out so efficiently
in the slow twitch muscle fibers that it doesn't have to go to the blood whereas the person who
doesn't have a very good mitochondrial function cannot oxidize lactate very efficiently locally
in the skeletal muscle and they have to export it to the circulation and that's a way to see the
metabolic stress and indirectly as we published a way to look at what is the matter kind of function
so let's talk about that now i do want to come back and talk about zones three and up but because
this is the perfect point to go back to the paper you and brooks recently wrote what you showed that
i just thought was so elegant was as you said you can either cap the output or clamp the power
required or clamp the lactate production and look at the power required and you did the latter you
basically said we're going to find everybody's zone two meaning we're going to find everybody's tipping
point at which point their mitochondria are no longer high enough in function to meet the
requirement and what you showed was world-class cyclists were able to get to an average of
something like 300 watts before they would finally flip that switch and have to start
recruiting the fast switch muscle fibers which was measured indirectly by lactate production
conversely the weekend warrior reasonably fit people guys like me could get to 200 watts
before that switch got flipped but most interesting was the people with type 2 diabetes
i think we're like 120 watts is that about right yeah we've been knowing for years now that are
typical characteristic that we know of people with pre type 2 or type 2 diabetes is that they have a
poor metabolic flexibility that is called also a poor capacity to oxidize fuels one of them is fat
we know that fat can only be oxidized in the mitochondria therefore by measuring the fat
oxidation of these patients we can indirectly see the mitochondrial function especially when
we put them in context or in comparison with those ones who are healthy individuals that could be
moderately active individuals who don't have diabetes or pre-diabetes or don't have any
medications or elite athletes so that's what we see that their fat capacity is very very low
and that's gonna but we can see directly but it's not often you see in biology such a difference
because if the numbers 300 versus 200 versus 100 sound extreme that's nothing compared to when you
normalize by weight so really the answer is in watts per kilo what's the difference and 300 watts
to a professional cyclist who only weighs 60 to 65 kilos is just below five watts per kilogram
whereas the person with diabetes almost assuredly weighs more so their 120 watts is probably 1.5
watts per kilo they're not a lot of examples of things in physiology where you see that much of
a difference you rarely even see that much of a difference in average glucose level between
someone with diabetes and not so this is this functional definition that you guys have proposed
is to me very important just as a clinician just as someone who's trying to gather more data
about a patient to understand their health it's sort of like in a magic scenario in a magic world
you would have these data on every single person you would want to know what is your zone two
threshold and that becomes a way to assess mitochondrial function now the story i was going
to tell earlier at this is as good a time as i need to tell it about five years ago in some of
the most insulin resistant patients that i was taking care of i began looking at baseline resting
respiratory quotient which you alluded to earlier this is the ratio of produced carbon dioxide to
consumed oxygen say a little bit about that number and how to interpret it and then i'll finish the
story so that's kind of we can see through expired gases we can see the amount of co2 that you produce
and the amount of oxygen that you utilize so under resting conditions and that's what's called
the respiratory coefficient or the respiratory exchange ratio the respiratory exchange ratio
is purely at the respiratory level at the lung level with the respiratory coefficient it's at
the muscle level they're quite similar but not academically you know that might not the same
but we can call it rq or rr2 so under normal conditions you don't produce much co2 so the
ratio it's always below one could be 0.7 something like that for example that means that it's co2
divided by oxygen so that's where you don't produce a lot of co2 you use more oxygen and
therefore the ratio is 0.7 as exercise intensity increases and so that ratio of 0.7 we can impute
from that that a person is virtually all dependent on fat oxidation at that moment probably yes and
that's what we can use through what's called stoichiometric equation you can deduct the amount
of fat it is oxidized because to oxidize one mole of fat you need x amount of oxygen and you produce
x amount of co2 so by measuring both you can see what kind of fuel you're burning and that's what
we're doing in our paper so as exercise intensity increases or if the person is not metabolically
flexible they cannot oxidize fat very efficiently so normally these people they tend to depend to
depend more on glucose or any other extra source of fuel and that's why you see use already people
at rest they have a higher rq or rr we could be in the 80s then as exercise if you were to do
exercise as exercise intensity increases you start producing more co2 and therefore the ratio starts
getting closer and closer to one when you and that's when we see that you start oxidizing more
glucose than fat when the ratio gets to one yeah it's just 100 of the fuel that you use is glucose
and you don't see any fat which is kind of what we also call kind of that end of the zone four
yeah so this was the observation i was noticing a subset of patients again very hyperinsulinemic
insulin resistant by whatever metric you would use to explain it that had resting rr or rq of 0.9
to one easily 0.95 so what does it mean when someone who is laying down to do this test under
no physiologic distress has an rq of 0.95 what does that mean obviously based on what you said it means
they are almost exclusively relying on glucose and not oxidizing any fatty acid but what is that
telling you at a molecular level about the illness or the function of that person's mitochondria it's
a red flag for mitochondria dysfunction right there because that's not normal obviously after
eating a meal of carbohydrates yeah for a while you're going to have a higher rq but at rest in
the fasting state when someone is in the 90s this is a morning fasted resting it's a red flag that
is already telling you that there's something going probably at the uh manaconda level and this is
what we wanted to do this paper that we wrote we want to see the same thing that is done usually
at the ekg level so when a cardiologist wants to study the heart if there's any abnormality
resting ekg has a reliability about 50 so you could see some red flags already but you don't
see everything you have to stress the heart exactly and you stress the heart and similar
protocol than what we did here and that's what you do when you do ekg in stress right situations the
rail ability is about 95 97 so you see a lot of things so i decided to take the same approach
and say okay now at rest as you very well said you see people in the 90s with rq and that's our
red flag now okay let's trace those mitochondria right so in other words the analogy is sometimes
you'll do an ekg on somebody at rest and you'll see changes in the st segment that tell you
immediately there's a problem but there are many people who have a normal resting ekg but only when
you put them on the treadmill and make them run do you see that change in the electrical signal
that tells you there's a problem and so similarly maybe somebody walks around with a resting rq of
0.8 and you think oh they're perfectly fine but you see that they're zone two level the level at
which they tap out at their fat oxidation maximum or their maximum aerobic output is much lower
than predicted and now you have a functional assay exactly you can categorize people by looking at the
fat and also looking at the lactate if you burn very little fat that means that you don't have a
good mitochondrial function and that confirms it that test if you produce a lot of lactate
that means that you don't have a good like a mitochondrial function either because lactate is
metabolized in the mitochondria so if it's in the blood that means that the mitochondria cannot
metabolize it so what we did with the three populations from war class athletes to morally
active individuals with people with metabolic syndrome which is a companion of type 2 diabetes
protect to cardiovascular disease as well or what we call not cardiometabolic disease because
80% of people with diabetes has cardiovascular disease and vice versa so these people what we
did then with these three groups is then we paired both the fat curve burning curve in the test as
well as the lactate and the correlations were in the 90s so we see that it's a valid indirect test
to see the mitochondrial function now as we speak and in this office right now we have all the
supplies we're going to do this now with muscle biopsies and we're going to try to prove not just
this but what are the metabolic pathways do you have the irb approved already yes we're going to
start next week we already have it tomorrow we don't have the laboratory set yet we're in the
recruiting patient's face i might have to come back and do this man we'd love to get a muscle
biopsy yeah we can do that because we're going to be looking at the muscle biopsy mitochondrial
density respiration we have uh two different machines or a boros and seahorse where you can
how many subjects are you looking to recruit well so far we want to have about 50 we're going to be
recruiting people who are well trained it's difficult how will you define well trained well
yes so well trained are people who are usually competing like for example in cycling would be
like a category three two and one okay so pretty serious yeah pretty serious cyclists i'm going to
try to see if i can fool a professional athlete to get a muscle biopsy which is might be difficult
but i'm trying to then we're going to have also moderately active individuals who are healthy
then we're going to have another group that is masters athletes those masters who are 50 60 70
years who don't develop type 2 diabetes and they're very healthy don't take any medication
to match for the age of diabetes and then we're going to be looking at pre-diabetics
and type 2 diabetics and we're going to be looking at mitochondrial function mitochondrial respiration
genomics proteomics metabolomics as well and try to find the exact mechanisms that go wrong
something that we see in this paper indirectly we know that something wrong but we don't know the
exact this is pdh enzyme or it is something that an ldh in the mitochondria that is not working
or is faulty or is both of them and that's where we're going to try to target the mechanism so that
it can give us maybe better diagnosis or open the doors for maybe potential therapeutics to
target those mechanisms that we have seen that they're dysregulated well my guess is people
listening to this if they're interested we'll be able to very easily come and find where the
enrollment is and i might have to come back and even if i don't fit into one of the nice neat
buckets i'll just i'd love to do the muscle biopsy now of course you talk about the need
for a treatment here but you already know you've already discovered arguably the single best
treatment imaginable for this which is more zone 2 how do you increase mitochondrial function
you train at the maximum level of mitochondrial output correct that's my hypothesis and that's
what i have been seeing for 25 years working with elite athletes that this is the exercise intensity
where i see the biggest improvement in fat burning and the biggest improvement in lactic
clearance capacity therefore that means that the mitochondria is where you see the biggest
improvement we see also the biggest improvement in performance pause there for a moment you're
coaching professional cyclists in the Tour de France so do they need to exercise at that low
level of intensity it's not at low level well for them for them it's low but for us it would be
excruciating but even for them because for them their mitochondrial density infection is so
incredible and the way they recruit the type 1 muscle fibers it's so big that you need to push
it so it's having a much bigger gear range exactly exactly it's like in the first gear that we say
when you get to the 70 000 rpm you're in the red zone okay you push it there these guys first gear
is in the 15 000 rpm so you still need to push into the 15 000 which could be uh they really go
very fast but then you see their lactate and the lactate is not more than 1.8 so it's telling you
that they're just so efficient they're incredibly efficient reusing that lactate and keeping it
confined to the muscle as another fuel for the adjacent fiber exactly and if you see that in the
blood there's such a low levels of lactate that means that they have a very good mitochondrial
function and they're stimulating that system there when you see that any athlete or any person is in
the three four five millimoles then you see that that system has given up already it has to be
exported in the to the circulation is the biopsy that you're going to do in this subsequent study
going to allow you to differentiate between two plausible hypotheses to explain this observation
one being that they actually make less lactate the other being their muscles actually utilize
more of it before it gets back into circulation both of those could explain the observation
because you're only sampling in the blood so you're only looking at how much lactate is making
it of the blood you don't know if it's just that they make less or they make the same amount but
use it much more efficiently do you have a sense of we know that because my colleague george brooks
will be also a co-author in this paper he already has described that that uh well trained individuals
they can get to produce more lactate and at the same time they utilize it better so their gift i'm
using air quotes the gift of the gifted athlete is not the production of less lactate it's the
ability to re-utilize it exactly yes and we choose the skeletal muscle and this is a very important
point in my opinion because it's the probably the first tissue where diabetes starts skeletal muscle
about 80 of all the glucose or carbohydrates that we oxidize in the body after a meal they're
oxidizing the skeletal muscle and within the skeletal muscle is in the mitochondria so that's
why looking at the mitochondria of skeletal muscle it gives us a very good ability to describe this
in a more precise way so again if you could sort of as a thought experiment if you're looking
at the muscle of someone who's going to get diabetes in two years versus the muscle of
someone who is not what do you think they look like in terms of differences so there'll be many
but i just want to hear you talk through them right in terms of so not talking functional at
this point i'm just talking purely visible will there be differences in glycogen capacity of the
muscle will there be differences in the actual density of mitochondria will you see differences
in the types of fibers i mean again just playing that game of you know this person's going to get
diabetes this person's not what looks different so you would see very clearly for example that
well trained athlete has at least three to four times the amount of mitochondria and the size of
the mitochondria that's very visible that you would see it right away and this is Toledo from
the university of pittsburgh he did a great paper where we can show it in the slides as well where
he can show that very well so three to four times the number plus larger yeah and that's the number
and the density of the mitochondria then we delving the function of the mitochondria how well they
function that's the zone two that you've been talking about yeah that's one of the things that
we believe in my stimulate different pathways for mitochondrial biogenesis as well as different
pathways for the improvement of the efficiency of the mitochondria itself are there other functional
tests used besides the amount of basically ATP to lactate which is what you're doing in a zone two
test non-invasively to my knowledge there are no other ways to look at mitochondrial function you
would need to look at a muscle biopsy and when they do a muscle biopsy what functional assay
are they doing in vitro when you look at muscle biopsy you can this is kind of what we're going
to be doing you can expose the tissue or the muscle to glucose pyruvate or fatty acids
and see what is the metabolism you label them and you see what goes where i see so you will
use metabolomics to get a signature of the preference for different circulating fuels
exactly so we would be seeing like this type two diabetics for example they barely use fat
when they're exposed to fat we trace that fatty acid but they have a much higher capacity or
willingness to use glucose for energy and that energy is might not be happening in the mitochondria
either happens in the cytosol that's one of the things that there's what's called the metabolic
reprogramming that happens in these patients happens in type two diabetics happens in cancer
patients as well and in other diseases there's like a local metabolic reprogramming but there's
also a whole body metabolic reprogramming where you just cannot synthesize fatty acids i mean you
cannot utilize fatty acids for energy purposes very efficiently because you don't have the
mitochondria and you need to rely more on glucose and at rest glucose is mainly oxidizing the
mitochondria as you said earlier goes to pyruvate pyruvate into the mitochondria but when your
mitochondria at rest are not functioning very well you need to rely on the cytosolic production of
ATP through pyruvate and then lactate so this is why we believe these patients rely on the most
to this cytosolic glucose utilization which is what we see in higher exercise intensities in
athletes and that's what we see higher lactate levels as a biomarker for mitochondrial function
do you see other differences between the very very fit and someone again who's going to go on
to get diabetes just to make the experiments such that you're not looking at someone with diabetes
in terms of glycogen storage capacity yes we see that too we see that so i developed with a
colleague here john hill from the school of medicine we developed a methodology to indirectly
look for glycogen content in a non-invasive way using ultrasound high frequency ultrasound and
we validated with the muscle biopsy as well and another researcher david neiman also validated the
system and we saw very good correlations with the scale that we use so you just doing a high
frequency ultrasound of the quadricep you can get to within what degree of accuracy of a muscle
biopsy with the muscle biopsy we saw in the 90s they are the correlation pre and post exercise
using the scale that we use there are a couple of authors that have done a replication of the study
but they have used a completely different scale we know that the skeletal muscle glycogen is stored
in different parts of the body i mean in different pockets of the muscle and in different muscles so
what we do is we look at the entire image of the rectus femoris for example but in the validation
we did not validate the score of the rectus femoris with the high frequency ultrasound
with the one square centimeter biopsy sample we validated the image the one square centimeter
image sample from the muscle biopsy with the muscle biopsy and that's where you have the same size
in image and therefore you have the correlation whether a couple authors they have correlated
the entire muscle with different pockets of glycogen everywhere with only the specific
you did apples to apples yes and you have an r squared of 0.9 the r is yeah it's in the 90s
93 94 pre and post wow without the need of doing this so if you had to guess two individuals
could differ how much between a person who's fit and someone who's in yeah so this is exactly to
your question so we see it very well others have done it before with muscle biopsies where they
have shown that fewer individuals they can store more glycogen than other individuals and that's
what we see so on a scale from zero to a hundred that we have you see the world class athletes
they can go to 85 90 100 whereas someone like myself i'm considering now like a weekend warrior
right i just you know try to exercise hang on hang on what's your ftp right now i'll be the
determinant of whether you're a weekend warrior not to be honest if you had to guess what is your
ftp above 300 or below no no i i don't know 275 yeah i would say something like that okay it's
still you're not a weekend warrior 275 is still a respectable i exercise four or five times a week
but to be honest and i don't use a power meter i i don't use a heart rate monitor i just go to
enjoy the ride how long does it take you to climb mount evans oh i've only done it once and it took
me a long time since years ago when i've been playing with numbers all my life and being my
own guinea pig i got to know myself quite well so i should not say that but um reading numbers all
day and the last thing that i want to do is like just read my own numbers you know when i go there
i haven't got there yet i've thought about it a lot but i still obsessively look at all my numbers
and i still use a power meter when i'm doing all of the zone two training like i could at this
point probably just put it away and ride based on feel but i don't know why i still love the
numbers even though it depresses me a little bit because the numbers are so bad but it's interesting
that you've been able to sort of separate yourself from that and say look i eat sleep and breathe the
numbers in the lab and with my athletes but when i'm riding it by myself you know what yeah just
enjoy myself yeah i mean the laboratory for eating all these numbers all day and working with athletes
and patients i just i just go riding and i know that i'm stimulating my mitochondria and here and
there that's right too i bring my portable analyzer with you here and there and i just double check
like okay the zone too so i sort of interrupted you but you were about to guess what your glycogen
storage capacity would be relative to the so the world class would be say 85 to 100 yeah so i might
be maybe 60 to 70 whereas uh people would like maybe type 2 diabetes might be 30 to 40 or 50 they
might have a normal glycogen storage capacity or on the low side but the well-trained athlete they
will increase it as well it's an irony because the fitter you are and the more glycogen you store the
less you are dependent on it yes isn't that interesting yeah exactly but at the same time
it's that energy that you need to move quickly for energy purposes this is the very interesting thing
on the other side looking at the fat oxidation the fat droplet if you heard about that the
intra muscular triglycerides they are highly related to cardiovascular disease and type 2
diabetes and insulin resistance and this is the athlete's paradox what's the name of the researcher
like sorry i blanked right now but what he did is like the same approach of looking at they had been
seen that people with type 2 diabetes they have this fat droplet it's like a little deposit of
fat right outside the mitochondria and it was a characteristic so what he did is like okay i'm
going to look at and then that was in comparison with people without type 2 diabetes they didn't
have this fat droplet so what he did is like okay i'm going to see if elite athletes or
world-torn athletes what histologically characteristic they have and he found a big
fat droplet as well adjacent to the mitochondria so that's the paradox it's like wow why in the
world they have that fat stored by the mitochondria so what it was found that in the people with type
2 diabetes that fat is not active and in fact it can produce ceramides and other pre-inflammatory
mediators that are not only involved with the insulin resistance but maybe with cardiovascular
disease or atherosclerosis they cannot be oxidized in the in the mitochondria so they build up
outside whereas in the well-trained athletes it's an rest reward there the fat that we burn in the
mitochondria it comes mainly from the succoutaneous fat and it has to travel it's a long trip all the
way to the muscle so why not from an evolutionary perspective why not having a reservoir right there
by the mitochondria and effectively about 25 to 35 percent of all the fat oxidation that elite
athletes do during exercise it comes from fat droplet it's very active so do you suspect that
in the study you're about to embark on the biopsies will also show this that in your fittest and your
least fit you'll see the droplets yes we're going to look at that as well why do you think that the
average people don't have droplets does that mean you and i probably don't have too many fat droplets
in our muscle probably not i would understand that if everybody had it sort of like structurally
but then there's a functional difference where there's a gradation from the person with diabetes
to the world-class athlete the gradation is in the utilization and activity of it but why do you
think people in the middle of the road like us have actually lost the capacity for that reservoir
well i think because we're not elite athletes but why do the people with diabetes still retain it
but in a static non-utilizable fashion that's what we're trying to find out why and in my opinion
is that hypothesis one of the one of tests is that the mitochondrial function is not good so
therefore fatty acids cannot be transported into the mitochondria and they're sort of building up
outside the mitochondria we can i see but we haven't completely built our capacity to use it
at high amounts so we don't have the reservoir it's like the glycogen thing we don't store 80 or 90
or 100 because we don't need it and at the end of the day the body is very wise and it's based on a
lot of evolutionary mechanisms and this is one of them glycogen storage capacity as well as the fat
right outside the mitochondria i've always thought of that paradox through the lens of fat flux which
is when you take a snapshot in time which is what you're doing when you do a blood test or a biopsy
you're looking at something in a moment it tells you nothing about the velocity and what i think
your example illustrates is that there's such a high turnover of things in the really really
fit person that even if it's elevated it's not problematic another place you see this by the way
in the blood is free fatty acid concentration so when you're doing a blood test to screen for
diabetes if you're doing very advanced testing you're looking at lots of things not just something
as sort of banal as the hemoglobin a1c but you'll you'll look at insulin and you'll look at insulin
under sort of provocation and you'll look at free fatty acids under provocation and amazingly
under the most metabolically flexible and least metabolically flexible conditions you see the
same pattern which is higher free fatty acids but again it comes down to flux exactly i suspected
in the person with diabetes it's just an accumulation of free fatty acid in the plasma whereas in the
very metabolically flexible person if you were putting a tracer on that ffa you'd see rapid
turnover exactly exactly and exactly and this blood analysis they don't use the tracers so you
just see whoa there's a lot of free fatty acids going around there and like what are they doing
where they're being metabolized for energy purposes in the metabolically flexible and you
see it very well kind of they're accumulating the other ones is this is kind of what we probably
see at the cellular level so i want to kind of finish the energy zones obviously at zone three
you're getting into you're exceeding the capacity to maintain a stable level of lactate which tells
you you're now exceeding the mitochondria's capacity to be the sole provider of ATP you are now
becoming obligately dependent on glycolysis in the cytosol by definition the percentage of fat
oxidation is now going down as the percentage contribution from glycolysis is going up is this
where the lactate threshold now occurs because i'm sure that people listening to this who are going
to say wait a minute wait a minute i always thought lactate threshold was around four millimolar so
how does that concept fit in so i would put the zone three as a transition zone where your
glycolytic system starts kicking in at a very high rate because the ATP demand and your fat
oxidation says okay i think i'm starting to be done here now you take over and that's where you
start seeing a decreasing fat yet you use fat so it's not a completely glycolytic state it's a
transition phase that is when we move into the zone four in the zone four that's where we see very very
well that the lactate also you see an inflection point that kind of where we could see the lactate
threshold where like all of a sudden the lactate accumulation is not steady it jumps and you see
the inflection point and at the same time that's where you usually start seeing the r of 1.0 the
rq and there's zero fat oxidation so we know very well it's like if there's a lot of lactate
and there's no fat oxidation that's another metabolic transition point that is indicating
that you don't burn fat anymore it's just dependent glucose yet you can breathe and it's
probably done in the cytosol so you're aerobic and that's the zone four we'll be calling the
lactate threshold if you will and what's the clinical significance of that or the even the
athletic significance of that i mean once an athlete goes above their lactate threshold
how long can they sustain that pace there are many lactate thresholds so we might believe that
lactate threshold could be maximal effort you can sustain for 15 minutes or 20 minutes or the ftp
the ftp could be away also of lactate threshold for a fat of 40k so for the person listening to
this who's not familiar with that ftp is defined as functional threshold power in cycling we use
it as the the maximum power that can be sustained for 60 minutes or sometimes we do a 20 minute test
and discount it by about 10 but i mean an ftp test for me has never felt linear you know what
i mean like if your ftp is 300 watts the pain at minutes 10 20 30 40 50 60 is not linear like the
last 10 minutes hurt more than the first 50 but now that i think about it whenever i did ftp tests
i was usually doing them on the road not on a stationary bike i never had lactate levels
throughout but my intuition is my lactate was increasing non-linearly i would always ftp test
on a hill because it was easiest to maintain a fixed power output but what's actually what do
you think is happening to a person's lactate when they're at that threshold i have seen that and i
presented american college of sports medicine poof like about 10 years ago and i have to publish it
is one of the things that you have so much things going on that sometimes you don't have the time you
need to get some med students working for you know i'm looking at the poster you're bringing up but
you haven't even published yet no 10 years ago yeah this is 2009 or something like that but this
is where back in the days a lot of people talked about power everybody would just train by power
and what's our what i started to see at the pro level a lot of people using just power output
and heart rate like as an old school i was one of those people actually you know five years ago
where it was i really didn't pay attention to heart rate at all except to notice that there
were some days when at the same power my heart rate was much higher and i felt and performed much
worse that was about the extent of my observation yeah i wanted to kind of show that with numbers
and that's what i say like okay power is power and speed is speed the ability of humans to perform
relies on the ability to convert chemical energy into mechanical energy the mechanical energy
that's your power output the chemical energy is like all the metabolic adaptations that get you
there so this is what i saw and we can put it as this is a poster you presented about 10 years ago
and by the way this is i hope there's a med student out there at the university of colorado who's
listening to this who's uh figured out what their next summer's task is going to be which has helped
turning this into a manuscript but tell us a little bit about this experiment and what it showed
because it's as i look at the figure i see it is answering it is answering the exact question i just
asked actually so yes one of the things is that a lot of people start to talk about watts are watts
right they ditched the heart rate monitor because watts are watts therefore metabolically speaking
is the same thing but as i said earlier the ability of humans to exercise depends on the
ability to convert chemical energy or biochemical energy into mechanical energy the mechanical
engine is the end product what but how do you get there so i wanted to see and put it to the test so
i had both a group of elite cyclists professionals and a group of recreational cyclists but well
trained as well and i did a maximal test where i could get that peak power output at the end of
the maximum test one group deleted cyclists the next test i put him at 80 percent at the big power
output from the first test and the second group at 75 and then i just let them stay there for 20
minutes so if the elite cyclist hit a peak power of 400 watts on the previous test 80 percent of
that so now you put him at 320 watts and say you're going to spend 20 minutes here and it's
like similar calculation for the recreational athlete though at a lower level exactly okay
so the whole thing was like if watts are watts it was like the whole bottle back in the days
is like okay then metabolically speaking we're not going to see changes in other words five minutes
into this test whatever is happening in you physiologically since you're not changing the
output or the demand for ATP there should be no change in anything else exactly so what happened
so what we saw is that after five minutes both groups they had about four millimoles of lactate
okay in the elite athletes five minutes later which is minute 10 they had about seven millimoles of
lactate and five minutes later which is minute 15 they had nine millimoles of lactate so right there
we see that watts are not watts at the metabolic level it was very stressful for them and they
could not keep it and this is kind of to what you alluded that you notice that towards the end of
some of this FTP it feels worse and this is exactly what i was observing with many professional
athletes and elite athletes as well i mean cyclists that they would get over trained more
and they said hey i i had to do let's say my coach told me i had to do five hours or four hours at 200
watts and i do the job and you can see i'm training picture so yeah you do 200 watts but
what's the price i used to be obsessed with training peaks and what was the other program called
there's another program we used to use but where does the TSS show up the training stress score is
that also training peaks yes and i remember i used to mostly just keep track of kilojoules
in the end of the day it was how many kilojoules today what's my TSS and my training score balance
and things like that but i think with this and by the way i'm looking at the graph the recreational
athletes basically had the exact same pattern just at lower levels meaning they fatigued quicker
at a lower level but the pattern is identical so heart rate lactate and and percentage of V2 max
and percentage as well as V2 max in liters per minute they all show statistical significance
so we see that watts are not watts that's when it's time to throw because i've been always like a
big believer of heart rate and when i was 15 i saved all the money that i had and i bought the
sports tester that back in the days was like 200 dollars no it was sorry it was like back in the
day it was about 500 dollars so i'm talking about 84 83 no 86 sorry i was my sports tester the year
greg lemond won his first exactly yeah and that's what i since then i've been looking at heart rate
a lot because we forget that heart rate is a physiological parameter watts is a mechanical
parameter but heart rate is a physiological parameter and response to the physiological
metabolic stress so if you look in the graph that the audience can see later when we look at
the graph of the lactate and the heart rate they go side by side when heart rate goes up lactate
goes up well i've noticed this and i'll show you more of my data over dinner tonight but for the
past year i've been recording four times a week my lactate levels on both devices plus heart rate
plus power at the end of i always like i'll do a minimum 20 minute steady power in a zone two
so anywhere from basically 20 to 45 minutes where the power is clamped i'm on a bike on an erg so
there's no deviation of power and there's a very interesting correlation between so even if you do
the same power for four consecutive workouts you can have different heart rates and you can have
different lactates now we're going to come back to this because i want to talk about it later
there's another confounder here which is metformin which will back burner even with or without
metformin there's a coupling between heart rate so for example if you don't sleep well and your
heart rate's higher you're not recovered your heart rate's higher you're under more stress for some
other reason and heart rate is higher lactate tends to follow it even at the exact same power
output yes yes and that's what we're showing and that's where like then joe freel started to talk
about the coupling where you should maintain the power output and the heart rate as well
so among a bunch of us we kept pushing for heart rate because it was getting to a point that it was
going to be erased and now everybody trains with both power output and the heart rate in fact now
the whole hrv the heart rate variability it's a big big deal and a lot of people look at and
listen to their hearts and i always tell the athletes the heart rate is going to tell you a lot
this is one of the things also why i decided to try to develop a way to look at glycogen
because i would see that in in maximal physiological states many athletes who were fatigued
or restricting carbohydrates they had a very low maximum lactate levels very low maximum heart rate
let's say that athlete that i have tested multiple times let's say a lactate of 12 and a heart rate of
190 when that athlete is fatigued or tired or restricting severely carbohydrates that
lactate could be maybe four and the heart rate could be maybe 162 and how much adaptation do
they have because i know you and i have spoken about this before and i don't know if we're going
to get into it on this podcast because there's so many things i want to talk about but your view
has always been that the fat oxidation data that we sometimes see in heavily heavily carbohydrate
restricted or ketogenic athletes may actually be an artifact we might not actually be seeing fat
oxidation of 1.7 to 2 grams per minute you're saying in a gc contender been the best cyclists
on the planet what is their maximum fat oxidation in grams per minute well what we're seeing here
normally in the 0.7 0.8 grams per minute under normal and we have done these experiments although
we haven't published them but we have done a normal athlete like category two or three they do
under normal diet not super high in carbohydrates not super low normal diet and their fat oxidation
the fat max it's uh let's say 0.4 then they do one week of carbohydrate restriction or two weeks of
carbohydrate restriction and their fat max yeah it's 0.8 but at the same time we see that the power
output decreases at least 0.5 watts per kilogram so about 30 or 40 watts and also we see that the
maximum heart rate decreases and the maximum lactate decreases that said this is more in uh
if you will a more cute situation i'll tell you this from my experience and i go when i began
carbohydrate restriction which was uh i went on a ketogenic diet in may of 2011 the first 12 weeks
were hell i couldn't even imagine approaching my anaerobic fitness so forget lactate threshold or
anything i couldn't even get to the same aerobic level i remember i still remember very clearly
november 2012 18 months later it came back and then some what that suggested to me and if i could
go back in time and do anything different i would have had muscle biopsies done all along the way
but it struck me at how long it took for that adaptation to take place now i only stayed in that
state for three years so i'm long out of that state now there's the only time i'm really in
ketosis is around fasting but it's always sort of piqued my curiosity what a very very very long term
state ketogenic state can do for everything outside of peak sprinting capacity because i just
i don't think there's any dispute that peak sprinting capacity has to be glycolytic and anything that
impairs glycolytic function makes no sense so there's such a debate about all of this stuff
i don't think it makes sense for someone trying to win the tour de france to be on a ketogenic diet
it's just too glycolytic even though 96 of that race can be done below peak power output
the race is won and lost under peak conditions so it makes no sense but if you're training to win
the western states 100 you technically don't need to sprint ever if you have a high enough threshold
so i still have that sort of point of view but again i'm very curious as to what those adaptations
are and how long they take because i don't think they're going to take place in a month
you bring up a great great point i'm extremely curious about that as well because i have never
seen an athlete at the elite level adapting and i'm going to tell you why in a second but at the
same time i believe that it cannot be possible that thousands of people around the world who are
getting into the ketogenic diet it might be working for them and they're making it up so i believe
there's something there at first when these things come up and i say come on man give me a break
but then i say there's so many people out there there's got to be something well there's one other
data point i'll add for you when i was on a ketogenic diet and cycling voraciously my
capacity to consume carbohydrates was much higher than what people think of as a ketogenic diet for
someone at rest as a general rule for somebody who's normal about 50 grams of carbohydrates is
the limit above that you begin to suppress the production of beta hydroxybutyrate but i used to
do lots of experiments and at my most extreme you know days when you'd have a three-day period where
you would do a hundred miles each day for three consecutive days at very high output so for me at
the time that might have been average power of 185 watts normalized power of 240 watts for seven hours
on three consecutive days when you're at that much demand i was able to consume 600 grams of
carbohydrates and stay in ketosis now wow i think that's because i'd spent so long adapting i don't
think you can show up and go into ketosis and then a week later eat 600 grams i mean i was pushing as
hard as i could to see how much of this can i consume but so there's the other thing to keep
in mind which is at some point the body became flexible enough that i could break all the rules
i could have 200 grams of protein 600 grams of carbohydrate and still maintain beta hydroxybutyrate
levels above two to three millimolar because i think the machinery with which the bhb was made
was i'd had two years of in fact this would have been probably three years in this is the summer of
13 maybe so you know i'd really been at it for quite a while and again biggest regret is not
having that there are lots of athletes out there that i think would be interesting to study so
that's something worth considering starting to interrupt the thing what i haven't seen that
adaptations in elite athletes is that they cannot afford it you mentioned that it takes months to
get there you don't have months because you get dropped in the races your performance is very poor
your contract is going to be trust they're not going to renew you and you're going to feel like
crap every single athlete who has tried to go whether you call it like a ketogenic diet or
carbohydrate restriction while training and competing for an event they fail that's what i've
seen in 25 years and the reason probably is this because they didn't have one year to say hey you're
not going to race in one year you can train very little your mission is to get adapted that that's
the way sports works but what i see is if you restrict carbohydrates we do blood analysis a lot
we do this metabolic testing in the laboratory while these athletes are competing we see right
away there's a catabolic response the body says holy crap what's going on here i need to survive
somehow so you enter in a in an evolutionary survival mode so obviously yeah your ketones
production might increase your fat oxidation might increase as well but your protein breakdown
increases substantially as well and we see this in the blood analysis that's why you see muscle
breakdown all the time although again it's transient which again speaks to because if it
wasn't transient i mean evolution would absolutely demand we preserve protein under long periods of
nutrient deprivation which of course is what the carbohydrate restriction is mimicking but it's this
time course that i think is very unusual and you're right there's no professional athlete that could
take that chance and again i we were talking about this earlier it's like there are some people whose
entire lives can be built around chat rooms and discussion boards where they can debate these
things endlessly neither you nor i have the time for that so i've largely stopped paying attention
to this debate truthfully but it's always struck with me how long it took to adapt and the price i
paid during that adaptation period if you were a professional athlete you would be out of the job
yeah oh absolutely and this is why i think that i have never seen that because sooner or later the
athlete they hit the wall they just cannot finish races or they just like hey what's going on here
and then that's when they have to go back and we see this quite often athletes don't always listen
to us they always go to the blocks and see things you know internet or they find where the neighbor
is telling them and a lot of people try many diets and the tendency now and it was before also was to
restrict carbohydrates and again i really think that you can adapt because the human physiology
is a wonderful machine but do you have the time to that while you're a competitive athlete that's
what i have a lot of thoughts that i don't think so yeah and again i think the discussion is
is interesting in academic but of course in the end i still think carbohydrate restriction is a
great tool for anyone who's not trying to win the Tour de France i think that's where people
sometimes get hung up right it's if you want to win an olympic gold medal there are very few sports
in which you could probably do that on a ketogenic diet and if you want to be the best cyclist or
runner or swimmer on the planet very hard to do that on a ketogenic diet the good news is by the
way if you're at that level your mitochondria are so remarkable that your carbohydrate tolerance
is unbelievable where it comes back to and i think where the biggest opportunity is
is the person who is not metabolically very healthy who thinks they need to drink a liter
of Gatorade an hour and no actually that person can absolutely be on a carbohydrate restricted
diet and they can exercise and yes maybe their performance initially is less than what it would
be if they still mainlined all the carbohydrates in the world but in the long run they're going to
produce a much more metabolically healthy phenotype even though they won't be in the top 0.1% of
athletes who will no exactly i agree and the thing with the elite athletes too is that yes and this
is kind of what i keep bringing up all the time there's no population on earth who has as many
carbohydrates and simple sugars as these athletes by a landslide right this guy said the Tour de
France for example yeah tell people like let's take a long stage of the tour so a 250 kilometer
stage that has say four high category climbs and one hc climb so one climb beyond category yeah so
these people they take first of all how long would it take them to complete 250 kilometer stage with
four high category and one non-category which means it's just a brutal yeah it would be more
like a 200 and it would be like a five five and a half hours and how long would that take you or i
to ride right now man that would take us two hours more easily yeah and how long would it take an hour
and a half or take me two hours more if i'm lucky how long would that take a person who
doesn't ride their bike too days yeah i mean 14 hours something like that because they will have
to do multiple stops and at the hc they might not even make the climb yeah yeah or much slower yeah
while they do this climbs that the Tour de France depends on the weight but they usually they go
between six and six point five watts per kilogram let's say a person of 70 kilos which is 70 kilos
is probably 150 154 pounds so that would be about yeah 420 450 watts so we cannot do that you know
like a normal well-trained person who exercises regularly can maybe do that in 300 watts but uh
person who doesn't train can do that in 150 watts only so that's poof that's a long long time and
their weight is usually significantly higher so that day it's hard to believe they can do that in
five to six hours by the way but they would consume how much on that day both on the bike
and off the bike so normally what they do and i have haven't published this but we keep track of
this all the time we keep track of how the amount of carbohydrates per hour we keep track of the
breakfast what they eat on the bike after the bike recovery right away we have these protocols
and these protocols are very up to what they need or what we think they need and also based on what
their demands are because they're the ones who like they need it you know and again as i said
earlier i've seen athletes even restricting carbohydrates in the races and they get totally
destroyed so these guys they consume a total or about 12 grams per kilogram of body weight per
day of carbohydrates so if you're 155 pounds which could be an average weight let's say 70 kilos
we're talking about close to 150 grams a day of carbohydrates more than 150 you said how much 12
850 yeah yeah yeah so i thought you said 150 okay which is 850 grams of carbohydrates
that's over three that's almost 4 000 calories yeah 3 500 calories of carbs and out of those
at least a good 30 percent of those 250 is simple carbohydrates let's say 30 percent of those so
we're talking about these people are having daily about 1500 grams of sugar i'm sorry 1500 calories
of sugar so almost give me an example of what type of sugar they're consuming like gels and yeah the
gels the goose the drinks and then obviously at breakfast at lunch and dinner they're more complex
but during the race in the first part we do more solid versus liquid but towards the end of the
race we do more liquid so more pure sugar simply because it's sub-sort faster and that's what you
need more energy but yeah these people again they do about 1500 calories a day just in sugar imagine
pretty much your entire daily caloric intake of a normal person a bowl of sugar if you want to do
this if you go to a nutritionist and you say i want to do this they will shoot you yeah look if i did that i'd have diabetes in a month
of course of course of course and we know that they don't have it in fact this is the
healthiest metabolically population in the planet now the irony of it is on two-fold one in many
other ways they're wildly unhealthy the rate of catabolism the bone density loss that these guys
experience over the tour de france is debilitating i mean these guys they lose so much muscle they
lose so much bone density the other thing we see is for many of these athletes the transition out
of being at that level to being normal again is devastating because especially i actually read an
article on this once i wonder if i could find it i believe that the answer was more common in males
than females where the rebound effect to becoming metabolically unhealthy was unbelievable it's very
hard to turn that spigot off of you're basically a non-stop eating machine and then all of a sudden
you're on the path to having diabetes three years five years ten years after being the fittest person
in the world yeah and that happened to me when i quit cycling between school work i was working
and traveling i was working 70 hours a week at least i was from doing 500 kilometers a week
to do 500 kilometers a year i would exercise literally six seven times a year and traveling
and eating and and one thing that i have observed is like insulin sensitivity these athletes have
the highest insulin sensitivity of any humans as well there's no insulin resistance because
first we know very well that exercise increases insulin sensitivity and they need it to utilize
carbohydrates it increases insulin sensitivity as well and the transporters there's all that
efficiency in the mitochondria comes with another benefit which we didn't really talk about which was
non-insulin dependent glucose uptake is also going up so now if you take a normal person
we are able to take up glucose with insulin that's the insulin sensitivity but we have a second door
that doesn't get utilized much which is the non-insulin requiring door to put glucose in the muscle
and there's no better way to stimulate that than zone two i mean i don't know if i have a study
that i can point to but i can clinically tell you without a shadow of a doubt and i'll tell you how
i know it's looking at people with type one diabetes exactly i was going to mention that yeah
you take people for whom you know exactly how much insulin they require i'm actually going to
be writing about one of these patients in my book he's type one diabetes completely dependent on
on insulin he's completely maniacal i love him three hour brisk walk every night so that's his
zone two three hours of zone two a day right you know how much insulin this person with type one
diabetes requires a day to five in units about eight to ten units a day he has the highest sex
hormone binding globulin i've ever seen in a human being which is inversely proportionate to insulin
level this guy has no insulin he doesn't require anything i learned from this a lot i was working
with team nova nordisk yeah tell people about what team nova nordisk is a professional team
where 100 of the cyclists are type one diabetics these are professional cyclists with type one
diabetes so the whole purpose of team nova nordisk was first to show the world that you're not going
to not only not die if you have type one diabetes but you can't become a professional athlete to
spread the word because a lot of people think it's a devastating diagnosis for many oh you're type one
you're going to die soon like no you're not going to die soon if you take good care of yourself but
and even you can become a professional athlete so that was the one message to spread the world and
the second is that to study diabetes and type one diabetes and the metabolic effects of exercise
because nowadays most endocrinologists working with diabetics they're telling to exercise the
problem is like they go to exercise and they have many hypoglycemias or hyperglycemias and they need
to correct it and all the hormonal system goes all over the map and they go back to their doctors
and they have no answers so it's the number one barrier they defined from exercise and they many
decide not to exercise because they can control their doses very well and let's explain why that's
happening to people we've talked a lot about the consumption of glucose but as you're alluding to
whether it's you me or someone with type one diabetes when i exercise very strenuously my
glucose goes way up so if i'm doing twice a week i do high intensity exercise as you can see on my
arm i wear a continuous glucose meter it's not uncommon especially if i do it right after a
zone two this is funny because zone two my glucose steadily falls let's say i get on the bike at 100
i do 45 minutes of zone two i get off at 75 you get too bunk sometimes you've enhanced
i don't go long enough to vahank for sure so then let's say i get on the air bike and i do a four
minute protocol it's not uncommon for me to go from 75 to 160 because of the hepatic glucose
output yeah like which in lysis yeah and that person with type one diabetes that number could
easily be 250 because they don't have the insulin to correct it exactly so then they need to correct
and they freak out so they use a lot of insulin they overshoot it exactly they're
reshooted and this is exactly to what you pointed out about the non-insulin dependent system which
is the muscle and this is what it was an educational process so then with jdrf the juvenile diabetes
found a research foundation that we put together they put together like a group of experts if you
will to train clinicians about this so what did you learn i mean how do people compete in
professional cycling without being on that glycemic roller coaster we learned a lot to work on
insulin usage as opposed to insulin correction and that's what we're taking now to the clinical
space because type one diabetes has been about correcting insulin and insulin and insulin and
eating carbohydrates oh you go low sorry man you just keep eating candy or things like that and
we know that that cannot be very healthy for you in the long term but the approach has been
always that to correct by either eating or using insulin but we're trying to really correct it by
really tackling insulin administration so using just longer acting forms is that either you're
longer acting or less insulin and therefore also to do exercise so when you do exercise if you say
first your insulin sensitivity increases so you don't need so much insulin and as i said earlier
the first tissue that develops type 2 diabetes or insulin resistance is the skeletal muscle
so when you eat carbohydrates the big percentage of that are going to go into your skeletal muscle
are people with type 1 diabetes who are exercising even more insulin sensitive at the muscle than
non-insulin dependent individuals who are matched they could probably be so the long-term exposure
this is what i observe for example about glycogen unfortunately it wasn't published because the end
was very low but the reviewers they didn't understand that you cannot do muscle biopsies to
a professional cycling team and there's only one professional cycling team in the world so i did a
the tour of colorado i did the team novone or disc and another team and look at the glycogen
what did you see about 25 higher glycogen content before the race and after the race in type 1
diabetics and about three times less carbohydrate needs than the non-diabetics which we already had
seen because we count carbohydrates and we know that a normal cyclist they have 20 grams per hour
of carbohydrates they're gonna hit the wall in a race type 1 diabetics they have 20-25 average
and they never have any issues you must see higher free fatty acid levels then yes so all
things equal do they just have higher fat oxidation across the entire spectrum they're not very good
necessarily at that and i'm trying to understand that puzzle but what i believe is like i have a
higher glycogen content because insulin drives glycogen synthesis is the main hormone behind
glycogen synthesis so if you've been for and the issue of people with type 1 diabetes they go from
non-physiological state which is not producing insulin to the exact opposite they use a lot more
insulin than normal people over years so 20 years usually insulin it must maybe elicit some
adaptations that might one of them could be increased glycogen synthesis i have no idea
but that was kind of what we would like to explore further so do you think that those athletes who
were able to get by with as little as 20 grams of glucose per hour which seems impossible to
imagine given their energy requirement do you think at some point that would cease to be the
case and in the tour of colorado maybe the longest stage is what four or five hours yeah yeah but
still that's hard to explain it's still a week-long race isn't it yeah yeah did you say that their
glycogen levels still were 25 higher at the end of the race before and after yes that's counter
intuitive yeah sorry was it i know it's 25 higher than the non-diabetic but what about relative to
themselves as the way they decreased how much do they decrease i don't remember because not a whole
lot because i mean in this stage you have to do within the same time and in the tour of colorado
in the mountains why not hotel is here there one is 20 minutes away so i had to do it in one stage
where all of them were on the same floor two teams that was a short stage it was like two and a half
hour stage so they eat normally and they decrease like 15 for 20 percent or something like that so
they didn't deplete completely by you could make the case that that team had some of the highest
levels of non-insulin dependent glucose uptake you've probably ever measured probably probably
yeah so that's what to your question of that the non-insulin uptake of glucose by skeletal muscle
that's what is a great approach we don't have a way to measure this in those of us who don't have
type 1 diabetes we're sort of taking a leap of faith that the more we work on our mitochondrial
efficiency the more we will drive that non-insulin dependent pathway but really it's only the person
in type 1 diabetes where that can be quantified it needs a skeletal muscle contraction first of all
in insulin what it does it initiates the cascade of events that translocate the transporters of
insulin called the glut-4s to the surface of glucose yeah yeah yeah yeah sorry to the
surface of the muscle and those transporters are stimulated by insulin so a skeletal muscle
that's the exact same action it translocate those glut-4s to the surface so therefore there's that
the non-insulin dependent and why does exercise increase that ability we don't know the exact
mechanism it just seems too good to be true i want to make sure that the person listening to
this understands what you just said so i'm just going to repeat it because it's so profound and
you said it like sort of you know you said it sort of like matter-of-factly because of course for
you it's common knowledge when insulin hits the insulin receptor on a muscle it sends a cascade
of chemical reactions inside the muscle that ultimately results in a tube called the glut-4
transporter being raised to the surface of the muscle and translocating across the membrane and
now you have bypassive diffusion glucose can enter the muscle the key is this insulin in the
lock is the insulin receptor and the downstream effect that occurs inside the house opens the
door and lets the glucose in what you said after that is you explained how non-insulin dependent
glucose works which is somehow just the contraction of the muscle so something that's going on inside
the house squeezes and out comes the same beautiful glut-4 transporter which now allows
the same passive diffusion of glucose into the cell but this time it didn't require insulin
this is the best of both worlds this is what henry richer from denmark and lori goodyear from
harvard they've been in dedicated many years to study these pathways so they found that this muscle
contraction stimulates pathways to translocate those glut-4 transporters to the surface and this
is why the pancreas in regular people who don't have type 1 diabetes decreases insulin secretion
about 50 percent during exercise because the muscle they do the rest and this is what causes
also that hypoglycemia in athletes if they don't correct their insulin before exercise they go
hypo so what we were doing and now we're doing clinically we're telling people to reduce the
dose wait a minute this is interesting now this is suggesting that the reduction that i'm seeing in
glucose when i do my zone 2 which is by far the most profound thing you don't see this at higher
levels of intensity see the opposite you see the opposite glucose going up but zone 2 is a sweet
spot where my glucose level always falls precipitously i shouldn't say precipitously
steadily and consistently i never thought of it this way it must be almost entirely the non
insulin dependent glucose uptake because it's a low enough level of intensity that my internal
glycogen stores are easily providing glucose what is needed so this is an additional amount
through that so that's i feel like this is another metric i want to start keeping track of each day
i'm doing zone 2 it's not just power it's not just heart rate it's not just lactate it's the delta
in glucose from start to finish could be yet another metric we look at and in fact one of the
things is like i'm trying to try to take this to the clinic for people who take two diabetes
it's like uh if you eat go exercise right away because when you exercise right away that muscle
contraction is going to translocate these glute IV transporters without the need of insulin
and i thought it was the opposite you know i thought that exercising will increase the
insulin dependent portion and therefore the best time for someone with diabetes to eat was right
after exercise it could be both it could be both yes i think there might be an patient by patient
base but if you have insulin resistance you're going to need to use more insulin after you eat
which it's a patch it doesn't solve the problem but if you exercise then you might need half of
the insulin because the other half is going to be provided of the glucose intake into the cell by
the muscle contraction so learning a lot from type one diabetics we can apply things to type two i
believe one of the things that we see the opposite effect that we saw in the races normal people who
are told to exercise they're not fit enough and they start jogging right and they're in zone four
already very glycolytic they see the opposite they see in a post-exercise hyperglycemia where
there as you said in the 260s so and they inject themselves insulin and they go down and sometimes
in the middle of the night and then they go home if it's towards the evening they eat and they
correct it again and sometimes end up in the er because they have a severe hypoglycemia but so one
of the things that i started to apply first to the cyclists and then to patients is the cool down
so after people would have this high post-exercise hyperglycemia the muscle contraction stops
and that's why i believe this is why it is happening first you have a very high adrenergic activity
high intensity a lot of adrenaline and that's what causes the breakdown of glycogen into glucose
as well as the glucose export from the uh from the liver but then when you stop that muscle
contraction stops completely so you don't have that you've taken away one of your sinks exactly
so that's when you start doing the cool down and that's a study another study i have the data i
have to publish but we could see clearly that everybody started to go down there's definitely
going to be some university colorado medical students or hopefully undergraduates who've just
lined up potentially a half a dozen interesting things to write with you we started to see the
cool down and the cool down would take care of it so people to the point that they would not need
insulin anymore to correct it whereas before they might need three four five units and now they
don't need it anymore because that cool down took care of it so through jdrf we've been traveling
throughout the country and other places in europe and even australia training clinicians about this
so they can go back to their patients and the cool down has been a basic thing and the feedback
we're getting is awesome this is incredible you know it's such a shame that the disease type one
diabetes and the disease type two diabetes share the same name in diabetes because i do think for
many people they just sort of think someone has diabetes but the nomenclature of one versus two
is profound they are really different diseases very completely they almost have nothing in common
except for high glucose as a potential consequence i agree hundred percent it's a real shame it's
there's an artifact of history and this is what i'm trying to also bring the concept of double
diabetes that very few people talk about it because it's mixed type two diabetes especially
now in the u.s. Novo Nordisk told me that i think about two-thirds of the entire insulin that is
sold in america it's for type twos not for type ones and this is the animal that is different
the type two diabetic people is a way different animal than it was 50 years ago i've always been
sort of critical of these companies like Novo Nordisk because i feel like there's just too great
a conflict of interest for them right i mean first of all insulin should be basically free
there's absolutely no from an ip perspective there's absolutely no reason insulin should
cost anything above some nominal amount so it's this cash cow for drug companies like Novo Nordisk
don't worry i'm not going to put you on the spot and have you speak critically at all i'm going to
do all the critical speaking yeah no because we get funded this group is funded by Novo Nordisk
indirectly what i'm going to do is come around and sort of pay them this compliment and say i like
realizing that there's something good that's done by an entity that i generally view not favorably
because again one the price gouging on insulin to me is the most unethical part of pharma but then
on top of that there's this issue of two-thirds of your sales come from a patient who shouldn't
be using your drug the drug really is for people with type one diabetes if you have type two
diabetes almost without exception changing the way you eat and exercise will at least get rid of
the insulin requirement you may still require other medications but you shouldn't require insulin
and that's been repeatedly demonstrated so all that said rant over it's nice to see that this
type of research is being done because these patients offer us a beautiful physiologic milieu
in which you otherwise couldn't see this so this kind of brings me to while we're on the topic of
diabetes something else that i want to talk with you about which is my recent and by recent i mean
over the last six months frankly maybe nine months it's sort of back and forth exploration of my use
of metformin when we very first time met a year ago we talked about how i use metformin i've been
using it for years with the basic belief that even though i don't have diabetes or insulin resistance
it offers some measure of protection from cardiometabolic disease inclusive of cancer
and that's all based on data that unfortunately is confined to people with insulin resistance
hyperinsulinemia or type 2 diabetes so there was always a leap of faith i was taking that if you
took a metabolically healthy individual they would still have some benefit and when patients would
ask me about it i would say my belief is that i'm probably receiving less benefit than someone who's
more metabolically unhealthy but i think i'm receiving benefit and i don't see a downside
and then all of that changed a year ago when we met and i started keeping track of my zone two
numbers and what i immediately realized was a gross mismatch between where i knew physiologically
i was clearly in a zone two just based on perceived effort and my understanding of my fitness level
but i couldn't get over how high my lactate levels were and then i remember you and i would speak and
you would say well what is your lactate level fasting and i'd say you know sometimes it's like
1.6 even before i start i mean this was back when i was in the business of using as many strips as
possible so expensive those stupid things so i would check two times fasting and then every
10 minutes check double double double double double man and there was no denying it i mean
my lactate levels were through the roof and i said to you do you think it could be the metformin
and then around this time a couple of papers came out that suggested that metformin could be blunting
the benefits of exercise so i mean let's go back to then and then we'll talk about where we are today
in our thinking but at the time that i told you all of this what was your thinking about my use
of metformin and these numbers we were seeing did it make sense to you yeah they make sense in a way
that we know that i've seen patients with metformin pre-type 2 diabetic or type 2 diabetic right before
entering insulin states where at rest i have even seen two millimoles also are you able to differentiate
how much of that was due to the metformin versus there because there's such a confounder when you
look at that population had you seen anybody like me where they're no i've seen these high levels of
lactate at rest but again i could not differentiate that but all these people coincided they were on
metformin one of the side effects of metformin is lactic acidosis right this is rare but it can
happen so we know there's something wrong with the lactate what we don't know are the mechanisms
it would be great to study the mechanisms whether or for to improve the cardiometabolic health or
maybe we might find that might not be what we thought we know there are some studies that show
that metformin decreases mitochondrial function it could be that magical drug against cancer
because one of the things that we see in cancer many forms of cancer they have a mitochondrial
dysfunction yet not enough for that cancer cell to be apoptotic oh i see so you're saying that
maybe in that patient metformin pushes them over the edge towards apoptosis towards the cliff that's
what i believe if in case that is true that metformin can cause mitochondrial dysfunction
but the fact that the metformin increases lactate it's either because it increases the glucose flux
into the cell and saturates pdh and then pdh the hydrogenase has a very what we call low
micaelis constant so it saturates very rapid and in my opinion acts as a fuse in the body
from an evolutionary perspective if the body sees there's a lot of high flux of glucose the
body might mean hey what's going on here we need to stop it because it's not good to become
hypoglycemic and maybe the majority of those glycolytic enzymes in the downstream action of
glycolysis they usually have a high micaelis constant but when they get to pdh it's like a fuse
so when that fuse goes then pyruvate is converted to lactate so that could be it either increases
the flux of glucose into the cell and that's why it could work well for diabetes or acts as other
sub shows this is very interesting so this suggests that let's just talk for a moment about
someone with type 2 diabetes who's not taking metformin their lactate levels are higher at
baseline you're now really offering two explanations for it the first is pdh because
their pdh is seeing higher glucose than the non-diabetic so that's the first thing it's doing is
as you say i like that analogy of the fuse it's just triggering the fuse and shunting more glucose
down the pyruvate to lactate pathway and then of course there's everything we spent the first
hour talking about which is in addition to that their mitochondria just tap out very early they're
not working well so those two things that are related but quite distinct would both push up
lactate so now the question is which one of those is more likely being driven by metformin is it the
inhibition of complex two in the mitochondria and it's simply reducing mitochondrial efficiency
if you picture a curve where the x-axis is mitochondrial function it's just moving you to
the left exactly it could be that and maybe it could be both it could be both what we know
epidemiologically speaking is that metformin doesn't cure diabetes and the immense majority
of patients they end up using insulin down the road so we know that metformin is not that magical
drug for type 2 diabetics it just kind of gets them by it buys them time but eventually the
majority enter insulin it didn't change their lifestyle the nutrition exercise they enter
insulin so why i mean so the first thing i did so i used to take one gram twice a day a gram in
the morning and a gram before bed i always do my zone two first thing in the morning so i was
basically doing a zone two right after taking a gram and basically 12 hours after having taken
another gram so you could argue i had very high levels so i think the first change i made was i
just stopped taking a gram in the morning and increased my nighttime dose to 1500 milligrams
so i reduced my overall dose by 25 but shifted it to the nighttime thinking well i should have a
lower concentration in my bloodstream in the morning i saw no meaningful effect so 1500 at
night was still producing basically the same effect as a gram twice a day now again keep in
mind when you're doing an n of one you can't actually make any statistics out of this it has
to be a big signal for me to notice it so then i lowered it to a nighttime dose of one gram
i still didn't really see much of a difference and then what i did is i stopped taking it the
night before doing zone two so that meant i now went from taking 14 grams a week a gram twice a day
to only one gram three nights a week because there's only three nights a week where i don't
follow the workout by a zone two so you've gone from taking 14 grams a week to three grams per
week you could argue why are you taking any of it at that point and that's when i saw the reduction
that's when i saw the lactate levels start to come down okay and in fact that latter part of the
experiment's only been going on for about three weeks so the next step is to stop metformin
all together and ride this out which makes me think we should do a little experiment in me
which is yeah we should do muscle biopsies complete proteomics complete metabolomics
everything that is doable in vitro in the muscle tissue along with the lactate testing and all the
other metrics under three states of physiology one under full dose of metformin two under a complete
washout say 30 days of no metformin and then the third one i think would be very interesting is
under complete water fast where i also by the way whenever i water fast i have no metformin
and i'd like to see what seven days of water fasting with no metformin looks like versus
again these other two states so i think there's an interesting pilot study here to come to our
our study and be part of it and we can do extra biopsies yeah yeah i'm totally game to do this
yeah it would be very interesting because it's fascinating the the whole role of metformin and
also how it can be used in other diseases as well and it's fascinating the the little that we know
about the mechanisms of action at the molecular level yet i think you bring great point is to try
metformin in different states and try to learn what happens at the mixed level metabolomics
proteomics level especially the latter ones because yeah we might see pathways maybe it's
mitochondrial dysfunction that causes that and we can see that quite well or uh maybe it's at
that translocation level that transporters and it would be really interesting assuming the irb gives
a quick approval for this little added protocol that includes me if we could recruit somebody
with type 2 diabetes and have them parallel me with without the metformin with without the fast
because my new hypothesis around metformin is i just have a stronger conviction i think around
my old hypothesis which is the healthier you are the less helpful it is i'm now wondering if it goes
one step further which is the healthier you are the less i mean it might actually cease to be
healthy in other words let's take the extreme example what would you predict would happen if
you gave a tour de france team a gram of metformin twice a day during the tour no other change you
just give them a gram of metformin throughout the tour do you think it would have no impact on
performance or a negative impact i mean based on looking at that it can affect mitochondrial
function and we see because there's increased lactate in my opinion and that's the very first
take and by no means i'm an expert on this it might be detrimental that's my first take if you
think you had a hard time getting professional cyclist a volunteer for muscle biopsies think
about how much harder it'll get them to volunteer for the take metformin and go off and do the vuelta
i know it would be really really difficult to get i or before that in the first place
and the permission from the manager livelihood yeah there's so much more i want to talk about
and i want to tell real quick that the double diabetes and i forgot and i'm sorry to interrupt
you is that that's something that worries me because there are many people with type one
who also have type two and they're not diagnosed and i think we need to raise the awareness
because if about 50 percent of u.s adult population has type two diabetes
yeah a big number of people with type one diabetes are going to have also type two is that a
projection of how many people in the united states will have type two diabetes right now about 50
of u.s adult population have either pre-diabetes or diabetes correct yeah and it's about is it maybe
10 percent have type two diabetes and the remaining 40 percent is pre-diabetes yeah and i was thinking
there's not such state as being pre-pregnant or pregnant you're pregnant or you're not so yeah
that pre-type two diabetes wouldn't see clinical symptoms yet but the disease is there already
yeah it's just i mean our definition of diabetes is so arbitrary and stupid that it's just a
continuum and we somehow decide oh you're hemoglobinate once you cross this threshold
and now you need or not it's kind of like with the symptoms with cholesterol oh you're 200 boom
you need a statin or 220 you need a statin and that no that's the other thing with statins
is that we know that they affect my kind of function how do we see this because in the
published literature five to ten percent of people experience muscle symptoms from statins
but what is the functional impact the function impact i mean we don't know much about it so
you're talking outside of myalgias and muscle pain the good news is i always say this to patients
when you're taking a statin you're going to get the feedback very quick one in ten of you
is not going to tolerate this and it won't be very subtle and you'll stop the medication
and within a week you'll feel better and again what's interesting is the disparate data based
on how it's studied but at the individual level it's pretty straightforward yeah it is pretty
straightforward and one thing that we know too is that it increases also in this research done it
increases the possibilities of becoming diabetic yeah so that's the two things i usually say to a
patient i said there's because everyone says look if you're going to do a statin what are the risks
and i say the short term risk is myalgias and again i just say directionally it's one in ten people
maybe it's 15 maybe it's five percent but you get the feedback quickly and you move on so the second
risk is a long-term risk which is about a four percent increase in the risk of diabetes the good
news there is that's not a sudden thing i think the literature is still pretty clear that the
benefit still outweighs that risk in terms of mortality but again it comes back to the idea of
the most potent drugs we have are food and exercise absolutely and it comes back to me as well
that it's not about how many years we live our longevity and it's how are the last years that we
live right and if statins are going to come back to hunt you in 20 years because they're going to
have extra or increase in diabetes for example yeah might buy you extra time now but again if
you have food and exercise as your main medicine the zone two training for me it's just become such
an important part of my training for myself and for my patients i question i get asked a lot that
i don't know the answer to so i'm going to ask you is what's the minimum effective dose because
obviously i would love it if i could wave a magic wand and have one hour per day to do zone two and
then on top of that layer in all other exercise that would be amazing but it's not i only do three
hours a week of zone two typically in four 45 minute to an hour sessions do you think that's
enough yes so this is what i've seen and i've learned from the athletes and i would love to do
this now with patients what's the right dose but we know or at least i've seen with athletes that
if you do that two days a week one is the dose and the other thing is the frequency so if you do
that two days a week you maintain and we see athletes who in the off season cyclists for
example runners or triathletes or swimmers or rowers if you do the zone two five days a week
for example you really push the needle then once the season starts you need to do more higher
intensity exercise and training and then you have the races and you need to recover so definitely
you cannot do it on two every day so what we see is like two days a week it tends to maintain so
that that's the frequency what's the dose yeah and the dose what i see is like obviously these
elite athletes they need to keep pushing the needle one hour is not going to do much for them
because they have that stimulus already or two hours they might need four or five hours but a
patient would tell you one diabetes maybe one hour is enough and that's what i'm trying to
fine tune you know what would be what i know very well is that three days a week it starts
moving the needle four five for sure and what i've seen or guessing that that's because we
don't have any real data this is about one hour to one hour and a half it does the trick for those
who have type 2 diabetes or pre-type 2 diabetes for example so we have last year a patient who
was diagnosed with uh that's what we're saying is like late pre-type 2 what the heck is that you
know and then uh with one year doing an hour into an hour and a half four days a week she
reverse that completely okay that's a pretty big dose so i mean for me just it's always for me
tuesday thursday saturday sunday is zone two it might be that those saturday sunday workouts i
need to push them longer maybe i need to do 90 minutes on each of those days and stay at 45
minutes on tuesday thursday it could be but at the same time it might be your right dose because
you're not in that unhealthy population side so your dose might be lower but my thinking now is
that this is such an important part of cellular longevity that this is the difference between
being a healthy 90 year old and being in my framework it's one quarter of the equation
what would you do i would do and this is my case when i stopped cycling when i told you earlier
right i gained 65 pounds because i was working 70 hours a week and exercising six seven days a year
and still eating like a cyclist and eating like a cyclist and i'm from the bus country and we like
to eat food because it's one of the best areas in the world and and probably also i had insulin
sensitivity developed from i was a cyclist which i would choose poor carbohydrates you know and then
i would not burn them so maybe i just transform more into fat i also have a familiar dyslipidemia
so i have a high triglycerides and high cholesterol genetically so i didn't take care of myself i would
not exercise and eat a lot so i gained 65 pounds in about eight years or so and then i i said wow
i went and did myself a checkup and then my blood pressure was 125 i was in my mid 30s 125 over 85 so
was getting there and my triglycerides once i saw them 800 which is huge off the chart right back in
the days people didn't do a1c that's when i started to work on these concepts too and so i
started to apply this to myself so i started doing four days a week even one hour was poof i was
banking because i was not used to that it was very depressing going to i was about to say that must
have just been devastating gosh to go from being a professional cyclist to struggling to do four
hours a week of cycling yeah and knowing the same roads that you go to and that you couldn't go up
the hill but i lost 35 pounds within seven months did you make much change to your nutrition exactly
that was i mean i decided to i was willing to eat a little bit less but not sacrifice many things
because again i mean for me nutrition is very important from my culture standpoint i love
chocolate i love wine i love pasta and bread it's ingrained in my culture i was not going to renounce
these things so that's what i said okay i'm going to try to give it a shot so you weren't going to
go on a ketogenic diet and it's an interesting example of there's give and take the more you're
willing to push this type of training the more you can keep on the other side versus you know
i've seen more patients than i can count with type 2 diabetes not exercise at all but go on ketogenic
diets within six months they're off insulin within a year they have a normalized hemoglobin a1c
but again so it's almost like two levers how hard are you willing to pull on each of the levers
exactly no that's a great great comment for sure and i think is the debate many for some people
giving up chocolate is not a problem for me it's death you know i just love chocolate it's not that
i eat it every day a whole bar but it is or a bread you know that's one of the things too that
is the the balance i lost 33 pounds and i stopped there i could not lose more than that i needed to
then i increased my dose so i went from one hour to an hour and a half four days a week i lost
another 10 pounds so i lost a total of around 50 pounds 47 to 50 pounds i was 11 years ago before
coming here and i kind of keep it like that now this is interesting as you're probably aware the
exercise and weight loss literature suggest that exercise alone is not sufficient for weight loss
i've always wondered if that was an artifact of the fact that they're studying exercise incorrectly
that the prescription it's either the dose or the frequency or the intensity were not optimized
you were doing a very specific type of exercise you were not exercising for the number of calories
you burned you were training your mitochondria to become better at fuel partitioning that's a very
technical description of what you did i think it's important for people who are listening to this to
appreciate that nuance you were not there calorie counting saying okay i'm doing six hours a day at
this many calories because you can achieve that in many different ways it was almost the maniacal
specificity with which you approached this that you basically said you didn't think of it as i'm
exercising six hours a week it's i'm doing mitochondrial conditioning or reprogramming
six hours a week exactly yeah i believe so and that's what we know now with patients when we
start in the laboratory that they always tell you i always train at this intensity and you know that
intensity they burn zero grams of fat they burn a lot of calories but zero are derived from fat
they're actually working too hard too hard and eventually number one you don't burn much fat you
burn but fat in the post exercise because you might increase your metabolic rate but can that
override the fat burning from the exercise itself and second it's too hard you haven't exercised in
a long time to start with and you get into these high intensity programs that they might not suit
you or they might injure you and many people give up we see the rate of people giving up from gyms
is about 50 percent or so within x amount of months they either give up or their adherence
decreases a lot so when i ask these people who get into this extreme either exercise or diets
i always ask them and they're successful i ask them can you do this for the rest of your life
and the question is hell no yeah if you can't do it for the rest of your life you have to come
back to the why am i doing this using an extreme example to do hill repeats up alp du as can you do
that for the rest of your life no can you do it if your goal is to win the tour de france yes you're
going to do it for five years you're going to train that hard for five years you're probably
going to take a chunk of time off your life by the way but that's your job you have to be the best
climber in the world exactly and to the point of the nutrition the nutrition is a must you need to
do something with it or do a lot more exercise but i think it's the balance that we all i think need
to understand better well that's for me why fasting has become so important now you were laughing at
me earlier before we started recording about how crazy it is that i can do these long fasts but
in many ways it's a way to provide me balance it's like sprinting it's basically every month
there's just a frequency with which every quarter i do one type of fast and every month a different
type and every week a different kind it allows me to keep a balance and it allows me to say yes i
could do this for the rest of my life whereas the reality of it is i couldn't do a ketogenic diet
for the rest of my life as powerful as it was in me couldn't do it the rest of my life so a couple
other questions i want to ask you about you've alluded to cancer twice now we've spent a lot
of time talking about type 2 diabetes as a disease state in which the mitochondria are not
functioning well and they provide this great contrast but you've touched briefly on cancer
is there any evidence that a patient with cancer has a higher lactate level on account of the fact
that they have mitochondria that aren't working as well the same way that the prismatitis diabetes
so it is a fact in 1923 almost 100 years ago Otto Warburg from Germany discovered
the transformation of a normal cell into a cancer cell at the metabolic level and the
characteristic of cancer cells was that they use a lot of glucose for energy purposes now they use
a lot of glucose back in the days there was no genetics or anything but what struck Warburg is
the amount of lactate that they produced was that what struck him more than the fact that they use
so much glucose even in the presence of sufficient cellular oxygen and insufficient ATP demand so it
was more the lactate accumulation more the lactate accumulation and that's why he came to conclusion
that cancer was a metabolic disease caused by an injury of the respiration system in the cell which
is the mitochondria and that's what was the thought for many years because of the lactate
even before glycolysis was invented Meyerhoff who discovered glycolysis sometimes it's called
ending Meyerhoff pathway which is glycolysis Meyerhoff was a student of Warburg before they
had even found out about glycolysis the way they measure glycolysis is by measuring lactate
so they would measure how much lactate the cell produces and that's where they would say wow they
are using a lot of glucose but what he saw in cancer cells that was an aberrant amount of
lactate production and that was one of the things that struck Warburg the most and now what we see
is that lactate is a typical feature of cancers cancers produce a large amount of lactate which
is also responsible of the famous microenvironment that a lot of people are talking about nowadays
the lactate microenvironment i mean the the microenvironment of cancer cells is more acidic
than non-cancer cells and it's a niche for carcinogenesis they're responsible for that
microenvironment is lactate and what we know is that yes just like that it's a fact that multiple
studies showing that uh or every study showing that every study trying to find lactate in cancer
they're going to find higher lactate levels so this would suggest three distinct but not necessarily
mutually exclusive explanations for the warburg effect the first being what warburg proposed
which is in cancer there is an injury to the mitochondria as a result of that injury the cancer
produces it takes an inefficient path to go then there's the 2009 explanation proposed by
thompson cantley vanderheiden in that science paper that was sort of a very important landmark
paper and said no no that's probably not it it's the glycolysis and the lactate production is a
byproduct of metabolic demand for building blocks it's the cellular nucleotides that are necessary
to build the cells so the mitochondria work okay what you're seeing is a deliberate and
obligate choice to grow and the need to grow literally from a mass balance perspective
requires taking this pathway versus that pathway and now you're saying well a possible third
explanation is the cancer relies on lactate as a signaling molecule and again these could all be
true on some level we know that they're not all always true i mean at least we know that in the
case of the warburg effect that's not universally true that the cancer damages the mitochondria
what are the next steps in figuring this out and perhaps more importantly much more importantly
how do we use this information therapeutically yeah so one of the things is that we have just
finished the study it's under review now and we're going to replicate it now with more cancer cells
but we have done a study with the mcf-7 cancer cells which are the most common type of breast
cancer or one of the most common type of breast cancer cells and what we have seen is like we
expose the cancer cells to glucose so we did experiment one exposing the cancer cells to
a media that contains nothing no glucose no glutamine which is also highly expressing cancer
and this can survive a couple of days in that state then another experiment we just expose them
to glucose that's it and in the other two other experiments we added to that glucose media we
added 10 millimoles of lactate and 20 millimoles of lactate what we did then is like we extracted
the dna by the way are those physiologically accurate doses do we believe the micro environment
of cancer is that high it's about 10 yes it's 10 times the normal level there's been studies
showing up to 40 but normally yeah 10 is a typical and what ph the ph is usually between 6
and 7 i was about to say that has to be below 7 yes for sure in fact the more aggressive in general
the more aggressive the cancer is the more glycolytic is and the more lactate is found and the more
acidic the micro environment is so we published an idea to propose lactate being the explanation for
the world war effect because what we looked into the medical research is that the genetics stops
in how the first cancer cell happens and maybe proliferation in cell cycle genes but there's a
lot more to that in cancer you need angiogenesis you need metastasis you need a mean escape and
you need also the cell sufficient metabolism the cancer cell have it's immortal so that's where
like what we saw is that lactate is necessary for each of these major steps in carcinogenesis
but what we wanted to see is like could lactate also be a signaling molecule
and that's where like what we observe is like looking at transcriptional activity looking at
the RNA expressions of the key oncogenes transcription factors and cell cycle genes
and proliferation genes in cancer lactate overexpress them between two and eight
compared to control and what was the difference between the 10 millimolar and 20 millimolar
lactate did you see a difference in transcription in 10 in 20 we didn't see much of a difference
but we saw more than in zero what struck us and that's kind of hopefully we can show is that if
you cultivate the cancer cells in glucose alone i give this presentation and the understand but
uh so we looked at the cancer cells and we looked at the major oncogenic i mean oncogenes
transcription factor and cycle genes we had no glucose incubation no uh glutamate either
just glucose and then we had a lactate 10 millimolars and 20 millimolar so we did RNA
extraction and we looked at in the cancer cells where they're without any media that is no glucose
no glutamine we didn't see RNA expression did the cells live of those oncogenes we killed it we didn't
in other words there's a very finite period of time in which you're looking to just see
yes we look in six hours and 48 hours so neither in six 48 hours was RNA expressions okay what about
glucose by itself so when you add glucose by itself we looked into the media and it was a
very high lactate levels looks like on your graph it's almost 30 millimole yes it was almost 30
millimole in the six hours and because lactate is also used by the cells for energy purposes over
time we expected also to see but we still see about 25 millimolar this is the waterborne effect
this is what waterborne observed incubating in cells and say wow they use a lot of glucose but
why in the world is this lactate it's amazing it's that high so what we saw then is like this lactate
alone was enough to trigger the expression of all the major oncogenes transcription factors and even
depress the cell arrest genes so is there an experiment that could be done where you constantly
change the media you have a flux of media that allows them to have a finite amount of glucose
but you constantly strip away the lactate to see what the true baseline level of expression is
absent the lactate as the signal yeah so this is now where we're going to be replicating this
experiment with multiple cancer cell lines from liver to pancreas to lung to kidney to thyroid
more glycolytic less glycolytic and then do all these kinds of experiments and include also
metabolomics i mean this is a complicated media device because you basically have to expose them
to a bath of constantly moving media that contains glucose but no lactate you see what i'm saying so
you have a negative flux of lactate across the cell because what you really want to do is see
how does this work with glucose but no accumulated lactate because that would answer the question is
lactate specifically singling because you could still argue here glucose is playing a role yes
but we believe this is through the lactate through the lactate but now how do we figure that's what
we did in the second experiment the glucose media is the same we just added more lactate
and we see a much amplified response how much is it amplified with so it was for example this is the
no lactate versus the lactate we can see but it looks like about 2x yeah sometimes even 2x so
that's where we saw that the media is the same but the more when we added the lactate it really
over expressed the transcriptional activity i was going to play devil's advocate you could say that
we know that the lactate could be serving a metabolic fuel so maybe it's conserving more
glucose for more glucose to be signaling transcription well we know that lactate is
being used by the mitochondria of our cancer cells everywhere is mitochondria there's lactate
what we believe is that it's a signaling molecule to really over express the transcriptional activity
of oncogenes transcription factors in cell cycle genes in a non-hierarchical way because the
traditional view of cancer is that you have the oncogenes they tap on the transcription factors
and they start an array of different downstream signaling that eventually transforms a normal
sending to a cancer cell this is so interesting because it again at the meta level flies in the
face of all of the observational data of how much metformin lowers cancer unless it comes back to
your explanation because if you just look at these data all things equal and by the way that
would be another interesting experiment add metformin to the dish as well in theory it should
amplify lactate by poisoning the mitochondria further and drive even greater upregulation of
these signals unless to your point earlier it becomes so toxic to the mitochondria that the
cell undergoes apoptosis yeah that's what's in my opinion and this is another thing that we want to
do but it's possibly that yeah because you're totally right it can amplify the lactate as we
know so i can amplify that that oncogenic or oncogenetic signaling for carcinogenesis or maybe
it just doesn't matter because these amounts of lactate are so high that we're not seeing that
from metformin maybe metformin isn't that inhibitory so much to the mitochondria and that
becomes a red herring in the equation and the benefits of metformin exist totally elsewhere
we don't know but it will be very interesting to see all this because it can have some application
and there's some research group studying already why i feel like i need to quit my job and come
and be a postdoc in your lab because there's just so much the more we talk about this stuff and i
know it's going to get way worse tonight when we have dinner with rick because it's going to be
50 other ideas that i just want to with the fructose as well yeah that's a lot of things
going on there let's talk for a few minutes about drugs in cycling many people argue that the era
from about 91 to 2010 there's a 20 year period of time the 90s and first decade of the 2000s
where the use of drugs was at its highest i don't think anybody can be a student of this sport and
ever say there's been an era when the top athletes weren't using some drug i mean even eddie mercs
the greatest cyclist of them all on many occasions was found to be using an amphetamine or something
like that how much of an impact do you think the performance enhancing drugs of that era the 90s and
2000s where again it's all out in the open now everybody understands how much blood doping and
how much epo was being used yet you a moment ago gave a number of six to six point five watts per
kilo as an ftp i recall reading at the time athletes hitting seven watts per kilo do you think
that is about the distinction of with and without epo do you think that's about the magnitude of
the improvement i could not know that number yeah i mean definitely we know the times and
back in the days we didn't have those power meters or cyclists they didn't use them so it's
difficult to calculate but it is possible to calculate with the times i haven't done the
numbers but what we know now is that the times going through molar albedoess or so are the same
times that people were doing in the 80s or early 90s it's hard to see any of today's cyclists being
at the top 20 best times now as they did before so that's something that shows that yeah cycling i
think goodness is a very clean sport right now the other thing is the fact that every cyclist now
who wants to do well they go to altitude and that's one thing that before didn't happen
and now it's just it's great to see people going to altitude because it's a physiological way
to increase oxygen carrying capacity is the data on altitude still the following so when i last
looked into this which is maybe a decade ago the answer seemed to be the performance enhancing
way to use altitude is to live high train low meaning your baseline exposure should be at a
low oxygen environment your low intensity training should be at a low altitude environment but your
high intensity training should be at sea level is that still believed to be the case that's an
ideal scenario in my opinion yes and i mean here in colorado because we're colorado here by force
we need to know we must know about altitude because we get a lot of athletes every year
and we get to study them and yeah one thing that happens at altitude your glycolytic capacity it
starts deteriorating their high exercise intensity it's like if you had a cap here at altitude and
this is something that everybody tells you when they're here like i cannot keep my hundred percent
here i cannot open up the same gas as i used to have and if you don't do that for three and a
half weeks or three weeks that your altitude yeah your glycolytic capacity is going to deteriorate
which for a marathon runner they don't couldn't care less but for a cyclist for example it's
important so that's more like the ideal scenario is to really try to find that balance but it's not
easy to do at high altitude levels has anyone ever proposed using little portable oxygen
producing devices for peak peak peak efforts for those who live at altitude to maintain top
end exactly and that's done it is done it is done yeah and that's something that we're building a
university in one of our campuses in color springs sports medicine and performance center where we're
going to have one room that is going to simulate sea level conditions so it's going to be hyper
so it's going to simulate living at sea level because that is going to allow athletes to do
very high intensity efforts without killing themselves because this is the problem that happens
here altitude these athletes who want to do very high intensity exercise which would they really
need also to they get over trained we see a lot of people leaving altitude in very bad form
and they're going to train or they live with a high oxygen carrying capacity but poor glycolytic
capacity so that's more like yeah by doing this space it's going to allow athletes to come and they
use these facilities while living at altitude because the problem that we have here you have
two days driving to the ocean so you cannot train low and deep high but at least train low
high intensity you can simulate that while still living in high environment so interesting Miguel
Indran have you ever met him yes an unbelievable specimen yeah yeah and an incredible person too
I've heard he is so he's got to be what now he's got to be 60 yeah 50s in the high 50s herself yeah
still incredibly fit I remember reading a paper about him maybe 20 years after he retired he
retired in 95 96 right I mean still unbelievable numbers I mean was he just a physical phenom to be
yeah he was incredible when I was doing my internship I was doing with Indran's physiologist
who was a very very good physiologist and I learned a lot and I remember once I was kind of
helping there and the one thing that struck me also was his numbers were unbelievable and also
the amount of sweat that he had I have never seen anybody sweating so much in my entire life he was
a big guy right he was 80 kilos six foot one six foot two it was incredible because usually when you
do physiological tests you might have a few one tower or a couple of towers even with fans people
sweat a little bit and yeah and back in the days I was I was just wiping the floors that's kind of
you're doing internships in these cases yeah if we didn't write you needed a mob and have you seen
athletes since never so do you think that's just true true and unrelated or do you think that also
spoke to his physiology like he had an unusual cooling system it was like out of this world I
have never seen anybody like him and if you observed in the two of the friends everybody
was with their shirts wide open right and Indran was always all seeped up always always always and
with the hat on so he had an amazing capacity to dissipate heat which is a double-edged sword so
obviously he drank a lot but I'm very sure and back in the days we didn't have the technology
that we have nowadays to measure that what we do now sodium concentration in sweat we do sweat tests
we have sweat patches and we can measure the sodium concentration in the sweat patches and then tell
someone whoa you're a heavy sweater in the first place and you also sweat a lot of
sodium but when someone and it's something that's very typical we see young people
or people who are not very well adapted to sweating you see like the white marks in this
yes shorts or in their helmets that's salt literally sodium but the more mature physiologically
an athlete gets the more they sweat that is I have never realized that that is a metric yet another
little trick of the trade to look at sort of metabolic flexibility is the ability to retain
the sodium as just the water leak yes exactly makes total sense yeah it's an evolution and you
sweat more back in the days I was just students just wiping the floors but now you'd bet that
there's low sodium in there you'd pull a William Osler and yeah he figured out that diabetes urine
tasted like sugar you'd figure out that Indran sweat tastes like water I would have tested it
for sure I couldn't tell you it was a man is no salt here Indran's interesting because he's right
on that precipice where there is no question that the person who won the tour right after him
was using herculean doses of EPO so Bjorn Reis won in 96 nickname Mr. 60 right I mean
hematocrit somewhere between 60 and 66 so you go from Bjorn Reis to Ulrich to Pantani to Armstrong
that's the era and then before Indran is Greg Lamond who again I don't really know anything
about what he was or wasn't taking but Indran has largely been left out of the discussion
on blood doping and I've read articles that have just talked about how he's generally been left
alone no one has come back to him because it's so I'm not going to ask you to speculate on that
because I know that from a personal standpoint I don't want to put you on that spot but do you get
the sense that he's just been left out of this discussion because of his place in cycling and
it's almost like people don't want to go back and revisit that I mean why do you think that is
I don't know I have no idea to be honest I could never give you an answer I know that he was a
freak of nature because of his size in the same manner that before Indran was Greg Lamond was also
a freak of nature a freak of nature as well and left out of all this I have no idea I've seen his
physiological parameters and seen a lot of athletes we don't see those physiological parameters and
also what I always say about Indran is his head and I work with a lot of athletes and in cycling
for example I have never met any athlete well there's one athlete I will tell you in a few years
meaning there's someone you work with now who maybe in a few years you'll tell us yeah I don't
want to be no you don't want to jinx him him too yes exactly but uh only one athlete with his head
he was calm he was relaxed he was super intelligent he could read the game ahead of things
he would never get nervous about anything and he would never doubt about anything which is
rare in athletes I've seen athletes getting to the top of the game and falling apart and start
crying there's the fear to lose but also the fear to win because when you win your life changes for
the good or for the bad and many athletes they were always nervous trying to find an answer or
trying to find a new diet or new training or something you know and that's where like
or very fragile athletes at the high level very very very fragile if you're considered like an
expert or you're a coach or you're someone with a little bit of a name in cycling for example
and if you go to a race and you see a cyclist wow you look fat I think you can wait that cyclist
is done yeah yeah exactly done I mean cyclists are like models in that regard right every ounce
matters exactly and that's how they are but Indran started the tour with two and a half kilos over
for example why the first week in the tour is flat no gravity his head is relaxed and calm like
okay I can do this no problem and in that week he loses a kilo kilo and a half and then he's
entered the second week with the mountains with half a kilo over okay no problem no big deal he
loses it and then boom the last week is in perfect weight it takes a lot of thinking and confidence
and confidence right and saying hey I got it and that's why I think that his head was also
unbelievable lemon's head was also incredible I remember as a kid reading a lemon's book it really
literally changed my way of looking at cycling I was 15 when he wanted to with the friends and
that's where like I started to see his complete book of cycling I don't know if you've ever read
it no it's the best cycling book I've ever read in my life and it's about how he trained and how
he ate and how the way he approached cycling and back in the days I'm talking 86 he was super
scientific yeah he was so far away everybody else everybody else yeah yeah we could go on for
hours but I think on this note we'll bring it to a close only because we're already late for dinner
and I don't want to keep uh rick waiting but I want to thank you so much for this this has been
incredibly informative there is a million follow-up things to do including we're going to do this
biopsy study so I'm willing to come back to to Colorado to do this again because I really
am curious about this metformin question around zone two and I think that this is going to be one
of those episodes where hopefully people are able to see the show notes because so much of what we've
talked about I think benefits from this type of being able to visually see what this stuff we've
talked about and and lastly I do think there's uh there's gonna be you know a shortage of medical
students and undergraduate students who are looking for summer projects to come and help you get a lot
of these really interesting posters published so thank you well thank you so much Peter for the
impact you've had on me personally with respect to how I think about this problem
and then hopefully by extension how others have as well well thank you so much it's truly
an honor to have you here and to speak with you and be invited to your podcast thank you very much
you can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast there
you'll find the show notes readings and links related to this episode you can also find my
blog at peteratiamd.com maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively
non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to the most interesting
papers I've read and all things related to longevity science performance sleep etc on social
you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id peteratiamd but usually twitter
is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments now for the obligatory disclaimer this
podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of
medicine nursing or other professional health care services including the givings of medical advice
and note no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the materials
linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk the content of this podcast is not intended to
be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnoses or treatment users should not disregard
or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the
assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions lastly and perhaps most
importantly I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures the companies
I invest in and or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about