Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Dr. Rick Johnson. Rick is a professor of medicine in the
Department of Nephrology at the University of Colorado, where he's been since 2008. He's
basically spent the last 17 years being a division chief across three very prestigious medical
schools. He's unbelievably prolific as an author. He has well over 700 approaching 800 publications,
seemingly every week in JAMA, New England Journal of Medicine, Science, et cetera. He's
lectured across 40 countries, authored two books, one of which we discuss in great detail in this
podcast called The Fat Switch, which he wrote about seven or eight years ago. He's been funded
extensively by NIH and in fact has received the most prestigious grants that NIH has to offer.
His primary focus in research has been on the mechanisms causing kidney disease, but it was
doing this that he became really interested in obesity, diabetes, heart disease. What connected
me to Rick, I guess about seven years ago now, maybe a bit longer, was his work on fructose
and fructose metabolism. That's really what we talk a lot about in this podcast. We start by
talking about high blood pressure, the relationship between salt and high blood pressure, which is
something that is incredibly controversial. I actually learned a lot in this podcast. I'm
really glad we had this discussion because I thought I had this thing figured out in it. I
clearly don't. We talk about one of the most interesting bifurcations in evolution with
respect to an enzyme that allowed us to use fructose in a certain way that was obviously
advantageous millions of years ago today, not so much. We talk a lot about uric acid,
which you've probably heard me talk about on other podcasts. This will then be the master's
class in it. We talk about artificial sweeteners and we touch on some of the most promising ideas
around pharmacotherapy that are being developed in response to the epidemics of metabolic disease,
especially in response to sugar. This episode gets a little bit deep on some of the biochem.
We're going to have obviously the show notes will as usual provide a great background analyst
of references. I hope you enjoy my discussion with Dr. Rick Johnson.
Hey, Rick. Thanks so much for opening up your office today and making time.
It's great. I'm very happy to have you here. I've wanted to sit down with you for about a year in
this format because I guess we've probably known each other for maybe about six years now. Every
discussion has been one of those discussions where at the end of the discussion, I think,
man, how am I ever going to remember all of this stuff? How will I be able to synthesize this to
translate it into what I'm doing? I've said this many times before, but that is the whole reason
that I started a podcast was I just found myself every week having a discussion with someone,
usually scientists, where I thought, this is something that's got to be shared. You would
certainly be one of the three or four people indirectly that was a real catalyst for the
podcast because of the frequency with which we would either have these dinner discussions or
discussions over the phone. Anyway, for that, I want to thank you and hopefully the listeners do
as well. In the introduction, I've set this up a little bit as to why this is such an important
discussion. Because there's so much to talk about, I just want to jump right into the meat of things.
It would be not an exaggeration to say you were one of the world's experts on fructose. I guess
I would just start with the why. Where did that interest come from? You've obviously been doing
this for a long time and that passion has been sustained. So what brought you to this point?
Well, I'm a kidney doctor. So normally we wouldn't be studying sugar. So it was kind of a circuitous
way that I got there. I was very interested in the cause of high blood pressure and had been
known for a long time that high blood pressure is linked with kidney. And in fact, the going theory
is for years was that the kidney in high blood pressure has a defect in its ability to excrete
salt. And so that you end up retaining salt and that leads to elevated blood pressure. And when
we were studying trying to understand how the kidney handles salt in high blood pressure and
so forth, we were trying to understand potential pathways. And we stumbled on the fact that
hyperuricemia or elevated uric acid could be a very significant risk factor for high blood
pressure. And when we started studying uric acid, we realized that when you raised uric acid in
animals, they developed high blood pressure. From there, we started to try to understand what made
the uric acid go up. And we knew from the literature that sugar and particularly fructose
raised uric acid. So we started studying fructose and pretty soon we were so excited about what we
were finding that we just kind of changed our research direction to focus more on how fructose
has all of its metabolic effects. Well, there's a lot to unpack there. So let me kind of go back
to bits of it. You sort of gloss over the fact that the conventional approach to high blood
pressure is that sodium is the culprit. And isn't it still safe to say that most advice around
reducing blood pressure comes down to reducing sodium intake? Well, we've actually been studying
this pretty extensively. There's a lot of pearls I can teach you, or I can talk about related to
salt. And when I was in training, I was taught that you restrict a certain amount of salt, you
should be on a low salt diet as a mechanism to prevent high blood pressure. It was always about
the amount of salt. In fact, we were teaching that for a long time that if you want to have a low
blood pressure, you should restrict your salt intake. Or if you want to try to treat your high
blood pressure, you should restrict your salt intake. What's happened in the last couple decades
has been the increasing knowledge that it isn't really the salt amount that makes a difference,
but the salt concentration. So when you eat salt, like if you eat a salty soup, the salt concentration
goes up in your blood first. And it translates into a thing called osmolality. And so your serum
osmolality goes up. So osmolality is sort of like the ionic pressure build up in a fluid? Is that a way
to... It's sort of like the number of molecules in a set of volume. So literally, when you eat salt,
if it's really salty, let's say you have a serum sodium concentration of 140 millimoles per liter,
if you eat a really salty soup, your serum sodium may go up to 142 or 143. What looks like pretty
insignificant, but that actually is what triggers a rise in blood pressure. And so we've actually
done the study where we took people and gave them soup with or without salt. And when they
drink the salty soup, their serum sodium goes up and their blood pressure shoots up.
How much would a person's blood pressure go up if their sodium went from 140 to 142?
It's about six millimeters. Okay. So they'd go from 120 to 126. Yeah. And that happens
acutely. And how long did it take to resolve? Maybe a couple hours. So if we give, and we did
this study, we published it last year, if you give salty soup with water so that the serum sodium
doesn't go up, they got the same amount of salt, guess what? The blood pressure doesn't go up.
And the serum sodium, does it so not go up or does go up? Right, right. It does not go up. So if you
block the serum sodium from going up. So basically the closer you can bring the total
accumulated concentration of what you ingest down, the more likely you are to prevent this
transient rise in serum osmolality and blood pressure. Yeah. Well, it turns out that serum
osmolality has a real major role, not only in blood pressure, but also in obesity. And we're
going to talk about that in a second. But when you take a high salt diet and your serum sodium
goes up, it triggers a rise in blood pressure and it's working through the brain and actually
through the liver and other sites too. Pause for a moment. Tell the listeners why it would be
better to have a blood pressure of 120 over 80 than 140 over a hundred. Well, there's a pretty
good epidemiologic data that shows that when your blood pressure is high, that you have an increased
risk for heart failure and stroke. Those are the two major ones, but it also increases the risk
for heart attacks and heart disease in general. Interestingly, there's a very significant
inflection point. And what I mean by that is when the blood pressure gets around 160 to 180, right
in that range, the risk for stroke goes significantly up and the risk for mortality goes up. And that's
because our body tries to auto regulate to blood pressure. So when the blood pressure goes up,
for example, the kidney, the arterioles will constrict to reduce the pressure load to the
kidney. But when it gets to about 170, it will overcome that restriction and the blood pressure
will injure the kidney. Likewise, the brain kind of responds to flow more. So it tries to maintain
blood flow. But if the pressure gets high, it tries to protect itself from the high pressure
by constricting. But when the pressure is like 170, the risk, it can't constrict enough. And you
don't want it to constrict that much because it has to maintain flow. And so the pressure ends up
increases to the brain and increases the risk for stroke. Now, current guidelines seem even more
aggressive. We would manage class one hypertension. We would consider something in the mid 130s to be
treatable. Yeah. So let me get there. So originally, when the studies came out, it was very,
very clear that if your blood pressure was like 170 or higher, that you had a dramatic increased
risk for stroke. And that's because it would pass the auto regulatory point. But then what happened
was epidemiologic studies showed that even a blood pressure of like 140 over 90 conferred increased
risk. It just was much less than the 170. So at 170, it just takes off, it's almost the line goes
up vertically. But between 140 and 160, there is still a stepwise increased risk, but it's just
kind of a more gradual risk. In fact, for things like a stroke, you can start showing an increased
risk from 120 over 80 to 140 over 90, leading people to view 120 over 80 as kind of the optimal
blood pressure. As you get older, if the blood pressure is really low, you lose your auto
regulation for low blood pressure. And so it increases the risk for kidney disease and
problems as well. So you don't want to be extreme on either end, especially as you get older.
This whole thing's kind of such a, it's a real clinical mystery in some ways still, because
in medical school, we learn about this term called essential hypertension, which is kind of a
wastebasket term for hypertension or high blood pressure for which we don't have an obvious cause.
The problem is, and so having sort of that wastebasket term would be okay if it accounted for the
minority of cases, but then you get to the clinic and you realize everybody walking around with high
blood pressure basically is getting labeled as having quote unquote essential hypertension.
So it really is this epidemic without a clear description. Now we're going to come to a lot
of reasons that, I mean, I think you have arguably one of the most compelling cases for what is at
the root of essential hypertension. But for people listening to this, for doctors listening to this,
who treat hypertension, I feel like we just haven't made much progress in the 20 years since
I've been out of medical school. There have been some real breakthroughs in the understanding of
primary hypertension just in the last five, 10 years. And there's two major aspects I can talk
about. The first one is that it does appear that salt really is important. And one of the key
discoveries was that the kidneys are often normally handle salt fine, but they develop or acquire a
change in the kidneys that lead them to hold on to sodium. And the mechanism has been identified
just in the last few years. It's due to the fact that there's an inflammatory inflammation that
occurs in the kidney. And that inflammation, which is driven by T cells and macrophages,
causes a constriction of the blood vessels that leads to low grade ischemia in the kidney. And
that ischemia can translate into increased sodium absorption, which then leads to high serum sodium
and the effects. Is there a correlation between serum, sodium and blood pressure across normal
physiologic ranges of say 135 to 145 milliquivalents per liter? Yeah, I believe so. I'm not sure I can
quote the paper, but yes, I think that's true. So what you're saying is in people with high
blood pressure that's otherwise viewed as quote unquote essential, there's an inflammatory response
mediated by both T cells and macrophages that injures the kidney ischemically, meaning it for
the listener that results in reduced blood flow and tissue damage due to reduced blood flow and
reduced oxygen. And it's that injury that then leads to aberrant retention of sodium. So there's
actually been really a lot of studies looking at the mechanism of the inflammation. And originally
it looked like it was people thought it might be a reactive response of the kidney. So we think that
there may be external stimuli that initially cause a decrease in blood flow to the kidney,
like a sympathetic nervous system response. You can do it transiently by giving medicines or
drugs that can cause a constriction of blood vessels. When you do that, you get a transient
reduction of blood flow to the kidney that induces an inflammatory response that then causes
persistent reduction in blood flow. And what we've learned in the last few years, and I'm an author
in one of these studies, is that this inflammatory reaction can actually be an autoimmune reaction.
And we've even identified certain proteins that there's an autoimmune response to, and one is a
heat shock protein. You can actually create high blood pressure in animals by inducing
an immune response to this. And you can block the immune response and block the high blood pressure.
And now there's even data showing that in humans that there's evidence for an autoimmune response
to heat shock proteins in people with essential hypertension. Which is not to say heat shock
proteins are necessarily bad because so many of the benefits we get out of sauna or exercise
may be transmitted through these. But you're saying in a subset of people where the heat shock
protein itself becomes the nidus for inflammation via an autoimmune mechanism.
Yeah. So heat shock proteins are great, just as you say. They do all these really good things.
But what happens is they're involved in the clearance of misfolded proteins and they're
helping keep a clean system. But what happens is when you trigger injury to the kidney, for example,
these heat shock proteins get produced to help fix problems. But the immune system can sometimes get
confused and make an immune response that actually is against the heat shock proteins. And when that
happens, you can develop high blood pressure in the animal and there's some evidence for it in humans.
Anyway, so that's one of the big breakthroughs has been the discovery that inflammation in the
kidney can be a mechanism for triggering persistent elevations in blood pressure and
probably has a big role in the cause of primary hypertension.
Before you go on, Rick, how prevalent do you think that particular mechanism is that you just
elucidated?
Oh, it's very major. In fact, we've even looked at genetic polymorphisms that link with the
development of primary hypertension and most of them are involved with the immune response. And
it looks like this is a major pathway.
This creates a bit of a quandary for someone who's trying to rid themselves of hypertension,
because wouldn't the implication of this be that exercise or things like exercise that induce heat
shock proteins may paradoxically increase their hypertension?
I don't think so. So hypertension is kind of a complicated pathway. So there's several different
aspects, but exercise is extremely good for improving mitochondrial function, improving the
ability for your blood vessels to dilate. It improves kidney function. The benefits of exercise
are so much greater and releasing heat shock proteins that really occurs with very, I don't
know if just general exercise would have a big effect on heat shock proteins.
So you're saying basically the net effective exercise is still going to far outweigh.
Yes, absolutely. But I'd like to get back to the link between salt and sugar, if I could.
Okay, because there is this data, as I say, that salt, when it increases the serum sodium,
is what drives the acute blood pressure response. And when the kidneys have trouble getting rid of
salt, it's easier to get that effect with a salt load. But even with a normal person, you can,
with normal blood pressure, you can raise their blood pressure transiently by giving them salt,
and you can block it by giving water. Interestingly, in the process of developing
high blood pressure, there's the initiators. And then there's the things that make it persistent,
and the inflammation in the kidney is involved in the persistence. But what is involved in the
initiation turns out that sugar has a major role. And what we discovered is that when you give a
high salt diet to animals, that the high salt increases the serum sodium. And the serum sodium,
when it goes up, it activates an enzyme that converts glucose, which is in our blood and in
our tissues, to fructose. And that conversion to fructose is driven by a high salt diet. And it's
driven by an increase in serum osmolality or increase in serum sodium. Once the fructose is
made in the body, so this is not fructose coming from the diet, this is made in the body,
the fructose gets metabolized and raises blood pressure. And when we gave high salt to
animals, they developed an increase in blood pressure. And they also were making fructose.
And when we block the metabolism of fructose, we actually block the rise in blood pressure,
as well as the hypertrophy of the heart. So let's pause for a moment. I've had Rob Lustig on the
podcast before, so anyone who's listened to that will be familiar with what fructose is, what glucose
is, what sugar is, all of these things. But can we spend one minute just defining these things for
people who haven't listened to that podcast? Sure. So there's different types of sugar. And
the main one that we call blood sugar is glucose. And this is the primary sugar that our body uses
to make energy. It's the main sugar that's used to make energy and it can be stored
in the tissues as glycogen. And when it's too high, we call it diabetes. When the blood glucose
is too low, it's hypoglycemia. And so glucose is like the principal energy fuel, the carbohydrate
fuel that we use. And as you said, we store lots of it in our muscles. Once it gets in the muscles,
it can't get out. And we store maybe a quarter to a third of it in our liver. And that's mostly
there to buffer the blood supply, in particular the brain. What does glucose taste like? A pure
drink of glucose. People like it, animals like it, but it isn't as sweet as classic sugar. But it is
often very much like by animals, humans like it. You can buy these dextrose pops and stuff like
that. Dextrose is another word for glucose. And also the kidneys store glycogen and produce glucose
too. The second type of sugar is fructose. And the best way to think of fructose is it is a fuel
first off it's present in fruit, but it turns out to be the sugar that is involved in energy storage
rather than energy production. And so when you eat glucose, you use that to produce energy, but when
you eat fructose, it will actually trigger changes in the body that will favor the storage of energy.
And this is the sugar that animals use to store energy. So and you store it in the way of fat,
in the way of glycogen and all those kinds of anything that will facilitate storing energy
is done by fructose. And fructose and glucose, if you were looking at pictures of them in a
biochemistry book, look pretty similar. They're both ringed carbon structures. They both have six
carbons. One of them has a five ring versus a six ring. But you know, it's sort of interesting to
think that molecules that look almost identical with the exception of a couple of bonds different
can have quite different properties. Now, fructose tastes a lot sweeter as well.
Yes. And so fructose is like in honey and in fruits. And then that's right. So it tastes a
lot sweeter. And the other thing is if you mix the fructose and glucose together, you can get what's
called high fructose corn syrup. And if they're bound together, you get table sugar. So table
sugar or sucrose is one molecule of glucose and fructose bond together. And that occurs in nature
and sugar cane and beets and things like that. Yes. And maple syrup and things like that.
Right. So just to clarify for everybody, when we get a little comfortable with this terminology,
throw the word sugar around quite liberally, but it's always important for people to think when we
talk about sugar, we could be talking about blood sugar, glucose. We could be talking about
fructose by itself. Oftentimes when we talk about sugar in diets, we're talking about added sugars,
such as the sucrose and high fructose corn syrup you just alluded to. I want to go back to what
you just said about the ability of fructose to store something. But if you don't mind, can we
do it through the lens of a beautiful story that you've written about in the past about a mutation
that basically allowed that to happen? This thing that took place about 12 to 15 million years ago?
Sure. So fructose again is a, it's in fruit and many, many animals use fructose as a means,
as their primary nutrient or, and also as a way to help store fat. And for example, animals before
they hibernate will often eat a lot of ripe fruit and the ripe fruit gives them the sugar that allows
them to store fat. And orangutans will eat huge amounts of fruit at one setting to try to increase
their body fat. And we don't get fat from eating fruit, but that's because we eat tart fruit that
has less sugar content and we tend to only eat a few fruit. Whereas if we actually drink fruit juice,
that large amounts of fruit juice can actually increase fat. So anyway, so fruit is a nutrient
that is used by animals to help store fat. So if you go back about 20 million years ago,
the very first fossil apes show up in the world and they show up in West Africa. And the original
one was called Proconsul. They were living about 22 million years ago and they were, these apes were
big breakthrough in evolution because the prior, the monkeys were, had already been around, but
these were bigger creatures. The apes were, they had bigger brain size. They were tailless,
but they did live in the trees and they lived in tropical rainforest and woodland rainforest.
And they would eat primarily fruit and they were quite successful. And by about 18 million years
ago, there were almost at least 10 to 20 species of ape that were living in this area of Africa.
There was a change in climate. There was some global cooling and the Antarctic started building
up ice and the Arctic started building up ice and sea levels fell. And when the sea levels fell,
land bridges developed that connected Africa, which had been separated from the other continents.
These land bridges opened up so that there was now a way to get out of Africa and to Europe and Asia.
And many, many species migrated across those land bridges about 17 million years ago.
And some of them were the apes. And we see the first apes fossils in places like Pasalar,
Turkey, and different places of Europe right around 16 million years ago. At that time,
there were still a forest that were fruiting trees, woodlands, there was fruit all year round.
And so the animals, when they moved into Europe, they didn't have to change their habits at all.
They were able to continue to eat fruit pretty much all year round. But unfortunately,
they continue to get cooler. And by 12 million years ago, the apes started to starve in Europe.
And you can tell that from the fossils because they actually have these
like tree rings on their teeth, developing teeth get this enamel. The enamel doesn't
lay down correctly. And they get these like tree rings that show intermittent starvation,
they would get a ring every time they would go through a period and the starvation was seasonal.
So it was during the cooler months when suddenly the fruit was not available. And the primary
reason was there was a loss of the fig tree. And the fig is a cool fruit that can fruit all year
round because the wasp that fertilizes the fruit does so at its own discretion. So the fruit will
have a fig tree kind of can occur all year round. So when the fig tree died, suddenly there weren't
too many, because of the global cooling, or perhaps it was the wasp, but the fig trees disappeared.
And suddenly these apes did not have enough food to survive during the cooler months, and they
started to starve. And by six to eight million years ago, the last ape became extinct in Europe.
But Africa, although there was global cooling there too, it wasn't as cold. And the fruit trees
survived all year round, the forest just retracted. So the apes there were able to maintain their
normal habits. Well, there was a lot of evidence that there was a lot of evolutionary change
occurring in our ancestors during this Miocene period, and this period of time when there was
the global cooling. And one of them was a mutation in uric acid metabolism. And as I mentioned,
sugar, and particularly fructose, when it's metabolized, generates uric acid. Glucose when
it's metabolized does not, but fructose when it's metabolized makes uric acid. And this mutation
led to a much stronger uric acid response to fruit, because this mutation was of an enzyme that
degrades the uric acid. And when you block that, and you eat fruit, your uric acid levels go up
much more. And this mutation basically allowed these apes to maintain a very prominent uric
acid response. Our group has shown that the way fructose stimulates fat, as well as its other
properties like insulin resistance and raising blood pressure, that those abilities are driven
in part by the uric acid. So when this mutation occurred, for the same amount of fruit, they were
able to store more fat. And so it was like a survival mechanism for this mutation. When it
showed up, it allowed apes that had very little access to fruit to suddenly maintain more fat
stores, and so they could live longer and survive those winters. And we were able to show with Peter
Andrews at the Natural History Museum in London, who studies these apes that this might account for
a very interesting finding. And the finding is that although we thought the apes became extinct
in Europe, and they certainly did become extinct in Europe, the fossil record shows that it was a
European ape that made it back to Africa, and also to Asia, to become our ancestors, as well as the
ancestors of the great apes that live in Africa and in Southeast Asia, like the orangutan, that
they all came from a common ancestor that was in Europe, and that went back to Africa. And we know
from the genetics that that ape carried the uricase mutation. And so this mutation probably
occurred at a critical time that provided survival for those apes in Europe to be able to get out of
there and make it back to these other regions. But it was now equipped with this mutation that made it
sensitive to sugar. And so humans are much more sensitive to sugar than most animals, and it's
because of this mutation. And in fact, we actually resurrected the extinct uricase and proved this
using the extinct uricase that showing that when you put it into human cells,
that it suddenly made us less sensitive to fructose. So the phenotype there, I mean,
I guess just to recap that story, which I find so fascinating, by the way, you guys wrote a story
about this in Scientific American many years ago, right? I know there was a paper that came out as
well. But I mean, that sort of the layperson version in science was really great. So basically,
these apes go from Africa up to Europe, it gets too cold, we sort of think they die out, but the
evidence emerges actually a sub sub subset of them developed the mutation in uricase, that gave them
a superpower, which was now they could be much more efficient at turning fructose into fat.
They had this little byproduct, which is they would also make a boatload of uric acid along
the way. But they actually came back to Africa and ultimately seeded the rest of the species. And
ultimately, that's why we as humans are among the very rare animals that have uric acid levels that
are quite high relative to cats and dogs, for example. Yes, that's exactly correct. So when we
were in medical school, Rick, we learned a lot about uric acid through the lens of a disease
called gout. And it didn't get a lot of airtime in school, maybe it gets more today. But at the
time, it was basically gout is a disease of civilization, it's from eating too much meat.
And there's no real problem with it, except for the nuisance of your toe hurts, because uric acid
crystallizes, it gets inside joints, it seems to favor the first joint of the great toe. And it's
a very painful inflammatory condition. And it's what happened to sort of the wealthy people of the
last few hundred years as they started getting and acquiring too much meat and protein. And that
was sort of the story. What you're describing is a little bit more nuanced. So tell us more about
uric acid. Yeah, so the big problem with having too much uric acid is gout, just as you say. And all
the animals that have the uric case mutation are prone to gout. But humans in particular are very
prone to gout. And it's because of our diet. So we do eat diets that are high in meat and purines that
increase our risk for gout. Can you tell folks what purines are specifically, since it always
shows up in this terminology? Sure. So we have proteins, we have fat, we have carbohydrates,
but we also have things like RNA and DNA and what we call nucleic acids. So these are the kind of
acids that are in the nucleus and that are also in the cell that help drive gene formation and
protein, you know, our genetic material and also help dictate the production of proteins. And so
DNA and RNA are made up of nucleic acids. And when they're broken down, they're made up of purines.
And then uric acid is appearing in it. It's basically the ultimate breakdown product
of DNA and RNA. So the reason protein consumption versus fat or carbohydrate would lead to this is
because if you're eating protein, you're eating the DNA and RNA that presumably were still in
that tissue. Yes. So the way you get gout from protein is from the DNA and RNA in the protein.
And so, and that relates to some extent to the how dense the nuclei are. And so like if you have
a very cellular thing like anchovies and these small fish that have lots of DNA and RNA,
if you have that, they will develop. You can get gout from that much easier than from other types
of meat. And so beer, for example, has brewers yeast and that is filled with RNA. And so that's
why beer can precipitate gout. Now I follow uric acid levels very closely in all of my patients
and myself. And there is an unmistakable difference between men and women, at least in my small
sample size of patients, where men on average have higher uric acid levels than women. Is that
true across the general population? Yes. Even in boys, they'll start to have a higher uric acid
than girls. However, after the menopause, uric acid levels go up in women. And that's because
estrogen helps excrete uric acid. So it's not, I had sort of, I guess, incorrectly assumed it was
that just unbalanced men consumed more protein than women. I think that also plays a role. I
think that's right. But it sounds like this estrogen explanation makes more sense if it
can also explain the observation of menopause. Yes. Going back, gout is also increased by sugar.
And even Sir William Osler, the famous physician from the 1890s in his book Principles and Practice
of Medicine, pointed out way back in the 1890s that sugar was a major risk factor for gout,
as well as very sweet fruits, he wrote. Anyone who's had gout usually will know that real
significant sweets can also precipitate gout. And the reason is because of the fructose content.
And when the fructose is metabolized, it generates uric acid. When people were developing gout in the
1800s, it was linked to the wealthier groups in England, for example, they were eating a lot of,
as you say, rich foods that included proteins and so forth. But one of the things they were eating
a lot of, they were drinking a lot of alcohol, to which they added sugar. I actually did write a
paper where we reviewed how much sugar was put in drinks, alcoholic drinks back in the 17,
the 1800s. And it was much more than today. They loved sugar. They put it in many of their drinks.
And in fact, I even have a picture of an old pub outside the Tower of London called the Sugar Loaf.
They talk about the old drinks that were served like hypocrites and some of these drinks and
sack and sugar was a name for a drink that they had. I mean, they added a lot of sugar to their
drinks. And so part of the rise in gout back in the 1800s and 17, 1600s relates to not only just
the alcohol and the rich foods, but also to the sugar they were adding. So you were sort of the
person who brought onto my radar that there are other things besides gout that one needs to be
concerned about when it comes to uric acid. And one of them is blood pressure. So how did that
understanding come about? So originally we were studying what causes high blood pressure. And
there was a lot of epidemiologic studies that linked uric acid with high blood pressure. And
as I mentioned, we also knew that there was subtle changes going on in the kidney associated with
high blood pressure. And people with gout often have low grade kidney disease. So I said, aha,
maybe uric acid could have a role in causing kidney disease through causing high blood pressure
through its ability to cause kidney disease. And so we took animals and we gave it this uric case
inhibitor to raise the uric acid of an animal. And by gosh, they developed high blood pressure.
And then we could lower the blood pressure by lowering the uric acid. And when we looked,
we were thinking it was might be like crystals of uric acid in the kidney.
But that was my thought is the crystals would cause the inflammation in the kidney. And that
was my thought too. We looked at the kidney, there weren't any crystals there. So then we realized
it was an effect of soluble uric acid. So we started putting soluble uric acid on cells and
so forth. And we saw that it had all these biologic effects. And we always thought uric
acid was kind of like a dead end product of something or even might be a good thing because
some people said it was an antioxidant, but it was causing pro-inflammatory effects. So then
we said, aha, fructose sugar raises uric acid. Maybe sugar could have a role in blood pressure.
What year is it that you're having that thought, Rick?
2002. We gave some animals fructose and they developed high blood pressure. And we gave them
alopurinol, which is a drug to lower uric acid. And it made their blood pressure go back to normal.
And it was like this big discovery. But what was totally exciting was these animals also developed
insulin resistance. They also develop elevated triglycerides in their blood. They had other
fatty liver. And when we lowered the uric acid, we showed benefits on all of those parameters.
How does alopurinol work? What's the mechanism by which it lowers uric acid?
It blocks uric acid formation. So uric acid is generated from other purines. And when we
blocked that, we blocked a lot of the effects of sugar to cause metabolic syndrome. And so when we
first did it, we said, ah, there's got to be something wrong here. So we repeated it and we did
it different ways and didn't matter. It looked like uric acid had a role in how sugar worked.
So as we studied this, we started realizing that the process by which uric acid is generated is
important in how sugar causes disease. No one believed us initially. I have to tell you that
everybody said, ah, yeah, sugar causes gout. But the idea that sugar raises uric acid that causes
gout, but the idea that sugar raises uric acid and that is involved in the obesity and the insulin
resistance, we don't believe it. What's happened since then is we've learned that the metabolism
of fructose is extremely different from the metabolism of glucose. The two look alike,
but when fructose is metabolized, there's this process that causes the energy in the cell to
fall before it goes up. So normally when you eat a calorie, when you eat any kind of nutrient,
we use it to make energy. That's what we do. But when you eat fructose, the energy in the cell
falls before it goes up. It's the only nutrient that lowers energy in the cell.
See more about what you mean by that. So are we talking about a cell in the liver, for example?
Yes. I'm talking about the cells that metabolize the fructose.
Okay. So we'll contrast it with glucose. So if glucose enters a cell,
it gets turned into pyruvate and ultimately ATP is made. So you're saying total energy goes up
as a result of metabolizing that glucose. So whenever you metabolize any kind of calorie,
any kind of food, you eat food, you're going to metabolize it to make energy. That's what we do.
We try to break down the food and we use it to make energy. That energy is called ATP and ATP
is the currency in our body that we use to make us run, walk, think, talk, everything.
So this ATP is pretty critical. But to make ATP, you have to spend a little of it to make it. So
the process of breaking down and metabolizing food or glucose or fructose requires spending a little
bit of ATP before you make it. Well, what happens is when you metabolize glucose, you do spend some
ATP, but the body has a system whereby feeds back to stop the process before any significant
ATP depletion occurs. So for example, there's an enzyme called phosphofructokinase that's used in
glucose metabolism. If ATP levels fall, that enzyme gets turned off to stop glucose metabolism
to allow ATP levels to come back up. But when fructose is metabolized, the enzyme that metabolizes
fructose is called fructose kinase. And when that metabolizes fructose, it consumes ATP in an
unregulated way. So if the cell sees a lot of fructose, the ATP levels can plummet by 40 or 50%
in the cell. And that signals a huge number of effects throughout the body. It's like a May Day
signal. It says, we're under attack, we're running out of energy. And so it switches the animal into
a condition in which they're trying to preserve their energy. So they reduce their metabolism,
they reduce their expenditure, they're resting the energy expenditure. They shut the energy
that they're eating, the calories they're eating into fat and glycogen as opposed to making more
ATP, they're trying to protect the body by putting you into a system where you try to store fuel.
It triggers hunger and thirst that makes you want to eat more. So you eat more to restore the energy,
but at expense that you're shunting much of it into fat and into fuel storage. So fructose turns
out to be used by animals as a mechanism to store fat. Normally, animals will regulate their weight
beautifully. They just maintain their weight normally. If you take an animal and you put a
tube down its throat and give it extra food to make it gain weight, if you take the tube out,
the animal will go right back to its normal weight. If you starve an animal, and so it's below its
normal weight, and then you let it just eat, it will eat back to its regular weight. But when it
wants to gain fat, it will do so usually through a mechanism that involves fructose. So what they do
is they, like a hibernating animal, will start eating a lot of fruit in the fall to increase
its weight and increase, induces insulin resistance. It gets hungry. It drops its metabolism so that
most of the energy it eats goes into fat. And the same thing with a long distance migrating bird,
they'll start eating fruit to get the fruit dose. And so this is a very common pattern. And it's
driven by that ATP depletion. And this is distinct, or in parallel, of course, to this uricase
mutation. So can you separate these two phenomenon? In other words, if you can restore uricase to the
non-mutated version, do you still have this problem around the ATP depletion? Yeah. So the ATP depletion
triggers a series of reactions. And what happens, what the key one is, not only does ATP decrease in
the cell, but intracellular phosphate also falls. And that activates an enzyme called AMP deaminase
that converts the broken down product of ATP, which is AMP, and it converts it to uric acid.
And that process has multiple steps. And we know that that whole pathway is involved in the
generation and stimulation of fat, insulin resistance, fatty liver, elevations in blood
pressure, a variety of effects. And that pathway is what seems to be critical for inducing obesity
from sugar. Let's go through that again, because that, what you sort of talked about at the very
end is effectively the thesis of your book, The Fat Switch. You explained what ATP is, adenosine
triphosphate. And the T of course stands for tri, there are three phosphates. It's the liberation
of a phosphate that is the production of energy. So when you need to breathe, you need to move,
when you need to do anything, you have to turn ATP into ADP. So the chemical reaction is adenosine
triphosphate becomes adenosine diphosphate, one phosphate escapes, and that's what gives us the
energy. Now that can happen again. ADP can lose one of its two remaining phosphates and become AMP,
adenosine monophosphate. What you said after is the really critical, critical piece of this,
which is when you have a molecule of adenosine monophosphate, it stands at a proverbial fork
in the road. It can either go down a path that is driven by something called AMPK or AMP kinase,
or it can go down the pathway of AMPD. Now let's go back to this point, because again,
it seems everything comes down to that choice. What happens if AMP goes down the AMPK pathway
versus the AMPD pathway? Yeah, so if it goes down the AMPK pathway, it actually is burning energy,
it's burning fat, it does a lot of really positive things. If it goes down the AMPD pathway, it goes
down a fat storage pathway. So it's their exact kind of opposites. AMPD, if you stimulate it,
it will cause insulin resistance and eventually diabetes. Whereas if you stimulate AMPK, you can
actually use that like metformin to actually treat diabetes. So that fork is critical. And what drives
that switch is the fall in intracellular phosphate. And the reason that phosphate falls is because
it's taken up in the fructose one phosphate, or it's taken up by fructose. So the fructose gets
phosphorylated by the ATP, and it becomes fructose one phosphate that sequesters phosphate. And there
is this process where both ATP levels fall and intracellular phosphate falls, and that triggers
this AMPD pathway. And if we interrupt the AMPD pathway, we can block a lot of the metabolic effects.
Do other animals also have this phenomenon? Oh yeah, no, we can show this, we actually showed
it in hibernating squirrels. So when a squirrel wants to gain weight, it will activate the pathway
for AMPD. When it's hibernating and burning the fat, it activates the AMPK pathway. I got it. So
even though humans and our most close descendants in primates have the uricase mutation, this
ability to toggle between AMPK and AMPD is unique to any species that has the potential to gain
weight and wants to use it to their advantage. Oh, absolutely. Part of the pathway through which
AMPD is working involves the generation of uric acid. So we know that the uric acid,
when it's going up inside the cell, is doing all kinds of biological effects, and the AMPD is
driving that. There may be other things besides the uric acid. So the hummingbird or the squirrel
can still store fat. They just don't get the bump in uric acid that comes with it because they don't
have the uricase mutation. Well, actually the hummingbird does have the uricase mutation.
Oh, really? Yeah. I don't know my evolution well enough. So birds have the uricase. Birds bifurcated
off after it. Yeah. Reptiles have the uricase mutation. Even dinosaurs had the uricase mutation.
Sue, the dinosaur, the Tyrannosaurus rex actually had gout. I mean, that's got to be why Tyrannosaurus
rex was so ornery because if you think of the size of the T-Rex great toe, I mean, that would
be infuriating to every bronchosaurus out there. Yeah, I think so. He's eating too many of the
bronchosaurae. Sorry to get back into the minutiae of this, but it's important. You still have to
phosphorylate glucose during its metabolism. Why is it that the phosphorylation of glucose during
its metabolism to pyruvate doesn't result in a strong enough drop in intracellular phosphate
to cause the same problem? Because the reaction stops. Whenever the phosphate and ATP levels
start dropping a little bit. You have that auto regulatory thing with the... There's an auto
regulatory thing with it. The enzyme stops functioning. It's inhibited and then that
allows the ATP levels to stay normal. So here's a really cool follow-up of this and that is that
sugar is much more likely to cause obesity if you drink it rather than if you eat it. And the reason
for that is that when you drink a drink that has fructose in it, we tend to drink a lot in a short
period of time. So if you have a soft drink, you can drink... Not only does it have a lot of sugar,
but we tend to drink it fast. And so the concentration of fructose turns out to be
high when it gets to the liver and it's the concentration that triggers this reaction. So
if the concentration of fructose is really low, the ATP depletion may not be significant to drive
dramatic metabolic effects. But if the concentration of fructose is really high,
then you're going to get a big metabolic effect. So eating like a candy bar where it's coming with
lots of fat, lots of glucose, lots of all sorts of things, lots of protein. If it's like a Snickers
bar and it's got nuts or whatever, even if it's the same amount of fructose, even if you're talking
about 25 grams of fructose versus 25 grams of fructose, you would drink very quickly. You're
saying equal amounts of fructose can produce a different effect if both the speed and the
concentration with which they arrive at the liver are different. Yeah, it's the amount,
it's the speed, and it's ultimately how rapidly it's absorbed. So if you drink something,
if you take a lot of fructose, like, I mean, candy is very concentrated fructose. I mean,
if you eat that, for example, on an empty stomach, that will be absorbed faster than if you eat it
with oatmeal or something, you know, where there's fiber and so forth. And so the speed of absorption
and the makes a difference. So for example, if I was working for a high fructose corn syrup company,
and I wanted to prove that a soft drink wasn't bad, I could do a study where I would give the
soft drinks to people, but I would give it over, you're only allowed to make a tiny sip every 10
minutes. So it takes you three hours to drink a soft drink. In that case, the amount, even though
you're drinking a lot, the concentration may never be enough. You never let the phosphate depletion
get significant enough in magnitude that it really triggers AMPD. Yes, that's it. You know,
it's really interesting. I think of all the sugar, the pro sugar studies I've read that are funded
by the sugar industry. I don't think I've ever dug into the methodology to look at factors like that
specifically. Well, the other issue is like if you just take a single dose of fructose,
most of the metabolic effects are best seen like in the first four hours following the ingestion.
So the triglycerides go up and the uric acid goes up and the blood pressure goes up.
But if you just do a single dose study, if you then look the following morning,
or the effects have now kind of come back down, then you can't really show it. And a lot of these
studies, they design it that way. So they say, aha, fructose doesn't raise uric acid, but we
measured it after fasting overnight. But the surge in uric acid occurred earlier. So that's the
one common trick. So all these things you're talking about with fructose seem to fit almost
directly into the five characteristics of metabolic syndrome, which are elevated glucose.
So that insulin resistance would be manifested as an elevated glucose, elevated blood pressure,
elevated waste circumference, storage of fat, elevated triglycerides, what you just said.
And the only one we didn't address is low HDL cholesterol, which is the fifth finding.
Now, of course, three out of those five are sufficient to put you in the category, but
fructose does all five. What is the mechanism by... So you've already described the mechanism by
which it does three of them. We alluded loosely to how it raises triglycerides, but I'd like to
talk about that more. And then of course, I'd like to hear how it lowers HDL cholesterol.
Okay. So the uric acid generated by fructose has a very pronounced effect to stimulate oxidative
stress in the mitochondria. And fructose also generates lactate big time. And the lactate also
has effects on mitochondria, as you learned from Dr. Sam Melan's talk. And in addition, fructose
preferentially decreases mitochondrial function and stimulates glycolysis. And so all those things
cause... You get this big oxidative stress to the mitochondria. And there's an enzyme in the
mitochondria that drives fat oxidation called enylchoahydratease. I mean, sorry to...
Throw it out there. This is what we're hearing.
No, no, no. We're here to talk about it.
But basically, the oxidative stress inhibits that. So fatty acid oxidation goes down. So you block
fat burning. And then in addition, you block an enzyme called econotase with oxidative stress
to the mitochondria. And that increases citrate, which drives fat generation. And so you end up
with fatty liver that's driven by both increased fat synthesis and a block in fat burning. The
mitochondrial oxidative stress also is very much linked with the development of insulin resistance.
And then uric acid is also the generated uric acid. It's also causing oxidative stress to the
islets, to the pancreatic islets as well.
Uric acid is actually harmful to the islet cells of the pancreas?
In fact, if you give sugar, we did a study where we gave sugar to animals where we actually
restricted the amount of calories. The rats were getting... They were on a diet, basically.
They were on a diet...
They were on a high sugar, low calorie diet.
Right. And then we had as a control,
rats that got the same number of calories, but they weren't getting the sugar.
Right. So just a low calorie, low sugar diet.
Yeah. And when we gave the high sugar, low calorie diet, all the animals developed fatty liver,
hypertension, insulin resistance.
Did they actually gain weight?
No. No. This is a trick. Weight gain really requires increased calories, really to show it.
You know, long-term, maybe just decreasing metabolism will do it.
But this is interesting. You're saying both animals lost weight. Did they lose about the
same amount of weight?
No. They maintained their weight. Even though they were eating 90% of what they normally eat,
they were able to maintain.
So both groups slowed their metabolism enough to maintain weight at a 10% reduction of calories.
So in the outside, they looked the same, but the high sugar group still developed fatty liver.
Severe. And they all became diabetic.
Do you recall in that study, Rick, what the actual percentage of their macros that came from fructose?
20%.
Right. So the critic will say, well, that's highly unnatural. Although in reality, it's not that
unnatural. There are lots of people, unfortunately, walking around getting 20% of their energy input
from that. So it's not physiologically completely out of whack, but as a proof of concept,
these animals got diabetes without gaining weight. They got fatty liver disease without
gaining weight. They were, by definition, insulin resistant.
Right. And when we measured their insulin levels, they first became insulin resistant with high
serum insulin levels, which is what we see.
Early diabetes, basically.
Early to type 2 diabetes. But over time, the serum insulin levels started to fall.
So they almost develop a type 1 diabetes.
Well, just like humans do. And what we saw is that the islets used to be the phrase was called
islet exhaustion because longstanding type 2 diabetes, we see the same thing, but it's
actually low grade inflammation in the islets. And we could show that there was low grade
inflammation and it was associated with big time upregulation of urate transport proteins
on the islet. And when we took isolated islets and we put uric acid on them and induced oxidative
stress and over time caused a drop in insulin level. So what we think is going on is that
sugar causes diabetes through this pathway that we've been talking about. And it involves
initially insulin resistance, but over time it will cause islet cell dysfunction as well.
And this has been confirmed by other groups now.
That sort of comes to the triglyceride story, right? If you have a net accumulation of fat
in the liver, you're going to have to export some of that in the form of VLDL, a very low
density lipoprotein. So that would drive up the serum triglyceride. What's driving down the HDL
cholesterol?
You know, I haven't studied that personally. I don't really know, but I did see that there
are reports that fructose can lower HDL, like in animals and stuff, but I don't really know
the mechanism.
When you sort of pause for a moment, Rick, do you ever worry that talking about fructose this way
just seems, I don't know what the word is. I don't think it's necessarily being too much of
a reductionist, but it almost seems too simple that this one molecule could simultaneously have
probably allowed our species to survive during this very cold spell six to 12 million years ago.
And obviously evolution wasn't thinking 12 million years into the future that we'd be flush with
fructose. And yet here we are today. One could interpret what you're saying to mean if you
simply had no fructose in your diet, most of the bad things we think about metabolically would go
away. Is that a fair assessment?
Yeah, I think that's true. So let me give you another one where we've really learned a lot.
I don't know if you are aware of the relationship with cancer, but what we've learned is that
fructose was an incredible survival nutrient in the setting of near starvation.
So as I mentioned, what we're learning is all these animals use fructose. They either get it
from their diet or they make it in their body, and they use that to help them survive. And we can
talk about it, but it involves not just storing energy, but they use fructose to store water.
And we can talk about that. And they use it to become insulin resistant. Insulin resistance is
a survival mechanism whereby increasing blood glucose and preventing glucose from taking up
in the skeletal muscle, it preserves it for the brain, which is what you want to do if you don't
have enough food around, you want to be able to think so you can escape predators and so forth.
So it was a survival tool to increase energy. And it actually also protected animals from a
low oxygen state. So by switching, by reducing mitochondrial function and stimulating this thing
called glycolysis, it allowed the animal to survive with a lower oxygen state. And so we know,
for example, that the naked mole rat, which lives in burrows, very low oxygen burrows,
they make fructose to survive when they're in those burrows. So suddenly the fructose goes up
in their blood and they use it to survive the low oxygen tension there because they switch from
mitochondrial metabolism to glycolysis. But why can't they just rely more on glucose for which
we have such an abundant apparatus to store it at large amounts? Is there an energetic reason for
fructose? A lot of the fructose is converted to glucose and to lactate, which can be converted
to glucose, and then it's driven through this glycolysis pathway. So it turns out, though,
that what happens is when you metabolize glucose, a lot of it will go through mitochondrial metabolism.
And so if we can inhibit mitochondrial metabolism, which uses oxygen, we can live off glycolysis,
which doesn't require oxygen. So what happens is in a low oxygen state, like the naked mole rat,
will use fructose to survive. But cancers... But wait, I'm still confused about this, Rick, because
wouldn't that fructose, but they're not storing that fructose as fat then, because that would be
the worst fuel they could have around in a low oxygen environment, right? Well, so fructose is
increasing glycogen and lipid, but it's also reducing mitochondrial use. When you're eating
fructose, you actually are not burning the fat. You are storing the fat. And then so what it's
doing is it's putting you into a glycolytic state. So animals use it to store fat, and then they
fast, and then they burn the fat. So they hibernate, or they go flying long distances,
where they have no food, and then they switch. And then the fat that they've stored suddenly
becomes their survival. But during the time that they're in a low oxygen state, they want to have
fructose on board, because the fructose is helping them to survive low oxygen by switching their
metabolism. But unfortunately, like cancers also live in a low oxygen state. And so these cancers
love fructose as their fuel, because it helps support them surviving in a low oxygen state.
So recently, it's been shown that many cancers, colon, liver, kidney, breast, brain,
all these cancer cells, intestinal, they all tend to like fructose as their preferential fuel.
There was just a paper in Science a few weeks ago, and if you block that fructose pathway,
the cancers don't do as well. And when you say block it, do you mean block
fructokinase? Yes. Which pathway specifically? Fructokinase. So if you take intestinal colon cancer,
you put high fructose corn syrup on it, they love it, they grow, they metastasize. And if you block
fructokinase and block fructose metabolism, you can block a lot of the growth of those cancers.
Do you have a sense of how much you're blocking it? It's pretty remarkable. It's like 50% or more.
And we know it's the fructose, not the glucose, presumably because we don't impair glucose
metabolism at all in that experiment. That's correct. And also they were able to show that
this was driven by that shift from a mitochondrial-based metabolism to a glycolytic metabolism.
And what happens to lactate levels in that setting? Oh, very high.
Meaning the more fructose they have, the higher the lactate level?
Yes. Again, very counterintuitive, because aren't we sort of taught that the liver is the only organ
that can really process fructose and that it all sort of accumulates there? And I mean, conventional
thinking is that fructose really doesn't have much of an interaction outside of the liver
unless converted to glucose, correct? That was said by a lot of people, but the findings show that
about 20% of fructose is used by the intestine, maybe 40% by the liver. And at least 10 to 20%
can escape into the circulation. And of course, if the larger the dose, the more that will pass.
And the kidneys are big target. There's fructokinase in the brain. There's fructokinase in the islets.
There's fructokinase in the adipose tissue. Does the muscle have fructokinase?
There's some thought that fructokinase may be in the muscle. It's got to be very low,
but there's some thought that fructose is being metabolized in the scallop muscle.
And one of the things that's interesting is there was a paper in Nature that showed that the heart
normally doesn't have fructokinase, but when you have a heart attack, the low oxygen state there
induces the fructokinase and there's probably production, endogenous production of fructose.
And it seems to be involved in cardiac remodeling. So it's probably involved in more things than we
think of. And certainly it's in the brain. Which means that in theory, the brain could actually use
free molecules of fructose to make ATP in addition to the mainstay of its energy metabolism, which is
glucose driven and lactate. I think we're now seeing lactate. There's actually some evidence
that first off, we know that fructokinase is in the brain. We know the brain can make fructose
and there's increasing evidence that insulin resistances can occur just in the brain and
maybe a forerunner for the development of Alzheimer's. And there are actually reports
that AMPD aminase is high in the brains of Alzheimer's patients. And it raises the possibility
that local fructose metabolism could be involved in disorders like that. Are there any people with
naturally occurring mutations in fructokinase that render it less capable? Yeah. So there are people
with a condition called the essential fructosuria where they are born without active fructokinase
and they live normally. No one's ever been reported to have type two diabetes or obesity. So these
people, if I'm understanding you correctly, are genetically immune to the harm of sugar. Yes. And
they pee out all the fructos. Yes. Okay. So that seems to be an interesting topic.
This must be very rare. I've never even heard of it. It's a rare condition. They actually don't pee
out all the fructos. Some fructos can be metabolized by an enzyme called hexokinase,
which is normally metabolized as glucose, but fructos is preferentially metabolized by fructokinase.
So these people have very sweet urine going back to Osler had he tasted their urine, he would have
confused them potentially with an even sweeter version than the people would ultimately type two
diabetes. That's how they were discovered because they would have reducing sugars, which was fructos
in their urine that was picked up with the old tests they used to use for diabetes, but then
they didn't have diabetes when they tested them. And these people could literally just consume
all the sugar they wanted and their uric acid is not going to go up. Their blood pressure is not
going to go up. Their trigs don't go up. They don't gain weight. They don't become insulin resistant.
That's right. So is there any benefit to having fructokinase if you're not hibernating or in a
world where famine is potentially coming your way? It's really a survival enzyme that was meant to
help in situations where there was food shortage. If you live in the Western world and you just have
to go down to the grocery store, no, I think living without fructokinase would probably solve a lot of
the world's health problems. I mean, and there are fructokinase inhibitors that are being developed.
Pfizer has one that's now in a finished a phase two trial. It was quite successful at treating
fatty liver. And so now they're taking that drug to phase three. Wow. That's a potential blockbuster
actually. Of course, it begs an interesting question, which is how will that drug be treated?
Will it be only used as a way to treat an active condition such as fatty liver, in which case it's
going to have a smaller on label market versus what will likely happen, which is people who just
want to be able to have more sugar without the consequences of it would take it. Correct. Yeah.
Although it's probably priced to avoid that. I'm guessing. Anyway, yeah, there's a lot of
interest in fructokinase inhibitors. There's other big farmer that are working on it now.
And so we'll have to see if it turns out to be as powerful as we think it might be. So the work that
we've just discussed is sort of been, you've been at this since 2002, basically specifically with
respect to this. Let's go back to allopurinol and uric acid in your clinical practice, because you're
still, you've spent 17 years as the division head of nephrology across three world-class medical
centers, most currently the university of Colorado. And yet I was surprised to learn over dinner the
other day that you still have a very pretty heavy clinical practice. You still actually take care of
patients in the inpatient ward and you probably spend a quarter of your time in clinic. So how do
you put some of this stuff into practice? Do you liberally use allopurinol even for patients who
have high uric acid but have not developed gout yet? I do. So our data strongly suggests that
lowering uric acid could be beneficial. So what I do is the following. So it turns out that allopurinol
is not totally safe. There's some people who can develop reactions to allopurinol drug reactions.
Especially Asians, about three to four percent of people who are Asian can develop an allergic
reaction to allopurinol where they can get rashes and it can be pretty severe. And it's about two
percent in African Americans and it's about 0.5 percent in Caucasians. You can test for it. There's
a test called the HLA B58 test. But the point of the matter is that no drug is fully safe. Every
drug has side effects. So ideally you'd want to really be certain that your drug's going to provide
the benefit that you want and you have to consider the risk versus benefits. Now although in animals
allopurinol is totally protective or protects a lot against sugar induced metabolic syndrome,
the data in humans is suggestive. So there's been for example four pilot studies showing an improvement
in insulin resistance with lower anuric acid in humans. All four are positive. There's a lot of
trials in kidney disease showing that lower anuric acid may benefit kidney disease. There's data on
blood pressure. We had a paper in the JAMA showing that lower anuric acid could improve blood pressure
control in adolescence with hyperuricemia. So there's a lot of supporting data. There are some
negative studies too but the overall weight is now in favor of lowering uric acid to benefit.
What would the target be? So what I do is when I see a patient in clinic I measure the uric acid
and currently we know that the risks start to go up when the serum uric acid is over 5.5.
So once the serum uric acid is over 5.5 they really start to have increased risk for
prediabetes, insulin resistance, hypertension, kidney disease, etc. And what's interesting is
most labs like my lab for example doesn't even flag it until it hits about 6.5 as a sort of
intermediate risk and it's really not until about 7.5 that it says well this is high risk but of
course that's only through the lens of gout I assume. Yes that's right. So if a uric acid comes
back really high like 9 or 10 I have no doubt that that based on everything I've done I have no doubt
that that's not good. Not only does it increase the risk for gout but it increases the risk for
kidney disease and all these things and I talk to the patient about the pros and cons of treatment.
I talk about the rash. I tell them to stop the drug if they get a rash and then call me. But I
always start alipurinol when the uric acid is like eight or higher and certainly when it's nine or
higher. When it's between 5.5 and eight I'll talk to them about the pros and cons but we don't have
full proof yet. But I tend to do it especially with patients with kidney disease where the data
is probably the strongest to start treating. I'll even do it with uric acid of six and a half for
example with chronic kidney disease. But anyway it's worthwhile discussing it with the patient.
But outside of the risk of Stevens-Johnson syndrome which you've alluded to, what are the
other potential risks of alipurinol? That's by far the big one. Some people will get just a mild rash
without true Stevens-Johnson syndrome. There are rare cases where liver function tests may be
elevated but it seems to be rare. If you start at a huge dose right away it can increase xanthine
levels in the urine. Theoretically there could be risk for xanthine stones but I've never seen it.
So it's really the risk of Stevens-Johnson. And do you have to use alipurinol or can you use
euloric or other drugs that also lower uric acid? Well the xanthine oxidase inhibitors are
the best because the way uric acid works to cause cardiovascular disease and kidney disease and all
these things appear to be through its actions inside the cell as we said works on mitochondria
and it does all these things. It's not it's work outside the cell so gout is really an extracellular
deposition but when you're thinking about uric acid and its biologic effects that's an
intracellular action. So xanthine oxidase makes uric acid inside the cell so one of the best ways
to reduce intracellular uric acid is to give us xanthine oxidase inhibitor like alipurinol or
fiboxestat. Now fiboxestat I think it's probably just as good as alipurinol but there was a big
clinical trial that was published in the New England Journal that showed that alipurinol
was associated with less cardiovascular risk than fiboxestat. There seemed to be an increased
cardiovascular events in the fiboxestat group. Meaning less of a reduction or more events.
Well see the problem was there was no placebo group. Oh yeah that's a disaster. Yeah that's
a disaster. This is the Vioxx problem with naproxen. Yeah I mean so the problem is
alipurinol is less than fiboxestat but there's no placebo group. Theoretically the placebo group
would be higher than both of them. Yeah it could be higher than both of them and there's actually
evidence that that's probably true but because of the CARES study the way it was designed we don't
know. So the FDA is worried about giving fiboxestat to people with cardiovascular problems because
they would prefer you to give alipurinol but the trouble is it's not necessarily that fiboxestat
is bad it's just that it's not as good as alipurinol. And it's like a hundred thousand times more
expensive too. Although it's I think becoming generic now so we may see a change in that.
I believe it when I see it and of course the way you trust the generics but that's a whole separate
issue. Exactly. So what about sodium restriction going back to how we started the discussion?
I'll tell you a story from I may have even told this on the podcast once before but in medical
school I remember when we were doing renal physiology we had a great nephrology professor
who was teaching something and I think he was quite ahead of his time because this was
more than 20 years ago and he was not sort of part of this salt is bad bandwagon even though
he was a nephrologist. And I won't do it because I won't do it justice but in a beautiful southern
accent he made the point that if you lined up all of the nephrons in the world all the functional
units of the kidneys in the world from dumbest to smartest and then all of the nephrologists
in the world from dumbest to smartest and you took that dumbest nephron and put it next to the
smartest nephrologist it's still smarter. His point being of course like the kidney is a brilliant
organ that is exceptional at auto regulation of everything from flow to osmolarity to
anion cation exchange. Again his point being he didn't buy this argument that salt is the problem.
You're saying something much more nuanced and I want to kind of go back to it because I think
there are important clinical implications of it. You're saying no no salt does play a role
but it's dose timing bolus concentration that matters. It can also be amplified
or mitigated by the state of inflammation. So how do you then translate that information to your
patients acknowledging that they're a very select group of people by definition they have kidney
disease or they wouldn't be seeing you. So it's the combination of salt and water. So if you don't
drink any water as you eat salt you're going to raise your serum sodium you're going to get
thirsty and as soon as you're thirsty you've triggered that in itself is a sign that you're
already making fructose from the salt. So when you eat salt you're making fructose in your body
and the fructose is then driving a lot of effects. Now we know that high salt diets are associated
with obesity not just high blood pressure they're associated with the development of diabetes.
There's many studies now but high salt looks like it works by producing fructose. So if you drink
water with salt the danger of the salt is much less. If you drink water and then eat your pretzel
you would be safer than if you ate your pretzel and then drink the water
because what triggers it is the rise in salt. And so when you see someone in the clinic what we try
to do is to tell them to drink a lot of water and to reduce their salt but it isn't the amount of
salt it's the balance of salt and water. Now that can be sometimes challenging for patients in a
kidney clinic because that would be one population in which you do have to be mindful of volume.
Right but most patients who chronic kidney disease they will excrete water normally or just
minimally abnormal and so there's actually clinical trials looking at the evidence that water may slow
the progression of kidney disease. It might be working in part by blocking the effects of salt
and so forth on the kidney and we experimentally can show that giving water can slow kidney disease
progression. So drinking water turns out to be good. Here's another thing it turns out that many
animals use fructose to make fat as a means for making water. So when you make fat although there's
no water stored in the fat when they burn the fat they make water. So whales don't drink salt water
they are fat because when they break down the fat they're making the water we call it metabolic
water. So it turns out that fructose drives fat production and in part to preserve water not just
energy. So animals will use that fat to provide an energy source but also to provide water. So it
turns out that if you take an animal on fructose and you give it a lot of water you can suppress
some of the obesity. You can suppress some of the effects of metabolic syndrome and so the old
wives tale that drinking six glasses of water a day is good to help keep you skinny is true. It
turns out that water suppresses some of the effects of fructose. And does it need to be water? Could
it be tea or coffee or something that's equally the osmolarity of water is what serum is about 280?
Yep. Okay so anything with the zero osmolarity is good enough? Yes. Technically a diet soda should
have a zero osmolarity as well right? Yeah diet soda would work actually. For the record you and
I are sitting here drinking just plain water. Right and diet sugars have their own issues.
We'll come back to that in a few seconds because that's interesting. So Rick you sort of you toss
these little nuggets out there like they're nothing but they sound I mean again just based on the sort
of breadth of research you've put into this it almost just seems too good to be true and so profound
yet you sort of throw it out there like an after the fact. Well look as long as you drink enough
water and don't eat fructose and god forbid don't drink fructose manage your uric acid levels etc etc
so you make it seem like a lot of problems could go away from these things. How would you shape
that advice for someone with normal kidney disease? Pardon me with normal kidneys. Would
you basically just say the same thing or can you be less restrictive with sodium for example?
If we could reduce our fructose intake I think it would have a huge huge effect but the problem
that most people face is that sugar and high fructose corn syrup are in almost everything.
So if you go to the supermarket like 70 percent of processed foods have sugar in it and packaged
foods actually 70 percent of packaged foods have sugar or high fructose corn syrup in it so it's
very hard to avoid it and here's another problem our bodies can make fructose. So our bodies as I
mentioned we can make fructose from a high salt diet we can make fructose if we get dehydrated
we can make fructose high uric acid stimulates fructose production. And we're making the fructose
out of glucose in all of these situations? Yes high glycemic diets normally if you take an animal
and you give it starch they will not really get fat but we all know that french fries which don't
have sugar in it they don't have fructose they are fattening but you've got potatoes which raise your
glucose and what we showed is that if you just give glucose to an animal the high glucose as it
hits the liver induces this enzyme to convert glucose to fructose. Which enzyme is that that
converts glucose into fructose? Aldose reductase so when we took mice and we gave them glucose
and we were thinking we might not see much because we were believing that fructose is the culprit but
over time these animals got really fat they got insulin resistant everything. But you had to
over feed them glucose. We put the glucose in their drinking water so they were drinking a
lot of glucose but they would eat less chow so we gave them chow and glucose in their drinking water
and their chow had it was normal chow it wasn't the high fat high sugar chow no just regular
chow and these animals started getting really really fat and when we looked at the portal vein
which goes into the liver the glucose levels were high and when we looked in the liver
we found that this enzyme was activated it's also activated in diabetics for example because of the
high glucose in the blood and when that enzyme got activated it started to make fructose so even
though these animals were eating no fructose they were producing fructose in their liver and then
when we blocked their fructose metabolism they're eating the same amount of glucose no change
exactly the suddenly they're not getting as fat they have no fatty liver they're not insulin
resistant. But this suggests Rick that a diet in excess carbohydrate even if it's not high in
sugar could lead to fatty liver disease. Yes yeah absolutely if you have that enzyme induced
but let's say that you are a young person when you're young this enzyme is really not present
in the liver once you're eating sugar though if you eat a lot of sugar it will induce that enzyme.
For how long? I don't fully know but let's say that you eat a lot of sugar and you get obese
so sugar itself it looks like the induction of this enzyme probably would be reversible
within a few weeks but once your uric acid goes up that will keep it elevated. So that's another
reason potentially to use allopurinol if necessary in addition to fructose restriction to keep uric
acid low is to prevent or mitigate the induction of this enzyme. Oh yeah right so it turns out that
if you give a starch or potatoes to a skinny person who does not have all those reductase induced
they can eat the potatoes they want. In Ireland back in the 1700s where potato was basically
the main thing they were eating there wasn't a lot of obesity but you wait until you eat sugar
and then develop the metabolic syndrome now you stop eating sugar but you continue to eat carbs
and the carbs are going to continue to activate through the same pathway. So a low carb diet
is really great because it's necessary if you're overweight or fasting but that's basically
reducing carbs too but a low carb diet when you're overweight is removing the high glycemic carbs
that are also driving the disease but it's through fructose. So it seems that fructose reduction
obviously comes with its own benefits do you have a sense of how much fructose can be produced in a
fructose free intake environment just from glucose is it a meaningful amount? Well we did our study
by putting glucose in the drinking water they're getting a lot of glucose we haven't done the study
is the one that you're talking about trying to figure out what the range is. I do think that if
you just give high glucose alone you probably have to give a lot but if you've already triggered
the production of this enzyme aldose reductase you probably don't have to give a lot. What about fat
what if you did that same experiment with rats or mice which would be hard because to eat pure fat
is difficult but if there was a way that somehow you could make it palatable enough that they could
you could overfeed them to the same extent using fat and protein. Let's say they're getting a normal
amount of glucose but the overfeed was coming through the fat would that induce any of these
properties? In other words is part of this due to an absolute sense of total energy being too high
or is this really about a particular carbohydrate? It's definitely about a particular carbohydrate
because we've actually done what's called pair feeding where you control how much they eat and
you can have your control group. This fructose effect will still as I mentioned cause fatty
liver. Explain what pair feeding is for people because it's a clever little tool done in this
type of research. So the way fructose works is it works by making you eat more and that's how you
gain weight but even when you control so that you don't eat more fructose will not cause weight gain
but it will cause fatty liver insulin resistance and diabetes and so forth and the way we can show
that is by pair feeding. In pair feeding we give each animal eats the same amount of food so if you
give one animal sugar which normally makes it want to eat more because it causes this thing called
leptin resistance where they want to eat more but if we don't give them any more food we only give
them the same amount as the control then there will be no difference in weight but there will be
differences in fatty liver metabolic syndrome and so forth. The sugar industry has used this to
their advantage so what they say is okay we're going to look at clinical trials where we've given
sugar and we're going to see if sugar causes weight gain but it's only fair to do that if we have it
controlled where we control the energy intake to be equal among groups. So they have a control group
where they've restricted there's a caloric restriction on both sides so you have a high
sugar and a non-high sugar group but it's not where you get to the people get to eat as much as they
want. Basically is this problem of not having ad libitum feeding so it's sort of like what the sugar
industry is saying is look a calorie is a calorie if I give you a hundred calories of sugar and
completely control what you can eat in response to that and compare you to another person who's
eating the same number of calories you're really not going to gain weight. Now the problem with that
experiment is it's not the real world in the real world you don't have a clamp on your response.
Exactly and so when you give sugar to animals they become leptin resistant over time and they
lose their ability to control their appetite so then they eat more and so then their weight goes
up but the fructose is also doing stuff where even if you control for the weight gain they still get
the fatty liver and stuff which the controls don't. Now a second ago you sort of alluded to
artificial sweeteners so comparing I mean I'm sure you get this question asked all the time
by your patients which is I just really love Coca-Cola is having a diet coke it must be
significantly better right I mean there's no fructose in it there's no glucose in it
so is there a downside to it? Yeah I think there are downsides but first let me just say the positive
side we have taste buds that sense sweet and so when we eat sugar the taste buds are activated
and it stimulates this dopamine response in the brain that tells us that we like this sugar. If
you actually knock out the sweet taste buds or just knock out the tastes in general animals will
still like sugar they will still eat sugar a lot of sugar. How hard is that to do experimentally
to knock out the sweet tasting capacity? It's been done and we actually have also done it where we
knock out all taste. Can you do it to me? No it's like a genetic knockout but anyway these animals
will still like sugar but they won't like artificial sugar so the artificial sugar is really driven by
the sweet taste but what makes animal like real sugar it's through its metabolism. I mean it is
true if you knock out taste they will tend to eat a little bit less sugar but they actually still
develop metabolic syndrome. That's super interesting so you're saying part of our
affinity for sugar is not just in our taste buds and in our brain but also in our periphery where
the metabolism takes place and the elegant way you demonstrate that is you give something of equal
sweetness concentration that's non-nutritive and you completely reduce the appetite for it even
though it might have the same central effect it doesn't have the peripheral effect. Probably the
sweet taste bud developed to try to encourage us to eat these foods that at the time were survival
foods but the food itself the sugar itself stimulates dopamine and other effects independently
of the sweet taste whereas an artificial sugar just is activating the sweet taste. Now if you give
a mouse or a rat artificial sugar they don't gain weight but if you give them regular sugar they do
so there is some evidence that artificial sugars are better than sugar and if a person says to me
oh doc I'm afraid to drink this diet coke because it's got chemicals in it I want to drink regular
coke because of that that's an error. Regular coke is more dangerous than a diet coke. However
there is truth that things like aspartame and sucralose we don't know fully the safety of these.
Aspartame when last I checked had been studied more by the FDA than any other molecule ingested
by humans. It's hard to make the case that at the small doses that people would consume them.
I'm talking about someone who has a serving of this stuff a day. I don't know I've always found
that argument that well we don't know the full safety profile of these things to be as like what
else do we need on this one. I think aspartame is kind of gross truthfully like I don't really like
it that much but I just think it's definitely the lesser of two evils isn't it. It's definitely the
lesser of two evils that part's for sure but we don't fully know the safety of some of these like
saccharin for example has been associated with little bladder tumors in mice my recollections
that aspartame can generate small tiny concentrations of formaldehyde. I think it really comes down to
dose. Yes I think it is. I think those studies were really based on rats or rodents consuming
doses that simply couldn't be replicated by humans. That's probably true. Nevertheless water is good.
Yeah that's generally been my take to people as well is look all things equal by certainly consume
water, tea, things like that but yeah there's this lesser of two evils approach but this point you
made this is completely news to me and very interesting because certainly much of the
neurobiology today would suggest that the response we have to sugar is mostly centrally mediated.
The quote-unquote addictive because everyone loves to talk about functional MRI and what happens in
your brain when you're eating sugar and all of these other things but I guess I haven't seen
this side by side but presumably the fMRI would light up the same for non-nutritive versus like
aspartame and sugar correct? Yeah. So let's talk about another taste which is umami. I remember we
were having sushi one night when we discussed this. What is umami? What is that taste? So umami is the
savory taste. And this is different from salt isn't it? So there's five taste buds. So there's salt,
there's sweet and as I mentioned both of these taste buds seem to drive a weight gain. Sugar is
by far the fastest. It takes only two months in a laboratory animal and salt takes four months,
five months. So high salt generates fructose but it's a much slower process than just eating sugar.
Then you have umami which is the savory taste and then you have bitter and sour and the bitter and
sour probably developed to help you avoid eating certain foods. So coffee is an example of bitter
like a coffee bean or something like a ground? I think so. Yeah okay. Anyway so umami is driven by
glutamate but it's markedly enhanced by purines like IMP and even uric acid. So it turns out that
umami is sort of a taste receptor for uric acid type foods. Foods that raise uric acid. Now is
MSG the purest form of umami that we would eat? Yes. MSG is the primary stimulant and people put
it in foods to encourage food intake. Now there's some link of umami with obesity in epidemiologic
studies and there are situations where you can give umami type foods and especially if you can
do it in a liquid form you can induce obesity. So umami may not be as safe as we think it is. So it's
got a lot of good things written about it in the literature. Don't most people view MSG as evil?
Yeah I think MSG is viewed as evil. But that seems to be largely unfounded based on my view
of the literature. I can't really find evidence that umami is harmful. There's this Chinese
restaurant syndrome where people get a warm and a headaches and it's thought to be due to excess of
MSG. But foods that are umami rich are often foods that we love. I mean shrimp has umami,
Caesar salad, the parmesan and things like that have umami. And so in general people like umami
foods and it's certainly in the websites it is often promoted. But if the umami foods have a
lot of purines which enhance the umami flavor it actually may raise uric acid and kind of bypass
the sugar pathway. And we think that that may turn out to be somewhat of a risk factor too.
So do you add this to the list of things that you caution people about? We've already got the
pair your salt with water idea, the restrict fructose and please god don't ever drink it.
Do you then add the MSG containing high umami foods to that playbook for ways to reduce metabolic
disease? I think so. Yeah I think that foods like shrimps and things like that if you eat a lot of
them they probably activate this pathway too. We're still trying to learn more about it but it looks
like it could be a contributor. I think it's if you rank it number one is is sugar and then
everything else is less. High glycemic carbs can be converted to sugar. What I usually say is
the big four are bread, potatoes, chips, and rice. Those four are the foods that you should
reduce a little bit. Wait chips as in like chips potato chips? Yeah potato chips. So you're giving
potatoes two votes out of four. Yeah well our corn chips are you know the kind of things that
people put out on their table before you eat dinner. And they coat it with salt which isn't
good. Anyway so high glycemic carbs I think really salty foods drink water. I mean that's
really important. And umami so for example what makes beer so much more dangerous than other
alcohols for inducing obesity is because beer has all this yeast in it, brewer's yeast, which
basically is activating umami pathways and it's one of the reasons we like beer. This is that
cellular density issue you spoke about. Exactly and so a beer raises uric acid more and there
really is this beer belly syndrome and if you look at people who drink a lot of beer it isn't just
they get abdominal obesity. They get fatty liver, they get high blood pressure, their triglycerides
go up. They basically have metabolic syndrome. Alcohol especially beer can also mimic sugar
and it's probably because of the umami component coupled with the alcohol. Those two. This is the
part that can sometimes drive a person insane when they're trying to think about all of these
things is it's very difficult to provide clear advice to people because there's so many caveats
that are required because the dose makes the poison, the speed of delivery, what it's combined
with all of these things. I'm using that as a preface to ask a question that I'm sure you get
asked a lot which is really a dose question around fructose. So let's ask it in two questions.
If a person is going to drink something in the form of fructose, whether it be fruit juice or
soda or sports drinks, which are from a fructose standpoint all basically the same, is there a
dose of fructose above which you think it really makes no sense under any circumstance or below
which you think once in a while is not the end of the world? I mean personally I would not drink
any liquids that have sugar in it or a fructose or high fructose corn syrup. That's fine. So we're
going to draw a hard line there. Hard line. Okay now what about eating fructose in the form of
fruit? Because remember there's some big ass fruits out there. Like you look at a Fuji apple,
which is my favorite apple. I mean I like these monster Fuji apples so like half the size of my
head or maybe a third the size of my head. That's got to have 30 grams of fructose in it. I don't
think it has that much. Oh really? I really don't. Most apples and that would be a big one,
maybe 10 grams at most I would think. No way. You think more? Well think about it. These are
the really big ones. Yeah yeah I'm not talking about a little Macintosh, I'm talking about a
huge apple and they're so sweet too. So you may be right then. Let's talk about natural fruit.
So we've actually done trials in patients with a low fructose diet with or without natural fruit
supplements and generally speaking natural fruit supplements do not seem to block the benefits of
a low fructose diet. Sorry what does that mean? You mean that if you took a patient and restrict
all fructose except fruit? That's correct. They tend to do okay? They did just as well as the
low fructose alone. And can you quantify how much fruit? Because here's the problem when you're
talking to someone like me Rick, I don't do anything in moderation. So we have these bowls
in my kitchen, they're called manly bowls, which by definition a manly bowl is a bowl that you can
wear on your head like a hat. It will come over your head and when I consume fruit I consume it
in that bowl. Yeah I would be careful. So no manly bowls. Yeah so the data suggests that a single
fruit, maybe not the giant fruit, okay I don't know the last time I had a single fruit. Yeah but a
single fruit has like some fruits like kiwi and lime and lemon have almost no fructose
and they're totally safe and other fruits. Pineapple and stuff. You have a fair amount of
sugar. Berries for example, blueberries have so many good things in it. You can eat a big bowl of
blueberries no problem. Raspberry, strawberries, they're all other berries in general are very
good. Grapes, they have a fair amount of sugar. You eat a bowl of grapes, you're going to probably
raise your uric acid and trigger the activation of this pathway. You eat a bowl of grapes, you
might as well be eating raisins based on what my blood glucose meter tells me. Exactly. It's a
disaster. Yeah what I would recommend is to try to not eat too many fruit at one time. So for example
there was a lady named Nott's, Cheryl Nott's I believe is her name and she's an anthropologist
and she was studying orangutans and there's a time when the massing season where all these fruit trees
bloom and then fruit at the same time and then these orangutans go in there and they won't eat
one fruit. They'll eat 100 fruit at one time. I'm descendants of those orangutans. Me too.
So anyway when they what she did is she would go up and collect the urine off the trees and show
that by measuring things like ketones and so forth she could show that when they're eating the fruit
they were actually impairing fat oxidation and they were storing energy and their weights go way up.
And it's because they ate so many fruit. If you eat one fruit you're not going to do that but if
you eat a huge amount of fruit and get all that fructose it will start to overwhelm the good things
in fruit but there's so many good things in fruit. There's vitamin c, there's epicatechin and flavonols
and potassium and all these things that help fight the effects of fructose. So we generally for
patients that have a non-alcoholic fatty liver disease we tend to restrict them to 10 grams a day
of fructose only in the form of whole fruit. Do you think that's overly stringent or is that reasonable?
I think that's wonderful if they can do it. Yeah it basically comes down to you can have a bowl of
berries. No bananas, no apples, none of the high fructose fruits or even large fruits. How do you
handle this with your kids? You have two kids. They're not that young anymore but they were young
during the time in which you were learning all of this stuff. How did you balance the knowledge that
you have? It sucks when your dad knows more about sugar than almost any human on the planet and you're
a kid and we're wired to want sugar. How did you balance the sane delivery of this knowledge to your
family? So first of all things like birthdays and stuff, I let them have birthday cake but we try to
make sugar-free Splenda type cakes at home. So if we make cookies or cakes at home we try to use
Splenda. Now they're still high carb and there can be chocolate in it occasionally you know so they
do get some exposure to sugar. We don't give them fruit juice and we don't give them soft. They are
not allowed regular soft drinks but they can have a diet soft drink. I have a 12-year-old and a 15-year-old.
What we try to do is not to be so restrictive that it's disruptive but we try to be encouraging
them to understand that sugar is playing a big role in obesity and diabetes and that it's unhealthy
to eat a lot. What age do you think kids start to... I think that makes sense which is to me it's
much more important that you would explain to your kids why you might be putting these rules in place
as opposed to just come down as an authoritarian sort of this is the way it's going to be. At what
age did your kids start to understand that dad wasn't just being a pain but there's a real reason
that he's in the short run asking us to make a sacrifice. Also I've been involved in local school
programs and there's a foundation called Living Closer Foundation that I've worked with where
we've gone into schools and tried to teach children elementary schools to learn from fourth
through sixth grade. We try to teach them how to look at labels on foods to understand the amount
of sugar. We do a game where we have someone come up with a cup of tea and add a spoonful of sugar
to it and the person likes it and then we say okay now we're going to make it like a soft drink and
we put in like eight teaspoons of sugar and it's like you can't drink it but that's the equivalent
of what is in a soft drink of the same volume. By the way do you think the carbonation masks some
of that sugar because when you put it that way which is a great way to do it I've never thought
of that experiment. It's almost grotesque. It is. It's a great way to teach kids about sugar. But do
you think the carbonation makes it a little easier to consume such a high amount of sugar in a soft
drink? I suspect so. I haven't tested it but I suspect that's true. Or the phosphoric acid like
there's something else in there that makes it more palatable. Yeah maybe it's the carbonation
probably is. What about dried fruit? Is that a no-no? You know it was so disappointing when I realized
that dried fruit was the fructose of fruits without the good things in it. So when you make
dried fruit a lot of the good things and natural fruits are lost. It's like pure fructose. It's
disappointing because I love dried fruit but I realize it's not the best food for you. Now if
you're out hiking the mountains and you're spending a lot of energy maybe it's good. Yeah exactly
that's the thing I've always got to kick out of. Two things have amused me to no end. One is trail
mix the other are sports drinks. Trail mix probably makes sense when you're mountaineering.
Sports drinks might make sense when you're a professional athlete but paradoxically most
trail mix is consumed off the trail and most sports drinks are not consumed by athletes
actively playing sports. So again the dose makes the poison context matters. Absolutely true. Well
Rick this has been awesome. I want to be mindful of your time and I know that this is a non-clinical
day for you which means every minute we're talking you're not in your lab and I want you
to get back to the lab. So I want to thank you very much again not just for this discussion today
which for me is super interesting and I think the listeners will agree but much more importantly for
the work you've done you've taken a very different approach to quote unquote the war on sugar. You're
less involved on the policy side of this and the sort of advocacy side of this but I think what your
work has done is created the strongest scientific foundation to the harm of fructose and you've done
it in a largely and I say this in a complementary way but in a largely unceremonious way which is
you've sort of had your head down and a lot of people don't know who you are so I hope that more
people become familiar with your work because your I mean your CV is comical in terms of like
it's like every week you seem to publish something in either journal of medicine. The paper we talked
about yesterday which we can't talk about today because it's not yet we're not there yet. I look
forward to seeing that paper in science hopefully in the next six months but that's an unbelievable
tour de force that almost requires us coming back to have a talk about it. Well thank you very much
those are very kind words. Thank you Rick. Really enjoyable and thank you. Thank you for listening
to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we
discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive
content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than
the price of the subscription. Now to that end membership benefits include a bunch of things.
One totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic paper person
thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these.
Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies which are a super short podcast typically less than five minutes
that we release every Tuesday through Friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics
discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes
without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I
believe in but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that
we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only
benefits you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple podcast
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes
only. It does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice diagnosis or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare
professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For
all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward
slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.