Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Ryan Holiday. Ryan is the bestselling author of many
books, including Obstacle is the Way, Ego is the Enemy. His first book, Trust Me, I'm Lying,
which basically predicted the rise of fake news, The Conspiracy, and a number of other books about
marketing, culture, the human condition. His most recent book, Stillness is the Key, came out
recently. And while we talk about it quite a bit, it's actually not even the focus of our discussion.
Instead, I think we talk more broadly about Ryan's influence, his work, the influence that
stoic philosophy has had in his thinking. And obviously, as it permeates into this book,
we talk about anger, we talk about just a number of things that I think factor into the way I try
to think about longevity more broadly than just living longer, but also this idea of suffering
less. And if there's anything I've learned from Ryan, and I've learned a lot from Ryan, because,
as I mentioned in the podcast, and I'll say it again, now, his daily newsletter, The Daily Stoic,
is one of the most important things that I look for in my inbox every morning. Being able to kind
of go into a little bit more detail on that, for me, was great. And I've been wanting to talk with
Ryan for probably about a year, and maybe six months ago, when we sort of realized, well,
the book was going to be coming out, we decided this would be as good a time as any to do so.
The book is fantastic. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Ryan Holiday.
Ryan, thanks so much for making time and for coming out here today.
Of course.
Like I was saying to you a minute ago, I'm kind of bummed I didn't get to come to the farm.
Yeah. So the problem with the farm is it's very wonderful, except we've got like a weird animal
balance going right now. So it's like, what will happen is like a cow will come, and then the dogs
will bark, and then that will make another bark, dog bark. And then it can be this whole cycle that
takes many minutes to settle back down. So it's great for writing. It's great for learning. It's
not great for podcasts or interviews of any kind. Also, the internet's no good. Well, I guess we're
not doing this live to anything, but that's the other big problem.
Talk to me about the joy of having lousy internet.
Yeah, it's great. Weirdly, the crappier it is, the more expensive it is. Like I have fiber at my
place in town and it's like 50 bucks a month for the fastest internet you can possibly imagine.
And then in the country, it's like 150 or 200 bucks a month for like barely Netflix streamable
speeds. And it goes out, you know, if it rains or it goes out all the time. But it's nice because
that's not what you're there for. And we have said this before, but we have like T-Mobile,
and it works great in Austin for cell phones. But out there, it sucks. And AT&T and Sprint both work
pretty good. But we purposely haven't switched just because you get less phone calls. Like if I have
it at the house, like because you pick it up off the Wi Fi, but if you walk too far from the house,
you basically lose cell service, which is good. 99.9% of the time, I'm sure there will be some
time when I cut off my leg with a chainsaw and I desperately need to call for help and I can't.
But otherwise, it creates a sort of an artificial silence, which is great.
Yeah, it's hard to believe that 20 years ago, the maybe a bit longer, but but directionally 20
years ago, the idea that we would have had cell phones with us 24 seven seemed kind of foreign,
certainly 30 years ago, completely a foreign idea. So from a relative, you know, standpoint
of our existence on this planet, this notion of being tethered to that type of device is
basically unbeknownst to our DNA. Yeah, or 20, 30 years ago, maybe you would have a cell phone,
but you weren't getting called on it all the time. So it was like, like, I remember when I got my
first, I got a Blackberry, when I got my first job in Hollywood. And it was great because now
I didn't feel like I had to rush home because there might be emails waiting for me. It gave
me some more freedom. And then increasingly, that freedom turned into now I all you know,
you know what I mean? Like, oh, yeah. So and I think about that with Twitter, I remember when
Twitter first came out and Facebook first came out. And all these things when I was using them
on the desktop, they were wonderful. But then when I was carrying them around in my pocket,
and I could always access them, they're always there. That's when it became much worse. So I
think we're trying to figure out how do we like just suddenly we want these things to go away.
Like when I hear someone they're like, I don't even have a smartphone, I go, well, what if you
get lost? Like how to use directions? You know, there's a lot of benefits to it. But how can you
how do we find a way just to turn back the clock a little bit? Because it was like, we almost had
the right amount. And now we have too much. That's right. Yeah, it's a min max problem that
just missed its optimization point, I think, at least if you were optimizing for our lack of
misery. Yeah, yes. We still have more to gain on the max if the objective is, you know, making
money for the companies and producers like that. Now, you know, I read something that you
wrote, and I got it said, you know, I've been following you for so long, Ryan, I've read so
much of your stuff that, at this point, I can no longer remember. Was this in a daily stoic one day?
Was this in this newsletter? Was this in this book? So I apologize in advance that I'm not even
going to try to reference for the for the listener where this came up. But you talked about
the sort of harsh realities of living on a farm. And we don't live on a farm. But you know, we've
got our chickens, we've got our garden, we've got all that kind of stuff. And I remember the first
time one of our chickens got killed by what turned out to be a bobcat at the time we took it took me
a while to figure out if I assumed it was a raccoon or a coyote. Man, it was super upsetting.
And more upsetting than you'd think you'd be upset over a chicken, right? Like you're like,
come on, they're chickens. They're, you know, how can you, you know, it's not like it's one of your
kids or something. Someone asked me, not that long ago, they were like, what is the strangest
or most surprising thing about a farm? And I was like, there's a lot of death, like just overall,
a lot of death. Chickens die, chickens are, I weirdly, I think chickens are the hardest animal
to have because they're the most defenseless and evolutionarily, like the most pointless.
And pretty much everything is a predator to chickens, like including other chickens.
We had chickens when we were more on the east side here in Austin. And I remember I met my
neighbor because I had to go over and say, hey, a raccoon grabs one of my chickens,
ripped its head off, and then left its carcass on your roof. You know, I need to go get this,
right? So it just familiarizes you with death in a way that I think human beings used to be a lot
more familiar with because like, your grandparents would die in your house, you know, or your wife
would die of childbirth in your house, or you would die being killed by Native Americans in your house,
you know, like, like, we were much more familiar with death, life was more brutal and violent,
but it was also more present, you know, when we first got our farm, we bought this goose and we
had this goose, it was super sweet and nice, it would follow you everywhere we played with it.
And I remember I was sitting in my office watching it and I watched it get attacked by
something in our lake, either a snake or I think maybe a snapping turtle or something in it. So
waddled back up onto the thing and it was like gutted. And we, you know, we hadn't lived that long.
And so we rushed to an emergency vet, we paid like $300 to get this goose, you know, that cost,
you know, eight bucks or whatever, that had no purpose for the farm whatsoever. But this is
what you do with pets. And so we had it all stitched up. And then, and then we had some other
goose, or geese, I guess, but nurse it back to health. And then, you know, a couple months later,
like a dog killed it, someone, one of the neighbor's dogs just like that gone. You're like, okay, one,
that was pretty ridiculous that we paid $300 to have this thing stitched back up. But I thought
it was also interesting, the other geese, like they didn't even care, like, like it was just like,
we're, what is it, a gaggle, we're a gaggle, and there were five of us, and now there's four of us.
Do you know what I mean? Like, it wasn't this like elaborate morning thing.
Well, my daughter asked about this, right after, because all the, all our chickens have names.
And I forget the first one that bit the dust, but we've lost a couple of them. But whatever the
first one was, I think it was GoGo was the first one. And I mean, and it was really sort of tender
to watch this, but you could tell like she was devastated, but she was also very sad for the
other ones. She was like, well, what do you think Sarah and Ginger and so and so think? Like, do you
think they're afraid at night now? And I was like, I mean, those are great questions, sweetie. I don't
know, but I don't think their brains are the same as ours. I'm not, I don't know, you know?
No, that's what's interesting. It's like, well, they're probably are afraid at night, but they've
always been afraid at night. That's that's why it's no fun to be a chicken. There's a D.H. Lawrence
poem where he says, you know, like, I've never seen an animal feeling sorry for itself. A bird
will drop dead of the cold before it feels sorry for itself or something like that. That's sort of
one of the lessons I've taken from living in a farm is that like, the animals are much more
present and focused, and not worried the way that humans are worried. And, and ironically,
they have way more to be worried about. Like, a mountain lion isn't going to come and attack me.
But if I'm a goat, like, there's a pretty reasonable chance that could happen. So
you can take some interesting lessons from it for sure. What do you think that that's robbed us of?
What do you think our sterile environment of not having the concerns you've described? Now,
that's not true, of course, for our species across the whole. There are plenty of interviewed, an
amazing doctor who is the only doctor that serves a million people in South Sudan, and they get
bombed by their government every couple of weeks or months. And every time it happens, people are
getting killed and he has to, you know, put bodies back together. But if you're living here in the
United States, for the most part, you've become insulated from that. There's lots of good that
has come from that. What do you think is the most negative aspect of that? You begin to assume that
you have unlimited amounts of time or that you're in control of your existence, right? So
you look at the actuary tables and it's like, oh, we're living longer on average, but we forget that
we're individuals, right? So the average means nothing to you, right? And even if it did, even
if you were given the genetics and you've taken care of yourself in such a way that you have the
chance, you know, you're likely to, let's say like, it's all preordained in the biological sense that
I'm going to be 78, you're going to be 112 or whatever it is. But like, I appreciate your
confidence. Of course, I could still get hit by a bus, a war could break out tomorrow, I could,
you know, I could still have an allergic reaction to something. So, so I think we have this sense of
unlimited time that we take from it. And we just believe we're much more in control of our
existences than we already are. So there's like a form of arrogance there. That's the biggest one.
You know, Seneca talks a lot about how we're really tight fisted over the things that don't
matter, which would be like money, property stuff, things you can get more of, and then time, we're
the most generous with. And I think that is rooted in the sense that all we think about are old
people, we don't even think about the people that died because they're not around. So you just assume,
like, I even think about this with like war, I think when we think about wars, we don't think
about the people we like, my grandfather fought in World War Two. So when I think about World War
Two, I think about it being really bad and horrible, but you come out the other side, right? I don't
think about the people who got shot before the boats, but as soon as they put down the door on
the landing craft, I don't think about that guy. And so there's this weird survivorship bias that
I think our lack of familiarity with death exposes us to. And that's why we're so shocked when it does
happen. Do you think it's even deeper than that, which is in addition to everything you've said,
let's assume that not only do you have the biologic track to get you to 78, but let's assume you are
guaranteed to get to 78. So somehow we've built a cocoon around you that no bus can hit you,
no peanut can get lodged in your throat or give you an allergy.
Isn't the other issue potentially that we are not in the moment that we're in anyway because we have
this view of infinite time? And so in other words, there's sort of a lack of quality in our life beyond
just quantity. Is that possible? Yeah, so there's two really good insights from the Stokes I love.
So one, Marcus Rioska is like, are you afraid of death because you won't be able to do this anymore?
He's like, you should ask yourself that question all the time. So much, we want to live for everyone,
we don't want to think about death, we don't want anything bad to happen, but we don't really
actually judge the quality of the existence that we have very much. I think there's a lot of people
who are alive, who are basically dead anyway, right? They're sleepwalking through life. So I think
that's one part of it. The other interesting way, and let's say, because I do think a lot of people
go through, they go, oh, the average person is 78, like lives to be 78 or whatever. That's when,
so they go like, okay, I'll start thinking about death at 60, right? They're like, I'm so far from
that. It's way off in the future. I'm not going to think about that. Just like when you're in
elementary school, you're not thinking about graduating from college. You're like, I got to
get through all this other crap first. The big flip for me, Seneca talks about we think that death
is something that lays off in the future. But actually death is something that's happening
right now. He was saying, so you don't think about it. In my case, I'm going to live to be 78. So that
means I have 40 years left. It should think about it instead that I've already died 30 odd years,
right? So he's like, the time that he's like, most of our time already belongs to death, the time that
has passed is dead. And I think that's a much more active, empowering, adaptive way to think about it.
It's like, oh, I'm dying all the time. And I'm every second that passes, you don't get back.
And then that allows you to decide how you're going to spend that time, or at least think about
that you're spending it. You were given a finite amount of time. Are you going to spend it on
whatever you're going to spend it on? And then I think the other part where this gets tricky is
people go, I have to do this, I have to do that, or this happens, this happens, totally agree. But
are you going to spend time on top of that being mad that that happened, or resenting that it
happened that way, or regretting that it so so people go, Oh, I spent this, you know, I'm mad
that I just spent an hour unnecessarily in traffic. Sure. But now you're spending an extra minute and
a half complaining about it. And which part of that do you control? So I think the death conversation
gives you some perspective and some urgency and I think some prioritization and perspective on
day to day reality that's really valuable. Now, I suspect the number of people listening here are
not going to be as familiar with stoic philosophy as you are probably very few are. But at least
I've had the luxury of I read your newsletter every single day or Monday through Friday, and
then there's a weekend summary, the daily stoic I can't I can't plug it enough. So thank you very
much for I mean, it literally is the single most important thing I subscribe to an email. So thank
you. Can we give people a little bit of stoic 101 here? Can we explain who Marcus Aurelius was,
who Seneca was, who Nero was at least enough to give people a context of the world in which these
people came from, how it shaped a philosophical field or bent? And more importantly, why should
anyone care about this today? Yeah. So it comes to be an Athens, the founder of stoicism is this
guy named Zeno. He was a Greek merchant who sort of suffers this terrible shipwreck, he loses
everything. And he gets exposed to philosophy, probably like a lot of people expected that
philosophy was abstract, that was academic was not things you use in real life. And he gets
introduced to Socrates and cynicism and ends up becoming instead a student of his own school,
which becomes stoicism. And then stoicism worms its way from these sort of interesting Greek figures
into Rome as Rome takes over the world. And so this is Cicero and Julius Caesar and Cato,
it sort of follows the rise of the Roman Empire, the fall of the Roman Republic. And then it's so
integral into Roman life that it becomes not just philosophy of ordinary people and senators even,
but you know, Marcus Aurelius is becomes the emperor of Rome. And he's this avid student of
philosophy. So it's fascinating, basically, in two generations, so Epictetus is this former slave,
philosophy is banned from Rome. So he's like sort of sent into exile. But this slave is writing
about philosophy writing about how to achieve freedom when you're literally in chains,
all of this. And then a generation later, Marcus Aurelius, the most powerful man in the world is a
student of the same philosophy. So it's this really sort of open ended flexible philosophy
for people in the real world doing real things, and sort of built around, depending on who I'm
explaining to, I sort of go one of two tracks, I'll do both. So that I would say the sort of
central precept of stoicism is basically this idea that we don't control the world around us,
but we control how we respond. That's like, that's the main if I had to give you one thing,
and just be like, you don't control other people, you control yourself, you don't control what
happens, you control your reactions. So that's like the core of it. If I was going to get a
little bit more nuanced, I'd say sort of stoicism is built around for virtues. And the virtuous life
is what they're aiming towards. And today, when we hear virtue, we think like, purity, chastity,
some sort of religious component to the stoics, the four virtues were courage, justice, temperance,
some moderation, and then in wisdom. So it's sort of truth, self control, doing the right thing,
having the stones to stand up for those things, right? Then that's sort of the, that to me is the
essence of this philosophy. Tim Ferriss sort of refers to as an operating system, I think that's
an interesting way to do it, although that might be a bit reductive. I think it's more of a way of
life than an operating system. We've learned a lot from the stoics. And I always find, I think one of
the things I appreciate about the way you write about them is they're still humans and they still
make mistakes. I mean, you, I think a couple of days ago, you were talking about, I mean,
Seneca is a great example, right? On the one hand, this remarkable example of stoic philosophy,
and yet in the end, probably a little bit of his desire to be approved by Nero, his desire to be in
his good grace has effectively cost him his life. Well, not just cost him his life, but it may well
have forced him to contradict all the things he believed in. And for people who have no idea.
Yeah, let's tell the story about that transition. Seneca is this fascinating figure in that he's a
Roman senator, he's a philosopher, he's a playwright, he's probably the smartest man in Rome at this
time. And he's sent into exile by an emperor, Claudius, who sort of doesn't like him, he sends
him in exile. And so there Seneca is, he's sort of on this rock in the middle of nowhere. And he's
writing this philosophy and it's sort of like for a philosophy all about adversity and perseverance,
it's like this sort of perfect opportunity. And then he gets this call or, you know, a letter,
I'm sure it was a messenger, but he basically gets summoned back to Rome. They said, look,
you can come back, but your job is you have to be the tutor to this, this young boy. And that young
boy turned out to be Nero. And so Seneca has this complex, like Nero was this very promising student,
but was about to be dictator, essentially, at the same time, you know, just a couple generations
before this, the Stokes were the ones who were fighting to preserve the Roman Republic. And here
is this guy as a sort of emperor's guy behind the throne. And so there's a little contradiction
there. But really, this promising student also has a dark side. It's almost like the plot of
Breaking Bad, right? Like he starts good and towards the end, he's writing speeches that help
Nero justify why he murdered his mother. You know, it gets very dark, very quickly, Seneca becomes
extraordinarily wealthy for his association with Nero. Ultimately, he it's sort of like, you know,
there's some analogies, I think, to the Trump administration, where you're like, I don't like
the guy, but I feel called to serve, how can I mitigate the impulses, but it's, you know, it's a
tough balance, right? And you're suddenly morally compromised in a bunch of ways that if you had
your choice, you wouldn't be, but you also have the choice to leave at any time. And so ultimately,
Seneca decides to leave towards the end. And Nero's like, No, you don't get to leave, I decide when
you leave. And so he it's sort of this, he basically is caught up in this thing you can't get out of,
he ultimately sort of goes into a second exile. But he knows he traded his life for whatever he
got, you know, and at a certain eventually, you know, sort of Nero senses his goons to call in
the chit. And that's the end of Seneca. And it's interesting, because Seneca, of course, is ordered
to kill himself rather than being killed, which was the way that the time you can't help but wonder
what would Seneca go back and tell himself on the day that he was called to come and be the tutor
for this boy knowing what he knew at the end of his life? Yeah, it's endlessly complicated and
complex, because maybe he said yes, because he thought he could prevent this from happening.
Or maybe he thought, like I was again, I'm not being political, I think we just want to look
at analogies. But like, John Kelly, Trump's former chief of staff just gave these interesting
comments where he was like, look, when I left, I told Trump, like, you're going to be in trouble,
because there are other people who are not going to be able to tell you no the way that I can tell
you no. And it's going to be worse. He's like, you'll be impeached if I leave. And, you know,
he ended up leaving or Trump had him leave. But I think what Seneca probably told himself is like,
I don't think he was in any denial about who Nero was, right? But I think he told himself,
who will do a better job than me. It's interesting. It's a slippery slope.
It's very complicated. It begs broader questions, right? Which is what are our obligations? Do we
have a greater obligation to our own principles and our own personal beliefs? Do we have a greater
obligation to society to maximize the impact we can have on others? Again, through the lens you
just described, you could argue that Seneca did the best he could have, which was if, I mean,
Nero was obviously a complete dictator, were lives saved as a result of Seneca's association
with him. Yeah. And there's another few Stoics. He's not the only one. There's other Stoics who
did actively conspire to assassinate Nero, right? Which is ultimately what Nero accused Seneca of,
right? Yeah. This is the pretext that he uses. And I would say, you sort of go back and forth
on the evidence. The evidence is not conclusive that he did. In some ways it would be redeeming
if he had, but I'm actually writing about this right now for a set of biographies I'm doing, but
you only have to go back a generation or two with Julius Caesar to find that it's never as clear cut
as you think, right? Like Cato is the sort of Stoic philosopher resistance leader at the time.
He was so led by his principles that one read on it is that he drives Caesar to do what he did. Like
like Cato's inability to compromise his insistence on principle and perfect solutions
essentially grind the Roman political machine to a halt. And there's all like, there's this
interesting story where so Pompey returns from his conquests. This is before Julius Caesar and Pompey
and the lepidus have joined together in the triumvirate. But what happens is Pompey seeing Cato,
largely agreeing with Cato, says, well, we should come together. And in the way that one did back
then, he proposed that he would marry Cato's nieces or one of Cato's nieces. And Cato says, you know,
how dare you try to bribe me? He's like, I will not have my politics corrupted through sort of female
influence. What do you mean? I'm not going to create this alliance. So Pompey is surprised by this.
But he looks at his options, and he ends up aligning with Julius Caesar instead. And even at the time,
the historians noted this, they were like, because of his purity, his inability to sort of make things
work in a less than perfect scenario. Cato ends up bringing about exactly the thing that he was
trying to prevent, right? He instead of allying with the lesser of two evils, the two evils teamed
up and destroyed the thing that ultimately Cato gives his life for. And what I think is really
interesting is that then, not long after, another sort of inspired stoic character takes up to
assassinate Julius Caesar, thinking that this will be the end of it. And it's not the end of it,
it sends Rome into a second civil war in which hundreds of thousands of people die, and more
people are destroyed, and ultimately ensures that another emperor takes Caesar's place. So I think
one of the things you end up taking as you study philosophy and history,
it's just some humility about how complex these things are, and how rarely they are as black and
white as they seem. And that I think what stoicism is really about is a sort of a personal code
that lets you try to figure out what you should do in your individual situations and not be so
concerned about what other people did, or why, or how, or whether they were perfect. I wasn't even
planning to ask you about this because there's so many things I want to ask you about, but I can't
resist a slight detour in going down sort of your past and how you got here. I mean, you grew up in
Sacramento, you go to college in LA. I remember the first time I heard about you was somehow after
your time at American Apparel and how you'd done all this amazing stuff there. Can you pick up the
story there? Like what are you doing? And how at this point in time have you already acquired
a taste for stoic philosophy? Yeah, I think I got introduced to philosophy early on in college.
I'd read Epictetus, I read Marcus Aurelius. So sort of interested in it. It was definitely life
changing for me when I was exposed to it, but how much you're really getting at that age, you know,
it's hard to tell. So this is a detour from the conversation was a detour in my life. I basically
went and I was a research assistant for a really great writer. I did marketing for a couple other
writers. And then through sort of all those experiences somehow ended up as the director
of marketing in American Apparel, which was a, you know, a crazy dysfunctional, chaotic, but ultimately
really fascinating place to work for about six or seven years. What year did you start there? Oh,
seven, maybe oh, eight, something like that. So the company was already, you know, doing hundreds
of millions of dollars in sales, but was sort of still early on in what its next phase was,
which was as a retailer and a publicly traded company. And you know, it turns out a lot of
the same dynamics that have always been true and sort of upstart, ascendant sort of movements or
businesses. It was just a lot of money, a lot of temptations, a lot of conflict, a lot of politics,
a lot of the human condition out on display. But there was also just, it was a really interesting
creative learning opportunity. And then I, you know, I got to do all sorts of cool stuff from
a marketing perspective that got seen by millions and millions of people. And so I sort of learned
how this might be how you write stuff, but this is where the rubber meets the road where you sell it
to people. What was the most or set of insights that surprised you most as you made that transition?
I mean, obviously, you're an excellent writer, but I have no delusions that people are born
excellent writers. You've worked very hard at your craft. But how did you make that transition
from being able to write to being able to market? Because they're not really one in the same.
No, I mean, they're both in the ideas business, but they're very different ways of communicating
ideas. One of the things Dove was fond of talking about that I liked and it's from
Dove was the CEO. Yeah, this is actually from Robert Greene who wrote the 40 Laws of Power
and was on the board of directors and how I ended up working there. But there's a thing in the 40
Laws of Power. He says, never appeal to mercy or gratitude, always appeal to self-interest.
His premise was like, look, I want to build a company that's ethical. I want to build a company
that pays its workers fairly, that doesn't destroy the environment. But he's like, no one will buy
clothes for those reasons. They ultimately buy clothes because they look good in them or they
feel comfortable in them or they're the right price or whatever. And that it's this sort of tension
between this sort of pure expression and the realities of the market. And I think
one of the things I definitely took from that as a writer is like, first off, it's not just what you
want to say, it's where that overlaps with the market. The perfect book idea is like what you
can't stop thinking about and what people can't stop saying they need a book about. When those
overlap, you get something really powerful. But more, it's that you have to figure out where people
are. People are not thinking, I really care about those workers slaving away in sweatshops.
They're thinking, I need a t-shirt for tonight. So you can deliver them a t-shirt that solves
that first problem. But if all you're solving is the first problem, you're not going to be successful.
And so it's funny, people, because of my marketing career, they'll be like, oh, he's like a mercenary
or he's just in this for money or he's in this to get rich. And it's like, dude, of all the things
that I could apply my marketing skills to. It seems kind of preposterous that I would have chosen
an obscure school of ancient philosophy as like where I was going to cash in. So it's more like,
I'm really interested in this stuff. This is what I find endlessly fascinating. I could nerd out with
you about stoicism all day. We're having dinner tomorrow night, so we're going to do just that.
But it's how can I find a way to channel that passion I have for this obscure,
boring, complicated thing and give it to people who are busy, tired, overwhelmed, don't like books,
don't like big ideas, can't pronounce any of the names. Do you know what I mean? So it's about
finding a way to take your idea and delivering it to people who are not interested in your idea.
I see this often. It's like, oh, you know, this is his pop philosophy or, you know, oh, this is,
he's simplifying. Oh, why don't you read the originals? And it's like, I would love for people
to read the originals, but guess what? They're not right. They were not doing it, right? The 1% of
people who are reading the originals. Sure. Don't read my books, right? That's not who I'm writing
these for. I'm trying to reach people who, who wake up in the morning and think philosophy. I
don't have time for that. And I think you learn that if you get out of the artistic side of your
profession a little bit at the outset of that, you explained sort of that Venn diagram of things that
are in your sweet spot, meaning you as the creator, the author are thinking about this constantly.
And if you're not doing that, you probably shouldn't be writing about it. And then secondly,
the market says, I want this. Those things rarely line up. Sometimes it's you're thinking about
this a lot, but you almost have to make a market. You almost have to create something that can be a
bit more timeless. And again, you've either spoken about or written about this idea, which is you
generally try to think about things that have a little bit, I don't want to say they're timeless
because maybe nothing is purely timeless, but they just have a longer tail to them. Was that
a conscious decision or is that some meaning it was that a conscious decision at the outset or is
that something that looking back now nine books into your career, you can say, no, that's actually,
I got lucky in that I was always doing the right thing that was sort of creating content that was
going to be relevant after a year after the book came out. Yeah. In publishing, like there's the
front list and the backlist and all anyone cares about is the front list, even though the backlist
is, it's not only where all the money is, is the only reason the industry can afford to buy front
list titles, right? Because the vast majority of books never end up selling. They buy a celebrity
cookbook for $2 million and it sells 20 copies, right? Or, or the, you know, this big book flops.
The reason this works is that the great Gatsby is selling all these copies and the greatest
selling all these copies in the four hour work week is selling all these copies into Kilimackingburg.
You know, it's the backlist, right? And so it was, I mean, it was certainly both convenient,
but also cultivated that I write about a philosophy that has endured about 2,500 years of
diverse human experiences. Like I think if you're sitting down and you're writing
something that you just made up the chances of it being relevant 2,500 years from now
are much slimmer. Like, I mean, it can happen. Maybe you're such a genius that you, you've nailed
it, but I'm not so convinced I have that ability. So I do think about that. I would say almost every
single one of my books is rooted in or inspired or in some way almost a ripoff of some very
brilliant, sometimes obscure, sometimes popular title from the past. So even my,
my first book was this book called Trust Me I'm Lying, which is sort of an expose of how the media
works. And it was... Which many people, by the way, have said in retrospect was sort of the canary
in the coal mine talking about what would become fake news and this idea that you sort of called
a shot on that one. Yeah. I mean, I wish subsequent events had proven me terribly wrong. That would
probably be a better world to live in. But yeah, I think I got some things right with that book. But
ironically, that book was as much as I'm talking about blogs and social media and tech and all
these sort of things that were even more new than. My main model for that book was a book that
Upton Sinclair published in 1913 called The Brass Check. And that book sold well when it came out.
It's still in print today. It sold quite well. And so the point is I'm less interested in doing,
although I do want to do things that haven't been done before, I'm still kind of thinking like,
how can I take some risk off the table by modeling it on something that has some proven staying power?
That's a really interesting way to think about it, actually. I never considered that the idea that
you can at least de-risk the market appetite for something. And again, you still have to do a good
job, but that's one fewer risk. Well, you think about Star Wars. Like on the one hand, you can
see Star Wars as this cutting edge sci-fi movie sort of inventing a new genre. It's using all
these expensive technologies. It's breaking, you know, it's introducing like robots and all this
sort of stuff and what it was. Or you can see it as a timeless story based on the hero's journey.
I mean, 40 years later, people are still watching the movie. I'm not sure it's because of the
cutting edge special effects. It's the story. And so I think when you root things in some arc or
story or deeper truth, you are taking some of that risk off the table. I just think that's a strategy
not employed enough. When did you first become aware of this idea that we all tell ourselves a
story? Well, I mean, I think narrative is one of the things that makes us human. We've been telling
stories in writing for 5,000 years. We've been telling sort of, we have an oral epic poem
tradition that's probably 10,000 years old. So it goes to the core of who we are. And I go back
and forth. Sometimes I think it's very powerful. Sometimes I think it's very dangerous. I sort of
written about it both ways. But at the end of the day, the core premise of my writing also ripped
off from someone. This is what I got from Robert Greene, which is like, you can tell people facts,
or you can tell them stories that leave them with the conclusions that are the same as the facts
that you would have told them. Right. And so what I decided to do with with obstacle you go and now
still in this was not write a book that tells people what the stoics say, but give people books
that illustrate what the stoics said or believed through story. And ironically, this is also often
how the stoics told stories that are, you know, sort of made their points themselves. But it's
just, I think, a far more compelling medium. It's far more memorable, it's far more enjoyable,
and it's less preachy and condescending as well, I think. What do you think is the downside of the
story, the story we tell ourselves? Like, how does, again, you've written about both sides of that,
both ends of that book, what are the negative parts of this? So I think stories are a great
way to learn lessons about other people. Stories are a bad way to think about your own life. So I
just see lots of people who are very clearly believing that they live in a movie or a novel,
you know, and they are going through life as if they are performing for an imaginary audience.
And I think this is a very dangerous, egotistical and often misleading sort of tendency, right? So
I think this is honestly why social media has exploded in terms of like, why it's such a
valuable, lucrative, addictive business. It's that people want to, like, we all used to have
an imaginary audience. We thought people cared about us a lot more than they did. And what
Twitter allows you to do or Instagram allows you to do is like actually believe that your life is a
movie. So we get caught up in this sort of performance and this sort of comes at the expense
of actually living in that moment. I want to come back to talking about stillness and being present,
but I know that once we start there, we're not going to leave it. So there are a few other things
that we're talking about first. You alluded to it just briefly at the outside of what you said there,
this idea of having enough. You tell a story, again, I can't even recall where I know it's not in,
well, I shouldn't say that. Again, your worlds are all one to me now. But you tell the story about
Kurt Vonnegut at a party. Yeah, that's in stillness. Is that in stillness? I guess I had such an early
copy of it because the book only actually came out in about a month ago, right? Yeah, exactly a month
ago. But I think I got a copy like six months ago. Maybe that's why I don't realize it. Tell the
story about the party that Kurt Vonnegut was at and the discussion that ensued. So Kurt Vonnegut
was at a party with Joseph Heller. Joseph Heller wrote Catch-22, Kurt Vonnegut wrote Slaughterhouse
Five, two of the writers of the generation. And they're at the party of this billionaire.
And I'm sure you've been at events like this where you're the candy, you're like the status symbol,
like, look who I got to come to my party. I'm never that guy, but I can picture it.
I know that you've been that guy because you're like, why am I here? I have no business being
here. Right. And so they're sort of standing in this enormous mansion and Vonnegut is teasing
Heller and he says, how does it feel to know that he made more money this week than your book will
probably ever make in its life? And Heller said, well, I have something he doesn't have. And Vonnegut
said, what could that possibly be? And he said, I have enough, you know, I have a sense of what
enough is. And I just, that's a very powerful word. I think a lot of people see enough as the enemy.
Right. Like if I have enough, I won't be good at what I do. My lack of satisfaction is what's
propelled me to greatness. And this is certainly true is, I guess with athletes, especially where
it's like, your desire to always improve, to always get better, to never be satisfied with
your last performance is what compels you to keep going. And it can be responsible for a lot of
victories. It can also be responsible for why you fail to appreciate or enjoy any of those
victories. So when I talk about the book, when I'm interested in what I'm exploring myself, having,
you know, experienced some success and certainly accomplish more things than I thought I would
relatively early in my life, is this idea of like, and I think this is what Heller meant,
can you do what you're doing? Well, you'll get an elite level even from a place of fullness,
or does it have to come from a place of craving? Do you know what I mean? Like, is it?
Yes, very much so.
Does it have to come from the, I'm going to prove them all wrong. I am going to beat anyone that
doubts me. I'm going to earn my father's approval. You know, whatever that motivation is, does it have
to be from there that's never good enough? Or can it come from a place of passion and appreciation
and gratitude and you know, what they call the sort of the love of a game? Like, is it possible
to do it the other way? Could you at least have a balance of the two? That's what I think about.
I mean, I have a lot of thoughts on this because it's a topic I've been interested in since I was
a teenager. But what is your take on that now? Do you think those states can coexist? Do you think
one can achieve the highest levels without, call it, a certain fire that is coming from a place of
more rather than enough?
Well, you know, it's hard to know because you're only speculating about other people and then
there's, it's sort of awkward to think about it with yourself.
But I suspect you've spoken with a lot of these people as well.
Yeah, yeah. I would say my opinion is probably the minority view, right? Like, I think you can do it
from a place of fullness, but you know, most coaches are like, oh, you got to, the guy's got
to have the hunger. He's got to have the, you know, my goal in my life is to be great at what I do,
but somehow be a normal person. Like that's for whatever reason, that's important to me, not to
not to have some semblance of a normal life, to not be so lopsided, to not be miserable, to actually
like what I'm doing. And, and I would like to think that I'm, I sort of know objectively in one sense,
like I'm performing at an elite level, like there's the results and there's the impact the
work has had and there's the sales and there's the financial success. So I go, oh, it's working,
right? Like you can, but then I also, then sometimes, you know, the doubts come in, you go,
oh, but what have I left on the tape? Like, could I have sold more copies? Could the books have more
impact? Could my speaking fee be higher? What, you know, blah, blah, blah. If maybe I was a little
hungrier. So again, I think these are complicated questions and I don't, I don't pretend to have the
definitive answer, but I do generally think fullness is better than craving and it's more
sustainable, right? Like how long can you exist in the, I'm going to shove it all in their faces.
That's what's driving me. How long can you operate on that fuel or does it eventually corrode the
engine? Especially with riding. I think about it as like, uh, I'm not in this to win in the
short term. I'm interested in to do, to do this for a long time. And so you've got to come up with a
sustainable process and a sustainable motivation because maybe it works in football or basketball
because your career, even if it's a great one is like 20 years max, but probably closer to two
years. I don't have a good answer, but I'd be curious to hear what you think. Well, I don't think
my thoughts are nearly as well thought out as yours, frankly, but I, I think the way I look at
it is it all comes down to these optimization problems and what you're optimizing for. So
if you're optimizing to have the most trophies or the most dollars or the most, whatever metric
it is by which we measure things. And by the way, those things generally have to be external and
quantifiable for this game to work, right? You have to be able to display it. It can't be ambiguous.
Right. And again, lots of things in our life do fit that criteria. If you are playing the pure max
game, so you're looking for the absolute maxima, the local, not versus the local maxima. My view
is it's probably difficult to achieve that without being myopically focused on that. But I also think
like when you talk about multivariate calculus, every time you go to a absolute maxima,
you're achieving local minima elsewhere. Or if you're going to be more accurate, you're very
likely not achieving local maxima in other areas. So if one of those other areas is some measure
of suffering or the inverse of supper suffering, I just think the likelihood. So again, it's all
stochastic, the likelihood you're going to hit an absolute maxima, not the local, the absolute
maxima of your quantifiable metric, money, likes, accept it, you know, whatever, trophies, whatever,
and that you could actually hit a local maxima of the inverse of suffering. I think that's
incredibly rare. I just don't see how that would happen. I think that would be, that's like, you
know, getting hit by lightning three times in terms of probabilistic. I think more likely if you choose
to select a local maxima around some measure of the inverse of suffering, you probably aren't going
to hit an absolute maxima on those other things. But as we were talking about even before we started
the podcast, who cares? Like, what game are we playing? And I just think if I'm only speaking
for myself, if I'm not thinking about or speculating on anybody else and only viewing this through the
lens of my own life, I think sometimes we suffer and we don't even know we're suffering. We've been
suffering so long. Yeah, it's like you eat carbs. You grew up not knowing anything about gluten or
carbohydrates. You know, you had a sandwich for lunch, then you had pizza for dinner, and then you
had cereal for breakfast. You cut all that out and you're like, well, I didn't even know I felt like
shit, but I felt like shit every day of my life. I was fascinated, so I wrote a lot about him, and
I'm fascinated with him now, someone like Tiger Woods, where, you know, that's what he said he
was like, I don't play because I love golf. He's like, I play for the hardware. He's like, he didn't
care even care about the money. He's like, I care about the trophies. And he even said this, like,
after even after all the shit happened, he said, winning is great, but beating someone is always
better. And there's no question that made him the greatest golfer of all time, maybe the greatest
run in the history of sports. I mean, he was the number one ranked golfer in the world. So the
number one ranked person in his sport with a lot of really good people in it for like 252 consecutive
weeks, you're just like, that's unprecedented. And he did it all on his own. It's not like, you know,
Tom Brady also has the benefit of Bill Belichick, right? Like, and an entire team of other people,
he did this all on his own. And yet, as you said, he's not just not achieving good results in other
areas. Those other areas are actually ticking time bombs that when they go off, those charges
take down the entire edifice that he'd spent so much time building and doing. And I don't know him,
I've never met him, I don't really even know anyone that knows him. But I would imagine these
last two victories, the US Open, and then the tournament that he just won. From what I can see,
maybe I'm projecting, but like, I bet those victories feel profoundly different. And I bet
they're coming from a different place. Because there's no if all he was motivated by was beating
other people, he would not have survived that 10 year drought. You know, that would have been
inhumanly difficult, he must have come to actually like golf in some like to, to love the process of
it in some way. Because why wouldn't he just walk away? I mean, he has unlimited amounts of monies,
you know, he hates the public side of things. So even playing in a tournament that he wins has some
cost to him, right? And yet he does it. I don't know. I also go like, look, you look at some of
these sort of tortured artists and actors, and then you go Tom Hanks looks like he's having a
good time. You know what I mean? And doing great work. So I'd like, I'd like to think that there
is some balance where you can be world class at what you do, not be a shitty human being like my
friend Austin Klee on who was an Austin, he said, he calls them art monsters, you know, like the
writer who's been married six times, there was just a baseball player got arrested for beating
the shit out of his daughter. It's like, there's got to be a way you can be world class at what
you do. And you don't have to trade that. And I think the reason for that balance is like,
and this, this is where we get back into the stoics, like Tiger Woods will be remembered
for many, many years after his death, right? Like maybe in 100 years, we'll still be talking about
Tiger Woods. But what good will that do Tiger Woods, right? And that Marcus really goes like
people who long for posthumous fame, forget first off that the people in the future are just as dumb
as the people who are alive right now. And second, you're not going to be around to appreciate it. So
what are you what are you trading now, like happiness now, for the fact that, you know,
Alexandria is still named after Alexander the Great, like doesn't do him any good.
I mean, this is why I think stoic philosophy is unbelievable to me not being a person who ever
studied philosophy. So I'm exactly the person that the philosophy snobs hate, right? Because
I just wasn't smart enough to study philosophy, right? I mean, I'd like to make the excuse and
say it was because I was taking all those math and engineering classes. But the reality of it is,
I wasn't smart enough. If I showed up to philosophy classes, I would have done I would
have been a very mediocre student. So now I'm just a poser who gets to go back as an adult and do it.
But to a point you made earlier, I wasn't ready to hear it then. I'd love to believe I could have
been caught sooner, but I don't know if I would have. I think it's very difficult for humans to
change without hitting a local minima. You have to have pain to change. And you know what, even
if that's not true, it's true of me. Even if it's not true broadly, it's absolutely true of Peter
Athea. He must hurt to change. This idea that it used to matter to me that I did something
that was going to be bigger than me. You would look at that at the first layer and say, oh,
that's nice. That's altruistic. Like you want to serve something that's larger than you. But I
actually don't think it was altruistic at all. I think it was really this sense of insecurity.
Like I want to do something that will be remembered after I go away. I want to advance
thinking in a way around a discipline of science or medicine or something like that. But as Marcus
Aurelius points out, who cares? You're not going to be there anyway. And furthermore, even though
this is to me the subtext of what he says, what does it cost you while you are alive?
Yes. And I think maybe this is evidence of my point that you can do important meaningful things
and not need to do it from that place of craving, which is what's interesting about Marcus Aurelius
is that we are talking about him right now, 2000 years. So unless he was lying or really didn't
mean what he was saying, and he really did just crave and care about his legacy and surviving
for thousands of years, which it seems like he would have taken more active steps. But somehow,
the journal that he wrote to himself privately for his own self betterment and never wanted to
be published, somehow that that the purity of that experience and the lack of intentionality
in it and the true egolessness inside of it is what actually allowed him to create something
that has survived for thousands of years and doing trying to be a good person
as an emperor rather than trying to expand the empire or build enormous buildings in his own
honor, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, somehow managed to create an example or a sort of a different
story that's actually proved more enduring than I'm more people know who Marcus really says the
Nero, right? And one of them was trying and one of them wasn't. And so I think that's really interesting.
What role do you think ego plays in in this, you know, you've written about this idea that
there are just certain things where the harder you try and the more you want them, the further you
get from them. Yeah, I mean, I make a big distinction. I didn't do it as well. And he goes,
the enemy is I should have in retrospect, but now I'm able to be a bit more explicit about it. But a
big distinction between ego and confidence. Confidence is important, right? You got to know
what you're capable of, you got to have some evidence of it, you got to have some knowledge
of strength and weakness. I think the problem with ego is it's not any of that ego comes from some
third place, right? And I think at the core of ego is an association of our identity with results
or with external things. And so in some senses, it's, it can be helpful in terms of driving external
results. But we see just as often that ego undermines those results once we get them.
Yeah, I think you said that, again, it's a long tail game here, but in the long run, you're
probably coming out below than above. If you're driven exclusively from this place, how would you
explain that to the 15 year old version of you? Yeah, I don't know. I mean, like historically,
it's like, are there any super egotistical people who died with their boots off surrounded by people
who loved them? Do you know what I mean? Or does the dictator tend to die like Saddam Hussein or
Julius Caesar or what? You know what I mean? Like, it very rarely ends well. Over a long enough
timeline, the ego eventually comes back to get you, you know? So I think the problem for young
people, and I think this is also true for people who are more sheltered, right, who have less sort
of life experiences or more sort of outsiders, it's very easy to confuse ego and confidence,
because you don't, you don't actually know, right? Like, I think there are people who go,
we need a president, I was getting trouble talking politics, but we need someone like Donald
Trump, you know, he knows what he's doing. He's someone like Putin is like, I can't wait to get
in a room with this person, I'm gonna fucking break this guy in half. Do you know what I mean?
Because he knows that Trump's simplified version of reality, and he can see all the weaknesses in
that ego and bluster. Do you know what I mean? I think the problem when you're 15 is you see Kanye
West, or you see you read a book about Steve Jobs, or you know, you see these athletes doing x, y,
or z, and you think that's what confidence looks like, because you're not, you haven't experienced
it enough to know what profound insecurities and weaknesses these strategies are compensating for,
and how vulnerable these guys are to slumps or mistakes, or you know, how often they
get in their own way. I think that's the other interesting thing we don't calculate when we
think about ego. We look at super successful people who have egos, and we go, oh, look at what they've
done. The graveyard is something we don't get to examine. We have no idea what the denominator looks
like for that field of observation. That's true, but look at Steve Jobs, right? He comes back,
he's the most successful CEO of probably the 21st century, blah, blah, blah. But like, what about
that loss period? Was that necessary? Did he actually have to get fired from Apple? So the
graveyard is we don't think about all the people who got fired from the company they started because
of ego and never came back, right? Like the Adam Neumanns of WeWork or whatever, we don't see
how many of them never even got that far. But let's say Travis Kalanick comes back and is the
CEO of Uber again, and he leads it to stratospheric success, he learned blah, blah, blah. What did he
lose? The thing about the time that he lost, the mistakes that he made. And yes, you of course,
we learned by experiences sometimes it's a touch the stove. But the point is, we're really bad at
calculating how much more successful a person could be if their ego wasn't getting in the way.
Anyone who's ever worked with or for or around other powerful people, like everyone knows,
do you know what I mean? I bet if you took every presidential candidate right now,
and you talk to the people on their staff, they could give you a list of five ways that person's
ego was hurting them in the campaign, right? So one of them is going to win. But that doesn't mean
those those traits were good. Yeah, that's right. You can be successful despite ego. And that's
different from saying you can be successful because of ego. Yes, we're really bad at calculating that
cost. And I think maybe you just have to see it enough times to know like, I mean, Dove ended up
getting fired from the company, company goes bankrupt twice, he lost everything, not only did
he lose everything, he lost shares, his shares were worth about $500 million. He now owes,
which you will never be able to pay about $20 million to the hedge fund that effectively
destroyed the company in his plan to save it. And 10 12,000 people lost their jobs. Like,
it's not until you really see just how toxic and dysfunctional ego is, at the sort of malignant
level that you walk away and go, I don't want any of that in my life. So what's our checklist?
If we weren't sitting here on this podcast, and we're just sitting here talking about this,
and I'm saying, Ryan, I want to make sure that I have an internal audit. I want to catch my ego
when it is creeping up. What are some of the things you would teach me?
Yeah, I wish I had a magical checklist, but it's more just sort of ideas. And I think why we look
at stories from history as we go, oh, it's the pattern recognition of being a little bit like
this person here, I'm being a little bit like this person here. I think when you feel like it all
rests and falls on you, you know what I mean? Like when you're Atlas with the world on your shoulders,
you have profoundly inflated your importance in whatever situation you're in. So that it's like,
when you feel that like, Herculean, I'm the one, like, that is ego, right? The other one is like,
when you feel paranoia, like people are out to get me, they're fucking me, they're screwing me
over. I mean, held back, I usually find that's ego. Colin Powell talks about like, you know,
making sure your ego is not associated with your position, right? And so it's like, when your
identity and worth as a human being is tied up in what you have or what you've done, and this is
where that the story you're telling yourself can be so dangerous. When you have really started to
identify with what you've accomplished, when you're like, you know, I've hit this bestseller list,
my podcast has this many downloads, you know, I'm the I'm the best in the world at x, when you have
really locked in these sort of arbitrary ratings or, or rankings or status. To me, that's ego,
because now you're not present, you're thinking about how do you maintain and control and get
these things. The last one I would probably say is, is when you are comparing yourself to other
people. So like, if you're comparing yourself against other people versus comparing yourself
against your intention or your own standards, also probably a decent sign of ego. Those are actually
really great. One I might add to it that, that I find myself having to check is when I'm more
interested in being right than knowing what the truth is, which I find can happen in the stupidest
example. Like literally an argument with my wife could easily, if I'm going to be brutally honest,
turn into, wait, stop for a second, Peter. There's an internal dialogue. You're arguing with her
and because you're a better arguer, you can probably look like you are right here. There
are five other ways that this could be viewed. If you're really being brutally honest, you should
be stepping out of yourself and seeing them all of these other ways. That's a loving example,
because it's with a person you care about. Where you really see it, I think, is when you're having
a debate with someone like you don't care about, like someone on Twitter, right? Like some random
person on Twitter attacks you. For me at least, that's very powerful and that's certainly where
I catch my ego the most. Right. Because what you're doing means you're associating your identity with
a totally meaningless encounter or situation and you're like, I can't let this person be better
than me. Or my identity is that I'm the best. I win. I'm right. Not I just want to know what is
true or real or I want to have a conversation with this person. So yeah, I think that's ultimately
why you go so dangerous is that it just sucks us into bullshit that we don't need to be doing,
whether they're competitions or they're arguments or they're, you know, I think that the sort of
rise and fall of we work is such a great example of someone who is just like, what happens when
ego is just utterly unchecked and how it served him well up until the point it all came, you know,
there's a joke about gangsters that like everything is wonderful until the last 15 minutes and then
it's brutal and violent and pathetic, you know, and I think that tends to be, it goes and it often
goes much longer than anyone thought. And then when it crumbles, it crumbles very quickly.
Not only there's nothing left, but there's not a lot of mercy from other people.
Again, I always think about things in terms of math. So to me, like that's just an amazing
example of non-linearity in everything, non-linearity in time and non-linearity in response.
So that's an interesting thing. You can think of ego is an amplifier of those curves.
Yeah. Cyril Connell's line is that ego sucks us down like the law of gravity.
And so I think the way you think about it is like, look, if you're not ever getting up off the couch,
gravity is not a big problem for you. But if you know you're jumping between buildings or you're
doing something really hard, really high up there, the falls can be real painful.
What do you think are the antidotes to the negative effects of ego?
Well, it's very hard to be egotistical while you're learning something.
Ego can prevent you from learning something. But I think the philosophers mindset, the martial art
mindset of like, I am a student in a thing in which you never truly master is sort of
humility embodied. So Epictetus's line is you can't learn that what you think you already know.
John Wheeler, the physicist, he says, as your island of knowledge grows, so does the shoreline
of ignorance. And so if you think about it that way, it's like, oh, as I'm getting smarter,
I'm actually getting more aware of what I don't know. And to me, that's a much better way to get
through the world. There's people who as they get more successful, there's less and less you can
teach them and there's less and less that they want to hear. And then there are people who as they
get better, become more curious, more interested, more open, less rigid. I think that's where you
want to go. Bob Kaplan, who's my head of research, he says this eloquently, and I'm sure he's
paraphrasing it from somebody else, but the further and further you get from the shore,
the deeper and deeper the water gets. I mean, sometimes Bob and I, we talk almost every day,
and a lot of times I'm just lamenting how little we know. I'm like, God, Bob, does it ever just
bug the shit out of you that we spend so much time? We've got seven analysts, like we eat,
sleep and breathe this literature. And I think I know less than I knew three years ago on a relative
basis. That's absolutely true. On an absolute basis, it might not be true, but on a relative
basis, which is we perceive relative changes, not absolute changes, that is unquestionably correct.
It's also sort of like the second valley of the Dunning-Kruger curve, right? It's like once you,
oh, I think I know what's going on here. Nope, actually, I have no clue what's going on here.
I've written about this before where it's like, okay, let's say the Civil War. You learn about it
in elementary school, whether you live in the North or the South, it's very simple. It's like,
we went to war to free the slaves. It was a war of Northern aggression, right? You learn one of
two things. It's very simple. Then you read about it a little bit more and it's really complicated.
Now it's not so clear. It's like, hey, Lincoln said over and over again, he didn't really want
to free the slaves. And, oh, how can we say it's just a war of Northern aggression when the states
wrote all these constitutions that basically all they talk about is slavery. It becomes complicated.
And then there's really no good guys. There's really no bad guys. And then it, blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah. And all of a sudden you're in this morass and this is like, you heard it from a
teacher at simple. You've read one book, it's complex. You've read 10 books, it's complex.
And you read 20 books, you really study it. And then all of a sudden it's very simple again,
right? And like you go, oh, the Civil War was a hundred percent about slavery. It was only about
slavery. And it's very simple. Even though you've come to the same conclusion that you had before,
you're understanding it in a profoundly different way. One is sort of egotistical and one is
a humility because you're aware of all the threads that go into it. Do you know what I mean?
When I look at this trilogy, now I just finished it. Like when I look at obstacle,
in some ways it's the tightest of the books and it sells great. I hear from people how it's
resonated, but I don't know if I could write it again. I couldn't write it that way again because
I wouldn't, in having done two other books, having read more studied, more experienced more,
I don't think I would allow myself to be as simple as I was. Does that make sense?
It makes so much sense, Ryan, because I'm, which I wanted to ask you this tomorrow night over dinner,
but I think I'm going to ask you now, apologies to the listener if you don't care about the nuts
and bolts of writing a book. As I'm getting closer to that first submission, which is probably a month
away, in fact, by the time people listen to this, I will have already submitted it and it'll be,
you know, going through the editing process for so long, because I've been working on this book for
three years. All I wanted to do was get here. And now I'm like, Oh, no, no, no. I don't want to hand
it in because I'm still learning. And I know things today I didn't know three years ago. And
that means that on the day this book comes out, there's going to be things I know that aren't in
the book. And there's probably going to be things in this book I don't fully think are the most
accurate representation of knowledge. And I just, now that I've had this profound empathy for authors
now, which is how the hell do you do this? How do you take your hands off something, knowing that
knowledge isn't static? Yeah, it's really tough. Winston Churchill, who most people don't think of
as a writer, probably wrote more books than just about anyone in the 20th century. He says, at some
point, you have to like, kill the book and fling it to the public. And I think it's right, you do,
you have to you have to stop at some point. That's why the book has to be what you were capable of in
that moment. It has to be a closed thing. Like, the game is four quarters, and then it's over,
you don't replay the same game, you play again, the next night or the next season. Do you know
what I mean? And but my point was more like you, I look at the book, and it's just, I didn't know
what I didn't know. So there's a certainty to some of the things that in retrospect, I see of,
I see with more nuance now. And so in a way, each of the books is a balance, right? Because
you want the books to be tight, you want them to be straightforward, you want them to be compelling,
but also you have to be intellectually on it. So each one of the books has gotten a little bit
longer, because not because I feel like I'm droning on, but because what I was comfortable
saying in one short sentence before, I now have to qualify and you know what I mean? So it becomes
complicated. But you at a certain point, you have to go, this is the best I was capable of,
up through November 2019. And that's where I'm when I can when I look at it in the future,
I can't be comparing it to who I am now. I have to be asking, did I leave anything on the table in
November 2019? Did you learn that from Robert? Yeah, a little bit. You just learn it from the
process. I had a weird experience because so trust me, I'm like, how did you meet Robert Green?
Through another author who I was working for. And we had lunch. And then Robert was looking for a
research assistant. Yeah, it was just transformative. You describe him as one of the most important
mentors you've had with respect to writing and maybe beyond. Of course, yeah, as a person,
as a writer, as a professional, he's just fantastic. So with my first book, I wrote it in 2011,
came out in 2012. I did the paperback, which is an expanded edition with some extra stuffs and
changes in 2013. And then I wrote an updated edition after the 2016 election. So it's like,
I've had this weird interaction with the text where I had to go back and edit and change.
This is where the ego thing comes in. Mostly what I take from that and when I try to think
about on a regular basis, is that certainty is the enemy. Because certainty is what you regret
when you look back. It's not that you took a stand, or you thought this, or you said this,
it's the tone with which you did it, that you can come to regret. It was the pretension that of
course, I'm right. When in retrospect, it's like, how could you have thought that you knew this,
you'd only thought about it for 10 minutes. I'd like to think that as I go on as a writer, that
it's softer and more balanced and more nuanced. Because if that's not the direction you're going
in, I think you're going in the wrong direction. Stillness to me seems like a lonely thing,
but you say just the opposite, right? Yeah, well, I think that we confuse stillness. We think
stillness is synonymous with meditation, or we think it's like stillness is what the Dalai Lama
has, or some person on a 30-day silent meditation retreat. Or even outside of that, there still is
this connotation of solitude, right? Like we practice stillness by ourselves with our thoughts,
being present, etc. Well, that's the easiest way to get there, right? Do you know what I mean? Like,
if you were busy and overwhelmed and stressed and having trouble coming up with your thoughts,
you're finishing this book, the easiest way to break through that would be to travel to a place
you don't live, like go to a cabin in the woods and just work on it. And I'm not saying there's
not a place for that in life, but that's not sustainable. You can't do that every day if you
want to maximize for these other things we're talking about. So I'm interested in how do you
have stillness in the real world where you have bills to pay and a family and a house and
neighbors and you drive a car in traffic. Do you know what I mean? So how do you access stillness
in the course of normal, real life? I think solitude and silence are a big part of it, but
I'm thinking just the stillness of reducing the expectations, reducing or extracting the
unnecessary, locking into what you're doing, whatever it is, even if it's a minor thing.
So I'm interested in Kennedy and the missile crisis or Anne Frank and her sitting in front
of her diary or I'm thinking of the opposite of whatever tiger was his life was like. I'm thinking
about stillness for actual people in the real world. Stillness for Marcus Aurelius as the emperor.
So actually I want to talk about meditation because you specifically don't talk about it.
And I think that was a deliberate decision, right? Yeah. What was the basis of that decision?
Well, again, we were talking about, you know, how do you find people where they are?
I think the evidence is pretty overwhelming that people don't meditate, don't really want to
meditate. The evidence is equally overwhelming that it works, right? And that it's great,
but we have trouble getting there. And so when I'm talking about stillness, I didn't want to talk
about first off, I think it's problematic that people live chaotic, dysfunctional,
disorganized lives. And then they think going on a seven day silent meditation retreat is
magically going to solve all of that when they're just coming back to their same life right
afterwards. So it's like going on a juice cleanse or something. Do you know what I mean? It's not
really doing anything. And so the idea was there's lots of great stuff about meditation out there.
It's not really what I do anyway. So I'm not going to pretend I'm the expert on it.
But what I can talk about is a more comprehensive sort of philosophical approach to stillness.
And let's see if we can't start there. And then at the end of it, I think you're in a better place
to try some of those things. Let's start with journaling. Yeah. Stoics journaled. Yeah, we
wouldn't have any stoics. We wouldn't have Marcus Rheelius if the stoics didn't journal. And what I
think is so interesting about Marcus Rheelius, having now started to really study some of the
more obscure earlier stoics, is you realize even a lot of the stuff, like a good chunk of meditations
is like quotes from other people. But even a chunk of the stuff that's not quotes he didn't make up.
Like that he's almost running through like flashcards in this journal. He's like running through
exercises or thoughts or things that he's paraphrasing things that he was taught by his
teachers. And you realize that philosophy is actually an active word-based writing process,
not a book that you read one time and then you've magically absorbed the insights.
Let's talk about this process, because I think the way you describe meditation,
you know, the way I sort of explain it to patients is sort of similar, right? Which is
it's not about meditation. Meditation is a tool, it's a training platform, if you will,
that teaches you a skill that for me, and I think people more sophisticated than me will be able to
talk about much more nuance around this. Like they listen to Sam Harris talk about this, of course,
it's infinitely more enlightening. For me, it's simply gap awareness. That's literally all I care
about is the gap between stimulus and response. I want a bigger gap, and I do this goofy thing
every day, most days, this practice where I sit there and I, you know, focus on my breath and I
catch myself thinking and I come back and forth and back and forth and back and forth, because as
Jeff Warren, who's a great meditation teacher, describes it, that's just a bicep curl. I might
go into the gym and I'm doing curls or squats or whatever exercise I want to do so that when I
leave the gym and I go and pick up my bag of groceries or I go pick up my kid, I have some
muscle to do that. And with physical muscles, it's so easy. We're so wired to see that. I think with
some of these cognitive, emotional muscles, we don't have quite the same. So how do you think about
the exercise of bringing stillness in? I mean, you've talked a lot about it, and I think we
should talk about these in detail. What are the enemies of stillness, right? You know, jealousy
and things like that. Maybe we start there actually, and then we'll sort of, unless you
think it's better to talk about it in the, yeah, whichever. Let's start with what are the things,
what are the obstacles to stillness? I mean, overactivity certainly sort of committing to more than
you can conceivably handle. We talked about sort of enough, like an insatiable demand or need,
certainly one of them. I think noise is the enemy of stillness, like unnecessary noise,
and that can be internal noise or exterior noise. Bad habits, bad routines, certainly, I think people
can get to, you know, they can go on a wonderful vacation, and every day they go to this coffee
shop, and they sit around, and they hang out, it's wonderful. And then they go back to their
sort of life where they, they wake up five minutes before they're supposed to go to work, and then
they're sprinting around, you know what I mean? Like, or they have a couple days without their phone,
and then they get addicted to some new app. So it's sort of routine structure limits,
the lack thereof is, to me, a huge, you know, obstacle to stillness. I think deficiency in
terms of like hobbies or practices and the like. So I think meditation is not just the practice of
doing it, it's the having a practice period. So if you're like, my practice is that I cook dinner
every night. That could be your thing, like having a thing that you do that you control, that you can
access on demand is hugely important. So for me, it's running or swimming, and just having this,
this place I can go to when I'm stressed or overwhelmed, or when I'm struggling with some
big decision is a huge source of relief and reflection for me. How long does it take you to
finally look at your phone in the morning? My thing now is I like, so this morning it was about
two and a half hours. So what's your morning routine? So I wake up early. With or without an alarm?
I mean, I got a three year old, so and a four month old. So usually, it doesn't even matter if I have
an alarm. If I am using an alarm, it's by phone, but it's in the other room. Like it's not near the
bed. That's a huge minor thing, but can have a major impact is like, do not sleep with your phone
in the room. But so I wake up, you know, let's say six or seven, don't touch the phone. Have you
spar? The app spar? Nope. Basically, you do these challenges. So it's like, let's do 50 pushups a
day. You do the 50 pushups a day, but you have to like video yourself doing the thing on the app.
And so people can verify whether you did it or not. And then if you miss it charges you like five
bucks or 10 bucks, or I'm sure it could be $100. But it charges you each day that you miss,
and this goes into a pot. And then at the end of the challenge, the people who didn't miss split
the pot, which is awesome. I use that to start to happen, which is I'm not going to check my phone
for the first 10 minutes, then we worked our way up to 30 minutes and an hour. How do you videotape
that you only do it if you made it so like I woke up at six, 730 right now it's an hour and a half.
Awesome. And people go Oh, great job. You know, it's like there's a community thing. But so I
started I worked my way up to about an hour. But now it's just like, how long can I go? And it
really it's very helpful for me in terms of just starting the day, not from my back foot.
So what did you do with that two and a half hours you had that weren't cursed with the phone?
Yeah, so this morning, I took my son for a bike ride, like in a bike trailer. So that was, you
know, 45 minutes, then we had breakfast, then I worked, like I went, I went and sat with a journal
and then I went straight into the writing for the day. And I forget why I had to get a photo off my
phone for something I was doing. So it wasn't even like, oh, now, you know, now I'm gonna go respond
to text messages. It was just like, the phone is a value. I mean, like, you know, yesterday, it was
probably two, two and a half hours. But then I needed directions to somewhere I was going. So
I'm it's not that I don't want to ever use the phone. It's just like, I want to be using the
phone rather than be used by the phone, which is what I think most of the time our use of these
devices is we're being used by the technology. Now, I'm guessing many people listening to this
will think, what the hell is this guy talking about? I don't have that luxury, right? And there's
going to be a, and whether that's true or not, I don't know. Like, of course, I'm just thinking
about it through my lens, like, how long can I realistically go without the phone? You know, like
you, I sort of have the privilege of working for myself, I probably have more things that are
pinging me that may be time sensitive, you know, vis-a-vis a patient or something like that, or
someone on my team needs to get a hold of me. But, but in the end, I still live a pretty privileged
existence relative to someone who's at the bottom of their pyramid, whatever their organization is.
And they're at the, you know, they're beholden to somebody else. Yeah. And I went through that phase
in my life. And you're trading things to get where you want to get. So I'm totally not saying that
this is for everyone for right now. But if what usually people go, Oh, this is, I'm early in this
phase. What actually tends to happen though, is that you actually get less freedom, the more
successful you get, right? Which is precisely the wrong way for it to go. So I'm thinking it's, I
don't know though, it's weird. I think people actively like, Oh, like when you hear someone's
like, Oh, I don't even have a smartphone or anything. They go, Oh, I, you know, I have, I
meditate for an hour each day, or I do this. People immediately try to make up some story about why
that's their sort of privileged existence. And that could never work for me rather than thinking
about how can I have my version of that? And it's like, I am probably busier than most of the people
who are saying, Oh, you, how did you have two and a half hours without your phone? Do you know what I
mean? Like I've got people who work for me. I've got projects that are going on. I've got deadlines
I have to meet, but it's precisely because I have all of that going on. I'm not fucking sending
Snapchat DMS. Do you know what I mean? Like it's not, it's not that I wasn't working. I was at my
computer. I was connected, but what I wasn't doing is using a device. That's main purpose is to make
me use the device. When you're on the computer, what is your relationship with that? You know,
obviously email people who listen to this podcast. I feel, I feel like I must be spending way too much
time railing on email because I'm at the point now where the first time somebody meets me,
they usually say, I know how much you hate email, you know, I'm sorry for emailing you or whatever.
So for me, I like emails. My preferred medium in the sense that like, I want it all funneling
towards there so then I can have control over it. So like, that's one of my things is like,
you're not also DMing me on Twitter. You're not also, you know, sending me Facebook messages.
You're not also chatting on LinkedIn. Email is like a pretty good medium for me because it's
asynchronous. That's what I like about it. What I hate are fucking phone calls. That's what I want.
Want to have the least amount of in my life. Or God bless WhatsApp with the little timestamp of,
you know, when you actually saw the message versus I can't stand WhatsApp.
Or the, hey, let's get together for coffee. And we'll, you know, like these sort of things where
it's like a thing that could have been a phone call that could have been an email. Do you know
what I mean? That could have been nothing because you could have just Googled this, right? Email is
good for me. So I think people should figure out what's good for them. But email is good for me,
but I'm not writing and simultaneously checking my email every time that, you know, it doesn't.
So do you have rules around how often you check email?
Not really. My thing is like, since it's my main thing of like how people get a hold of me,
it's like I'm sort of peripherally checking it throughout the day. So it's, I can see if things
are happening. But what I'm, the way my morning is set up and the way my life is, is it's like,
I'm getting everything in the right headspace. So I can go right into whatever the main writing or
the main task that I have to do for the day is before I get sucked into the email, like reactive
response stuff for the day. So yesterday I had some articles to write and then I had a presentation
I had to make that probably took me through towards, you know, 12 30 or one. And then so it's
like after lunch, now I got to respond to all these things people want for me. So how does
jealousy factor into stillness? When we've talked about the relationship of jealousy and ego,
are these things synonymous? I mean, when you find something that is anti stillness,
is it pro ego or not necessarily? Well, I would find there's very few egotistical people who I
think we would define as still take the five or six most egotistical people that you can think of
historically, or that you know, personally, I would say you'd probably trade places with very few of
them, even if they are extraordinarily successful, right? I do find the ego and stillness are pretty
mutually exclusive. Why do you think that is? Let's pick an example of somebody, let's use someone
other than the president to throw it at somebody else. I mean, was Bill Clinton a still guy?
Bill and Hillary's ego has caused them a lot of problems, but it's in a less sort of day to day
misery sense of the word, I would think. Who's a good example? I mean, you look at a Kanye West,
right? Or you look at an Elizabeth Holmes, or you look at the guy that did fire fest, you know,
that's not, you don't want to be that person. And look at the fire fest guy, I think it was a great
example. Weirdly, he called me before he went to jail, he wanted to talk, we never ended up
connecting, but uh, that's because he called you, should have emailed you. Yes, what I found so
compelling about the documentary. So okay, he commits this massive, yeah, tell folks what fire
fest is. And yeah, so it was a concert organ. It was a basically a scam artist to put together this
thing called fire fest was just supposed to be this enormous concert on this island in the Caribbean.
And it ended up sort of blowing up all over his face. They made this fascinating documentary about
just like, what happened? But the point what I love, have you seen the documentary? I have not. I mean,
I'm familiar with the story. What's it called? They're both called fire fest or something. One's
on Netflix and one is on Hulu. You wouldn't think this would be worth two documentaries, but totally
is really. Yeah, it's fascinating. Okay. But so in one of the documentaries, I forget which one
he commits this massive fraud. It's kind of intentionally kind of unintentionally blows up
in his face. He's humiliated, it costs him all his money gets investigated. When he gets back,
instead of looking in the mirror and going, how did this happen? What change am I going to make
in my life? You know, he ends up starting this other scam. Like he starts trying to sell these
concert tickets. The point is like he couldn't stop himself. It becomes like a compulsion. And
I think I keep doing Trump, but when you look at Trump, people are like, why can't he just not tweet?
Because it's like, that would make sense. He could be a pretty good president, I think, in some ways
without doing it, but he can't. He's not in control. The ego is in control. And so you just see that
time and time again, it prevents one from being able to stop. And it goes so far beyond self
interest, right? Like it becomes actively self destructive. So I think what you were saying is,
well, you were asking me a specific question about stillness, how it pertained to stillness.
Well, and jealousy. Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Theodor Roosevelt's line was comparison is the thief of joy. I like Joseph Epstein's line. He
said, of all the seven deadly sins, envy is the only one that's no fun. And he's totally right.
Let me think about that for a second. Yeah. At least in the moment,
Gluttony is pretty fun. Sloth can feel okay in the moment.
It's the only one that primarily punishes the recipient. When you are envious, it is
always a negative feeling. You're only feeling bad about what you don't have. And you are
angry or resentful or hurt that someone else has it instead. Right. And so jealousy and envy are
just, you know, it's a zero sum way to go through the world. It's a negative way to go through the
world. It prevents you. I think that the irony of envy is often we are envious of people who are
envious of other people. In some cases, we don't know it, but secretly they're envious of us.
Right. Like, you know, it's like, think of all the people right now who are giving up everything and
working incredibly hard because they want to become famous. And then you think of all the famous people
who complain about being famous and would in some ways give everything to have their privacy back.
This is why the Stokes are saying we sort of question these things and we think about them
because under examination, they make a lot less sense that they do just sort of in the sway of
whatever that feeling is. You wrote that the call to stillness comes quietly, but the modern world
does not. And that creates a pretty negative pressure against stillness. Yeah. No one's beaten
on your door begging you to be still. Like all the incentives are lined up for the opposite.
How much of that do you think is sort of been a monotonically increasing function? In other words,
like if we could transport you back to, you know, just before the civil war, right? It's whatever
that would be 150 years ago, 140 years ago, I guess 150 years ago now. How still was the world then?
I think it's in pockets, right? Rome is a super noisy place. I mean, I opened the book with
just the incredible noise of the city that Seneca is trying to tune out as he's writing.
But one of my favorite quotes in the book, Blaise Pascal, in like, you know, mid 1500s,
he goes, all of humanity's problems stem from our inability to sit quietly in a room alone.
What do you think Pascal was getting at there? How much of that is about comfort within our own skin
versus the ability to silence our monkey mind versus the ability to distance yourself from all
of these other forms of suffering? I mean, Pascal has said some brilliant things about suffering.
Yeah, I think he means all of those. I think he means that also in the sense that all of our
suffering stems from the things we go out and do to try to alleviate that suffering
that ultimately create new forms of suffering. I think it was Pascal who actually said the
distraction is the greatest thing that we pursue to combat our misery. Of course, I'm paraphrasing,
yet it is in and of itself our greatest form of misery. Yeah, yeah. So, you know, there's this
famous story. It's now like a viral email, but it actually dates to around the same time as
Pascal and he may reference it, but there's that story, you know, it's like the rich CEOs on
vacation and he sees like a Vietnamese fisherman and he says, this is so beautiful. What's your
plan? The guy's like, oh, I fish a couple of hours a day. And the guy goes, oh, well, what you got to
do is buy another fishing boat. And then you buy it. He talks about this whole scale of like how to
expand and grow the business. And then the fisherman says, well, then what do I do? He's like,
well, then you sell it and you retire. And basically the point is it brings you right back
to research. But this story actually dates back like 600 plus years. It's the story of a minister
speaking to a king and the king is saying, well, you know, we have to invade Prussia and then after
Prussia, we have to invade Vienna, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. And it's like, and then we can live in
peace, which is where they were. Right. And so that I think that's part of what Pascal is saying
is that like, if we could sit quietly in a room alone, we wouldn't go do these things that then
are prevent us from sitting quietly in a room alone. They've actually done some studies. Maybe
you know more about it than I do, but the study where they'll sit someone in a room and they will
say, I'm going to come back in 15 minutes. You have to wait here, or you can press this button,
which will give you an electrical shock. And then you can leave right now and people will take a
painful electrical shock than to sit quietly with themselves. So I Pascal was more right than I knew.
You know, it's funny. I always interpret those studies as
is the pain of the shock worth more than my time, you know, to leave. But, but, but I, I see that
that's sort of interesting. I thought about that too. Yeah. What is 15 minutes of your life worth?
But is that person going to, what are you going to do at home? Like you're going to sit there for
15 minutes, right? So I, I don't remember. Maybe there's some reward in the study also, but the
point is like, sometimes you feel this as a father, you're like, I got to rush home. I got to drive
dangerous. I gotta get, I gotta see my kids. And then you see your kids and like two minutes later,
you're like, I'm going to go to the other room and do my thing now. You know, like, like we have this
good urge to do the right thing, to be there with people. But then are we actually doing it when
we're there? That resonates a lot because I find, you know, my wife was recently away for four days.
So I was, that's the longest I'd been with all three kids for that period of time. It was awesome.
I actually enjoyed virtually every second of it, infinitely harder than one can imagine. If you're
me, who's not used to being there for throughout all of the interstitial parts of existence.
And you sort of realize like how many times was I tempted to just get up and go do something that I
couldn't go and do in that moment? Because in the, if my wife's there, I can just go and get up.
You're handing them off between each other. Yeah, totally.
I don't know. I just wonder like how did we get here? And I guess it's tempting to want to blame
our electronic environment, but there was no electronics in Rome. So it's not like electronics
are the cause of this. There's simply a convenient outlet for it. What is the cause of this?
Well, I don't know, but I was thinking about this actually this morning because
on Sunday I have to fly to Europe. And so there were two flight options and they were both,
I'm not paying for either of them. They were both miles or something like that. But it was like,
okay, there's a business class flight at 10 or there is a coach flight at two. It's a long flight.
You know, it's like eight hours, but it was like, obviously I'd rather be comfortable, but am I going
to, I've been gone so much. I've been on the road for this book. Four hours is a lot. Four hours on
the Sunday is a lot of family time, right? You know, it's also like, you know, leaving at 10 is
profoundly different than leaving at two because you know, you have the whole, you know, how much
are they awake? What are you doing in the morning? Whatever. So I chose the coach flight again. This is
a very privileged dilemma, but I took the coach flight and I was sort of proud of myself. They
did the right thing, whatever. But then if there was something I wanted to do in town this week,
I might be gone for four hours and not think anything of it. There's the subtlety with which
that creeps in versus the distinct and stark contrast of the big decision. Yes. When it's a
big black and white decision, we kind of know what the right thing is, but the drifting towards
this or that where it's a little more gradual, it's harder. And so again, this is where that
momentum more stuff comes in, which is like, don't think about it as you have an unlimited
amount of this to choose from you. You got to always be coming back to it actually kind of is
a black and white decision because you'll never get the time back. And so was it actually more
important that you went and did X, Y, and Z? Maybe not. That's a great story because I see that
example in my life all the time. I'm generally better at drawing boundaries when the asks are
enormous. I'm really bad at drawing boundaries when the asks are subtle and tender and slight
and barely noticeable. Yeah. But the integral of those, the area under the curve of that latter
category often eclipses the former. Yeah. Well, there's just way more of them and they probably
add up to be. So it's like, yeah, if you went away for two days, you'd feel like, oh, that's a huge
deal. But if you went away for two days, but you were present a hundred percent of the time you're
home, it'd be nothing. The problem is when you're home, you're also running around and doing this
and that you're not actually there. Yeah. It's, it's tough. This is about living well, but you also
say this is about dying well. What is, what does dying well mean? Well, I don't have a ton of
experience with dying naturally, but it is the sort of the theme of momentum or the theme about death
is this is where we're all going. Right. So Cicero and then through Montaigne, they say to philosophizes
to learn how to die. It's maybe something we've lost, but that's sort of death as your last
gesture as the final thing, the most important thing you do in life is, is maybe something that
the ancients were much bigger believers in than we are today down, you know, in some cases it's
these dramatic suicides. In other cases, it's just, you know, sort of what are you going to do in these
final moments where the last things you're going to say, but I just, I like the idea that you're
training for that or that you're moving towards that as a reminder that this stuff matters, you
know, these ideas, these things that you're training for something important. Expand on that a little
bit because I think for many people that's counterintuitive, right? Which is, wait a minute,
how could focusing on my death make my life any better? One of the things I left from Seneca is
talking about is talking about these sort of old people that you see who can't, can't let go. He's
like, you should look with pity on the aged lawyer who continues to plead in court for his clients.
He's talking about the guy who can't accept that his moment is past and he has to pass the baton to
the next generation, right? That's a person who, for whom despite all their success, all their fame,
all their money, there's not enough. It's like they're going to be pleading in court until they
drop dead on the spot. Now, what about the argument that says, but if that is their greatest source of
joy, don't we want them doing that rather than sitting in a rocking chair is using the proverbial
counter example? Yeah, I guess the question is, is this actually fun or is this a compulsion?
There's this fascinating video you can watch of Joan Rivers where they're asking her, she's like,
why are you still performing? Why are you doing this? Like, not in a judgmental way, but she
brings out her calendar. She flash forwards a couple months and she goes, like, see these blank
pages. She's like, if these pages stay blank, it means that I'm nothing, that I've fallen off,
that my career was pointless. Like, she basically goes in, she reveals that sometimes you get those
glimpses of people's internal monologue and you get a glimpse of her internal monologue. And on
the one hand, it gives you a sense of how she managed to accomplish this credit. She built this
incredible career. She was one of the first sort of huge female comics, how she persevered through
all the bullshit she would have had to put up with. But I think it's impossible to watch that video
and not feel very sad also, right? Like, that's craving verse fullness. It wasn't, see this blank
calendar? What am I going to do? I'm going to sit around at home. I love being on the road. I love
working, you know, I love being with an audience. Like, this is what I was put on the planet to do.
That's a very different answer than, you know, these blank pages mean that I'm worthless as a
human being, right? And so the idea of aging gracefully, of going out well, is it's not this
separate thing. It is the culmination of these principles that we're talking about. Death isn't
this separate random other thing. It is a process that we're already engaged in, whether we know it
or not, right? Like you're dying now, and that you've already died however many years you've been
alive and you're just doing it every day until you finally get to the last time that you do it.
And maybe that's more of it. I find it clarifying. You're a father now twice. How has that changed
your thinking about this? Because obviously you're a father as your, your first child was
already born by the time you were writing this book. Your second child came along after you
finished the book. How did the influence of them in your lives, I mean, you've written about the
impact of being a father, but how does that help you think about this runway? One of the interesting
things you experience, it was a shock for me. When you bring your kids home from the hospital for the
first time, maybe people prepared me wrong, but I was prepared for like complete chaos, right? Like
this sort of sleep deprived craziness. And that's certainly there, but actually it's like those like
first couple weeks, you're not doing anything. Especially as the dad. Especially as, but you and
your wife or you know, whatever your arrangement is, it was this rude, but also wonderful awakening
that like, that's what being a parent is like. Being a parent is not like running around and
taking them places and doing things. Like being a parent, it's just what your life is. The stillness
of that period I still think of quite often because you're not supposed to be anywhere,
right? You're not supposed to be doing anything. You don't have the ability or the energy to do
anything. It's just like what we're doing is being very quiet while this person sleeps. Like that's
what we're doing. You're not also mowing the lawn, right? Or, or, you know, renovating your bathrooms.
Like you're not doing anything. You can't do anything. That's an energy I try to access
quite often as well, which is like, like Saturday doesn't have to be this, you know, complicated,
orchestrated event. It's not a choreographed dance. It's a, oh, are we just sitting out in the
yard and, you know, digging holes for the next three hours? Is that what we're doing? And being
okay with that. I think parenting and presence are very related because what is fascinating and
entertaining and stimulating for them to an adult is usually an incredibly boring thing. And so you
almost are forced to adopt that, that childlike existence. And it's, I find it very refreshing.
How do you feel about Saturdays in general? You've talked about this idea of what does your Saturday
look like? And the paradox of those days that are hyper scheduled aren't necessarily very
productive days when it comes to doing important work. When I talk to people about success, I sort
of go, not like, what do you want to accomplish? What do you want to have? What do you want to have
done? But like, what do you want? How do you want that to manifest itself into your life? Like, what
do you want your life to look like? So, you know, if you're, if you're a basketball player, you want,
you know, probably game days, your, you know, your dream life, you know, you got the routine,
you go and then you're in the crowd, you're playing. For me, it's like, I like a day with
almost no interruptions, exterior interruptions, I like a little time to write. I like not feeling
pressure. I like time with family, like being outside, you know, like, and so when I think about
what that dream day is, you know, it's like when you visit somewhere on vacation, and then you're
like, wouldn't it be wonderful to live here? You know, it's like, I think when you have one of those
perfect days, you should go like, how can my whole life be like this? And you have a lot of power over
that. But then we go back to green shit we don't want to do. How much power do we have over that? I
mean, again, the skeptic would say, well, Ryan, you're successful. Of course, you have control
over that. But I have a nine to five job where I'm a single parent or, you know, how much control do I
have over my ability to make every day my Saturday? Yeah, again, using Saturday as this sort of analogy.
Yeah, yeah. And I think Saturday is hard for people because they think like, I don't work
Saturdays, right? Like, my Saturday involves me doing what I do, right? But it wasn't free for me
to set up this life. There were real costs to it. I could live in New York and be on television more,
you know, I could live in LA and have a bunch of different writing opportunities that I don't have,
or I could spend more time in town and it would be better. But it's all relative because we do
different things, we have different wants and needs and different, you know, sort of expectations for
life. But the point is like, this life that I set up was not gifted to me, this this required a bunch
of different compromises and a bunch of different, well thought out intentional decisions. You know,
it was buying a house that was less than I could afford so that I didn't, I could actually enjoy it
and not have to go be away from said house to pay for that house. It means saying no to things that
would be awesome to do or cool to do or great stories to tell someday but don't want to.
How do you navigate that?
Well, I try to go, you know, is this getting me closer to that day or further from that day?
So this month had maybe one of those days, two of those days. So it's like, look, it's wonderful.
The book has done well, the tour has been awesome, you know, the experience has been great, but like,
I've got to figure out how to make this not happen as often.
And how do you know how to juggle that? I mean, I've heard you, I think I read it in one of your
blog posts. It's actually an old post you wrote a long time ago, I think about so you want to be
an author. How long ago did you write that? Oh, that would have been 2013, maybe 2012, a while ago.
Yeah. And I'm glad I read it because it also it gave me a great sort of warm up for what's to come
because there's a part of me that's sort of thinking, Oh, look, once I write this book, I'm
done. I never want to have to talk about it. I don't want to have to go on any podcasts. I,
God forbid, don't want to have to go and do book tours or any of that stuff. And reading
that post was a real kick in the groin in a wake up call. It's like, no, dude, like you got to work.
Yeah. I mean, I finished this book in December. So that's how long this process has been going on.
The administrative, right? It's a nine month lead from the time you are fully done with this thing
until it comes out. And, and, and there's lots to do. I guess my, my question really is, how do you
know you're not just on a slippery slope where you're saying, well, it's because of the book that
I'm going to only have one of those days for this month and this month. And how do you know that
that doesn't ultimately just become the new norm? I don't know. I mean, I was just talking to my
wife about this. It's like you tell yourself it'll go back to normal after a certain point,
but it doesn't go back to normal. You have to put it back to normal, right? Like you have to,
it's a stop. It's a draw line. Bringing this out of the world of just you and to the, the average
person that's going to be listening to this. It's, it's really easy to rationalize. This is the
season when I have to work extra hard. Yeah. People say it's going to be two years while I start this
company. And then, and it's like, no, it's, that's not how this works. Right. And so that's why I'm
much more interested in creating sustainable ways of doing, I'm not like for a launch, there is a
little bit of a sprint element to it. It's a month, I think is a manageable amount of time.
But I think when you start to get into these, like the next 10 years are going to be really hard,
but then after that it's going to be like when that period starts to get more than a couple
weeks or a couple months, like I think you're probably doing it wrong. You want to be thinking
about how do you build something more sustainable and endurable? What do you think is with meditation?
Again, one of the things that makes meditation nice is you're talking about the practice,
not the state. In other words, meditation by itself is not particularly interesting. It's not
even enjoyable half the time, but it's a practice. And once a person understands what that practice
is, it allows them to function better outside of their meditative practice. Yeah. Conversely,
you're writing about stillness, which is the desired outcome. And I've always found that to
be a harder way to explain the things. I mean, it's a beautifully important way to do it, which is,
this is the state you want versus this is the practice you do to get a state. So how do you
think about the journey there and the tangible skills that one puts in place? Well, you know,
it's interesting to say that because when I think about ego and when I think about this book,
I think the title or the premise or the introduction is, okay, here are the costs of ego. Here's
maybe what a better place to be in would be like. In this book, it's like, here's how busy and chaotic
the world is. Here's maybe a better way to do it. But then when you actually look at the chapters,
the chapters of both of those books are either examples or counter examples of processes or
practices that allow that state to ensue. Because the problem with like what you get from meditation
or what you get from stillness or whatever the opposite of ego is, is that there's an ineffability
to it. Like you can't really describe what it is because it's fleeting and ephemeral and also deeply
unique to each person and each time you have it. So what I'm trying to do in the books is just
give you a bunch of slices of approaches or ideas that if followed, if thought about,
if sort of integrated into who you are, will hopefully ensue to that place. So I'm mostly
only thinking about practice and I can't even give you a definition of what stillness is,
let alone like a magical recipe, but I can give you some tools or strategies that tend to be
correlated with achieving that outcome. What do you think are three of those that are, I don't
actually want to say the easiest to enact, but I'd rather frame it as, let's say the most reliable.
The most potent activators. I think walking is a huge one. Every day I walk. Not only do I try to
go on walks just like to be outside and do nothing. Usually I take my son if we're not doing
the bike thing, but just some sort of low impact physical exercise, but doing the exercise for the
mental benefits, right? Just being outside. And you don't get this from your running and your
swimming. I do, but it's separate. The running or swimming I'm doing for the physical benefits,
primarily. The walking is just for the walking. It's where you think it's where you're outside.
It's where you're looking around. When I'm running, I'm not like, Oh, look how wonderful this is. Do
you run with music? I do, yeah. Swimming, I used to swim a bit. And one of the things people used
to always ask me was, doesn't it drive you crazy that you don't have your phone with you ever?
The whole point. Yeah. And of course nowadays they do have, and I was like, are you kidding?
Like that's the greatest part of swimming is the sound of the water going against your ears.
Or the fact that it's almost like a sensory deprivation tank. So many of the parts that are
normally alive are turned off. And I think this is why the mind becomes more perceptive. And obviously
you're walking without your phone, without music, without interruption. Are you being deliberate
about anything? When you, for example, I don't mean to bring this back to meditation all the time,
but one of the things I do enjoy is a walking meditation where you focus on the sensory
experience of walking, both in terms of sound, feel, air moving past you. Are you doing anything
sort of deliberately in that way? The only thing I'd be doing is if I find I'm getting caught up in
something mentally, to just be like, come back to the experience. So that is kind of a meditation.
Yeah. Okay. Walking would be a big one. I mean, I think journaling would be a huge one. We could
talk about the exercise thing. I mean, to me, Austin is the most underrated swimming town in
America. Like Barton Springs is incredible. Deep Eddie is incredible. Just like the nature you can
get here is fantastic. Maybe the other one I would talk about is like a hobby of some kind.
What do you do that's not work? I define some of these hobbies as hobbies where pure effort and
anger or rage can make you accomplish a little bit more like running or lifting weights and hobbies
like golf and archery, where that's the opposite and more effort does not, do you think it's the
latter that are, and I'm biased because I love archery, but. Yeah, no, ideally it's not something
you can win at. It's something. You know, not hobbies where effort equals outcome. Yeah. And
willful will. It's not a willpower related endeavor. I think is painting. If you're an
athlete, maybe writing is a hobby, right? For me, I can't also write as a hobby because it's my
profession, but I could play sports, right? So having some sort of practice or activity that you
do on a regular basis, for me, it's the farm. Like people go, oh, isn't it a lot of work? And it is a
lot of work, but it's the opposite of my work. So it's restorative. And I think you find people
that they're just, they basically sort of become monks in what they do. And that's a very unbalanced
I think way to live. It's really easy to do this. And I feel like I could be the worst defender of
this. It's tempting to optimize our life so much that there is no downtime. It's tempting to say,
you know, all play is highly structured. There is no just doing nothing. And I guess that's really
one of the beauties of kids as you alluded to is like my middle son who's five, he loves gardening
so much. And he loves Home Depot. It's his favorite place in the world. So really, if you ask him,
like, what is his perfect day? It's getting up, going to Home Depot, getting paint, getting buckets,
getting flowers, coming back, planting them, fixing the hose, painting the fence, all of these things
that one don't even seem like they're fun things to do. But they turn out to be pretty fun. When
you're doing them through that lens, and it would be easy to outsource a lot of that stuff. Oh, come
on, we're not gonna paint the fence. We can hire somebody to paint the fence. And they'll do it
better job. I'm really bad at painting fences. It's funny, because you alluded to this idea that
we expect them to bring a tornado to our lives. And yet, ironically, they can bring stillness,
despite their movement. Yeah, totally. My son loves to get his hair cut. So we go and get hair
cuts. It's a thing. But me getting a haircut by myself is in no way a pleasurable meditative
experience. But when I'm getting with him, it's not the haircut that's the thing. It's the that
we're doing this thing together. Or he wants to go get the mail. Like, you know, there's these
little things that you end up doing. And you realize, that's all that you have to be doing.
And then you're fully present in that thing. You know, like, oh, going and getting the mail is an
activity for him. I think Alexandra Horowitz, she wrote that she wrote that book Inside of a Dog,
about the oomwelt of the dog experience is really great. She wrote another book called I think,
Ways of Seeing or On Looking or something like that. And I've told the story before, but and
it's obviously in her book, so I'm not making it up. But she went on like seven walks with seven
different people in different areas. So she went through on a walk with like a geologist in New York
City. And he was like showing her all the different things you could learn about that. Or she went,
you know, walked through a field with a biologist and different walks with different kinds of people,
you know, a code inspector in a neighborhood. And just like what are they seeing that a normal
person isn't seeing? That's what the premise of the book is. But on this one, she goes on a walk
around the block where her apartment is with like a two or three year old or two or three year old
son or daughter, I forget. But one of the things I think about that I took from that book,
is she talks about how she thought the walk began when they left the building. But so she's like
interviewing her kid after the kid thought the walk was from there. She's like, we're going on
a walk. And to the kid, the walk started when they left the apartment and walked to the elevator and
then went down the elevator, and then across the lobby and then out the door. Do you see what I
mean? And so to a kid, that actually is a far walk. That's the other part you don't realize you take
for granted how easy things are for you. But just the idea that the definition of what the is
is, is something kids bring to the table. And as a parent, like, oh, like, yeah, this is what we're
doing. We're like, my son is like, I want to play dirt. Like, it just means he wants to play with
dirt. And it's like, this is what we're doing. We have these expensive toys that could take you
somewhere to do anything. But like, what we're doing is like, we're sitting here, and we're
playing with dirt. And there's a purity to that. And a magic to that, I think that that is as much
stillness as Kennedy in the Missile Crisis. And that I think they're accessing the same place.
And what do you think it was about JFK in, you know, certainly three most stressful moments of
the 20th century, certainly three of the most high stakes moment of the 20th century that could have
truly altered the course of civilization? What do you think prepared him for that moment?
In a way, he was like, not prepared. You almost set up to fail in that moment. I mean, like,
if you compare the Bay of Pigs, Kennedy to the Missile Crisis, Kennedy, and then even the events
in between, you're, you're not thinking that's how that's going to go. Had the Bay of Pigs not
happened. So let's assume that when Kennedy comes into office in 61, the CIA has already decided the
Bay of Pigs, you know, yeah, Johnson wanted to rather Eisenhower wanted to do this thing, but
we think it's kind of a dumb idea. And he goes, yeah, yeah, that's a dumb idea. We're not doing
it. So there's no Bay of Pigs. And yet all the events that unfold in the Cuban Missile Crisis
unfold, does he behave differently? I don't know. I mean, I think it was a variety of factors. I
think one of the biggest ones is that he had read Barbara Tuchman's book, The Guns of August, like he,
he had some understanding of how badly it could go if he wasn't aware of what was happening as it
was happening, right? Like the idea that we kind of slept walked into this war that we didn't
understand that a lot of people were making very short sighted decisions, decisions that made sense
in the moment, but they weren't thinking about how that decision related to the other decisions,
I think was hugely impactful for Kennedy. I think he'd had some humility to sort of getting his
ass kicked by Khrushchev in some sort of diplomatic exchanges, had made him realize that the job was
really hard and that you can't just go with your gut. You can't just listen to what people say,
that it really required sort of deliberation and consultation and consideration. You know,
his expression says we got to use time as a tool and not as a couch. Just even that the
Missile Crisis takes 13 days, it's kind of impressive. Like you could imagine, let's not
even say, you can imagine George W. Bush does not take 13 days to think that one through,
because it's kind of obvious what you should do. Like our gravest military enemy has put nuclear
missiles 90 miles from the shore of Florida. What you're supposed to do there is like very obvious,
right? You blow the shit out of that, right? And you believe you're 100% justified in doing so,
but it's more complicated than that. You can imagine Bill Clinton, you can imagine Lyndon
Johnson gets called into the Situation Room and there, I don't know if it's the Situation Room
then actually, but so he gets called in and he's like, we got to do it. There are other presidents
who would not have taken 13 days to unwind that. What's also interesting is they all have different
strengths and weaknesses. You know, I didn't grow up in this country, but I'm still incredibly
fascinated by its history and I'm always impressed by the different character strengths
of different presidents. Johnson being like the master politician, right? The master of
relationships, but maybe in that moment too impatient. If you do move to Texas, you've got
to read the Lyndon Johnson series or the Robert Caro series on Lyndon Johnson, but he talks about how
Kennedy believed that civil rights were so obvious. And so it was such a morally superior position
that all he had to do was say, this is what we're going to do. And of course that would happen.
And Lyndon Johnson, I would say equally believed in that idea, but, or maybe actually believed in
it less, but he knew politically it would be a lot more complicated. And ultimately he was the only
one that was able to get it done. And actually some of Kennedy's sort of moral superiority and
assurance made it harder than it needed to be, right? Like he sort of telegraphed his intentions.
He basically said like, we are going to pass a civil rights bill. And then this sort of solid
South was like, well, we're going to make that even harder for you now that you've told us what
you're planning to do. Yeah, different strengths and weaknesses certainly, but if you could bottle
whatever he was exhibiting there in that missile crisis, and there are very few leadership
situations that would not be improved by that. It's not like this guy was perfect. It's not like
this guy was without ego. It's not like this guy was the flawless character that you want to believe
the first time you read a chapter on him in grade school. I mean, he cheated on his wife in the
missile crisis, right? He's expecting that the world could end at any moment and he's spending
that time not at home. So it's not great, but I think what's so fascinating to me about the
missile crisis is it's not just that he slowed it down. He was also incredibly decisive, right?
It's not like he, it was non-negotiable that those missiles were going to go. So it's not like he was
waffling. You see that bad leadership can, that's what he means by a couch. You can use, you could
take 13 days just to think about it and go swing this way and that way. Kennedy was like, this is
the outcome, but I am very open to a variety of ways to get there. And that's what he figures out
over those 13 days. There's one last topic I want to get to, Ryan, and it's a sort of pivot away
from this, but it's something you've written so extensively about and just on a personal level,
something that has been very helpful to me, which is anger. Let's start with when it's helpful,
when it's not helpful, what is it about anger that can be destructive? What do the Stoics think about
anger? Let's say as a group, they're against it. I mean, Seneca writes a beautiful essay called
Of Anger that's basically a warning to young Nero about the costs and the dangers of anger.
It pops up over and over again in his letters as well. But I mean, anger is one of those things
where like ego, we're really eager to make excuses for it, like to go, oh, it's part of who I am. It
helps me what I've done. It's great fuel. When I look at all the times I've lost my temper, I've
been really angry about anything, I never think back going, I'm really glad. You know what I mean?
Like that's different than sort of moral outrage about, like when I hear about something that's
wrong and my immediate reaction is that's not okay, I'm upset that that's the status quo. To me,
that's different than anger in the sort of the temper sense of the word. So maybe if we're making
a distinction that Stoics are very anti-temper. But even Seneca talks about Seneca is like, look,
like someone murdered your father, you'd still get vengeance. You don't want to do it from a place
of anger. And I think he just means that like, there's an objective idea of justice. Not being
angry doesn't mean you accept everything and that you wilt and you tolerate the gravest injustices.
But it's that you're not being jerked around by those reactions. There might be people listening
to this who can relate, but sometimes when we're angry, we actually break inanimate objects. You
had some really interesting things to say about this recently. You wrote about this in one of the
newsletters. Again, reading it is so funny because it's you write about it in a way that's light,
but like I can't count the number of inanimate things I've smashed in my life. Not that long
ago, I had, you know, I had, I couldn't find my AirPod. So I had like the regular iPod headphones
and they weren't tank, they were all tangled. I was getting mad. And then it was like, I ripped,
I ripped it apart. And it was like, well, I really punished these headphones. You know what I mean?
And now it's like, I can't do the thing that I wanted to do. Yeah, I do think it's interesting.
Anger can so get ahold of us that we will essentially be talking through our actions
to a stove or a wall or a computer. Yeah, my desk has got, you know, crack in it from where I hit it
because something was right. Yeah, we, I don't think the stokes were perfect. And I feel like
if they were perfect, they wouldn't have talked about anger so much. I think they're talking
about anger because it's a perpetual problem in their life. Think about Marcus Aurelius, like,
have you seen the movie Lincoln? That's, you know, that scene where that sort of argue, I think it's
one of the greatest scenes in all of movies where they're like telling him why he can't do this. And
he's like, he pounds on the table. He's like, I am the president of the United States. He's like,
I am clothed in immense power. That's impotence. Like he's angry at the impotence that he got this
far. This thing is so obvious of passing the 13th amendment is profoundly, obviously the right thing
to do. It's the only court can't even will it to happen in that moment. That's so much of where
our anger comes from. But then when you even think about that situation, it's not the anger that's
all said, it's that he then leaves that room and he's willing to, to basically do all sorts of
complicated, even some cases, morally dubious things to get where he needs to go. So I thought
about this a lot because I wrote this book about Peter Thiel and his sort of quest to destroy
Gawker. There's that expression that revenge is a dish best served cold. People think that means
you want to enjoy the fruits of your victory. But it's no, it's a dish best served cold,
which means what they're saying is you don't want to touch a hot plate. You don't want to do it out
of anger because you get burned. Right. And so that's what I think about anger. I think
politically, we've now confused anger and political change. We almost conflate purity
or moral superiority with how angry you are. That's not how you solve any problems.
Do you have a sense of where we are historically on our anger meter?
There is so much moral outrage. It's easy to now lose sight of what,
what's the root and what's the response? Yeah, it's really hard to tell. And I think what's
interesting to me, like people are we on the verge of a civil war? A friend of mine was,
works in DC. He was like, who the fuck's fighting in this civil war? He's like, none of these people
were. I think that's what's actually interesting about all the anger that we have is that it's
primarily sort of verbal and social. It's not real. Is that because we're not willing to die
for something anymore? I mean, I just don't like going back to stoic virtues.
Yeah, I think, I think this is all a performance. I think this is largely a performance or it's
almost therapeutic. Like it's a, it's in the way that we used to be really into music. We're now
really just into being angry about political and social issues. Anyways, there are very few problems
to which anger is the solution. And the most serious problems, the ones that are the most
aggravating are the ones that require the most discipline and the least amount of anger. Like I
think about that again, politically, it's like, okay, most of the wrong in the world is not being
done deliberately. It's being done by people who don't know better, who are ignorant, who are being
manipulated, or in some cases, think they're doing the right thing, right? So anger at those people
is not going to make them change their mind, right? You're not going to yell at someone into waking
up to the bad assumption they've taken in, right? And then there are real bad people in this world.
There's evil and there's sociopaths and there's, there's real bad actors. Those people, you're
certainly not going to yell at a sociopath into not being a sociopath, right? It's like precisely
the most dangerous high stakes situations require our utmost cognitive and rational resources. So
I'm not talking about anger from a place of someone who has no temper, who doesn't get angry
about shit. I'm just stating the fact that less anger is better. The story you led with, or the
example you led with, which you've written about as well, I think is, it's really humbling, which is
go back in time, consider every time you've lost your marbles and ask, when did it accomplish what
you wanted? When did it actually make the situation better? And I can't say it's never happened,
but it's, I can't remember when it did. Or Seneca talks about like, when you see other angry people,
like just really, like I have some memories of Dove who had a bad anger problem. When I think
about what he looked like angry and just how shockingly immature and childish and ridiculous
and embarrassing it was, you know, you could see his neck and he felt like he was going to drop
dead of a heart attack. I've never seen anything like it. But when we see other people get angry,
we're like, what are you doing? But how he talks about Seneca just talks about looking in the mirror
when you're in, he's like, have you ever actually seen yourself get angry? That was, I think,
day four of the anger. Oh, yeah, sure. Program you put together. Like, did you see that photo in the
March Madness from last year of Tom Izzo? He's the coach at Missouri. He ends up, some player
messed up and he's yelling at him and he's so you got to just just look at this after when you
get so angry. He's like clenches fists. He's clearly he's so angry. You know how at the end of
it, it almost becomes physical, right? He's like trying to physically intimidate a child like,
you know, an 18 year old basketball player. And he's in his face, he's yelling and he's trying to
get his point across. He's it's like almost like a gorilla, you know, the gorilla is like trying to
show don't mess with me. And he's the photo snaps him doing this as another student is another
athlete is stepping in to separate the two like he a child is stepping in between a man yelling
at another child, right? It ended up a lot of people under rationalize and this is what coaches
do, blah, blah, blah, and there's like no evidence that yelling makes players better. But if we could
get that photo of ourselves, though, whenever we were the most angry, I think it would cut it in
half because you'd be like, I never want to do that again. I agree with that completely. And that was
sort of the first thought I had, which was I need a picture of me like that in my pocket. As a
reminder, as I'm getting worked up, like, don't go here, don't become the Incredible Hulk. Sometimes
I think about like, you know, you have security cameras at your house or whatever I'm wondering,
like, and I know they've caught it before, but I'm actually too scared to look at it. But like,
what would watching an argument between you and your spouse look like, what would you actually
take from that? Like, I almost know what I would take from it. That's why I don't want to watch it.
Do you know what I mean? But like, in the same way, I'm sure you found this with your podcast,
when you listened to your first episode with your you were like, fuck, that's how can anyone listen
to this person? Do you know, like, when I hear my own audio books, I'm like, Oh, this is awful.
I can imagine what looking at yourself in an argument with another person would be just
utterly repugnant. Yeah. You know, and you would realize you do a lot of things that you don't
realize you're doing. Ryan, this has been great. I've been wanting to speak with you for so long,
long before stillness came out, but it just became a great reason to have more than one
thing to talk about. Again, as I said to folks, if they don't already subscribe to the Daily Stoic,
they should what's the best way that people can sort of get ahold of all of the this type of
wisdom that you're you're very generously providing. So I'm at Ryan holiday, most platforms,
rent holiday.net, do stoke calm, do you get the daily dad email? It's I don't and I realize I'm
gonna have to I'm gonna have to bite the bullet and get another email. That's that's the one I
like doing. I got to find some way to combine them or so. I know it's weird that it's two,
but they feel very different to me. So dailydad.com is the other daily one I do each day.
I know I said I would that was my questions. I do have one last question for you. How the hell can
you be so prolific? It's my it's my job. I mean, like I have a practice, I follow the practice
every day, and it comes out the backside. It's unbelievable. I'm not jealous, nor am I envious,
but incredibly respectful. I think that the process is where it comes from. I personally
am incredibly grateful as a result of that process. And I know that I'm far from the only one. So
thank you very much. Thanks. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive.
If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership
program that allows us to bring you more in depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription.
Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass
comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss
on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or
ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely access to our private podcast feed
that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The
QALYs, which are a super short podcast, typically less than five minutes that we release every
Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple podcast
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures
and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.