Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Dr. Mark Hyman. Mark is a family physician,
a New York Times bestselling author and the director of the Cleveland Clinic Center for
Functional Medicine. It turns out we're going to talk about pretty much none of that today.
We talk almost exclusively on his new book, which is due out tomorrow called Food Fix,
How to Save Our Health, Our Economy, Our Communities, and Our Planet One Bite at a
Time. And if that sounds like a mouthful, it's because it is a mouthful. This is a kind of
staggering topic. And even by the standards of this podcast, it's probably too much for one
episode. Mark basically lays out a thesis that if you fix the food system, you fix a lot of problems.
So it's not a one-fer, it's not a two-fer, it's like somewhere between a three-fer and a four-fer.
We don't spend a lot of time talking about the health consequences of fixing food,
although we open our discussion with that talking about the health impact of food. We talk a little
bit about gut health, but we spend more of our time probably speaking about some of the social
consequences and the environmental consequences. And of course, it ultimately does come down to
health at the individual level. We do get a lot into agriculture, energy usage around food. We
talk a lot about the impact on climate. We also talk quite a lot about GMO, the strength of the
evidence for and against it. We go through a lot of the policy ideas around how one might fix
the food system. And actually we close with a nice anecdote of an explanation that I thought
Mark provided that was pretty interesting around the difference between food in Europe and North
America. Many people, myself included, have commented on this, which is, why is it that
when you go to Europe, you seem to be able to eat with impunity things that in the United States
just feel like they're about to kill you. Anyway, this is a really interesting episode.
I learned a lot in preparing for it. And truthfully, I still feel like there's a lot I just
don't understand in this system. There's probably a lot I need to go back and get smarter on.
There are so many big numbers in this type of a discussion that the scale
doesn't make sense at times when you start to think about what it means to feed the world
and how making changes in that system can have enormous knock on effects for both good and bad.
So without further delay, please enjoy my discussion with Mark Hyman. And we may end
up revisiting this topic with other guests. Should people find this interesting?
Hey Mark, thanks for coming over, man. No, I'm so happy to be here. It's beautiful.
Chickens running around and everything. Ben is in the freezer, my kind of place.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It's in keeping with a lot of what we're going to talk about today. I think,
Mark, a lot of people would associate you with other topics that we might get into,
functional medicine, the role of toxins in the environment, certainly food, but from the
standpoint of health, what to eat. But what we're talking about today is actually something that
when you first mentioned to me, you were working on this book. Actually, at the time you were
putting the finishing touches on it about a year ago, I was like, wow, that's definitely something
I want to understand more. So I can't wait to kind of have this discussion with you today.
And that is basically how food is made, how food is delivered and how food is consumed and what
the impacts of that are. I mean, what made you decide to tackle a problem of this magnitude,
which is not just a scientific problem, but it's a political problem. Totally. It's a religious
problem if we're going to be brutally honest. I mean, the nutrition religion. Yes, exactly.
So it's about as complicated as a topic as one would go after.
It is. And I think as a doctor, seeing patients day after day for 30 years
as a functional medicine doctor, my focus is on why. Why are my patients so sick? And not always,
but the majority of them, it has some relationship to food. And then I began to wonder, well,
I could sit here all day bailing the bucket and the boat with a hole in it, but I have to figure
out why they're eating the food they're eating. And then you're going to think about it and go
upstream and well, the food they're eating is caused by the food system. And I'm like, well,
why do we have the food system we have? Well, our food policies. And then I'm like, why do we have
our food policies? It's the food industry that influences our government policies through
lobbying and other influences that they do across the spectrum of society to drive their products
to the market and sell them, which are predominantly killing us. I mean, there's 11 million people that
die every year from eating ultra processed food and not enough for the good food. And I think it's
an underestimate. So basically the answer to the question is I realized I couldn't treat my
patients in my office or in the hospital or the clinic. I had to go to where the source of the
problem was. Yeah. And I want to sort of put this in context, which is the evolution of this. The
domestication of crops, the institutionalization of agriculture has for, we're going to demonize
it a little bit here, but the reality of it is it's been kind of a remarkable transformation.
It would certainly be akin to the printing press when you think about step function changes in our
civilization, when we went from hunter gatherers to an agricultural society. So I want to be careful
that we're not just sort of saying the answer is agriculture is the end of the. The agriculture is
a solution if we do it right. Yeah. So let's start with what you see as the sort of main pillars of
the problem. How did we get to a point where the food environment is toxic? Because that's
effectively what you're saying, right? If you eat on default, you're going to probably eat the wrong
things. Yeah. It goes deeper than that. The food system as a whole, as I began to dig in this rabbit
hole, I realized it wasn't just causing chronic disease, but it was causing most of the global
crises that we're thinking about in silos that are all connected. And I'll just sort of quickly
lay them out and it'd be good to go over them in detail as we go through the podcast. But
clearly food is the biggest driver of chronic disease affecting six out of 10 people.
It's clearly the biggest driver of economic stress in this country in our $22 trillion debt,
one third of all Medicare expenses over diabetes alone, and one third of all of our federal
budget is Medicare. If it was a company, it would be the biggest company in the world at a trillion
dollars annually. It's also driving climate change. A food system end to end and we'll unpack it,
is the number one cause of climate change more than fossil fuels. It's causing massive
environmental degradation, including loss of biodiversity, plant species, animal species,
livestock species. It's driving social injustice in many ways through how it affects our kids'
cognitive development and ability to learn. And there's huge academic achievement gaps.
It leads to massive health disparities because poor communities are more affected by these
foods and are more targeted by them. It affects even behavior, violence, conflict. We see such a
device of society today. Why do we have that? 40 years ago, it wasn't like that. And I think
our diet has changed so radically, not just in the last 10,000 years, but in the last 40 years
with the advent of massive amounts of ultra-processed food. And that's driving
cognitive behavioral issues, violence, suicide, conflict, and even threatens our national security
because 70% of military recruits are unfit to fight and are rejected. So we've got these global
problems that are affecting us. And then of course that leads to massive political instability
because of our food system of climate refugees, because the food system is driving climate.
What is that going to do? I mean, think about it. We had a million Syrian refugees
and that created a global crisis. The UN estimates that within a decade or a few decades, we're going
to have 200 to a billion climate refugees. That's unimaginable. So how do we begin to sort of grapple
with these problems and think about the solutions? And the beauty is since they're all connected by
food, they can all be solved by going to the root and fixing our food system. And that's the leverage
we have, which is so exciting to me because it's not, oh, doom and gloom, the world's ending. It's,
yeah, we identify the problem, how it's connected, think of it as a system, and then be able to solve
the problem by going to the root and dealing with these issues collectively. So which one of those
would you like to start with? Would you like to start with sort of the impact of processed food
on health, which is probably not one that we need to spend a lot of time on? I don't think there's
many people that would debate that, are there? Oh, you'd be surprised. I mean, there's 12 billion
dollars spent by the food industry on nutrition, quote, research that confuses people, muddies the
waters, declares that Gatorade is a great sports drink and that sugar doesn't cause obesity and
that, I mean, I could go on and on. People are confused and certainly our political leaders
certainly don't get this. And I think when you think of our healthcare system, it certainly
doesn't get that food is medicine. Do you really think that political leaders, I know you've spent
some time interacting with said folks, do you really think they don't get it or do you think
that they're just in a difficult position, which is how do you appease all of these constituents?
On the one hand, a lot of the bills get paid by the entities that endorse these agendas. And on
the other end, they probably have empathy for the damage that's done. I mean, do you actually think
there's a lack of awareness? I do. I mean, forget about politicians, academics, doctors,
health professionals have no clue how powerful food is to heal disease. I mean, they get that if you
eat too much, you're going to get fat, right? But that's about it. Or if you eat too much carbs,
maybe now, maybe you'll get diabetes, but not even that. I mean, the American Diabetes Association
is still telling people to eat a lot of carbohydrates. I think we have a real lack of
understanding of the power of food to cause disease and the power of food to cure disease.
And so there's a real gap in that. I think it's starting to become in the public awareness that
food is medicine, that there's a food is medicine working group in Congress, Cleveland Clinic,
where I work now is a food is medicine initiative. There's hospitals around the country. They're
talking about this. It's more the exception than the rule. So I do think people don't understand
the magnitude. I mean, if you say to a politician, what is the biggest killer on the planet? They're
going to go smoking or lack of exercise or maybe they're going to get this being overweight,
but they don't get that it's the ultra processed food that kills more people than smoking,
violence, wars, everything else. So I mean, I think if there was a disease like Ebola or
Zika that was killing 11 million people a year, I mean, people would be talking about it. And it's
just not in the conversation that's happening. Even for example, Medicare, Medicare for all,
has anybody said the reason we have the trouble with Medicare is because people are eating bad
food and that we need to fix the food? They're no saying, let's get Medicare for all. Let's
repeal Obamacare. I mean, those aren't the solutions. It's like that would be a disaster
if we had Medicare for all because everybody's sick and it's just going to bankrupt the country
unless we fix why they're sick in the first place. What do you think it is about processed foods
that are particularly difficult metabolically for our species? Historically, we ate 800 different
species of plants, a lot of roots and tubers, 100 grams of fiber a day. Now in the average American,
it's about eight grams, which is nothing. And we had a very complex diet, which was very difficult
to obtain sugar. You got lucky if you found a honey thing. I mean, I remember reading this
article about these Nepalese honey hunters where they have to climb up a hundred feet
into the trees with a burning bush and it's like, if you had to climb a tree with a burning bush to
get a cookie, you probably wouldn't eat so many cookies. And I think it's just become so easy for
us to have this abundance of sugar and flour and refined foods. And the good intentions that were
there in the post-war period that led to the development of industrial agriculture were to
provide a lot of starchy, abundant calories to feed the hungry and solve real hunger issues
around the world. And I think that was a good thing, but there was unintended consequences of
the intensive chemical agriculture that we're using, intensive fertilizer use, and the commodity
products, which are wheat, corn, soy, and rice in some other areas of the world that are driving
this obesity epidemic. So our biology isn't adapted to eating highly refined foods, which
essentially is most of what we're eating now. It's 60% of our calories and every 10% of your
calories that's ultra processed food, your risk of death goes up by 14%. So it's not something
our bodies like, it's something you're adapted to. And then of course there's all the other stuff
in there that may be problematic like refined soybean oil or food additives or chemicals that
are in our food that have all sorts of metabolic consequences like BPA or other metabolic toxins
that are consumed within the food we're eating. So it's complicated. It's sugar and starch and
flour are the big drivers, but there's all these other components. And then who knows what's
happening with pesticides and glyphosate affecting our microbiome. I mean, it's such a complex web
of different factors that alter our metabolic pathways that drives disease. And just kind of
digging into this a little bit more, how much of it do you think is the energy balance and the
dysregulation of energy balance that comes from these processed foods? So there are certainly
people out there that would argue that part of the trouble with processed food is it sort of
hijacks our energy homeostatic systems. So if you put a human in an environment akin to what
our ancestors evolved in, there was enough auto feedback and regulation that you sort of
maintained energy balance. You would eat more when you needed to eat more, you would eat less
when you needed to eat less. One of the drawbacks of processed food, if not the biggest drawback,
is it sort of hijacks that system. And if you cut the feedback out of that loop, they're eating when
they don't really need additional energy. Do you think that's the biggest issue or do you think
it's the void of nutrient that then creates sort of an abundance of junk calorie as the body
search for nutrients? Do you think it's this loss of fiber? Probably both. I mean, kids who are iron
deficient eat dirt. It's called pica. And it's well known that if you're looking for nutrients,
you're just going to eat anything. So that may be part of it. I think the main part of it is,
and you've talked about this a lot, is the ways in which these refined starches and sugars affect
your biology. They raise insulin, which has a cascading effect of fat storage in your belly,
which is a dangerous fat. It leads to increased hunger, affects your brain chemistry. It actually
locks the fat in the fat cells so they can't get out. So it gets like a one-way turnstile that gets
in but can't get out. And it slows your metabolism. So you're in this cascade of vicious cycles. So
you're talking about energy balance. I think most people when they hear that think about calories
and calories out, I think I both understand that it's more complex than that, that there's different
effects of food on your biology independent of calories. In a lab, all calories are the same.
750 calories of Coke is the same as 750 calories of broccoli. But to get 750 calories of soda,
you'd have a big gulp, which is 40, 60 spoons of sugar. And 750 calories of broccoli is 21
cups of broccoli with 35 grams of fiber and no sugar. Profoundly different effects on your
biology, same calories. But we don't really appreciate that medicine. And most of our current
thinking about weight loss is focused on calories in, calories out. It suits the food industry
because they go, well, it's all about moderation. There's no good or bad calories. It's exercise
more, eat less. Like that's their mantra. And it serves them to sell more of their junk food as
long as it's part of a Pope balanced diet. But the truth is that these foods affect our brain
chemistry and create all sorts of metabolic issues that are incredibly difficult. And I was
chatting with my friend David Perlmutter who just wrote a book called Brainwash where he's talking
about, he's a neurologist where the prefrontal cortex and the amygdala are uncoupled with an
inflammatory diet, which is what we're eating most of us in America and around the world.
What that means is that the adult in the room, the prefrontal cortex, which is the decision maker
that understands the consequences of its behavior is not talking to the impulse part of your brain,
the fight or flight part of your brain, the pleasure seeking part of your brain. So there's
this disconnection and your decisions are not in your best interest. And that's why we have so much
bad behavior and conflict and so forth, because we're eating this inflammatory diet that's
literally disregulating our brain. So the adult in the room is asleep.
Say a bit more about that. What is it about the diet that could be inflammatory and how could one
measure the consequences of that? Because is it possible that two people could consume the exact
same subpar diet and have very different inflammatory responses?
Yeah, sure. I mean, there is a, listen, if people are eating junk food and processed food, their
metabolism, whatever they look like, whether they're overweight or not, is not going to be as
good as someone who's eating a whole foods unprocessed diet. But there is a lot of genetic
variability, but you can actually measure inflammation in response to diet through various
biomarkers. There's new panels of sort of looking at the inflammasome, which is really cool. It's
more than just a CRP or a CED rate, which are blood tests you can do to look at inflammation.
And the ways in which it causes, particularly it was talking about insulin, it also drives this
visceral belly fat, which is a basically metabolic fire that starts in these cells and it spreads
inflammation throughout the body. So just the nature of eating sugar and processed food drives
up inflammation. If a patient has normal biomarkers through the lens of all of those things,
their interleukins and C-rective protein, fibrinogen, if all of those things were normal,
would you still think that there's potentially an inflammatory response that's coming through
their diet? The question is how sensitive are our current tools for assessing the immune response
to food? And I think they're pretty crappy. And I think there's more and more lab diagnostic
measures that are coming about that are going to help us look at that. I was talking to someone
from the Buck Institute of Aging last week and he said, yeah, there's a whole new panel of
inflammatory biomarkers that are much more specific and much more sensitive and it enabled
us to have a look at the inflammatory response that's happening in the body related to aging
or diet or anything else. How much of that inflammatory response do you think is mediated
by permeability in the gut specifically versus, because I have to be honest with you Mark, this
is an area that I've never understood. It gets talked about a lot. There's lots of hand waving.
Sometimes I see it certainly in patients. I mean, when we see subtle elevations in fibrinogen and
or C-reactive protein or at least two of the interleukins, we usually put patients on elimination
diets till we find out what the culprit was and we're trying to basically titrate symptoms versus
these biomarkers. But I find that to be staggeringly crude. And to your point, I don't know what we're
missing and I don't know what's true, true and unrelated. And then of course it gets back to the
question of what's the mechanism of this. And so one potential mechanism is that the permeability
of the gut is altered. And if bacteria that could normally not translocate across the lining of the
gut do so, that would certainly be a reason for inflammation. A, do you think that that's a
prevalent source of it? Oh yeah, huge. I mean, all our guts are messed up and there's a whole
phenomenon called metabolic endotoxemia. It's been well described and studied. And the fact that your
gut microbiome has a huge role in regulation of weight independent of calories. So they literally
can take the poop out of a skinny rat into a fat rat and make them skinny and vice versa. They've
done in humans. I think the way in which it works is that your microbiome is regulated by what you
eat. A lot of fiber, prebiotics, the phytonutrients, the phytochemicals, the polyphenols all affect the
quality of the garden you have growing inside of you. And you can get a lot of nasty weeds in there.
When that starts to happen, they start to disrupt the gut microbiome. They disrupt the lining of the
gut. They cause what we call leaky gut on top of everything else, which is our low fiber diet,
high sugar, processed food, increases bad bugs in the gut, antibiotics, acid blockers,
anti-inflammatory drugs, hormones, all screw up our gut. And of course, toxins, environmental
toxins, glyphosate is super toxic to the microbiome. And so all these things that we know and those
things we don't know are disrupting the microbiome. And when that happens, the lining of the gut
becomes slightly damaged, the biofilms get disrupted, and you end up absorbing bacterial
products, bacterial toxins, as well as food antigens, things that we should normally tolerate,
and start to create an inflammatory response. And 60% of your immune system is in your gut.
And what's really striking to me, Peter, is the discovery that many of our metabolites in our
blood, probably a third or more, may be from microbiome. In other words, when you check your
blood tests, we're checking human analytes. But when you actually start to do some more sophisticated
metabolic testing and metabolism, you find all these things that aren't human, that come from
bacteria that are regulating your immune system, that are activating your mitochondria, that are
regulating your DNA, that are affecting your brain chemistry, affecting your mood, affecting
all sorts of diseases. So this is like a really exciting area. And I think getting people's
microbiome sorted often happens when you shift to a whole foods, plant-rich diet, not plant-based,
but plant-rich. How can one measure these things? I mean, one of the things that I've found difficult
is finding valid commercial tests that can enable patients or physicians to understand if they're
in this sort of regulated state. I mean, to me, the black box is when someone comes in and says,
I have gut dysbiosis or I have poor gut health. And they may be right, but it's very different
than someone who says, I have type 2 diabetes, where we have really clear ways to diagnose it.
We kind of have some understanding what the pathophysiology is here. This is much more squishy.
And frankly, there's an enormous disconnect between people like you and sort of the
stuffy upper-lipped gastroenterologist who makes his or her living in the gut,
but doesn't necessarily sort of see the problem this way, right? They're looking at different
problems. You know, honestly, Peter, the evidence has become so overwhelming that mainstream medicine
is bought into this whole microbiome story. And Cleveland Clinic, for example, they're studying
the microbiome and heart disease and arthritis and cancer. And it's like, they just got a $12
million grant from the NIH to study the microbiome and heart disease, which is pretty amazing.
And yet, if you go to your doctor and say, is there any evidence that I should be on this
probiotic or this? Yeah, they don't know. The clinical translation is challenging. So I'm
somebody who's been practicing functional medicine for 30 years and the gut has been the number one
focus of our ability to really move diseases in a powerful way. And they used to call me Dr. C
every poop because I've done literally tens of thousands of stool tests and I've looked at all
the different ones. And you're looking at a moving target. You're looking at an ecosystem. And so,
we look at a lot of different biomarkers to assess what's going on in the gut. Is there adequate
pancreatic enzyme function? Looking at pancreatic elastase, are there absorption issues? Looking at
fecal fats? Are there inflammatory markers in there? For example, Calprotectin or eosinophil
protein X, which are standard markers to look at inflammation in the gut. What's your IGA levels,
your antibody levels? And then we look at indicators of dysregulated gut microbiome,
such as short chain fatty acids, which are essentially produced by good bacteria that are
the fuel for the gut and have anti-cancer properties, anti-inflammatory properties.
And those can be low like butyrate and we can see that. Then we look at sort of different microbiome
characteristics using DNA or PCR analysis through the micro RNAs. And that allows us to see, for
example, if there's low acromancia, which is a very important bacteria that regulates your biofilm,
that regulates immunity, that's linked to autoimmune disease and cardiometabolic diseases,
cancer treatment therapy risk. So we can modify those things. And then we look at culture, we look
at other kinds of testing for parasites. It's PCR testing. So there's a lot of things that we look at
and get a gestalt. It changed over time, but you can see if someone's got a good gut or
okay gut or a terrible gut. So if you take a patient who is both symptomatic and by some
consolation of tests has a quote unquote bad gut, what percentage of those are quote unquote fixable
by subtraction? So you take things out of their diet or addition, you add more of certain food
to their diet or the third choice would be intervention based where you have to use
sort of supplements and antibiotics or probiotics or things like that. So that's an oversimplified
look at this. But if there's three levers you have, which means take something out of their food,
add something to their food or add a different type of food or then use a bigger gun like a
supplement, how do those tools fit into this treatment? Well, functional medicine is a very
organized framework for addressing gut dysfunction called the 5R program. The first R is to remove,
remove things that shouldn't be there, whether it's foods that are triggering a problem like
gluten, which affects permeability or dairy, grains for some people, remove bad bugs. So if
you have a parasite, I mean, I just had a patient who had a common parasite. She had stomach issues
for 20 years. She was always waking up feeling like crap. I gave her a linear, which is an
anti-parasitic medication, six days she says she's never felt better. So sometimes you just need to
do that and maybe bacterial overgrowth you have, maybe there's yeast overgrowth. You need to address
that. And so that's the first step. The second step is to replace what might be missing. So fiber,
prebiotics, enzymes, various things that may be needing to support the system. And sometimes
that's just through food, but sometimes that's also supplements. Sure. You can take prebiotic
fibers and prebiotic foods like plantain and artichokes and all kinds of different foods.
And then re-inoculate, which would be provide probiotics where necessary. And that can be
through foods like fermented foods or can be through probiotic supplements. And those are,
that's still sort of a wild west, but there are things that up there that really work.
And then to replace what's missing. So maybe there's nutrients that the body needs to heal,
things like glutamine, vitamin A, fish oil, maybe even things like butyrate and replace things that
might be needed for healing the gut. Like polyphenols, for example, are a wonderful thing
you can get from food, pomegranate, cranberries, green tea, et cetera, that have powerful, great
effects on the microbiome that we didn't really appreciate. So we thought it was prebiotic and
probiotic, but it turns out the polyphenols in plant foods are super helpful for the gut microbiome.
And then the last R is to restore, which means to sort of restore your nervous system because
you need to sort of deal with the way in which your stress level and everything affects your gut
and your gut microbiome. You can get a leaky gut just from stress, for example. So working on all
those in a systematic way that's personalized is really the approach. There's no sort of,
oh, take this or do that, it's going to work. So bringing it back to what you started this point.
Yeah, we got down with the rabbit hole.
Yeah, well, it's such an interesting topic. You've laid out basically the enormous health
consequences of eating poorly. Six out of 10 Americans have a chronic disease, four out of
10 have two or more. In 10 years, 83 million Americans are not three or more, which is
bankrupting our country. And one in two Americans has prediabetes or type two diabetes. These
statistics are staggering. 75% of us are overweight. Most states now have 40% obesity
rates. I mean, when I graduated medical school, there wasn't a single state that had a 20%
obesity rate now. Everybody's got 30 or almost 40. These are massive things that are happening
at a scale that we've never seen in human history that we haven't been equipped to deal with,
that we haven't really thought of how to address, and it's like we're trying to scramble to fix it.
And you certainly in the book talk about how there are racial differences in terms of the
susceptibility to the bad policy, which we'll get to down the line. Is there also sort of racial
variability and discrepancy in the actual physiology in response to this? There's clearly
economic health disparities. Health disparities are a result of targeted marketing from the food
industry that are driving various problems, or obviously the food swamps and the food deserts
and food apartheid, all of that is true. But genetically, there's certain segments of the
population that are much more likely when they are in an abundance of sugar and flour
to get diabetes and obesity. And that includes Native Americans, probably the worst,
African Americans, Latinos, and of course, the people from the South Pacific, and even Indians
from India, Chinese, and Asians often are at much higher risk, even at lower body rates. So
this is really a global problem, and that's why we're seeing 80% of the world's type 2 diabetics
in the developing world. Is there any country or government in particular that seems more
attuned to this problem than the American government? Many, in fact, most. Chile, for
example, was seeing massive obesity rates in kids and adults, healthcare costs staggering for that
country. And again, we're inundated by all the processed food from the food industry and soda
industry. And it took a doctor who was elected to the Senate, who was vice president of the Senate,
and a doctor who was elected president, Michelle Bachelet, who was a pediatrician,
to stand up and say enough and put in a set of regulations to try to stop the onslaught of
these conditions on their population driven by the food industry. So they did a number of things.
One, they put in an 18% soda tax. Two, they put on warning labels on the front of bad food. So
on your Frosted Flakes cereal box, there's black warning labels. They eliminated any cartoon
characters from all the kids' food. So no Tony the Tiger, no Toucan Sam on Fruit Loops. They
eliminated any processed food from schools and they made the school lunches healthy. They
eliminated any advertising on junk food from six in the morning till 10 at night so kids wouldn't
see it. And then they measured these outcomes based on that and they see tremendous improvements. And
it was surprising to me. I talked to Barry Pockin, who's from UNC, who worked with them on developing
and Michael Bloomberg, I think gave him $30 million to assess the impact and so forth. So
they're studying this. And even more than the 18% soda tax, the restriction of food marketing
and the warning label and so forth had a fourfold increased benefit compared to the soda tax,
which is being heavily fought here. There's incredible opposition to any limiting
of marketing to kids. And the saying it's the breach of the First Amendment and free speech
and so forth. The First Amendment doesn't have to keep our responsibility to protect our children.
If a foreign nation was doing to our kids what the food industry is and our government is who
has policies, we'd go to war to protect our kids and we just sort of sit back and let this happen.
It's interesting. I'm not a constitutional expert, which would be such an overstatement.
I know nothing about the constitution. There is a constitution.
I know. My understanding of the First Amendment is provided the advertising is quote unquote
honest. It is constitutional. And that's a gray area because if you say fruit loops are part of
a healthy breakfast, how do we know that's honest? I can't help but think about the analogous
situation, which is tobacco. And what I think most people don't know, and it's possible I'm wrong,
but I believe everything I'm about to say is correct. Because at one point I knew this story well.
When the surgeon general came out with his declaration of the harm of tobacco, which was
in about the mid sixties, and that was the peak of smoking in the United States. I believe something
to the tune of 50, 55% of people over the age of 18 smoked cigarettes. At the time the surgeon
general came out and said definitively cigarettes are causing lung cancer. A number of things took
place that got us to where we are today, which is somewhere below 20% of people. Last time I looked,
it was about 18% of adults smoked. Yeah, a lawsuit is what worked. Well, but here's a big one. A big
one was the removal of advertising. But here's the part that I was surprised to learn. It was
voluntary on the part of tobacco. In other words, the tobacco industry was not banned from advertising.
What the policy makers said is the law is now that every time a tobacco commercial airs,
it must be followed by an anti-tobacco commercial. So they didn't ban tobacco, they added anti-tobacco.
So every time you have a McDonald's commercial, you say how bad the food is, it's going to kill you,
right? I think that's not a bad idea. Well, what's interesting is the anti-tobacco ads were so
devastating that the tobacco industry voluntarily withdrew its ads. They were getting hurt so bad
by the anti-tobacco ads that they said enough is enough. And that's to this day, we don't have
tobacco ads on television. So A, someone needs to fact check that to make sure I have that story
correct, but I believe it is correct. And secondly, if it is, it at least suggests another angle to
this problem, which is rather than go down the First Amendment fight, maybe great. Okay. I love
that idea. Keep all the commercials you want on, but we're going to come up with something different.
Now, of course, it's like a drug ad. You can eat this soda, but it's going to cause obesity,
diabetes, cancer, dementia, and kill you early. Fine. Maybe that's a good idea. Yeah. And of course,
tobacco is the easiest thing to demonize because you just show somebody a hole in their throat
after they've had throat cancer or a black lung or a corpse. I mean, there's so many grotesque
ways that you can make the point that are more difficult with food. A lip cigarette. Yeah, yeah,
exactly. But nevertheless, I've always found that to be a very powerful point because it's true that
eventually taxes were introduced into tobacco and they turned out to be quite powerful. Additional
measures in 1989 was also a big step when secondhand smoking became well enough understood that they
banned tobacco in airplanes and things like that. But I wonder how much of a playbook there is there
on tobacco to copy. Well, there is, but guess what? The food industry is copying tobacco's playbook
to slow or stall or stop this. And one of the most egregious things was something they've picked up
recently, which is from the tobacco playbook. There have been soda taxes that passed predominantly
in the 2016 election in California and other States. And the soda industry is a Vietnamese
opposed to this. They passed in California. They spent about $38 million avoiding these taxes
against these taxes. Bloomberg and the Arnold Foundation spent about 20 million and it didn't
pass. I mean, it did, taxes did pass and it freaked out the soda company. So the American Beverage
Association essentially went and tried subversive tactics. So they went to California where most of
these taxes were passed and they put in a ballot measure, which was designed to prohibit local
taxes unless there was a two thirds majority, meaning you couldn't fund your school, your police
department, your fire department, your cleanup, road cleanup, unless there was a two thirds majority.
That would hamper local governments dramatically. And they spent millions of dollars pushing this
ballot measure, even though it had nothing to do with food. And at the last minute before the
election, they went to Governor Brown, who's probably the most liberal governor in the history
of the United States, Governor Moonbeam. And they said, look, we'll pull this measure, but you have
to put in place a preemptive law that prohibits any future taxes on soda or junk food. And it
happened all behind closed doors, completely co-opted the government, impression them to do
something that they didn't want to do. And they're doing this in state after state after state. And
this is exactly what tobacco did. So we can say, oh, they're not bad actors are trying to do things
that good. They're making water, they're making low sugar beverages. They know exactly what they're
doing and they have an existential threat and they're trying to fight it in every way possible.
That's just one example. There's another funny example, which is an initiative called the Global
Energy Balance Network Gurn or something like this. Right. Yeah. Yeah. On a hot O'Connor, I believe
played a pretty important role at the New York times exposing this for what the sham it was.
Do you want to tell people a little bit about the Global Energy Balance Network? So the whole idea
of this is that energy balance is the mantra of the food industry. And what that means is all
calories are the same. Soda calories, broccoli calories, no difference. So it's just a matter
of balance, calories in, calories out, moderation, et cetera, et cetera. And so they essentially
run Apple bomb, who was one of the top BPs at Coca-Cola put together a strategy because you saw
the vilification of soda and all these horrible outcries against sugar that were unmet by enough
aggressive force from the sugar industry and the soda industry. And she said, look, let's start
with something called the Global Energy Balance Network. She found a bunch of scientists who she
could co-op, paid them lots of money, funded their research to actually promote the idea that all
calories are the same. Like James Hill, for example, who was part of an NIH study, legitimate
scientist, but completely co-opted and they funded about 20 million and they built the website. They
organized this messaging and the talking points and they did it all sort of behind the scenes.
And when there was discovery and so the FOIA Freedom of Information Act, it was a public
university, we got all the data. It was really clear how they were behind the scenes, manipulating
all this to fund millions of dollars of corrupt research to prove their point and tell a different
story. And then as soon as the New York Times article came out overnight, it was disbanded
saying it's run out of resources. I mean, come on, Coca-Cola has what billions and millions of dollars
over here. They have plenty of resources and the whole thing collapsed because of investigative
journalism. But it just goes to show how these food companies are co-opting scientists,
co-opting professional associations, co-opting social groups, co-opting the government, putting
forth front groups and spinning all kinds of misinformation in a very coordinated strategic
strategy to disrupt public opinion, to confuse the public and to allow their shenanigans to keep
going. Is the opposition to this industry that you can't fight this at the individual level? In
other words, it has to be solved structurally because of the economic disparity. Let me ask
the question another way. Why not focus all of the efforts on helping people understand so they can
make the informed choice, which is if you have to have a Coke, make it a diet Coke. That may not be
as good either. Yeah, but using that as an example, right? But in other words, do we really believe
that this has to be solved at the level that seems almost unwinnable, which is
fighting an unethical opponent with infinite resources? I mean, that's a very dangerous
combination. Yeah, well, look what happened to tobacco. I mean, think about this country.
But you don't need tobacco to live, right? The advantage that you would have as an anti-tobacco
crusade person is the ground is not muddied by the notion that tobacco is part of a group
called food that you need to live. Although it depends how you define food. Our Fruit Loops food,
I don't think so. I mean, they're a highly industrialized processed product. But they still
fit into this bucket of food. They do. And therefore they sort of they ride a little bit of the coattails
of they're still riding on the, hey, we're putting B vitamins in these things and they're fortified
and all this other sort of nonsense. So you're asking is do we need just a grassroots effort to
focus on individual choice and action or do we need a public policy change? Well, and I wouldn't
even ask it as either or because the obvious answer to that would be you could do both. I guess what
I'm getting at is would you be better off putting more effort into sort of the grassroots campaign?
It's complicated. When you think of the big changes that happened in policy in this country,
the abolition, I mean, there were a few people running people on the underground railroad and
pushing for abolition back in the early 1800s. And it took decades and decades for change. But
eventually, our entire agricultural and economic system collapse that was founded on slavery and
it was reimagined and rebuilt. And I think look at women's rights, same thing, gay rights, civil
rights, all those things are things that were really starting on the periphery through grassroots
movements, but had to push Congress to make different laws. And I think that's what has to
happen. But I think we have to be smart about it as well. I mean, yes, consumers make a difference.
That's why we're seeing General Mills commit a million acres to regenerative ag. It's why we're
seeing big companies nextly reformulating their products and why there's sustainable regenerative
ag initiatives at Danone. I mean, these companies are starting to see that the consumers want
different things and they're starting to shift their product lines. They're starting to shift
their focus on how their supply chain works and where they get and source their products to
regenerative agriculture. So I do believe that the individual has a huge impact through their
vote with what they're eating, their fork with their wallet, and of course, even with their vote
and their voice. And I think we don't use a ladder enough. That has to all happen. And unfortunately,
I do believe that individual choice matters. Yes, we can all have compost piles. We can have community
gardens. We can have a garden in our backyard. We can choose to eat, we generally meet. We can
be like you, Peter, and go hunting our wild deer. I mean, I'm jealous, but that alone is not enough
because there are structural problems that are not solvable unless we change how we grow food,
what we grow, how we process, distribute, market, sell, eat, and waste it. And if we don't deal with
every aspect along that food chain, we're really not going to solve this problem. And we haven't
really talked about it yet, but things like climate change are an increasingly important
part of the conversation about food. And that is something that's just not in the radar. Like,
how does fixing food fix climate? It does. It's actually one of the only ways to really reverse
climate change. Let's talk about that. Some people don't think climate change is real. They call it
weather. I mean, whatever you want to call it, there's stuff happening. We're having a million
acres flooded in the Midwest, cropland that's destroying farmers' livelihood. We're seeing
increasing weather patterns of hurricanes and wildfires in Australia and California. We're
seeing melting of 3 trillion tons of ice from the Antarctica. These are just undeniable facts.
Can I give you my two cents on this? Yeah. I think the term climate change, global warming,
were sort of in retrospect not the best ways to describe this phenomenon. And climate volatility
would have been a better way to have explained it because one, it's actually more accurate.
And two, it provides a better explanation for what you're describing. Because when you say
global warming is a problem, well, then how do you explain a record cold year?
It's the high highs, the low lows, and the frequency with which they're cycling,
both through hurricanes, fires, things like that. So I wish we could have gone back in time and said,
look, the problem is climate volatility. Yeah, it's instability. 2019 was the hottest year on
record rather than 2016 in human history. So all of us can feel it. We know it. And I think,
so the question is, why is it happening? And what's the cause of it? And clearly,
most people think it's fossil fuels and taking up all the carbon that was stored in the earth's
crust and burning it and releasing that carbon through fossil fuels. And that's a big part of it,
maybe a third, but half of it comes from our food system through all sorts of different mechanisms.
One, deforestation, you lose the carbon capture from the trees. The soil destruction from
destructive agriculture, which we have, which essentially is a method of industrial growing of
food that tills the soil, which disrupts the normal organic matter, causes soil erosion,
releases carbon, the environment. It also, when you look at the soil as an issue itself,
it's probably the biggest cause and the biggest solution to fixing climate change. And most people
don't think about that. They think about oil, not soil, but a third to 40% of all the carbon
in the atmosphere today that's causing climate volatility is from the loss of soil. That's a
staggering amount. Explain how that's the case. Yeah, well, the soil, when it's alive and has
living matter and carbon in the soil, organic matter, which is carbon, it can hold three times
the amount of carbon that's in the atmosphere today, which is a trillion tons of carbon.
It can hold three trillion tons. The UN estimated that if we take two million of the
five million degraded hectares of land around the world and we intensively use regenerative
agriculture, which I'll explain in a minute, and restore the soil, we could stop climate change and
delay the progression for about 20 years. And it would cost $300 billion, which is essentially what
we pay every year for diabetes in America through Medicare. And it's basically the amount of budget
for the total global military spend for just two months or 60 days. So this is a solvable problem.
And the reason that the soil is such an issue is that it basically takes when the grasses are on
there and the plants are on there, it sucks the carbon out of the environment. Can you explain
the difference between soil and dirt? Yeah, soil is alive. Soil has all kinds of bugs in it,
mycorrhizal fungi, it has all kinds of bacteria, it has all kinds of carbon in it from the plants,
and it holds a huge amount of water. For example, for every 1% organic matter, it can hold 27,000
gallons of water, which would prevent floods and droughts, which it does and creates more
resilient farms. Explain that again. When you have soil, it's like a sponge. So when it rains,
instead of the rain running off or running through, gets stored like a sponge in the soil
so that you don't need to irrigate, that you don't have to worry about floods and droughts.
Now, the reason we had so much of these floods and these flooded farm fields in the Midwest was
because these soils are just dead and you have to do more and more fertilizer. So we're killing
the soil by using fertilizer, by pesticides, herbicides, tilling, not using cover crops,
not using crop rotations, not using animals in an integrated way to actually create more soil.
And everything we're doing is just destroying the soil. When you have a live soil, when you have
the ability of these plants to suck out carbon dioxide, because they breathe carbon dioxide,
that's what plants do. They breathe out oxygen, which we breathe, and it's a vicious, I mean,
a beautiful virtuous cycle. And the carbon dioxide from the atmosphere gets pulled through
the plants into the soil and stays there. And you can build soil simply by using this technology
and integrating animals that poop and pee. So I don't think I was aware of that. I'll put my
ignorance on full display. I always assumed that the majority of the carbon that came in,
that the plant brought in through the photocell, was for carbon fixation, which was creating
bio matter. So in other words, carbon and oxygen are coming in the form of carbon dioxide. That
carbon is being fixated to other carbons. That's how we make hydrocarbons within the plants.
Yeah, carbohydrates.
That's right. And then the oxygen is being released. But I didn't realize that there was
any carbon dioxide stored in soil.
Yeah. And if you look at the mechanism, it goes into the plant, but it also goes into the roots.
And so you've got this incredible root system and you've got micro isofungi that are fed off.
I see. So you're just saying the hydrocarbon within the roots of the plant is the storage,
not in the soil per se, not in the actual dirt and bacteria.
No, no. Then it gets eaten by the bacteria, eaten by this massive micro isofungi, and it creates
a lot of necrotic dead, but like actually organic matter. It's an incredibly rich living organism,
and dirt is just dead. Dirt doesn't hold water. It doesn't have much carbon in it. It doesn't have
much nutrients. And in order to actually to extract the nutrients from the plants,
you have to have organic matter, which allows this and bacteria and all these micro isofungi,
which make the nutrients in the soil available to the plant. And since we are growing food in dirt,
we see 50% less nutrient density of even healthy food. Like broccoli has less minerals than it did
50 years ago. So you have all these complicated factors that are driving the destruction of our
soil. Fertilizer is another one. I don't think people really understand the fertilizer story.
There's 400 billion pounds of fertilizer used everywhere in the world. It's a seven-fold
increase over the last 40 years because they're two thirds as effective. The way you make fertilizer
is a chemically intensive process that uses energy. It's one of the biggest utilizers of energy and
the number one utilizer of fracking produced natural gas, which I didn't even know. So when
you look at the fertilizers, they use more natural gas than Exxon. And in order to make the gas,
they use more fertilizer than Exxon produces. So they use more energy than Exxon produces.
Yes, they use more natural gas than Exxon uses. So the Yara and Mosaic, these big fertilizer
companies are making fertilizer using this intensive energy process that needs natural gas.
When you frack, you actually release methane from these methane leaks that come out of these
fracking wells. Recently, there's one in Ohio that you could see from space. And that actually
is about a quarter of all methane-releasing gas in the environment today, which is as much as
factory farm cows. And that's from growing plants. Do you know what percent of, I don't know the
numbers anymore, but there was a day when the United States was consuming 20 million barrels
of oil and oil equivalent per day. It's probably a bit less than that today. Do you know what amount
of that is in the production, transport, consumption of food? Oh, yeah, sure. One fifth
of all our oil consumption is for the food system. That's more than all cars, planes, boats,
transportation combined. So it's a staggering amount of oil and part of it is-
It can't be combined though, because those-
No, combined. All transportation combined-
Is less than one fifth of our total oil consumption?
Mm-hmm. Because a lot of it's industry and other things. So yeah, it's pretty staggering.
And so the fracking-
So 20% of our energy utilization is to make fertilizer, deliver seed, harvest-
Yeah, pesticides, herbicides, all come from fossil fuels.
Stribute.
So the fertilizer starting gets even worse because once you, now you have all the gas you're using,
the methane release from that, when you put on the soil, it kills the soil.
And sorry, the purpose of fertilizer is to provide-
Nitrogen.
Generally nitrogen phosphorus, right?
Nitrogen, yes, nitrogen to the plants.
So again, just taking a step back for the biochemistry understanding of this.
I think plant biology by the way is so incredible.
Great.
Because I don't think people appreciate the significance of carbon fixation,
how complicated a chemical reaction it is to take carbon and join it to carbon like a plant can do.
So, I mean, it's very energy intensive, which is why it requires sunlight.
So you've got this photosynthetic thing. But basically plants need carbon,
which they're getting from the air. They need nitrogen and phosphorus,
which they're getting from their soil and they need energy and water,
which they're getting from the environment. And then they make biomass.
Yeah, exactly.
So the fertilizer is where we give them the nitrogen and the phosphorus, correct?
Yes, but most of the fertilizer that was growing plants historically came from
either nitrogen fixing plants like the legumes or from the animals.
The reason we have 50 feet of topsoil in some areas in this country,
150 years ago, is because of all millions of bison running around.
There was like bison and elk and all these ruminants that were running around in big herds,
chomping things down, moving on to the next spot, peeing and pooping, digging the thing,
saliva makes the grass grow. So it's this beautiful symbiotic system that built
literally tens of feet of topsoil. And it's not that we have too many cows, it's how we're growing.
I mean, I think it's worth pausing for a moment to explain for folks.
I'll try to do it quickly. There was a day, believe it or not, like 10 years ago when
I was obsessed with understanding agriculture. So everything I'm saying is 10 years old.
So you can correct me if I'm wrong. But basically, if you use corn as the model system,
and you look at the only metric that really matters, which is bushels per acre per year,
yield, it all comes down to yield. Basically, from the Civil War to about the end of World War II,
if you look at crop yield and you see the plot, it was about 20 bushels per acre per year.
So every acre could produce 20 bushels of corn per year. Obviously, it fluctuated quite a bit
from year to year, but it was a largely horizontal jagged line from about the end of the Civil War
to the end of World War II. And then something really interesting happens. At the end of World
War II, that line just turns up and just almost in a linear fashion rises to 200 bushels per acre
per year. And I think what a lot of people erroneously assume is, oh, it's the goddamn GMO.
Well, actually, no, not at all. GMO didn't even kick in until that number was 160.
It was nitrogen-based fertilizer, crop rotation, industrial farming, meaning the ability to actually
use machines to not just have a farmer out there doing something. It was selective breeding,
crossing. So it was a bunch of things that came in. Then basically, GMO has put a 10%
plus up on that from a yield perspective. Maybe, maybe. That's debatable.
So yeah, anyway, the point here is this process really began in earnest about 70 years ago.
And prior to 70 years ago, it's been remarkably flat. So of course, this goes back to something
you said earlier, which is post-World War II, we had to figure out how to feed a bunch of people.
And 20 bushels per acre per year was not cutting it. We're now 10 times the yield,
as you're pointing out, at quite a cost.
At quite a cost, yeah.
So the question then is, I mean, you talk about in your book how we're wasting a third of the food
produced. So we don't really need 2200 bushels per acre per year if we stop wasting. Have you
figured out or at least calculated what you think the sweet spot is, which is if you were to back
off the aggressive yield measures, not waste, how much of the benefit could you recapture that was
there when, for example, we used animals as our fertilizer?
That's right. There's sort of a fallacy in the idea that we can't produce the same amount of
food using regenerative methods. I think that's been disproven.
Do you believe, in other words, there is 200 bushels per acre per year using regenerative methods?
Well, let me just share a quick story. Now I want to share this story and I'm going to come back to
the fertilizer and talk about the rest of the different aspects that are causing climate change.
I think people need to understand that. There's a guy named Gabe Brown who was a North Dakota farmer,
5,000 acre farm, devastated by hail, devastated by weather, and was about to go bankrupt and then
decided he wanted to try regenerative agriculture. And many years ago, he started it. And now he says
he's built 29 inches of soil. He uses no chemical inputs, makes his own fertilizer from the animals
and the plants that he plants, the nitrogen fixing plants. He produces more food, better
quality food, and makes 20 times as much money as his neighbor. So in terms of productivity,
a regenerative farm is far more productive. And I think there's this fallacy that we need
green revolution, we need industrial agriculture to feed the world. That's really been disproven.
And I think that's the mantra of Big Ag. It's the mantra of Monsanto and now, which is bare,
and a lot of these big agrochemical companies that are trying to push their products on the
marketplace. And so I think we have to sort of be smart about going, wait a minute, it's not just
about trying to sort of go back to some old form of agriculture that isn't going to produce the
yields. No, I think this is not what was done. This is a sort of a new way of thinking. It combines
organic, but it also goes beyond that. And the reason is it sort of interrupts all these problems
that are actually driving climate change. So we talked about the fertilizer. Once you put it on
the soil, it damages the soil and it releases nitrous oxide, which is 300 times more potent
of greenhouse gas than carbon dioxide. So you're getting all the fracking, you're getting the
destruction of the soil on top of that. It's like a triple threat. As a backend side effect,
all that runs off into the river streams and lakes and goes into the oceans and has created dead
zones in 400 areas around the world the size of Europe. There's one the size of New Jersey in the
Gulf of Mexico that kills 212,000 metric tons of fish every year. It's a lot of gumbo and sushi.
And there's 400 of those around the world that are feeding 500 billion people. So this is what
fertilizer does alone. And then of course you have deforestation, the soil erosion, so forth.
And why is that not a problem when the fertilizer is coming from an organic nitrogen source versus
an inorganic one? Well, of course, right. So an organic nitrogen source poop goes in there and
nitrogen fixing plants and it stays in the soil as opposed to running off through this degraded soil
into the river stream. So is the issue the fertilizer or the nature of the soil that can't
hold the fertilizer? It's both. In order to get dirt to produce plants, you need to put on huge
amounts of fertilizer. Like I said, the increase in the use of fertilizer is seven fold compared
to 40 years ago. So if I'm understanding what you're saying, the problem with fertilizer
is it allows us to be lazy and rely less on healthy soil and because you can dump fertilizer
on dirt and eventually grow. Beating a dead horse. But if you actually want the healthiest soil
possible, you will get your nitrogen contribution from an element that stays within the ecosystem
of the soil because it's a part of it. And therefore you're not going to have the runoff.
Is that accurate? Exactly. And so you've got deforestation, you've got damage to soil and all
the ways we talked about and you've got transportation, refrigeration, processing,
distribution, those all cost energy and then food waste, which is a big cost. So how do you estimate
that? That is a staggering number that a third of our food is wasted. That is just what the sort of
conventional assessments are around food waste in the world. It's not in my opinion, it's what the
UN says. But I mean, what's the methodology by which one calculates that? Good question. I don't
know the answer to that question, but that's a good question. But I think it's a generally
accepted thing. It's between 30 to 40%. It's different for different reasons in the developing
world versus here. We throw out food in our kitchen, they have lose food in the food chain
because of lack of storage and transportation, refrigeration. So you've got all these causes
which add up to about 50% of climate change. And by shifting how we grow food and focusing on
regenerative agriculture, which specifically means regenerating soil and ecosystems, in other words,
increasing the amount of organic matter in the soil, increasing water retention, using crop
rotations, using cover crops so there's no bare soil, so using animals in very specific
grazing patterns that mimics nature to actually intensively graze the land and move the animals
around to actually stimulate the growth of the plants, stimulate the soil and so forth. So
all those techniques could be easily applied and are done in literally millions of acres around
the world with great benefit and high productivity and mitigating climate at the same time.
What's the obstacle to it? The obstacle is you've got a $15 trillion food industry that's
dependent on the products of industrial farming and is actually selling the seeds, it's selling
the fertilizer, it's selling the pesticides and herbicides, it's selling all the...
Is it the convenience? For example, when you talk about the gentleman you alluded to earlier
who basically switched, how many acres does he have?
5,000.
5,000 acres and he switched over to fully regenerative. Sounds like he's increased his
profitability.
Dramatically and resilience.
Has that increase in profitability come through higher price, higher volume or lower cost?
I mean, these farmers lose an average in this country about $1,600 a year. That's their net,
is minus $1,600 a year.
Per acre.
No, per farm. Like if you're a farmer, the average farmer, according to the USDA and other statistics,
loses money every year. He's making money because...
On the subsidies.
What do you mean?
Is the only reason he can make a living because of the subsidy?
This guy in North Dakota?
No, no, no, no. The farmer who's losing $1,600 a year.
Yeah, I mean, they have write-offs and subsidies and so forth. I mean,
Trump just bailed them out for $20 billion, which is almost as much as all the subsidies
that exist in the country annually, which is a lot of money. And the farmers struggle and they're
caught between basically the big ag and the government. The government's saying, you need
to produce these foods, here's the money to support you to do it. But that money then goes
to buy the seed from Monsanto or the glyphosate from Monsanto or the other agrochemicals and
fertilizer from Yara. So they're taking... They're just sort of the pass-through of the money from
the government to big ag and the industry. And that's the problem. Whereas this guy,
Gabe Brown in North Dakota, he doesn't have to buy seed. He doesn't have to buy fertilizer.
He doesn't have to buy glyphosate. He doesn't have to buy pesticides. He doesn't eat a lot
of irrigation because his soil holds so much water. He has a diverse ecosystem of animals and plants
that he can grow and sell and make a profit that's more than the others. And how long would
it take someone like him to make that transition? So it's about three to five years, depending. So
we need a massive effort for supporting and transforming our agricultural system to a
regenerative ag. And there's groups that are working on this like Kiss the Ground and
Carbon Underground that are consulting with governments around the world to help them
understand this. And the UN gets this. There's a huge report called Climate Change and Land Use
that came out in August 2019, which laid these problems out and how we are degrading our land
that's contributing to climate. And the solution is multifaceted, but includes restoring these
degraded lands. And people say, oh, we can't do this at scale. It's too expensive. The truth is,
if you look at all the conservation land in this country, if you look at all the conservation land
in this country, if you look at degraded lands that aren't being used properly, if you look at
land that's used to grow corn and soy for factory farm animals, that could be converted. And we
can literally double the amount of cows we produce every year on regenerative farms than we do now.
Not that we should, not that we need all that meat, but I'm just saying the argument that it's
not scalable, that it's not cost effective, it's just not true. And the truth is you can say you
can be vegan, fine, but we should all grow more plants. But there's a lot of land on the planet,
about 40% of the arable land, you can't grow food for humans. So these animals upcycle
inedible food and put it into a form that we can eat that's extremely nutrient dense. There's a
beautiful symbiotic ecosystem here. And you don't have to eat the animals if you don't want to,
I don't care, but they're needed for the regeneration of soil.
Who has done the most comprehensive life cycle assessment on this transformation as you describe
it? So how many acres are there of agricultural land in the United States, approximately?
Oh, good, Lord, I should know that. I don't, it's a lot of millions.
It's a lot of millions.
So if you take that number and on a per acre basis do the calculation of over five years,
everybody transitions to a more regenerative, appropriately rotated, covered ag position.
How many tons of CO2 can be sequestered per acre under those scenarios?
A lot. So the book called Drawdown is a wonderful explanation of the top solutions that exist today
that don't need to be invented that can draw down carbon out of the environment. And collectively,
the food solutions, Paul Hawken, yeah, he's a good friend of mine.
Yeah, actually, I'd like to interview him. He looks like someone who would be interesting
to interview on this topic.
Yeah, he's coming up with a new book called Regenerate, which is how do we regenerate
our health, regenerate the soil and so forth. And unexpectedly found that the food solutions
were the top solutions to fixed climate change that aren't really being implemented. And it's
been estimated that this much investment in billions results in this much value in trillions
and it reduces carbon by this many gigatons. And it's all in the book. So the calculation
has been done, the analysis has been done. And I think it's been estimated by some that we could
draw down anywhere from 30% to 100% of all the carbon that's been released since the Industrial
Revolution if we can scale this up. What's the biggest counter argument to this?
There isn't any. I mean, I think the argument is we need to have industrial agriculture to
feed the world. That's the mantra. It's like calories are all the same. It's that same mantra
that isn't science-based, but that suits the needs of agrochemical and agribusiness.
But there's no one that's got a pushback argument that says, no, these calculations are overly
optimistic and you would introduce a new problem if you do this.
Of course, there are people all the time who are trying to refute this. And whether it's
agribusiness or even the vegan communities come out and say regenerative agriculture is not going
to solve a problem. People like Pat Brown from Impossible Foods has been really clearly stating
that we need to get rid of all meat, that even regenerative meat doesn't work in terms of
protecting the environment. And he quotes various studies that were, I do analyze in my book Food
Fix, talk about how they're flawed and actually miss a lot of the data. So I think it does take
time to create regenerative agriculture. It does take effort. But once you do it, there's an
incredible value chain that gets put in place. And there are countries that are understanding
this. We take out of the earth a lot of natural capital, about $125 trillion a year of resources
and soil and everything else that we steal from the earth. We don't put it back and it's running
out. How much did you say? 125 trillion. And the global GDP is probably 80 to 90 trillion.
I was about to say that's more than the global GDP.
Yeah, which is about 80 to 90, right? It's more than that every year. And there's a lot of people
working on this. For example, there's a private equity company called Farmland LP that's buying
up conventional farms, converting them to regenerative agriculture and moving those farms
from single digit profits to high double digit. Their first fund had a 67% return. And when they
look at the benefit they provide to the environment, we call ecosystem services. That's the $125
million of ecosystem services, the natural capital we borrow. They add $21 million of value on their
farms versus a similar amount of conventional farms would actually steal $8 million of value
from the earth. And countries like Costa Rica are paying for ecosystem services for their farmers
or paying them to produce more soil to actually conserve water, to increase biodiversity, which
we haven't even talked about, which is a whole other topic.
I want to get to it. Let's see. Talk to me a little bit about, it's funny, Pat Brown was one
of my professors in medical school. Oh, geez. Okay. So I mean, I don't know if a lot of people
realized what a prominent scientist Pat was. And if you look at the type of work Pat did in the 90s,
I mean, it's not inconceivable. He could have gone down the path of a Nobel prize.
Yeah. I mean, they're a smart guy, but the challenge is you don't have to vilify
people wanting to do regenerative agriculture. Yeah. And I was just going to say, I don't know
anything about Pat. I know very little about their philosophy around why they've created the,
is it the impossible burger? There's two of these out there. One's-
Beyond burger, beyond meat and impossible burger.
Okay. And I can never get the two of them straight, but-
I mean, one is pea based, which is the beyond meat and one is GMO soy based, which is-
And that's up the GMO one must be Pat's.
If you look at the light, you last about a life cycle analysis, Qantas, which is an
independent life cycle analysis company did an analysis of the impossible burger compared to
regenerally raised beef burger. And the impossible burger was far better than a
conventional factory farm burger, but it added three and a half kilos of carbon for every burger
you ate. Which one did?
The impossible burger.
So say that again.
So the impossible burger was better than a factory farm burger by far,
but it still added three and a half kilos of carbon to the environment for every burger.
A regenerally raised burger, including methane, everything, all the inputs,
took out three and a half kilos of carbon. Meaning you'd have to eat
one regenerally raised beef burger to offset the carbon emissions of a impossible burger.
So I'm not against plant-based meats, but I think we can't overstate the importance of-
And what, by comparison, what was the factory farm burger? Do you remember how much carbon was added?
Three and a half kilos of carbon were removed-
No, no, no. Sorry, the factory farm-
The factory, oh, it was a lot. It was like 50 or it was a lot. It was significantly less.
But still, it's not the only answer. When you think about scaling up impossible burgers on a
GMO monocrop soy field using tons of glyphosate, which has all sorts of harmful consequences,
causing soil erosion to the way we farm, damaging the waterways, damaging everything else. I mean,
just it doesn't even add up, right? So let's do it right.
So let's talk a little bit about GMO. This is a loaded topic.
Again, I think people don't understand what it means. And that's sort of, I want to talk about
it, but I also want to just put it in context for people so that we understand what GM means
and why it came about. So we go back to the 1940s, we had growing old maize on 20 bushels
per acre per year. Well, we got to remember that used to be something called Tia-cente.
That was like this little tiny, silly crop that was the size of our finger. And it had like four
little kernels on it. That's where corn came from. So I was explaining this to my kids the
other day, because we were, my kids are obsessed with gardening and stuff. And I was saying, look,
there's four things about a plant that really matter. If you're planting crops, yield matters.
How much do you have? Product profile. I mean, is it good to eat or not? Yeah. Or in the case of
Tia-cente, it had a lousy product profile because it just had four kernels on it. Harvestability.
The other problem with Tia-cente is the little kernels would always fall off it. You actually
wanted the kernels to stay on the thing so you could harvest the whole plant. And crop protection.
Can you keep it away? Can you keep the critters away from it? So GMO has had by far its greatest
impact in crop protection. The BT insertion is basically what allowed Roundup Ready crops to be
resistant to glyphosate. We'll use the terms glyphosate. The BC is for the cotton, right?
Oh yeah. Yeah. It's pesticide resistant. Yeah, pesticide resistant. So there's a glyphosate
resistance that, and we'll use, like I said, we'll use glyphosate and Roundup interchangeably.
But if you could basically genetically modify a plant to be resistant to the thing that you use
to kill the pest, you can use that thing liberally, right? I mean, for all the promise of GMO,
basically the only two inventions have been the BT pesticides. The BT and the glyphosate resistance.
Yeah. That's it. And that's led to massive increases in the use of pesticides.
The first point to make here is most of the yield gains came long before this. So obviously you do
get some yield gain with crop protection. So there's an overlap, but virtually all of it came
before this. All of the harvestability, to my knowledge, there's been no GM addition to
harvestability and no GM addition to product profile. Although some might argue that it's
low hanging fruit. For example, I know Monsanto was very aggressively looking at trying to
engineer tomatoes that could grow in brackish water. And that way you would obviously open up
the ability to grow it in areas that where you don't have fresh water. Okay. So with all of that
said, the next question for the person to be thinking about that you're going to take us through
is there are at least two things about GM that could be problematic. The first is it could be
problematic that you are eating an organism that now has a gene that looks different from the
gene that we evolved to consume it. In other words, it now makes different proteins that it
didn't make that are foreign. And cause food is information. So how is that different information
affecting your biology and how's it regulating the different body functions? I don't think we
know much about that. The second thing that could be harmful about GM is that by its very success,
it enables the use of chemicals in a higher concentration than you would be able to use them
in the absence of GM. And we'll use Roundup or glyphosate as the poster child for that.
Can you talk through both of those and what the state of the evidence is for the harm of GM?
Because it should be noted that what you're about to say is that the backdrop or stands at odds with
what the USDA would tell us, what the National Association of Scientists would tell us, which is
GMO is safe. Feel free to consume it liberally. And so tell us where you think that might be
questionable. Well, there's a bunch of issues there. First is it's a large uncontrolled experiment
on humanity. Just like Crisco was invented in 1911 as this great new invention was in our food supply
for, I don't know, 80 or 90 years more before people were like, wait a minute, this isn't good
for us. It's killing hundreds of thousands of people a year. Let's get it out. So we don't know.
I think there's animal studies that looks concerning. There's various issues. I think
in terms of the use of these chemicals, there's two issues there. One is the plants are
increasingly mutating to be resistant to these substances. So you need more pesticides and more
glyphosate to do the same job. So there's all these weeds that are becoming resistant to glyphosate
that they're trying to fight. And then that's a problem because we're using more and more of
these chemicals. Europe followed a different path. It didn't allow GMO foods, didn't allow any of
that. And so what the comparative analysis of agriculture in the US versus Europe was no
difference in yields and far less use of pesticides and herbicides. It sort of didn't fulfill its
promise of yields and decreased use of chemicals. It was transient. I believe there was a transient
reduction in pesticide use until we started to see resistance. Is that correct? Yeah. And we're
using more and more of these chemicals. And glyphosate is 70% of the agrochemicals used on
the planet. It's increasingly being linked to harmful human effects. So forget about the
insertion of the gene as an issue. We know that these chemicals are harmful to this. Do we know
this? This is an important point. Yeah. I mean, aside from the litigation, which is not a scientific
judgment, it's a traditional judgment, but there's 14,000 lawsuits around glyphosate. There's been
billion dollar settlements. A friend of mine's a lawyer is involved with those lawsuits. He told
me that on Discovery, they found that the Trump administration said to Monsanto, now bear, we have
your back. And the EPA recently is trying to shut down any further lawsuits on glyphosate,
which is fascinating because it's sort of disclosed emails. And I think the effects on animal studies
are really clear. I just read a study in epigenetics in glyphosate where they looked at
interventional studies on rats, where they looked at giving the generation zero glyphosate and
infected their grand rats in multiple ways through prostate disease, cancer, various things.
But we've seen this before, Mark. I mean, we've seen lots of things where in the lab,
they're using doses that are significantly higher than the human exposure and or laboratory animals
behave differently than humans. Okay, fine. But are we willing to take that risk? I know it's
another study where glyphosate disrupts the microbiome in significant ways in animals. And
the dose that's in one impossible burger is 110 times the dose that was used in the animal studies
to totally disrupt the microbiome of the rats. But do we know how bioavailable it is and how
much it remains? Well, it's on the food. I mean, I try to eat organic. I try to eat non-GMO. Like I
travel, I'm not perfect. And I did my urine test to look at my glyphosate levels. And I was shocked.
I have a 50th percentile glyphosate in my urine. How do we do this test? You could pee in a bucket
and you send it into the lab. Great Plains Lab has this test available and you can check your
glyphosate levels. I was shocked. And I think most of us are sort of walking toxic dumps. And if you
looked at average fat biopsy of a human, it's full of DDT, dioxin, pesticides. It's pretty
bad. So I think we are still in an uncontrolled experiment. So your view is basically to take the
precautionary principle, which is look, we may never know this definitively. There's enough
suggestion that this could be harmful through animal models or other things like that. I mean,
for example, I mean, again, I'm just, I'm pushing back not because I don't necessarily agree with
you on a personal level and make a lot of the same choices myself. You're not sprinkling glyphosate
on your salads. You know, I stopped a couple of weeks ago. I used, I just, I love the taste of glyphosate.
You're like putting it all over your lawn. But again, I always think it's important to sort of
at least let people understand when something is where our level of confidence is very high versus
modest, but there's a precautionary approach to take out of it. In other words, I feel much more
comfortable saying tobacco is causally responsible for lung cancer than I feel saying glyphosate is
causally responsible for human disease. I just don't, I just haven't been convinced by the data.
If it was the only way to grow food, fine. We deal with the risk. It's not, it's not the best way.
It's not the most effective way. And there is potential risk. And there's real concern about
our industrial agricultural system on the earth and soil biodiversity. And also,
I sort of interrupted you when you were about to make a point about biodiversity.
That was something I learned recently. Yeah, it's an important issue. But before I get to that,
I just want to finish this thought about how this industrial system has sort of usurped
small farmholders, which are the majority of farmers that feed the majority of the world.
And these farmers are getting squeezed by these big ag companies are coming in and saying they're
going to improve their livelihood, but then forced them to buy their seed, forced them to buy their
chemicals. And there's increasing suicides and terrible economic consequences from these
farmers around the world because they're not able to maintain a livelihood doing what they're doing.
So it's not just that it's an issue around health. It's also an issue around squeezing a lot of the
people who do grow most of the food in the world. So it's another issue I talked about in the book.
Before we leave that then, do you know what the median farm is in the United States
in terms of acreage? I don't. I did know, but I don't, I can't keep all the facts in my head.
And what is approximately most farmers in the world, it's like less than five acres is most of
the farmers in the world that feed most of the world. Does that include the United States?
No. We're more industrial. Yeah. More industrial. Yeah. For sure. I mean,
either less and less farms for you and for farmers, it's increasing all the time, bigger and bigger
farms. I mean, girl, but said it under Nixon, go big or go home. In doing the research for your
bookmark, did you spend any time with these farmers and did you sense in them a degree of
dissatisfaction or let down with this promise of big ag that came about 20 years ago?
Oh my God. Yeah. I think more and more farmers are thinking about this. There was an article
in Time Magazine where all the Democratic candidates in Iowa were going out of the farms
and the farmers were like, look, our livelihoods are being destroyed. We're having floods. We're
not able to grow food. The system isn't working. We want to explore regenerative agriculture. So
it's definitely happening, not because they're hippies who want to go back to the land. It's
happening just from an economic imperative and the way to restore and save their farms.
But do farmers feel captive now to Monsanto and Pioneer and these other companies?
They do. They have a system and they don't have a way to get out of it. So they're in a vicious
cycle. They've got all this capital and their equipment. They're stuck in this vicious cycle
of growing the same crops and they have no way out. So we do need a bridge for these people and we do
need mechanisms through government and private equity and others to actually help fund the
transition. I think, like I said, the UN said $300 billion, boom, we could solve the problem
of climate change and give us 20 years more runway to solve the bigger issues.
So it's a massive effort that could actually transform our quality of our food, quality of
our soils, save our water, increase biodiversity, which we'll talk about, and so many of our global
problems just starting at the seed. So back to biodiversity. So what that means is that we talk
about extinction of species, but it's not just some frog in the Amazon. We've lost 90% of our
edible plant species. Basically 60% of our calories comes from corn and wheat and rice and soy,
and mostly from 12 species. We've lost 90% of our edible plant species, half of all our livestock
species. There's a lot of weird animals all over the place and you travel to foreign countries,
you see these weird cows and weird pigs and weird goats and they all look different. Now they're
all the same that we produce in this country. And we have lost 75% of our pollinator species,
which our agriculture depends, which Einstein said, if we lose bees from the face of the earth,
humans have four years left to live, which may be true or not, but it's an existential threat.
Butterflies, pollinators all damaged also by these pesticides and chemicals that are indiscriminate
in what they kill. They were basically nerve gases that were produced in World War I and II that were
factories retooled to produce agrochemicals. That's what the bombs were. I mean, how Timothy
McVeigh bombed in Oklahoma, that building was through going to a farm store and buying nitrogen
fertilizer and turning into a bomb. That's where it actually came from. So these chemicals that
we use in the soil, the methods of farming destroy the ecosystems, both from all those,
but also the biodiversity of the soil, the organism, the soil that are so critical,
the mycorrhizal fungi, the bacteria, the nematodes, the worms, all these different animals that live
in the soil that are necessary to actually create food and to create sustainable agriculture. And
so I think we're sort of asleep to the idea that we're sort of running out of soil, running out of
these biodiverse animals that are essential for our health and our survival. I mean, coral reefs,
I mean, with climate change, we're destroying all the coral reefs. And again, 500 billion people
depend on these coral reefs for food. So how would one go about moving the needle on this?
Well, I'm trying, I'm trying. So I wrote the book Food Fix, How to Save Our Health, Our Economy,
Our Communities, and Our Planet, one by at a time in order to lay out the problem and lay out the
solutions. And they're multifaceted. They're what citizens can do, they're what can happen in
business innovation, like I mentioned. We're going to come back and talk about an example around food
waste. And they're what policymakers need to do. And there needs to be the political will, but it's
really tough. So can we start at the bottom of that? And let me ask you another couple of
questions. What does organic really mean when it comes to plant or meat? If a person says,
okay, Mark, you've definitely convinced me that I want to be more mindful of what I'm buying.
Let's just assume that this is a person who has the economic flexibility to make the food choices
that might even increase their budget on groceries. So first of all, what does it mean when you go to
the grocery store and you see two boxes of strawberries, one's organic, one's not?
Well, organic is a certification that's delivered by the government that means no antibiotics,
no pesticides, no herbicides, and has to be certified that it's clean of all of that. However,
it doesn't certify the method of growing the food. So Michael Pollan, his book, Omnivore's
Lemma, talked about industrial organic. So if you have these massive monocrop lettuce fields,
you're doing tillage, you're not doing cover crops, you're not doing crop rotations,
you're also not super helping the soil. It's better than industrial farming, but it's not
fully regenerative. Regenerative is a method of farming that actually includes organic,
but goes beyond it. And there is now a regenerative organic certification, which you can look up,
and I talk about in my book. But the chemicals and the pesticides that we consume have an impact on
our health. It's been estimated that pesticide exposure just in children is responsible for
an average loss of seven IQ points or 41 million IQ points in kids. So there's a lot of brain power
that's killed, and not to mention how many per kid. I think it's like seven IQ points. There's
literally millions of pounds of these pesticides and herbicides that are in our food supply and
our water. And some plants have more than others. So I'm on the board of the Environmental Working
Group, and they produce a really great guide called the Dirty Dozen and the Clean 15. So you can
look at that list, and if you're having economic issues or whatever, you can say, well, strawberries
are the worst thing I could buy if they're not organic. Whereas, you know, banana or an avocado,
maybe not a big deal if it's not organic. So you can look at that list and go,
I'm going to save money by buying organic of the things that are the worst contaminated,
and I can cheat on the other ones that are not. And it's part of that because in the case of
bananas and avocado, you're eating what's inside and not outside. Whereas in the strawberry,
it's like got this surface that you collect it all. Celery is terrible. Never have anything
but organic celery, for example. In meat, besides not using hormones in the animals and not giving
them antibiotics, is there anything else that comes in the distinction of organic meat?
Again, it's not using the inputs that are chemical inputs that are on the corn that you have or the
soil that they have. So that's good. But again, it doesn't mean that they couldn't be fed organic
corn that's still grown in ways that are destroying the soil. So we really have to sort of think more
nuanced about what that means. That's why regenerative is sort of organic plus, you know,
it's like a whole next level. How ubiquitous is that regenerative organic label? It's not.
It's not. It's not. It's not even a label yet. There's just a proposal for a regenerative organic
certification. And yet there are farms who are doing this, and there's ways to regulate it and
measure it. And I think the government's going to be able to sort of put out field service workers
to measure soil, to measure these things, to look at is it regenerative. And places like Mariposa
Ranch in California, you can buy half a cow with a bunch of friends and it's eight bucks a pound,
which for a four-ounce serving is less than you'd pay for McDonald's hamburger. So you can, with
little ingenuity and effort, you can actually start to sort of find how to get these things.
But it's the demand that's going to increase. And that's why, for example, General Mills and
Danone and Nestle and Pepsi even are looking at how do we get our supply chain to be more
regenerative and how are we going to move that needle. It's kind of exciting to me.
Is there anything else a consumer can do absent the types of bigger changes that you're pushing
for and hoping for? I mean, I think being really focused on what you eat and where it comes from,
buying at local farmers markets, joining a community supported agriculture,
looking for regenerative sources online, buying things together with friends.
What are the resources people can use to find those things? Are these centralized in any way?
Yeah, they're on my book, Food Fix. And they're on our website.
What's the URL?
Foodfixbook.com. And there's a video on there and five steps to heal the planet and yourself. And
there's an action guide that is good for citizens, businesses, governments, and so forth. So that it
says, what can you do? And so, yes, you can vote with your fork and all the ways I just mentioned.
You can be active in your community. Maybe you should have a compost pile. I'm talking about
that, but you can be active to sort of have community garden to get it.
You know, my son for his fifth birthday, it's like, okay, what do you want, Reese?
He wanted a compost box. All right. There you go.
You know how hard it was to find one? You couldn't go to Home Depot and get one. You couldn't go to
the local garden store. Like it took... Really? They have them on Amazon. You can buy them and
have them shipped to you. I think ultimately, it sounds silly. I think ultimately we did that,
but I was, I think with kids, sometimes it's fun to take them to the place and get the thing.
I was amazed how hard it was to get a big compost.
You don't even need that. I just put a little fence, a little kind of some two by fours and
built a little box and you just throw it in my backyard and just throw it in there year after
year. And I've got like tons of feet of this dark, rich soil, like a humus that goes on the garden.
It's great. If you want to be politically active, you can go in your municipality and say to your
local government, say, look, let's have a composting law. Let's make it mandatory,
like San Francisco did. You can't go and throw your garbage in San Francisco anymore.
I just don't know if I want to do anything San Francisco is doing. I gotta be honest with you.
No, whatever. But I mean, France, if you have mandatory composting there and if you don't,
you get a fine, you go to jail. In Massachusetts, they passed a law that if you make a ton of
organic waste every week, you can't throw it out in the landfill. And they actually created
innovation there. There's people coming up like dairy farmers are making less money struggling.
The dairy farmer creates these anaerobic digesters, which gets food waste. They get
about a hundred tons of food waste every week in this one farm from like Whole Foods and other
grocery stores. They put in their manure from the animals. It basically combusts in this digester,
produces electricity for 1500 homes and makes the farmer an extra hundred grand a year.
And it's a win-win-win for everybody. To me, I always feel like that's the better. Whether
that particular example works at scale or not, I have no idea. But it seems to me the we're going
to put you in jail if you don't compost approach is the wrong approach versus the let's economically
incentivize you to do this thing differently. And I worry that there's too much emphasis on the
punishment side of things. I don't think humans work that way. And it's also a slippery slope
because the government doesn't exactly have a track record of great competence. So for everything
that they do right, they're probably doing three things wrong. And therefore, I mean, again, I don't
want to sound like too much of a libertarian anti-nanny state guy, but I feel like I kind of need to
sound like the libertarian anti-nanny state guy when it comes to these things. Because the government,
as you point out, is a big part of the reason we got in this mess. And to quote Einstein again,
and I might be bastardizing this quote, but the same level of consciousness that produced
these problems will be incapable of solving them. That's true. But we do have a lot of regulations
that protect citizens, right? We have seatbelt laws and emission controlled laws and cars. We have
baby seats and all sorts of things that we mandated that now people accept. And we have airbags, which
the industry didn't like, and seatbelts, which they hated. And we just sort of accept that. And I think
there's a role for government in actually helping incentivize the right thing. And I think the law
making it not okay for big companies to throw out all their waste in a landfill. And the reason to
back up a little on that is food waste, incredible problem. Like we said, 30 to 40% of all food
producers wasted. If it was grown on landmass, it would require the entire country of China
to grow all that food that we throw out. The average family throws out about a pound a day
or about $1,800 a year of food. And if it were a country in terms of the greenhouse gases that get
produced when you throw it in landfills and it rots and emits methane, it would be the third largest
emitter of greenhouse gases after the US and China. And it's about $2 trillion of resources
that we waste in throwing out all the food. And we produce more than a food for 10 billion people
on the planet. It's just not equitably distributed. It's a big problem to solve and nobody's for it.
Even Trump administration has created a food waste initiative with the EPA, the FDA, and the USDA. And
they basically like, oh, it's the FDA, the EPA, yeah, and USDA to actually deal with the food waste
issue. So I think each of us can stop that. That's an easy thing to do. And there's a lot of other
things we can do to get involved in our political process through being involved in communicating
with your Congressman senators or something called the Food Policy Action Group, which is
foodpolicyaction.org that rates your senators and congressmen on their voting records on food and
ag policy. So you can see, and they can, they've literally unseated congressmen who are doing bad
things and voting the wrong way around food and policy issues that people care about. So there's
a lot of things we can do as individuals. USDA, what's their role in this? Oh my God,
you have another couple of hours. I go through all this in the book, but just at the high level,
the USDA is responsible for a number of different food and ag policies that are the majority of the
things that are going on. Our dietary guidelines, which are messed up. Our school lunch guidelines,
which are messed up. Our SNAP program or food stamp program, which is 75 billion a year. It's
one of our biggest government programs that feeds 46 million Americans, including one in four kids
who are food insecure. Great idea, but there's no nutrition guidelines in that. So there are
$7 billion a year just in soda that we spend, about 30 billion servings a year. You can buy
soda with food stamps? Oh yeah, of course you can buy anything except alcohol and cooked food. So
you can buy a two liter bottle of soda, but you can't buy rotisserie chicken in the grocery store.
And 75% of the food stamps is junk food or soda. That's about a $730 billion program, which is
massive over a period of 10 years. And so there's no nutrition guidelines in there. And so you've got
all these government programs, plus the crop insurance and agricultural supports that support
an industrial agricultural system. And those are harmful in sense. So if you have a big soy and
corn farm and you want to grow a whole bunch of veggies, you can't, even if you want to,
because you will get penalized and not get your crop insurance. So farmers are disincentivized
from growing fruits and vegetables. And the government tells us on the one hand to eat half
of our plate as fruits and vegetables, but less than half a percent of industrial supports,
of agricultural supports from the government are for fruits and vegetables. So it's like,
basically, if we were eating what the government actually funded in agricultural supports,
we'd be having a giant corn fritter, deep fried in soybean oil. And it's like, that's not exactly
what we should be eating. That's a very powerful image, Mark, is that not that necessarily the
USDA's recommendations on nutrition are correct, but even if you took that as an aspiration,
it's interesting to note that the funding doesn't align with that. So how does the USDA respond to
that, especially because it's not a subtle, they're not off by a little bit. They're off by an order
of magnitude. A quarter of less than a half a percent versus 50%. So what is their response to
that? I don't know. I just think it's just the right hand is not talking the left hand. And so
there's all these disparate policies. I was working with Tim Ryan and my friend Dariah
Mazafarian from Harvard Tufts to get an analysis by the government accountability office to look
at what our disparate policies were doing to our public health and to our economic health as a
nation because they're all cross purposes. We say, don't drink soda, eat healthy diet,
so forth with dietary guidelines, but then we pay for 75 billion a year in junk food for the poor.
How does that make sense? And so I think we have all these government agencies, which the FDA that
has confusing food labels or that allows antibiotics in our animal feed or that allows
substances that are banned in other countries to be, they're toxic to be in our food supply like
Azodicarbonamide, which is basically a softener for flower products for bread. I mean, if you use
that in Singapore, you get a $450,000 fine and you go to jail for 15 years. I mean, Singapore is
Singapore, but still like it's not even allowed. And we have the FDA, the FTC, which regulates the
airwaves allows all this unrestricted marketing to kids. So you've got all these different agencies
that are working cross purposes that aren't coordinated and aren't creating a coherent food
policy. So we need a national food policy. We need activism to change some of these food policies
and support regenerative ag and to reform food stamps and dysfunctional policies to reform
school lunches and to actually help advance in healthcare food as medicine. All these things
can be done. And I'm actually working on a campaign with some extraordinary people who are
launching a nonprofit and an advocacy group, otherwise known as a lobby group for the good
guys to start to work on these issues in Washington. Because while it may seem like
nothing can be done, I think behind the scenes a lot can be done. And I think there are a lot of
these issues are bipartisan issues. I just think people are ready for this. There's a movement and
a readiness around the country and even in Washington to address these issues. I mean,
I just gave a talk at somewhere and someone knew one of the centers from Maine and they called me
the next day and was like, what can you help with this? And I said, well, 70% of the military recruits
are unfit to fight and 70% of the evacuations from Afghanistan and Iraq were not for more
injuries, but were for obesity related injuries and the soldiers. And then they want to figure
this out. So I am hopeful because I see that despite all these issues, people are waking up
to these problems. I see these big food companies like Nestle, Denone, Unilever, and so forth,
General Mills actually starting to take on these issues. I mean, they still are part of the problem,
but they are trying to move their super tankerships and it takes a while, but I do see room for hope.
I see business innovations, food and act tech companies are billions and billions are flowing
into these areas for innovation, which is all a good thing. What do you think are the
top three changes? If you were foods are, and you had to rank order sort of the biggest,
are there three things that could make 70% of the difference? Yes, I would immediately transform
healthcare reimbursement to focus on food as medicine through paying for food for those who
are food insecure, for reimbursing fruit and vegetable prescriptions, for making food a
central part of the government. And that would include having all the government is probably
the biggest food purchaser in the country. Have them only purchase food that is going to promote
health and not disease. I would then secondly, reform these dysfunctional food policies. I would
transform SNAP, transform school lunches, transform the dietary guidelines to be science-based.
And lastly, I would actually support Regenerabag in every way possible through government policies
and through business innovations, incentives and other things. So those three pillars,
one fixing food is medicine into the healthcare system and reimbursement policies and in every
government institution, reforming dysfunctional government food policies and supporting Regenerabag.
And that's really the whole agenda of the Food Fix campaign. We've sort of glossed over it a
little bit, but I guess no discussion on this would be complete without coming back to maybe
some of the confusion that exists around a plant-based diet exclusively as a solution for, and let's
put aside the health issues for a moment, because there's obviously lots to debate around whether
animal-based products have deleterious health consequences. And let's put aside also the sort
of egregious cruelty to animals that takes place under farmed conditions. And factory farming should
be banned period, full stop. Yeah, I don't think anybody that spent any time actually going and
watching how animals are harvested in that way would disagree with that. So let's instead focus
on specifically the environmental concerns. You've already talked about it a little bit,
but can you say a bit more about it? Yeah, you know, this interesting report came out
called the Eat Lancet report, which was very well-intentioned and had a lot of great
science in it that talked about how we link climate and diet and food and what is a healthy
diet and how do you define that. There's a lot of great science in there. There were challenges
though, because some of the language in there was really driven through the food industry,
and a lot of the sponsors for that were Big Food and Big Ag. One of the, for example,
messages is we need to grow more plants, more grains and more beans through something called
sustainable intensification or climate smart agriculture. These are buzzwords sort of like
clean coal, which sound good, but when you look behind the curtain, who funds those organizations?
60% of the members of climate smart agriculture are the fertilizer companies. Sustainable
intensification means using more and more chemical inputs on farms in the developing
world to grow more grains and beans. That's not the solution. And lastly, without animals integrated
into regenerative agricultural systems, you cannot restore soil in the way we need to restore it as
fast as we need to restore it. It's just a scientific fact. So what you... Is that based on
the need for the, basically the transfer of nitrogen through the animal? Pooping, peeing,
digging, the saliva makes the plants grow. It's a whole symbiotic ecosystem. And when used properly,
not over grazing, but proper management, which is called holistic management or managed grazing or
adapted multi-padded grazing, there's a science to it. You can dramatically increase soil. So it
takes like, I think a thousand years to get three centimeters of soil, naturally. Gabe Brown in North
Dakota got 29 inches of soil just through these methods that are sort of supercharged methods.
They're like sort of agriculture 2.0. It's not about going back to old waste. It's about inventing
new ways, using all the science to actually grow soil. Because a lot of, I mean, through human
history, we were destructive. I mean, we would grow food on land and we would deplete the land
and we'd move to the next plot of land. Problem is now we're running the land. There's no more
place to go. So I think we absolutely need to actually scale this regenerative agriculture
model in order to solve all these global issues. Can regenerative ag be superimposed on fallow
land? Yeah, then people are basically taking degraded land, which is almost desert and turning
it back into lush fields and lush agricultural practices. So when those people say we have to
be vegan to save the planet, it's actually not accurate. Whether you eat meat or not is a personal
choice, a moral choice. If you think it's a health choice, fine. But whether or not you believe in
eating meat or not, from an environmental, from a regenerative, from an climate standpoint, we must
have animals integrated into the process in order to restore soil, which is the biggest carbon sink.
So the take home message here for people is there are a lot of ways to fix climate change,
but the quickest, fastest, and most effective and scalable way, and using ancient carbon capture
technology that is more effective than anything that exists today is free, called photosynthesis.
It's basically sun and carbon dioxide in the air. We can solve a lot of the global issues we have.
So Mark, how are you spending your time today? You wear a ton of hats.
Yeah. I mean, you're involved in the education of functional medicine at the Cleveland Clinic.
You commute there and back from your home in New York. You're obviously very involved in this
initiative. What does the pie graph look like of how you allocate your time?
Well, I'm always doing the same thing in my mind. I'm trying to end the need and the suffering
through the power of functional medicine, systems thinking, and sort of restoring communities and
behavioral change through that. And this is just part of that story. Like I said,
there's so much suffering that's unnecessary, whether it's chronic disease or poverty or
mental illness or kids struggling with learning in schools or violence. These are all needless
suffering. If we have the solutions, then we need to focus on them. And as I began, began at the
beginning, talk about, as I sort of went down the rabbit hole of why are my patients sick,
I came to this bigger conclusion that unless we deal with the systems issues, unless we go
upstream, we're just going to be treading water or bailing a sinking boat. And the acceleration
of these problems is so big that I feel like I'm focusing more and more on these bigger issues in
order to solve them. So yes, I write books and I feel like this is my last one for a while,
but like to write books and teach and speak and do all these things, have clinics.
But at the end of the day, this is an existential threat. And once you've seen it, you can't unsee
it. I just were researching the book for the last two and a half years. I just sort of was shocked
by a lot of things that I learned that are not really common knowledge, even with really
educated people. If I go in a room of highly educated people and say, what's the number one
source of climate change? They're not going to say food, but when you actually unpack it,
that's the biggest threat. Well, Mark, thank you very much for making the time today. And more
importantly, of course, for doing this work and bringing it to our attention. This is an area that
I have become increasingly interested in. And my views are kind of constantly evolving. I mean,
I think there was a day when I didn't question the health of GMO. I'll just share with you an
anecdote, which is when I went to Europe a year ago, I just made the glib observation, which was
sort of the bread, the pasta, all of the food that I ate in Europe, which I actually went out of my
way to eat, did not seem to produce the same effect as it did here. And that was actually kind of the
thin end of the wedge in my mind that said, what's going on? What is the difference between the crops
that they are using in Europe? And it's funny because it reminded me of my childhood because
when I was a kid, we used to go to Egypt every year. And because my parents are from and I've
got my mom each year and usually spend two months there. And I remember the way bread tasted there.
It had a very distinct taste that you'll never taste, even if you buy like pita bread or other
Middle Eastern bread here in the US, it tastes very different. And I remember sort of having
those neurons tickled again when I was in Europe going out of my way. Because most of the previous
times I'd gone to Europe, I kind of don't eat that sort of stuff. But on this trip, I was like,
hey, I'm going to win in Rome. So yeah, tell me about what you think those four differences are.
So you're talking about wheat products, right? So what's happened to wheat is that we've
hybridized the wheat to make it extremely drought resistant and hardy. And it's called dwarf wheat.
And the guy who invented Norman Borlaug won the Nobel Prize and increased in yields. But what was
sort of the unintended consequences is the starch in there is called amylopectin A. It's a super
starch, raises your blood sugar more than regular sugar. So one, it's basically just like eating
sugar worse. Two, when they breed plants, it's not like humans, you get 23 pairs of chromosomes,
one from your mom, one from your dad, 46 chromosomes in plants is 46 plus 46. It was like 92.
And so there's extra proteins that are formed and there are many more gliding proteins,
which are inflammatory and more active in terms of causing disruptions in the gut. So they're
more likely to cause leaky gut inflammation. The third thing is they spray wheat, even though it's
not a GMO food plant, they spray it with glyphosate at harvest. Why? Because it defoliates the plants,
it gets rid of all the sort of leaves and stuff. So it makes it easier to harvest. So right at
harvest, they spray this with glyphosate and your Cheerios have more glyphosate than vitamin A and
vitamin D they're adding their per amount of weight. So even if you buy organic wheat?
Organic wheat, no. Organic wheat could still be the dwarf wheat. And then lastly, this is
interesting, maybe five reasons. But second to last, the calcium propionate, which is a
preservative, is added to the wheat in this country and it's known to cause toxic neurological
effects, behavioral hyperactivity, and even linked to autism. In fact, when you give babies
breast milk, it increases butyrate, which is an impactful short chain fat in the gut that makes
your gut healthy. When you have formula, it causes high propionate levels, which can cause neurotoxic
effects. And in animal models, it has caused autism if you put propionate in rats' brains.
And then lastly, in Europe, they have different methods of making them. But here it's like quick,
quick, quick, quick. They want it to level and rise in a couple of hours. There it can take overnight,
12 hours, 14 hours, and it tastes very different. And it's a very different structure and it does
different things to the gluten and so forth. So there's a lot of reasons that that happens, but
I would say over and over, I see this happen with my patients who can't eat this stuff here and they
go over there and there's no GMO over there. It's a complex web of things.
Can one make bread here in the US on their own using wheat, like an actual wheat that comes from
Europe? Sure. You could, or you could get heirloom wheats, like ankhorn wheat, which is very different.
Or now there's new forms of wheat, like kerns of wheat by Wes Jackson was developed in the Midwest.
It has incredibly deep roots. It's a perennial wheat, super nutrient dense, really amazing,
amazing product. So there's incredible grains out there that I was talking to my friend,
Jeff Bland the other day, who's developing this company. And he's working with this guy
to develop these phytochemical rich foods, super foods. And he got a bunch of things from the USDA,
a bunch of seeds. And one packet came in, it was like 4, 3, 2 on 6 or something. He's like,
what's this? I don't know what this is. And they sent it to him by accident. And it was this
Himalayan buckwheat, which apparently is one of the most protein rich, low glycemic, phytochemical
dense, hearty super food on the planet. And they're now, they have this sort of seed because, and
they're not selling it, distributing it, but they couldn't give it back. So he's like literally
taking this packet of seeds and turning it into a whole business, which is pretty amazing. So
there's a lot of stuff out there that we could use. It's much better for us, but we just kind of
homogenized our food supply and we've taken out all, like I said, we eat 800 species of plants
before when your hunter gathers. Our bodies need all those different phytochemicals and nutrients
and minerals and so forth and vitamins to actually run itself. And we're now just in this
sort of nutrient devoid diet, even if we're eating organic stuff, if it's not grown in good soils,
if it's hybridized plants, it's just not great. I always say eat weird food. So I always try to
eat weird food. I gotta tell you, I'm hungry right now. I know. All right, Mark. Well,
thanks very much. Sure. Thanks a lot, Peter. Have me. Thank you for listening to this week's
episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss,
we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content
without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price
of this subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally
kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss
on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or
Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed
that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qwally's,
which are a super short podcast, typically less than five minutes that we release every Tuesday
through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not
getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head
over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only. It does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and
they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.