Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Dr. Luke Bennett. Luke is the medical and sports
performance director for HINSA Performance, a company focused on human wellbeing and athletic
performance with a particular emphasis in motorsport. Luke received his medical degree,
as well as his master's degree in sports medicine at the University of Queensland. He then spent
seven years training in intensive care before working for six years in remote emergency
aeromedical retrieval with the Royal Flying Doctor service of Western Australia, something
that we actually talk about in this episode that despite knowing Luke, I didn't know this
about him and didn't understand what that meant. I wanted to interview Luke because I talk a lot
about my interest in Formula One, my passion for it. I realized that a lot of people who listened
to this podcast might not fully understand why. I thought that no one could do a better job
explaining some of the ins and outs of it the way Luke could. He does a really great job of
that. Again, you can come into this without having ever watched a Formula One race or finding any
interest in it. I think you're going to come away from this thinking, wow, you learned a lot and
you have a greater appreciation for the sport of Formula One, what makes it special, why it's so
emotionally, cognitively, and physically appealing. We talk a lot about Luke's background. We do,
again, an overview of F1, including the races, the driving, the unbelievable travel and physical
and logistics and sleep constraints and everything that are placed on all of the drivers and the
teams. We decided to release this episode specifically to coincide with the release of
season two of the Netflix documentary series, Formula One, Drive to Survive, which just came
out on February 28th. If you haven't seen season one of that, I recommend going and watching that
first. I think I binge watched it in two days when it came out. Can't recommend this series
enough. It does a really good job of showing you not just the drama of what happens on the tracks,
but perhaps more importantly, the drama of what happens off the circuit. My hope is that if you're
not a fan of F1, this will give you a great overview of the sport, why I love it so much.
And if you're already a fan, you're definitely going to enjoy this. So without further delay,
please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Luke Bennett. Luke, it's so good to see you, man.
Thanks Peter, back in Austin. Yeah. And thank you for making time. We had spent a couple of weeks
trying to figure out how we were going to make this happen with your schedule because obviously,
you have more important things to do than sit here and goof off with me. So I really appreciate
you making time. That's why we're doing this so late at night. No problem. We got the races the
other way around this year with Mexico and Austin. So we actually had a free day beforehand. It worked
out well. So let's start with the most interesting thing on your CV and we're going to get to a lot
of things that you do, but tell me what a flying doctor is. The Royal Flying Doctor Service of
Australia is pretty unique. I don't think there's anything like it anywhere else in the world, even
considering the continent of Africa. Western Australia in particular is a state that's about
the same size as Western Europe. It has only 2 million people by way of population and only
really one. And one of those is, I mean, most of them are in Perth, right? Exactly. So all of the
clinical services essentially are in Perth and it's actually more economical for the health
system to fund an aeromedical retrieval service by fixing aircraft for the entire state rather
than building and funding hospitals around. So it's this huge expanse with a vibrant sort of
mining industry in particular, lots of underprivileged indigenous communities, a big tourist
industry during the winter months and all sorts of crazy action happening out there. And a couple
of these flying doctor bases where you'd have a crew of a doctor, a nurse and a pilot flying to
retrieve patients and then taking them to the capital city. So regardless of the problem, you
are usually at best three or four hours from help, but more often than not up north, half a day to a
day away from tertiary specialist care and some really, really sick patients on a daily or weekly
basis. So when you take something like childbirth, for example, where there was at least some
anticipation of when a person is going to need medical care, do those patients just sort of come
to Perth or is childbirth something that would be done locally? There's often a plan to fly the
patients to Perth and also there's high rates of unexpected premature labour. So we spent a lot of
time actually on obstetrics, which terrified me to be honest, I came from adult intensive care
medicine and learning obstetrics and pediatrics on the fly like that was sometimes a pretty nervous
situation. So if somebody suffers a motor vehicle accident or a heavy machinery accident in the
field, the first responders could take how many hours to get there? So first of all, when I started,
the first responders were often volunteer ambulance crews. So it might be the local teacher or the
local shopkeeper going out to do the first response. They can be easily three hours each way drive back
to the nearest small hospital. And there's even parts of the state where we would land on the road
on the highway because it was the fastest way of retrieving the patient. Now that was pretty
uncommon, but typically patients have had a pretty good trial of life by the time we got to them. It
was minimum three to four hours after the insult. Wow. So there's just things we take for granted as
far as, I mean, do they have AEDs locally and things like that for people who are having heart
attacks? Yeah. So there's reasonable basic resuscitation equipment in these small nursing
posts. A lot of really nurse led clinics around the place and these nurses were unbelievable. You
know, the stress they must face on a daily basis, having to deal with whatever comes in the door.
Good resuscitation facilities were there, but it's a case of getting the patient to them and then the
appropriate medical skills to them as well. Now you're from the other coast. You're from the east
coast of Australia. Yeah, grew up in Brisbane and live more recently on the Sunshine Coast,
beautiful place called Noosa Heads. So what took you out to Perth? Did you train there?
I did not. The flying doctor job was something that had interested me. And in fact, the Western
Australian division had a lot more of this primary retrieval work, which was far more
interesting than routine shuttling of patients between regional hospitals, which is more the
case on the east coast. So it was really the nature of the work attracted me to WA and it's
a beautiful part of the world and this amazing remote desert and coastal scenery up there. And
it was just a new adventure and something that I look back on as probably the most professionally
satisfying part of my career clinically so far. So what was the transition from that
which I think sounds like it came out of critical care, big hospital critical care to that to what
you're doing today with HINSA, which we'll talk about what of course what that is.
Throughout my time working in hospital intensive care and then in the flying doctors, I was
essentially volunteering to work trackside doing trauma and rescue for different motor
sport events. So we worked at the Australian Grand Prix for about 11 years in Melbourne.
The Australian team did the Korean race when it was there for a couple of years. And then I also
did a lot of rally and off-road and that stuff was a lot of fun and very interesting medicine-wise.
You had long response times. You typically had two injured patients. You had to do your own
extrication and fire suppression and the patients were generally more heavily injured than in
circuit racing. So that was the overlap in terms of career during that phase. And then at the
Australian Grand Prix, I met a guy called Adam Costanzo who was Lewis Hamilton's first physio.
He was an Australian guy who'd been to university in my sister's year group. And so we got talking
one year and I met his boss and our founder, Dr. Aki Hinsa, who we can discuss perhaps and kept
in touch with them over subsequent years to the point where Aki was eventually looking to step
back from travel and I was in the right place at the right time to take the role that we're in now.
And when was that?
2014 was my first year. So just coming up to the end of my sixth full season in Formula One.
Tell me a little bit about Aki and his philosophy of training.
So Dr. Aki Hinsa was a Finnish trauma surgeon. He was actually doing humanitarian work in Ethiopia
in the mid 90s. And he was thinking about human well-being through a humanitarian sort of lens,
but met Halley Gabrissoulasi and those legendary Ethiopian Olympic runners during his time there
and translated some of those principles into the needs of an athlete. When he moved back to Finland,
Mika Hakkinen asked him to start to support him and his family trackside and Mika won a couple of
world championships side by side with Aki in 98, 99. He became sort of the McLaren team doctor and
then famously had long associations with Lewis Hamilton and Kimi Raikkin and Sebastian and
other young drivers as they came through. And Aki unfortunately died a couple of years ago,
but he attained this guru-like status in the paddock. He was a really kind and inspirational
figure, a great doctor and a real father figure to many of the drivers that we see doing so well
today. And how did he overlap with Sid in the role that Sid played beginning probably in the 70s,
right? Yeah. So Professor Watkins was appointed and employed by the FIA. So the governing body
of the sport, Sid was doing all of the trackside rescue. He was in the medical car, which chases
the first lap of the race. And in those days, he was kind of the only doctor around through the
70s and the 80s. And I guess as the 90s wore on, there was a little bit more of a trend towards
teams having some of their own doctors, which is what Aki was. So I don't think Sid overlapped
directly with Aki. There was a gentleman called Gary Hartstein who followed Sid and did a great
job. Sid retired what in the late 90s? That's correct. Yeah, it was the mid to late 90s. Yeah.
And he was around at FIA conferences and things for a number of years. I met him a couple of times,
a guy who really established trackside medical care from nothing in the 1970s. And a number
of drivers probably owe their lives and their health to Sid and his successors.
I was recently rereading Damon Hill's biography. And it's sort of interesting to go back to even
25 years ago and think about how dangerous that sport was. And it went through sort of these step
functions of improvement and safety sort of in the mid 70s, there was a big step up. And then
there wouldn't really be another huge step forward until the mid 90s after Senna's death.
And even just two years later, you see how in just a span of a couple of years, the sport got
considerably safer, which is something I'd love to dive into with you. So let's talk a little bit
about F1 because for many people listening to this, they probably don't understand so many
dimensions of it. Starting with the way I describe it to my friends who don't follow it, it's like
having a Super Bowl every two weeks. That's the only way I can explain it to people who
don't pay attention to Formula One, which not a lot of Americans do. Would you agree with that
assessment? Yeah. It's the world's most interesting and expensive circus really. It's endlessly
fascinating on the social level and the human level. And I'm not sure if you saw there was a
Netflix series which came out based on last season's Formula One.
I've only watched each episode 14 times. So now I have no idea what you're talking about. My family
knows every episode off by heart and then actually they keep calling for more and more. I
heard there's going to be another season. They are filming this year as well, but you wouldn't
be surprised to learn that many of my friends and families, and particularly female family members
and friends, people who've never had more than a passing interest in motorsport, have suddenly seen
this series and understood the human story that's unfolding all through the midfield and the teams
and the politics and the appreciation that you can have for not just the on track action, but the
human stories that are going on behind the scenes is phenomenal. In terms of a comparison to Super
Bowl, I mean, it is a massive television event. It's outside of probably Summer Olympics and
Football World Cup. It's got, if not the largest TV audience of an annually recurring event. It's
certainly up there in the top three. I mean, it's not uncommon for 200,000 people to show up at
every race throughout the course of the weekend, correct? Yeah. I think we had 360 odd thousand
attendance over the three days in Mexico last week, for example. Some races are better attended
than others. The TV audience is there regardless. And we got new owners of the sport a couple of
years ago, so they're modernizing a lot of the approaches to digital coverage as well, which is
starting to get some traction. And this year, there are 20 races, 21 races, 21 in next year, 22,
and possibly 23 or 24 the year after. So we're probably going to hit a ceiling there somewhere
of what the human beings involved in working the sport can take. There's a lot of discussion
about how the teams will approach, for example, a 24 race season, because there's a lot of travel.
It's a great life. It's a great privilege to work in Formula One, but it's very, very hard on
particularly mechanics, engineers, catering staff, people with families at home. There's a limit to
how much you can sustain being away. And the teams are going to be budget capped in 2021 at the same
time as they're going to have this interesting problem of perhaps rotating staff. So it's never
a dull moment. Things are changing all the time. One of the things that first intrigued me when I
really started to think about this through the lens of human performance was the management of
jet lag. Walk me through what a typical travel schedule would look like, especially when they're
on the one week pace, which is quite common. Maybe just stepping back and thinking about the
structure of the Formula One calendar. So we have these 20 on races and they're organized in
absolutely no logical geographical order. The races pay to be the first or the last race of
the season. They pay to be on a traditional fixed date. They might be aligned with a particular
public holiday or a school holiday block. And that's always the priority over any sort of
travel planning logic. So we start the season with four races, which are long haul, mostly in
Australia and Asia. Going to be five races next year when the Vietnamese Grand Prix starts. We
then have a slightly nicer period sort of through the European summer where we are on the road,
working out of trucks in Europe, a little bit less flying. And then we're in this phase now,
which is the hardest part of the year. So seven or eight long haul flyaway races again, back and
forth to Asia a couple of times, Russia, three races in the Americas now, and then finishing
in the Middle East. And again, most personnel will go back to Europe in between each of those races.
So most people have done a dozen long haul intercontinental sectors over the last month or so.
And this is the time when championships are being won or lost. And it's in terms of sleep management.
I listened to your Q&A with Matthew Walker a couple of days ago, and there's an ideal to
sleep management, which we really try to adhere to as much as possible. But there's a really
pragmatic element to that as well. And particularly around the psychology of arriving at an event.
And this is not as much the drivers, but the crews, the mechanics and the engineers,
people who probably have a very narrow window to either get onto the new time zone or not.
And if they get to a point where there's been two or three nights of disrupted sleep, getting into
the phase of the week where the cars are on track, it can be actually quite a disturbing thing. So
we try not to use sleep aids, sleeping medications too much. But there is probably a case where
athletes and others around them need to perform for just having that one night reset with a
sleeping pill on arrival in the new location. As much as that's kind of the lesser of two evils,
it can improve somebody's outlook and mindset for the rest of the weekend to come. We do quite
detailed sleep and jet lag planning for the drivers and on occasion for the teams as well.
But the reality of the schedule, the weekend schedule, the flights that can be chosen,
there's a limited number of flights to take a thousand people into each destination
with limited flexibility. So it's a case of being very pragmatic, not letting the perfect be the
enemy of the good. And things just move so fast. You have to just keep getting through each day
the best way you can. I think a number of people watching Formula One casually might not appreciate
the magnitude of the team that supports the two drivers. So again, let's start at the top of the
food chain with the two biggest teams, Mercedes and Ferrari. 10 teams, 20 drivers, so two per team.
How big is the entirety of the Mercedes team or the Ferrari team?
So you're looking at probably between 900 and a thousand people at the Mercedes Formula One
factory, for example. Ferrari would be very similar. And then again, in the Mercedes case,
you've got another six or 800 just building the engines in a separate facility, a separate
company. So probably looking at an average of a thousand people per car up and down the 10 teams.
And again, that's going to be challenged soon when there's a budget cap and there's going to have to
be a lot more rationalization and prioritization of how teams approach building the fastest car
possible. Will that budget cap apply? For example, you have some teams that aren't building their
own engine. Mercedes is building the engine and the other team is buying the engine from Mercedes.
Will that cap still apply the same to those teams? It seems a bit unfair.
So this hasn't been announced yet. I think the final regulations are due to drop any week now,
but these are precisely the topics that have been so controversial. A car manufacturer under a budget
cap faces a completely different scenario to one of the traditional privateer teams like Williams
or McLaren. So for precisely those reasons, it's not resolved yet. And I suspect the regulations
will continue to evolve over the next couple of years. Now, of those people, how many are actually
traveling to support the drivers and actually be at the race versus stay in the factory?
So there's a core race team of about 43 people with a specific pass, which is all electronically
regulated in terms of the times they can be at the circuit. So those 43 people are operational.
They're allowed to touch the car and interact with the race event itself. At a typical large event,
like Monaco or Austin, the traveling staff might be something around 150 per team where there's a
huge marketing and communications and media apparatus that goes along with the team's
activities for that week. There's a core bunch of engineers, of course, and the catering team and
the truck logistics guys, because they all are guys at the moment. And those teams are pretty
constant, but they'll vary. For example, a European versus a long haul flyaway race.
Yesterday, I was in the car with my daughter coming back from a cross country meet and we were on
the freeway and driving 75 miles an hour, which feels like nothing when you're just driving in a
straight line. And I said, Olivia, do you realize that those cars we watch every Sunday can go three
times this fast in a straight line? It was fast enough that she sort of got what that felt like.
And then I tried to explain to her the difference in G-forces that we feel when I would break really
hard for her to feel a hard break or turn relatively quickly. It's very hard, I think,
for people who haven't been inside a race car to even try to extrapolate what's happening in
Formula One. I was actually trying to reflect as I was having this discussion with her about the
greatest G-forces I've felt inside of race cars that I've been driving. Nothing like what those
guys experienced. Maybe 2G, 1.9, 2.1G. What type of forces do drivers experience in F1 today?
So we're between 5 and 6G on some of the fastest very high speed constant radius corners,
like the final turn of Monza, for example, a couple of the Suzuki turns as well. So it means
your head, your four kilo head plus helmet is four or five or six times its normal weight,
and you've got to resist that with your neck muscles. So it's an extremely physical activity.
And I had a ride in, there's a two seater F1 car, which is used at some corporate events. I did some
laps of Mexico as a passenger last year. And we got to drive two of the X Minardi drivers with the
greatest names ever in the history of Formula One. We had Patrick Freesacker driving around,
and Zolt Baumgartner was also there helping out. So I honestly couldn't have done five or six laps
as a passenger. The forces and the experience was so brutal. And our guys, it's probably equivalent
to doing a pretty intense CrossFit circuit for two hours with a maximum of five or 10 second brakes
around it. While someone else is doing CrossFit trying to push you out of the way of your
equipment and someone's in your ear asking you to solve maths equations. And there's two or 300
million people watching. And maybe you don't have a contract from next year either that you're sort
of thinking about at the back of your mind. So there's an enormous amount going on while a driver
has to hit that millimeter perfect apex every lap. And it all just happens so fast. It's a lot more
instinctive, I think, than people think, especially when the drivers are in traffic, but very,
very physical. Yeah, I think I'm probably more empathetic to the mistakes that drivers make.
What race was it when Seb came back on track without looking left, Stroll almost hit him,
and then Stroll did the exact same thing 30 seconds later? So the Italian grown pretty
a couple of months. Yeah, that's right. It was Monzo. So I got to tell you, people were up in
arms and, oh, he should know better. He's a four-time world champion. My view is in the heat of the
moment. I don't even understand how people can be critical. I mean, I guess that's the nature of
what we do as spectators. And you can't see out. No, that's the other thing. The cockpits are so
high now. Yeah, and you can turn your head only a couple of degrees in each direction. The mirrors
give you a little bit of view. The halo, which we'll discuss, does restrict a lot of vision as well.
And it's a difficult problem. The drivers can see sort of the top of their tires. They can't see
most of the extremities of the car. So those front wings hang out a long way and they're very
susceptible to damage. So it's almost unfathomable the way they can race in close quarters and
literally millimeter perfect, sweeping the front wing of one car across and missing the tires of
their colleague and the other. So crazy. It never gets old to me when I'm trying to show someone
what type of precision and proprioception is necessary. Because when we think of athletes
having proprioception, I mean, that's one of the hallmarks of all great athletes. They sort of
always know where they are in space. But driving takes it to another level because it's not just
where you are in space. It's where this car is in space. And I mean, because I'm biased, of course,
watching Senna onboard laps in Monaco. I mean, I could do that all day long because you realize
he's coming within three to six inches of curbs of walls lap after lap after lap at speeds that
are sort of dizzying. Yeah. Change of gears manually, no power steering. Yeah. Incredible
footage, some of that stuff. But you touch on an interesting point there, Peter. I think this
proprioceptive aptitude is something that really separates the great drivers from the good. And
as someone who thinks about driver performance, I haven't worked out how we could even study this,
let alone modify it. But the way a driver senses what's going on in the adhesion between their
car and the track, the fine movements of the car, they sense it sort of through their back,
through their legs, through the contact that they have with the seat. And I think the truly
great drivers just have this unbelievable level of truncal proprioception and sensory awareness
that allows them to feel what the car is doing. And I think perhaps if there's ever a way that
we can measure and train that, it might lead to some step forward in driver skills training.
Well, that's a great point. And I mean, I think anybody who's been in a simulator will tell you
that's true. I mean, I have a simulator at home and I know it's so much harder to catch oversteer
in the simulator because you don't have that feeling of oversteer that comes before your visual
change. Whereas understeer is all visual anyway. So the simulator seems great for helping you correct
that. But that to me just says exactly what you're saying, which is when you deprive somebody of the
ability to sense that in their trunk, in their butt, there's that scene in Rush when the character
playing Nicky Lauda talks about how he was gifted with a great ass. And that's how he sort of knew
that this tire was a little bit low in pressure. But I think that stuff's all true. I mean, I just
think that the great ones, they feel something. Now, of course, the more interesting question is
the one you pose, which was how would you train that? Most great drivers come from a karting
background off the top of your head. Are any of the 20 guys on the grid now not from a karting
background? No, everybody would have started in karting. Yeah, they've taken different paths
through Formula Four, Formula Three and different ways to the top, but everybody starts out karting.
Yeah, karting is thought to be probably the best training that a Formula One driver can do. There's
very limited testing nowadays. So if a driver does want to train skills, then karting is
typically the go-to activity. Why do you think that is over, for example, being in a simulator?
Is it because you still get the feeling of the experience? You still have to manage the slide
and all those things? Yeah, it's a very raw experience. It probably comes back to the very
stripped out basics of feeling tire adhesion and car control and car movement in a very accessible
way. Going and running a Formula One car of any recent era on a track is not a trivial exercise.
It probably takes a team of at least 20 people just to get the thing fired up. But karting is
a pure technical skills exercise that's still worthwhile doing. I know, I sure enjoy it. Any
time I can take my daughter karting, I'm like, this is the greatest thing in the world. There is
no greater smile on your face than when you're sliding around on your side on those things.
So you alluded to the complexity of the cars today. Give people a sense of that. You also talked a
moment ago about how in addition to doing the CrossFit thing and getting screamed at and blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, you've got an engineer talking to you. When we're watching television,
we hear a fraction of that discussion between the driver and his engineer. How much is actually
going on and what are the sorts of things that a driver is actually being expected to manage?
So there's a number of layers to that. On the team level, there's probably 10 or 20 different
radio networks involving all of the key personnel. So from the team boss to the strategist to the
chief engineer to the individual driver engineers. There's also a huge infrastructure back in the
factory in the UK. And they might be looking at the radio messages from other vehicles. They might
be looking at all sorts of telemetry from the car. There's hundreds and hundreds of streams of data,
which sort of ultimately have to feed through this one person, which is the individual driver's race
engineer. So it can get pretty busy on the radios. And the art of being a race engineer is
probably being able to not only understand and manage your driver emotionally, but to filter that
information and deliver it in a way that's concise and useful. A related question, I guess, is what
is the driver doing around a lap? And there are limitations on what the car is allowed to do.
I mean, just for perspective, when I'm in a car and my coach is talking to me,
there are only certain parts of a circuit when I can even talk back. I have to be on a straight away
to even just have the presence of mind to push the radio button and say, got it. Okay, we'll do.
Yep. Noted. Next lap. I'll hit that apex a little different. I can't do that when I'm cornering.
Yeah, for sure. And in the ideal world, there are structures to the radio talk that occur at a
certain point around the lap. But there are times when you don't have that luxury and
you reference sort of button pushing, but the modern Formula One steering wheel is an
unbelievable piece of complexity in its own right. I mean, these steering wheels are worth
50 or 60,000 pounds each. And there's probably 20 or 25 buttons on there, all of which have sub
menus and sometimes sub sub menus. And the drivers by regulation have to drive the car themselves.
They can only be given a limited amount of instruction from the pit wall as to what
settings to use. And it's got to the point now where they're more or less changing the
settings of the car between each corner so that it's optimized for each particular corner. So
the really great drivers not only have this proprioceptive feel, they've got a bandwidth
excess where they can really tune into the car. They can make all these changes fairly automatically
around a lap. They have just the experience and the knowledge to understand how the car is going
to work. And then on top of that, they have enough cognitive capacity left over to sort of
sit above the race to understand what their competitors are doing, what is the context of
their pitstop strategy and when they need to push, when they need to conserve tires. So it's really
an incredible cognitive load. And that's a big part of what we are managing with our coaching
staff across a race weekend. Give me an example of some of the complexities that can be managed
corner to corner by the driver. Things like brake bias, diff settings, and then these modern
engines are absolutely incredible hybrid pieces of art. They're hybrid electric engines. Tell folks
what that means. So we had the last reg change. So these came in in 2014, 2015. Okay. Yeah. So
prior to that, we were talking a pure naturally aspirated, was it a V10? 1.6 litre V6. Yeah.
The V10s were the good old days, some time ago now, but these are electric hybrid engines. So
they have a couple of different methods of energy recovery. There's braking energy recovered from
the vehicle. There's heat energy from the turbocharger. And these are fed back through a battery
to augment probably about a quarter or a third of the engine's power comes from this recovered
electrical energy. But to reference your previous question, so deploying that energy in the most
appropriate way around a lap is an enormous part of driving a current F1 car and save the energy
for a period where you might be trying to defend from an overtake, but deploy it in the parts of
the lap where it's going to give you the maximum benefit in terms of lap time is just a massive
engineering puzzle in itself, which the drivers have to keep on top of. So the engines themselves,
I mean, this is incredible. The internal combustion engine was invented what in the late 1800s,
early 1900s and for the entire history of the engine to 2014, the thermal efficiency went from
maybe 20, 25% to 28 or 30% at the very best scenario. But since 2015, Formula One has taken
that efficiency from about 28, 29% to over 50% now. So just a massive quantum leap in the way
engines work and for all of its faults in terms of carbon footprint flying this great circus around
the world and racing cars, when you multiply that kind of engine technology by 80 million
new cars sold around the world each year, you can see that there is a case to be made that Formula
One does a lot of good as well in developing these technologies. I think it does good on two
main fronts, that being one of them and of course, auto safety being another one. Let's go back a
little bit to the efficiency. How long do you think it takes for those types of benefits to
trickle in? Certainly, it trickles to the very high end halo supercars quite quickly within a
couple of years. But I think if you look at some of the technology that's coming into your average
medium family sedan nowadays, it's probably reasonable say within 10 or 15 years, a meaningful
amount of this stuff becomes relatively standard. And I guess it depends on regulatory pressures in
different jurisdictions around the world. But the technology is there if governments mandate the use
of it, I suppose. And we'll see, I guess, where we are on this planet over the next decade or so,
we're going to see a lot more emphasis on these technologies. I want to come back to safety in
a moment, but I can't help but ask a question that actually, I mean, I've thought about in the past,
but I still don't really understand all of the complexity you've discussed. It's mind boggling.
I know that if I spent the rest of my life, I could never drive one of those cars. I could do
goofy sedan laps, but I could never do a real lap, let alone race with anyone else out there. We might
have trouble just driving it out of the garage. I mean, they're not easy. And yet the drivers are
getting younger and younger. Sometimes, again, I'm sitting there, we always watch the races together
every Sunday. And because we're in California, we actually like watching them in real time. So we do
get up at five to watch them first thing in the morning or whatever. And I'm trying to explain to
my daughter in particular, because she's old enough, how old Norris is and Leclerc and even Verstappen.
I'm like, these guys are really young. And there was a day when a 30-year-old was in his prime. A
30-year-old is not in his prime in this sport anymore. And certainly by the time you're a
30-year-old couldn't break into the sport, put it that way. Whereas Damon Hill was 30 in effectively
his rookie year, 29, perhaps. But how is it that these drivers are getting younger and younger as
the complexity of these cars is getting greater and greater? I'm just blown away by it.
I think there's a couple of dimensions to that. One of them is purely cultural. I think people
just didn't think you could be a Formula One driver at all before the age of 23 or 24 previously.
I think maybe some of that complexity plays into a gaming culture. A lot of our younger drivers do
a lot of gaming. And it's kind of a bit of a cliche to make the comparison. But I think there
probably is an element to that. But I think now that it's been done, we had Max Verstappen come
into the sport just out of his 16th year, I think. And we've had a couple of teenage drivers
since then, Lance Stroll, Esteban Ocon, and others. I think now that it's accepted that it's possible,
the teams are more open to looking at younger talent. I think the pathway to Formula One
previously, let's think about the 90s or the early 2000s when we did have these brutal V10
engines and the cars were physically very much harder to drive. I think there was a physicality
about that that probably suited a slightly older driver as well. The cars are not easy to drive
nowadays by any means, but they are probably less of that brutal, raw, explosive, muscular power
required for perhaps an individual more well-developed physically. And it remains to be
seen, of course, but does this mean that Formula One drivers will have longer careers today coming in
earlier and staying longer? Or does it mean that the turnover is going to be higher? And it's sort
of interesting when you consider, I always think of Lewis as really young. I don't know, 2007 seems
like it was sort of yesterday. And yet Lewis is what, 34? Yeah, Lewis and Sebastian are both 33,
32, 33 now. Which would make them two of the oldest guys in the grid, right? Yeah, we had
Kimmy turned 40 last week, but he's a bit of an outlier. I think there's an opposing sort of
trend though. The seat time is so valuable now. There's so little testing. It's relatively
difficult to get a super license, which is the qualification. You need to collect points in other
series. You need to do well in other series just to get to Formula One. And then on top of that,
the cars are just so complicated to drive that there's a huge premium placed on anyone with seat
time and seat experience. So I think that will trend very strongly towards longer careers. So
people will come in earlier and they'll be retained for longer. You'll have to have a much stronger
case to bring an unproven rookie into the sport. Let's take a step back a little bit and kind of
talk about some of these changes that have really taken over. You've alluded to the halo. Explain
what the halo is, when it came about and what the effect of that has been. So the halo is a cage
like device, which sort of sits over the top of the driver's cockpit. So just going back to basics,
we're talking about open cockpit racing here. And that's one of the classic characteristics of a
Formula car. It's got open wheels and an open cockpit. And traditionally you could see the driver.
The halo is this device which has been constructed over the top to protect the head of the driver,
which was the one last remaining big vulnerability in terms of safety. And the halo has been in for
two seasons now. I must admit personally, I was a little skeptical. I could understand
the rationale for it. I did wonder whether it was a solution in search of a problem. Having said
that we've had probably at least four distinct incidents now in Formula One and Formula Two,
where the halo has prevented a significant impact with the driver's head. So regardless
of what anyone thinks of it now, it's here to stay. The current halo is not a pretty thing. It's
definitely probably in its first iteration at present and it will be developed. I think in
IndyCar this year, they're using an evolution of the halo, which has more of a jet fighter screen
around it, which is much, much more aesthetically pleasing. And I think instead of that bar down
the middle, correct. And I think when things like fogging and airflow and you have to account for
all weather conditions and all visibility conditions and when those problems can be solved,
probably we'll move towards an arrow screen with an opening out the top so that it's still
technically open wheel racing. And it's a pretty impressive piece of kit. I mean, it's seven kilos
of titanium. The test, the halo apparatus has to pass by FIA regulation is something like a 10 to
12 ton load, a large bus being sat on the top of this seven kilo device and not deforming at all.
Just again, another example. That's unbelievable. Remarkable technologies that go into these
beautiful works of art, these cars that we can sometimes take for granted. And there's another
thing that we wear in a car called the Hans, which it's been around almost exactly 20 years now. It's
been in Formula One a little bit less than that, maybe 15 years. You've indirectly alluded to it
by explaining why the driver can't turn his or her head. Well, in Formula One, his head, I guess,
but left to right. What is the Hans doing and how is it saving a life? So the Hans is a head and neck
support device. Hans is actually one of several brands that are on the market, but it's the one
used most commonly in open wheel series. It's a carbon fiber device that sits on the top of the
shoulders of the driver. It has the race harness, the seat belt straps over the top of the device.
Pressing it down into the driver's shoulders and then the helmet is attached by some very
high tensile straps to this device. The effect of that is that if the driver has a head on or a
rotational impact, the movement of the head, especially the flexion of the neck is greatly
limited. And the Hans device has no doubt across many categories of motorsport, saved many, many
drivers from high cervical fractures. So fractures of the neck that would have killed them or severely
disabled them for their life. It's interesting. We probably only have anecdote about this and
don't get me wrong. I think that the Hans and other devices like it have been an innovation
in motorsport that shouldn't be questioned at all. But the force transmission down the spine is
interesting to think about. And I think if you look at a lot of the accidents we get in rally nowadays
and also in close foot racing, we seem to get these thoracic and lumbar crush factors a lot
more commonly. And I don't think this has been formally studied, but it seems like the Hans
probably changes the loading on the spine and produces something that's transmitted more
axially down to other parts of the spine. Do you think that's something that they experience when
they hit a bump or is it more when there's a head on collision? It would be more in a very high
speed impact where the loadings on a driver and an impact like that vary with the exact circumstances.
I mean, it totally makes sense because if there's a vector that's going forward
and that normally would have been distributed between C1 and C3, and now you've locked that
up with the Hans, well, then you're going to see that presumably below about T1. The force has to
go somewhere. I think the thoracic spine is braced somewhat by rib structures and the drivers in their
cars are in a highly recumbent position. They're almost lying flat on their backs, which a lot of
people don't appreciate. And that also adds to the unbelievable skill required to just control
one of these vehicles, the fact that you're more or less lying flat on your back with limited
visibility. So that changes the force distribution as well. I was in Italy last year and I got the
chance for my wife to see a Formula One car and get inside one. And she's like, what, five, seven
or something like that. And I'm like, okay, so a Formula One driver might be a total of an inch
taller than you, two inches taller than you. Get in there and now try to imagine doing what they're
doing from the position. And she couldn't believe how little she could see from being in this
position. It was just, it is overwhelming. The modern F1 car is very long and very wide and
very heavy as well. And controlling those cars with limited visibility in traffic is a very
underappreciated part of the art. I think it's the hardest, I mean, there's nothing I've ever
dabbled in that I could extrapolate to and say that's harder. I just don't think anything is,
people say, oh, you've swum from here to here or something. And I'm like, that is a trivial,
trivial task. That is simply a matter of just putting your head down and trying harder.
That doesn't speak to what you're describing here. It's a sport with many complex layers and a lot
of that social complexity too. Yeah. How do you manage? I mean, is that part of your job
description or is that just something that based on your own personality, you're obviously very
thoughtful, you're very introspective that you've sort of gravitated to, which is you have the
luxury of not being, you have the luxury of being sort of there to serve everyone, but you have huge
personalities. You have a sport with only 20 athletes, but 10 owners and they all have to be
under one roof effectively 21 times a year. Yeah. First of all, like, yes, with reference to our
position, we're extremely privileged to be working across multiple teams. How many teams do you work
with of the 10? We work with at least one driver in every team at present. So about 14 drivers in
some form are under our care. I never take that for granted. It's an enormous privilege. And it
goes back to Aki's time really when the model we use is medically led and the medical services that
we provide, I think are kind of the glue that cement those relationships. And I would say,
so our model is that we have a performance coach that people would refer to as the trainer or the
physio companies each driver. This coach will attend all of the races and normally train with
the driver in between races as well all year. So they have a very close one on one relationship.
We tend to use mostly sports scientists in our team. They have a good broad understanding of
the physical preparation, the nutrition, the sleep management, and the other things that we need to
think about across the race season. We do use some physiotherapy staff as well and increasingly dual
qualified sports scientists, physios are probably the ideal for this job. But all of that specific
preparation aside, probably the most important role for our coaches is management of the cognitive
bandwidth of the driver across a race weekend. So we discussed driving the car and the drivers will
have about seven hours in the vehicle across a race weekend. But on top of that, there's probably
10 hours of engineering meetings in which they get very, very deep in the data and the analysis
of what's happened on track. And then endless other hours of media and marketing commitments,
as well as just all managing the politics of any athlete's career. So as you referenced,
you might think about the NBL or the NBA, sorry, or the NFL, where most weeks you're going to have
two team bosses under one roof at any one time. But in Formula One, every two weeks you have 100%
of the competitors in the world, all 20 seats, they're all there. You've got all the team
principles, you've got a good percentage of the team owners, you've also got the principal
regulators of the sport and the owners and promoters. And all of those people are mingling
freely with the media, you know, there's nowhere to hide in a Formula One panic. It's a, it's a
big traveling family. So that does add a certain level of political, I wouldn't say tension, that's
probably pejorative or negative, but it does add a real social complexity to what these athletes
need to get out and do, which is ultimately drive the car. And our coaches get to know their
drivers, they manage a lot of their key relationships, they manage the time of their driver,
they will usually develop a role where they can sort of interface between the marketing team and
the media commitments and things and certainly recognize when the driver needs to be left alone,
where they may need a holiday, when they can push, when they can train, when they can do more or
less. So that's probably, and these drivers are all human beings. People think of professional
sport and especially Formula One as a place where everything is done with an unlimited budget
to absolute perfection. And I think Peter, you probably have contact with enough professional
athletes in various categories to understand that it's just not like that, is it? Regardless of the
funding, regardless of the techniques and the science and the innovation available,
professional sport is just about human beings and all their flaws and faults.
Well, yeah, I probably don't have nearly as much experience as you, but I think what's most
interesting to me is that even the people who are the best, most of them still have the same sorts
of doubts that quote unquote normal person would experience. And you see it across seasons where
people get into slumps and you get a bad bounce, you get things that just don't go your way for a
period of time and all of a sudden it sort of shakes your confidence. And I don't know. I mean,
I think in a sport like Formula One, I would have to guess that the toll of that is really great.
There is nowhere to hide. It's like tennis. There's no ambiguity about who's driving that car or
who's on that side of the tennis court or that side of the tennis court. And yes, there are
plenty of examples when a driver is doing everything right and the car fails. Certainly
Seb a couple of weeks ago, best line of the whole Formula One season, by the way, bring back the
bleep in F12s, V12s rather. I just have, like I said earlier, I think I just have great empathy for
the load that they must be under. And yeah, you can say, well, come on, they're athletes. They're
doing something really fun and it's really great. But I often wonder if it's as fun as we think it
is compared to, you know, I'm always reminded of Senna at the very end of the documentary,
talking about how you get the sense that Formula One just wasn't as fun to him at that point in
his life because he was hearkening back to his days of karting. He just kept saying like, there
was no politics. There was no money. It was just about the pure joy of racing. And I do wonder
when you talk about some of those obligations that these guys have in the political games that they
have to play and just the unhappiness. You referenced the younger drivers coming through.
Yeah, there's a lot of satisfaction to be derived, of course, from working with world champions and
winning championships. But actually one of the joys of my job as well as bringing these young
kids through and we typically start working with them in F3 or F2. Can you explain to folks the
difference between F1, F2, F3 and what does that look like? I mean, we're going to come back and
talk about the recent events of F2, but help people understand what those different formula mean.
So this has been greatly simplified in the last couple of years to the credit of the FIA. There's
a more or less straight pathway through F4, F3, F2 and then F1 nowadays. Formula Two occurs at
F1 race weekend. So the drivers in F2 are very much on the radar of the Formula One teams and
bosses. They're a car which is maybe five to 10 seconds a lap slower than an F1 car. A lot simpler
in terms of the controls. They're not these remarkable hybrid sort of engines. They've got
some similarities, probably the most important element being the tires. So tire management is
incredibly important in Formula One and the drivers in F2 and to a lesser extent F3 have to learn that
art in those categories. F3 cars are a little bit simpler again. Sort of no power steering, a lot
more physical, a lot more brutal to drive, but slower. And typically how old are the folks in F3
and F2? You're probably talking an age range of 16 to early 20s. These guys and girls are playing
for keeps. Every year could be the end of their driving career. So I commend anyone who has a bit
of time to watch the F2 racing. It's genuinely exciting. Week in, week out. And it's a big job
for the stewards to keep on top of driving standards because you know so much is at stake
in those categories. And then F4 is more or less the graduation point from Carts to Open Wheel
Racing and national F4 championships in many different countries that sort of feed through
to the higher categories. So the cars get a little faster and a little more complex as you go each
step up the chain. What's the role of money as one goes up the chain? When you look at a sport like
basketball, you referred to the NBA a moment ago. If you're good, if you live in the United States
and you are really good, you can make it to the NBA. You don't need any money. Usually that'll
take you through a college scholarship through to the NBA. But if you're exceptional enough,
you could even go straight from high school into the pros. Same is true in baseball. Again,
you almost always go through the minor leagues. You very rarely go straight from high school into
the major leagues, but you could go through college. You could go from high school into minor
league baseball, et cetera. But Formula One is not quite like that, which doesn't mean you have
to come from wealth, but you certainly have to get the endorsement of someone with a lot of money.
Where does that begin in the chain? So you take a really promising kid in a go-kart. How do they
get to Formula Four, Three, Two, and One? So first of all, I guess, karting as a hobby and karting
starts at the age of six or seven or eight years old. So it's not like strapping on running shoes
or football boots. You have to have a parent with a little bit of budget and a little bit of interest
in motorsport, even to start karting. Typically, motorsport can run within families. So often,
there's a father, usually there's a father who's competed and who has the funding to bring a young
competitor through. And then I guess as you get good at motor racing, there's two streams. There's
those who continue to pay their way and roll the dice and take their chances and hope that their
day will come. And there's others who are really an obvious, outrageous natural talent who will get
picked up by one of the three or four big teams and inducted into a junior driver program. So
those opportunities are relatively scarce. But if you're really good, you'll probably find yourself
aligned with one of the big teams. And are those geographically relevant? Are you more likely to
get one of those streams if you're coming out of Europe than if you're coming out of South America?
I think Europe is absolutely the geographical center of the sport. It's very difficult to
succeed from Asia or from any of the Americas without ultimately ending up in three or F2 in
Europe, because that's simply where the racing is conducted under the nose of the F1 teams. And
that's where those top levels of category actually unfold. So yeah, there's 20 seats in Formula One,
unlike tennis or golf or football, where there's 100 or 200 or more competitors at the very highest
level. These drivers are competing for an extraordinarily small number of positions. And
everybody who's there, regardless of how they've been funded, is there on some kind of merit.
They've had to win championships or do well in junior categories just to get the super license
points to be eligible to drive in F1. So I would posit that the depth that we see in the field
currently is by far the best it's ever been. And it's getting better every year and really adds to
the stories all down through the midfield where some of the most interesting action unfolds. It's
not just about the Mercedes cars or the Red Bull cars in recent years dominating at the front of
the field. There's all sorts of fun to be had. I think that's actually, and I heard that this
year for Netflix, both Ferrari and Mercedes are being filmed. Is that true? So the Netflix series
has focused on the midfield where a lot of these stories are. Mercedes have agreed to some limited
involvement this year. And I'm not sure actually what Ferrari is doing, but I think they probably
will feature to a limited extent. That'll be great because I'd love to see it. But I actually think
last year worked out really well not having them in the story because you could have just talked
about Ferrari and Mercedes the whole time, but to talk about everybody but them made it incredibly
interesting. I agree. It was one of the really powerful outcomes of the series. And it's actually
one of the hazards of work in the paddock at the moment. Trying to avoid the camera. Well, I spent
a lot of time talking to drivers about their health or their medical issues or the troubles
that they're having in their career. And it can be very easy to be having a private conversation
in a corner somewhere and suddenly find a Netflix boom microphone over your head or a camera for a
distance. To be fair, the team are relatively sensitive to that sort of thing. And it's probably
not just Netflix. I mean, we are performing our work in front of cameras day in, day out,
the entire year. And it's just something you've got to be a little bit mindful of.
How would you handicap the safety of Formula One today? To put it in perspective,
in the 1960s and in the 1970s, there was a very good chance that if you did this for a living,
you were not going to retire. In fact, it's kind of amazing the exceptions to that rule because
they're the ones that we tend to know about today. Most people, unless you're sort of a diehard fan,
you've forgotten the names of all the people that died. I think Yawken Rent is the only one to have
won a Formula One title posthumously. So by definition, if you're rattling off the names
of Formula One champs, they usually at least lived long enough to win. And many of them went on to die
prematurely in retirement. But the list of people that most people wouldn't remember,
like the Peter Revsons of the world. And I mean, everybody remembers Joel Vilnev, who never won a
title, but would still be considered one of the greats of all time. But there's this belief that
Formula One today is so insanely safe to is not be interesting. But one, do you think that that's
true? And two, can we learn anything about the recent fatality in Formula Two that can give us
a sense that no, actually, it's still a very dangerous sport. It's a really delicate argument,
because I think if we're honest with ourselves, the danger, there has to be a small element of
danger, at least to provide that depth of interest in what the drivers are doing. It has to be hard.
It has to be something that has to be something that we can't do. Yeah, exactly. So Formula One
is extremely safe. And we referenced all of the terrible things that happened in the 70s and early
80s. But there's a number of strands that track design is getting much better. The car design has
come on in leaps and bounds. And the trackside intervention, the medical and rescue services are
also light years ahead of what they used to be. But we have had three or four notable fatalities
over the last two decades. And so there is always some part of the Swiss cheese that lines up some
unaccounted for possibility that can still result in a death. And one of the big vulnerabilities
is a side on impact with a stationary vehicle. And unfortunately, we had a terrible accident
about six or eight weeks ago at the Belgian Grand Prix in Formula Two, where a car who'd
had a relatively innocuous spin Antoine Hubert was stranded side on stationary in the middle of the
track and was just hit at well over 200 kilometres an hour, 170 miles per hour by one of his fellow
competitors who was just unsighted. So we had this nose to side impact, which as good as the F2 and
the F1 cars are. And believe me, they're very, very good. The intrusion properties of the chassis,
the tub are exceptional, but there are some forces that you just can't account for in every situation.
Yeah, I'll never forget the press conference a couple of days after Senna died when Max Moseley,
then very new in his post as president said, and I thought he was so spot on by the way, he said,
the question isn't why did Senna crash? Because that's all anybody wanted to talk about. To this
day, there's still great debate about why he crashed. So the question is, why did he die?
And he said something I'm paraphrasing, and he said it much more eloquently.
You are at the highest level of the sport at the absolute limit of mechanical and human capability.
There are going to be crashes all the time, but nobody should die in one of these crashes.
I don't know if the statistics bear this out, but it certainly seems like they do just watching
races. It doesn't seem like there are any fewer crashes today, but there's no denying that the
fatalities are an epsilon fraction of what they used to be. And let's be honest, the crashes are
a massive part of the appeal of motorsport, especially to the more casual fan. It's spectacular
when a vehicle crashes and there's parts flying everywhere and it adds to the drama and the human
tension as well. So that will always be part of the sport, but as you reference, it needs to be
made as safe as possible. And you talked about the Senna footage driving around Monaco. And one of
the remarkable insights there is how high the drivers are sitting up out of the car. And
after Ayrton died, that was one of the big innovations. So the head and the shoulders of
the driver were much better protected. There's a shroud around the head and the helmet,
which limits any sort of intrusion. And the cockpit sides are much higher nowadays.
Senna's death probably had a greater impact on the safety of F1 than any single tragedy in the
history of this sport. When Jim Clark died, it's not like the sport changed that much. And Jim
Clark was to Formula One in the 60s almost. I mean, no one was quite to F1 what Senna was, but
comparable, certainly. There was an enormous amount of low hanging fruit in terms of safety
during that time. So a lot of the simple things were done. Yeah, yeah. I mean, but they still
drove unmartialed. They still did. I mean, I guess to this day, I don't think anybody knows
what actually happened to Clark's car. Yeah. Senna's death was the first in a generation,
really. There had not been a death apart from Roland Ratzenberger the previous day. There had
not been a death for 14 years. And so it was a bit of a shock. And so there was another step
change in safety for sure. The wheel tethers, all sorts of things. You recall, it wasn't even 10
years ago when Mark Webber had that unbelievable crash. You know the one I'm talking about?
In
To see the wheels not coming off was sort of unbelievable. Yeah. And he walked away, went
back and did his TV interviews. Yeah. It's very hard to injure yourself in a Formula One car.
I had a look at this in a couple of years ago now, but just the accident patterns in Formula One. And
it was interesting. I defined a medical incident as any time a driver was reviewed and assessed at
the track medical center, either because they had an injury or because they had a mandatory
attendance. And what forces a mandatory attendance? It's come down a little bit in
recent years, but it's 15 G on the car now. So there's an impact light which comes on in the car.
So the trackside marshal, the medical crew can tell if the impact has exceeded this amount,
then they automatically are assessed at the trackside medical center. It was actually
quite revealing to look at these incidents over a couple of years, because it was a little bit
counterintuitive to be honest. So more than two thirds of the incidents happened on the Sunday,
on the race day, and 90% were in dry weather. So this is medical incidents.
What fraction of those were in the first lap? I'd say most were in the early laps, but you do
definitely get mid to late race safety cars as well, where a car can go off at high speed by itself.
So the bigger impacts were on Sunday in the race. They were in the dry when drivers are perhaps
self-evidently pushing and they're doing their high speeds in close quarters with other cars.
But there were five rollover accidents, I think, during the time that I looked at,
only one of which resulted in injury. That was Fernando's massive crash in Melbourne a couple
of years ago. The impacts that happened in the wet, they're often very spectacular. There's lots
of parts flying off the car, but they tended to be sort of low to medium impact. And the real
high risk for injury was a 40 G plus impact in dry weather. Can you even put that in context for me
for what a normal person would experience on a freeway? We don't have the sensors, I know,
but can we even estimate? The impact on a car, it's a very crude measurement actually, because
it's measured sort of on the chassis. It doesn't really correlate that much with what the forces
are on the driver. And of course, the direction of the impact influences the vector of that measure.
And where is it picked up on the chassis? Because if it's before the chassis collapses,
then obviously a much lesser fraction of that would hit the driver, hopefully.
That's a very good question to which I do not know the answer. So the drivers also have this
in-ear accelerometer. They have three axis accelerometer in their earpiece,
and that's interrogated later. So there's a much more accurate data analysis, which comes after
an accident by the FIA. But usually that information, it comes not going to benefit
the treatment or the management of the driver on any given day. That's going to be a lesson
for the future. And that reflects, of course, the forces on the skull much more closely,
because it's actually sitting in the middle of the air. The driver can sustain very, very high
peak G forces if they're instantaneous or very, very rapid in terms of a spike of force. The
lower forces, if they're sustained over a longer period, and we're talking sort of
tenths of seconds rather than thousandths of seconds, those are the impacts that can do a
little bit more damage. That's interesting. And of course, if you come down to seconds,
holding 5G for two seconds on part of an arc is... Yeah, that's not going to injure you,
but it's because... It's not going to injure you, but boy, that's next level. People don't get,
I suppose, how tired drivers are after the race. I mean, I've got to see some drivers after races,
and they look as exhausted as someone who's, as you said, done two hours of a brutal crossfit
workout. And even walking up a flight of stairs looks like it's asking them a lot.
The cars took a step change in speed and power and grip. It was the beginning of 2017, so
they became much more physical to drive at that point. By and large, an experienced F1 driver
will cope with most scenarios. They'll be tired, but they're well within their physical capabilities.
How much weight will a driver lose during one of the harder races?
I guess Singapore is the archetypal physical race. It's a race which always goes for the full
two hours. It's a city-street race. It's got more corners than any other circuit, 24, 25 corners,
and it's all 90-degree turns at moderate speed. So in tropical heat and humidity, the drivers,
they will often lose three or four kilos in weight. They have in the car a drinks bottle.
If their engineer is being very kind to them, that might be 1.2 to 1.5 litres for a race like
Singapore. Usually, it's about half a litre, but it's hot. It's like drinking tea after a few
minutes in the car. So the driver area at the end of the Singapore Grand Prix is quite something to
behold. It's a driver coming in flushed and exhausted in a far away look in their eyes.
And that's a race where recovery is particularly important.
Now, there was a rule change a few years ago with respect to drivers' weight. What was that?
Yeah, the drivers have always had a pressure on them from the engineering teams to maintain
their weight at the minimum possible. And I guess you're trying hard and spending millions of
dollars in some cases to shave hundreds of grams off the car. So losing a kilo off the driver is
a relatively easy thing for the teams to ask with a favorable cost benefit analysis.
My favourite example of this was back when I used to be a sort of pathetic cyclist. I remember once
going to the bike shop to get some new bottle cages and they had like the regular cages were
this much. And then the super duper fancy carbon fibre cages that were 19 grams lighter were
10 times more. And the guy at the bike shop was trying to talk me into getting them. And I was
like, look, dude, before I go and drop an extra couple hundred bucks to save 19 grams, I've got
about two kilos I could afford to shed. I think I'll save my money for now. Yeah, fair cool.
So we were at the point where we had these younger drivers, these teenage drivers coming in,
a number of whom were quite tall. We had some of the older drivers like Mark Weber who were in a
continuous battle to save weight. And honestly, we were starting to see some unhealthy.
What was the minimum weight set at?
So minimum weight was car and driver combined. So at that time, there was no reference to the
driver's weight. It was just lose as much as possible. We had people running into problems
with overtraining, undernutrition. We had some eating behaviours coming out, which I was not
comfortable with. And we had Charlie Whiting, who unfortunately passed away earlier this year,
was the great technical leader of the sport for the last few decades. And to Charlie's credit and
the FIA's credit, I raised this issue with them and they acted very quickly. So we have a new
regulation this year where 80 kilos is the mark. That's the driver plus their helmet, their race
suit and their seat. And any driver who's below that level is ballasted up to 80 kilos. So it
basically takes the driver weight out of the equation to a large degree. And I must say the
drivers are absolutely delighted with this. They've just got the luxury of being a kilo or a kilo and
a half heavier. They can put on a little bit more muscle. Their nutrition is just not quite the
chore, the daily misery that it used to be. And I think we're in a much better place for that
regulation. Now, we've had women get very close to F1. I think there's even been women that have
competed in races, but not for a complete season. Is that correct? Yeah, there've been two or three
women who competed and one scored half a point, I think, in the 1970s when half points were awarded
from time to time. So it's been a pretty rare thing. We've had Susie Wolf drive in free practice
on a Formula One recandis recently, it was a couple of years ago, but it's been a long time since a
female driver has raced in a Sunday race. Are there any females in the F2, F3 pipeline? Not
obviously at the moment, no, but we have this year seen the advent of an all women's racing series in
Europe called W series. And we've been closely involved in that. And I must say it's been really
a huge success on many levels and a wonderful experiment. And I look forward to seeing that
develop over the next decade or so because it's a really vexed question, gender and motorsport.
I think there's a perception that driving F1 cars like being a fighter pilot, for example,
where I think intuitively men and women should be relatively equal. It's a fine motor and a
cognitive skill. But the truth is that as we've discussed, Formula One is an extremely physical
activity and it's not so much F1. I think F1 maybe does play to the strengths of women in some ways,
some of the social complexity, some of the spatial stuff, the power steering. I think a woman
absolutely can succeed in F1. But the problem comes at the grassroots levels of motorsport where we
A, have a very small pipeline of competitors coming through and B, the environment in F3,
for example, is pretty hostile. The cars are more physical to drive and they're up against,
frankly, teenage males with differences in risk taking behavior, testosterone levels.
There's both physical and- Right. So the lack of prefrontal cortex in these male drivers
is actually a competitive advantage to them at that stage in driving probably.
Again, I mean, there is academic literature of this kind of stuff in Olympic sports, for example.
There is some evidence for the physical and cognitive differences between male and female
athletes. But I think basically to find a woman who can succeed in F1, they are absolutely out
there, but they'll probably be an outlier. And by definition, then you have to be bringing more
women through the pipeline to find those outliers. And W series is a great first step, in my opinion,
towards just providing another avenue for women to get to the top levels of motorsport. And
certainly there are cultural things that need to change as well. I mean, fathers who are funding
motorsport careers undoubtedly favor sons at the moment, but hopefully that will change as well.
W series has proven to be a great TV success and the TV ratings have been great. The depth of the
driving talent has been, I think it's exceeded all expectations. The racing has been really good to
watch and they'll go to an expanded calendar next year and probably in the future more powerful cars
as the series becomes established. For perspective, what are the, if you go through the W series,
the formula three, two, and one, what are the relative horsepower of each of those cars?
Oh, I don't have that on the top of my head. Well, a formula one car today is less than a
thousand horsepower, correct? Yeah. The electrical power makes them very talky as well. So it's not
just a top line power. Yeah, the acceleration is staggering. Yeah. It's kind of amazing in the
eighties. You look at the MP4, four, which is 1988. I mean, that was a 1200 horsepower car.
Yeah. A beast, absolute beast. With no downforce and a manual gearbox. Yeah. Yeah. And back then
they had much more power available to them at qualifying. They would detune the car for the
race and they would use the engine once for an hour and then throw it away. Right. So the engine
was there to be blown up essentially at the maximum speed possible. It is crazy. This is
the other, I guess, environmental dimension to current formula one, the reliability of these
engines is unbelievable. They have three engines to do the entire season. Yeah. Explain to people
what a team has at their disposal. How many tires, how many gearboxes, how many engines,
what are they trying to manage over the course of these 21 races? And this is all part of the chess
game, part of the really interesting strategy. So you have, as I referenced, three engines across
and the engine comes in different parts. There's the heat recovery system, the kinetic recovery
system, the battery. So you can replace some of those parts individually without some penalty,
but basically you've got to do your Friday practices. You've got to do your Saturday qualifying
and a third of the races on one engine. And I mean, that again is an extraordinary step forward
from where we were even 2010, 2011. So principally a cost cutting measure, but something that
absolutely will flow through to the reliability of road cars. Tires, there's 12 sets of tires for
the weekend. And again, you have to select well in advance, eight or 12 weeks ahead of the race,
what tires are you going to take to that event. There's three compounds to choose from. So
the different compounds are either faster, don't last very long or a little bit slower in terms of
lap time, but they'll get you through a much bigger chunk of the race and the engineers and
the strategists need to work out what tires they're going to bring to a race weekend and then how
they deploy them in each session, which ones are you going to use to practice, which ones you're
going to qualify on and then leave yourself with enough options for the race. Let's talk about the
2021 rule changes. How many of those have been solidified? I think they're getting closer to
the final document. There were some meetings I think last week in Geneva between the regulators
and the various team bosses and other stakeholders. I think we have a bit of an understanding of
the fact that the car is going to have some simplified aerodynamic characteristics.
The engines probably will stick to something very similar to the current formula. And then the
budget cap will probably more apply to the teams and the operations and what they can do in terms
of the number of upgrades, the number of different parts, the level of activity that they can bring
to upgrading the car through the season. What kind of changes will take place with the tires?
The tires, there's going to be quite a big change. So we're going from 13 inch wheels to 18 inch
wheels. So the tire will be a lot smaller in profile, which is, it may not sound very significant,
but actually the tire currently is relatively old school, big balloony piece of rubber that
is a big part of the car's suspension at the moment. And bringing in an 18 inch wheel with a
very much narrower tire sidewall is going to change everything in terms of suspension and
breaking and aerodynamics over the cars. So that's a huge challenge for the engineers are working on
even as we speak. What got you interested in motorsport in the first place? In 1985, the
Australian Grand Prix returned to the International Formula One calendar. And so
for whatever random reason, I happened to watch the Australian Grand Prix this weekend in October
in 1985. And the TV coverage was done with a huge amount of enthusiasm. This was a big international
event coming to Australia. And I just caught the bug. I haven't missed a race in the 34 years since.
It's been an incredible ride. You were a triathlete, right? Did a little triathlon. I have to say not
a lot of training in the current schedule, but did my first race in 1988 and struggled through
a couple of Ironmans. Yes. Learned a lot about being an athlete actually, even by being a
hopeless weekend warrior. Yeah. What did you learn from that that translated to what you're doing
today? I think you have a basic understanding of what it's like to train. I think what it's like
to get up in the morning and have to do a training session that might be a bit of a chore on that
particular day. I think you have a fundamental understanding of the difference between aerobic
and aerobic training. Some of those really simple things. I mean, as we referenced, I come from an
intensive care, critical care background. So I rely very heavily on my coaches and my coaching
director, Pete McKnight, to implement the technicalities of coaching for our drivers.
This is not my strength or forte, but I think just having been an amateur athlete gives you a little
bit of appreciation for what it's like to have to stick to a training program and then compete even
on whatever level. Race day is a race day, right? No matter what the stakes are. Yeah. It's
interesting, right? I mean, it's sort of like you can take your own race as seriously as it's being
taken on the world's biggest stage. Yeah. And I look back now and Ironman in particular so badly.
There are so many things I would do in terms of nutrition, in terms of sleep, in terms of
structure of training now. I'm looking forward at some point in the next decade to having a second
triathlon career and implementing a lot of the things I've learned from my fantastic coaches
in recent times. It seems that the drivers today are much more tuned into nutrition and exercise
than drivers of 25 years ago. Again, Senna, I keep referencing him, was kind of the outlier. I mean,
the seriousness with which he took his fitness, with which he took his training was the stuff
of legends. That was not the norm. I mean, when you look back and you watch James Hunt, amazing
driver, not training. It's interesting that you mentioned James. I think probably Nicky
Lowder was the first and Nicky in recovering from his horrendous injuries in the Nrburgring in 1976
was maybe the first example of somebody who really implemented a serious physical training regimen,
but certainly Senna was a big standout in his time. And then Michael Schumacher perhaps built
on that into the current era. But yeah, the benchmark keeps rising and most of the drivers
even if they're not particularly interested in the absolute peak of physical preparation,
they have a pretty reasonable understanding of what a strength workout is and what their aerobic
capacity needs to be to get through a two hour race. So I didn't know this about you until
somewhat recently, but you survived cancer and it was quite advanced. I sort of don't think of that
time as any sort of great survival threat. Like an F1 season, it all happened so fast. It all
moved so quickly. But 10 years ago, just last month, actually, I was working in the north of
Australia with the flying doctors in a very remote area. And I had developed testicular cancer, which
I diagnosed by myself on one of the very early portable ultrasound machines we had up there.
As you know, it's a cancer if you had to choose a cancer to have, it's the one with
the best survival prospects, you know, in excess of 90%. So whilst it was, you know, it was real
chemotherapy and real surgery. You did not have seminomatous cancer, right? So it was non-seminoma.
And I actually did have pulmonary metastases as well. And looking back now, it was a relatively
rough ride. I had some thrombotic complications as well, had a pretty profound paraneoplastic
thrombophilia. Can you explain to folks what that means? So in some cancers, in some people,
you'll develop a clotting tendency. And in retrospect, the first day I went in for a scan,
I had an IV drip put in and a sort of a little clot formed all the way up my arm,
that should have been a bit of a warning sign. But you then have a permanent catheter implanted to
receive the chemotherapy drugs, a portacath. And that sits in the large vein next to the
heart and mind, in fact, clotted up completely. So there's something called superior vena cava
syndrome, which every medical student sees in the textbooks. And I had never seen really in real
life. And I woke up one morning, looked in the mirror. And yeah, I had basically a complete
blockage of blood returned to the heart from the upper part of my body. And but it was a an
interesting lesson in the realities of being a patient. I think I had always been a relatively
empathetic doctor, but just the logistics of having to go to appointments, having to be stabbed with
needles multiple times a week, the fatigue of the drugs, having to find a car parking space at the
hospital every day, I think it just gives you a great appreciation for the experience of being
ill and being a patient. And I had access to really good private care, I had access to
virtually my handpicked specialists in the different fields that I utilised. But even then
things go wrong, you're still subject to the same vagaries of nursing and nursing shifts and blood
collectors and adverse reactions to drugs, no matter who you are, we're all still human, right?
Was there any point during your illness when it wasn't a given that you were going to survive,
even getting through all the chemo? So not to get too deep into the weeds, but I did have
these lung lesions which... Yeah, I mean that stage four non-seminomatous
testicular cancer is not a walk in the park or a given that you're going to survive.
Lance Armstrong also had stage four non-seminomatous testicular cancer. His odds were 50-50 at the time
of his diagnosis. I mean, mine were a lot better than that, I think closer to 80 or 90%, but it's
still a non-significant, non-trivial chance of death, I suppose. But I'd travelled in Africa a
lot. I'd had a couple of screening chest x-rays in the past, an occupational screening x-ray,
and then another one when we... Was this part of your TB screening?
We'd actually had an intensive care patient who turned out unexpectedly to have a diagnosis of TB,
so the staff in the unit had been screened. So I'd had two little lesions on my lungs which were
known from previous x-rays, whether it was an old granuloma from somewhere in Africa or whether it
was... I think one of them was probably an intra pulmonary lymph node. So there were these lesions
and they were on the scan and nobody sort of really knew if that was significant, but lo and
behold, they actually disappeared with the chemotherapy. So it was really only at the end
of the process that it was absolutely understood to have been a stage four tumor. So I didn't get to
necessarily live through all the anxiety of that and it was only in retrospect that
the understanding was there of perhaps the prognosis wasn't as good as we had thought all along.
So how much time are you on the road each year now?
I had about 40 nights in my own bed in Switzerland last year.
You don't live in Australia anymore?
No, I'm a Swiss resident present. I do get to spend about seven or eight weeks per year at
home in Australia. So we have a race in Melbourne, so get a little bit of time before and after that
event. And then around some of the Asian races, I try to sneak home for a week. It's always very
refreshing to see friends and family and have a surf as well.
So how do you manage this toll of the schedule on you? I mean, your job is to take care of
everybody else and manage the toll, but what do you do to manage it in yourself and your team?
I mean, you have a very large team, of course, of people like Pete and Tommy, and then of course,
all of these trainers that are working with the drivers. I mean, how do you manage yourself and
that team?
Managing a business, as you probably know, as a clinician, is not necessarily something that
comes naturally. So it's pretty demanding. And honestly, if it wasn't a sport that I had a great
passion for, I wouldn't do this. If I was invited to a similar job in football or basketball or
something else, I probably wouldn't do it. It's passion for the sport and living in the middle of
the history that you make in appreciation of where the sport has come from that makes it work.
I think it's been really difficult to do any sort of structured formal physical training.
I have tried to pay a lot of attention to sleep. It's very difficult at this time of year in terms
of the travel schedule, but I really try and prioritize seven or eight hours sleep wherever
we do, wherever we go. And nutrition, I suppose, I've used a lot of time restricted eating in
recent years, as you saw last year when you visited us in the paddock, we're presented with
an abundance of really palatable, excellent food and team buffets. And it's remarkable to the extent
to which you can eat quite healthy if you choose to. But there's certainly some desserts there,
which are hard to pass up. And I think time restricted eating and a little bit of fasting,
not to the extent of long and fast like you've famously experiment with yourself, Peter, but
that stuff can be really powerful. And just trying to get outdoors, get in the sunlight,
it might be only every three or four weeks that you get to get outdoors three or four days in a
row, but just try and get on the bike, try and paddle, try and do something and also move
throughout the day. I'm lucky that in the F1 paddock, we are on our feet and getting our
10,000 steps almost in the course of a routine workday. So that helps. So basically, you got
to be a little more careful with respect to your sleep and your exercise than your default
environment would allow you to be. You could very easily sort of fall off a cliff doing this. Yeah,
it could be an extremely unhealthy job. And part of our work is managing the team members through
their same experiences. We have two or three of the teams with an embedded coach or physiotherapist.
And so we try to pass on this kind of insight, these healthy habits to the teams as well. And
many of the traveling team members are very invested in this. Others are less interested,
but I think it has an impact for sure. What have you not yet brought to this sport that you think
you're capable of bringing through your team? So Formula One is perceived as being the pinnacle
of excellence in every area, certainly in motorsport. And in terms of the engineering
and the development of the car, that's absolutely true, probably operationally as well. On the human
side, honestly, there's still a lot of low hanging fruit. And we've spent a number of years, Pete and
myself, just honestly getting basic systems in place. Our coaches have a fair bit of latitude
and freedom to work within their individual skills. And very importantly, they work within
the individual skills and strengths and weaknesses and attention spans of their own driver. So making
our system a system though has been priority. So it's just getting everybody doing some basic
fundamentals of monitoring, working to a schedule of assessments across the year. So that job is
done now. And I think we're looking to start to innovate. And I think, again, in any sport, there
are literally hundreds of scientifically proven interventions that you can make for an athlete.
But the art of what we do is fitting that into the lifestyle and the travel schedule. And again,
the attention span and interest level of the athlete that's in front of you. So I think there
are things that we can do in terms of cognitive skills, perhaps eye training, perhaps proprioception.
I don't know what those things are yet, but I'd like to study them in a little more detail.
There's an incredible lack of physiological monitoring of any driver in the car, even now.
And perhaps we can talk about that a little bit in a moment. But the other interface probably is
bringing together the way that an engineer manages their driver across a race weekend
with the coaching that we are doing. And we've started over the last year to really
try to get the engineers to work more closely with the performance coaches. And likewise, to
give our performance coaches a bit more engineering knowledge and understanding of what the overlays
of a good lap time looks like, what it means to brake later, to steer differently, and try to get
those two streams of information coming to the driver to talk to each other and integrate a lot
more. Why is there such a dearth of physiologic information going back to the paddock? I mean,
when you sit in one of these garages and look at the information that's coming in about the car,
it makes the information that the mission control was getting from the moon landing.
There is more information coming in about tire pressure than the entire Apollo 11 rocket going
to the moon. And yet you don't know their heart rate. You don't know their heart rate variability.
You don't know their electrolytes. You don't know fluid status. There are so many things about the
actual driver you don't know. In fact, do you know anything about the driver in real time?
In the car, very little. And there's a few historical reasons for that. One is a simple
matter of the regulations. So there's race suits and the fireproof underwear that the drivers are
wearing are heavily, heavily regulated. So right down to the stitching on the sponsor labels,
there's actual standards for that kind of stuff. And it has to be tested and homologated.
So there's a safety issue there.
Yeah, there's been a real limitation of what you can attach to a driver in terms of physiological
monitoring. On top of that, the teams will not add any weight to the car. So even 100 grams of some
kind of measuring or monitoring device in the vehicle would not be acceptable. And then whilst
what we do is absolutely incredibly valued in terms of promoting human performance, it's often
a bit of a low priority compared to the time pressure that's involved in just getting a car
out on the track and getting it developed. The bandwidth for any sort of human innovation has
traditionally been relatively narrow. The FIA also mandate that any sort of monitoring on the driver
has to be purely for a safety purpose. So at present, there's not a lot of interest from
the governing body in terms of performance or physiological measurement for understandable
reasons. But wouldn't those translate to safety? For example, we don't really have a sense of how
often accidents are taking place because of fatigue that is physiologically predictable.
Yeah, indeed. I think we're a long way from measuring that probably. But this last two years,
we've had a biometric sensor glove introduced for the driver. So they have essentially heart rate
and oxygen saturations measured in the driving glove. And the defined purpose of that is so that
the trackside intervention services can see what the driver is physiologically doing after an impact
whilst they are on their way to the scene. So that's a first step. And I suspect we'll be a
little more liberal in the future. There's going to be some pressure from television and digital
streaming as well to measure physiological parameters of the driver in the car as well,
which I must say is not an idea that has received such a warm reception from the drivers themselves.
It's a potential competitive advantage and information advantage that they're giving away
to their competitors. But I think we'll see more of this. We're looking at a couple of devices now,
which will probably be compatible with the regulations. And we'll have a couple of projects
potentially next year where we're measuring in the car a lot more.
How long does it take a driver to learn a new circuit? So this race in Vietnam next year,
how long does a driver have to prepare to learn that in a simulator?
It's probably less than you think. The good drivers will get out there within half a dozen
laps and they should be pretty close to on the pace. You know, they'll take another 10th or two
off across a race weekend as they get better. But the SIM is a very important part. They'll
prepare for each circuit specifically with a simulator session, but it's not the same as
being out there sitting in the seat and feeling the forces.
So as they go from this weekend, let's just say when we're done with this race on Sunday night,
two weeks from now, they'll be in Brazil. So that's a long enough stretch that many of them
I assume will go home. Everyone will go home for sure. Yeah.
When did they start getting in the simulator and driving in our Lagos before they get down there?
So simulators are a limited resource. And depending on the infrastructure of the team,
there will be junior drivers, there'll be test drivers, there'll be others who need to use the
SIM. So probably somewhere next Wednesday or Thursday, most of the race drivers will
have their day or their half day in the simulator. They are learning the circuit for sure, but
actually a big part of their job on that day is evaluating other aero parts and other upgrades to
the car. So it's not just there for the luxury of the driver learning the circuit.
Is it expected the driver learns the circuit in the off season and they've-
At the European circuits, they will have driven most of the circuits many times in the junior
categories. It's in these long haul flyaway races where a rookie driver will be encountering the
circuits for the first time. And honestly, they'll have a lot of engineering briefings across the
weekend to help familiarization, but they'll get into the swing of the circuit within a handful
of laps and then build on that across the race weekend. By Sunday, they should have a very limited
disadvantage to people who've been there before. It's still amazing to me when I think about how
long it takes me to learn circuits. You've got to remember, I guess each circuit is different
from year to year. The adjustments that are being made to the car from corner to corner
will change with the characteristics of the car from year to year. So even people who've been
there before are kind of relearning how to drive the circuit in this year's car to achieve the
optimal lap time. It's unbelievable. I don't know that I'll ever be able to successfully communicate
to my friends, to my family, to listeners of this podcast who if anyone's not a fan of Formula One
and they're still listening at this point, that would be kind of a minor miracle, I guess. But
this has been a great discussion because I think it has probably been the most complete discussion
I've brought to the podcast of this sport, why I think it's so special and what's involved in it.
I think that this sort of physical, emotional, and cognitive piece, I don't think we've talked
much about the emotional. I think we've talked about the physical for sure. The cognitive
overload is staggering. I don't consider myself one who lacks in cognition, but I could never
manage the cognitive load that these guys manage. But then there's this other piece, which is the
emotional piece, which is it's not a sport where getting pissed off does you much good.
Emotional control in the car is incredibly important. And it's in the car, it's in front
of the media, because you can easily with an errant comment, create an enormous amount of stress
next week at the next race, let alone contract renegotiations and fighting for one of those
precious 20 seats. And as we reference, we're dealing now with teenagers in many cases and
teenage drivers are just like other teenagers. We may have an enormous amount of wisdom to impart,
but there's a point where a young person perhaps doesn't even have enough life experience to
understand the lesson that they're being given. And it's gratifying, obviously, to see a driver
develop through the junior categories. And then some point in their early 20s, the pennies start
to drop and the pieces start to come together. And they just have gathered enough experience to
understand how all the strands of their behavior and their approaches to things and the motives and
the layers of social complexity around them all come together and can be coordinated in a way
that's to their advantage. And they have relationships, they have family relationships,
they may gel well with their race engineer, there may be other team members that they have to
manage more judiciously. So all of this stuff is going on all the time. And it's a privilege to be
there, sort of helping and guiding in some way, making a small contribution to not only growing
competitive race drivers, but good human beings in this crazy sport that we live in. Do you think
2021 will sort of reshuffle the order of the teams a bit? There's reason to think that the midfield
teams might have their day more often, we may get more variability occasionally in the results. But
whenever there's a large regulation change, the teams with the most resources are the ones who
will exploit that to the best of their abilities. And you do risk the top teams getting further
ahead for a period of time. Although with the last reg change, we did see a big swap between
Red Bull and Mercedes. Indeed. So Mercedes, to their credit, were well ahead of their competitors
on the engine development. Red Bull and Ferrari were busy fighting for championships through
2013, 2014. And Mercedes had put a lot more resource into the new engine regulations and
probably stole the march on everybody by a year or more. And that's taken five or six years for
that convergence to happen. You add aerodynamic changes on top of that. And I think it's going
to be a fascinating year. What's been the biggest surprise for you this year performance wise? Has
it been the sort of mini sort of performance comeback of McLaren? What has surprised you?
We've got a long history with McLaren. I worked closely with McLaren for a number of years. And
it's a team that's had a massive cultural transformation in the last 18 months. And
I think you're right, it has been a surprise to see how quickly they've started to turn things
around. They're the solid number four team and they've had some really bad luck and they're still
right there in number four. They really are the best of the rest. Yeah, absolutely. And you can
make a case that the traditional private team that's not a manufacturer owned team could be a
truly endangered species in Formula One now. So it's to the credit of everyone at McLaren
who's been able to turn that project around, bringing a lot of fresh momentum, fresh blood.
And I think they're going back to Mercedes engines in a couple of years. I think their future is
looking pretty good at the moment. Luke, this has been awesome. It's so late here in Austin
tonight. I'm just glad we got to record this. I knew that it was going to be really hard for us
to find a window to talk. So I'm grateful that we've been able to find this one and I'm grateful
for all the insight you've shared with us. And I never get tired of talking about Formula One with
you. So thank you for humoring me, continuing the discussion and doing so in front of a few other
people. Yeah, well, we've got a couple more days to dissect a lot more detail about the sport.
Can't wait to do so at the track. I appreciate the opportunity, Peter, particularly to talk to
a North American audience about this sport because it is traditionally very European centric. And I
think anyone who watches the sport for a couple of months or watches the Netflix documentary gets
into a little bit of the soap opera, understands a few of the personalities there. There's a richness
there, which is pretty difficult to stop watching once you're into it. I agree. I actually just had
this discussion with my wife yesterday is tell me another professional sport where you can name
every athlete. Yeah, indeed. There's only 20 of them. I know every one of them by name. I'd
recognize any one of them if I bumped into a grocery store or an airport. And as you said,
the Netflix special gives you a layer of nuance in the tension that you don't even catch off TV.
And it shows you the drama that exists up and down the field, even when it's not about winning the
championship. Yeah, very special. Thanks for the opportunity. All right, Luke, I'll see you
tomorrow. Indeed. Looking forward to it. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive.
If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership
program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of this attrition.
Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass,
comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person,
thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these.
Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast, typically less than five
minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only, and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures in the
companies I invest in or advise. Please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.