Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is David Epstein. David is the author of the bestselling
book, The Sports Gene, and more recently, range why generalists triumph in a specialized world,
which ironically makes him a specialist of generalists. He was previously a science and
investigative reporter at ProPublica, and prior to that, a senior writer at Sports Illustrated.
I have followed David's work for some time, have enjoyed his articles, his books, and reached out
to him several months ago, asking to interview him, even though I had already heard him on a couple
of other podcasts that frankly, I thought did a great job, but I just knew there was more I wanted
to explore with him. So of course, if you've heard David on other podcasts, I wouldn't let
that discourage you from listening to him here. We go into, in my opinion, sort of a broader,
deeper discussion that's sort of enabled by our long format. We talk about a lot of things, but
I think at the root of it, it's basically trying to get a better understanding of how we can improve
our own performance. And perhaps you can see we get into a lot of stuff around kids, but as parents,
how do we manage the exposure of our kids to various things? I think anyone listening to this,
who is a parent, obviously feels pretty strongly about giving their kids the best chance at finding
something they love and doing well at it. There are so many things we go into in this podcast that
are just fascinating beyond belief, including a really good explanation of why the 10,000 hour
rule that most people take for granted is essentially an axiom or dogma, i.e. that 10,000
hours of deliberate practice is what is required for mastery and greatness. And I think David goes
into a great explanation of why that's probably completely nonsense, which is not to say that
deliberate practice is not incredibly important, but to break it down to something as simple as
10,000 hours is almost assuredly incorrect. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation
with David Epstein. Thank you so much for coming. It's a pleasure. Thanks for having me. Your work
has been something I followed for quite a long time now. And even before your most recent book
came out, just on the basis of the book you wrote, was it in 2013? That's right. Yeah, just on the
basis of that book, people had always said, you got an interview, and I was always like, yeah, yeah,
I know, I know, I know, I know. And then the new book comes out and it's like, well, now there's no
excuse not to. So, and I guess it's tough for you because you have this new book and everybody was
talking about it, but I kind of want to talk about the old one too, if that's okay. Whatever you want.
We can talk about something other than my books if you want. We have a lot to talk about actually,
because I learned a number of things about you in getting ready to sit down today, but somehow it
escaped me that you were a fan of Ira Tencena. Yeah. I mean, first of all, one of the all time
great sports documentaries if people have seen Senna, but I used to follow racing and just,
I loved racing in general. Like if you put two paper boats on a pond, I was interested basically.
And then as I learned about him and his start in karting and the different types of racing he did,
the fact that he was a good gymnast as a young guy, that he basically tried to retire from racing
at one point, and that he was also very quietly charitable. And I think kind of a sensitive soul
in a lot of ways and obviously a very dramatic story. And I think the greatest deaf one driver
ever. And so just a lot of, I don't really as much as you, so I'm kind of cautious about saying
anything, but yeah. I think all of those things are really interesting and resonant. And so last
week I went to the beach and was with my kids and the two older kids were in the water. So just me
and the toddler who's two, who's actually named after Senna, his name is Ira Tencena. And then
these other two boys came up and started playing. And so then I'm sort of overseeing a play group,
basically one of mine and two others. And for like 20 minutes, this is going on. And then the
mother of these two other boys comes up and she's thanking me or whatever playing with them. And I
can sense a Brazilian accent. I said, Oh, are you Brazilian? She says, yeah. And I said, Oh, great,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. And we get chatting and I can't talk to somebody who's Brazilian for
more than five minutes without of course asking them, do you remember when Senna died and blah,
blah, blah. And I'm still waiting for the exception to this to happen. It's never happened yet where
that person doesn't immediately transform into, Oh my God, Senna is the greatest manifestation
representation of Brazil. It was the saddest day of my life when he died. And this woman would have
been seven when he died. And our nanny also Brazilian, same thing was like four when Senna
died, but it's seared in her mind. So I'm talking Uber driver person at rest. It doesn't matter. Any
time I meet someone from Brazil, we talk about Senna and it is without exception. They speak of
him with a reverence that I don't think Americans can relate to. There is no athlete we talk about.
There's no politician. There's no scientist we can speak about in the way of Brazilian talks about
Senna. It's amazing. So it sounds like what people hear of certain generation might think of where
they were when Kennedy or Martin Luther King were assassinated or something like that.
It's absolutely that way because of course, everybody in Brazil was watching F1. So the world
stopped every Sunday to watch the race. So now you take everybody is there stopping to watch your
guy doing this thing. And then you see this person die. But unlike maybe with say JFK, where yes,
anybody who was old enough at that moment would remember it. I don't even think that they can
speak about JFK the way with as much love or reverence as they do Senna. So it's kind of amazing
to me and humbling. That's interesting. Because obviously we have Ali is the first person who
would come to mind. But in his day, a lot of people hated him. It's a lot of athletes like him,
I think they become beloved once they're sort of older and non threatening feeling. And so a lot of
people who love them don't actually really know what it was like for them at the time. But that's
fascinating. And I think his reputation, I think a lot of the it turned out after Senna died that
he had been doing like a lot of charity that people didn't even know about with no, no fanfare
whatsoever. And so I think his legacy was, that's amazing. That's not very, very common.
That's right. Very few people know about how much he did for for the people in Brazil and how
seriously he took his position of he came from privilege came from a wealthy family, achieved
this unbelievable success. And people love this humility that he had that because remember,
it's not like he was the first Brazilian F1 champion in Fittipaldi was a two time champion,
Nelson Pique, a three time champion, who by the way, Senna won his first championship the year
after Pique won his last. So it's like a complete overlap with another, but they don't even belong
in the same sentence for most Brazilians. In fact, I asked this question of almost everybody as well,
which is how does he compare to Pile? And they're like, Oh, Pile was great, but oh, really? Oh,
that's interesting. Yeah, yeah. It's really kind of amazing. Yeah. I guess that's the most telling
question you could ask in Brazil probably. Yeah. I'll be going for my first time actually to Sao
Paulo soon to watch an F1 race and to go and I want to be able to visit the memorial where he
was buried and go to the foundation and stuff like that. How did you get so interested in him?
I don't do anything in moderation. I think is what it kind of comes down to. And I've always
loved and been attracted to people that are incredibly passionate and great at what they do.
And I do think that his perfectionism, well, I'll take a step back and say, I was probably
attracted to things about him that I didn't appreciate the pathology in at the time. So
I do think that his desire to win probably also killed him. And I think that the sharpness of
that edge I probably found incredibly appealing in a way that almost maybe speaks to my own
demons. And I think that's probably true of a lot of people. I don't think I'm unique in that. So I
just remember one of the things I remember loving about him during his career was how much he cared
about the engine and what was going on with the car and the setup and the time he would spend
with the mechanics. I mean, it was always telling to me that the Honda mechanics loved him. I mean,
just loved him. You'd have some guys that would show up, they would drive and they would leave,
but not send out. Like he could spend the entire night in the garage, machinating over every minute
detail of the car. So it was just this sort of incredible degree of perfectionism. Also,
I do think that there was just a certain, there were just things that he did that to this day
can't be explained. I think his qualifying session in 1988 at Monaco, there is no explanation for what
he did that day. I'm sure you're familiar with it just for the listener. Monaco is a very short
circuit. So in a short circuit, the difference between qualifying times should be tenths of
seconds, hundredths of seconds. His teammate that year, meaning someone driving the exact same car,
which they had the best car in the field was Alan Prost, who was himself a three-time world
champion at the time. Unbelievable driver. Some would argue one of the more underrated drivers
ever. Senna outqualified him by a second and a half. A second and a half on Monaco in a quality
might as well be a day. It's like winning the hundred meters of the Olympics by a second and
a half. That's exactly right. It's like even Usain Bolt at his most dominant couldn't win a race by
a second. Even though there's no actual onboard footage of Senna during that quality lap because
he was already on pole. So I don't think the networks were even paying attention to his very
last quality lap, which why would he try to go any faster? He'd already secured pole. But when
you watch Senna at Monaco over and over again, which is one of the most demanding circuits
because of how tight it is, I have my kids watch these videos because I'm like, I don't think you
guys understand. You think daddy drives a race car and that's fun because he can go fast. But I want
you to see what the best in the world is seeing in real time because we can't do this. Humans can't
do what he's doing. The other sort of extension to that story that speaks to this sort of love I
have is the tormented nature of this, which is what most people don't realize is he qualifies
first in Monaco or what most people I think have forgotten is he qualifies first from Monaco in
1988 by literally a second and a half. As the race is going on and on and on, he has built up such a
lead. He almost has a lap lead over the field with a very short duration to go in the race. I don't
remember how many laps I think like maybe six to 10 laps to go. He could basically stop, get out of
his car, get back in it and still win the race. But he's pushing very hard. He's pushing so hard
that he actually crashed. He is disgusted with himself. He gets out of the car, literally leaves,
go straight to his home in Monaco, doesn't speak with anybody for days. And to me, this is a guy
for whom it's not about winning. Yeah, yeah, this actually gets to something. You said I could be
digressive. So I'm gonna make a multi multi jump. Let's do it. Something I've been thinking about
that I used to think about a lot and then came up recently was at a certain point when I was at
Sports Illustrated, and I was doing reporting on doping. And I would get a lot of reader feedback
of why are you reporting on this sort of a killjoy, that kind of stuff. I took it seriously and started
thinking about, should I be doing this? What's the value that comes out of sport? And somehow I landed
on this book called the Grasshopper by a Canadian philosopher named Bernard Suits. And it's called
the Grasshopper because it's sort of an inversion of this Aesop fable where there's a Grasshopper
who's playing games all summer. And while the ant is storing up food in the summer, and then come
winter, the Grasshopper doesn't have any food and the ant does and the Grasshopper goes to the ant
and asks for some food and the ant says, no, you were playing while you should have been collecting
food. And so morals kind of obvious. But in Suits, there had been this philosophical debate that was
supposed to be settled by Wittgenstein about is there any necessary and sufficient core of sports
and games? And he said no, he said, no, absolutely, there's not. And Suits, in writing this book,
the Grasshopper, the Grasshopper is a character who's playing these games. And his disciples are
saying, you should be storing food, you're gonna die. And he says, no, this is who I am, I understand
what's coming. But this is the best thing I can be doing this endeavor for the love of what he was
doing. And Suits says there is a core to all sports and games. And it's the voluntary acceptance of
unnecessary obstacles, which I thought was kind of amazing. And he talks about what he calls the
Lucerie attitude, which is the attitude you adopt when you get involved in these things, which I
think is kind of a love of difficulty, essentially. And I think he sort of united something Aristotle
had these two, he put actions into two categories. One was kinesis, which is like, build a house,
you're doing it for the end. And the other was an ergea, which is something like philosophical
contemplation, you're doing it for the doing, not for the end. And he said, these two things have to
be separate. And I think what one of the things suits was saying was in sports and games, these
things are united, there is an end that you're going for. But the love of difficulty in the middle
is what's really important. And you're always doing something, you're intentionally doing
something inefficient, right? Like you could walk a ball and put it into a goal, that would be the
most efficient way to do it. Or you could cut across the track and get there faster, but you're
intentionally engineering an inefficiency in order to facilitate a certain experience. I'm sure Senna
had that love of difficulty. And one of the things, not to tie it to my own stuff, but one of the
reasons I think about it is, to me, I don't know that readers would say this. But to me, one of
the major themes of my new book is that sometimes the things you can do to cause the most rapid
apparent short term progress can undermine long term development. And that actually, you don't
always want to be as efficient as possible. And I think that's very much embodied in this love of
difficulty in sports and games where you are intentionally engineering in inefficiency in
order to facilitate an experience that you have some value and some learning. So sorry,
that was my multi jump. No, that is so true. I think that actually in one sort of story captures
the essence of the greatness we see in sports, which is, as you said, it has to have a struggle
in it. It's not interesting if there's no struggle, but it's in service of some destination
that can be quite arbitrary, by the way. I mean, race car driving happens to be one of the less
arbitrary ones. Going fast seems somewhat understandable in innate mountaineering seems
somewhat understandable in innate get to the top. But many sports like basketball and football are
kind of arbitrary in what we're asking people to do. Think of baseball. It's like bananas.
If you were just watching it with no sense of the conceptual structure, look ridiculous. Like,
why doesn't the guy just stay at home plate? They're already there. Yeah, that's so funny.
Well, before we get to your new book, because there are so many questions I have on that theme,
both personally and then with respect to my profession and then even more broadly,
I do want to go back to the gene because I remember when the book came out, I think it
came out on the heels of an article you had written in Sports Illustrated. Correct? Wow.
I'm surprised you remember that. Yeah, the sports team. Yeah, yeah, it did. Yeah. I want to confess
something really quick. This nobody really calls me on is I wrote that article in Sports Illustrated.
It passed fact checking at Sports Illustrated. Because when the fact checkers called back the
scientists, they said, Oh, this is true. This is true. But then after a year of before my books,
the first year, I tried just read 10 journal articles a day every day for the first year,
no writing. And having done that for the year, researching the sports gene, I realized that while
I had quoted these scientists appropriately, some of them had told me things that could not
be concluded from their data. And so I cited my own article as one that was mistaken, but nobody
really called me on that. But that's I think if you're writing about science, something you're
writing about is going to be wrong. So you have to kind of be ready for that. Well, it's so funny
you bring this up. So Bob Kaplan, who's my head of research, we are in the process now of going
through the fact checking for this book that I've been painfully and slowly working on for more time
than I care to admit. And what we've realized is he can't be the fact checker, nor can I,
because it's not just facts we're checking, it's interpretation. And we are already so biased by
our view on this. So we actually have another one of our analysts doing the fact checking,
but we specifically refer to it as fact plus interpretation, fact plus interpretation,
which turns out to be really a long process and a very challenging process because you do, I mean,
I've done this a handful of times where you pull up one of the citation classics in medicine or
science that people have referenced so many times. It's been triply referenced internally
to the point where I don't think the people referencing it anymore even know what the paper
says, let alone what it's citing. Telephone game of citations. It's unbelievable. And the few times
I've had our team extract from those papers, I've been mortified at how wrong they are,
which again, they're not necessarily orthogonally wrong, but they've missed so many things. Like,
it's like, oh, well, of course this so-and-so does such and such and such and such. Well,
let's go back and look, wait a minute. You realize that was in one really, really, really bad
experiment in mice in which you could never make that inference into another mammal. And now yet
it's taken as sort of a fact. I have to say not that that's good, but I have noticed that that
sort of thing provides opportunities for people like me where I'll go and read the original
research of things that have just been at the core of other bestselling books. It's kind of a great,
if you're willing to do it, it's sort of a competitive advantage. It gives an opportunity,
not that I want people to be citing things wrongly, but I think you're totally right.
I started as a fact checker at Sports Illustrated, and that's where you realize how many ways there
are to go wrong. Are you looking for any more work right now? No, no, no. I was happy to get
out of my fact checking days. I'm in my post book never again phase, which I was in before,
but that's where I am right now. No, but yeah, I hired independent fact checkers also. And that
doesn't mean there aren't things that are wrong or interpretations that are wrong, but it certainly
certainly cuts it down compared to, I think most books probably have no fact checking at all.
Yeah, I'm super paranoid about it because I also realize that we can't catch them all. That's the
difference between a blog post and a book is, and I've written more blog posts than I'll ever be
able to count. And the good news is the week it comes out, someone smarter than you is going to
catch something that you did wrong. And you're like, oh my God, yeah, totally right. Thank you
for that. Boom, I can change it. I can't do that with a book. And that is crippling me.
Yeah. I mean, you can do small stuff for second printings and things like that, but it's not as
easy, right? It doesn't happen right away. And if it will, especially if it's the interpretation,
it's one thing if you get a fact wrong, when you start to interpret something incorrectly and you
come around, it's very difficult to unwind that definitely. And if you're going to change, yeah,
as I learned this time, the both of my books, there are 352 pages, I guess, if you count the
front and back and because they get printed in sets of 16, so everything has to fit to a multiple
of 16, including the index and the citations and everything. So if you have to change something
major, like an interpretation where it's not one sentence, if you're going to mess up the page flow,
not so doable. You're making some unhappy folks. You alluded to something there, which is
the opportunity to go back and look at something that people have sort of taken as dogma and
questioning it. And in many ways, that's a big part of what the gene does and what your current
book does. I'll share with you sort of my bias coming into this discussion, not this discussion
with us per se, but sort of this theme, which is so Daniel Coyle wrote a book in 2009 called The
Talent Code. And before that, there were a number of other books and pieces of literature on that
subject matter. And I was obsessed with this. I was obsessed with this idea of how can one be great,
obsessed with this even as a child. And certainly when I was doing my surgical training, I really
remember spending lots of time reading literature on technically achieving mastery, like what does
it mean to be a great musician, or a great surgeon, or a great athlete, things where there's some sort
of dexterity and skill required that goes beyond just thinking and cognitive prowess. And so I would
say I completely bought this idea that deliberate practice is the only thing that matters. And I
think a lot of people sort of have taken that to be the case. What made you question that in the
first place? Or did you not question that and instead stumbled organically into questioning
that? I did not question it in the first place. And I should say Dan's a friend and I'm a big fan
of his writing also. And yeah, I did not question it. In fact, if you saw my book proposal for the
sports gene, the Talent Code in the book proposal, sometimes you do a section that I don't know if you
had to do this or not. But other books that other books like yes, yes, yes. I skipped that part for
my second proposal. But in the first one, I had to do it and Talent Code was one of the ones that I
said it was going to be like. And obviously, I would say for the casual reader, it looks like
they're actually diametrically opposed in many ways. And I don't see them as diametrically opposed,
but there are certainly some differences. And it was probably when I went back and started looking
at some of the original literature, the 10,000 hours rule was who was I to question that? I mean,
the one good thing is I was in my past training to be a scientist. And I was like living in a tent
in the Arctic when I decided for sure to become a writer. So I knew I should leverage that
background of I was in the geological sciences, which are pretty methodologically rigorous,
I would say as the sciences go. And so I decided to go look at these original papers, if I'm going
to study them. And I come across the first, the so called 10,000 hour study that the scientists
wrote, I wouldn't call that but this was with violinists violinists, yeah, 30 violinists,
famous music Academy in Berlin, split into three groups, the top 10 who were deemed to potentially
be international soloists practiced in deliberate practice is highly focused error correction focus
practice, on average 10,000 hours by the age of 20. The first thing I noticed was that there were no
measures of variance reported in the study, which is not something when I was a grad student that
one could have gotten away with reporting no measures of variance. So I was explained to
some folks might not even know what that means. So like these are examples. So if you look at a
table, and it says, this person practice this many hours, this many hours, this many hours,
what was missing in that description? First of all, no range. So several of the books and the paper
wrote that there was complete correspondence between the number of hours of practice and what
group someone fell into. And I said, Well, I can't tell that from this data, like, maybe someone in
the lowest group actually practiced more than someone in the highest group, but you haven't
included the range of practice hours or the standard deviations of practice hours. What is
the individual variation? Anytime you take an average, it could be that nobody practiced 10,000
hours, it could be that somebody practiced 100,000 hours and a bunch of people were much less.
So sort of like what's my average, your average and Bill Gates average wealth?
Sure, right.
Sometimes averages can be wildly mislead.
That's right. I mean, so for example, in the chess literature takes 11,053 hours on average to reach
international master status. So 10,000 hours would be low. That's one level down from Grandmaster,
but some people have made it in 3000 hours. And some people finished a study at 25,000,
they still hadn't made it. So we don't really know where their endpoint is. So you can tell someone
well, it takes 11,053 hours on average to reach international master status, but doesn't tell you
anything about the breadth of actual skill acquisition. So how is that possible? By the way,
I mean, I can't imagine looking at a paper that wouldn't at a minimum include a standard deviation
for that type of calculation. Don't know. Okay, so eventually I organized and noticed that the most
famous researcher on that paper, who I think has done some very interesting work, especially in the
area of memory, some work that I myself have tried to incorporate into things I do. So,
but I noticed that he was in a lot of his work saying there's no such thing as talent. It doesn't
matter. Just pick any random thing and you'll be great at it. You know, provided you put the work,
right? Right, exactly. That it doesn't matter what you match with. And I noticed he was citing a lot
of physiology papers that I knew something about like sports physiology papers and not, like you
said, not in the way the interpretation, it was kind of like these secondary interpretations,
telephone game stuff that, and so I organized a panel at the American college of sports medicine
invited him because this was, I thought a problem. He was citing a lot of their papers. His work,
Anders Ericsson was super influential in expertise. I think that 10,000 hours papers,
clearly the most influential paper ever in the development of expertise, but they weren't talking
to each other. So we organized this panel and in that a researcher stood up and Tim Lightfoot and
asked what's the variance around that 10,000 hours? And he said, well, that doesn't really matter
because the people were actually inconsistent on multiple retrospective recalls. Because what they
did is they just asked for retrospective recall and then had the performers keep a diary for a week
and then extrapolated it basically. Which by the way, don't even get me started on the noise that's
introduced by both of those decisions. Right. There was just a replication attempt by the way,
last month it published and failed, but we can talk about that if you want. But in that there was
actually in the new replication attempt, there was someone at 4,000 hours who got to the highest
group and someone at 11,000 hours who was still in the lowest group. But anyway, so he asked what's
the variance around that 10,000 hours? And Ericsson says, he said, first of all, there was inconsistent
recall. And so Tim says, yeah, a lot of us struggle with imperfect data, but we still put measures of
variance. And so Anders says, well, that'll be like more valid when we have video diaries and we can
really track it because we're not being that precise anyway. And he says, again, we all struggle
with imperfect data, but we include measures of variance. Was it? And then he asked, so what was
it? And he says, I don't know, I'd have to go look back. And so Lightfoot says, definitely more than
500. And that's where we leave it. And then I think two years ago, something couple of years ago,
Ericsson did publish measures of variance and turns out there was enormous variance. Not only was
there enormous variance in the original paper, the papers from 1993, and it was three or four
years ago that he finally published the variance made clear that their conclusions were wrong,
that there was not complete correspondence between the number of practice hours and the
group that someone was in. Well, I think that's sort of where I'm going with this question, which is
you can't even make an observation of statistical significance without variance. So I don't really
understand what the paper is saying. This is the first thing where I was reading it and saying,
something's not right here. And so then I started asking these very basic questions,
because I'd been an athlete, I'd gone from being like the worst walk on on my college team to being
like a university record holder. So I'm like, yeah, maybe if I had trained even more, I would have
been even better. And that probably is true. But but I was I was like, Oh, okay, so there is no such
thing as talent. I was convinced for a while. And then when I started seeing this, I started asking
the very basic questions like, okay, in my third year of training, I could break the women's world
record. So there has to be at least some basic genetic difference because I haven't worked harder
than the women who are pros by any stretch of the imagination. And so I said, Okay, let's start
with that basic question. I'd contact sort of some of the I shouldn't call them the 10,000 hours
researchers, because they kind of disavowed that, but the deliberate practice framework. And I
remember contacting one and saying, wouldn't you agree that a man and a woman who practice the same
like the man has advantages, which is why we separate sexes in sports. And she sort of hedged
and said, maybe not if they all trained the same. I said, Really? And so she sent me a paper saying
in fact, we think this applies to other organisms. If you look at this paper about racing dogs,
you'll see that they practice the best ones in the highest class practice about the equivalent to
their lifespan of 10,000 hours. And so I'm reading this, and I started reading all the citations. And
one of them notes that like half of these dogs have what is otherwise an incredibly rare myostatin
mutation. Let me pause for a moment explain to the listener what myostatin mutations are. So if you
knock out the myostatin gene, you look like a bodybuilder myostatin is a gene that inhibits
muscle growth. And there are lots of myostatin mutants out there that all have hypo functioning
myostatin and therefore super muscular. Yeah. And so racing readers had been, they didn't know about
the gene, but they were breeding for fast. They were clearly selecting for this trait. Yeah. Yeah.
And what they wanted was a single myostatin. And if you get to then you have a bully whip it and
Google that it's pretty cool to see bully with that thing probably can't even move. It's so big,
right? So they want the single mutation. Yeah. And so I'm like, okay, most of these dogs doesn't
even mean anything. So I wasn't gonna like use this study or anything. But I just started saying,
these people aren't reading the primary stuff that they're citing, or they're not tracking the
references back. And so I started to have doubts. Is this a broader problem with non experimental
science? I think so. Because we do the same dumb thing in medicine, by the way, people sort of
think of medicine, which we're going to get to in spades as it's so rigorous. And yeah, sometimes
medicine does get to leverage the scientific method and actually get to do what Francis
Bacon talked about. But a lot of times you don't. I mean, when you think of some of the most important
public health measures that are out there, oftentimes they are based on exactly the type
of inference you're being appropriately critical of, which is observational, heavily selected,
range restricted, which I can't wait to you talk about this so eloquently that I cannot wait to
have you go off on your tangent soapbox, whatever ran on that problem. But these are huge issues.
Yeah, yeah. I mean, that was the other thing. I don't know if I should skip to range restriction.
Well, let's start with medicine. So I wrote this one article when I was at ProPublica called
when evidence says no, and doctors say yes. And I should say, I love the medical profession,
I think it's filled with variety of people like any profession, but a lot of people who really
care and get into the profession because they want to do something that is challenging and useful.
But also there's like a lot of poor science and there are a lot of things that continue to be
done even once evidence shows they don't work anymore. What Mike Joyner at the Mayo Clinic
always calls bio plausible, something that clearly makes sense. It definitely should work. It's just
that when somebody does like a randomized controlled trial, it doesn't. You probably saw the
finished study of partial arthroscopic meniscus repair. I think there's a lot of devils in the
details. That said, it was interesting. They gave some people sham surgery where they basically made
an incision, banged around like they performed surgery and sent them to physical therapy. And
they did as well as the people who were getting the surgery, which is mind boggling because
everyone's doing something that seems like it has to work. Someone's got knee pain, you bring them in,
you give them imaging, they've got a tear, fix it. How could that not work? But then I guess it turns
out that some huge number of people have incidental tear that doesn't have anything to do with the
knee pain. The meniscal tear is a huge thorn in the side of the orthopedic specialty because,
frankly, I don't know the answer. I mean, my intuition is that that's a procedure that is
probably done far too much, but it's also probably a procedure that if you knew how to select the
right patients, you could probably make a difference. But because we don't, we end up
applying the tool far too broadly and we dilute the outcome. I'll give you a much more specific
example that is so nerdy, but there's a drug called azetamide or Zetia, which blocks cholesterol
reabsorption. So the body makes a ton of cholesterol. Virtually all the cholesterol in the body is made
by the body and it gets recirculated throughout the body. Well, part of this recirculation pathway
requires that cholesterol be dumped into, along with bile, into the gut. And then in your gut,
you can reabsorb it and the body has a way to regulate how much of that's happening. But it
turns out there's a drug that blocks this thing called the neiman pixie one like one transporter
that drags cholesterol back in. Now, when that drug is given in monotherapy, it lowers cholesterol,
but not that much and it doesn't save lives. So it's not a drug that's really, in fact,
it's absolutely therefore not considered a first line agent and it's never considered something
that should be used in isolation. Now, when you give it with a statin, it turns out it lowers
cholesterol and it reduces events. So the things that you care about, the actual heart outcomes
change. And it's not just the statin. Correct. That's right. Because you can compare it to statin
versus statin alone. So I have probably kind of a contrarian view on this, which is I actually
think this drug alone would work if you actually only gave it to people who were hyper absorbers.
But that's never been done because we can measure how much absorption capacity a person has. But
that's a kind of advanced measurement. You wouldn't normally do that in a clinical setting.
But if you select for patients who have mega amounts of absorption, it's certainly possible
that those patients. So I don't know the answer to this. And only if a trial was done testing that
way could you get it. But I do think that this problem exists in medicine, which is you dilute
by taking such a heterogeneous population to test an intervention on. And you're therefore not really
powered to detect an effect because in your power calculation, you're using the entire population as
your denominator. And really, it probably needs to be a subset. And so my intuition is that's
probably the case with some of these procedures like meniscal repairs, which still offers no help
to you or I right now if we're having knee pain with an MRI that shows a meniscal tear. I actually
don't know the answer in that setting. That's interesting on so many levels. The first is
what you're talking about with absorption is this sort of lesson that there's huge individual
variation in that stuff. Staggering variation, by the way. I measure absorption synthesis in every
single patient, non-negotiable, no questions asked. And I am constantly amazed at how much variation
exists. Basically, three variables are determining this, right? It's sort of how much do you make,
how much do you absorb, and how much do you clear out of circulation with the LDL receptor.
And the variation is overwhelming. And yet it's amazing to me that our profession looks at just
one metric, which is how much LDL cholesterol is there. And that's going to be the basis for
treatment. It strikes me as flying without instruments and deciding you only get to look
at the horizon. That's interesting. That gets at two things I want to remember. First, this idea
of the McNamara fallacy you've heard of named after the Secretary of Defense during Vietnam, which is
he said, are we winning the war or are we losing? Let's use something measurable, our bodies versus
their bodies. And since we're always winning, by that metric said, okay, we're winning, obviously
ignoring a lot of other important things. What's the collateral damage? And yeah, yeah. So it's like,
we often deem things important because they're easily measuring them because they're important.
But that individual variation gets to another thing that got me interested that sort of
caused the sports team to be very different from my proposal, which was underlying the 10,000 hours
rule, which is actually called the deliberate practice framework. So again, Erickson would not
call it the 10,000 hours rule. There's something called the monotonic benefits assumption. And
essentially, if you have two people who've never done something for every equal unit of practice,
they should progress exactly the same amount. So it's everyone's practice response is the same
is one of the assumptions underlying it. And I started, how can that be? It's not to say it's not
would be an interesting conclusion or but how could that even be the null hypothesis? It seems
so counterintuitive. I don't know does it? It might be if people started from zero. I'm not sure what
I would think if they would progress exactly the same or not. But then people have done those
studies. Meaning if we took 100 people who have never spoken Spanish and we gave them Spanish
lessons, give me the evidence that that if that were the case, wouldn't we see much more
homogeneity in schools? I would think I mean, Erickson would make the argument that well,
some of those kids are engaged and some of them aren't or maybe some of them had more practice
before. So I think to really evaluate this, you have to get some skill that nobody else
has tried before that these people haven't done at all, because who knows what they bring to
school, all sorts of other stuff. But there are studies like that where people who are sedentary
do the exact same exercise. One of the famous ones called the heritage family study where every
member of two generations of 98 families, totally sedentary, put on six months of identical cycling
training. And the range of variation was like 1000% doing identical training, identical training.
And you can see things like the military does this and people learning sort of perceptual
motor skills for air traffic controller simulations. And it very simple simulations,
actually, it's kind of like that, like they converge. If it's very simple, you just have to
see the one planes coming, move one off the runway. And then it becomes about like, how fast
can you basically just move the mouse when you're doing a simulation. But as it gets more complex,
people start diverging with more practice. And so that monotonic benefits assumption,
I could find no evidence of it. It's like never shown up in a study of anything unless it's an
extremely simple task that everyone masters very, very quickly. And so again, I was sort of saying
that average is just obscuring individual variation. So I keep preventing you from talking
about this because I can't stop asking those other questions. But when you look at the title,
the sports gene, the assumption would be, oh, this is a book that explores the notion that
a great athlete is genetically gifted. Michael Jordan is Michael Jordan because he clearly has
a set of genes that separate him from the rest of us. And that's probably a bad example because
it's so extreme. But talk to me about some of the things that you found in that book that
surprised you. And there were certain elements of that book that didn't get that much attention,
by the way, that I, in retrospect, thought I'm surprised more people didn't fixate on that thing.
Like, I don't know, did it surprise you what people drew out of that book as the most important
insights? Yeah, yeah, I didn't think the thing that people were going to find the most controversial
was the 10,000 hour rule, to be quite honest. I guess I didn't realize how ingrained that is
in our psyche. Yeah, and that people were actually planning certain training plans,
soccer teams to 10,000 hours on the dot. And the thing that was the most important to me,
I tried to write a book about one of my closest friends and former training partner
dropped dead at the end of a mile race. He was like one of the top ranked guys in his age group
in the country, young Jamaican guy was gonna be the first in his family to go to college,
all these things. And that kind of threw me for a loop. And anyway, I got his family to
sign a waiver allowing me to gather up his medical records and turn out he had hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy, textbook case, misdiagnosed, because not easy to diagnose. If he had had a
good family history, it turned out he probably clearly had a relative who it's like I went and
started going to meetings for families that think they have HCM in their family. And they'd say,
well, we're not really sure. But cousin Jimmy died in the pool, and he was a varsity swimmer.
And like Uncle Fred was in a one car accident. You're like, all right, these might be cardiac
arrest. And I wanted to write a book, one of the main reasons I got off the science tracks,
I wanted to write about sudden cardiac death and athletes. And that's what I tried to pitch a first
book on. But I didn't have the professional capital at the time and couldn't sell it. But
there's a section of that that I smuggled into one of the chapters in the sports team, which is
the most personally important thing to me that I don't think I got asked about one time ever. So
I don't know if that's surprising or not. It just is the most surprising findings of the book to me
were things like I still don't know how to summarize the book, but that things that I assumed
were genetic, like the reflexes it takes to hit 100 mile per hour fastball turn out not to be the
fact that major league baseball players don't have faster reflexes. That was a surprise to me.
I had assumed they did. The same is true, by the way, for Formula One drivers. Is it? Yeah. So it
turns out that makes sense. Perceptional motor skill, right? They're probably using cues like
the changing size of something in there. Well, one of my favorite exercises that you can see when you
compare. So if you put a novice next to Lewis Hamilton in a simulator, even adjusting for the
speed at which things are moving, you won't be blown away at where Lewis's eyes are at every
moment that he is driving, how far ahead he is able to see what's happening. So a few weeks ago,
I was on the track and in an effort to really force this type of learning, we have one camera
that is actually looking directly at me, one camera that is looking directly at the road and capturing
all of the telemetry. And then I sit with my coach and we review these two side by side, because what
I'm working very hard to overcome is the desire to narrow my field to where I'm driving. And when
you're going fast, that's innate. You don't want to be looking somewhere way down the road. You're
worried about falling off the road right now, but you can't do that. So that's the thing that they've
been able to train to do. It's not that they're going faster. Sorry, that's what they have faster
reflexes, which again, remember when I first was shown these data, I was like, wow, you're looking
at Senna. You'd think he has the fastest reflexes on the planet. Right, right. Once you start reading
about perceptual motor skills, it makes perfect sense because any activity that's happening too
fast, I mean, the things they have to do are too fast for any human, even if they did have
were the top 0.001% of human reflexes, it wouldn't be fast enough. So in boxing, there was this study
I came across doing this boardstain where these someone, I don't even know if they were doctors
or scientists did some tests of Muhammad Ali. I think that what they were trying to show was that
even this brilliant black man has slower than normal processing speed in his brain or something.
And so they reported his, they would have him like throwing a punch in response to a light or
something like that. And they were saying like, look, it's lower than average. And then, then
someone said that they were testing it wrong. If you subtract the delay for whatever cue they were
giving, he actually from first perceptible motion to full extension, it was like 150 milliseconds,
which is extremely fast. But that means when he's throwing a punch, also, I think other people throw
punches that fast. I don't think it was like an alone outlier for that, that it's faster than the
minimum human reaction time, which is a fifth of a second, just to see that something's in front of
you and for that message to get to your muscles, not to dodge. And so you literally have to be
seeing things before they happen or else you'd get hit by every punch. Of course, his genius at
disguising what he was doing and was an attempt to confound people's ability to see the future.
And so anything I think that's happening at that speed, those aren't skills that anyone comes with,
there might be things that facilitate you downloading that software, but it doesn't
doesn't come with the machine. You talk about kind versus wicked. I'm jumping between these books.
I think we're just going to end up doing that, by the way. I really wanted to talk about the gene,
but now I can't stop, but how moving. So maybe use that example in boxing as an example. Is boxing
a kind sport or is it a wicked sport and explain what those two distinctions mean? Yeah, kind and
wicked are. So those are terms coined by the psychologist Robin Hogarth and a kind learning
environment. He was trying to reconcile this issue in psychology and the study of expertise about
why some people who studied experts saw them get better and better and better with very narrow
experience. And some people saw them not get better, sometimes get worse or get more confident
and not get better. Like what was the difference? And it turns out that the difference often has a
lot to do with one, the way they're training, but also the environment that they are training in.
And a kind learning environment is one where all your information is clear. The next steps and
goals are totally clear. Work tomorrow will look like work yesterday. Patterns recur. And
whenever you do something, you get feedback that is immediate and fully accurate. On the other end
of the spectrum. So golf is a really kind learning environment because the ball is never actually
moving towards you. You're always starting with a static ball and there are almost a finite number
of things that you can see in that position and there's no rush. And you get automatic and
real time feedback every time something happens. So I think some of the people who study golf
characterize it as like almost an industrial task in the sense that part of what you're doing is
trying to do a similar things over and over with as little deviation as possible. Archery, which is
my obsession, a very kind learning environment. Absolutely. Totally kind. Absolutely. And a wicked
learning environment on the other hand is you might not know exactly what you're supposed to do next.
You might not even know the goal. Human behavior might be involved. There may be time pressure.
And work next year might not look like work last year. And importantly, you don't always get
automatic feedback. And sometimes when you get feedback, it's delayed and sometimes it's inaccurate.
There's actually a medical example that I know the story you're going to tell. Yeah, which is
this doctor, this New York doctor who got wealthy and famous because he could miraculously by
palpating patients tongues or feeling around their tongue with his hands before they showed any
symptoms, he could predict they would get typhoid. And he was right over and over and over again. And
one of his colleagues later observed using only his hands. He was a more productive carrier of
typhoid than even typhoid Mary. So he was giving people typhoid by touching their tongues and
getting the feedback that he was an amazing predictor and so would do it over. So he was,
the feedback was reinforcing the wrong lesson. So I wouldn't say most of us are in that wicked of a
situation either. But what Hogarth was doing was setting up this spectrum of learning. What do you
think is a bigger wickedness within the wicked environment? Because there are really at least two
variables that I think make that type of learning environment challenging. The first is the number of
scenarios you can face and the unpredictability of them. So an archery, the goal of archery actually
is to make every single shot identical non-negotiable. So everything from the way you stand
to the way your shoulder sits to the way the release sits, we pay tremendous attention to
the feeling of the string on the nose and the feeling of the string on the corner of the mouth.
You're trying to reproduce the same thing ever and ever. So part of it is, well in tennis for example,
there are an infinite number of ways that you could be standing and your opponent could be
standing and the ball could be coming with this spin versus that spin. Or maybe not infinite,
but there are so many more variables. The second piece is this delay between feedback and reality,
which anybody who's ever tried to talk when they can't hear themselves or when there's a delay
realizes how much feedback matters. Which of those two do you think is more important
in creating that environment? I think delayed feedback is usually a killer. I think that the
changing scenarios is easier to accommodate with broader training in some ways. So this classic
psychology finding that can be summarized as breadth of training predicts breadth of transfer.
Transfer is, and by the way, I'd say tennis is definitely more on the wicked end than golf,
but I would still... It's still not, yeah. As Hogarth said, most of us in the knowledge economy
are playing Martian tennis. You see some people playing, nobody's told you the rules, you have to
deduce them, and by the way, they can change without notice. And so breadth of training predicts
breadth of transfer. Transfer is the term psychologists use to mean your ability to
take skills and knowledge and apply them to a situation you haven't quite seen before. It might
be similar, but something's a little different. And what predicts your ability to do that is how
broad your training was. If your training is broad, it forces you instead of expecting the
same thing over and over to build these sort of flexible conceptual frameworks that you can bend
when you see a new problem instead of just doing the same thing over and over. So I think you can
mitigate that with the right kind of training. The delayed feedback, that really screws people up.
In studies where people have to sort of drive remote controlled things, if they build in a delay
between what they do and the movement, it completely screws them up. All the way to...
There's some interesting studies of software project managers. There's this famous essay.
I had to cut like 20 or 30,000 words from the book. This was something I had in there called
the Mythical Man Month. And it's an essay by this guy, Fred Brooks, who was like head of research at
Microsoft. And he went on to found the computer science department at the University of North
Carolina. And what he meant by the Mythical Man Month was he had noticed that when project
managers, when their projects got behind in software, if they were complicated, they would
start adding more person power, adding more man or woman power to the team. And that would cause
the project to become more late. And so Brooks's law is if you add people to an already late
software project, it will become more late in proportion to like how many people you add.
And that's because there was a delay between those people adding to the team. They needed to be
assimilated. And the managers never learned that lesson because of the delay. And so they keep
doing the same thing over and over and over. And a couple of researchers sort of followed up on that
more recently and call this the experience trap where these project managers, they come up with
simpler projects where adding people does help it get done faster because they can right away
figure out what to do. And then they get promoted and promoted and end up with more complicated
projects. And in those cases, they do the same thing and bring people on and they never learn
about the assimilation delay that it takes. So these researchers were saying we need to start
telling them, this is the time between you bringing someone on and them making a positive
impact. But they never learned that lesson because of the feedback delay. So I think that's
from the motor skills up to these much more sort of management kind of softer skills, the feedback
delay is really difficult. That concept ever since I read about it in your writing, I sort of look at
the world a bit differently now. I actually think of that question specifically. I'm like, how kind
is this? How wicked is this right now? That's what happened when I was reading this. I was like, oh,
this is going to be the frame that I'm going to think through. I bet for everything in this book.
Well, I think about it a lot with kids. You have a kid, right? You've got one.
One, seven months.
Yeah. So, I mean, think about the learning that's taking place. Think about the neuroplasticity of
a seven month old. And for example, it's why, sort of going back to the example before, if a child
is deaf, it's going to delay speaking, not because they can't speak, but because they can't get that
real time assimilation and feedback. And watching, it almost makes you think about how much do you
want to intervene when they're doing something wrong too? I don't know if you've found that,
but it's like, okay, as long as they can't really hurt themselves, I should probably let them do
that thing that is going to hurt, but hopefully not irreversibly hurt.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, then that's a huge question again. Like I said, what I think of as this would
make a terrible subtitle, so it's not the subtitle of my book range is the things that you can do
that seem the best in the moment, maybe are not the best for long-term development. And I think
that applies to like parenting. Maybe we should talk about the college admission scandal or
something. The snowplow parent isn't the new, but clearly that's not the best for long-term
development in many cases. There's a story you write about, I think it's at the Air Force Academy.
Yeah. That illustrates that point. Yeah. Explain that insight. This was one of my favorite studies
in range, partly because the experimental setup is so cool. You could only do this at the US Air Force.
It's a true experiment. It has randomization, it's prospective, and there's blinding. Check all the
boxes. Yeah. Yeah. So at the US Air Force Academy, about a thousand students come in every year,
and they have to take a sequence of three math courses, Calculus I, II, and third course. And
they are randomized to professors in year one, re-randomized in year two, and re-randomized in
year three. And the characteristics they come in with are spread evenly across classes. And so a
pair of scientists wanted to see, okay, this is a great experimental setup for looking at what is
the impact of different math teachers. So they followed about a hundred professors and 10,000
students over a decade. And one of their main findings was that the better a professor was,
oh, and everyone takes the same test in every class also, and it's graded by committee, so there's no
one can make their own students do better. What they found was the better a professor was at getting
their students to overperform in Calculus I, the more those students then underperformed in the
next two follow-on courses. So there's an inverse relationship between how well students with a
certain professor did in the first course and how well they did in the second and third. So for
example, and how they rated their teachers. So I think the professor who was rated the sixth best
by his students in Calculus I and his students got the seventh best scores overall, I think,
out of a hundred professors, his students did the seventh best, was dead last in how his students
then did in the next two courses. And essentially it turned out- And just to be clear, were they dead
last or were they dead last in improvement? So there was a value added score which said here are
the characteristics these kids come in with, and here's how we'd expect them to do. Are they over
or underperforming? Yeah, so it's not that they were the worst in Calc II, it's that they underperformed
relative to where they came in. That's right. So they grew the least maybe is the right way to
think of this. That's right, yeah, absolutely. Compared to other people who came, other students
who came in with the exact same characteristics, they did worse than them in the following courses.
And what these scientists found was that the way to get students to do the best in Calculus I was
to teach a very narrow curriculum that was tailored to the test where they learn a lot of what's called
using procedures knowledge, where they just learn how to execute algorithms and things like that over
and over. Whereas the professors who got rated worse by their students and their students did worse
on the Calculus I test, they learned more called making connections knowledge, where you have to
draw together concepts essentially, and you're facing different types of problems instead of
repeating the same type over and over, which is another thing we should talk about after this. But
then when they go to the next courses, they have this more conceptual flexible knowledge. They're
learning how to match a strategy to a type of problem instead of just how to execute procedures.
So they do better later on. And so there's this real conflict between how they feel they're doing
early, and how they rate their professors, and how they're really being set up for later success,
which is kind of wild. And that spoke to me on many levels, but one of which being is I love
mathematics. And I think we spoke before, and maybe we'll tell the story, get into that, get into the
issue later about, I've always wondered about the transition I made when I decided to take school
seriously. But that teacher who I think sort of turned my life around would go on to teach me
Calculus as well. And he had a very unique style of teaching, which was you approach every problem
through the lens of understanding what is being asked physically, and seeing if in the end the
question says, okay, Johnny throws a ball at this speed in this angle, where does it land? That might
be the question. I mean, that's a very simple calculus question, but that's an example. But
as the problems get more and more challenging, he would still really insist that you try to
understand graphically using sort of functional calculus, like graphically what is happening,
algebraically what is happening and numerically what is happening. And how can you converge the
numerical solution with the algebraic solution with the graphical solution? He said, in calculus,
you should almost always be able to come up with an estimate of where the answer is based on
graphing the functions and looking at how they behave. Hard. I mean, a lot of kids
didn't do very well in calculus, and yet those lessons took me all the way through honors math
and engineering. And another sort of example on that path that really spoke to me was in my
freshman year of calculus, I met this guy studying in the stacks. His name was JP, and he became a
legend to me because he had simultaneously, he couldn't decide if he wanted to be a mechanical
engineer or an electrical engineer, so he did both. And he literally got both degrees in four years.
It's not impossible to get both of those degrees in five or six years, but to do both in four years
is crazy. And he said the only way he was able to do it was he never wanted to memorize how a type
of problem was solved. He wanted to derive everything from first principles. At the time,
I think we were learning about Coriolis acceleration, which is basically the acceleration
of a body in rotation where the radius is changing. So named after a guy who failed to
figure this out when miners in a shaft were moving down. So now you actually had a shrinking radius
relative to the center of the earth, and that changes the forces on the elevator shaft.
And he said, you realize you could derive that all from Newton's first law. And I was like,
I never thought of it that way. And he goes, yeah, let's go through it. And it's about a one-page
derivation, but you can do it. And that lesson stuck with me for the remainder of my life,
which was, oh my God, if you just think of it in these broader, initially more painful ways,
it yields huge dividends. This gets at so many things. I'm not even sure where to start and
range. But first thing popped my head was I just saw somebody tweeting research on Twitter today
about how active learning students actually learn more, but they rate themselves as having learned
less. And they also rate their teachers worse. So it turns out we're early on, we're not actually
that good evaluators of how we're doing because the feeling of fluency and learning makes us think
we're doing well, but but we're actually not is what I wrote about called desirable difficulties.
But what you were talking about, I mean, that's serious making connections knowledge. In Japan,
they actually have a term called ban show that means the type of writing on the blackboard that
tracks all these different approaches to the same problem, sort of what it sounds like your teacher
was doing. But I want to get to the derivation point, because there was some research I wrote
only a little bit about in range, but that I read a lot more about that was about what college
students understand about math, essentially. And there were some really startling examples where
one of the problems was like, I can't remember what the exact numbers were. But let's say it was
500 plus 200 equals 700. And the students were asked, how can you check if this was right? And
so I'd say, okay, 700 minus 200 equals 500. Right. What's another way you can check if it's right,
and they wouldn't come up with 700 minus 500 equals 200, because they were taught to subtract
the number on the right of the addition sign. And when their professors were shown this sort of
stuff. So this is wicked feedback. So you get the feedback that the student understands, because they
know one way to do it, but they actually don't understand at all. And the professors would say,
oh my gosh, and the students would in interviews, they'd say like math is a system of rules and
executed procedures. Professors would say like, I went into math because I didn't have to memorize
stuff, because you could derive it. And it makes sense. It's just concepts. And so they were just
in a totally different place than the students were. And it sounds like you had some opportunity
to avoid that. But I think that's the norm of how math teaching works. Yeah. And it's hard because
my daughter who's in sixth grade, I'm doing this thing. And it's really hard. I mean, I can't
imagine I'm the only parent that struggles with this, but I want her to love math. I don't want
her to view it as a subject. I want her to view it as math is more fun than playing video games.
Math is the most beautiful thing in the world. I want her to look out the window and see math,
and see that math is a beautiful tool that we have to explain the world around us through this thing.
And yet every time as a parent, I try to ask her a question to ask her to think a certain way,
I end up sort of putting her on the spot. And so I'm struggling with this thing of,
one, is it just that I'm a bad parent and I don't know how to do this correctly? Definitely.
You're a bad parent. I didn't want to say anything, but since you brought it up.
Or is it that a child needs a certain base of facts? Like they have to know a handful of things
and be confident with the language, like the times tables and all these other things before
you can even get them to start thinking beyond the problem. I think a lot about this actually,
because I feel like I'm underperforming on this actually. It's a good point though, and I should
say, so again in research, these are called using procedures knowledge, which is kind of the knowing
stuff and making connections knowledge, which is derivation, understanding concepts. And they're
both important. It's just that like in some of these famous studies in the United States, almost
100% essential, sometimes literally 100% in classrooms would be the using procedures knowledge
and not the making connections. But I think that is a tricky thing. There's a study that came out
after range, so I couldn't include it, but was on the topic of desirable difficulties. And it was
about interleaving, which is, well, I'll explain the study. Seventh grade math classrooms were
randomly assigned to different types of math teaching. Some of them got what's called blocked
practice, where you get problem type A, A, A, A, A, B, B, B, B, and so on. And the students get
better really quickly, and they rate their teachers well, they rate their own learning well.
Other classrooms got interleaved practice, where it's like as if you threw all the problem types
in a hat and you pick out randomly. And that condition, the students are frustrated at first,
they rate their own learning low, they rate their teachers poorly. But again, they're learning how
to match a strategy to a type of problem instead of just do the same thing over and over and come
test time, they all took the same test. The interleaving students who had interleave practice
blew the block practice students away. It was, I think, like the largest effect size I've ever
seen in an education study that was randomized, 0.83 standard deviations, it was like taking a kid
from the 50th percentile and moving them to the 80th percentile. But they didn't like it early on,
they don't feel like they're learning. And so I'm not sure what the balance is as a parent,
where you know some of this desirable difficulty is in the long term desirable,
but you also don't want to turn someone off from the subject. So what's that delicate balance? I
think that's sort of kind of the art of coaching and everything we do, whether that's someone in
sport trying to develop someone for the long term or a parent is like, how do you balance
maintaining enthusiasm with optimal development, and helping someone have that vision of their
future self like your professor did for you without having them be burned out? I don't know.
I really think that's why there's what like great coaches kind of do is they figure out how to
balance these things when to make things difficult and when to allow things to be easy and sort of
more easily inspirational. But I think that's an art as well as a science. So what was sort of the
takeaway of the idea that, and I don't like using the extreme examples because they're
more to silly and that's the problem with them, but if you look at a high school track team,
okay, and you look at you pick a big division one school, and you look at their sprinters,
are they genetically predisposed to be sprinters, but without a certain degree of training could
never appreciate it? Or could a certain amount of training overcome a lack of genetic predisposition?
I mean, how do you feel about that today versus when you wrote the book versus when you wrote the
article? Because again, you're getting smarter as we go. Yeah, when I wrote the article, I was more
convinced than I had been before the article that genes were unimportant, completely unimportant.
And by the time I wrote the book, I came to feel that there were sort of two extreme camps,
one that felt genes have no influence on performance, and another that I'd say the other
extreme wasn't that practice has no influence. I don't think anybody thought as uncontroversial.
So I think one extreme was only practice matters. And the other extreme was practice and genes
matter. I think that is not as extreme saying they both matter. Which and my bias is the latter. My
bias is just that I mean, that's what the evidence shows. And it's like, people don't randomly pick
to train for the marathon to the 100 meters if they're trying to get to the top level,
because there's some zero some physiology going on there. And so I think to be a sprinter, you're
not turning a cart horse into a racehorse as the saying goes, like you have to have some predisposition
to being fast and being explosive. And there's a reason why those people are particularly bad.
Usain Bolt would be a worse marathon runner than a random person picked off the street,
because it's different physiology. But, but I also think it's important to note that at the
beginning of the season and six months later, someone like him are very different in how fast
they are, even over the course of one season, they change how fast they are. So I think the
practices is incredibly important, but you also need talent. Now, which is maybe a reasonable segue
into a story that I know you just get asked about all the time. So but I also feel like for the
sake of the listener, if they haven't heard you on another podcast, it's worth them hearing you
explain the difference between Roger Federer and Tiger Woods. But of course, I once you're done
with this, I want to kind of go down more extreme examples and stuff. So is it safe to say that the
contrast between Tiger and Roger are elite examples of opposing views? Yeah, yeah, definitely. And it's
sort of interesting because well, I'll give the quick versions of the story first before I
criticize myself. The Tiger Woods story, I think, even if people don't know the details, they probably
kind of absorbed the gist. Seven months old father gives him a putter not trying to turn him into a
golfer, by the way. Oh, this reminds me, we should talk about how the Tiger and Mozart stories I
think are told wrong after this. So I'm just putting that on our court board here. 10 months,
he starts imitating his father's swing. Two years old, you can go on YouTube and see him on national
television, demonstrating his swing on the Mike Douglas show at three or four, he starts saying
I'm gonna be the next Jack Nicholas. Fast forward to age 21. He's greatest golfer in the world. And
that's sort of the quintessential I think that story has seeped into culture so much that people
don't even follow golf ever kind of know it. Federer on the other hand, every bit is famous as an
adult, but obscure every bit is dominant. I mean, it's dominant and more so over a longer time for
sure. And when he was a kid, he played some basketball badminton tennis. His mother was a
tennis coach refused to coach him because he wouldn't return balls normally. He continued on
to skateboarding, swimming, wrestling, soccer. When his coaches want to move him up a level,
he declined because he just want to talk about pro wrestling with his friends after practice.
He went on to play handball. Maybe I said volleyball already. I'm not sure some rugby.
Do we know how good he was at these other sports, by the way, he was good at soccer,
for sure. Most the other sports, I'm not really sure. But he kept playing badminton basketball
soccer, longer than some of the others. And then soccer was the one that he finally decided he had
to he had to choose between soccer and tennis. And what age is that when he's having to make
that decision? I think he was starting to think about that as he was like entering his teens,
and he wasn't focused. Tiger saying I'm music, Nick, this one I'm for Roger was actually when
he first got good enough to get interviewed by local paper. The reporter asked him if he ever
became a pro what would he buy with his first hypothetical paycheck and he says Mercedes his
mother doesn't want him putting all his eggs in this basket is like appalled and asked the
reporter if she can hear the interview recording and the reporter obliged as it turns out Roger
said mercedes in Swiss Germany just wanted more CDs, not a Mercedes and so his mom's like,
all right, fine. But it's just very different in every way from the tiger story. And the way I
sort of use these as a device to start range first to set up just the concept going forward,
the book proposal was titled Roger versus Tiger, and it was going to be like, when should you be a
Roger? And when should you be a tiger? But they felt everyone would think it was a biography of
those two guys, my publisher, and I thought it was telling that we only know only hear one of those
stories. And my question was, which of these is the norm? Obviously, they both worked for these
individuals. And I think there's many paths to the top as there are people. But what was the norm?
And it turns out that the norm when scientists track athletes en route to becoming elite is
that early on, they tend to have what they call a sampling period, where they try a wide variety of
activities. That often includes things like martial arts and dance and doesn't just have to be other
sports gymnastics. And they learn these broad general these physical skills. And they learn
about their interests and their abilities, importantly, and delay specializing until later
than peers who plateau at lower level. And that turns out to be the norm. And so I sort of felt we
should let people know what the norm is instead of always focusing on these very few exceptions that
happen to be in like the most kind learning environment sports and that aren't that good to
extrapolate to everything else. Now, how much of that do you think is the psychology of it and
the neuromuscular physiology of it? So looking at Roger, for example, who I know very little about
Roger Federer. That's not the obvious stuff that most people who are not. I'm not a tennis
fan or anything like that. But part of his longevity, is it possible to be explained by
the fact that he never burnt out versus just sort of slowly acquired a love for this thing versus
had it shoved down his throat? I'm sure like there's lots of stories of trying to create these
tennis prodigies where it probably backfires because by the time the kid is 16, they're great,
but they've lost the desire. So it's more of a above the neck phenomenon than a below the
like environment. How much of it do you think is that versus in playing all those other sports,
Roger actually developed synaptic connections that served him better in tennis. He basically
created a bigger foundation across his neuromuscular system that ultimately came to serve him when he
specialized. So there are a couple points. So this will be a sort of a longer point for us because
you bring up a couple good things. Initially, I thought that most of the effect was going to be
accounted for by the fact that if you allow people to delay selection, it's more likely you get them
in the sport that they're the best at. Whereas we know the earlier you force selection, the more
likely you put the wrong person in the wrong sport. And when selection occurs really early,
you end up seeing this huge relative age effect where coaches just pick for kids who are born
early in the selection year because they're seven or eight or nine or 10 months older than their
cohort. And so they're at young ages, that's a huge difference. And so coaches mistake biological
maturation for talent. So I thought most of it was just going to be the fact that if you delay
selection more, you'll get the right people in the right sport more. But then I started coming
across these studies of German national soccer players or people in the national development
pipeline, where they were matched for ability at a certain age, tracked for several years, and they
see who improves more. And at certain ages, you have to focus eventually, but at certain ages,
like in the early and mid teen years, it was those who did a wider variety of activities.
And so then I started to think maybe there really is something to the skill benefit,
which didn't surprise me intuitively, but I didn't to see it empirically was interesting. And then I
spent some time with I should say, by the way, my colleague, John Worth, I'm asked Roger Federer
about this, one of the questions you asked on the tennis channel recently. And Roger Federer said
it contributed to his not burning out, you know, you never know how much to trust someone's own
story. But it's worth noting that that's what he said. I spent some time with this physiologist
for Cirque du Soleil. And he noted that they started implementing this program where some of
the performers are former Olympians and things like that to where they would have performers learn
the basics of three other performers disciplines, not because they were ever going to perform them,
but to see if it would vary up what they were doing, maybe reduce stress related injuries and
stuff like that. And they track their injuries next to Canadian gymnastics, I guess it's a Canadian
company. And he said it reduced their injuries by like a third. So they implemented it, they must
feel really strongly about it if they're taking away from practice time for those performers,
their main discipline, there seems to be something this showed up in another longitudinal study of
young athletes, where the best predictor of suffering what they called an adult style over
use injury was how specialized the athlete was. And it wasn't necessarily their total time spent
in physical activity, it was if it was just the same thing over and over. So there was like some
protective effect from diversifying, we can guess at what that is, I'm sure your guesses would be
better than mine. But ultimately, my feeling is the roger pattern is more prevalent. One, because
you have that breadth of training that predicts breadth of transfer, you're exposed to much more
neuromuscular stuff, much more perceptual stuff. And when the challenge gets harder, as you go up,
you need to draw on those. There's a funny book called extraordinary tennis for the ordinary
player, I think by this guy, Cy Ramo, who's better known as the father of intercontinental
ballistic missiles, but also wrote some books about tennis and a couple other things. And in
one of the interesting things in it was that he shows he does some like serious analysis of
gameplay at different levels and shows that even for good amateur players, something like 80 or 90%
of the points are scored by just keeping the ball in play and someone making an error. And then when
you get to the elite level, it's totally exactly the opposite. It's like 80 90% of points have to
be earned. And that completely changes the kind of game that you're seeing. Because I think the
challenge that a lot of these athletes are facing really changes a lot as they go up in levels. And
so they really want to have that kind of breadth of training in this experience responding to
different types of things. Do you think this overlaps with the Air Force Academy example, where
having the harder, more orthogonal education in calculus prepares you for more real world
problem solving, which is what's happening as you go from calc one to two to three?
I think so. I think so. And I mean, again, that's why I think the theme of the book is the things
that will cause you to be the best today might not be the best for five or 10 years from now,
the best way to develop a 10 year old might not be the best way to develop a 20 year old,
or certainly isn't. And it's also I think the specialization model may well there's a surprising
dearth of research and golf for how popular sport it is. But I think the specialization model may
well work for golf, because you're not facing some of that same stuff. It is a very kind learning
environment. And I mean, I guess the best guy in the world right now, Brooks Kepka didn't come
until later. And it's unclear if he even likes golf, but I could see it makes sense to me that
the specialization model would work or at least not be deleterious in golf, whereas in the other
sports. What about the sports where physiology is undeniably huge? So the big three being swimming,
cycling and running. Cycling is hard to talk about because people tend to conflate the use of drugs
with somehow discounting the remarkable physiology of these guys. But if you take a Chris Froome,
for example, four time Tour de France champion, grows up in Kenya, we can speak to what the
importance of early exposure to hypoxia could have been. What is our belief about the training
effect and the duration of the training effect necessary to produce world class athletes at that
level? Because to me, that's as foreign like if you said to me, Peter, I'm going to put you in a
time capsule. You're going to be 16 or 14 years old again, knowing everything you know today,
if you have to become a professional athlete, which sport would it be in? The answer is none.
I positively know there's nothing I could ever be good enough in. And that includes if I was
willing to do everything that was necessary to become the best cyclist, runner or swimmer.
You have to do what some countries host the Olympics. What they focus on is
just recruiting more people in the much less competitive sports.
If there's a basket weaving, I have a friend who joked about this because my interests are so
diverse. He goes, Peter, do you realize that if someone comes up with an Olympic sport that
requires solving a differential equation, driving a car fast, shooting a bow and arrow, and doing a
deadlift, you could be one of the best. That's basically modern pentathlon. You're pretty much
there. And he listed off 10 other really stupid esoteric things I do. And I'm like, yep, that's
great. That's my claim to fame. Modern pentathlon is like fencing, horse riding, swimming, running.
It's like, we should have that. I think there was a time when chess and fiction writing were in the
Olympics. So there's hope for you. I suck at both of those things. Or like the Brits, I think, in the
winter sports when Skeleton got introduced, which is where you slide. Yeah, hilarious. And there's
a great innovation story about that if we want to get to that. But one of the guys who I talked to
in their program said, we've got this down like 80% to a science. We make like an open call for
women. We do some measurements. We know what size they need to be. We know what kind of explosion
they need to have. We pick the gold medalist and they've done that. So that stuff's kind of amazing.
But do you think that for these super physiologic things where presumably mitochondrial density,
mitochondrial efficiency, fiber distribution matter the most? Is that more of a golf? Is that
more Tiger? Is that more Roger? Not withstanding the psychological component, which is obviously
enormous. So I think in sports in general, more people, 100 years ago, you could have come to the
Olympics and been the only person to do anything about training or the only person who was really
talented and win. Now, I think in every sport, many more people are ruled out by either their
nature or their nurture, no matter what the sport is. But I think in those, meaning they're not
willing to train hard enough, no matter how much their ability. So that rules or they don't have the
opportunities. I mean, a huge portion of people in the world don't have an opportunity to be exposed
to most sports. So they don't have the opportunity. I mean, I think one thing, the impact of Title IX
in the US is showing in how dominant we are in some women's sports, where I think I just saw
a stat. I think Ross Tucker, he's at Science of Sport, prominent sports scientist. He tweeted that
the United States has something like 40% of all the women's registered soccer players in the world.
So like, of course, we're awesome, because we're giving more opportunities. So I think a lot of
people, either they're not willing to train, they don't have access to training, one of those, or
they don't have the nature for it. And the more competitive the sport is, the more important that
is, right? Because obviously, if we had everyone do identical training, only genes would separate
them. And if we had everyone be identical twins, only training would separate them. But I think
people are more quickly filtered out by their nature and things like sprinting.
And so how old are you?
I'm 38.
38. So I'm 10 years older than you. But directionally, like we're both clearly past our prime,
right? In the sense of like sports wise, sports wise. Yeah, I think I'm past my prime and everything.
Clearly athletically. Is there a reason that I, let's assume I'm a decent athlete, which I'm
actually not, but let's assume I was. Could I, if I decided tomorrow, like I want to play tennis,
I don't think anybody would ever assume I could become a good tennis player.
But is it because the deliberate practice argument would be there aren't enough hours
left for you to devote to this? Another argument would be no, you've missed a critical window.
Just as we say, by the way, this might be totally BS. I'd like to hear your view on it. This view
that we learn languages best at a certain window. And once that window closes, it's sort of like a
growth plate closing over a bone. It becomes really hard to learn languages thereafter.
Is there something about this critical window of exposure? I guess is really the thing I'm trying
to get at with this question when it comes to physical talent.
That's a tough question. And there's this book by a neurologist called Why Michael Couldn't Hit.
And it's about why I love this book was one of my favorite books.
So he was saying Michael Jordan kind of missed the critical window for developing the perceptual
anticipation skill that you need to see things that are coming because your reflexes are too slow.
Why the greatest athlete we'd ever seen of a generation was a 188 hitter in AAA ball.
Yeah, I'm a little bit of a gadfly about that, though, because I think that was a great book.
I love the book. I love the Wayne Gretzky story, by the way, but we'll come back to another.
And one season, I think Michael hit like 220 or something like that in the minors,
which I think if we went down and picked a random person off the street, they would hit zero
in double A. These are people who are stars of college and high school teams or foreign teams.
So did he do well or poorly? I don't know. If he had hit 10, you know, I wouldn't have been
surprised because he hadn't been playing in a long time. So I'm kind of impressed with what he did.
But I also think there is something to I mean, I think the point, though, was the expectation.
It's not that hitting 288 or whatever in AAA ball is horrible. No, it's just why isn't the
guy that seemingly has the best hand-eye coordination in the world immediately able to absorb it?
Right. And in that sense, I do think there was probably something to the critical period.
And there are always people there are always exceptions to everything. One of the most
dynamic players in baseball now is Lorenzo Cain. And he did not play a game of baseball until age
16. That surprises me. He did not know how to play. I think most people would need to have some
exposure, not necessarily specialized, but have some exposure at that age. So there's always
exceptions. But I do think you want some of that early exposure, partly just because you run out
of time because you want your perceptual expertise to coincide with your physical. Yeah. Right. So
you're just under a serious time limit. And in relating that the language, I actually do think,
and you know, there was a guy who tried dropped everything when he read about the 10,000 hour
rule and decided to try to become a pro golfer by doing 10,000 hours exactly. No,
and he got Erickson to consult with him and everything to name Dan McLaughlin. How far did
he get? He got to something like 7,000 hours or something like that. And then he stopped. He was
having injuries. And what happened was, I think he didn't make it and he didn't nearly make it,
but he got really good. So he got better than like 90% of amateurs or something,
but wasn't nearly going to get into Q school qualifying for a professional tour. And so what
I think, and I didn't know if he was going to make it or not, because my point has been like,
people were saying, Oh, you were right. He didn't make it. I wrote a little bit about him. I'm like,
that's not what I said. I said, there's huge individual variation. If he's going to make it,
it's not going to be exactly 10,000 hours. And so he didn't make it. By the way, do you think
there's enough variation that it almost is uncoupled? Like what would be your 90% confidence
interval on that? Or does it even matter? I mean, I think there has to be a 90% confidence interval.
Right. If you think about it, is it a thousand to 40,000? If you had to say 90% of people that
become, that achieve mastery do so in a certain amount of deliberate practice.
I think it really depends on the sport. I listed in the sports team, I listed some hours and it
varied a lot by sport. And so I think it sort of depends what it is. Most of them were in sports
were lower than 10,000 hours significantly, four to 6,000 hours kinds of things. And again,
these are averages in chess. It was higher than that. So I think it depends. I think it's sport
dependent. And again, something like skeleton, there's a great paper called ice novice to
winter Olympian in 14 months, where it's basically just pick somebody and then they're, they can go
to the Olympics. So I think it depends on what you're doing. And also when I sat in a Harvard
Business School class for some reporting I was doing for range, you just reminded me of something
where the professor asks the students, he asked them all these things like, how many subway
sandwich shops do you think there are in America? Give your 90% confidence interval. And basically,
we can't do it. Because if you're asked that question, if you're asked 20 of those questions,
you should be able to get 18 correctly in a reference range. I've played this game myself
and with people, I've never seen anybody come close to it. People don't go big enough, give
your 90% confidence interval and you'd be better off going like, well, I know there's 10, you know,
to like a million and instead they go much narrower and they end up missing almost all of them.
So what would my 90% confidence interval be? And it sort of, it depends what counts too,
because there's some accounts of athletes who have done a bunch of different sports. So there
are studies that show that invasion sports are the ones that require anticipatory skills. People
can't see me doing air quotes, I guess we're on a podcast, but that's the term that they use in the
invasion sports where you have to anticipate things that are happening faster than you can react to
boxing, soccer, whatever, baseball, things are flying, trying to get past you. There's some
studies that show that people who have done a variety of invasion sports will then pick up
any subsequent invasion sport more rapidly. And so I think there was a case of one woman who
had played a variety of sports and then it only took her like 500 hours to become one of the best
basketball players in the world, but she'd played netball and she'd played a whole bunch of other
sports, volleyball and all this stuff. So it sort of depends what do you count as deliberate,
like Erickson wouldn't count that as deliberate practice because it's not the same sport,
but clearly it is like lowering the threshold. Well, and that's really the Federer point,
isn't it? It's that all those other sports he's doing, soccer, badminton, et cetera. I mean,
there's still training in a more diffuse way, a set of skills that obviously have gone on to
serve him greatly in tennis. Yeah. And I think this relates to language. I want to segue to
language a little bit, which is I wanted to write about language in the book. As I was going through
all the research, I found so much of it contradictory and confusing that I decided
to kind of stay away from it largely because I just couldn't figure out. I was hoping there'd
be in my proposal, I wrote about this. I'd seen this really cool study and I had video for it
where infants who were being raised bilingual, they were given like this leucite box sort of thing
and plexiglass or whatever it was. And there was some object and they had to find the opening in
this clear box and get an object out of it and then put some other object in it. And the ones
who were bilingual would try more different strategies. And the researchers were saying,
well, they think differently and they have more executive function. And I thought that was
tantalizing and I loved the video, but I just, the research was all over. And my conclusion was kind
of, there's a lot of tantalizing stuff, but nobody's quite sure really for a lot of it. But one that
I did think was pretty strong was the idea that people who grew up bilingual had an advantage
for then learning a third language without being taught it formally. So there were studies where
they'll be given like a fake made up language and fake grammar and just have to learn it by immersion
and they seem to do that better. And I think that's sort of akin to what we see in sports.
And with regard to the sensitive period, I do think there is a real sensitive period in language
where I think about after like age 12, you're not going to make something your native language
anymore. And I think there are cases where kids, feral children cases, these rare cases where a
kid like grows up in the woods or isolated from people. And if they haven't learned some, if they
haven't had exposure to language by age 12, they never learn it basically. And that also happens
to be about the age you have to start. If you don't start studying chess patterns by age 12,
your chances of reaching international master status drop. International master status, again,
one down from grandmaster. They drop from like one in four to one in 55. So I think there are some
critical periods, but I don't think for most things, maybe for these feral children, but for
most things, I don't think it's nearly the expiration date that people think it is. I think
most people can get better at most things than they think they can. And they can get better most
things than they think they can at older ages than they think they can too. Yeah, it's funny you say
that that's kind of where I wanted to pivot for a second, which was all of this discussion is
interesting through the lens of being the absolute best tennis player or the absolute best golfer on
the planet. But isn't that really besides the point for most of us? Because if there's seven
billion of us on this planet, 6.999999 billion of us are never going to be good enough at anything
to make a living at it outside of our day jobs anyway. I was asked on a podcast recently why I
love archery and driving a race car so much. And part of it is there is still every six months,
I'm still able to look back and appreciate the progress I've made. In other words, I'm coming
from a place of being so not expert at these things that the joy is actually in the monotonic
increase in skill. That is actually the joy to me. It's the, I don't want to say mastery because
that implies you are mastering it, but it's the path towards mastery that is more joyous. And
I don't know, it's almost like on some levels it must, maybe it's not that much fun to be the best
in the world at something because by definition you only have one way to go at some point. And
that's probably a lot less enjoyable than working your way up the curve. And I guess generalists
have the ability to, I don't know, this gets more into the psychology, but again, but you don't have
to tether your identity to just this one thing. I always feel bad actually for athletes who,
it's a brutal, brutal way to make a living in the sense that you have a far narrower window in which
you can be the best at something versus like say any sort of normal career. Yeah. And if you
interact with a lot of athletes, you hear a lot of them say now it's just a job and it's something
that they loved at a certain point. I think we were talking about Ayrton Senna earlier. I seem
to recall him saying something like the times of the sport that he loved the most were not when he
was necessarily on the top of the world. It was earlier. It was actually during his last two
seasons in karting. It was racing this British guy named Fullerton. Everything he did that karting
was his favorite time. Absolutely. It was pure bliss, no politics as he said, just pure racing.
I just actually interviewed a friend of mine the other day, this podcast, it'll come out at some
point in relation to this one. I'm not sure when, but same question I asked her, she's an Olympian.
And it was like, okay, you were the second best in the world on this day. You got a silver medal.
When was the sport the most fun? And it's like, oh yeah, two years before I went to my first
Olympics was when it was its most fun. Yeah, yeah, it's amazing. I mean, this makes me think of so
many things. One, I think people that are performers need other stuff to do. There was a study I
mentioned in range where Nobel laureates are 22 times more likely than a typical scientist have
like a serious aesthetic hobby, even though they're certainly not as good at it as they are at their
day job. For me, I noticed while I was writing this book somewhere along the line, I sort of
started to forget what I loved about writing, I think. And I keep this thing I call my little
book of small experiments where at least every other month, I think of some skill I'd like to
learn a little bit about or some interest I'd like to explore a little bit. And I put a hypothesis
of well, what could I try to almost like my grad student notebook? What could I try to get some
insight into this and it forces me to try something new every other month. It doesn't have to be a big
deal. Maybe it's some job that I don't know about. I just have to find somebody to talk to about it.
But when I was sort of losing my enthusiasm for the kind of writing I was doing and starting to
feel more pressure because my first book was a surprise success. And then all of a sudden,
you get a lot more pressure after that. I took an online beginner's fiction writing course. I've
been reading this book about the Zen concept of beginner's mind, where you just always keep your
mindset as a beginner never as I've arrived. And in this class, it's like, nobody cares who you are,
nobody cares what you've done, you get back into that feeling of being uncomfortable. And I loved
it. I mean, it reminded me what I loved about doing this, it made me totally uncomfortable,
because it's still writing, but it's very, very different. I think it had these huge benefits.
Like one of the exercises was you had to write a story using no dialogue whatsoever. And after I
did that, I went back to my book manuscript that I had and was like, I've been leaning on quotes in
a lazy way when I don't understand stuff. I don't understand it, the reader is not going to understand
it. So I need to learn it better and clarify with narrative writing instead of people's voices. And
so in every way, it refreshed me. And so now it's like something I really, I really want to do. And
one of the kind of share this will attack on another story here, but this is one of the greatest
things I've ever seen in sports live has to do a little bit with this having something else going
on your identity, which was at the Vancouver Winter Olympics in 2010. Yeah, 2010. I was up at
the women's 1.6 K cross country sprint, they say sprint, but you go like way up a big hill and come
back down. And there's like four rounds, they're all in a day from the prelims to the medal round.
And this woman named Petra Meidich, Sylvanians gear, had been one of the top ranked people in
the world for years and never metaled at World Championships or Olympics, totally snake bitten,
something would always go wrong. They didn't bring the right skis or the technician didn't
have the right wax or ski breaks like just freak stuff. And here she's favored to get silver,
I think in Vancouver. And in the warm up right before the first round, she slides off a curve,
falls into a frozen creek bed and bruises up all of her side. And they take her through quick
examination because she has to go to the first round and say, Okay, nothing's broken. It's just
pain. Like if you're okay, you can go and she goes to the first round qualifies on time when
she's she was the favorite in that round barely makes it through. Second round similar thing,
the examiner, it's just pain, you know, if you can do it, you can go. Third round, she falls down
after the finish line screaming, they have to carry her away and examine her again and say,
if anything was really wrong, we tell you couldn't go. But if you can go, you can final round,
you hear her screaming every time she's like pulling the ground, gets the bronze medal just
nips in there, then they have time to examine her and find she broke a whole bunch of ribs on her
side. One of them broke off and punctured her lung. And so she came to the medal ceremony with
a tube sticking out of her chest in a wheelchair. And I remember she was I talked to her sports
psychologist and they were saying if we had known that she had broken all these ribs or
had a frickin pneumothorax, yeah, they weren't gonna let her go to the mail ceremony. She was like,
I will die in the middle of something I'm going, you know. And so they brought wielder. And they
all said, well, first of all, it's a kind of a testament to the mentality that if if they told
her it was an injury, she wouldn't have done it, right? But it's just pain. And I was talking to
our sports psychologists about what got her here? Like, what's the journey been like, especially
after she's always having this stuff going wrong, this must have been like, Oh, again. And he said,
one of the most important things was like diversifying her identity, she was getting so
fixated on and so much pressure. He was like, you need to do something else. So he forced her to
start building a house, basically. And that became like a task for her to do and a whole new thing and
a new skill. And he felt like, I thought maybe he was going to talk about some new type of cross
training. He was like, No, the building the house took the pressure off, it gave her some other part
of her identity. So it wasn't just as the person who's like always having something go wrong. And
I just thought that was so interesting that his what he felt was his main contribution was giving
her a hobby, essentially, and that he thought that really allowed her not to feel like the pressure
that would break her in some way. You sort of alluded to it earlier with the story of the
Nobel laureates as well. I can't remember if it was I think it was Francis Crick who said this,
I could be wrong, that it might have been Watson, but I think it was Crick who said
the key to doing great science is always being a little bit unemployed. And I'm also probably
paraphrasing that and bastardizing it, it must have been said much more eloquently. But you get the
point that just if it is great insight in science comes from having time to wander in your mind.
You said something a while ago about which made me very jealous, by the way, and kind of pissed me
off, you would read 10 papers a day in the exploration phase of writing. And it's like,
I'd give anything to read 10 papers a day today. Instead, I feel fortunate at least to have a team
that can read 10 papers a day for me. I remember that bliss of you just get to read the paper all
day, every day, highlight it, take notes, call the author, go to journal club, like, like, that was
unbelievable. And we don't mean it's very difficult to be a scientist today, because
nobody's paying you to be just thinking. Nobody's really rewarding you. Nobody's promoting you
based on that. So we've created this very perverse set of incentives. And in some ways, honestly,
I consider it a miracle that there are still really good science being done. Most science being done,
by the way, just sucks. I mean, if we're going to be brutally honest, if you pull up PubMed,
and you look at every one of those 100,000 papers every month that makes the way on the PubMed,
I think 90 to 95% of them are absolutely useless, serve absolutely no purpose to our civilization,
do not advance natural knowledge, do nothing beneficial for us.
They increase the publication count of the person doing them, which is why they're doing them.
That's right. It's an economic tool of the journals, and it's a promotional tool. So
you don't have any absolutely nefarious actors in the situation, you just have a system with such
perverse incentives that nothing could- Some of the predatory journals, but those are-
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah. And I think a lot of the science is bad. I confess in range that I think
my own master's thesis was not good science and wouldn't replicate, but I didn't know,
like I was rushed into studying the specifics of Arctic plant physiology really quickly without
learning what was actually happening when I hit a button on the statistics program and how science
has to be set up to make conclusions. And I think that's kind of the norm for a lot of scientists.
I think this 2005 paper by John Ionitis that was titled,
Why Most Published Research Is False, that people kind of wrote off. Now it looks like
he's a genius, right? Oh, and now I hope I'm not saying something John wouldn't want me to repeat,
but I think John's been pretty vocal about this probably like seven or eight years ago.
I was having dinner with John and I said, John, I want to know a bullshit answer on this. What
percentage of people who do science for a living? So they apply for grants, they get the money,
they do the thing. What percentage of those people shouldn't be doing that? Which doesn't
mean they can't work in a lab, but they can't be principal investigators. I mean, he said something
to the tune of 95. He's like 19 out of 20 people who basically for a living are in the business of
generating hypotheses, testing them experimentally and evaluating the results of those experiments.
That's the scientific method. 19 out of 20 people who do that can't do it and probably should not
be doing it. That's scary, but also I would guess that we don't want to try to narrow it down to
just the people that should be doing it because you'd have this purifying form of selection where
you have to like allow some failure. So this is kind of where I want to go with this thinking,
right? So why aren't we going down as tangents? So you've obviously written a lot about the importance
of even generalists within science and you've given a couple of examples which we should go into
about the hard problem that gets solved by somebody whose native scientific tongue is not
the one that is being addressed. So I want to talk about that, but I want to contrast it with
this other thing which is I have this thesis that I harp on all the time which is mostly my way of
communicating with myself to not get so upset at the lack of scientific insight in the world.
And the idea is genetics and evolution have never prepared us for science. So the scientific method
is less than 400 years old. Even the earliest signs of formal logic as a construct to describe
the way we think represents less than 0.1% of our genetic existence. So Attia, why would you ever
get upset at somebody who can't think logically? Why would you ever get upset when you pull up a
story on Goop that is written like the most insulting thing you've ever seen in your life
with respect to science? Why would you let that upset you Peter? It's like you're expecting
something that is simply too much. And you might be assuming that the people writing for Goop are
trying to get things right. So that might be the assumption that I would love to hear you hold
forth about Goop to be honest. So I contrast this with there has to be some degree of rigidity and
formality in the training. I like to think of myself as a pretty good critic of science. I have
the ability to read papers and immediately most of the time figure out why these are total crap
and what all the biases are and all these other things. But to take any credit for that would be
ridiculous. I can't take any credit for that. That's simply because I was mentored by people
and I went through a formal type of training or informal type of training. Really it wasn't formal
and codified, but it was informal. It's going to journal club. It's doing the experiments yourself,
putting something together, thinking you're slick and having people tell you,
hey, numb nuts, did you realize how many ways you screwed this up and how you've drawn the wrong
conclusion? So how do you balance that you have to go through that type of training with, but
sometimes you have to be an outsider? Yeah. And by the way, what you mentioned, informal training,
I think we underestimate the importance of informal training and you have to kind of set
up cultures for it and things like that. So I have a master's degree in geological sciences
and I got a much better education in genetics writing a book than I did in a grad program.
I wouldn't know how to run like the equipment in the lab, but I basically kept like a statistician
on retainer and just to talk to me about a paper anytime. And that's an amazing way to learn. You're
not just being talked at, you have a specific question of why is this right? He's like, no,
you can't use this. And so it's amazing way to have like informal learning. And you're right.
I think the way to balance that, I think it's difficult because you're right. You do need some
formal training in it. Like in other words, the takeaway from your book is not that the person
who's going to crack the code on pancreatic cancer is currently working at an investment bank as a
finance analyst who's never taken a science course. That's not going to happen. Not even close. And I
don't think you're trying to suggest that, but I've heard people try to take your work and paraphrase
it as, oh, well, all these scientists working on cancer, screw it, man. They're not going to figure
anything out. We need to, we need to go get the history majors to solve the cancer problem. And
I'm like, not a freaking chance without some modicum of scientific training. Yeah. And I mean,
I think the scientific community, I would say the tech community in particular would do well to
interact with historians. Like I think there are a lot of things they could learn. Sometimes I feel
like the Silicon Valley set maybe doesn't respect history quite enough or it'd be useful for them.
But that's a side point. My guess is that when people are saying that, that just like
go pick some person at random to do science, maybe they're taking that from the chapter where I wrote
partly about InnoCentive, which was the VP of research and development at Eli Lilly in the past
on a guy named Alf Bingham. Who's that? I remember when I first talked to him, he said, look,
I'm an organic chemist. It doesn't have a carbon in it. I'm not even supposed to play with it. Okay.
I'm specialized. And I guess he realized at a certain point that chemists at Lilly were getting
so specialized that there were certain things they were great at, but it also narrowed their view. So
he talked a lot about this terminology in some of the business literature, exploration versus
exploitation. Exploration meaning essentially going and looking for new ideas and solutions,
exploitation. Once you find them, how do you make the most out of them? Both of those incredibly
important. And he said, basically, the exploration phase is increasingly found outside because people
are so specialized, so they're just not covering as much ground. And so he had this idea to just
post online some of Lilly's problems in drug development. And at first everyone was like,
no way proprietary information. He said, well, pick stuff. Well, nobody will know what we're doing.
And they said, who else is going to be able to solve this? So he posts some online and like a
third of them get solved. I remember one of his favorite memories was an attorney who solved
some important chemical synthesis project because he had worked on some tear gas copyright case or
something. And it reminded him of that. And so a third of those problems get solved, which is
amazing. Yeah, that story amazed me actually. And in those problems, it does tend to be because
they've selected for problems that have stumped the specialists, right? So it does tend to be the
more likely the problem is to get solved, the diversity. And I think my question on that, to
really double click on it is, did the generalist actually solve the problem or did the generalist
just come up with a clue that completely changed how the specialist went about approaching it? Like
in the case of that example, the attorney doesn't actually know how to completely synthesize the
molecule. What they're basically saying is you guys are looking at it this way. Stop. Rotate 90
degrees over there and turn around. And I think the answer is over here, to which case either a new
set of specialists could do it. Is it sort of a bit of that hybrid? Yeah. And actually,
InnoCentive evolved to where they give different, now they help other operations post their questions
in a way that will attract what they call solvers. And there are different monetary rewards depending
on what kind of contribution it is the person makes. And sometimes he did get people sent in
powders and stuff. They synthesize stuff on their own. Other times it was much more like you're
taking the wrong approach. And here's another thing to think about. But they were still chemists
that had to do this, right? Not all of them. Not all of them. But there was a lot of that. Sometimes
they'd be chemists from some other area. But sometimes it was totally random people. But again,
you're farming it out to the whole world. People have not the whole world. I mean,
most people don't know about InnoCentive, but a huge number of people. And I think he was surprised.
Sometimes things would come from people who worked with machinery, but weren't really formally
trained in it, but had a lot of experience. And so I think sometimes there were true outsiders.
But most of the problems don't get to the InnoCentive stage anyway. They're being handled
by the specialists. And I wouldn't extrapolate InnoCentive to mean that specialists aren't
incredibly important. I mean, my broad view of this is the same as physicist Freeman Dysonry gave
this great speech. We said we need birds and frogs. The frogs are down in the mud looking at
the granular details. The birds are up above. They don't see the detail, but they're integrating the
knowledge of the frogs. And he said, the world is wide and deep. It'd be stupid to say one's better
than the other. You need both for a healthy ecosystem. His concern was we're telling everybody
to be frogs. And so we're not having birds. And that's kind of how I conceive of it. And I think
the biggest impact would come from what Arturo Casadaval, who's this kind of one of the prime
characters of the last chapter, is trying to do where adding range to people who are within
science already. Like these people are being formally trained. He's just backing up the formal
training instead of jumping right into kind of the reductionist, studying the body as a machine sort
of thing. It's like the initial classes in the program he's pioneering. And he's like one of the
I think his H index, which is a measure of his productivity as a researcher, surpassed
Einstein's recently, which isn't fair because people publish a lot more now, as you alluded to,
for their careers. But it still puts him in very rare company. And so he's starting people with,
how do we know what is true and the anatomy of scientific errors and also how errors have
sometimes led to breakthroughs. And so he's just like backing up the training into these broader
concepts and saying, you can learn the more specific didactic stuff later. But if you don't
learn the broader conceptual stuff, you never get it because you're only going to get more and more
and more specialized from here. So I think one way we can approach this is just by backing up the
training basically, because I don't think we have to worry about people will learn the specialized
stuff in their field just by doing it and being there. But the other stuff, but that's what we
kind of teach them and start them with. But the other stuff like scientific thinking, how does it
work? What constitutes evidence? They'll never get that stuff if they don't get it early in training.
Yeah, I sort of cite the examples you've given when I get asked a question a lot, which is
someone going to college who wants to go to medical school saying, what is the best thing
to study in college? To which I don't know the answer, but my advice is anything but pre-med.
So you couldn't really do anything. And I'm sorry, because I know there's somebody listening to this,
I'm sure who's doing pre-med who's going to go into medical school. And my only take for you is,
okay, I'm sorry that you're in pre-med right now, but make sure you spend a lot of time doing
non pre-med stuff in college. You still have the bandwidth to take other classes. You should be
doing so liberally, but you are better off being a history major who goes to medical school than a
biochem major who goes to medical school. In my opinion, I could be wrong, but having seen enough
people go through it, you're going to learn as much biochemistry as you're going to need to learn
when you get there, both interpersonally and frankly in the breadth of thinking you'll be
better off if you studied something else. I mean, a lot of Arturo's argument too,
I saw him make this argument talking about he went from Einstein to Johns Hopkins School
of Public Health because they're allowing him to start this new grad program. And I saw him on a
panel about the replication crisis in science, this problem with a lot of work basically not
being true. And the head editor of the New England Journal of Medicine said, you can't do that.
Training is already too long. And Arturo said, it's clearly not working. He said, I'm saying drop
the didactic stuff because it's not been working. I think he actually pointed out that the New England
Journal of Medicine had the highest retraction rate in some study also. But so I thought that
was interesting where he said, a lot of that stuff is in one ear and out the other anyway,
if it's really didactic, people don't even know if they're going to need it or when they're going to
need it. And so I thought that was an interesting take. He said, you can just drop some of that
other stuff. But to your point about telling people not to do pre-med, when I was at Sports Illustrated,
not so much anymore, but when I was there, I would get asked by young aspiring journalists,
what should I do if I want to work as a sports writer, which I major in English or journalism.
And my first instinct was to say journalism. If you know what you want to do, get a head start.
Second instinct English. And then if I thought about it, I'd be like, well, I major in geology
and astronomy, so I have no idea what to tell you. But stats course, biology course, never hurt anyone.
You should do one of those because you'll learn the job by doing the job. And that's the only way
you'll learn the job. That is the challenge of giving advice, isn't it? Because I don't feel
this way at all anymore. I'm totally comfortable with my nonlinear path to doing what I do.
But I spent a great deal of time frustrated that I couldn't figure out sooner in life what I wanted
to be when I grew up. And I thought of all the time squandered. But again, that was through the
paradigm of you only had one to two 10,000 hour windows, you didn't take them, you spent them
doing something you will never do again. I had my 10,000 hour shot and I put it in the wrong thing.
And now I never do it again. And but I think that speaks to probably the insights of your book,
which is you're discounting a bunch of things you learned in doing that. And also sorry,
I didn't mean to interrupt you. Were you gonna? No, no, no. And also, I think your insight into
yourself, your skills and interests in the world are constrained by your roster of previous
experiences as her mini a bara who studies how people find what's called match quality, the degree
of fit between their interests and abilities and the work that they do, which turns out to be really
important for how likely they are to burn out for their performance for all these sorts of things.
And we really underestimate it. She studies basically how people seek this out and transition
careers. And she said, we learn who we are in practice, not in theory, which means there's
this kind of cultural idea and lots of career gurus and personality quizzes, they kind of seek
to convince you that you can just introspect and know what you should do putting in that time. But
in fact, the way we learn about what we want to do is we have to do stuff to act and then think you
have to do stuff and then reflect on it. And that's the only way you figure it out. And match quality
seems to be so important that spending some time in that experimentation is worth it. So one of the
that I think is sort of representative of that this economist who found a natural experiment in the
higher ed systems of England and Scotland where in the period he studied, students in England had to
pick a specialty in their mid teen years to apply for a certain program in college.
The Scottish students could keep sampling throughout university. And he said, who wins
the trade off? Otherwise, the systems were very similar who wins the earlier late specializers.
And what he found was the early specializers do in fact jump out to an income lead because they
have more domain specific skills. But the late specializers sample more things and when they do
pick, they have better match quality. And so they have higher growth rates. So by year six out,
they fly by the early specializers. Meanwhile, the early specialized based on the economics. Yeah,
what about when you look at things that probably matter even more is just happiness and satisfaction.
He was only looking at finance and career switching. So because he was looking at huge
numbers of people, but we can talk about fulfillment in a sec. So the early specializers
then start leaving their career tracks in much higher numbers, even though they have much more
disincentive from doing so they're made to pick so early that they more often make a wrong choice.
So the return to match quality was higher than the return to getting a head start and domain
specific skills. The dark horse project, which I wanted to get around to anyway, as to a fulfillment,
because I think you should tell more of your story. Because sounded really interesting. And
I want to hear more of it. But that project, the dependent variable was fulfillment. And it was
about how people go on. Yeah. Well, before we started the podcast, I said, there's this thing
I've always tried to explain when I've told my story to high school kids or something like that.
It doesn't really make sense, which is growing up, all of my energy went into boxing and martial arts.
And I didn't do anything in school. I was super mediocre. And then I had this awesome teacher
who when I was in grade 12 in Canada, you say grade 12, not 12th grade. Sounds stupid.
So weird. I can't believe we can even get a lot of the guys.
It's hard that we can even have a discussion. And he called me one morning and he said,
Hey, I heard you're not applying to university and stuff. And I said, that's right. And he
certainly didn't bust my chops. In fact, I wrote about him after he died and how amazing it was
that he just knew what to say. He knew the right thing to say at the right time, which was,
Hey, I totally get it. When I was your age, all I wanted to do is play in the NHL. And it was the
only thing that mattered to me. And you really ought to don't let anybody tell you that your
dream of being middleweight champion in the world is a dumb idea. It's not. But he said, but it was
almost like a Steve Jobs moment. Like one more thing. I think you have a gift for mathematics
and you should at least entertain the idea that maybe that's your calling is more in terms of
math than it is in fighting. And I remember that day as clear as, I mean, that got so long ago.
It's more than half my life ago was that moment, but it did change the course of my life completely.
And then I did come back to high school to finish and did better than anybody expected I could ever
do. And I've always assumed the reason I was able to do that is I simply took the work ethic of
exercising six hours a day, which was sort of what I did in high school. I was, I would run five to
13 miles every morning, 400 pushups before bed every night, and everything in between was training
around that. And I just applied that to calculus, algebra, physics, geometry, et cetera. So that
sort of gets into the Duckworth grit stuff. The question I guess I have in that is, had I taken
the grit of age 13 to 18 and basically with no other cognitive capacity turned it into then
doing well in school? I definitely wouldn't say no other cognitive capacity because, well, I think
those things take a different, certain cognitive capacity, that kind of discipline, but clearly the
teacher recognized something in you that you did not recognize in yourself. Didn't just pick you out
randomly. And I assumed, well, especially because I wasn't even the top student in mathematics at
the time. I wasn't even near the top. So yeah. So obviously he saw something that you didn't
yourself see. And so it seems to me like you had this training, whether that was something that
was part of who you are naturally or something that motivated you, that you could take that and
transfer that to then something that had better match quality for you. And so it was a combination
of you using certain skills and approaches that you would learn and somebody helping you find
better match quality, basically. I think that's like an explosive combination in a good way,
but it is interesting. I wonder what he saw because he was right. But did you have any inkling
that that was the case at the time? Was that total news to you that he thought, you know,
no, in fact, I found math incredibly frustrating because it wasn't something you could BS your
way through. At least in English class, I remember this well, because I'm actually still very close
to my English teacher from high school. I always managed to find a way to weasel through by writing
every essay I wrote was on Muhammad Ali or Mike Tyson or Marvin Hagler or Jimi Hendrix. I basically
screwed my way through English by always figuring out a way to read a book that I was interested in
and figuring out a way to write. But you couldn't do that in math. You sort of had to do it. So what
I remember is that math frustrated me more than anything. But I wish Woody was still alive for
many reasons, but one of them being I wish I could ask him why he said that. Yeah, no, it's
curious. I mean, and I think a lot of people find math more frustrating in English class. It's like
English class and more subjective and you kind of get through even if you don't a lot of people even
if you don't know what you're doing. But that is that is interesting. I wonder what he saw. And
I think that's the reason I said I think it resonates with the Dark Horse Project, which was
this project by these two Harvard researchers to sort of figure out how people who find fulfillment
in their work go about it in a wide range of careers. Essentially, there was a huge variety.
But most of the people did not stick on their first sort of dream. Basically, there were some,
but it was a small minority. Most of them had this, they actually called it the Dark Horse
Project because people would come in and say, well, don't tell anybody to do what I did,
because I started this other thing and then I something else came up or something random
happened or I realized there wasn't what I want to do. So I had to start my own thing.
So they also felt sort of sheepish about their nonlinear path. Yeah. And they saw themselves
as having gotten lucky and come out of nowhere, which you do have to get luck. Luck is important,
but they all saw themselves as having come out of nowhere, which is why they called it the Dark
Horse Project. What they kind of had in common was this. They would sort of respond instead of
sticking to like an ironclad long term plan, they would respond to their lived experience by
zigging and zagging and kind of finding what they were good at, whether that was someone
helping them figure that out, which I think is often the case for a younger person or them
being older and maturing and sort of realizing that. And it sounds like that kind of happened
to you in some way. You view yourself as coming out of nowhere because you had a talent and also
some transferable skills that could come together in a way that you hadn't conceived before.
And it worked really well. So I think you'd be kind of the type for the Dark Horse Project.
I mean, to take something you said a moment ago and couple it to this. So let's say we fast forward
whatever 18 years and your son says, dad, I don't want to go to college. I'm going to learn a bunch
of stuff that I don't need to learn because I could teach it on my own. I'm going to get a degree in
something that doesn't necessarily imply what I'm going to do with myself thereafter. The letters
don't really matter after my name. And by the way, notwithstanding the fact that maybe by the time
our kids are going to college, the debt that they'd incur to do so is itself more debilitating
than anything else. So can you make a case that one does not need formal education at that level
to go far? I mean, notwithstanding the fact that sometimes you need it from a professional standpoint,
like you can't become a lawyer without going to school. I don't see that changing and things
like that. At least in California, you just have to pass the bar. Actually, that's a great point.
You can't become a doctor, I guess, without going to school. And so does this change the way you
think about higher education? Yeah. And gosh, I don't even know where to start with this question.
I hope that college looks different 18 years from now than it does now, because if we keep ramping
up people's debt, then we will make sure that they fall prey to the sunk cost fallacy where
the more you invest in something. One of my favorite writers, Maria Kanakova, wrote a book
about con men. And one of their strategies is they start with asking for small things.
Oh, I thought you meant con-a-men. Oh, no, no, not con-a-men. No, no, con-men playing confidence
games. Yeah, the book's called The Confidence Game. And she's a psychology PhD and a great
writer. And she notes that they'll start with these small, lots of small asks, because the more you
invest, the more likely you are to fall prey to the sunk cost fallacy of then saying, well,
I've already put some in, so I should keep going, even when to an outsider, it's clear that it's a
disaster. And I think the more debt we saddle people with, like that study we were just talking
about with the higher ed systems in England and Scotland, the English students who specialized
earlier have more disincentive from quitting, even though they should. When they do quit,
their growth rates are then higher because they're quitting in response to information
about themselves that they've learned. And I think the more time and debt we saddle people with,
the more we make sure they will not respond to match quality information. And instead we'll say,
Yeah, you blunt their receptivity to the signal. That's right. And I think we want to, Steve Levitt,
the Freakonomics economist did this interesting study where he had people flip a coin to determine
major life decisions. And the most commonly asked question was, should I quit my job? And what he
found was the people who flipped, I think it was heads and changed their job were better off when
he checked in with them later. And so I think you want like as little friction as possible to people
job changing. In fact, when I was watching one of the Democratic primary debates recently, and people
were talking about universal healthcare, I would think one of the advantages might be that it would
lower friction to job changing because you're not as worried about so that maybe people can shuffle
around more and have better match quality. So I think something has to be done about the debt
situation. I think there's plenty of evidence that for a lot of students, so the economist Brian
Kaplan wrote a book called The Case Against Education. I certainly don't agree with that entire
education specifically, I certainly don't agree with everything in the book, but I think it's
provocative and a rigorous take. And his argument, so we know that some part of college education is
signaling to the job world that is not about anything that you've learned. It's just about
I am smart enough and I'm serious enough. And yeah, it's like the minor leagues for the job world.
So we're doing them a favor because they don't have to be good scouts. And basically, what he was
saying is nobody says that either signaling or learning is all of the effect of college. But his
argument was that he thinks signaling is like 80% of it, whereas other people would say, Oh, maybe
it's 20%. So he thinks most of it is just, you need this credential to signal to the work world
that I'm okay. And I don't know if he's right about how much it is. But I think it's probably
more than people into it, because research seems to suggest that it doesn't change people as much
as we might think in some ways. What I do think is important about it, though, is that it does give
that kind of sampling ability, like I didn't know about so the Scottish students in that study also
much more often the late specializes end up studying something that wasn't offered in their
high school, because they didn't know about it. I didn't know about the stuff I studied until I got
to college. And so without it, I would want it to be some other mechanism for sampling. But I think
that kind of communication technology that we have now on the internet may, if we use it smartly,
it can expose you to a lot more stuff. And I think there's huge potential of online courses.
I love some of these online courses. So I do think while I would want him to be able to have a
sampling period, my kid, I think I don't know that the same kind of college model that we have now
will be the answer. And I think there are other things that could expose him to more other things.
And but if society forces the signaling to continue, then what can you do, then it's just
like you have to pay your dues because you have to pay your dues. The way I see my role as a parent,
you mentioned Angela Duckworth, by the way, I should mention the week that my book came out,
I've subscribed to her newsletter. Her newsletter was titled Summer is for Sampling.
And she said, kids shouldn't be too gritty until they figure out what to be gritty in.
And she says it took me a decade of trying stuff to figure out. So it really speaks to a broader
point here, which is a lot of these insights that we sort of latch onto are slightly out of context.
Yeah, definitely. Definitely. And I mean, so now, if her point is you should be gritting when you
should be gritty. I'm totally on board with that. I view my roles, I write a little bit in that
section about grit, about something I should have written more about about the way the army adjusted
when they realized in an industrial economy, and they had this strict up or out structure,
it was great, because you did want to be specialized, because work next year did look like work last
year. And there were huge barriers to lateral mobility, but knowledge economy comes along. And
now there's tons of lateral mobility for people who can engage in knowledge creation and creative
problem solving. So their highest potential officers started quitting if they didn't have
any agency over their career matching. And so first, they tried to throw money at people to
retain them and people who were going to stay took it, people who are going to leave left anyway,
half a billion dollars of taxpayer money down the drain. Then they started programs like when they
call talent based branching, where instead of saying, here's your career track, go up or out,
they say, we're gonna pair you with a coach, and try this one career track and reflect on how it
fits you and then try these other two and these other two and we'll triangulate a better fit for
you. And that improved retention more than throwing money at people. They've basically built
in a match quality sampling system. And so maybe we could do stuff. That's how frankly,
how I view right now my parenting role as being the coach in the math town based branching system
for my kid facilitate, help him know that a lot of things are available and get the maximum amount
of signal about himself from each one. And I think there are ways that that can be done,
possibly more effectively, and a lot more cheaply than the formal education structure.
How do you know how long to push? So give you two examples with my daughter. And I feel so bad
sometimes telling these stories about her because one day she'll listen to this and she'll be like,
dad, I can't believe you embarrassed me. But when she was five, she said, I want to play the drums.
And we've had lots of parents who have interacted with us who said, are you crazy? How did you
listen to her? But we were like, oh, we just did. So we got her like a set of cheapo little toy
drums just to see would she actually do anything? And she did. She wouldn't stop wailing on them.
And though she was four when she said that. Then when she was five, she said, no, I really want to
keep playing. So I said, OK, fine. So we got a drum teacher, got her a real set of drums,
and away she went. And here she is now. She's 11. She still drums. She loves it. She's I mean,
she's really good. I can say that without too much bias, just objectively based on what her
teacher tells me, which is like she drums better than most anyone. And she's only 11. And we never
pushed her. Right. So it was just she just wanted to do this. There was one time when she kind of
wanted to quit when she was about seven. And we talked to her teacher and said, hey,
let's spend way more time just letting her play Taylor Swift songs than doing scales for a while
and see what happens. And then that was great. Like it all came back into the mix. A year ago,
she starts taking tennis lessons. I think her tennis teacher is the most awesome guy. He's like
this young Russian kid. He's so fun. He's so smart. I've watched them. I mean, he just has a
beautiful way of explaining things to her. She never feels bad. Like he never hammers her,
but he's strict. If she's screwing around, he tells her she's like, I don't want to play tennis
anymore. And I'm like, Olivia, are you freaking crazy? Do you know what I'd give to have played
tennis when I was a kid? And I don't get into the sob story of like, we didn't have the opportunity
for private tennis lessons or whatever, but it's more the tennis is such a beautiful sport. You
will be able to play this forever. How can you not want this? And I'm really torn. Do I push her to
continue taking lessons? And I'm not saying like you have to go and even compete. It's just sit
here and play tennis for two hours a week. You and mom play. It's fun. Why wouldn't you want to do
this? Or do I just say, well, she only wants to play basketball, which is the only sport she wants
to play right now. I just, I don't know if this is a great example, but I think you get the point,
right? It's like, there's a part of me that thinks it's really good for her to keep playing tennis.
Yeah. Yeah. And she's crazy to stop. Obviously you're saying she'll regret it. It sounds like it.
That's my potentially stupid fear, which is you're going to be 51 day and you're not going to be
playing basketball because nobody's playing. No 50 year old woman is running around playing pickup
basketball, but you will still play tennis. So why wouldn't you continue to learn this now?
Well, you have this critical window in which you could get good at this sport. Yeah. And she could
play tennis at startup at 50. She just wouldn't be as good at it. Exactly. Yeah. And you're
oriented toward achievement. So she might be a great drummer and a crap tennis player. She
starts at 50. She might still like tennis though. Yes. And I'm trying to balance the, yes, I think
that's the part of it. I can't let go of this idea that I'm not great at anything. It would be really
cool if my kids had the potential to be great at something world-class. Like wouldn't it be cool
if she could be a world-class drummer one day? I have no delusion. She won't be as the interest
or even the talent to be a world-class tennis player, but I still think why wouldn't you,
you have this wind. I think I'm still stuck to this idea that there's a window in which you can
assimilate skill, be it language, music, sports, that to go a little further. If she said, I don't
know, anyway, that's sort of. And when she's younger also, you have more time to put into it and you're
a lot less concerned about making mistakes. So you'll throw yourself in and practice in a way
that you probably won't when you're older and most things. I mean, that's a great question. It sounds
like in drums, you found a way to sort of when she was saying, I don't really want to do it anymore
to keep her foot in by sort of changing what she was doing. Right. And it was just this one little
audible called on the line of scrimmage. Everything was fine, but also it would have never even
occurred to me to put a kid in drums. Like this was 100% her insisting on it. And there was no
resistance from us. I was like, right. But if she'd said piano, violin, fill in the blank, we would have
been equally interested in letting her pursue that. So maybe it just comes back to this broader issue
of is there an age at which parents should force some of the sampling? Is there an age at which
parents say enough is enough. You've sampled enough. If you don't want to play tennis anymore,
don't play tennis. I should make clear I don't want to prescribe diversification anymore than
I want to prescribe specialization. Right. And this gets to something I mentioned before,
which is I think we tell the tiger and the Mozart stories a little wrong. Yeah, let's do that story.
Okay. So Tiger said in 2000, his father never asked him to play golf. So his father did put a putter
in his hand when he was seven months old, but he wasn't attempting to make him a golfer. He was
just giving it to him as a toy. And he responded. So he said in 2000, my father never once asked me
to play golf. It was always me asking him, it's the child's desire to play, not the parents desire
to have the child play that matters. That resonates with the work of this woman, Ellen Winter, who's
maybe the world's authority on prodigies of that nature, that they're usually driving their parents
crazy, not the reverse. And that there's not really. Yeah. I mean, Wayne Gretzky is a great example of
that. He listened to these interviews with his parents like they couldn't get this kid to come
in for dinner. And what Ellen Winter, I think she alluded to some research. I don't think this
research was exactly hers, but it's really a problem when someone's parents, if they're low
socioeconomic status and they have a prodigy and the person has this incredible drive of master,
whatever it is they're doing, and the parent can't accommodate that because it really is hard for the
parents. Obviously, Tiger's father responded to his very unusual display of interest in prowess.
Mozart is probably the second most famous example. Tell people just what's the mythology
around Mozart? Oh, that his father basically was Tiger Woods' father, except for music,
that he started a very young... Shoved the violin into the crib. Yeah, exactly. And so I was going
through these letters, and one that I remember really well about Mozart's early life was a
musician who'd come over to play with Mozart's father, who was a musician. And he recalls young
Mozart coming in with the group of adults and saying, I want to play the second violin part.
And Mozart's father says, go away. You haven't had any lessons. You obviously can't play violin.
And then the letter writer, his name is Andreas, something, I can't remember the last name,
says little Wolfgang started crying. And so I said, okay, I'll go play with him in the other room.
And his father says, but play quietly. Don't disturb us. Next thing you know, they hear the
second violin part coming from the other room. And so they walk in and look, and young Wolfgang
Mozart's playing the second violin part with made up fingering, because nobody's taught him
the fingering. And then the letter this part, I remember verbatim, he says, young Wolfgang was
emboldened by our applause to insist that he could also play the first violin part. And so then he
goes and does that. And that's when his father says, holy crap. Yeah. And responds to it. So
neither of those cases were they like manufactured the way we tell that story. So I don't think we
should be scared about missing a tiger Mozart, because the best way to find one of those people
is probably still to expose them to a bunch of things and see if something lights their fire that
way. I mean, I think a Mozart. That's a great point. That's a great point. Yeah, I think those,
I'm sure there's a lot of those people who never got exposed to the thing that would have ignited
what Ellen winner calls that rage to master. And most people, you're not gonna have a lot of tigers
and Mozarts, no matter what. And obviously, those are exceptions. But I think that's important to
keep in mind. To go back to when do you allow your kid to quit? This is something I've seen Angela
Duckworth has tried to respond to a number of times. It's very difficult. She'll say things like,
don't quit on a bad day, which I think is sensible. But also, should you quit on a good day? It's kind
of hard to know what is the calculus for when you should quit. Like if you're having tons of bad
days, maybe you should quit on a bad day. And Levitt and Dubner have written about this, right?
I think it's in one of their maybe their third book. Well, Levitt is always saying my best thing
is I know when to quit, like everything like fields of study, projects, whatever. Yeah. By the way,
is a funny aside, you know, Steve has tried very hard to get me to take up golf? No, really? Yeah.
So he's a very good golfer. I don't know. A lot of people don't know how good a golfer Steve is
incredible. And he's convinced that taking sort of a freakinomics approach to golf, you could take
a novice and make them really good in a short period of time. We've had very serious discussions
about if I would give him one year, he could turn me into a really good golfer as someone who's never
even touched a golf club. I don't know if that's true, but I'm curious enough that I'd love to try
it if I had the time, because when he's explained to me the logic behind it, like how many steps you
can shortcut if you're purely optimizing around this thing and how he's figured out a bunch of
these hacks. I'm like, it's kind of fun. It's not going to happen with me. I don't think but. Yeah,
probably don't have time to do that. But if you did take him up on that, like that guy we talked
about earlier, Dan McLaughlin, who dropped his job to try to become a pro. Right. Who got 7,000 hours
into it. I think he got better. So he was getting way better at first, like anything, the learning
curve is. But I think how quickly he got better and he had never golfed before ever was surprising
to most people how quickly he got better early on. And so I think doing that plus,
I mean, he was practicing. That was like his full time job for the time. But
if you did that for a year, plus whatever hacks he's talking about, I bet you'd pass most of the
amateur golfers out there because most of them are just going in like swatting and it's like stress
relief. They're not even really trying to get better a lot of times. But I bet you'd surprise
yourself with how good you'd get. But I'm not a huge golf fan. I'm putting all of that energy
into the things that I'm currently doing. But this idea of quitting, it is really an
underappreciated thing, isn't it? Because sometimes it's time. It really comes down to
time and exposure. And that's the most valuable resource we have. But the when to do it is still
the million dollar question. Totally. I mean, I think that's why I like this model of talent
based branching that the Army use so much because they pair someone with a coach to help them make
that decision. And it's still not a science. And I also like they call it talent based branching
because basically it's coached quitting. But they use a different term. So it doesn't sound
bad. But I don't know what's perfect. I mean, I think someone a mother asked me recently said
her son is really good at violin and now he just wants to quit. And I think like just wants to play
tennis. And she was saying but he's so good. And I know he'll love it when he's older. And the best
thing I could think of was try to help him keep a foot in whether that's playing Taylor Swift songs
or whatever, maybe he just needs to back off and try something else for a while. Can you keep a foot
in that pool so that he doesn't totally detach from it? And when he feels regenerated or whatever
can go back to it. We know that progress comes from alternating stress and rest and things like
that. So maybe they just need a break or maybe they need to try some other type of training. I
think that's undervalued. If someone wants to quit and say, Oh, either you have to stick with it or
quit. But the approach you took was, let's try varying what you're doing. I think that's incredibly
undervalued. We act as if it's a binary choice instead of why don't we see what else this area
has to offer. Maybe you just need to get on a different track. And again, I think that's the
brilliance of good coaches is they help personalize that environment. So the person continues to be
interested and continues to progress. And so the first thing I would try is varying up what they're
actually doing. And if they really want to quit, I'd say maybe keep a foot in if you can for a little
while. But then ultimately, if they really want to quit, then it defeats the purpose. If some
aspiration of life is to find happiness, then yeah, and make it if they want to come back,
maybe they just needed a break, keep it available if possible. But if they quit and they don't
regret it, then what are you going to do? The proofs in the pudding. There are a couple other
stories in range that I wanted to ask you about. One of them is the story about the space shuttle
Challenger. I'll let you tell the story and then I'll bring my question to it. Cass, I don't even
know how to tell this story quickly. I'll set the stage. Everybody knows what happened. Let's assume
everybody knows the following. January 1986, space shuttle Challenger is scheduled to launch,
happens to be the first time there's a civilian on board. It also happens to be the first time
it's ever launched on a day that's that cold. And everybody knows what happened, which is
whatever, 73 seconds after liftoff, the O-ring failed to contain one of the liquid fuels. I
can't remember if it was liquid oxygen, but basically there was a spark, an explosion,
and the rest is history. You write about one, the decision to launch that day, two,
the challenges of figuring out what was the cause of that. Talk about both of those, especially the
former actually. And then I'll tell you where I'm curious. What I focused on was this emergency
conference call the night before the launch when the weather report came in that it was going to be
an unusually cold day in Florida. And so engineers at Morton Thiokol, which was the rocket booster
contractor, and NASA, they get on this big conference call in three different locations,
a group of engineers, and they say, what should we do? Is this a problem? Should we worry about it?
The shuttle was supposed to be cleared for cool temperatures, but nobody really knew because they
had never launched below 53 degrees. And they were concerned. As an aside, by the way, that O-ring
was from the Apollo program. That's a great example of engineering shortcut, which is they never
actually redesigned the O-rings for the shuttle. They literally just took the O-rings from the
Apollo project, which had a different spec and brought them over. Maybe I should describe what
O-rings are a little bit. It's like, it's a strip of rubber that runs. If you can picture the rocket
booster, you know, it looks like a missile attached to the shuttle and the O-rings it's put together
in different vertical segments and the O-rings run along the perimeter of the missile like rocket
booster and seal the joints between pieces. And they have to stay sealed so that they block the
rocket fuel coming down the booster from shooting outside essentially. And there was concern that
the rubber of the O-ring launched. There were forces that moved the O-ring, that moved the
metal pieces that were being sealed apart and the O-ring rubber had to expand immediately
to maintain contact so that fuel didn't come shooting past. And the concern was that the
rubber would harden a little when it was cold and so it wouldn't expand quite as quickly. And so some
rocket fuel would basically shoot through the wall of the booster. And that is exactly what happened.
And the question was that they were trying to answer is, should we be worried? Because twice
before they had had cases where they saw soot on the wrong side of the O-ring, which meant
rocket fuel had gotten past it, but it wasn't catastrophic. One of those was when they launched
at 53 degrees, which was the coolest temperature they'd launched at. One was at like 75 degrees,
which was one of the warmest temperatures they had launched at. And so... And on this day,
it was like 30 something, right? It was like 38 or something like that? They were looking at it,
that it was going to be like 40, but it ended up being colder than they expected even. And I think
in retrospect, some of the temperatures of actual components were even colder. There was like ice on
the... So it ended up being colder than anybody expected anyway. But their question was,
in these temperatures, will the O-ring work or not, basically? And the fact was that they didn't
really... There were only two cases of this so-called blow-by when the rocket fuel goes past.
Again, one at the coolest temperature, one at one of the warmest temperatures, and the whole
shuttle was thought by the project manager to be cleared for lower temperatures anyway. And so all
of a sudden, they're having this last minute meeting where they're saying like, how do O-rings
work and when do they work? And the only real... They didn't have enough data to answer the question.
And one of the engineers was saying, we shouldn't do this because I inspected the joints and in the
53 degree day, there was lots of black soot behind the O-ring. So that means a lot of gas got by and
we're lucky it came back. And the 75 degree day, something else must have happened because only a
little bit got passed. I don't know what happened, but only a little got passed. And so we go colder.
So he said, they asked him to quantify this. So what's the relationship between temperature
and gas blow-by? And he said, I don't know. I can't quantify it. All I know is colder is away from
goodness. That's how he put it. And they kept saying quantify it, quantify it, quantify it. He said,
I can't. I've got photographs. That's it. And I think they're telling a story. And the fact that
he couldn't quantify it meant that essentially it was deemed inadmissible evidence, basically,
because they couldn't quantify what the problem was. And so he made the decision to launch.
The rest is history. So the story is tragic on so many levels because it would almost be easier to
accept a disaster like that if nobody had seen what could have been done. That's what makes it
so painful. But on a second reading, what makes it even more painful is the way the questions are
being asked, which is, were they asking for him to assign a probability? Like, I don't even
understand what the question was. Quantify it. What does that mean? Yeah. I mean, I think they
wanted him to say, at what temperature would it fail? Because the. Well, it clearly had already
failed. So really, this is a probabilistic question. Exactly. Yes. But again, that's not a linear
question. Yeah. Right. That's an asymmetry question. That's the question of so and so has an
actuarial risk of having a heart attack of 5.4% in the next decade. Should you take preventative
measures? I don't know. I mean, depends on your view of the world. What's the upside? What's the
downside? What's the risk of doing something about it versus the risk of not doing something
about it? Those are very asymmetric risks. Yeah. And I mean, actually, if you read the Rogers
Commission, which investigated the Challenger disaster, Richard Feynman. My middle son is
named after him, by the way. Oh, okay. So Senna. Senna and Feynman are two heroes of mine. And
your daughter named after? Actually, she's named after her grandmother. Okay. Who was also, I'm
sure, an exceptional person. There was a point where Feynman was asking this questions like this.
Like, what were you trying to get him to say? They say, well, he couldn't quantify his case. He can
have data. And Feynman says, when you don't have data, you have to use reason. And he was giving
you reasons. And there is a point at which they're trying to say, well, at this temperature, based on
this data, the chances of failure should have been like one in a, I don't know, a fulfilling,
some enormous number. And Feynman's like, that's nonsense. You had two cases that had like a small
failure here. And you're telling me it's basically impossible. On a small finite number of launches.
Yeah. Yeah. And so obviously there was a lot of cover your ass stuff going. And they even knew
that at the time. So there was this unusual on that conference call. Once Morton Diacol said,
well, our engineer is saying, don't launch, we're going to support that. And then there was all this
discussion. And they went for an offline caucus where they said, where they kept being asked for
data, quantify your case, quantify your case, quantify your case. And they said, we can't,
okay, I guess we agree to launch. And then they were required to do a sign off that they didn't
have to do in the past. So obviously people were sort of in the CIA mode at some level,
or they felt protected by the process. But yeah, I don't think they weren't the best questions that
they were asking. I mean, I think they want to know at what, again, at what temperature will
we suffer catastrophic failure? And the answer was that they didn't know, but that things didn't
look good. And there was reason to be worried. Think about that question, even through the lens
of the financial crisis at what loan to value ratio at do you see a default or if you go through all
the metrics, it's like, it's a probability distribution. The only way you can really answer
these questions is you can't answer them this way, but the only way you can even get estimates
of that is to run simulations across distributions, assuming you even know how to predict the
probability of failure, which in that case, I would argue they didn't even have that.
And spatial most complicated machine ever made, maybe not as complicated as the credit system,
but most complicated machine ever made, not whatever 24 launches, they all come back safely.
And you're right, they didn't know. And in fact, when Morton Thiokol gave its first
recommendation, their initial recommendation was don't launch below 53 degrees because
NASA wanted a temperature. And I think the project manager thought that the whole shuttle
was cleared from 33 to 99. So they were putting definite boundaries on it. So they said, don't go
below 53. And they said, well, what's your reasoning for that? They said, well, we've done
53 before and it came back. And that actually totally backfired. So basically, they set the
lower bound at what they'd already done and said, don't go below it. And so it backfired in the
sense that they NASA had this very strong engineering culture, of course, that it worked
great up till then. And so he said, that's not science. That's tradition. That's not an answer.
You've departed from engineering. Give us an engineering story. Don't say just do what we've
done before. And I get that like as Mary Schaeffer, a NASA engineer later said, perfect safety is for
people who don't have the balls to live in the real world. So you can't, it is a probability
distribution. You can't have perfect safety. But I think their attempt to be prudent backfired
because it was viewed as an emotional rather than a scientific case, essentially. But as Feynman
said, the data wasn't there. So you have to start thinking about reason. And that doesn't mean,
maybe they would have gone with the same solution, but they had to start thinking about this problem
in a different way than they were used to, because usually they did have the data they needed to make
a decision. And in this case, they didn't. The other challenge of these case studies,
because it's easy to just stop there. But we also don't realize in the 24 launches prior and the
God knows how many launches that followed it, including one or more disaster, by the way,
on reentry, what's the denominator? How many times did somebody, first of all, how many disasters
were barely avoided? Maybe at least another one on the day that it was 53. And could you ever have
had a full consensus on any given day? This is a great case study because it has so much, the
richness of the data that follow are there. But we don't know if every time one of these things goes
up, there was also somebody in the room that said, and by the way, with perfectly good reason,
no way, no way, no way. And here's the reason. And if that's, so is this the price we have to pay to
live in an uncertain world, or in retrospect was Feynman Wright, and this one should have been
averted using reasonable engineering insight? Yeah, I think, I think, and it's so easy to say
in retrospect, of course, these people are under incredible pressure. They've had all successes in
the past. The astronauts know they're taking risks, everyone knows they're taking risks.
But I do think there's a case to be made that this one should have been averted like voices
were being raised. And in fact, I think one of the reforms that came you mentioned narrowly averting
crisis before this the 53 degree launch. I think one of the I spent a lot of time talking to the
head of the rocket booster program while I was reporting the book, and I think it was saying one
of the changes that occurred was sharing information like that with the astronauts themselves,
because the feeling was had they known what happened with that O-ring, then they would have said,
no, no, no, no, no, we're not ready to go. You guys need to figure this out. And so I don't know
whether that would have or it wouldn't. That's an interesting idea. But I think maybe I think
it's worth getting a different view when you're assessing that risk. Was it Atlantis that which
was the one that burned upon reentry Columbia, Columbia. So totally different issue had to do
with culture. I was going to ask you, was there a cultural similarity in the screw up? Totally.
Or was it a different totally different type of cultural carbon copy? In fact,
the investigation commission for the Columbia accident wrote in their conclusions. This is so
similar to the Challenger disaster culturally, that we deem NASA not a learning organization
because they didn't learn from that experience. And what I write about is they had this incredibly
strong process culture, essentially, that was at a sign like on the mission, one of the rooms that
said, in God, we trust all others bring data, which is great. Like they were super rigorous.
But when they would get into these situations where you didn't have the data you wanted,
then continuing to sort of ask for it and follow these very strict procedures meant they really
kind of constrained their thinking like with Columbia, there were engineers who said we'd
like photographs of a part of the shuttle we think is damaged. And so they went and asked the
Department of Defense for those photos. And their superiors not only blocked them, but apologized to
the Department of Defense for going outside of the normal process for trying to acquire things
like that. And so in both cases, they kept sticking to this very rigid process, we need an engineer
case, we need a quantitative case or these concerns like they're not being quantified, and you're not
going through the proper channels. And so it doesn't count evidence and hunches kept being
deemed inadmissible because they weren't part of the normal formal process. And it happened in an
exact same way. Both times, people suspected what was going to happen. But because their concerns
didn't fit into the normal procedural boxes, they were discounted. No, we don't know the denominator,
we don't know how many times people had concerns that were completely unwarranted and would have
thwarted so therein lies the challenge. And that's what Alan McDonald, who was the head of the rocket
booster program told me he's like, look, if we called off that launch for Challenger, people would
be called as he said, chicken littles, because you have to be willing to take risk in the space
program. And you don't really get credit for not launching. I was about to say, let's assume they
had not launched that day, and they'd waited until the next day, and it was warmer, and they
launched, we wouldn't be having this discussion about it. You're never a hero in that situation.
That's right. And I think there's one sort of thing that I didn't write about, but that I think
has been attributed a little wrongly, where some people have said there was pressure on Morton
Diacol, for sure, more pressure, because there was a civilian and this was more high profile,
or what was the No, for Diacol, there was more pressure because NASA said they were going to
like open up the rocket booster contract on it. But so people have said, Oh, that pressure,
maybe that pressure was a problem, but I call gave the initial recommendation not to launch.
So they were okay not to launch, and then they were pressed for the quantitative case. So I don't
think that pressure was definitive, because they initially came with the recommendation of not to
launch. So speaking of stories in the book, this is different, but it's equally perplexing to me,
which is the firefighters and these guys who are doing these crazy jump rescue things. It's not
that I don't believe the stories I do, but I can't, I'm trying to be empathetic to that situation and
say, where am I making a similar mistake in my life? So spend a moment explaining what that is.
Yeah, this comes from the work of a psychologist named Carl Weick, who writes a lot about what he
calls sense making, like how do people collectively make sense of a dynamic situation. And one of the
things he noticed when he was studying wilderness firefighting teams, hotshot firefighters who hike
in kind of dig trenches around wilderness fires or smoke jumpers who parachute into them, is that
they do a great job. They're very reliable. But sometimes something unusual happens like a fire
jumps from one slope across a gulch to another slope and starts chasing them uphill. And when
when unexpected things happen, sometimes they have trouble and sometimes they die. And when they die,
what he noticed was they tend the ones who die tend to die with their tools, chainsaws, drip torches,
axes, whatever, hundreds of pounds of equipment, and the ones who survive or much fewer have dropped
their equipment and run. And in many cases, the hotshots or firefighters will refuse orders to
drop their tools. And so I was going through like reports of some of these tragedies and you'd see
victim is 100 feet from safety still carrying chainsaw and drip torch and backpack and things
like that. And even accounts of survivors would say they'd be running, they'd be looking for a
place to put their they couldn't believe they were dropping their equipment because it was so central
to their identity. As a firefighter, Norman McLean, who most famously wrote a river runs through it
also wrote a book called the young men and fire. And he wrote that being asked to drop your tools
is like being asked to forget that you are a firefighter because that's your whole group
identity. And all your training is built on never getting rid of your tools. But an unfamiliar
situation holding onto them kills you. And so like used that as kind of an allegory for what he saw
in other usually highly reliable organizations like commercial airlines where when things go
as expected, these very formal strict procedures work incredibly well. But sometimes having done
them so many times makes the organization rigid such that when things change, and when it's
obvious to an outsider that they should drop their tools and run, they don't do it because they're so
used to doing one thing. And so what he was arguing for is how can we make training so that we have
those reliable procedures, but also so that people know they have to improvise and we can't train them
exactly what to do for improvising necessarily, although now they do get trained to drop their
tools. But who knows what the other How many people had to die to figure that out. And again,
the more powerful part of that allegory is the what's my tool, right? What are the tools that I
am lugging around that are probably helping me 99% of the time, but 1% of the time, not only are
they not helping me, but they could be catastrophically wounding me? Yeah. I mean, have you
thought about this in your own life? Oh, for sure. In fact, when I told that, and this is not nearly
as it sounds like it has so little gravity compared to this, but when I was talking before
about taking a fiction writing class, I was trying to think about the joy of it and think
about new structure, learn new structure for writing. But what really came out of it was this
thing where it said to me, I'm using quotes in a stupid way, because I've been writing investigative
magazine articles for the last couple of years where you and the lawyers really want other people
to explain stuff in their voice if they can. But that's not good for this kind of book. And I didn't
even think about that it was not the right way to go about it until I was like knocked out of it by
doing something different. Again, that's not, that's not anything on the level of tragedy. But
some of the other things white wrote about work to commercial airlines, they have these incredible,
incredibly safe, it's pretty remarkable, actually. But when there are problems, it was usually the
large majority of problems would be caused when a situation would change. And the flight crew would
do the thing they were used to anyway, even though to like an outsider would become obvious that they
had to shift what they were doing. So I think it's this sometimes paradox of expertise where,
if you haven't learned to do some improvisation, then you kind of get stuck doing similar things
over and over, you know, you get like the typical, when all you have is a hammer, everything looks
like a nail problem. And I think there's plenty of that in medicine. You could argue medicine is
probably has more of that than anything else, given the degree of specialization, but also,
I think the tacit kind of, it's the word I'm looking for sort of the air of invincibility,
not invincibility, either is the sort of the, I think part of exemption, the privilege of medicine,
which is like you can sit down with, you could meet a person for the very first time in the
emergency room, and they'll take their clothes off, and you're going to examine them, and they'll
tell you a detail about their life. They've never told another human being. There's just something
about that that says, well, there's still something about this profession we place so much faith in.
And then by extension, those in the profession start to project that faith on their own decisions.
So I think that coupled with the stakes, coupled with the specialization, I think probably creates
a fertile environment for exactly that type of thinking. Now, I mean, I guess the last point I
want to ask about on this particular issue is, had those firefighters, going back to this
particular example, been trained as lifelong firefighters versus they had been sampled across
a much broader group of people coming in, is the point of the story that if you'd come in
to that role, having been an accountant working at Subway, just pick a totally random distribution
of people, would it be more intuitive to that group to have dropped their tools? That's a
suggestion. Yeah, that it would be. And in fact, what Wyken McLean argued is that in the first of
the famous disasters called the Man Gulch Fire, a few people survived. And the leader of the group,
he ordered people to drop their tools. They refused the orders, essentially, except for the
two that did survive. And one of the things they pointed out was that he had a much broader training
base. He was used to doing lots of other things with tools, not only firefighting. And so they
thought that he was, we don't know for sure, but the argument that they made was that he had had
a much broader experience with tools. So he didn't think of them as like only these things that he
used in a certain way for firefighting. And so in fact, what he did to save himself was he's ordering
his guys to drop his tools. Most of them aren't. He realized he wasn't going to, he was far down
the Gulch. He realized he wasn't going to be able to run away from the fire. So he actually lit a fire
in front of himself, burned the grass and dove into the ash and the fire burned around him.
So he improvised. And now people are trained to do that. The idea that you would stop a fire by
lighting a fire in the grass in front of yourself and that worked. But so they made the argument
that he was much better set up to improvise because he was used to improvising with tools.
David, I could continue having this discussion for another couple of hours, but I want to be
sensitive to your time. And so before we wrap, is there anything that I feel like we've only
scratched the surface, frankly, of these two books? I actually thought we'd get through more,
but I guess that speaks to how long winded I am when I ask questions.
No, you told me before we started that I could go on and be digressive. And I told you that I'm
naturally digressive. So I took you up on it.
Perfect. Perfect. It was match quality at its finest. Anything we didn't talk about in the last
few minutes that you want a chance to sort of discuss?
Someone who became that I don't get asked about much in the book who became sort of a role model
for me works not so far from here. A woman named Frances Hesselbein, who took her first real job
at the age of 54. And I'll keep her story short here. But basically, she essentially became she
became a CEO of the Girl Scouts. And when she had one semester of junior college under her belt in
her entire life, but now has 23 honorary degrees, she likes to know. And when she actually interviewed
for the CEO position, the people before her had had incredible leadership credentials. Captain
Dorothy Stratton was one she started the Women's Coast Guard Reserve and was university dean.
Another was Cecily Canaan Selby, prominent scientist and leader in industry and education.
Frances Hesselbein, one semester junior college leader of one of 355 local councils of Girl Scouts.
And again, first professional job at age 54. And so she says, No, no, I'm not taking that CEO job.
I'm never moving out of Pennsylvania. She grew up in Johnstown. And her husband says, No, I'll
drive you to New York, you can turn it down in person. And so they asked her if you took over
Girl Scouts, this is late 60s Girl Scouts is in total crisis, free fall of membership and volunteers.
And what would you do if you took it over? And she doesn't want the job, she feels fine to say
whatever she just speak her mind freely. And she says, the rollout our sacrosanct handbook, I'd
replace it with ones that appeal to girls of different ages, and start working on diversity.
If an indigenous girl near an ice flow in Alaska, opens a book, I want her to see herself in a Girl
Scouts uniform, she just goes through all this. I sell some of the underused campsites, even though
it'd be painful, get rid of some of this homemaking stuff, focus on educate girls about sex and drugs
and math and science and all this. And she's like, Well, that was fun. But I'm never gonna hear from
that again. Of course, she comes back. I mean, it's actually the early 70s when she was interviewing,
but so she gets the CEO job and totally transforms the organization turns the cookie business into
like a third of a billion dollar business. Triples diversity representation adds 130,000
volunteers people she's paying in a sense of mission, not in money, and basically saves the
Girl Scouts. And she works every week. I'm sure she's at her office right now, because she works
every weekday in Manhattan, she's only 103 and a half. So she has a lot of I'm sure she has a lot
of place to go. But I think she meant a lot of things to me. One, people can make an impact when
they're older than they think they can. She's now running the Francis Hesselbein leadership
Institute and teaching at West Point. Also, she never expected to do any of the things she did.
Every time she got offered an opportunity, she'd say like, No, I'm not doing it. And then they tell
her, Well, then this Girl Scout troops gonna have to be folded sorry, and she'd be like, Fine, I'll
do it for a month and would get to try it and then be like, Wait, I actually love this. And that's
everything she did. So she sort of short term planned her way through life. And she had two
sayings that really stuck with me. One was leadership is a matter of how to be not a matter
of what to do. I think that's a powerful thing to think about so much about leadership is,
is being a good example, not having to know everything. Sometimes I think we have this
George Washington standing up in the boat crossing the Delaware, which I don't think that's an
accurate depiction. I think there's a real painting of him somewhere. And obviously, he's
sitting down in the boat. But it's like this idea that they know everything ahead. They're
clairvoyant. It's like, No, they need to be a good example. And part of that is admitting that you
don't know stuff. And the other was her saying was, you have to carry a big basket to bring
something home. And she told me when she was at one of her first training events, some woman
complains she wasn't learning anything, she already knew all this stuff. And then this other
woman told that saying to Francis, and then it sort of became one of her mantras. And I loved
that saying, because I realized, again, it was part of this, I don't want to keep coming back to
this online beginners fiction writing class I took, but it was it was sort of the emphasis of
hearing her say that they said, Sure, I can take a beginner's class. And I realized there's like no
amount of beginner's classes I could take that I wouldn't learn something from. Because if you go
in open minded, you'll learn something from it. There was one day in my neighborhood, I live in
DC now, I noticed a bunch of increase in the population of wizards in my neighborhood. And
so I walked over a nearby hotel notice they were having like a Japanese conference conference.
And they had a beginning Japanese comics writing class. So I'm like, I'll sit in on that.
Probably not gonna write a Japanese comic, but it's structure and its story and narrative and
dialogue and all this stuff. You can't not learn from it. So it's just just made me realize that
if you go into it with that mindset, you're just constantly learning something. And so that's an
approach I try to adopt two of those phrases really stuck with me. And I am glad you told that story.
That is a beautiful story. And I think it dovetails perfectly into this idea of being a lifelong
student, which I think, well, frankly, that's sort of one of the things that's fun about a podcast.
So basically, it is an excuse to learn a whole bunch of stuff. So I figured, I mean, you don't
have to be doing this for any professional reason. Yeah. Well, David, thank you so much. I really
appreciate it. Thanks for coming up to New York today. I appreciate it. Pleasure. I enjoyed it.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rivalties. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast, typically less than five
minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise. Please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.