Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest today is Dr. Peter Hotez. Dr. Hotez is a renowned vaccine scientist,
pediatrician, and an expert on the current coronavirus outbreak. His titles are almost too
numerous to get into at this point, but I'll make an attempt to do so. He's the Dean of the National
School of Tropical Medicine and professor of pediatrics and molecular virology and microbiology
at the Baylor College of Medicine, where he's also the director of the Texas Children's Center
for Vaccine Development and the Texas Children's Hospital Endowed Chair of Tropical Pediatrics.
I learned of Peter a few months ago for unrelated reasons that pertained to microbiology,
vaccination, et cetera, and had wanted to interview him at the time and postponed it for a number of
unrelated reasons. More recently, about three weeks ago, I saw him talking about coronavirus,
which was really around the time I started to think I had miscalculated. This would have been
mid-February, the second week of February, and I started to realize at that point in time that this
was going to be a much bigger deal than I had naively assumed in January. I reached back out
to him and said, Peter, let's get on a podcast when the time is right and assumed that that would
mean when we had enough facts that it was worth talking about. But what I did not really anticipate
was the past seven days until they were upon us, basically about a week ago. So if you're
listening to this on the 14th of March, that would have been about the 6th of March. A lot of things
really changed in my mind. And I reached back out to Peter and said, hey, we should probably talk
at the end of next week, which gives you enough time to manage the very important responsibilities
that you have, but also allows us to sort of fill in some pretty big gaps in knowledge. And we attempt
to do that, and this podcast is actually quite short by the standards of our podcast. It's about
an hour long. And I think what we'll probably do is shorter, more frequent podcasts at this point in
time because the information is changing at a very rapid rate, such that anything we talk about
on this podcast is likely to be background information at best a week out. So we do talk
about a number of things. We talk obviously about the etiology of the virus, the difference between
the virus, which is SARS-CoV-2 and the disease state that it causes COVID-19. We talk about how
it's spread. We talk about where it came from, what we know about it, what we don't know about it,
what some of the treatment options may be, may not be, why a vaccine is probably not likely in
the near term. We talk about something called convalescent serum, which is something that looks
kind of promising. And at this point, anything promising, we want to put sort of all hands on
deck with interpreting. So with that said, let's just get to this interview with Peter, and we'll
be following this up with a number of other interviews. Also, I should point out on pretty
much every day I'm putting updates up on Instagram, where you can find me at PeterAttiaMD.com is the
website. And that'll point you to Instagram, or you can just go to Instagram at PeterAttiaMD. And
that'll be kind of daily updates. But as I said, expect to see podcasts at a slightly irregular
cadence, just as a way that we can sort of communicate with you. This podcast and all podcasts
pertaining to the coronavirus will have show notes available to all listeners. So these podcasts,
show notes, and the subsequent ones that pertain to this subject matter will not be behind the
paywall for subscribers. So this will be available to everybody. We will attempt to provide show notes
as quickly as we can. So hopefully that allows everyone to access this information without any
bottleneck. Without further delay, then please enjoy my discussion today with Dr. Peter Hotez.
Peter, thank you so much for making time to speak with us. You're in unbelievably high demand. I saw
you on the news at 5.30 this morning, your time, and I don't think you've stopped since. And of
course, you've been nonstop for weeks now. And you've been very generous in making time to speak
with me and my team prior to today. So again, greatly appreciated on behalf of many people
listening. Let's start with a little bit of just the nomenclature. People are a little bit
confused, I think, about the nomenclature between COVID-19, SARS, COV-2, maybe explain which one's
the virus, which one's the disease and what the history is here.
Sure. COVID-19 is official designated name of the disease by the World Health Organization. The
causative agent is the SARS-CoV-2 virus, SARS Coronavirus 2. Just like there's AIDS and there's
HIV, there's the name of the disease and the name of the virus. And the fact that it's called
SARS-2, as I often like to call it, has some meaning because there's a lot of similarity in
the type of virus it is compared to the original SARS, which I often call SARS-1 that originated
out of southern China in 2003 and caused a very serious pandemic, a deadly pandemic that affected
Toronto, Canada, among other places. This is a somewhat different type of disease in terms of
transmissibility and fatality. We can talk about some of the differences between SARS-1 and SARS-2.
Maybe we should do that because I think transmissibility and lethality are two things that
are very important to understanding this and maybe touching on the distinction between SARS-1 and
SARS-2 will be helpful.
Yeah, so actually we've had now three major pandemics caused by coronaviruses in the 21st
century. You know, up until then, when I was being trained in microbiology and infectious diseases,
we knew about coronaviruses, but they were considered of relatively minor importance. They
were coronaviruses that caused upper respiratory infections in kids and rarely they would cause
lower respiratory tract infections. But we had our first really serious experience with a
coronavirus in 2003 when SARS-1 caused a serious pandemic that disrupted the economy of China and
Canada and elsewhere. Another second coronavirus occurred in 2012 with Middle Eastern Respiratory
Syndrome that emerged out of Saudi Arabia. Now it's around 2012 and now this is the third one,
SARS-2. So the point is we've had a new coronavirus pandemic every decade of this 21st century. So
hopefully we're starting to realize these are pretty serious actors here in terms of global
health threats. And that has a lot of relevance when we talk about ultimately developing vaccines
and why we should prioritize coronaviruses moving forward.
Peter, six days ago I spoke with a colleague of yours who will remain nameless just because we
didn't speak on the record. And I asked him point blank, what is your level of concern today? And
keep in mind, this was a discussion on March 7th, six days ago. I said, what is your concern with
SARS-CoV-2 relative to the coronaviruses responsible for MERS and SARS, which were very
deadly viruses? And he said something to the effect of, I am much more concerned with what I'm seeing
today. Do you share that sentiment and do you think that that is an overreaction?
I think it is an appropriate reaction. And I would have shared that concern six days ago,
but for very quirky reasons. So you might say, well, everyone knows, or a lot of people know from
the from all the public news that SARS-2 is not as deadly as SARS-1 or MERS, but it's a cause of
serious mortality. We'll go into that a little bit more. And it's also highly transmissible.
So while it isn't necessarily the most lethal virus we've ever seen, nor is it the most transmissible,
it's high in both categories. And that combines in this very unique way. Let me explain that a
little bit better. So SARS-1, the original one was highly lethal. And if you had it, you were sick as
hell and you were going into the hospital in the ICU. And that meant that you didn't have a lot
of people walking around transmitting SARS-1. And that's one of the reasons it tended to burn out
pretty quickly, although it could cause serious nosocomial outbreaks in hospitals and MERS-2
more or less went by that same playbook. This one is fatal only for certain groups,
a serious disease in certain groups. And what that means is you have a lot of other, a large segment
of the population walking around shedding virus, including kids. So kids for reasons that, and
adolescents and young adults for reasons that we don't understand are getting the infection
transmitting the virus, but they're not getting very sick. And there's always the outlier that
will, but more often than not. So the problem is you have a lot of virus circulating and only
certain groups seem to be getting serious disease. And those tend to be individuals over the age of
70, those who have underlying disability, including diabetes or hypertension or heart disease,
maybe those that have immunosuppressive therapy, although we don't know as much about that.
Also quite an interesting healthcare workers. So a lot of healthcare workers are getting infected
because this is so highly transmissible and they're coming into contact with patients.
And for reasons that we don't understand, healthcare workers are getting a higher level
of serious disease than you would expect given their age groups. There have been a lot of medical
mysteries about this virus, why kids are not getting seriously, why adolescents, young adults
not getting seriously ill, but why healthcare workers are getting seriously ill. So we saw this
in Wuhan in China where this virus emerged, at least a thousand healthcare workers became infected
and about 15% of those developed serious illness or in the intensive care unit. So they seem to get
much sicker than you would have expected. And whether that's due to a higher level of exposure
or a higher inoculum of virus and whether that is reproducible in the US, we'll have to see. So
those are the people that seem to be the most vulnerable, the very old, those with underlying
disability and healthcare workers. And that also is a perfect mix because you're knocking out a
lot of people out of the healthcare workforce that have to self-quarantine or are getting sick.
And we were seeing these tragic situations play out in China or elsewhere where
colleagues, healthcare colleagues are taking care of healthcare colleagues in the ICU. And that is
also highly destabilizing. Yeah. And it's also very nonlinear because if you lose 10% or 15% in
that situation of your healthcare workforce between physicians, nurses, respiratory therapists, et
cetera, the knockoff effect of that is much more than a 15% hit to the ability to provide care.
So that's right. And then the other population we're seeing at high risk, we're getting sick
are the first responders and the first responders are coming into contact with
very severely ill people. They're getting infected and then they have to self-quarantine.
So we're seeing large numbers of first responders knocked out of the workforce. And then it's going
to reach a point potentially where we're going to have this perfect storm of not having enough
healthcare workers and first responders to help us. And so for all of these really odd features
of the virus, it starts adding up to become a very serious epidemic and highly destabilizing
for any country that has large numbers of people. And of course, we didn't help our case at all by
the US being so behind in diagnostic testing and allowing this virus to circulate for long periods
of time. As of today, Peter, do you know how many tests are available? I know that as of yesterday
morning, we were at about 75,000. How long until we hit a million, which in theory was promised as
of yesterday? Who knows? The promises keep coming. And this also has a lot of serious consequences
because my colleague Mark Lipsich has done some nice studies with his doctoral student,
Ruan Li, in China showing that the city's docket hit hard in terms of depletion of healthcare
workforce and run on hospital beds and ventilators are those that allow transmission to go on for
long periods of time without intervening. So whether or not you're a city that is totally
overrun in terms of having patients on ventilators and hospital beds and depletion of healthcare
staff is very much depends on how quickly you picked up transmission. So in Wuhan, where
transmission went on for six weeks without people intervening, it was a catastrophe. So it was,
and we all heard the stories of what went on in Wuhan and creating 10 cities of hospitals as
opposed to Guangdong where they picked it up after a week and there were 20 people in the ICU.
So it's night and day. And in the US, now we probably think transmission likely began in
the middle of February if our first known indigenous case occurred, I think it was around
February 26th. So back data on five or six days, the average incubation period, we're getting up
there now three, four weeks where transmission has been going on undetected because we haven't had
the testing available. And that's what I'm worried about is in over two weeks from now,
all of a sudden, we're going to see hospitals inundated with large numbers of sick people.
We don't know for sure this is a new virus, but that is the consequence of the failure
that our government has had in terms of getting testing available.
And Peter, that's a really important point that I just don't think can be overstated,
which is coming back to this point of the importance of social distancing now to buy time.
Because if we could do anything at this point, there is no stopping this. The opportunity to
prevent this virus from entering this country or reaching a sufficient number of the population
seems pretty slim at this point. It's a question of if 100,000 people are going to be infected,
and it happens over a year versus a month, that has enormous consequences. Do you think
there is still an opportunity to shift that curve? If we can get a big order of magnitude level of
testing in the next week, and we can see which communities have significant levels of transmission,
potentially we could intervene. So yeah, we still have to try. But boy, it would have been nice to
have that three, four weeks ago when there was maybe just a handful of communities that had
transmission. We could have focused all of our energy on that. And so we did lose an opportunity,
I think, to prevent this from becoming a large epidemic. And I get asked about this a lot.
For instance, I got Alison Camerata on CNN asked me this morning, whose fault is this? And I think
my response to her was a bit surprising. I said, look, now's not the time to start
assigning fault. There's going to be time for that later. And we can have a federal investigation of
where the breakdowns occurred. But I think right now we've got to focus on what the task at hand is.
And I introduced this new concept this morning, both on CNN and on Fox News. And I did it after
calling my friend and colleague Arturo Casadoval, who's a professor at Johns Hopkins,
who's been pushing this idea for a few weeks that there is a low cost intervention that we could
apply right now. And that is identifying patients who've been infected, recovered, and looking at
their convalescent serous. In other words, people develop antibodies and antibody response to varying
their degrees, collecting that serum, isolating antibody, and then using that as a treatment.
Because that's all we're going to have right now. I already think the window is passed
when we're going to start having significant numbers of people sick from this virus in hospitals
and intensive care units. And this is the one thing we can offer them given the fact that we're not
likely to have any effective antiviral drugs for a while. And it could be very effective
based on what we learned historically from things like the 1918 flu pandemic, the Spanish flu,
or even from experiences that we heard about from SARS and MERS or even this virus and Wuhan,
both as a treatment, which would require large amounts of antibody, but also as prophylaxis.
So you can give a small amount and keep healthcare workers and first responders on the job because
it's preventing them from potentially from getting sick. Peter, when it comes to convalescent serum,
I want to make sure I understand something, which is from a technical standpoint, this is easy.
Obviously from a theoretical standpoint, it makes sense. This is, as you point out, not a new trick.
However, when we start to think about bottlenecks in the supply chain, it does require a phoresis,
correct? Yeah, it looks that way. And so we really need the help of blood banks and any,
I don't know if you do this only in academic health centers or whether
every community hospital would have this capability. And we would need some guidance
from the drug administration from CBER, the Center for Biologics Evaluation Research. So
this is kind of a 30,000 foot aerial view of the problem. Speaking to Arturo, he thinks putting
together a federal task force to really look into this and to help with standardizing it and
figuring out what we can do. But if we wind up having a situation similar to Italy
in the United States or even part of the United States, having this at our disposal
is going to be really important because otherwise we've got nothing. Otherwise we go back to the
14th century in terms of using quarantine methods and that kind of thing. And we see
what happens when we have to do that. It's not a good look for our country.
Peter, do we have a sense of how many individuals could be helped by the serum of one
convalesced patient? How scalable is it? The kinds of numbers people are throwing out are 300
mils, three to 600 mils for someone who's potentially seriously ill. So that looks like
a one-to-one donor per patient. But for the prophylaxis, if we're talking five mLs, a single
donor could potentially prophylaxis dozens or maybe even 100 individuals. And who knows how
off those numbers really are. But given the fact that it's relatively low technology, doesn't need
to bring in a lot of specialized equipment, I think it's something we need to look into. And
Arturo gave me the permission to sound the alarm on CNN and Fox News. And we'll see how it resonates
in the coming days and weeks and see if it catches fire. What about remdesivir, which seems
like one of the more promising things that could be repurposed? Do you buy that argument that this
drug, which has been developed by Gilead for Ebola is potentially, I mean, it's being used now on
compassionate exemption. Do we have a sense of its efficacy or is it too soon? I haven't seen those
numbers. And so it will require a clinical trial and whether you use combination therapy, certainly
antivirals will go a lot faster than vaccines. And we've developed a recombinant protein vaccine,
but it's, you know, we'll see how quickly that can come up to speed in terms of clinical development.
You've said in the past, a vaccine is really not something we're going to have in the next 12
months. And it might even be longer than that. Can you just explain to folks two issues? One,
the technical challenges of vaccinating against this coronavirus per se versus say an influenza
and the lessons we've learned from say RSV viruses. And then secondly, the logistics of
getting a vaccine tested, vetted from a safety and efficacy standpoint to be used on
asymptomatic people. Those seem to be two separate issues that are both stacked against us.
Well, yeah, I mean, vaccines are about the highest bar there is in terms of testing because you're
essentially typically you're immunizing well individuals or healthy individuals. So you have
to be pristine in terms of its safety. And historically, it's been very difficult to
compress those timelines to something quick. So it's not unusual for a clinical development plan
for a vaccine to last a year, two years, sometimes three years to go through the series of phase one
trials for safety and then graded trials for phase two to show that those are expanded safety
studies, maybe getting a hint of efficacy and then the phase three pivotal study for licensure
in an area of transmission. So even under ideal circumstances that will take time. Now, I think
there are opportunities to streamline this. So my colleague, Rina Rapioli, who's one of the real
thought leaders in vaccines, he's at GlaxoSmithKline has drawn up a lot of interesting roadmaps for
doing more things in parallel rather than serially and accelerating those timelines.
And I think that just a lot of interest in applying that for this vaccine. But I've made
the statement that I'm not sure this is the one you want to do it with even though there's so
much urgency. And the reason I say that is coronavirus vaccines have, at least in laboratory
animals, shown that they could create a problem known as immune enhancement, where the vaccine
could actually make things worse. This is a phenomena that was found originally with the
respiratory syncytial virus vaccine, the RSV vaccine, that was a killed virus vaccine, a formal
and inactivated vaccine that was tested by the National Institutes of Health at Children's
Hospital in Washington in the 1960s, where vaccine recipients actually did worse than the non-vaccine
recipients after they were exposed to the natural virus living in the community. And the
mechanism is not still entirely clear, but those who were vaccinated had more hospitalizations
and there were even two deaths. And there was the added layer of complexity that this study,
when you look at the paper, I only realized this recently was done among almost all African
American kids as well, when it was done in Washington, DC, and there were potentially
two deaths. So this squashed enthusiasm for RSV vaccines appropriately, so for a long time.
And the question is, was this unique to respiratory syncytial virus or is there
others that do it? Well, after SARS in 2003, there was an initial effort to, again, develop
killed virus vaccines to test in animals. And unfortunately, after virus challenge,
those animals also exhibited a lung pathology that bore some resemblance to what we saw
in the kids with RSV in the 1960s. And we said, oh, no, this is, are we going to be faced with this
again? And so the thinking was, well, okay, maybe that was unique to a killed virus vaccine. Let's
do this with the whole spike protein. So if you look at a cartoon of what coronavirus looks like,
you always see these little spikes all around it. That's the part of the docs with the receptor.
So a recombinant protein vaccine was made with the whole spike protein. Sure enough,
we also saw immune enhancement, although it was more in the liver than in the lungs. But the
thinking was, can we get around this? Is it going to be impossible to develop coronavirus vaccines?
Well, then our colleagues at the New York blood center, Shibujiang and Lanying Du,
found that if they only use the receptor binding, no main, the smallest part of the S protein that
docs with the receptor, the acetylcholines 2 receptor in the lungs, they seem to get protection
in laboratory animals without all the immune enhancement. That was pretty exciting. And that's
the concept that we partnered together to write a grant to the NIH together with the Galveston
National Laboratory, where they had the virus for potentially doing preclinical studies. And Walter
Reed, and we wound up making a vaccine manufacturing it that showed pretty good
levels of high levels of efficacy and seemed to get around the problem of immune enhancement.
And that's why we got so excited at the prospect of maybe we could develop this
receptor binding domain as a vaccine. And we did, and we got funded by the NIH.
It took us several years to do it to show all of the safety, none of the immune enhancement,
and the efficacy had it manufactured. But after then, by then, nobody was really interested in
coronavirus vaccines anymore. And we couldn't attract any investment in moving into clinical
trials. We kept it on stability studies, but that project more or less was done until a few weeks
ago when this new coronavirus emerged. And we began look in the Chinese were really good about
putting up their data. Everyone says how non-transparent they were, but I disagree. They
were very transparent. They were putting up all their data on these preprint servers like
BioArchive, MedArchive. And we were able to see that the SARS-2 coronavirus bore a lot of
resemblance to SARS-1. It was about 80% similar in terms of its genetic code bound to the same
receptor. We realized, oh my God, we might actually have a vaccine that we could repurpose
for this epidemic. In the meantime, we also started trying to make the new one as well,
the receptor binding made for the new one, but this was already manufactured. And now we've been
in this hunt to try to identify prospective donors to see if we can now move this into
clinical trials. That's been a few weeks now. And it's sad to report we've still not been able to
raise the money to move it into clinical trials, which is really tragic. It's already manufactured.
We can move as fast as anybody, but this really goes to show you the problem of dealing with
vaccines, either for neglected diseases that I've devoted my whole life to. We've made vaccines for
schistosomiasis and hookworm and shoggis disease and moving them into the clinic through our
National School of Tropical Medicine, the Baylor College of Medicine, and Texas Children's Hospital
Center for Vaccine Development, taking on this coronavirus. But you'd think that people would
be pretty eager to support us to move this forward, but so far it hasn't happened.
Should that change? I assume people can pretty easily get a hold of you if there's interest in
this. What's the easiest way for people to get a hold of you at this point in time? I assume just
through the university? Yeah, just send me an email. My email is pretty public. It's just
Hotez last name at BCM stands for Baylor College of Medicine.edu. And we can do this through either
the college or Texas Children's Hospital and be fantastic. What do we know about the ACE2
receptor and its role here? Certainly a few weeks ago, I remember seeing a paper that
discussed this in the context of the first SARS outbreak. This was a 2005 paper, and that got us
very interested in looking at angiotensin receptor blockers and things like that. But is the
following still our understanding, which is that the virus gains access to these cells in the lung,
the type two pneumocytes that make surfactant, probably through this ACE2 receptor, though there
may be a co receptor. Once the pneumocyte is infected, it reduces its capacity to produce
surfactant, which is one of the more telling pieces of the pathology. Is that still largely
accurate to our understanding? Well, I think there's a couple of things. I think first of all,
the receptors not only in the lungs, it's also found in the intestinal tract, and you can see
intestinal pathology with this. And that may even be even myocardial potentially. And it's in endothelial
cells as well. And that may partly explain some of the diverse pathology that we're seeing. So for
instance, patients who are very ill with this, if you look at the med archive reports coming out of
China and elsewhere, a lot of them are getting acute myocardial injury. And we don't really know
if that's from myocarditis or whether just getting myocardial infarction as a consequence
of the infection. But I think that's probably a major mode of death for a lot of these patients.
And it's very confusing because there's a lot of things going on at once. You have
acute myocardial injury, but you're also seeing acute respiratory distress syndrome, ARDS.
So therefore, is the heart injury due to the ARDS in shock or is it occurring in parallel? And then
what's the basis for the ARDS? Is it overwhelming virus invasion in the lungs or is there a huge
inflammatory component to this? And there's differing opinions on that. And that also has
implications for treatment. Then the intestinal pathology as well. And we've seen patients,
at least 10% of the patients reported in some hospitals in Wuhan, they presented with GI symptoms
and were erroneously admitted to the surgical suite. And those are the ones that wound up
actually infecting large numbers of healthcare workers because nobody suspected this was SARS-2.
So that's confusing as well. And you can imagine how all the confusion that would create for
monitoring and figuring out who should get tested. So my colleague Paul Offit is of the opinion that
he thinks the GI route is actually a major mode of transmission. As noted and speculated,
well, at least he's talked to me on the phone about whether the fact that cruise ships are so
widely affected, he says it reminds him a little bit of norovirus when it affects large numbers of
cruise ships. So is it getting into the food? So we don't really know the modes of transmission of
this. We know droplet contact is going to be important. People are coughing micro droplets
onto surfaces and then people come into contact with them with their hands and auto inoculate
themselves in the mucous membranes of their eyes and mouth or whether they're coughing directly
onto people's faces. But the other modes of transmission are also interesting. Is there
a lot of fecal oral transmission? I don't think we know that. Is there a true airborne transmission
where the virus can travel on micro particles long distances? It turns out not many respiratory
viruses do that. We know measles does, chicken pox does. So we're still in this deep learning
curve about this virus. Which again brings us back to this point of can you buy time? Because time
presumably brings clarity, reduces uncertainty. Did you see the paper today that just came out
from the New England Journal of Medicine that looked at the fomite transmission? No, I didn't
see that. What did it find? Well, here, I'm going to pull it up. The telling figure in this sort of
looks at four different surfaces, actually several plastic, steel, cardboard, copper
surfaces. And it looks at the median and half-life survival on these surfaces. And not surprisingly,
I think based on what you just said, Peter, there's pretty reasonable survival. So until you reach a
level that they think is not compatible with transmission takes about 72 hours on plastic,
takes 48 hours on cardboard, takes about 24 hours on steel, and takes about eight hours to 24 hours
on copper. So a couple points I'd make there from a public service announcement. There's, I've seen a
lot of talk on Twitter of all you need to do is have copper on your door and nothing gets in.
Well, apparently not. And we have evidence that at least a day of survivability on these fomites.
And again, I think that speaks to the R0 being as high as it is. And maybe this is a reasonable
time to explain exactly what R0 is and what we think our best estimates are of it and why it
probably feeds into what you've been saying about the concern over the transmissibility.
I think all of this put together presents a picture of why this virus is so highly transmissible.
You have the fact that this virus can live on surfaces. So the droplet contact motor transmission
is significant because it depends on the virus being able to survive on fomites and surfaces.
And the fact that this virus will often land on people's face and they can auto inoculate
themselves, that's a motor transmission, maybe fecal oral and maybe airborne transmission as well.
And so what does that all add up to? It all adds up to the fact that when people have looked at it,
it's a pretty high, what we call reproductive number or what the Brits call R0, what we call R0,
which refers to roughly the working definition is the number of people that will get infected
if a single individual has this virus. So the number that I carry around in my head is between
2.24 and 3.58, roughly between two and four people infected for every single individual.
And some people will shift those numbers around more or less. And I think that level of transmission
varies depending on location and number of other factors, but it's pretty high. If you look at
seasonal flu, for instance, which is around 1.2, 1.3, so this would be two or three times more
transmissible than seasonal flu, clearly not as transmissible as measles, which is up to 12 to 18,
but still quite high. So as I mentioned before, every new emerging pathogen has its own little
shop of horrors. In the case of this one, it's pretty highly transmissible. And there are a lot
of people in this case who are running around who are not sick that are spreading this virus around
and infecting a subgroup of individuals who happen to get very ill and with very high mortality
rates. So the case fatality rate of this virus is between 0.6 and 3.4%, which may not sound all that
high, but that's easily between four and 20 times higher than influenza. And that, given the fact
that there is a group walking around with this, means you're going to have a lot of people in
hospital in intensive care units, and especially among older populations where that mortality rate
is between 10 and 20%. And that's what's so devastating is the fact that when this virus
goes into areas where large numbers of older people congregate, especially older people
with underlying disability, can have some devastating effects. And the Chinese told us
this was going to happen. They told us about what happens when this virus goes into a nursing home
or affects older people and large numbers of deaths of those individuals over the age of 70.
And I don't know if it was because we didn't believe them or we just had to learn it on our
own. But when we had our first community transmission in Kirkland, Washington, we saw
how this virus raced through that nursing home and killed 13 people in a nursing home of about
100 individuals. So 13%, which is exactly right in that area of 10 to 20% that the Chinese told
us about. And then I became very concerned, not only from the lack of government response from
the debacle with the testing, but also that there was not a lot of guidance being issued
around nursing homes or assisted living facilities. And I had the opportunity to testify to Congress
about our vaccine to the House Science, Space and Technology Committee. But I hear I had the
attention of Congress when it was being filmed on C-SPAN 2 or C-SPAN. And I said, look, this is my
chance to really sound the alarm on what's not happening to protect our old people. And as I was
saying it, I knew it was being very provocative and I was being deliberately provocative. And I
knew it was going to be on the evening news and be on the news the next day, but I felt,
no, I had to say something. And that's when I used that expression, this is the angel of death
for older people. And indeed that had that effect, but it was a wake up call to people. And now we're
starting to see nursing homes across the country take those extra measures to carefully screen
people going in and out of nursing homes to review all of their preparedness plans. And now
the Health and Human Services Secretary is mobilizing inspectors around infection control.
And that's an example of where over the years, I've always had this interesting career that
balances being a working scientist and MD, PhD vaccine scientist developing vaccines and for
neglected disease interventions with that advocacy in places that are where I've seen gaps. So I saw
a gap in getting people to care about these poverty related neglected diseases in the early
2000s and helped raise awareness that's now led to treatment of more than a billion people annually
for neglected tropical diseases, raising awareness about diseases of the poor in places like the
United States. And now we've been working with Senator Booker, Cory Booker around this issue,
getting people to counter the anti-vaccine movement. So I'm a parent of an adult daughter
with autism and wrote this book called Vaccines Did Not Cause Rachel's Autism to kind of counter
the false narrative and the misinformation from the anti-vaccine movement. And here was another
example of using my voice to really help people who didn't have a voice otherwise.
Peter, what geographies in the United States are you most concerned about? And then I guess I would
also ask you that question at a global level, but we'll start maybe in the United States.
Well, I mean, right now it's all bets are off. I think any urban area of the US now is vulnerable.
And we've seen this now take off in Seattle. We've seen this take off in New Rochelle in
Westchester County. We're starting to see some uptick in New York City. And there's nothing
really unique about those cities other than their congregations of a big urban population. So on
that basis, I have to believe any large urban center is vulnerable. And it could be any places
vulnerable. It's just that urban areas tend to have more physicians and so more healthcare,
better public health infrastructure. So maybe it's just being picked up there for. So I said last
week, this is going to be a difficult week for America because the testing is going to start to
gear up. And now that it's in the hands of Quest Diagnostics and LabCorp and Roche, we're going to
get a much more full picture of the extent of this virus in the United States and North America.
And I think we're starting to see that the numbers are going up 1600. Who knows what it'll look like
by next week? Is it going to be 10 times that number? I think that's quite possible or even
more. And with that, we'll undoubtedly be picking up new foci of infection.
That's a pretty frightening thought to have a log increase in a week. But when you look at other
countries that have not done well, that's exactly what we have seen, isn't it?
Well, the question is whether that's the true log increase or whether we've had that
transmission all along. It's just that now we're cherry picking communities to detect it.
Or maybe both going on simultaneously. But I suspect we're going to see those numbers
deeply rise again. And so this gets back to my, what I was talking about with Mark Lipsich's
paper where he says the more sustained community transmission goes on, the health burden is going
to be in terms of hospital beds and ICU beds and the demands on healthcare staff. I think as we
pick up these new levels of transmission in places that's been going on for a while, next week. So
the horror this week was we realized we're seeing a lot more cases and maybe new areas of community
transmission. I would say the same for next week with the added piece. Now we're going to start to
see hospital beds fill up. And that's why I'm really pushing now for blood banks to implement
this new antibody therapy because I think the need's really going to be there. And if you don't offer
people any hope of anything, I think that's where panic starts to spread where you start seeing
panic, not only among the population but among the healthcare workers. And we've got to be able
to stop that. So I think just like this week was challenging because we're starting to see an
increase, I think in the next two weeks maybe the critical period when we may start to see
this start to reach a peak. Peter, do we have a sense of what the
excess capacity is in the ICU and where is the bottleneck going to be in the supply chain? Is
it the number of ventilators, the number of ICU beds or beds that could be repurposed for ICU? Is
it going to be the number of anesthesiologists, respiratory therapists, nurses? There are so many
things here. Yeah, I think only now we're really starting to look at this. And if you've ever
listened to Zeke Emanuel, he's been commenting a lot about this. We don't have a great capacity.
Hospitals for cost saving measures and everything else have operated at slim margins. So it's not
like we have a lot of excess capacity laying around. And does this mean we're going to have
to build tent city hospitals? Will we have to bring in the National Guard? I think all of that,
it's a big unknown. I mean, the only good thing that we have going for us is we did make that
sacrifice of shutting down things we love like the National Basketball Association, the NBA, and
the rodeo and that sort of thing. And that's a good thing about America. We did this to protect
our most vulnerable or older citizens, a lot of them veterans of foreign wars. And
I think that that's important. And maybe if there is a seasonality to this virus, maybe we're just
hitting it right in terms of moving it to warmer weather. But we have no evidence for that.
That certainly was not the case with the first SARS, right? I mean, it didn't seem to stop when
the summer came, did it? Well, you know, if you look at the curves, the peaks that I saw looked
like more around the springtime, but who knows? I mean, we certainly can't count on it. And there's
some people who feel that it may start to go down in the summer, but not disappear entirely and then
come back in the fall. So we just don't know. As I've also been saying is confronting a new serious
virus pathogen is one of the hardest things our country faces, has faced the last 20 years. And
it always starts out pretty bumpy and pretty rocky, I think, in part because it takes the CDC a while
to figure out how the federal government and the CDC how to work with state and local health
authorities. This one has been rockier than most because of the inability to do the testing and
other factors. But the problem is, unlike Ebola, which was never going to be transmitted widely
across the country because of that very low reproductive number, unless you're taking care
of a dead or dying Ebola patient, you're not going to get Ebola. This one is pretty transmissible. So
our margin for error is much smaller, as the studies in China have pointed out. So we could
be in for some very serious times. Mark Lipsich has stated that he believes we could be entering
kind of a new world where two years from now, half the world's population or thereabouts has
been infected by this virus. And even if you use the absolute lowest estimate of mortality that's
being provided, which is 0.5 percent or one in 200 people dying, the impact of what I just reiterated
as his estimate is staggering. Do you share that view or do you or do you at least think that that
is a plausible scenario? Yeah, it's absolutely plausible. And Mark's an outstanding epidemiologist.
And you know, a lot of these estimates are based on models. I would say the only thing about models,
and I'm not a modeler, but I've collaborated with modelers to look at projections of our different
vaccines and to give us a sense of what level of protection we would need to have a significant
impact on a population and how wide a coverage we would need. And one of the things that always
impresses me working with modelers is that a modest change in assumptions of what goes into
the model can often have huge differences. So the only comfort I take in that is to say, well, maybe
if those models are like the ones I've worked with, a few tweaks to the model can result in two or
three log reductions in deaths and cases and that sort of thing. So it's models are useful exercises
to help you think through problems, but how predictive they are is only as good as the
assumptions with the new virus agent where we don't even know all the modes of transmission
and everything else. They'll fully understand reproductive number that might help us.
Yeah, as a physicist, a very famous physicist once said, all models are wrong, some are useful.
So hopefully that model is woefully wrong. But I think part of that is, as you said,
it's a little bit in our hands how wrong that model is going to be, isn't it? I mean, it's still
we still have some say over our response to this, both in terms at the federal level,
but also at the local and state level. And then at the individual level, we can all take steps
to reduce our risk and buy more time. How are you thinking about this? I don't want to say
personally, because you're in a very unique position where you have to be out there talking
about this. You don't have the luxury of maybe being a little bit more sequestered. But are there
a certain subset of people that at this point, Peter, you would say absolutely need to be
self-quarantined, either the symptomatic folks, obviously, who run the risk of infecting others
if they can't be tested, but also people who are showing no signs or symptoms, but who are at high
enough risk. How are you helping people create their own sort of framework around that very
difficult decision? Well, certainly older individuals where they're clustering together,
we've seen the devastation. So we can't repeat the debacle that we had in that nursing home. And so
it's all hands on deck with protecting those individuals. Then you can say, okay, Peter,
well, tell us what that means. Does that mean thinking of my 90 year old mother in the Hebrew
home in Brooklyn, outside of Brookline, Massachusetts? Do we now tell her that she has to stay in her
room and can't go down to the cafeteria and sit with her friends? Is that what you're telling us?
So these are going to be really tough decisions. We know how important socialization is for older
people, for anybody, right? But for older people in nursing facilities, that's really heartbreaking.
So Dr. Hotez, is he telling us that the grandkids can't visit? So these are really
tough decisions for us. Because at what point do you say, we know older populations are so fragile
in terms of suffering serious mental decline. And do you want to do that just to protect them from
this virus? And this is where I say, well, I'm a vaccine scientist. I'm pretty good at understanding
infectious disease, epidemiology, because I've had to really understand how to make the best vaccine.
But there's a certain point where the decisions become so tricky that I have to say, no, I'm
starting to exceed the limits of my comfort zone. And here's where we start needing some federal
guidance, state and federal guidance, people to really think about this very deeply and bringing
experts together that understand that. And I don't see that happening, unfortunately. What I'd like
to see are key task force created around not in general, as has been done, the president's created
sort of an overarching task force for this. But there are so many specialized pieces to this that
we have to focus on, like creating an antibody based technology, bring those experts together,
bring experts together around what nursing homes are like and how they're structured,
which would include experts in the mental health of older people, those experts in diabetes,
hypertension to understand what's going on. And I think that's going to be really critical as well.
Peter, what are you personally going to be paying closest attention to in the next seven days besides
the potential for using convalescent serum both from the sort of clinical trial standpoint and or
utilization standpoint? And in terms of data that are going to say, hey, are we heading towards the
Italian path or are we heading towards sort of the Singapore path? What data are you monitoring
closely? Well, certainly, incidents and prevalence data is going to be really important because right
now there's none, right? We've done so little testing. So as we ramp up and also starting to see
which new communities are becoming infected, I think that's going to be absolutely critical and
seeing if the situation that we've seen in the Pacific Northwest and New Rochelle is being
replicated elsewhere or the demographics taking on a different characteristic. Those are some of
the big things that I'll be looking for. And then also there are some vaccine trials that have
started in the Washington area. Interest in following those because my understanding is
the one in Seattle began with one of the vaccine trial evaluation units at the University of
Washington and it was initiated at a time where there wasn't transmission of this virus. Now there
is. So you're doing something that is going to be very interesting but also a little bit scary
because if there is immune enhancement, now we're going to start to see it among those volunteers
who are getting immunized. Peter, I want to be respectful of your time and I promised you we
would only take an hour. We've now gone a little over an hour. So I want to let you go with the
ask that either we can speak again, either formally or informally because again, I think it's probably
less important to spend hours at any one point in time and maybe more important to. And this is
what I've been saying, you know, on CNN, Fox and MSNBC and it's not easy going from one network to
the other, right? Especially those networks. Yeah. Well, you know, one, you have to say something
nice about the president. The other one, you're not allowed to say anything nice about the president.
It's also polarized and threading that needle is interesting. But one of the things I always say
is this is where we are right now. And this virus is racing so quickly that new pathogens in general
set you up to look stupid because even when you're trying to learn something about a new pathogen,
but this one, especially because it's so fast moving and transmissible, I would cringe if I
were to look at my interviews from two or three weeks ago in terms of the things I said, I think,
and probably a month from now, I would say, Oh my God, I can't believe I said that is what we're
talking about now. So I think absolutely that's important to update this and to say, to take a
step back and look to see what have we learned in the last week. And because we're trying to make
our best guesses, best estimates on what we're seeing now, but this is, as I say, it's moving
so quickly. We have to continually reevaluate that. And that's why I'd like to see the white house
out there every day because this thing is moving so quickly. Yeah. Well, look, for those listening
to this, probably on a Saturday, it's now Friday night in real time, March 13th, Peter, let's let
you get back to work. Let's touch base next week and continue to look at the data and in real time,
try to come up with the best assessments of what we can. Thank you very much, Peter. Thanks for
having me. Thanks for all your great work. One of the things that I do when I give talks about
confronting anti-science, and I do that a lot standing up to the anti-vaccine movement, I say
part of this is our fault because as physicians and scientists, we're too inward looking. We've
somehow decided that engaging public audiences is not important. And so the kinds of things you're
doing is really critical to break that. I think the best weapon against ignorance and false
information is the kinds of things that you're doing. So I just want to congratulate you on what
you're doing and there's nothing more important. Thank you, Peter. We greatly appreciate it. And
I hope you get some rest tonight and we'll be back in touch next week. Thanks. Me too. I hope
we get some rest. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested
in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to
hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qwallys, which are a super short
podcast, typically less than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting
the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.